<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>In Defense of Publius Sestius </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <pb n="151"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF PUBLIUS SESTIUS.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>Publius Sestius, when tribune of the people, had been one of those who had
                    exerted themselves most strenuously to promote Cicero's recall, and had shown
                    himself most devoted to his interest, though some coolness had sprung up between
                    them afterwards owing to Sestius's thinking that Cicero was not sufficiently
                    sensible of his obligations to him. Having, however, become very obnoxious to
                    all the friends of Catiline's party, Clodius instigated Marcus Tullius
                    Albonovanus to prosecute him on an accusation of having been guilty of violence
                    and breaches of the peace during his tribunate and they both expected that
                    Cicero would be neutral in the cause, but he went of his own accord to Sestius,
                    and offered to undertake his defence. Pompeius attended this trial as a friend
                    to Sestius, but Caesar sent his friend Vatinius to give evidence against him.
                    (See the next speech.) </p>
                <p>This speech was delivered A. U. C. 698. </p>
                <p>Sestius was unanimously acquitted.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>If any one in times past, O judges, was used to wonder what was the reason why in a
                republic of such power, and in an empire of such dignity, there were not found any
                great number of citizens endowed with so fearless and magnanimous a spirit as to
                dare to expose themselves and their personal safety to danger on behalf of the
                constitution of the state and of the general liberty; from henceforward he must
                wonder if he ever sees any virtuous or intrepid citizens, rather than if he
                occasionally finds one timid, and caring more for his own interests than for those
                of the republic. For without calling to mind and considering the case of each
                separate individual, you can see at one survey those men who joined the senate and
                all virtuous citizens in raising up our afflicted country, and delivering it from a
                horde of domestic robbers, now with sad countenances and mourning garments
                struggling as defendants for their freedom, for their characters, for their rights
                as citizens, for their fortunes, and for their children; and those who have
                polluted, and attacked, and thrown into confusion, <pb n="152"/> and overturned all
                divine and human laws, going about the city merry and joyful, and, while they are
                without any provocation, contriving danger for the bravest and best of the citizens,
                in no fear whatever for themselves. </p>
            <p><milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And though there is much that is scandalous in such
                a state of things, yet is there nothing more intolerable than that they now seek to
                employ not their bands of robbers, not men desperate through want and wickedness,
                but you yourselves, the best men in the city, for the purpose of bringing us and
                other most virtuous men into danger. And they now think that, as they were unable to
                destroy them by stones, and swords, and firebrands, by violence, and personal force,
                and armed bands, they will be able to effect their purpose through the
                instrumentality of your authority, your integrity, and your judicial decisions. </p>
            <p>But, O judges, since I am compelled now to exert that voice in order to ward off
                danger from them, which I had hoped to be able to devote to returning thanks to, and
                to commemorating the kindness of those men who have conferred the greatest services
                on me, I entreat you to allow that voice to be useful to them to whose exertions it
                is owing that it has been restored at all to myself, and to you and to the Roman
                people. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And although the case of Publius Sestius has been summed up by Quintus Hortensius,
                that most illustrious and most eloquent man; and though nothing has been omitted by
                him which he could possibly urge either in the way of complaint over the condition
                of the republic, or of argument for the defendant; still I will come forward also to
                speak for him, lest my exertions in defence should appear to be wanting to that man
                to whom it is owing that they are not wanting to every one of the citizens. And I
                consider, O judges, that in this case, and now speaking as I am at the close of it,
                the part which belongs to me is to argue the matter on grounds of affection, rather
                than to defend my client by an appeal to the strict law; to employ complaints rather
                than eloquence, and to display my grief rather than my ability. <milestone n="4"
                    unit="section"/> And, therefore, if I plead with more vehemence or more freedom
                than those who have spoken before me, I beg of you to listen to my speech with much
                indulgence, and to make all the allowance for it that you think is due to pious
                grief and just <pb n="153"/> indignation. For no man's grief can be more intimately
                connected with his duty than this present grief of mine, being caused as it is by
                the peril of a man who has done me the greatest possible services. Nor is any
                indignation more praiseworthy than that with which I am inflamed by the wickedness
                of those men, who have thought it their business to declare war against all the
                defenders of my safety. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But since his other
                counsel have spoken of each separate charge, I will speak of the entire state of the
                case as affecting Publius Sestius of his conduct throughout his life of his natural
                disposition, of his habits, of his incredible affection for all good men, of his
                zeal for the preservation of the general safety and tranquillity; and I will
                endeavour—if it be only possible for me to succeed—to prevent anything, in all this
                miscellaneous and general defence, from appearing omitted by me which has any
                connection either with this investigation before you, or with the defendant, or with
                the republic. </p>
            <p>And since the tribuneship of Publius Sestius was placed by fortune itself in the most
                critical period of the state, and amid the ruins of the overthrown and prostrate
                republic, I will not approach those most important and serious topics before I have
                first shown you by what beginnings, and on what foundations, the great glory was
                built up which he gained under the most trying circumstances. <milestone n="3"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="6" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Publius Sestius, O judges, was born (as most of you know) of a wise and conscientious
                and strict father, who, after he had been appointed as the first tribune of the
                people among a number of most noble men and in a prosperous time of the republic,
                was not so eager to obtain the other honours of the state as to seem worthy of them.
                By the advice of that father, he married the daughter of a most honourable and
                thoroughly tried man Caius Albinus by whom he had this boy whom you see here, and a
                daughter who is now married. My client was so highly esteemed by these two men of
                the highest class of old-fashioned virtue, that he was beyond all things beloved by
                and agreeable to both of them. The death of his daughter took away from Albinus the
                name of his father-in-law, but it did not take away the affection and good-will
                engendered by that connection. And to this very day he is very fond of him, as you
                may judge by his constant attendance here, and by his anxiety for him, and by his
                    <pb n="154"/> frequent solicitations to you on his behalf. <milestone n="7"
                    unit="section"/> He married a second wife, while his father was still alive, the
                daughter of a most virtuous but most unfortunate man, Caius<note anchored="true"
                    >Caius Scipio, surnamed Asiaticus, was proscribed by Sulla, and compelled to
                    retire to <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName> for safety.</note>
                Scipio. And with respect to this man, the piety of Publius was shown in a most
                remarkable way, and one acceptable to all men, for he immediately went to <placeName
                    key="tgn,7008781">Massilia</placeName><note anchored="true">Now <placeName
                        key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName>.</note> to see and comfort his
                father-in-law, cast out as he was by the waves of the republic, lying in a foreign
                land, a man who ought to have stood in the footsteps of his ancestors. And he
                conducted his daughter to him, in order to induce him, by that unexpected sight and
                embrace, to lay aside, if not all, at least some part of his sorrow; and as long as
                he lived he supported with the most unceasing attentions the sorrow of the father
                and the desolate condition of his daughter. </p>
            <p>I might here say a great deal about his liberality, his attention to his domestic
                duties, his conduct as military tribune, and his great moderation in his province in
                the discharge of the duty of that magistracy; but I keep always in my view the
                dignity of the republic, which summons me to the consideration of herself, and
                exhorts me to pass over these minor points. </p>
            <p><milestone n="8" unit="section"/> My client, O judges, was indeed, by lot the
                quaestor of Caius Antonius, my colleague, but by his sharing in all my counsels he
                was in effect mine. I am prevented by scruples concerning the pledge of confidence,
                as I interpret it, under which such duties are performed, from explaining to you how
                much information he brought to me, and what great foresight he displayed. And of
                Antonius I will only say this one thing; that in that time of exceeding fear and
                danger to the state, he never once attempted either to remove by any denial or to
                allay by any concealment the general apprehensions of all men, or the especial
                suspicion conceived by some persons with respect to himself. And if you were
                accustomed with truth, while I was occupied in supporting and restraining that
                colleague of mine, to praise my indulgence to him, united as it was with the
                greatest watchfulness over the interests of the republic, almost equal praise ought
                to be given to Publius Sestius, who kept such a watch on his own consul that he <pb
                    n="155"/> seemed to him to be a good quaestor, and to all of you to be a most
                excellent citizen. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="9" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>Moreover, when that conspiracy had burst forth from its hiding place and from
                darkness, and stalked about in arms through the city, he came with the army to
                    <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>; which city we suspected, on
                account of its exceeding resources and advantages in time of war, was likely to have
                attempts made on it by that impious and wicked band. And he drove Marcus Aulanus, a
                military tribune devoted to Antonius, headlong out of <placeName key="perseus,Capua"
                    >Capua</placeName>; a profligate man, and one who without much disguise had
                mixed in the intrigues of the conspiracy at <placeName key="perseus,Pisaurum"
                    >Pisaurum</placeName>, and in other parts of the Gallic territory. He also took
                care to get rid of Caius Marcellus out of that city, after he had not only come to
                    <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, but, as if from a fondness for
                warlike arms, had frequently visited a very numerous troop of gladiators. On which
                account that illustrious body of Roman settlers which is at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, which, on account of the way in which I
                preserved the safety of that city during my consulship, has adopted me as their only
                patron, returned the greatest thanks to this Publius Sestius, when he was at my
                house; and at this very time those same men, changing only their name, and appearing
                as colonists, and decurions,—most gallant and virtuous men that they are!—come
                forward to give evidence, and to declare the services done to them by Publius
                Sestius, and to inform you of their public vote according to which they entreat you
                to protect him from danger. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Read, I beg, O Publius Sestius, what the decurions<note anchored="true">It has been
                    said before that <foreign xml:lang="la">decuriones</foreign> was the name of the
                    senators of a senate of a colony.</note> of <placeName key="perseus,Capua"
                    >Capua</placeName> decreed, in order that your childish voice may be able to
                give some hint to our adversaries what it appears likely to be able to do when it
                has acquired strength. [The decree of the decurions is read.] I am not having a
                decree read which has been dictated by any obligations of neighbourhood, or
                clientship, or relation of public hospitality, or which was passed because of a
                canvass for it, or because of the recommendation of some powerful man. I am reciting
                to you the expression of a recollection of dangers which have been passed through,
                the declaration of a most honourable service done to a people, a present return of
                    <pb n="156"/> kindness, and a testimony of past events. <milestone n="11"
                    unit="section"/> And at that very time when Sestius had released <placeName
                    key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> from fear, and the senate and all good
                men, by the detection and crushing of all domestic enemies, had, under my guidance,
                delivered the city from the greatest dangers, I sent letters to summon him from
                    <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName> with that army which he had at
                that time with him. And the moment he had read the letters, he flew to the city with
                inconceivable rapidity. And in order that you may thoroughly call to mind the
                atrocity of those times, listen to the letters, and stir up your memories to a
                contemplation of the time that is gone by. [The letters of Cicero, the consul, are
                read.] <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>By this arrival of Publius Sestius, the attacks and attempts of the new tribunes of
                the people, who then, in the last days of my consulship, were endeavouring to give
                me trouble on account of the deeds which I had performed, and all the over violent
                designs of the conspiracy, were checked. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And
                after it was perceived that while Cato, as tribune of the people, a most fearless
                and excellent citizen, defended the republic, the senate and the Roman people by
                themselves, without any assistance from the military, could easily uphold both their
                own majesty and the dignity of those men who had defended the general safety at
                their own personal risk, Sestius with that army of his followed Antonius with the
                greatest possible rapidity. Here why need I mention by what conduct he stirred up
                the consul to act with energy? or how many motives for exertion he suggested to that
                man, desirous, perhaps, of victory, but still too much afraid of the common dangers
                and chances of warfare and of battle? That would be a very long story; but thus much
                I will say briefly. If the courage of Marcus Petreius had not been most admirable;
                if his virtue in state affairs had not been faultless; if his influence among the
                soldiers had not been overpowering; if his experience in military affairs had not
                been most surprising; and if, above all, Publius Sestius had not cooperated with him
                in exciting, encouraging, reproving, and spurring on Antonius,—winter would have
                overtaken them before the end of that war, and Catiline, when he had emerged from
                those frosts and snows of the <placeName key="tgn,7008531">Apennines</placeName>,
                and, having the whole summer before him, had begun to plunder the roads of
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and the folds of the shepherds,
                would never have been <pb n="157"/> destroyed without enormous bloodshed, and most
                miserable devastation extending over the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>These then were the feelings which Publius Sestius brought to his tribuneship that I
                may forbear to speak of his quaestorship,—and come at last to things nearer to
                ourselves. Although I must not omit to speak of that singular integrity of his in
                the province of which I lately saw traces in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                    >Macedonia</placeName>, not lightly imprinted to celebrate something for a short
                time, but fixed in the everlasting recollection of that province. But, however, we
                will pass over all these things, though not with out turning back and fixing one
                last look upon them. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Let us come with eager zeal and rapid course to his tribuneship, since that has been
                for some time inviting us to contemplate it, and since it occupies a large portion
                of my speech. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And that tribuneship has already
                been spoken of by Quintus Hortensius in such a way that his speech not only appears
                to contain a complete defence to every count of the accusation, but would even be
                worth recollecting as laying down admirable rules for the principles and system on
                which a man ought to proceed in discharging the duties of a public office. But still
                since the entire tribuneship of Publius Sestius did nothing but uphold my name and
                my cause, I think it necessary for me, O judges, if not to discuss the whole matter
                with precision at all events to speak of it in a tone of lamentation. </p>
            <p>And if while speaking on this subject I were inclined to inveigh against some men
                with something like severity, who would not make allowance for my attacking those
                men with some freedom of expression by whose wickedness and frenzy I had myself been
                injured? But I will proceed with moderation, and I will be guided rather by what is
                suitable to the present time than to my indignation. If there be any people who
                secretly are vexed at my safety, let them conceal themselves; if there be any who
                have at any time done anything against me and who now are silent and quiet, let us
                also forget it; if there be any who are puffed up to behave insolently, and who
                still wish to attack me, we will bear with them as far as they can be borne with,
                nor shall my language offend any one except those who so put themselves in my way
                that I shall appear not to have attacked them, but to have run accidentally against
                them. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="158"/>
            </p>
            <p>But it is necessary, before I begin to speak of the tribuneship of Publius Sestius,
                to lay before you all the circumstances of the shipwreck of the republic the
                preceding year; to the repairing which, and to the restoration of the general safety
                all the words, and actions, and thoughts of Publius Sestius will be found to have
                been devoted. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>That year, the whole republic being in a state of great commotion, and many people
                being in just fear, had been like a bow bent against me alone, as men ignorant of
                state affairs used commonly to say; but in reality against the whole republic, by
                the transference to the common people of a furious and profligate man, angry with
                me, but a far more zealous enemy to tranquillity and the general safety. This man,
                that most illustrious of citizens, and, though many tried to alienate him from me,
                most friendly to me, Cnaeus Pompeius, had bound by every sort of security, and
                promise, and oath to do nothing during his tribuneship contrary to my interest. But
                that wicked man, sprung as it were from the very dregs of every sort of wickedness,
                thought that he should not be doing enough in the way of violating his engagements,
                unless he terrified the man who was so eager to guard against danger for another, by
                personal danger to himself. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>This foul and savage
                brute, hampered as he was by the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, tied
                down by the precedents of our ancestors, fettered by the bonds of holy laws, was on
                a sudden released by the consul,<note anchored="true">There is great reason to think
                    that there is some corruption here.</note> who, as I imagine, was either won
                over by entreaties, or, as many people thought, influenced by hostility to me, and
                to at all events was ignorant and unsuspicious of the impending crimes and
                misfortunes. And that tribune of the people, if he was successful in his design of
                throwing the republic into confusion, did not owe it to any energy of his own. For
                what energy could there be in the life of a man maddened by the infamy of his
                brother, by his own adultery with his sister, and by every sort of unheard-of
                licentiousness? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But that, forsooth, did seem like a fortune appointed for the republic by fate
                itself, that that blind and senseless tribune of the people should find two—must I
                call them consuls? must I honour by this name the overthrowers of this empire, the
                betrayers of your dignity, the enemies of all good men? men who thought that they
                had been adorned <pb n="159"/> with those <foreign xml:lang="la">fasces</foreign>,
                and with all the other insignia of supreme honour and command, for the purpose of
                destroying the senate, of crushing the equestrian order, and extinguishing all the
                rights and established principles of our ancestors. And, I beg you in the name of
                the immortal gods, if you do not yet wish to recall their wickedness and the wounds
                which they have burnt into the republic, still turn your recollection to their
                countenances and their gait. Their actions will more easily present themselves to
                your minds if you bring their faces before your eyes. <milestone n="8"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="18" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>The one reeking with perfume, with curled hair looking with disdain on the agents of
                his debaucheries and the old plagues of his youthful age, formerly when tossed and
                driven about by the troops<note anchored="true">The text here is very corrupt. The
                    Latin is “<foreign xml:lang="la">puteali et foeneratorum gregibus inflatus atque
                        perculsus</foreign>”. The <foreign xml:lang="la">puteal</foreign> was the
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">puteal Libonis</foreign>, mentioned in Horace, the
                    enclosure surrounding a well erected by Scribonius Libo to preserve the memory
                    of a chapel which had been struck by lightning, and it was a common place of
                    meeting for usurers.</note> of usurers lest in that Scyllaean state of debt he
                should be dashed up against the Maenian<note anchored="true">See <bibl
                        n="Cic. Div. Caec. 50">vol. i. p. 123</bibl>, note.</note> column, fled into
                the harbour of the tribuneship. He despised the Roman knights, he threatened the
                senate, he sold himself to the artisans, and proclaimed openly that they had saved
                him from being prosecuted for bribery; and he was used to say, moreover, that he
                hoped to obtain a province from them, even though it were against the will of the
                senate; and if he did not get a province, he did not think it possible for him to
                remain in safety. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The other, O ye good gods! how
                horrible was his approach, how savage, how terrible was he to look at! You would say
                that you were beholding some one of those bearded men,—an example of the old empire,
                an image of antiquity, a prop of the republic. His garments were rough, made of this
                purple worn by the common people you see around us, nearly brown; his hair so rough
                that at <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, in which he, for the sake
                of becoming entitled to have an image of himself, was exercising the authority of a
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">decemvir</foreign>, it seemed as if he would require the
                whole Seplasia<note anchored="true">“Seplasia was the name of the forum at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, where the perfumers
                    carried on their trade.”—Nizol.</note> to make it decent. Why need I speak of
                his eyebrow? which at that time did not seem to men to be an ordinary brow, but a
                pledge of <pb n="160"/> the safety of the republic. For such great gravity was in
                his eye, such a contraction was there of his forehead, that the whole republic
                appeared to be resting on that brow, as the heavens do on Atlas. <milestone n="20"
                    unit="section"/> This was the common conversation of every one: “He is, however,
                a great and firm support to the republic; we have some one to oppose to that
                pollution, to that mud; I declare solemnly by his mere look he will check the
                licentiousness and levity of his colleague; the senate will have some one this year
                whom it can follow; good men will not be in want of an adviser and a leader this
                year.” And men congratulated me most especially, because I was likely to have not
                only a friend and connection, but also a fearless and dignified consul as an ally
                against a frantic and audacious tribune of the people. <milestone n="9"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And as to one of them, no one was mistaken in him; for who could suppose it possible
                for a man rising suddenly from the long darkness of brothels and scenes of
                debauchery in which he had lain, to hold the helm of so vast an empire, and to
                undertake the guidance of the republic in so important a voyage, amid such
                threatening waves?—a man worn out with wine and gluttony, and lewdness and
                adultery?—a man who, beyond his hopes, had been placed in the highest rank through
                the influence of others, when his drunken eyes were unable not merely to gaze on the
                impending storm, but even to stand any unusual glare of light? <milestone n="21"
                    unit="section"/> But the other did deceive many men in every point; for he was
                recommended to men's favourable opinion by the fact of his high birth, which is of
                itself a very powerful recommendation, for all virtuous men naturally look with
                favour on noble birth, both because it is advantageous for the republic that nobly
                born men should be worthy of their ancestors, and because the recollection of men
                who are illustrious, and who have deserved well of the republic, has its influence
                over us even after they are dead. And because men saw him always morose, always
                taciturn, always neglectful of his appearance and coarse-looking, and because his
                name was such that frugality appeared a quality innate in his family, they favoured
                him, and rejoiced, and in their hopes called him a man fashioned after the model of
                the integrity of his ancestors, forgetting the family of his mother. <milestone
                    n="22" unit="section"/> But I, (I will tell the plain truth, O judges,)—I myself
                never thought that there could be so much wickedness, audacity, <pb n="161"/> and
                cruelty in any man as, to my own cost and that of the republic, I have experienced
                that there was in him. I knew the man was worthless inconsistent and that it was a
                pure mistake that made men think well of him deceived by the appearance of his
                youth. His disposition, in truth, was concealed by his countenance, and his vices
                within walls, but this sort of disguise is never continued, nor so well maintained
                that it cannot be seen through by inquisitive eyes. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>We saw the course of his life his indolence and sloth; those who were in the least
                acquainted with him saw his secret licentiousness. Moreover, he gave us, by his
                conversation, plenty of handles to enable us to grasp and comprehend his inmost
                feelings. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Being a very learned man, he used to
                praise philosophers,—I don't know which, and indeed he could not tell their names
                himself;—but still he used to praise those above all others who were said to be
                beyond all the rest the admirers and panegyrists of pleasures: of what sort of
                pleasure,—of pleasure enjoyed at what times and in what manner he never inquired but
                the name itself he devoured with all the energy of his mind and body. And he used to
                say that those same philosophers were right when they said that wise men do
                everything for the sake of themselves, that no man in his senses has any business to
                trouble himself about the government of the republic; that nothing is better than a
                life of ease, full of, and loaded with, all sorts of pleasures and he used to say
                that those men who said that men ought to regard their own dignity, and to consult
                the interests of the republic, and to have a regard in every action of life to duty
                and not to advantage, that men ought to undergo dangers on behalf of their country,
                and to encounter wounds and to seek even death for its sake, were crazy and mad.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> And from these incessant and daily
                conversations of his, and because I saw who the men were with whom he lived in the
                more retired part of his house, and because his house itself (as I may say) smoked
                so as to emit a steam from his discourse, and to show what he was about, I made up
                my mind that nothing good was to be looked for from such a trifler; but at the same
                time certainly that no evil need be feared. But the fact is, O judges, that, if you
                give a sword to a little child, or to a powerless and decrepit old man, he himself
                by his own violence cannot injure any one, but still if the sword touches the <pb
                    n="162"/> naked body of even the strongest man, it is possible that he may be
                wounded by the mere sharpness and power of the weapon; in like manner, when the
                consulship had been given as a sword to enervated and worn-out men, who, of their
                own strength, would never be able to wound any one, they, armed with the name of
                supreme command, murdered the republic. They openly made a treaty with the tribune
                of the people, to receive from him whatever provinces they chose, and an army, and
                as much money as they chose, on this condition,—that they themselves were the first
                to hand over the afflicted republic in fetters to the tribune. And they thought that
                that treaty could be ratified in my blood. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> And
                when this matter was divulged, (for such enormous wickedness could not be dissembled
                or hidden for any length of time,) motions are proposed at one and the same time by
                the same tribune, concerning my destruction and concerning the provinces of the
                consuls, allotting them to each of them by name. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>On this, the senate being anxious, you knights being in a state of great excitement,
                all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> being agitated,—in short, all
                citizens of every sort and of every rank, thought that they must seek help for the
                republic from the consuls and from the supreme power, while they were the only men,
                besides that frantic tribune,—those two whirlwinds (so to say) of the republic,—who
                not only did not come to the assistance of their falling country, but who even
                grieved that it was falling so slowly. They were every day solicited both by the
                complaints of all good men, and by the direct entreaties of the senate, to undertake
                my cause, to act on my behalf, and to bring some proposition before the senate. They
                attacked all the most eminent men of that body, not only refusing their request but
                even laughing at it. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> But when on a sudden an
                incredible multitude from the whole city, and from all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>, had assembled at the Capitol, they all decided that they
                should put on mourning garments and defend me in every possible way by their private
                resources, since the republic was destitute for the time of its public leaders. At
                the same time the senate was assembled in the temple of Concord, a temple which of
                itself recalled the recollection of my consulship, when the whole body in tears
                addressed this curled consul with entreaties; for the other rough and fierce-looking
                one was keeping himself at home on purpose. With what haughtiness did <pb n="163"/>
                that filthy fellow, that pest of the republic, reject the prayers of that most
                honourable body, and the tears of the most illustrious citizens. How did that
                glutton and devourer of his country scorn me! For why should I say devourer of his
                patrimony, which he lost while engaged in some sort of trade? You, I say,—you, O
                Roman knights,—you and all virtuous men changed your garments, and in the cause of
                my safety threw yourselves at the feet of that most profligate debauchee. You and
                your prayers were alike trampled on by that robber. A man of extraordinary
                integrity, magnanimity, wisdom, and firmness, Lucius Ninnius made a motion to the
                senate concerning the republic and the senate in a full house passed a resolution
                that they should change their garments for my safety. <milestone n="12"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="27" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Alas for that day, O judges, fatal to the senate and to all good men! grievous to the
                republic! bitter for me as far as my domestic grief was concerned, but glorious as
                relates to my fame in the eyes of posterity. For what since the first beginning of
                human memory, can any one produce more splendid than for all good men by their own
                tacit agreement as individuals and for the whole senate by public resolution to have
                changed their garments and put on mourning for the sake of a single citizen? And
                that change of dress was not adopted at that time for the sake of averting a
                calamity from me by entreaty, but to show their grief at that which had befallen me.
                For to whom could they address their entreaties, when all were in mourning alike,
                and when the fact of a man's not having changed his dress was a sufficient proof of
                his being an ill-disposed person? After this change of garments had taken place, and
                while the city was in such grief, I say nothing of what that tribune, that plunderer
                of all things both human and divine, proceeded to do; a fellow who ordered all the
                most noble youths, and the most honourable Roman knights who were eager to entreat
                him to ensure my safety, to attend at his house, and who then exposed them to the
                swords and stones of his troop of artisans. I am speaking now of the consuls, on
                whose good faith the republic had a right to rely. <milestone n="28" unit="section"
                /> Frightened out of his wits, he flies from the senate with a mind and countenance
                less agitated than it would have been a few years before, if he had fallen in with a
                crowd of his creditors. He convenes an assembly. He, the consul, addresses them in
                such a speech as even Catiline himself, <pb n="164"/> if he had been victorious,
                would never have delivered. He said “that men were greatly mistaken if they thought
                that the senate had any power in the republic; and that the Roman knights should
                suffer severely for that day on which, in my consulship, they had appeared with
                their swords on the <placeName key="tgn,7006963">Capitoline Hill</placeName>: that
                the time had come for those who had been in fear” (he evidently meant the
                conspirators) “to avenge themselves.” If he had said no more than this, he would
                have been worthy of the last extremity of punishment; for a mischievous speech of a
                consul can of itself undermine the republic. But see now what he did. <milestone
                    n="29" unit="section"/> In that assembly he banished Lucius Lamia, who was
                exceedingly attached to me on account of the exceeding intimacy which subsisted
                between me and his brother and his father, and who was also willing to encounter
                even death itself for the sake of the republic; and issued an edict that he should
                remove two hundred miles from the city because he had dared to address solicitations
                to him on behalf of a citizen,—of a citizen who had deserved well of the state, and
                who was his own friend,—and on behalf of the republic. <milestone n="13"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>What can you do with this man? or for what punishment can you reserve this profligate
                citizen,—I should rather say this impious enemy? who, to pass over other particulars
                of his character, and other actions which belong to him in common with his infamous
                and savage colleague, has this one thing to boast of peculiar to himself, that he
                expelled from the city and banished (I will not say a Roman knight, I will not say a
                most accomplished and virtuous man, I will not say a citizen deeply attached to the
                republic, I will not say a man who was only joining his own lamentations for the
                calamity of his friend and of the republic to those of the senate and of all good
                men; it is enough to say that)—he, the consul, banished a Roman citizen without any
                trial, by his own simple edict. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/> The Latin allies
                had never anything worse to submit to than (and it was a case of very rare
                occurrence) the being ordered by the consul to depart from the city. And they had
                the power then of returning to their own cities, to their own household gods; and in
                that general disaster no peculiar ignominy was attached by name to any single
                individual. But what is the case here? Is the consul to banish, by his edict, Roman
                citizens from their household gods? is he to <pb n="165"/> expel them from their
                country? is he to select whom he pleases? to condemn and banish men by name? If he
                had supposed that you, who are now sitting here, would continue to exist in the
                republic,—if he had supposed that any image of the courts of justice would remain or
                that there would be the least vestige of the old constitution left in the state
                would he even have dared to wipe the senate out of the republic in this way? to
                reject the prayers of the Roman knights? in short, to overturn the rights and
                liberties of all the citizens by new and unheard of edicts? <milestone n="31"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Although you are listening to me, O judges, with the greatest attention, and with
                exceeding kindness, still I fear that some of you may, perchance, marvel why I am so
                prolix, and what is my object in tracing things back so far, or what connection the
                offences of those men who harassed the republic before the tribuneship of Publius
                Sestius have with his cause now. But my desire is to show that all the counsels of
                Publius Sestius, and the whole object of his tribuneship, was to remedy the
                misfortunes of the afflicted and ruined republic as far as was in his power. And
                pardon me, if in laying open those wounds, I appear to say rather too much about
                myself; for you and all good men decided that that disaster which befell me was the
                heaviest possible blow to the republic. And Publius Sestius is now on his trial, not
                on his own account, but on mine —for as he devoted all the powers of his tribuneship
                to the promotion of my safety it is inevitable that I should look upon my own cause
                in past time as united with the defence which I am now making for him. <milestone
                    n="14" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="32" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>The senate then was in grief, the city wore an appearance of mourning, its garments
                having been changed in accordance with the public resolution of the senate. There
                was no municipal town in all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, no
                colony, no prefecture, no company of men concerned in farming the public revenues,
                no guild or council,—no public body, in short, of any kind whatever,—which had not
                passed most honourable resolutions concerning my safety, when all on a sudden the
                two consuls issue an edict that the senators are to return to their former dress.
                What consul ever prohibited the senate from obeying its own decrees? What tyrant
                ever forbade men who were miserable to mourn? Is it a small thing, O Piso,—for I
                will say nothing about Gabinius, that you have deceived men to such a degree as to
                disregard the authority of the senate? to <pb n="166"/> despise the advice of every
                virtuous man? to betray the republic? to crush a citizen of consular rank? that you
                must dare also to issue an edict that men are not to mourn for a disaster affecting
                me, and themselves, and the republic, and are not to show their grief by changing
                their garments? Whether that change of garment was assumed as a token of grief, or
                as a form of solicitation, who ever was so cruel before as to forbid any one
                mourning for himself, or entreating for others? <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                What? Are not men accustomed of their own accord to change their garments on the
                occasion of danger to their friends? Is there no one who will change it ever for
                you, O Piso? will not even those men do so whom you have appointed as your
                lieutenants, not only without any resolution of the senate to authorize such a step,
                but even in defiance of a vote of that body? shall, then, whoever pleases mourn for
                the misfortune of a desperate man, of a traitor to the commonwealth, and shall not
                the senate be allowed to mourn for the danger of a citizen, strong above all men in
                the good-will of all virtuous men, who has deserved admirably well of his country,
                which he has saved, especially when with his danger is combined danger to the whole
                state? </p>
            <p>Those same consuls, (if, indeed, it is proper to call those men consuls who, every
                one thinks, deserve not only to be eradicated from men's memories, but to have their
                names erased from the consular registers,) after the treaty about the provinces had
                been ratified, being brought forward to the assembly in the Flaminian Circus by that
                fury and pest of his country, amid universal grief on the part of all of you, gave
                their verbal sanction and formal decision in approval of all the things which that
                fellow had then uttered against me and against the republic. <milestone n="15"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>In the presence and sight of these same consuls, a law was passed that the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign> were to have no validity; that no one was to
                interrupt any proceeding by declaring that he was taking them; that no one was to
                have the power of arresting a law by his veto; that it should be lawful to pass a
                law on all days of festival; that the Aelian<note anchored="true">“The <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Lex Aelia</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">Lex
                        Fufia</foreign> were passed about the end of the sixth century, and gave all
                    magistrates the power of dissolving the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>
                    by <foreign xml:lang="la">obnuntiatio</foreign>, i.e. by observing the omens,
                    and declaring them unfavourable.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 560.</note> and Fufian
                laws should have no validity. And who is there who can fail to see that by <pb
                    n="167"/> that one motion, the entire constitution was destroyed? <milestone
                    n="34" unit="section"/> In the presence and sight of these same consuls, a levy
                of slaves was held before the tribunal of Aurelius, under pretence of filling up the
                guilds, when men were enrolled according to their streets, and divided into
                decuries, and stirred up to violence, and battle, and slaughter, and plunder. It was
                while these same men were consuls, that arms were openly carried into the temple of
                Castor, and the steps of the temple were pulled up; armed men occupied the forum and
                the assemblies of the people; slaughters and stonings of people took place; there
                was no senate, no magistrates were left; one man by arms and piratical violence
                seized on all the power of all the magistrates not by any power of his own, but
                having bribed the two consuls to desert the republic by the treaty respecting the
                provinces, he insulted every one, domineered over every one, made promises to some
                held down many by terror and fear and gained over more by hope and promises. </p>
            <p><milestone n="35" unit="section"/> And when such was the state of all things, O
                judges,—when the senate had no leaders or traitors, or I should rather say open
                enemies, in the place of leaders,—when the equestrian order was being put on its
                trial by the consuls,—when the authority of all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName> was trampled on,—when some men were banished by name others
                frightened away by terror and danger,—when the temples were full of arms and the
                forum of armed men; and when those facts were not concealed by the silence of the
                consuls, but were openly approved of by them by their speeches and their formal
                decision,—when we all of us saw the city not yet perhaps razed and destroyed, but at
                all events already stormed and in the power of the enemy,—nevertheless relying on
                the exceeding zeal of the virtuous part of the citizens, we would have resisted, O
                judges, even these enormous evils. <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="36" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But there were other grounds for fear, and other reasons for anxiety and suspicion, O
                judges, which influenced me at that time. For I will explain to you this day, O
                judges, all the principles of my conduct and of my designs; and I will not be
                wanting to your great desire of hearing the truth, nor to this multitude, the
                greatest which within my recollection, has ever appeared in any court of justice.
                For if I, in so good a cause, when supported so zealously by the senate, and by such
                an inconceivable unanimity on the part of all <pb n="168"/> virtuous men, ready to
                act in my behalf, and when all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> was
                stirred up and braced for the contest,—yielded to the fury of a tribune of the
                people, one of the most despicable of men; if I was afraid of the trifling but
                audacious characters of those most contemptible consuls, then I should be forced to
                confess that I was too timid, that I was a man of no courage, of no decision, and of
                no wisdom. <milestone n="37" unit="section"/> For what was there in the case of
                Quintus Metellus similar to mine? Although all good men considered that he had right
                on his side, yet the senate did not espouse his cause by any public resolution, nor
                did any separate body of men by any private vote, nor had all <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> undertaken the advocacy of his cause by
                their decrees. For he had shown greater regard for some sort of private credit of
                his own, than for the manifest welfare of the republic, when he alone had refused to
                swear to a law which had been passed by means of violence; and lastly, his great
                bravery appeared to be exercised with this qualification, that his own credit for
                consistency was not to be sacrificed to his affection for his country. But he had to
                contend against the invincible army of Caius Marius; he had for an enemy Caius
                Marius, the preserver of his country, now for the sixth time administering the
                affairs of the republic as consul. He had to contend against Lucius Saturninus, now
                for a second time tribune of the people; a vigilant man, and one who in a popular
                cause conducted himself, if not with moderation, at all events with due regard to
                the prejudices of the people, and in a very disinterested spirit. He yielded, lest,
                being conquered by brave men, he should fall disgracefully, or lest, if conqueror
                himself, he should deprive the republic of many gallant citizens. </p>
            <p><milestone n="38" unit="section"/> But my cause was embraced openly by the senate,
                with the greatest energy by the equestrian order, by all <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> by means of public resolutions, and by all
                good men with the greatest earnestness, as if it were their own personal quarrel. I
                had performed achievements with regard to which I had not been the sole originator
                of them, but the leader of the universal inclination of all the citizens; and which
                were designed to promote not my own single glory, but the common safety of all the
                citizens—I may almost say of all nations. And I had performed them in such a manner
                that all men were bound at all times to uphold and defend my conduct.<pb n="169"/>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And I had to contend not against a victorious army, but against a lot of hired
                artisans, men excited with the hope of plundering the city. I had for an enemy,—not
                Caius Marius, the terror of our enemies, the hope and support of his country,—but
                two ill-omened monsters whom want and the immensity of their debts and fickleness
                and a wicked disposition, had delivered over to the tribune of the people as his
                slaves. <milestone n="39" unit="section"/> Nor had I to contend against Saturninus,
                who was seeking to satisfy his own indignation with great earnestness of mind,
                because he knew that the superintendence of the import of provisions had been, as an
                intentional insult, transferred from him while he was quaestor at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Ostia">Ostia</placeName>, to the chief man both of the senate and
                of the city, Marcus Scaurus. But I had to struggle with the debauched favourite of
                wealthy buffoons, with the adulterer of his sister, with the very high-priest of
                lewdness, with a poisoner, with a forger of wills, with an assassin, with a robber;
                and if—as was very easy to be done, as ought to have been done, and as many most
                virtuous and brave citizens entreated me to do—I had overcome those men by force and
                arms, I had no reason to fear that any one would reprove me for having repelled
                force by force, or grieve for the death of those abandoned citizens, or, as I should
                rather call them, domestic enemies. But these were the things which had weight with
                me. That Fury was in the habit of crying out in all the assemblies that all the
                things which he was doing to the prejudice of my safety, he was doing with the
                approval of Cnaeus Pompeius a most illustrious man, and both then and now a most
                intimate friend of mine as far as he was able to show himself such. Marcus Crassus a
                most gallant man with whom I had every imaginable intimacy of friendship, was
                announced by that same pest to be most hostile to my fortunes. Caius Caesar, who had
                no right to he alienated from me as far as any action of mine could have deserved
                such feelings on his part, was constantly stated by the same man in his daily
                harangues to be a most determined enemy to my safety. <milestone n="40"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>These three men he said he was going to avail himself of as his advisers in forming
                all his plans, and as his assistants in all his actions: of whom he said that one
                had the most numerous army in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; and
                that the other two, who were private men at that time, could easily get an army
                a-piece if <pb n="170"/> they chose, and that they would do so. And while he menaced
                me, he threatened me, not with a judicial decision of the people, nor with any legal
                or legitimate sort of contest, nor with any discussion or regular trial of our
                dispute, but with violence, and arms, and armies, and generals, and camps.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>What then? Did the harangue of an enemy, especially so foolish a one as that, and
                aimed as it was so wickedly against the most illustrious men, move me? No. It was
                not his speech, but the silence of those men against whom that most infamous speech
                was directed that influenced me. For they—although the real cause of their silence
                was quite a different one—appeared, nevertheless, to men who were afraid of
                everything, by their very silence to speak, and by their forbearing to deny his
                assertions, to confess them. </p>
            <p><milestone n="41" unit="section"/> But they, being then under the influence of
                excessive fear, because they thought that those actions and all the events of the
                preceding year were being undermined by the praetors, and annulled by the senate and
                by the chief men of the city, were unwilling to alienate a popular tribune of the
                people from their interests, and were in the habit of saying that their own dangers
                touched them more nearly than mine. But still Crassus said that my cause ought to be
                undertaken by the consuls, and Pompeius implored the aid of their good faith; and he
                said that he, though a private individual, would not desert the cause which was
                taken up by public authority. And as he was most anxious for my welfare, and eager
                beyond measure for the preservation of the republic, certain men, trained for that
                purpose, warned him to be more careful; and said that a plot was laid against his
                life, to be carried into execution in my house; and they kept this suspicion alive
                in him, some by letters, some by messengers, some by coming and talking to him about
                it; so that he, though most certainly he had no fear of me, yet thought it necessary
                to guard against them, lest they should attempt anything against him and lay the
                blame on me. But Caesar himself, who those men, ignorant of the truth, thought was
                angry with me most especially, was at the gates, was in military command; his army
                was in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, and in that army he had
                appointed to a command the brother of that very tribune of the people, my enemy.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="42" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>When I saw all this (for there was no secret about it), that the senate, without
                which the constitution could not <pb n="171"/> stand, was entirely abolished out of
                the city; that the consuls whose duty it was to be the leaders of the public
                counsels, had so managed matters that by their means the great public council was
                entirely destroyed; that those men who had the greatest influence were held up to
                every assembly, (falsely indeed, but still in a way calculated to strike my friends
                with great fear,) as the great approvers of my ruin; that assemblies were held every
                day in opposition to me; that no one ever uttered a word in defence of me or of the
                republic that the standards of the legions were believed to be unfurled against your
                lives and properties, (falsely indeed, but still they were believed to be so,) that
                the veteran troops of the conspirators, and that ill-omened army of Catiline, once
                routed and defeated, was now recruited under a new leader and under the existing
                unexpected chances of circumstances;—when I saw all these things, what was I to do,
                O judges? <milestone n="43" unit="section"/> For I know well that at that time it
                was not your zeal that was wanting to me, but more nearly my energy that was wanting
                to second your zeal. Was I, a private individual, to struggle in arms against a
                tribune of the people? No doubt the good would have defeated the wicked, the brave
                would have defeated the inactive; he would have been slain who could by no other
                remedy be prevented from being the ruin of the republic. What would have happened
                next? What would have become of the remains of his party? What would have been the
                end? Was there any doubt that the blood of the tribune especially when not shed in
                consequence of any public resolution would have had the consuls for its avengers?
                especially when we recollect that that fellow had said in the public assembly that I
                must either perish once or be victorious twice. What was the meaning of my having to
                conquer twice? Why no doubt that after I had struggled against that most senseless
                tribune of the people, I should have to struggle with the consuls and with all those
                who would avenge him. But for myself,—<milestone n="44" unit="section"/>if I alone
                was to have perished, and if that incurable and deadly wound would not also have
                been inevitably inflicted on the republic, with which he threatened it—I should have
                preferred at that time, O judges, to perish once rather than conquer twice. For that
                second struggle would have been such, that whether we were conquered or conquerors,
                we should have been alike unable to preserve the republic. What would have <pb
                    n="172"/> happened if in the first struggle, being overcome by the violence of
                the tribune, I had fallen in the forum, with many virtuous citizens? The consuls, I
                imagine, would have convened the senate, which they had already expunged from the
                state; they would summon men to arms who had decided that the republic should not be
                upheld, no not even by a change of garments; they would, no doubt, have been sure to
                revolt from the tribune of the people after my death, who had intended the same hour
                to be that of my ruin and of their own reward! <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="45" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>That one thing remained for me which, perhaps, some men of bold, and energetic, and
                magnanimous mind will say,—“You should have struggled, you should have resisted, you
                should have fought to the death.” With respect to which idea, I call you to witness,
                you my country, and you, O household gods, and gods of my country, that it was for
                the sake of your abodes and temples, that it was on account of the safety of my own
                fellow-citizens, which has always been dearer to me than my own life, that I avoided
                combat and bloodshed. In truth, O judges, if it had happened to me when I was
                sailing in some ship with my friends, that many pirates coming from many parts
                threatened to overwhelm that vessel with their fleets, unless they surrendered me
                alone to them; if the crew had refused to do so, and had preferred rather to perish
                with me than to surrender me to the enemy, I should have thrown myself into the sea
                in order to save the rest, rather than bring those who were so devoted to me, if not
                to certain death, at all events into great danger of their lives. </p>
            <p><milestone n="46" unit="section"/> But when, after the helm had been wrested from the
                senate, so many armed fleets appeared ready to attack the vessel of the republic,
                tossed about on the deep by the tempests of sedition and discord, unless I alone
                were surrendered; when proscription, and plunder, and massacre were threatened; when
                some stood aloof from defending me from suspicion that their doing so might bring
                themselves into danger, and some were prompted by their long-standing hatred of all
                good men, and some envied me, and some thought that I was in their way, and some
                wished to revenge some grief or other which they had suffered, and some were
                influenced by hatred of the republic itself, and of the present state and
                tranquillity of good men, and on account of all these numerous and <pb n="175"/>
                various causes were demanding me alone to be given up to them,—was I to fight
                against them to the extreme, I will not say destruction, but danger at all events,
                of you and your children, rather than by myself encounter and endure on behalf of
                all that evil which was impending over all? <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="47" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>No doubt the wicked would have been defeated. Still they would have been citizens and
                they would have been defeated by that man as a private individual, who as consul,
                without any appeal to arms, had preserved the republic. But suppose the good men had
                been defeated, what would have remained? Do not you see that the state would have
                fallen into the hands of the slaves? Was even I myself as some people think to
                encounter death with entire equanimity? What? Was I at that time seeking to avoid
                death? or was there anything which I could think more desirable for myself, or at
                the very time that I was accomplishing these great exploits amid that multitude of
                wicked men, were not death and exile constantly present to my eyes? Were not these
                very events, even at the moment of my performance of those exploits, prophesied as
                it were by me as parts of my destiny? Or was life worth preserving at a time when
                all my family and friends were in such grief when there was such confusion such
                misery such destruction of everything which either nature or fortune had given me?
                Was I so stupid? so ignorant of affairs? so destitute of all sense and all ability?
                Had I heard nothing? Had I seen nothing? Had I learnt nothing myself by reading or
                by inquiry? Was I ignorant that the duration of life is brief, that of glory
                everlasting? that, as death was appointed for all men, it was desirable that life,
                which must some day or other be given up to necessity, should appear to have been
                made a present of to one's country rather than reserved for the claim of nature? Was
                I ignorant that there had been this dispute between the wisest men? that some said
                that the souls and senses of men were extinguished by death; but that others thought
                that the minds of wise and brave men were then in the greatest degree sensible and
                vigorous when they had departed from the body? And one of these alternatives would
                seem to show, that to be deprived of feeling was not a thing to be avoided; the
                other alternative must evidently be very desirable, to become possessed of a more
                perfect sensation. <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="174"/>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, as I had always considered everything with reference to what was becoming,
                and had never thought anything in life desirable if unaccompanied by propriety, was
                I, a man of consular rank, who had performed such great deeds, likely to be afraid
                of death, which even Athenian maidens, daughters I fancy of king Erectheus, are said
                to have despised in the cause of their country? Especially when I was a member of
                that city from which Mucius went forth when he penetrated,—by himself, into the camp
                of king Porsena, and endeavoured to slay him, at the imminent risk of his own life;
                from which, in the first instance, Decius the father, and many years afterwards his
                son, endowed with his father's virtue, went forth when, while their armies were
                drawn up in battle array, they devoted themselves and their own lives to ensure the
                safety and victory of the Roman army; from which a countless host of others besides
                have gone forth, and with the greatest equanimity have encountered death, some for
                the sake of gaining glory, and some with the object of encountering disgrace; and
                while I, myself, remember that in this city the father of this Marcus Crassus, a
                most gallant man, put himself to death with that same hand with which he had often
                scattered death among the enemy, that he might not live to see his enemy victorious.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="49" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Influenced by these and many other considerations, I saw that, if my death were the
                destruction of the common cause of the state, no one would ever live who would
                venture to undertake the defence of the safety of the republic against wicked
                citizens. Therefore, I feared that the result would be, not only if I were put to
                death by violence, but even if I died from natural causes, that the example of a man
                labouring for the preservation of the republic would perish with me. For if, while
                all good men were so eager for it, I were not restored by the senate and people of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, (and most unquestionably that
                could never have happened if I had been killed first,) who would ever dare
                afterwards to encounter the very slightest unpopularity for the sake of having
                anything to do with the affairs of the republic? I, therefore, saved the republic, O
                judges, by my departure. At the expense of my own grief and misery I averted
                slaughter, and devastation, and conflagration, and plunder, from you and from your
                children. And I, by myself, twice saved the republic once with glory, once <pb
                    n="175"/> with misery. That I will never so far deny that I have the feelings of
                a man as to boast that I felt no grief when I was deprived of my most excellent
                brother, of my most beloved children, of my most faithful wife, of the sight of you,
                my fellow-citizens, of my country, and of my rank as a senator. If those had been my
                feelings, what obligation would you be under to me, if for your sake I had only
                abandoned those things which I considered of no value? This, in my opinion, ought to
                be considered by you a most certain token of my exceeding devotion to my country,
                that though I could not be absent from her without the deepest grief, yet I
                preferred to endure this grief, rather than to allow her to be destroyed by wicked
                citizens. <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>I recollected, O judges, that that godlike man, sprung from the same district as
                myself, for the preservation of this empire, Caius Marius, in extreme old age, when
                he had escaped from violence little short of a pitched battle, first of all hid his
                aged body up to his neck in the marshes and from thence crossed over in a very
                little boat to the most desolate regions of <placeName key="tgn,7001242"
                    >Africa</placeName>, avoiding all harbours and all inhabited countries. And he
                preserved his own life, that he might not fall unavenged, for the most uncertain
                hopes, but still for his country. Should not I, who (as many men in the senate said
                during my absence) had the safety of the republic bound up with my life, and who on
                that account was by the public order of the senate, recommended by the letters of
                the consuls to the protection of foreign nations,—should not I, I say, have been
                betraying the republic if I had neglected the preservation of my own life? In the
                city now since I have been restored there lives in my person an example of the
                public good faith, an instance of its being worth men's while to defend the
                republic. And if this example is preserved for ever who is there who can fail to see
                that this city will be immortal? <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="51"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For the foreign wars waged against us by foreign kings, countries, and nations, have
                long been so completely put down, that they are treating them, to our own great
                credit, as people whom we can allow to remain at peace. Moreover it has not been a
                common thing for unpopularity to attach itself to any one of the citizens on account
                of any warlike triumphs. We often have to resist domestic evils and the counsels of
                audacious citizens; and it is indispensable to <pb n="176"/> retain in the republic
                a remedy for these dangers; all which, O judges, you would have lost if the power of
                declaring its grief at my position had been taken from the senate and people of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> by my death. Wherefore, I warn
                you, O young men, and I enjoin you by the right which belongs to me to do so, you
                who have a regard for propriety, for the republic, and for glory, not to be slow, if
                at any time any necessity summons you to defend the republic against worthless
                citizens, and not, from any recollection of what has happened to me, to shun bold
                counsels. <milestone n="52" unit="section"/> In the first place, there is no danger
                of any one ever falling in with such consuls as these, especially if these are
                requited as they deserve. In the second place, there never will again, I hope, be an
                instance of any wicked man saying that he is attacking the republic with the
                approval and assistance of virtuous citizens, while they keep silence; nor of such a
                man's threatening citizens in the garb of peace with the terrors of an armed
                soldiery; nor will there be any excuse for a general stationed with his army at the
                gates, allowing the terror of his name to be used as an instrument for opposing and
                alarming the citizens. For the senate will never be so oppressed as to have no power
                of even entreating or lamenting; the equestrian order will never be bound hand and
                foot so completely as to allow Roman knights to be banished by the consul. But yet
                even after all these things had happened, and many other more important events also,
                which I pass over designedly, still you see that, after a short interval of
                suffering, I was recalled to the enjoyment of my former dignity by the voice of the
                republic. <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="53" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But to return to that point which is the one which I have particularly proposed to
                myself to establish in this speech; namely, that the republic was afflicted and
                oppressed by every sort of calamity that year owing to the wickedness of the
                consuls. First of all, on that very day which was fatal to me and grievous to all
                good men, when I had torn myself from the embrace of my country and from your sight,
                O fellow-citizens, and when from fear of danger to you, not to myself, I had yielded
                to the frenzy, and wickedness, and treachery, and arms, and threats of one man, and
                had abandoned my country, which was the dearest of all things to me, out of
                affection for my country herself; when not only men but the very houses and temples
                of the city were lamenting <pb n="177"/> that misfortune which befell me,—so
                horrible, so lamentable, and so sudden; when no one of you could bear the sight of
                the forum, or of the senate house, or of the light of day; on that very day, do I
                say? at that very hour, at that very same moment, at that very instant of ruin to me
                and to the republic, their provinces were decreed to Gabinius and to Piso. O ye
                immortal gods, guardians and preservers of this city and empire, what monsters of
                wickedness, what crimes have you beheld in the republic! That citizen was expelled
                who, in compliance with the authority of the senate, had defended the republic with
                the cooperation of all good men and he was expelled, not because of any other charge
                being brought against him, but expressly because he had done so. And he was expelled
                without any trial, by violence, by stones, by arms, by bodies of slaves excited to
                sedition. A law was passed after the forum had been desolated and abandoned, and
                given over to assassins and to slaves; a law to prevent the passing of which the
                senate had changed its dress and gone into mourning. <milestone n="54"
                    unit="section"/> The city being in this state of confusion, the consuls did not
                allow even one night to elapse between my misfortune and their acquisition of
                plunder. Instantly, the moment that I was struck down, they flew to drink my blood,
                and, while the republic was still breathing, to carry off and divide my spoils. I
                say nothing of their mutual congratulations, of their banquets, of their division of
                the treasury, of their liberality, of their hopes, of their promises, of their booty
                of the joy of a few amid the universal mourning. My wife was attacked, my children
                sought for in order to be murdered, my son-in-law,—yes, my son-in-law, Piso, was
                rejected as a suppliant by Piso the consul after he had thrown himself at his feet;
                my property was plundered and carried off to the houses of the consuls; my house was
                burnt on the <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine Hill</placeName>; the consuls
                passed the time in revels and joy. But even if they were rejoiced at my distress,
                they ought to have been moved at the dangers of the city. <milestone n="25"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="55" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But, however, to give up dwelling on my own case, recollect the rest of the
                calamities of that year. For by that means you will most easily perceive what a
                rigorous application of all sorts of remedies the republic required from the next
                magistrates, and what a multitude of laws wanted remedying, both such as had been
                passed, and such as had been <pb n="178"/> only proposed. For some were passed while
                those consuls (shall I say, were silent respecting them? Yes, rather while they)
                actually approved of them; laws, that the notice of the censors and the most
                important decisions of the most holy magistrates should be abolished; that not only
                those ancient guilds which had existed before should be restored in defiance of the
                resolution of the senate, but that innumerable new ones should be established by one
                gladiator; that by abandoning the collection of the half as, and third of an as,
                nearly one-fifth part of our revenues should be destroyed; that <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> should be given to Gabinius instead of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, which he had bargained for, if
                he succeeded in betraying the republic; that one glutton should have the power of
                deliberating twice over about the same thing, and that he might propose a new law
                for the purpose of changing his province, after one law had been actually passed on
                that subject. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="56" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>I say nothing about that law which at one swoop destroyed all religious observances,
                all the privileges attached to the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, to the
                civil magistrates, and all the enactments which refer to the common law, and to the
                time of proposing laws; I say nothing about all the internal misfortunes which
                afflicted us; we saw even foreign nations shaken by the insanity of that year. </p>
            <p>By a law proposed by a tribune of the people, the priest of the Mighty Mother at
                    <placeName key="tgn,6004655">Pessinus</placeName> was expelled and stripped of
                his priesthood; and that shrine of the most holy and most ancient of all religious
                ceremonies was sold for a large sum to Brogitarus, a profligate man, and unworthy of
                any such sacred character; especially as he had desired it not for the purpose of
                doing honour to the goddess, but only of profaning her temple. People were styled
                kings by the people, who would never have even asked for such a title from the
                senate: condemned exiles were brought back to <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium"
                    >Byzantium</placeName> at the very time when citizens, who had not been
                condemned, were being driven from the city. <milestone n="57" unit="section"/> King
                Ptolemaeus, who, if he had not as yet been himself styled an ally by the senate, was
                at all events the brother of that king, who, while his cause was identical with his,
                had long since received that honour from the senate; and was of the same family,
                sprung from the same ancestors as his brother, and had the same claims from the
                antiquity of his alliance; who, lastly, was a king, and if <pb n="179"/> not yet an
                ally, still most certainly not an enemy; was enjoying the kingdom which had belonged
                to his father and his grandfather in peace and quiet, relying on the sovereign power
                of the Roman people in a condition of royal ease and tranquillity. While he was
                never thinking of any such thing, never suspecting any such thing, a motion was made
                and put to the vote of the same troop of labourers and artisans that he while
                sitting on his throne, with his purple and sceptre and all the other ensigns of
                royal authority, should be placed at the mercy of a public crier;—a motion was made,
                I say that the Roman people, which has been in the habit of restoring their kingdoms
                even to those kings whom they have subdued in war, should order that a king who was
                a friend of the nation, who was not even said to have done them any injury, who had
                never had any claim preferred against him or any demand for the restitution of
                anything, should have all his property confiscated and sold with his own person and
                liberty. <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="58" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>That year was a year of many cruel, of many shameful, of many turbulent proceedings,
                but I know not whether I ought not deservedly to call this the nearest in iniquity
                to that crime which their wickedness committed against me. Our ancestors determined
                that that celebrated Antiochus called the Great, after he had been subdued in a long
                and arduous struggle by land and seas, should be king over the districts within
                Mount Taurus. They gave <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, of which they
                deprived him, to Attalus, that he should be king over that district. With Tigranes,
                king of the Armenians, we waged a serious war of very long duration; he having, I
                may almost say, challenged us, by inflicting wanton injuries on our allies. He was
                not truly a vigorous enemy on his own power and on his own account, but he also
                defended with all his resources and protected in his territory, that most active
                enemy of this empire, Mithridates, after he had been driven from <placeName
                    key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>; and after he had been defeated by Lucullus
                that most excellent man and most consummate general, he still remained in his former
                mind, and kept up a hostile feeling against us with the remainder of his army. And
                yet this man did Cnaeus Pompeius—after he had seen him in his camp as a suppliant
                and in an abject condition—raise up and placed on his head again the royal crown
                which he himself had taken off, and, having imposed certain conditions <pb n="180"/>
                on him, ordered to continue king. And he thought it no less glorious for himself and
                for this empire, that the king should be known to he restored by him, than if he had
                kept him in bonds. <milestone n="59" unit="section"/> Therefore, Tigranes—who was
                himself an enemy of the Roman people, and who received our most active enemy in his
                territories, who struggled against us, who fought pitched battles with us, and who
                compelled us to combat almost for our very existence and supremacy—is a king to this
                day, and has obtained by his entreaties the name of a friend and ally, which he had
                previously forfeited by his hostile and warlike conduct. </p>
            <p>That unhappy king of <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>—who was always
                our ally, always our friend, concerning whom no single unfavourable suspicion was
                ever reported to the senate or to our commanders in those parts—has now, as they
                say, while alive and beholding the light, been seized and sold with all his means of
                support, and all his royal apparel. Here is a good reason for other kings thinking
                their own fortunes stable, when by this example, handed down to recollection from
                that fatal year, they see that one tribune and six hundred journeymen have power to
                despoil them of all their fortunes, and strip them of their whole kingdom!
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="60" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But they even designed to stain the character of Marcus Cato by that transaction;
                ignorant of the extent of such a man's wisdom, and integrity, and magnanimity, and
                virtue; which is tranquil during a terrible tempest, and shines amid the darkness,
                and, though driven from its proper position,<note anchored="true">Clodius had an old
                    grudge against Ptolemaeus king of Cyprus for refusing to ransom him once when be
                    was taken prisoner by pirates; and now, having proposed a law to reduce his
                    kingdom to the state of a province, and to confiscate all his property, he got
                    the execution of the decree given to Cato, partly to throw discredit on Cato,
                    and partly to oblige him to acknowledge the validity of his acts by submitting
                    to bear a part in them: and Cato was much pleased at the commission. Ptolemaeus,
                    as soon as he had heard of the law and of Cato's approach, poisoned himself in
                    despair.</note> still remains, and clings to his country, and shines at all
                times by its own unassisted light, and is never tarnished by the dirt or disgrace of
                others. Their object was, not to do honour to Marcus Cato, but to banish him. They
                did not think that they were entrusting that commission to him, but imposing it on
                him; and said openly in the assembly, that <pb n="181"/> they had cut Marcus Cato's
                tongue out, which had always spoken so freely against all extraordinary commissions.
                They will feel, I trust, in a short time, that that freedom of his still continues;
                and even if that be possible that it exists in a still greater degree from this
                circumstance, that Marcus Cato, even when he despaired of being any longer able to
                do any good by his authority, still with his voice and with every expression of
                indignation struggled against those consuls and, after my departure, weeping for my
                misfortune and for that of the republic, attacked
                    <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName> in such language, that he made that
                most abandoned and most shameless man almost repent of his bargain about the
                province </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>Why, then, did he obey the law?”as if he had not
                already sworn to obey other laws also which he considered to have been unjustly
                passed. He does not give in to such rash counsels, as to think himself at liberty to
                deprive the republic of his services as a citizen, when he can do no good to the
                republic. While I was consul and when he was tribune of the people elect he
                voluntarily exposed his own life to danger he delivered that opinion, the
                unpopularity of which be saw would be so great as to imperil his life. He spoke with
                vehemence; he acted with energy, what he felt he stated in the most open manner. He
                was the lender and the adviser and main advocate of those measures,—not that he did
                not see his own danger, but in such a storm as that which was threatening to
                overwhelm the republic, he thought that he ought not to think of anything but the
                dangers of his country. <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="62"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>His tribuneship followed. Why need I speak of his extraordinary magnanimity, and of
                his incredible virtue? You remember that day on which, when the temple was occupied
                by his colleague,<note anchored="true">Metellus Celer</note> and while we were all
                alarmed for the life of that good man and that great citizen, he himself came most
                courageously into the temple, stilled the clamours of the men by his authority and
                checked the violence of the wicked by his intrepidity. Then, indeed, he encountered
                danger, but he encountered it for an adequate reason and how great that motion was,
                it is not necessary for me to say at present. But if he had not obeyed that most
                wicked motion with respect to the affairs of <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
                    >Cyprus</placeName>, the same disgrace would nevertheless have attached to the
                republic. For after the kingdom had been confiscated, the motion was made about
                        <persName><surname>Cato</surname></persName> mentioning <pb n="182"/> him
                expressly by name. And suppose he had refused to obey it, can you doubt that
                violence would have been used towards him, since in that case all the acts of that
                year would have seemed to be undermined by that one man? <milestone n="63"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And he saw this also: since the stain attached to the republic of having confiscated
                that kingdom, a stain which no one could efface; he thought it more advantageous,
                that whatever good could arise to the republic out of those evils, should be secured
                by him rather than by others. And if, by any means whatever, he had been expelled
                out of the city at that time, he would have borne it easily. In truth, could he,—who
                in the former year had absented himself from the senate, though, if he had come
                thither, he would have been able to have me as the partner of all his counsels which
                concerned the government of the state,—could he, I say, have continued with
                equanimity in this city then, after I had been expelled, and with me the whole
                senate too, and when his own opinions had been condemned? But he yielded to the same
                time to which we did; to the same frenzy, to the same consuls, to the same threats,
                and plots, and dangers that we did ourselves. We, indeed, suffered the greatest
                misfortune of the two, but his indignation and grief of mind was not less than our
                own. <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="64" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>It is the consuls who ought to complain of these numerous and enormous injuries done
                to our allies, and to kings, and to free states. Kings and foreign nations have
                always been under the protection of that magistracy. But have any words of the
                consuls been heard on the subject? Although, indeed, who would listen to them if
                they wanted to complain ever so much? Could they make any complaint about the king
                of Cyprus, who not only did not defend me while I was still standing,—me, a
                fellow-citizen, who had no charge brought against me, who was attacked only as a
                screen to conceal the attacks intended for my country,—but who did not even protect
                me after I had fallen? I had yielded, if you assert that the common people was
                alienated from me, (which it was not) to unpopularity; if you think that everything
                was thrown into confusion, to the times; if violence was at the bottom of it, to
                arms; if there was a confederacy against me, to a bargain made by the magistrates;
                if there was danger to all the citizens, then I had yielded to the one great
                consideration, the safety of the republic. <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>Why,
                when a motion was <pb n="183"/> brought forward concerning the status of a citizen,
                (I do not say what sort of citizen,) and the confiscation of his property; when it
                was enacted by the sacred laws and by the laws of the Twelve Tables that it was not
                lawful to decree a <foreign xml:lang="la">privilegium</foreign> against any one nor
                to make any motion affecting a man's rights as a citizen;—why, I say, was the voice
                of the consuls never heard? Why was the rule established that year,—as far as those
                two pests of this empire could effect its establishment,—that any citizen might
                lawfully be driven out of the city by name by the mob of artisans in a state of
                excitement, and by the contrivance of a tribune of the people? <milestone n="66"
                    unit="section"/>But what measures were proposed that year? what promises were
                made to many? what engagements were committed to writing? what hopes were
                entertained? what designs formed?—What shall I say? what spot on the whole surface
                of the globe was not allotted to some one or other? what whole business was there,
                which could be thought of or wished for or imagined of which the management was not
                already given and assigned to somebody? what description of command, what province,
                what contrivance for finding out or amassing money was overlooked? what district or
                territory in the whole earth was there of any tolerable extent in which some kingdom
                or other was not marked out for somebody? and what king was there who did not think
                that year either that he could buy what he had not, or else that he must ransom what
                he had? Who was there who asked for any province or for any money or for any
                appointment as lieutenant or as ambassador from the senate? If men had been
                condemned for acts of violence, restitution of their fines was made to them; by
                every means the way to the consulship was smoothed for that priest who was so
                devoted to the people. The good groaned at these things; the wicked cherished hopes;
                the tribune of the people was active; the consuls were assisting him. <milestone
                    n="31" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="67" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>About this time a little later than he himself would approve, Cnaeus Pompeius,
                greatly against the will of those men who by their own contrivances and by false
                alarms had turned away the inclination of that most virtuous and gallant man from
                the defence of my safety, awakened again that habit which he had of devotion to the
                cause of the good government of the republic, which had been, I will not say lulled
                asleep, but a little checked and blasted by some sort of <pb n="184"/> suspicion.
                That man, who by his virtuous valour had subdued the most wicked of citizens, and
                the most active of foreign enemies, and the mightiest nations, and kings, and savage
                and hitherto unheard-of tribes, and a countless host of pirates, and also the
                slaves; who, having put a happy end to every war by land and sea, had made the
                boundaries of the empire of the Roman people co-equal with the extent of the world;
                would not allow that republic to be overturned by the wickedness of a few men,
                which, he himself had repeatedly saved, not only by his counsels, but even by his
                own blood; he came to the succour of the public cause; he resisted the remainder of
                those men's measures by his authority; he addressed to the authorities complaints as
                to what had already happened. <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>Some inclination
                towards a better state of things appeared to arise. The senate, in a full house,
                passed a decree respecting my return, on the first of June, without a single
                dissenting voice, on the motion of Lucius Ninnius, whose good faith and virtue never
                wavered in my cause. Somebody of the name of Ligus, some obscure fellow, some
                contemptible addition to my enemies, interposed his veto. The affair and our cause
                were now in such a state that we seemed to look up, and to be coming to life again.
                Whoever had had the slightest participation in the wickedness of Clodius as
                connected with my sufferings, wherever he came, or in whatever trial he appeared,
                was sure to be condemned. Not a man was found who would admit that he had given a
                vote against me. My brother had departed from <placeName key="tgn,2097781"
                    >Asia</placeName>, with every appearance of mourning, but with far deeper grief
                at his heart. As he came towards the city, the whole city went forth to meet him
                with tears and groans. The senate was speaking with unusual freedom. The Roman
                knights were constantly meeting. That excellent man
                        <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName>, my son-in-law,<note
                    anchored="true">He was dead.</note> who was not allowed time to receive the
                reward of his affection, either from me or from the Roman people, kept beseeching
                his relation to give him back his father-in-law. The senate refused to entertain any
                proposition whatever till the consuls had made a motion concerning me. <milestone
                    n="32" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="69" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And as the facts of the case were now notorious, and as the consuls, by their bargain
                respecting the provinces, had parted with all their freedom of action, and when they
                    <pb n="185"/> were asked in the senate to deliver their opinions respecting me
                as private men,<note anchored="true">The text here seems undoubtedly corrupt.</note>
                said that they were afraid of that law of Clodius: as those men could not stand this
                state of things any longer, they formed a plan to murder Cnaeus Pompeius and when
                that was detected and when the assassins had been taken with the arms in their
                hands, he remained shut up in his own house as long as my enemy continued tribune.
                Eight tribunes supported a motion for my return, from which it was understood that
                my friends had increased in my absence and that, too, while I was in a situation in
                which some whom I had thought to be my friends were not able to show<note
                    anchored="true">Here also the text is probably very corrupt.</note> it; but the
                fact was that they had always the same inclination but not always the same freedom
                of action; for of the nine tribunes who were at that time in my interest one, while
                I was absent, dropped off from me, who took his surname from the images of the
                Aelii, though he looks more as if he be longed to their nation than to their
                    family.<note anchored="true">Aelius was of Ligurian family originally, and the
                    Ligurians were not very famous for their good faith.</note>
            </p>
            <p><milestone n="70" unit="section"/> Accordingly, in this year when the new magistrates
                had been elected, when all good men turned their hopes towards them and began to
                found expectations of a better state of things on their honesty, Publius Lentulus,
                as the chief, took up my cause with his authority and by the open declaration of his
                sentiments, in spite of the resistance of
                    <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName> and Gabinius; and when eight
                tribunes made a motion in my behalf, he spoke in favour of it in a speech very
                honourable to me. And though he thought that it would redound greatly to his glory,
                and would secure him gratitude as having performed a most important service to the
                state, if that cause was not as yet proceeded with, but was reserved entire for his
                consulship, still he preferred having my business settled at once by others, to
                having it accomplished after delay by himself. <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="71" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>In the meantime Publius Sestius, O judges, the tribune elect, undertook a journey to
                Caius Caesar, for the sake of my safety. What he effected, how much real good he
                did, has nothing to do with the matter. I think indeed if Caesar was, as I believe
                him to have been, well-inclined towards <pb n="186"/> us, that Sestius did me no
                good at all; if Caesar was a little angry with me, he did not do much good; but
                still you see the unwearied activity and loyalty of the man. </p>
            <p>I now come to the tribuneship of Sestius; for he undertook this journey for the sake
                of the republic when he was only tribune elect. He thought that it concerned the
                unanimity of the citizens, and the facility of accomplishing what he had at heart,
                to show that Caesar's mind was not averse to the business. </p>
            <p>That year passed away. Men seemed to breathe, not from having actually attained their
                wishes, but from their hopes of recovering the republic. Two vultures in the robe of
                    war<note anchored="true">The Latin word is <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >paludati</foreign>. “The <foreign xml:lang="la">paludamentum</foreign>
                    always denotes the cloak worn by a Roman general commanding an army, and by his
                    principal officers, in contradistinction to the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >sagum</foreign> of the common soldiers, and to the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >toga</foreign> or robe of peace.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 713, v. <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Paludamentum</foreign>.</note> went forth with evil omens and
                the execrations of the citizens. I only wish that everything had happened to them
                which men then prayed might happen; and then we should not have lost the province of
                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, nor our cavalry, and those
                gallant cohorts in <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>. <milestone n="72"
                    unit="section"/> The tribunes of the people enter on their office, who had all
                pledged themselves to bring forward a motion concerning me. The chief of them is
                bought over by my enemies, whom men, laughing at him amid their indignation, were
                used to call Gracchus; since it was the fate of the city, that even that weasel
                escaped out of the brambles should attempt to gnaw a hole in the republic. But the
                other fellow, Serranus,—not the Serranus<note anchored="true">A name of Cincinnatus,
                    given to him also by Virgil:—<quote xml:lang="la">
                        <l>Velte sulco Serrane serentem.</l>
                    </quote>—<bibl n="Verg. A. 6.845"><title>Aen.</title> vi. 845</bibl>.</note>
                from the plough, but the one from the deserted granary of Gavius Olelus, where you
                might count<note anchored="true">There is probably some corruption here in the text.
                        “<foreign xml:lang="la">Calata comitia</foreign>, a kind of <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> for the consecration of a priest; hence
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">calatis granis</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >comitiis</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="la">facete</foreign>. Cic.”—Riddle,
                    Lat. Dict. in voc. <foreign xml:lang="la">Calo</foreign>. There seems a sort of
                    pun on Calatus and Calatinus.</note> the grains,—being inserted among the Atilii
                Calatini, on a sudden, after the names had been entered on the tablets, withdrew his
                name from the list. </p>
            <p>The first of January arrives; you are better acquainted with what ensued than I am;
                however, I say what I have heard. You know what a numerous attendance of the senate
                there <pb n="187"/> was, what expectation of the people, what a concourse of
                deputies from all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; how great too was
                the virtue and activity and authority of Publius Lentulus, the consul; and also how
                very moderate towards me was the behaviour of his colleague, who, though he said
                that he had taken a dislike to me on account of a disagreement between us on the
                affairs of the republic, still said that he would give it up to the conscript
                fathers and to the critical times of the republic. <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="73" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Then Lucius Cotta, being asked his opinion first, said what was most worthy of the
                republic,—that nothing had been done respecting me justly, nothing according to the
                usages of our ancestors, nothing according to the laws that no one could be removed
                out of the city without a regular trial, that it not only was illegal for any law to
                be passed, but that no decision even could be come to except at the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign>, that that was all violence, a flame
                arising from the confusion of the republic, and the agitated state of the times,
                when all rights and all courts of justice were destroyed, that when a great
                revolution was impending, I turned aside a little, and out of hope of future
                tranquillity, had shunned the present waves and tempests. Wherefore, as I had when
                absent delivered the republic from no less serious dangers than I had previously
                when present, he said that it was fitting that I should not only be restored, but
                also complimented by the senate. He also discussed many other points with great
                wisdom, arguing that that most insane and profligate enemy of modesty and chastity
                had framed the law which he had enacted concerning me in such a manner, in such
                language and with such statements of fact that even if it had been legally proposed
                and earned still it could not have had any force. Wherefore he said, that as I was
                not away because of any law, I ought to be recalled not by a law but by the
                authority of the senate. </p>
            <p><milestone n="74" unit="section"/>There was no one who did not say that this opinion
                was most sound. But Cnaeus Pompeius, who was asked his opinion after him, having
                expressed his approval of the opinion of Cotta, and praised it, said that he, for
                the sake of my tranquillity, in order that I might be in no subsequent danger from
                any popular disturbance, voted that the kindness of the Roman people should be added
                to the authority of the senate in my behalf. When all had vied with one another,
                each one <pb n="188"/> speaking about my safety in a more dignified and
                complimentary manner than the other, and when in fact a unanimous vote was just
                taking place, up rose, as you know, Atilius Gavianus; and he did not dare to
                interpose his veto, although he had been bought for that purpose, but he asked a
                night to deliberate on the matter. Then ensued a great outcry of the senate, and
                loud complaints and entreaties: his father-in-law threw himself at his feet. He
                pledged himself to cause no delay the next day. He was believed. The senate broke
                up. In the meantime that deliberate gentleman, in the course of the long night that
                intervened, got his wages doubled. Only a very few days followed during the whole
                month of January on which it was lawful for a senate to be held; but still nothing
                was discussed except my business. <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="75" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>While the senate was being hindered by every sort of delay, and mockery, and false
                pretence, there came at last the day appointed for the discussion of my case, the
                twenty-fifth of January. The chief proposer of the motion, a man most friendly to
                me, Quintus Fabricius, occupied the temple some time before daybreak. On that day
                Sestius was quite quiet, the very man who is now on his trial for violence. He, the
                advocate and defender of my cause, takes no step at all, but waits to see the
                maneuvers of my enemies. What next? How do these men conduct themselves by whose
                contrivance Publius Sestius is now put upon his trial? As they had occupied the
                forum, and the place for the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, and the
                senate-house, at an early period of the night, with a number of armed men and
                slaves, they fall on Fabricius, lay violent hands on him, slay some men, and wound
                many. <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>They drive away by force Marcus Cispius, a
                most gallant and virtuous man and a tribune of the people, as he was coming into the
                forum; they make a great slaughter in the forum; and all of them, with drawn and
                bloody swords, looked about with their eyes for, and demanded with their cries, my
                brother, a most virtuous man, a most brave one, and one most devoted to me. And he
                willingly, such was his grief, and so great his regret for me, would have exposed
                his body to their weapons, not with a view of resisting them, but with the object of
                meeting death, if he had not preserved his life in the hope of my return. However,
                he endured some violence from those wicked robbers; and as he had come down for the
                purpose of begging <pb n="189"/> the safety of his brother from the Roman people,
                having been driven from the <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign>, he lay down in
                the place of the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, and covered himself with
                the corpses of slaves and freedmen, and defended his life that day by the protection
                which night and flight afforded him, not by that of the laws or courts of justice.
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>You recollect, O judges, that on that day the
                    <placeName key="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName> was filled with the corpses of
                the citizens, that the sewers were choked up; that blood was wiped up out of the
                forum with sponges; so that all men thought that such a vast number and such a
                magnificent show of gladiators could not have been provided by any private
                individual, or plebeian, but must be the exhibition of some patrician and man of
                praetorian rank. <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>Neither before this time nor even
                on this most turbulent day itself was there any word of accusation uttered against
                Sestius. But there was great violence used in the forum. No doubt of that. When was
                there ever greater? We have often seen men pelted with stones; not so often, but
                still too often have we seen swords but such great slaughter as this,—such vast
                heaps of corpses piled up who ever beheld in the forum, except perhaps on that
                miserable day of Cinna and Octavius? With what animosity did the parties fight! For,
                indeed, seditious disturbances often arise from the pertinacity or firmness with
                which some magistrate has exercised his veto or from the fault and wickedness of
                some proposer of a law having held out hopes of great advantage or great bribes to
                the ignorant; they arise from the rivalry of the magistrates; they arise gradually
                from clamour at first, and afterwards from some division of the assembly it is
                unwillingly, and slowly, and seldom that acts of violence are resorted to. But who
                ever heard before of a sedition in the night, when not a word had been spoken, when
                no assembly had been summoned and when no law had been read? <milestone n="78"
                    unit="section"/>Is it probable that a Roman citizen, or that any free man,
                should have descended with a sword into the forum before daybreak, in order to
                prevent a law from being passed respecting me, unless he were one of those men who
                have been fattened up this long time on the blood of the republic by that
                destructive and wicked citizen? </p>
            <p>Here now I ask the prosecutor himself, who complains that Sestius used to keep a
                great multitude and a large guard about him during his tribuneship, whether he had
                them with <pb n="190"/> him on that day? Certainly, most undeniably, he had not; and
                therefore the party of the republic was defeated; and it was defeated, not by
                unfavourable <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, not by any exercise of the
                veto, not by the suffrages of any assembly, but by violence, by force of arms, by
                bloodshed. For if the praetor had given notice to Fabricius, and had said that he
                was observing the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, the republic would have
                received a blow, but still one which it could have lamented. If his colleague had
                interrupted Fabricius with his veto, he would have injured the republic, but still
                he would have injured the republic in a legal and regular manner. Are you to send
                raw gladiators, got together in expectation of the aedileship, with a pack of
                assassins let loose out of the jails, into the forum before dawn? Are you to drive
                the magistrates down from the temple? Are you to cause a great massacre? to desolate
                the forum? and then, when you have carried everything by violence and arms, to
                accuse a man who has protected himself with a guard, not for the purpose of opposing
                you, but of defending his own life? <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="79" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But not even since that time has Sestius endeavoured to take care to be able, being
                defended by his people around him, to discharge the duties of his magistracy in the
                forum, and to conduct the affairs of the republic in safety. Therefore, relying on
                the sacred nature of his office as tribune, as he considered that he was armed by
                sacred laws, not only against violence and weapons, but also against words and
                interruption in speaking, he came into the temple of Castor,—he gave notice to the
                consul that he could not proceed because he was observing the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign>; when on a sudden that band of Clodius, which had already
                been repeatedly victorious in the slaughter of citizens, raises an outcry, hurries
                forward, attacks him. Some fall with their swords on the tribune unarmed and
                unprovided, and some with pieces of fences and with clubs; and he at length, having
                received many wounds, and been weakened and disabled by the injuries which he had
                received from these men, fell down in an almost lifeless state, and was only saved
                from actual death by their believing that he was dead. For when they saw him lying
                on the ground with numberless wounds and gashes, scarcely breathing, pale and
                exhausted, they at last left off wounding him, more because they were tired, <pb
                    n="191"/> and because they were mistaken, thinking him dying than from any
                feelings of pity or moderation. <milestone n="80" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And now Sestius is on his trial for violence! Why is this? Because he is alive. But
                that is no fault of his. One last blow was wanting; and if that had been added he
                would have yielded up his last breath. Accuse Lentidius; he did not wound him in the
                right place; accuse Sabinius that fellow from <placeName key="perseus,Reate"
                    >Reate</placeName>, and ask why he was so prompt to cry out that the man was
                dead. But why accuse Sestius himself? Was not there enough of him for their swords?
                Did he resist? Did he not stand to be killed as gladiators are often ordered to do?
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/> Is this of itself a proof of violence not to
                be able to die? Or this, that a tribune of the people profaned a temple with blood?
                Or this, that when he had been carried away and had begun to come to himself, he did
                not order himself to he carried back again? Where is the crime for which you blame
                him? <milestone n="81" unit="section"/>Or this I ask, O judges, if on that day that
                family of Clodius had done what it wished,—if Publius Sestius, who was left for dead
                had really been slain, would you have had recourse to arms? Would you have roused
                yourselves up to the courage of your fathers and to the valour of your ancestors?
                Would you at last have endeavoured to wrest the republic out of the hands of that
                deadly robber? Or would you even then have remained quiet and dawdled, and been
                afraid, when you saw the republic overwhelmed and taken possession of by the most
                impious assassins and by slaves? If then you would have avenged his death, if you
                had any idea of continuing free men, and of retaining the constitution, do you think
                that you ought to hesitate as to what you ought to say, and feel, and think, and
                decide as to his virtue now that he is alive? <milestone n="82" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But even those very parricides, whose unbridled frenzy is nourished by long impunity,
                were thrown into such consternation by the violence of their deed, that if the
                belief of the death of Sestius had lasted a little longer, they would have done as
                they were thinking of, and have slain their own friend Gracchus, for the sake of
                attributing the crime to us. That clown, however, being rather wary, (for those
                wicked men could not conceal their design,) perceived that his own blood was sought
                for for the purpose of extinguishing the unpopularity of this atrocity of Clodius,
                and got hold of a <pb n="192"/> cloak belonging to a mule-driver, in which he had
                originally come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> to the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, and put a mower's basket on his head, and when
                some were asking for Numerius, and some for Quintius, he was saved by the mistake of
                the double name.<note anchored="true">The man's real name was Numerius Quinctius,
                    who had assumed the name of Gracchus, to which he had no right, in order to make
                    himself popular with the multitude; who, perhaps, on that account elected him
                    tribune.</note> And you are all aware that he was in danger until it was
                ascertained that Sestius was alive; and if that had not been discovered a little
                sooner than I could have wished, they would not, indeed, have been able to transfer
                the odium of the death of their hired tool to those on whom they expected to shift
                it; but they would have diminished the infamy of their abominable wickedness by one
                crime which every one would have been glad of. <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>And
                if Publius Sestius had then yielded up, in the temple of Castor, that life which he
                hardly retained, I have no doubt that if only the senate had continued to exist and
                if the majesty of the Roman people had ever recovered, a statue would at some future
                time have been erected to him in the forum, as to a man who had been slain in the
                cause of the republic. </p>
            <p>Nor, indeed, would any one of those men to whom you see that statues after their
                death have been erected by our ancestors in that place in the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >rostra</foreign>, deserve to be thought more of than Publius Sestius, either as
                respects the cruelty of their death, or their attachment to the republic: if, when
                he had undertaken the cause of a citizen oppressed by undeserved misfortune,—the
                cause of a friend,—the cause of a man who had done great services to the
                republic,—the cause of the senate, the cause of <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>, the cause of the republic; and when, in obedience to the
                requirements of religion and to the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, he
                had given notice to the magistrates of what omens he had observed, he had been slain
                by those impious pests of their country in the light of day, openly, within the
                sight of gods and men, in a most holy temple, in a most holy cause, and while
                invested with a most holy magistracy. Will any one, then, say that the life of that
                man ought to be stripped of its proper dignity and honour, when you would have
                thought his death entitled to the honour of an everlasting monument?<pb n="193"/>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="84" unit="section"/>“You brought,”
                says he, “you levied, you got together a band of men.” What was he going to do with
                them? To besiege the senate? to expel citizens who had not been condemned? to
                plunder men's property? to set fire to buildings? to plunder private houses? to him
                the temples of the immortal gods? to expel the tribunes of the people from the
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign> by force of arms? to sell whatever
                provinces he pleased to whomsoever he pleased? to give men the title of king? to
                restore to free cities, by means of our lieutenants and ambassadors, men who had
                been condemned for capital offences? to blockade the chief man of the state in his
                house with armed bands? It was to effect all these objects, I suppose, which could
                never possibly be attained unless the republic were overwhelmed by armed men, that
                Publius Sestius got together his multitude of men, and his troops, as you call them.
                But the pear was not yet ripe. The circumstances of the case did not as yet invite
                good men to have recourse to such means for their protection. We were defeated not
                indeed by that body alone, but still not entirely without its agency. You were all
                mourning in silence. <milestone n="85" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>The forum had been taken in the preceding year; the temple of Castor having been
                occupied by runaway slaves, as if it had been a fortress! not a word was said
                against such conduct. Everything was done by the clamour and impetuosity, and
                violence, and assaults of men desperate through indigence and through their natural
                audacity. And you endured that it should be so. The magistrates were driven from the
                temples; others were altogether cut off from all approach to them or to the forum.
                No one offered any resistance. Gladiators were taken out of the praetor's train and
                introduced into the senate and confessed that they had been thrown into prison by
                        <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>, that they had been released by
                Serranus. Yet no mention was made of these things. The forum was strewed with the
                corpses of Roman citizens murdered in a nocturnal massacre. There not only was no
                new sort of investigation into such events instituted, but even the old courts of
                justice were abolished. You saw a tribune of the people lying down stricken to the
                ground with more than twenty wounds and almost dead; the house of another tribune of
                the people, a man of godlike virtue (for I will say what I think myself, and what
                all men agree <pb n="194"/> with me in thinking,) a man of most eminent, unheard-of,
                unprecedented greatness of mind, and wisdom, and integrity, was attacked with fire
                and sword by the army of Clodius. <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="86" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And while speaking on this topic you praise
                    <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>, and you praise him deservedly. For
                what man have we ever seen of more admirable virtue? a man who, without any
                expectation of reward beyond this, which is now thought an old-fashioned and
                contemptible thing—namely, the esteem of the good, has voluntarily encountered every
                sort of danger, and the most arduous labours, and the most severe contests, and the
                most bitter enmities? who appears to me to be the only citizen who has shown not
                only by words but by actions what ought to be done, and what was necessary to be
                done, in the republic by the leading men; that such men's duty was to resist the
                wickedness of audacious men, men who would overturn the republic, by means of the
                laws, and of the courts of justice; but that if the laws were inefficient, if there
                were no courts of justice, if the republic was seized and held in subjection by the
                violence and conspiracy and armed force of audacious men, then that it was
                absolutely necessary for our lives and liberties to be defended by armed guards and
                by troops. To think in this way is a sign of prudence; to act in accordance with
                such sentiments is a proof of bravery; to think rightly, and to act bravely at the
                same time, is a proof of perfect and consummate virtue. </p>
            <p><milestone n="87" unit="section"/><persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>, as
                tribune of the people, entered on the administration of the affairs of the republic:
                and I will dilate yet further in his praise; not because he is more anxious to be
                praised than to be respected, or because I have any particular wish to give him this
                reward of praise in his presence, especially as I cannot find words equal to his
                exploits; but because I think that if I prove that the conduct of
                        <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName> has been approved of by the
                voice of the prosecutor, you will think with reference to this accusation, that the
                cause of Sestius stands on the same ground. Titus Annius, then, entered on the
                administration of the affairs of the republic with the feeling that he wished to
                restore to his country a citizen who had been undeservedly driven from it. The case
                was a plain one; his conduct was consistent supported by the unanimous consent and
                concord of every one. He had his colleagues for assistants, the greatest possible
                zeal in his favour of one of the <pb n="195"/> consuls, and the disposition of the
                other was nearly friendly. Of the praetors, one was unfavourable; the enthusiasm of
                the senate in the cause was extraordinary, the feelings of all the Roman knights
                were roused to further it, <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> was on the
                tiptoe of expectation. There were only two enemies who had been brought over to
                create obstacles; and if those despicable and contemptible men could not support the
                weight of so important a business, he saw that he should not be able by any means to
                accomplish the object which he had undertaken to effect. He laboured with all his
                influence, with all his prudence,—he laboured by means of the cooperation of the
                highest order in the state he laboured exciting others by the example of the
                virtuous and brave citizens,—he meditated with incessant diligence on what conduct
                was worthy of the republic and of himself, on his own station and character, on what
                hopes he ought to entertain on what return he ought to make to his ancestors for
                what he had received from them. <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="88"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>That gladiator saw that he could not be a match for such wisdom as that of
                        <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>, if he proceeded according to
                ordinary usage. He resorted to arms, to firebrands, to daily slaughter, to
                conflagration and plunder, with his army. He began to attack his house, to meet him
                on his journeys, to provoke him by violence, to try and alarm him. He had but little
                effect on a man of consummate wisdom and consummate firmness; but although
                indignation of mind, and an innate love of liberty, and prompt and excellent valour,
                encouraged that gallant man to break down and repel violence by violence, especially
                now that violence was so repeatedly offered, still so great was the moderation of
                the man, and so excessive his prudence, that he restrained his indignation, and
                would not avenge himself by the same conduct as that by which he had been provoked;
                but he resolved rather to entangle in the toils of the law that fellow who was
                exulting and dancing in triumph over all the murders which he had committed in the
                republic. <milestone n="89" unit="section"/>He came down to the court to accuse him.
                Who ever did so, so peculiarly for the sake of the republic? having no private
                enmity of his own to urge him on, having no reward in prospect being persuaded by no
                entreaty on the part of any one, nor even by any general expectation that he was
                going to take such a step. The fellow's courage was shaken. For when such a man as
                        <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName> was the prosecutor, he <pb
                    n="196"/> had no hope of such an infamous tribunal as his former one. See now
                the praetor, the consul, and the tribune of the people, propose new edicts of a new
                sort: “That no one be brought before the court as a defendant; that no one be
                summoned before the judges; that no investigations take place; that no one be
                allowed to make any mention to any one, of judges, or courts of justice.” What was a
                man to do who was born for virtue, and dignity, and glory, when the violence of
                wicked men was fortified in this way, by the destruction of all laws and courts of
                justice? Was tribune of the people to place his life at the mercy of a private
                individual? was a most virtuous man to hold his life at the will of a most
                thoroughly wicked one? or, was he to abandon the cause which he had undertaken? was
                he to keep at home? He thought it would be a base thing to be defeated, or to be
                frightened from his purpose. In truth, he thought it for the advantage of the
                republic, since he was not able to employ the laws against him, that he should not
                show any fear of his violence, with respect either to personal peril to himself, or
                to the danger of the republic. <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="90"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>How, then, can you accuse Sestius with reference to this fact of his having provided
                himself with a guard, when at the same time you praise
                        <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>? Is it legal for that man to
                provide himself with a guard who is defending his own house, who is repelling fire
                and sword from his altars and his fire-side, who seeks to be allowed to present
                himself with safety in the forum, in the temples of the gods, and in the
                senate-house; but do you think that man who is warned by the wounds which he sees
                every day over his whole person, to defend his head, and his neck, and his throat,
                and his sides, by some protection or other, deserving to be prosecuted for violence?
                    <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>For who of you, O judges, is ignorant that the
                nature of things has been such, that at one time men, before there was any natural
                or civil law fully laid down, wandered in a straggling and disorderly manner over
                the country, and had just that property which they could either seize or keep by
                their own personal strength and vigour, by means of wounds and bloodshed? Those men,
                therefore, who showed themselves to be the most eminent for virtue and wisdom, they,
                having considered the character of men's aptitude for instruction and of their
                natural disposition, collected into one place those <pb n="197"/> who were
                previously scattered abroad, and brought them over from their former savage way of
                life to justice and mildness of manners. Then came those constitutions devised for
                the utility of man, which we call commonwealths. Then came collections of men which
                were subsequently called states; then men surrounded with walls sets of houses
                joined together, which we now call cities, and divine and human laws began to be
                recognised. </p>
            <p><milestone n="92" unit="section"/>And there is no point in which there is so much
                difference between this manner of life, polished by civilization and that savage
                one, as in the fact of law being the ruling principle of the one, and violence of
                the other. If we do not choose to be guided by one we must adopt the other. Do we
                wish violence to be put an end to? Law must inevitably prevail; that is to say,
                courts of justice must, for in them all law and justice are comprehended. Do we
                disapprove of courts of justice, or are they destroyed or suspended? In a moment
                violence must be supreme. Everybody sees this.
                    <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName> saw it and acted in such a manner
                as to try the power of law and to banish violence. He wished to avail himself of the
                one, in order that courage and virtue might defeat audacity; he had recourse to the
                other from compulsion, in order to prevent virtue and courage from being defeated by
                audacity. And the principle of conduct of Publius Sestius was the same if not in
                prosecuting Clodius, (for, it does not follow that exactly the same details of
                conduct are to be pursued by every one,) still at all events in the necessity of
                defending his safety, and in preparing a defence against force and personal
                violence. <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="93" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>O ye immortal gods! what an end do you show to us? what hope of the republic do you
                hold out to us? How few men will be found of such virtue and courage as to embrace
                the cause of the republic when it is the justest of causes? and to consult the
                interests of the virtuous part of the community? and to seek no glory but that which
                is solid and genuine? when he knows that of those two monsters so nearly fatal to
                the republic, Gabinius and Piso, one is every day amassing a countless sum of gold
                from the peaceful and opulent treasuries of <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName>; and is waging war on quiet tribes, in order to pour into the
                deep and bottomless gulf of his lusts their ancient and hitherto untasted and
                undiminished riches; and is building in a most conspicuous <pb n="198"/> place a
                villa of such a size, that that villa, of which that very man, when tribune of the
                people, once unfolded a picture in the assembly of the people, in order (virtuous
                man and free from all taint of covetousness that he was) to excite odium against a
                most virtuous and brave citizen, appears now little more than a hut by the side of
                it. <milestone n="94" unit="section"/>The other man first of all sold peace for an
                enormous sum to the Thracians and Dardani. Then, in order that they might be able to
                make up the money which they were to pay him, he gave up <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> to them to ravage and plunder. Moreover,
                he distributed the property of their creditors, Roman citizens, among their Greek
                debtors; he exacted immense sums from the people of <placeName key="tgn,7010750"
                    >Dyrrachium</placeName>, he plundered the Thessalians, he exacted a fixed sum of
                money from the Achaeans every year; and, above all, in no public or consecrated
                place has he left one statue, or picture, or ornament. Who, I say, will embrace the
                cause of the republic when he knows all this, and when he sees that these men are so
                triumphant who deserve most richly, according to every law in existence, every sort
                of penalty, and every extremity of punishment? and that these two men whom you see
                here are brought to trial? I say nothing of Numerius, and Serranus, and Aelius, the
                mere dregs of the sedition of Clodius; but still, even these go triumphantly about
                as you behold; nor, as long as ever you are in a state of apprehension for
                yourselves, will they ever be alarmed for themselves. <milestone n="44"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="95" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For why need I speak of the aedile himself, who has even commenced legal proceedings
                against <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>, and instituted a prosecution
                against him for violence? Not that <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName> will
                ever be induced by any injury to himself to repent that he behaved with such virtue,
                and with such firmness of mind towards the republic; but what will be the thoughts
                of the young men who see all these things? The man who has attacked and destroyed
                and burnt the public monuments, and the sacred holdings, and the houses of his
                enemies; who was constantly escorted by assassins, fenced round by armed guards, and
                surrounded by a band of informers, of whom there is far too great a plenty; who
                stirred up even a foreign band of wicked men, and bought a lot of slaves ready for
                bloodshed, and who in his tribuneship poured the whole contents of the prisons into
                the forum, now struts about as an aedile, and accuses the <pb n="199"/> man who did
                to some extent check his exulting frenzy. And the man who has hitherto defended
                himself in such a manner, that, as a private individual he has been defending his
                own household gods, and in his public capacity the privileges of his tribuneship and
                the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, has been prevented by the authority
                of the senate from prosecuting that man with moderation by whom he himself has been
                prosecuted in a most nefarious manner. </p>
            <p><milestone n="96" unit="section"/>This, in truth, is the question which you put to me
                earnestly and most repeatedly while pleading in behalf of the prosecution,—namely,
                what I mean by the race of best men? For this is what you said. You ask a question
                which it is very desirable for the youth of the city to learn and not very difficult
                for me to explain, and with respect to it, I will, O judges, say a few words. And,
                as I think what I say will not be wholly unconnected with the advantage of those who
                hear me nor with my duty, nor with the very case which we are arguing of Publius
                Sestius. <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>There have always in this city been two kinds of men who have been ambitious of being
                concerned in affairs of state, and of arriving at distinction by such a course and
                of these two kinds one wish to be considered popular men and the others wish both to
                be and to be considered of the party of the best men in the state. Those whose
                object it was that whatever they did and whatever they said should be agreeable to
                the multitude, were the popular party; but those who conducted themselves in such a
                way as to induce all the best men to approve of their counsels were considered of
                the best party.<note anchored="true">It is quite impossible to give Cicero's meaning
                    here in any translation. The Latin word he uses is <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >optimates</foreign>, which when spoken generally means the nobles and the
                    aristocratic party but all through this passage he connects it with <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">optimus</foreign>, best most virtuous.</note>
                <milestone n="97" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Who then are they? Every good man. If you ask what are their numbers, they are
                innumerable. For if they were not, we could not stand. They are the chief men of the
                public council; they are those who follow their school they are the men of the
                highest orders of the state to whom the senate house is open; they are the citizens
                of the municipal towns and Roman citizens who dwell in the country; they are men
                engaged in business; there are even some freedmen of the <pb n="200"/> best party.
                The number, as I have said, of this party is widely scattered in various directions;
                but the entire body (to prevent all mistakes) can be described and defined in a few
                words. All men belong to the best party, who are not guilty of any crime, nor wicked
                by nature, nor madmen, nor men embarrassed by domestic difficulties. Let it be laid
                down, then, that these men (this race, as you call them) are all those who are
                honest and in their senses, and who are well off in their domestic circumstances.
                Those who are guided by their wishes, who consult their interests and opinions in
                the management of the republic, are the partisans of the best men, and are
                themselves accounted best men, most wise and most illustrious citizens, and chief
                men in the state. </p>
            <p><milestone n="98" unit="section"/>What then, is the object proposed to themselves by
                these directors of the republic, which they are bound to keep their eyes fixed upon,
                and towards which they ought to direct their course? That which is most excellent
                and most desirable to all men in their senses, and to all good and happy men,—ease
                conjoined with duty. Those who seek this are all best men; those who effect it are
                considered the chief leaders in and the preservers of their states. For men ought
                not to be so elated by the dignity of the affairs which they have undertaken to
                manage, as to have no regard to their ease; nor ought they to dwell with fondness on
                any sort of ease which is inconsistent with dignity. <milestone n="46"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p><milestone n="99" unit="section"/> And of this easy dignity these are the
                foundations, these are the component parts, which ought to he upheld by the chief
                men, and to be defended even at the hazard of their lives: religious observances,
                the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, the civil power of magistrates, the
                authority of the senate, the laws, the usages of one's ancestors, the courts of
                justice, the jurisdiction of the judges, good faith, the provinces, the allies, the
                glory of the empire, the whole affairs of the army, the treasury. To the defender
                and advocate of all these things, numerous and important as they are, is a task to
                employ great courage, great ability, and great firmness. In truth, in such a vast
                number of citizens, there is a great multitude of those men, who either, from fear
                of punishment, because they are conscious of their own misdeeds, are anxious for
                fresh changes and revolutions in the republic; or who, on account of some innate
                insanity of mind, feed upon the discords and seditions of the <pb n="201"/>
                citizens; or else who, on account of the embarrassment of their estates and
                circumstances, had rather burn in one vast common conflagration, than in one which
                consumed only themselves. And when these men have found instigators, leaders in and
                promoters of their own objects and vices, their waves are stirred up in the
                republic, so that those men must watch who have demanded for themselves the helm of
                the country, and they must strive with all their skill and with all their diligence,
                in order that they may be able to preserve these things which I have just now called
                its foundations and component parts, and so keep in their course and reach that
                harbour of ease and dignity. <milestone n="100" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>If, O judges, I were to deny that this path is rugged and difficult, and full of
                danger and snares, I should speak falsely, especially as I have not only always been
                aware that it was so, but have been alive to its perils and labours more than any
                other man. <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The republic is attacked by greater forces and more numerous bodies than those by
                which it is defended because audacious and abandoned men are impelled on by a nod,
                and are even of their own accord excited by nature to be enemies to the republic.
                And somehow or other good men are slower in action, and overlooking the first
                beginnings of things, are at last aroused by necessity itself so that some times
                through their very delays and tardiness of movement while they wish to retain their
                ease even without dignity, they, of their own accord, lose both. <milestone n="101"
                    unit="section"/>But those who are desirous to be defenders of the republic, if
                they be fickle men, soon give up the task; if they be at all timid men, they abandon
                it; and those alone remain and endure everything for the sake of the republic, who
                are such men as your father was, O Marcus Scaurus, who resisted all seditious men,
                from the time of Caius Gracchus to that of Quintus Varius, whom no violence, no
                threats, and no unpopularity ever shook; or such as Quintus Metellus, the uncle of
                your mother; who, when as censor he had branded a man most flourishing in the
                popular esteem, Lucius Saturninus, and when he had expunged a pretended Gracchus
                from the list of the citizens, in spite of the violence of an excited mob, and when
                he alone had refused to swear obedience to a law which he considered had not been
                legally enacted, preferred to abandon the city rather <pb n="202"/> than his
                opinion; or, (to leave off quoting ancient examples, of which there is an abundance
                worthy of the glory of this empire, while yet I avoid naming any one who is now
                alive,) such as Quintus Catulus lately was, whom neither the tempest of danger nor
                the breeze of honour could ever move from his straight course, either by hope or
                fear. <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="102" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Imitate those men, I beg you in the name of the immortal gods, you who seek for
                dignity, and praise, and glory. These examples are honourable; these are godlike;
                these are immortal; these are celebrated in fame, and are committed to the eternal
                recollection of our annals, and are handed down to posterity. It is a labour, I do
                not deny it. The dangers are great, I admit it,—<quote>
                    <l>The path of virtuous men is full of snares.</l>
                </quote> That is a most true saying. The poet says further,—<quote>
                    <l>But to demand those honours which excite </l>
                    <l>The general envy and desire of all, </l>
                    <l>And yet to shun the toil and ceaseless care </l>
                    <l>Which can alone conduct to such a goal, </l>
                    <l>Is purest ignorance.</l>
                </quote>
            </p>
            <p>The same poet says in another place, (a sentence which wicked citizens are inclined
                to catch at,) “Let them hate me, as long as they fear.” For he gave those admirable
                precepts to the young men. <milestone n="103" unit="section"/>But nevertheless this
                path and this system of undertaking public affairs was formerly more formidable, as
                in many particulars the desire of the multitude and the whim of the people were at
                variance with the interests of the republic. A law for the establishment of the
                ballot was brought forward by Lucius Cassius. The people thought that its liberties
                were at stake; the chief men of the state dissented, and in a matter affecting the
                safety of the nobles, they feared the rashness of the multitude, and the
                licentiousness of the ballot. Tiberius Gracchus brought forward an Agrarian law. It
                was very acceptable to the people; the fortunes of the poorer classes appeared
                likely to be established by it. The nobles strove against it, because they saw that
                discord was excited by it; and because, as the object of it was to deprive the
                wealthy men of their ancient possessions, they thought that by it the republic was
                being deprived of its <pb n="203"/> defenders. Caius Gracchus brought forward a law
                respecting corn. It was a very pleasing proposal to the common people at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; for food was to be supplied to them in
                abundance without any trouble. The good resisted it because they thought that its
                effect would be to lead the common people away from industry to idleness, and
                because the treasury was likely to be drained by such a measure. <milestone n="49"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="104" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>There have been also many cases within our own recollection, which I pass over on
                purpose, in which the desire of the people has been at variance with the wisdom of
                the nobles. At present there is no subject on which the people need disagree with
                its chosen magistrates and with the nobles; it is not demanding anything, nor is it
                eager for a revolution, and it is fond of its own tranquillity, and pleased with the
                dignity and worth of every eminent man, and with the glory of the whole republic.
                Therefore seditious and turbulent men, because they cannot at present stir up the
                Roman people by any bribery, since the common people, having gone through some most
                violent seditious and discords, appear for the most for ease and tranquillity, now
                hold packed assemblies, and do not concern themselves about saying or proposing what
                those men who are present in the assembly may like to hear, but they contrive by
                bribery and corruption that whatever they say may appear to be what those men wish
                to hear. </p>
            <p><milestone n="105" unit="section"/> Do you think that the Gracchi, or that
                Saturninus, or that any one of those ancient men who were considered devoted to the
                interests of the people, had ever any hired fellows in their assemblies? No one of
                those men ever stooped to such a course. For the mere liberality of their proposed
                laws, and the hope of the advantage which was held out to them, excited the
                multitude sufficiently without any bribery. Therefore, in those times, those men who
                set up for friends of the people, were hindered in their plans by wise and
                honourable men, but they were great men in the opinion of the populace, and received
                every sort of honour from them. They were applauded in the theatre; they gained
                whatever they sought for by their suffrages; men loved their names, their language,
                their countenances, their very gait. But those who opposed this class of men were
                accounted wise and great men; they had great influence in the senate, great
                influence among all <pb n="204"/> good men; but they were unpopular with the
                multitude; their inclinations were frequently thwarted by the suffrages of the
                populace; and if any one of them at any time received any applause in the theatre,
                he began to be afraid that he had done something wrong; but at the same time, if
                there was anything of more than ordinary importance under discussion, then that same
                populace was chiefly influenced by the authority of those men. <milestone n="50"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="106" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Now, unless I am mistaken, the state is in such a condition, that if you take away
                the artisans who are hired to support the party of these wicked men, everybody in
                the republic appears to be of the same opinion. In truth, there are three places in
                which the opinion and inclination of the Roman people may be ascertained in the
                greatest degree; the assembly, the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, and the
                meetings at the games and at exhibitions of gladiators. What assembly has there been
                of late years, which has not been a packed and bribed one, but a genuine one, in
                which the unanimity of the Roman people has not been very perceivable? Many
                assemblies were held concerning me by that most wicked gladiator, to which no one
                ever went who was unbribed, no one who was an honest man; no good man could endure
                to behold that ill-omened countenance, or to listen to that frantic voice. Those
                assemblies were, I admit that those assemblies of abandoned men were necessarily
                turbulent. <milestone n="107" unit="section"/>Publius Lentulus, too, held an
                assembly, also about my affairs. There was a vast flocking to it of the whole Roman
                people; all ranks of society, all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>
                stood side by side in that assembly. He argued my cause with the greatest authority,
                and the greatest fluency of language amid such silent attention and such visible
                approbation from every one, that nothing so pleasing appeared ever to have fallen on
                the ears of the Roman people. Cnaeus Pompeius was brought forward by him, who
                displayed himself then not only as the main author of my safety, but even as a
                suppliant to the Roman people. His oration also was one of great weight and was
                pleasing to the assembly. And I assert that no opinion of his ever carried more
                authority with it; and that no eloquence of his was ever more agreeable. With what
                silent attention were the other chief men of the city listened to while speaking in
                my behalf;<milestone n="108" unit="section"/> whom I do not mention in this place,
                only lest my speech, if I say too little of any one, <pb n="205"/> should seem
                ungrateful and if I were to say enough of each individual, interminable. </p>
            <p>Turn now to the harangue of that same enemy of mine concerning me the same person of
                whom those great men had been speaking, delivered in the Campus Martins, to a
                genuine assembly of the people. Who was there who (I will not say approved of it but
                who) did not think it a most scandalous thing that he should be allowed to live and
                breathe at all, much less to speak? Who was there who did not think that the
                republic was polluted by his voice and that he himself, if he only listened to him
                was implicated in his wickedness? <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="109" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I come now to the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, whether those for
                electing magistrates or for enacting laws. We often see many laws passed. I say
                nothing of those which are passed in such a manner that scarcely five men, and those
                only of the lowest class, can be found to give a vote for them. He says that at the
                time of that ruin of the republic he carried a law respecting me, whom he called a
                tyrant and the destroyer of liberty. Who is there who will confess that he gave a
                vote when this law was passed against me? But when, in compliance with the same
                resolution of the senate, a law was passed about me in the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia centuriata</foreign> who is there who does not profess that then he was
                present, and that he gave a vote in favour of my safety? Which cause then, is the
                one which only to appear popular? that in which everything that is honourable in the
                city, and every age, and every rank of men agree? or that to the carrying of which
                some excited enemies fly as if hastening to banquet on the funeral of the republic? </p>
            <p><milestone n="110" unit="section"/>Suppose Gellius is present anywhere, a man
                unworthy of his brother, who is a most illustrious citizen and has been a most
                excellent consul and of the equestrian order of which he retains the name, though he
                has squandered the fortune which entitled him to it;<note anchored="true">It is not
                    quite certain what was the amount of property requisite as the qualification for
                    a knight; most probably, it was 400,000 <foreign xml:lang="la">ases</foreign>,
                    or, pounds weight, of copper. But whatever it was, a knight who had squandered
                    his property, so as not to have the requisite qualifications, was liable to be
                    struck out of the body by the censors.</note> will his presence make an assembly
                a popular one? For, to be sure, he is a man quite devoted to the Roman people. I
                never saw one more so. Why, even <pb n="206"/> when, in his youth, he might have
                shared to some extent in the credit arising from the ample honours of that most
                admirable man, Lucius Philippus, his step-father, he was so far from being fond of
                the people, that he devoured the whole of his property by himself. Afterwards, from
                having been a profligate and licentious young man, after he had brought down his
                paternal property from the easy circumstances in which stupid people take delight,
                to the strict rule of philosophers, he wished to be considered a man of Greek
                learning, and a quiet scholar, and on a sudden devoted himself to the study of
                literature. But his old Greeks did not do him much good; his slaves who read to him,
                and his books, were often pledged for wine; his appetite was as insatiable as ever;
                but his resources fell short enough. Therefore he was perpetually occupied with
                thoughts of revolution; he was growing old and weary of the peace and tranquillity
                of the republic. <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Has there ever been any sedition of which he has not been a prime mover? Has there
                ever been any seditious man with whom he has not been intimate? Has there ever been
                any turbulent assembly of which he has not been an exciter? Has he ever spoken well
                of any good man? Spoken well, do I say? Yes, rather, is there any brave and good
                citizen whom he has not attacked in the most wanton manner? A fellow who—not, I
                fancy, out of any desire, but merely in order to seem a favourer of the common
                people—took a freedwoman for his wife. <milestone n="111" unit="section"/>He voted
                concerning me; he was present at the assembly; he was present at all the banquets
                and mutual congratulations of that parricidal crew. However, he avenged me well when
                he kissed my enemies with that impure mouth of his. For, just as if it were owing to
                me that he has lost his property, he is an enemy to me on that very account, because
                he has nothing left. Have I, O Gellius, taken your patrimony from you, or have you
                devoured it? What? Were you, you gulf and whirlpool of your patrimony, were you
                gormandising at my risk, when you wished to prevent me from remaining any longer in
                the city, because as consul I had defended the republic against you and your
                associates? There is not one of your family who can bear the sight of you. All men
                avoid your approach, your conversation, your society. Postumius, the son of your
                sister, a young man of great prudence and high character, with the judgment of an
                    <pb n="207"/> man, branded you, when amid a great number of guardians he did not
                appoint you as one of the guardians of his children. But I have been carried away by
                indignation on my own account and on that of the republic (and I do not know which
                of us two he hates most) to say more than I need have said against that most frantic
                and impoverished glutton. <milestone n="112" unit="section"/>I return to my original
                subject, that, when the proceedings were being carried on against me, while the city
                was taken and oppressed, Gellius and Firmius and Titius, all Furies of the same
                class, were the chiefs and leaders of those mercenary bands, while the proposer of
                the law himself was in no respect free from being implicated in their baseness, and
                audacity, and iniquity. But when the law was passed for my restoration to my
                dignity, no one thought that either infirm health or old age supplied him with any
                reasonable excuse for being absent, there was no one who did not consider that by
                his vote he was recalling not only me but also the republic at the same time to its
                ancient position. <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="113"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Let us now consider the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> held for the
                election of magistrates. There was lately a college of tribunes, among whom three
                were considered not at all attached to the party of the people; but three were
                supposed to be most violently so. Of those who were not considered friends of the
                people and who were unable to stand before a packed and bribed assembly of that
                sort, I see that two have been made praetors by the Roman people and as far as I
                have been able to understand, by the conversation of the common people and by their
                votes, the Roman people openly alleged that the consistent and illustrious courage
                exhibited by Cnaeus Domitius in his tribuneship and the good faith and fortitude of
                Quintus Ancharius, would have been pleasing to them for the mere good-will which it
                proved even if they had not been able to effect anything. We see, now, what is the
                opinion which is entertained of Caius Fannius; and what the opinion of the Roman
                people is likely to be when he seeks for honours, ought to be doubtful to no one.
                    <milestone n="114" unit="section"/>What more shall I say? How did those two
                friends of the people fare? One, who however had put some restraint on himself, had
                proposed no law; he had merely entertained very different sentiments respecting the
                republic from those which men expected of him as he <pb n="208"/> had been a
                virtuous and innocent man, and one at all times esteemed by virtuous men; but as in
                his tribuneship he had shown himself very little able to comprehend what was
                approved by the genuine body of the people, and because he imagined that that was
                the Roman people which attended those assemblies, he did not attain that honour at
                which he would easily have arrived, if he had not hunted so much after popularity. </p>
            <p>The other, who was so frantic in his desire for popularity, that he thought neither
                the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, nor the Aelian law, nor the authority
                of the senate, nor the consul, nor his colleagues, nor the estimation of good men,
                of any importance at all, stood for the aedileship along with some virtuous men of
                the highest character, but still not men in the first rank for riches and personal
                influence; and did not get the vote of even his own tribe. He lost also the vote of
                the <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine</placeName> tribe, by the assistance of
                which it used to be said that all those pests were able to annoy the Roman people;
                and, indeed, (as was very acceptable to all good men,) he got nothing but repulses
                at that <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>. You see, therefore, that the very
                people itself—if I may use such an expression—is not for a seeker after popularity,
                since it so vehemently rejects those men who are accounted popular characters, and
                considers those men the most worthy of honour who are the most opposed to that class
                of men. <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="115" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Let us now come to the games. For the way in which I see your attention given to me,
                and your eyes directed towards me makes me think that I may be allowed now to speak
                in a lighter tone. At times the intimations of opinion which take place in
                assemblies and <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> are to be depended on; at
                times they are worthless and corrupt. The crowd of spectators in the theatre and at
                the gladiatorial games, are said at all times to pour forth their purchased
                applauses in small and scanty proportion at the caprice of a few directors. But it
                is easy, when that is the case, to see how it is done, and by whom, and what the
                entire people are doing. Why need I tell you now what men, or what description of
                citizens, receive the greatest applause? There is not one of you who is ignorant of
                this. However, let this be a matter of slight consequence, not that it really is,
                since it is given to every virtuous man; but, if it be a matter of slight
                consequence, it <pb n="209"/> is so only to a wise man. But to him who depends on
                the most trivial circumstances, who (as these men say themselves) is fettered and
                guided by popular rumour and popular favour, it is inevitable that applause must
                appear immortality and hissing death. </p>
            <p><milestone n="116" unit="section"/>I, then, ask you, above all men, O Scaurus, you
                who have exhibited the most splendid and magnificent games of all men,—whether any
                one of those popular characters was ever a spectator of your games? whether any one
                of them ever trusted himself to the theatre and to the Roman people? That very chief
                buffoon of all that man who was not only spectator, but it the same time actor and
                spouter,—that man who filled up all his sister's interludes who is introduced into
                companies of women as a singing-girl,—neither ventured to go to see your games in
                that furious tribuneship of his, nor any other games either except those from which
                he had some difficulty in escaping with his life. Once altogether, I say, did that
                popular man venture to trust himself among the spectators of the games when in the
                temple of Honour and Virtue honour was paid to virtue and when the monument of Caius
                Marius, the preserver of this empire had afforded a place in which the citizens
                could provide for the safety of a man who was a fellow citizen of his own municipal
                town, and defender of the republic. <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="117" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And at that time it was shown plainly enough with reference to both parties what were
                the real feelings of the Roman people in the first place when, after having heard
                the resolution of the senate universal applause was given to the proposer of the law
                and to the senate as a body, though it was not present and secondly, when every
                individual senator, as he returned from the senate to see the games, was received
                with loud clapping of hands. But, when the consul himself, who was exhibiting the
                games, took his seat, then the people stood undertaking him with extended hands, and
                with tears of joy declared their good will towards and pity for me. But when that
                furious enemy of mine with his senseless and frantic mind, arrived the Roman people
                could hardly restrain itself; the men could hardly abstain from wreaking their
                hatred on his foul and wicked person. Words indeed, and menacing gestures of the
                hands and loud outcries in the war of abuse and of curses on him were universal <pb
                    n="210"/><milestone n="118" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But why need I speak of the disposition and courage of the Roman people, looking back
                on their liberty after their long slavery, as shown by their conduct towards that
                man, whom, though he was at that time standing for the aedileship, even the actors
                did not spare to his face. For as the play being exhibited was one of Roman
                life,—“The Pretender,”<note anchored="true">This was a play of Afranius, on the
                    subject of the pretended madness of Junius Brutus, the expeller of the
                    Tarquins.</note> I believe,—the whole troop of actors, speaking in most splendid
                concert, and looking in the face of this profligate man, laid the greatest emphasis
                on the words, “To such a life as yours,” and, “The continued course and end of your
                wicked life.” He sat frightened out of his wits; and he, who formerly used to pack
                the assemblies which he summoned with bands of noisy buffoons, was now driven away
                by the voices of these same players. </p>
            <p>And since I have mentioned the games, I will not omit that circumstance, that amid
                the great variety of sentences and apophthegms which occur in that play, there was
                not one passage in which any expression of the poet had any bearing on our times,
                which either escaped the notice of the main body of the people, or on which
                particular emphasis was not laid by the actor. <milestone n="119" unit="section"
                />And I entreat you, while speaking on this topic, O judges, not to think that I am
                led by any levity of disposition to an unusual description of oratory, if in a court
                of justice I speak of poets, and actors, and games. <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>I am not, O judges, so ignorant of the forms of proceeding in trials, I am not so
                inexperienced in speaking, as to hunt for topics of every sort, and to gather and
                taste every sort of flower from every quarter. I know what is due to your dignity,
                and to my duty as counsel for the defence, and to this court, and to the character
                of Publius Sestius, and to the magnitude of his danger, and to my own age and to my
                own honour. But I have considered that while speaking on this point it was desirable
                to explain to the youth of the city who were the best men. And in explaining that
                point it was necessary to show that those men are not all friends of the people who
                are thought to be so. And that I can do most easily, if I represent to them the
                genuine and unbribed opinion of the Roman people, and the real inmost feelings of
                the citizens. <pb n="211"/><milestone n="120" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>How was it that,—when the news of that resolution of the senate which was passed in
                the temple of Virtue was fresh, and was brought to the people while engaged in
                beholding the games, and to the actors on the stage, in a very full house—that
                consummate actor, a man in truth who always performs the best part in the republic
                as he does on the stage weeping both from recent joy and also from a mixture of
                grief and regret for me, pleaded my cause before the Roman people in much more
                impressive language than I could possibly have pleaded for myself? For he gave a
                representation of the genius of the great poet whose play was being acted not merely
                by his art as an actor, but by his real grief. “What, shall he who with a constant
                mind assisted and supported the state; who has always stood on the side of the
                    Greeks<gap reason="* * *"/>” He said that I had always stood on your side; he
                pointed to your ranks; he was encored by every body. “Who in a critical state of
                affairs, did not hesitate to expose his life, did not spare his own person or
                    privileges<gap reason="* * *"/>.” <milestone n="121" unit="section"/> What
                shouts were raised as he recited these passages! when, omitting all consideration of
                his acting, the people applauded the words of the poet and the zeal of the actor,
                and the encouragement of their expectations respecting me. “A most excellent friend,
                in a most important war<gap reason="* * *"/>:” for the actor added that of himself,
                from his friendly inclination towards me; and perhaps men applauded it on account of
                their regret for me: “A man endowed with the highest ability.” <milestone n="57"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Then came those words in the same play, with what groans on the part of the Roman
                people were they accompanied when the actor repeated them! “Oh my father<gap
                    reason="* * *"/>.” He thought me,—me, I say, deserving to be lamented as his
                father, whom Quintus Catulus and whom many other men had repeatedly styled in the
                senate the Father of my country. With what great weeping for my ruin and for the
                confirmation of my property were his words accompanied, when he deplored his father
                driven away, his country afflicted, his house burnt and destroyed. He acted in such
                a manner, when after having dilated on his former fortune, he turned his description
                in this way. “All these things have I seen destroyed by fire<gap reason="* * *"/>,”
                as to rouse the tears of even my enemies and my enviers. <milestone n="122"
                    unit="section"/> O ye immortal gods, what did he do next? in <pb n="212"/> what
                way did he pronounce the next words? which indeed seem to me to have been acted and
                written in such a manner, that they might appropriately have been uttered even by
                Catulus himself, if he had come to life again; for he was; accustomed at times to
                reprove and attack the precipitate counsels of the people, and the blunders of the
                senate as well, with great freedom. “O ungrateful Argives; empty-headed Greeks;
                forgetful of kindness!” That, indeed, was not true; for they were not ungrateful,
                but miserable in not being allowed to secure the safety of that man from whom they
                had received their own: nor was any body ever more grateful to another than all of
                them were to me. But still what that most eloquent poet wrote was; applicable to me;
                and that not only best but also boldest of actors applied it to me, when he pointed
                at all orders of citizens, and accused the senate, the Roman knights, and the whole
                Roman people: “You allow him to be banished, you have voted for his being driven
                away, you endure his being driven away.” I myself only know by report what
                indications every one then gave of their feelings on that occasion, and how
                universally the whole Roman people declared their inclinations towards a man who had
                never sought to curry favour with the people; but they can judge more accurately of
                that who were present. <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="123"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And since my speech has carried me on to this point the actor bewailed my misfortune
                so repeatedly, while he was pleading my cause so mournfully, that his beautiful
                voice was hindered by his tears. Nor were the poets, whose genius I have always had
                an affection for, wanting to my necessities at that time, and the Roman people
                approved of their words, not only with their applause, but even with their groans.
                Ought then Aesop or Accius to have said these things on my behalf of the Roman
                people had been free, or ought they to have left them to the chief men of the state
                to say? In the Brutus, I was mentioned by name: “Tullius, who had established the
                liberty of the citizens.” It was encored again and again. Did the Roman people
                appear to be giving slight indications that it had been established by me and by the
                senate, though profligate citizens accused us as having destroyed it? <milestone
                    n="124" unit="section"/>But above all other times the sentiments of the entire
                Roman people were declared at the <pb n="213"/> exhibition of the gladiatorial
                games. For they were the gift of Scipio, worthy both of him and Quintus Metellus, in
                whose honour they were given. And they are a spectacle of that sort which is
                attended by immense numbers and by every class of men, and with which the multitude
                is delighted above all things into that crowd of spectators came Publius Sestius as
                tribune of the people when during his whole period of office he had been nothing
                whatever but serving my cause and he went among the people, not from any personal
                desire of applause but that our enemies might themselves see the inclinations of the
                universal people. He came, as you know, to the Maenian pillar, and such great
                applause ensued from all the places for beholding the spectacle all the way from the
                Capitol, and such universal clapping of hands from every seat, that it was said that
                there had never been in any cause whatever, greater or more manifest unanimity on
                the part of the Roman people. <milestone n="125" unit="section"/>Where at that time
                were those regulators of the assemblies, those masters of the laws, those expellers
                of citizens? Or have these wicked men any peculiar people of their own to whom we
                have given offence, and by whom we are hated? <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I think, indeed, that there never was a time when the people were assembled in
                greater crowds, than that time of those gladiatorial games; neither at any assembly,
                nor even at any <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>. What then did this
                innumerable multitude of men, this extraordinary indication of the will of the
                entire Roman people, without the slightest disagreement on those very days when it
                was thought that my cause was going to be decided, declare, except that the safety
                and dignity of the best citizens was dear to the entire Roman people? <milestone
                    n="126" unit="section"/>But that tribune of the people, who was accustomed to
                put questions to the assembly, not according to the usual custom of his father, or
                his grandfather, or his great grandfather, or of any of his ancestors, but like a
                Greek schoolmaster, “Did they wish me to return?” and when an outcry was raised
                against it by the faint voices of his hirelings, he said that the Roman people
                affirmed that they had no such wish,—he, though he used to go and see the gladiators
                every day, was never seen when he did come. He used to emerge on a sudden after he
                had crept along under the benches, so that he seemed as if he were going to say, <pb
                    n="214"/> “Mother, I call you.”<note anchored="true">These words, quoted also by
                    Horace, are from Pacuvius's play of Ilione, the mother of Polydorus, and are put
                    into the mouth of the shade of the murdered Polydorus.</note> And so that dark
                way by which he used to come to see the games was called the Appian Road. But still,
                the moment the people got sight of him, not only the gladiators, but the very horses
                of the gladiators, were frightened at the sudden hisses that ensued. <milestone
                    n="127" unit="section"/>Do you not see, then, what a great difference there is
                between the Roman people and an assembly? Do you not see that the masters of the
                assemblies are the object of the hatred of the Roman people? and that those who are
                not permitted to appear without insult in the assembly of artisans, are honoured by
                every possible mark of respect by the Roman people? </p>
            <p>Do you speak to me of Marcus Atilius Regulus, who of his own accord preferred
                returning to <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> to execution, to
                remaining at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> without those prisoners
                by whom he had been sent to the Senate, and then do you deny that I ought to be
                anxious for a recall procured by means of trained households of slaves and bands of
                armed men? <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Certainly, I suppose I was anxious for violence, who, as long as there was any
                violence going on, did nothing whatever, and who could not possibly have been
                undermined and injured if it had not been for violence. <milestone n="128"
                    unit="section"/>Was I to regret such a recall as this, which was so honourable
                to me that I am almost afraid of seeming to have left the city from a covetousness
                of glory, in order to return in such a manner? For what citizen except me did the
                senate ever recommend to the protection of foreign nations? For whose safety except
                mine did the senate ever publicly return thanks to the allies of the Roman people? I
                am the only person concerning whom the conscript fathers ever decreed that whoever
                went in command to any of the provinces, whoever were quaestors or lieutenants, were
                to take care of my safety and my life. Mine is the only cause since the foundation
                of the city in which every one who had any regard for the safety of the republic was
                summoned to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> from every part of
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, by letters written by the
                consuls in obedience to a resolution of the senate. That which the senate never once
                decreed at a time of peril to the entire republic, they thought it necessary to
                decree for the preservation of my individual safety. Who was <pb n="215"/> ever more
                regretted in the senate house? who was ever more lamented in the forum? who was ever
                so much missed in the courts of justice? At, and in consequence of my departure,
                every place immediately became deserted, melancholy, mute, full of grief and
                lamentation. What spot is there in all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName> in which there is not imprinted on the public monuments some
                proof of the zeal of the people for my safety, some testimony to my worth?
                    <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="129" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For why should I mention those resolutions of the senate, of more than human kindness
                towards me? Either that which was passed in the temple of the all-good and
                all-powerful <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, when that man, who has
                marked by three triumphs that he has added himself three countries and nations to
                this empire, read a long written speech in support of his opinion, and bore his
                testimony to the fact that I alone had preserved the country; and the senate in the
                fullest possible house adopted his opinion so entirely that only one enemy of mine
                dissented from it, and the decree as supported by Pompeius was recorded in the
                public registers for the eternal recollection of posterity? Or that which was passed
                the next day in the senate house, at the suggestion of the Roman people themselves,
                and of those men who had come up from the municipal towns to the effect that no one
                was to observe the heavens that no one was to cause any delay whatever, that if any
                one did so, he should be considered at once as one who wished to overturn the
                republic, and the senate would be very much offended, and that a motion should be
                immediately made respecting his conduct? And when the senate, meeting in great
                numbers, had checked the wickedness and audacity of some of those men by its
                authority and dignity, it added this clause, moreover; that if within the next five
                days in which my affairs could be discussed, they were not brought to a termination,
                I was to return to my country and be restored to all my former dignities. <milestone
                    n="62" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The senate decreed at the same time that thanks should be given to those men who had
                come up from all parts of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> for the
                sake of my safety; and that they should be requested to come again when the
                consideration of the subject was renewed. <milestone n="130" unit="section"/>And
                there was such a rivalry between all people to show their zeal for my safety, that
                the very men to <pb n="216"/> whom entreaties were addressed in my behalf by that
                senate, did also themselves address entreaties to the senate respecting me; and,
                accordingly, in all those transactions but one man alone was found who openly
                dissented from this earnest unanimity of all good men, so that even Quintus
                Metellus, the consul, who had been in a very great degree an enemy to me in the
                violent party contests which had arisen about political affairs, himself, made a
                motion in favour of my safety. And when he, being roused up by the exceeding
                authority of Publius Servilius, and also by a certain energy which gave weight to
                his eloquence, when he had invoked all the Metelli from the shades below, and had
                diverted the thoughts of his relation from the piratical attempts of Clodius to the
                dignity of that family by which they were connected together; and when he had
                brought him back to the recollection of their great domestic example and to the fate
                (shall I call it glorious, or melancholy?) of that great man Metellus Numidicus;
                then, I say, that illustrious man,—that genuine Metellus wept, and gave himself up
                from that moment to Publius Servilius even before he had come to the end of his
                speech. Nor could he, as a man of the same illustrious family, withstand that
                godlike dignity of eloquence so pregnant with the virtues of old time, and, though I
                was absent, he still became reconciled to me from that moment. <milestone n="131"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And certainly, if it be the case that illustrious men retain any sense or feeling
                after death, then he did a thing which was most acceptable to all the Metelli, and,
                above all, to that bravest of men and best of citizens, his own brother, the
                companion of all my labours, and dangers, and counsels. <milestone n="63"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But who is there who is ignorant of what a triumphant return mine was? how the people
                of <placeName key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName> held out to me on my
                arrival the right hand, as it were, of all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>, and of my country herself; and when the same day, the fifth
                of August, was the day of my arrival, and also the birthday of my dearest daughter,
                whom I then beheld for the first time after our long regret for one another, and our
                mourning; and was also the day consecrated as the day of the foundation of that very
                colony of <placeName key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName>; and also the
                anniversary of the dedication of the temple of Salus, as you know. And when I had
                been received into the joyful house of those most excellent and learned men, Laenius
                    <pb n="217"/> Flaccus and his father and brother which had received me with
                tears the year before when I was leaving <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName> and had defended me not without risk and danger to itself;
                and when along my whole road all the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName> seemed to be keeping the days of my arrival as days of
                festivity and the roads themselves were filled with a multitude of deputies sent
                from all quarters, and there was a vast throng of men crowding towards the city,
                full of exultation and congratulation to me; and my whole path up from the gate of
                the city, my ascent to the Capitol and my return to my house, was of such a nature,
                that amid my excessive joy I grieved also that so grateful a city should be so
                miserable and so ill-treated. <milestone n="132" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You now, then have an answer to the question which you put to me—who were the best
                men? They are not a race, as you termed them, an expression which I recognised at
                once, for it was one invented by that man by whom above all others, Publius Sestius
                sees himself opposed,—by that man who has wished the whole of this race of Romans
                destroyed and slaughtered,—who has constantly reproached and constantly attacked
                Caius Caesar, a very mild-tempered man and very averse to bloodshed, asserting that
                he, as long as that race lived, would never be free from anxiety. He gained nothing
                by his attacks on the whole body, but he never ceased to urge the point against me.
                He attacked me first of all by the instrumentality of the informer Vettius, to whom
                he put questions in the assembly, concerning me, and concerning the most illustrious
                men in the state. But while doing this, he joined those citizens in the same danger
                with me, bringing forward the same accusations against them, so as to deserve great
                gratitude from me for connecting me with the most honourable and bravest of men.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="133" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But afterwards he in a most wicked manner contrived all sorts of plots against me,
                for no provocation which I had given him, except inasmuch as I was anxious to please
                all virtuous men. He was every day mentioning some fault of mine to those men whom
                he could get to listen to him; he warned the man who was of all others the most
                friendly to me, Cnaeus Pompeius, to beware of entering my house, and to be on his
                guard against me; he united himself with my chief enemy, in such a manner that he
                said, with respect to that proscription of mine which Sextus Clodius, a fellow
                thoroughly worthy of his <pb n="218"/> associates, promoted, that he was the tablet
                on which it was written, and that he himself was the writer. And he alone of our
                whole order openly exulted at my departure and at your grief. And I, for my part, O
                judges, though he was every day attacking me, never said one word against him; nor
                did I think, while I was being attacked by every sort of engine and weapon of
                violence, and an army, and a mob, that it was suited to my dignity to complain of
                one archer more. </p>
            <p>He says that my acts displease him. Who doubts that? when he despises that law which
                expressly forbids any one to exhibit shows of gladiators within two years of his
                having stood, or being about to stand, for any office. <milestone n="134"
                    unit="section"/>And in that, O judges, I cannot sufficiently marvel at his
                rashness. He acts most openly against the law; and he does so, who is a man who is
                neither able to slip out of the consequences of a trial by his pleasant manner, nor
                to struggle out of them by his popularity, nor to break down the laws and courts of
                justice by his wealth and influence. What can induce the fellow to be so
                intemperate? I imagine it is out of his excessive covetousness of popularity, that
                he bought that troop of gladiators, so beautiful, noble, and magnificent. He knew
                the inclination of the people, he saw that great clamours and gatherings of the
                people would ensue. And elated with this expectation, and burning with a desire of
                glory, he could not restrain himself from bringing forward those gladiators, of whom
                he himself was the finest specimen. If that were the motive for his violation of the
                law, and if he were prompted by zeal to please the people on account of the recent
                kindness of the Roman people to himself, still no one would pardon him; but as the
                fact is that this band did not consist of men picked out of those who were for sale,
                but of men bought out of jails, and adorned with gladiatorial names, while he drew
                lots to see whom he would call Samnites, and whom Challengers, who could avoid
                having fears as to what might be the end of such licentiousness and such undisguised
                contempt for the laws?</p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="135" unit="section"/>But he brings forward two arguments in his
                defence. First of all, “I exhibit,” says he, “men fighting with beasts, and the law
                only speaks of gladiators.” A very clever idea! Listen now to a statement which is
                still more ingenious. He says <pb n="219"/> that he has not exhibited gladiators,
                but one single gladiator; and that he has limited the whole of his aedileship to
                this one exhibition. A true aedileship truly. One lion, two hundred men who fight
                with beasts. However, let him urge this defence. I wish him to feel confidence in
                his case; for he is in the habit of appealing to the tribunes of the people, and to
                use violent means to upset those tribunals in which be has not confidence. And I do
                not so much wonder that he despises my law, as having been framed by a man whom he
                considers his enemy, as at his having made up his mind to regard no law whatever
                which has been passed by a consul. He despises the Caecilian Didian law and the
                Licinian Junian law. Does he also deny that the law of Caius Caesar—who he is in the
                habit of boasting has been adorned and strengthened and armed by his law and by his
                kindness, respecting extortion and corruption,—is a law? And do they complain that
                there are other men, too, who wish to rescind the acts of Caesar, while this most
                excellent law is neglected by his brother-in-law and by this slave? <milestone
                    n="65" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And the prosecutor has dared, while pleading in this cause, to exhort you, O judges,
                to show at last some severity, and at length to apply some healing measures to the
                republic. But that is not a remedy when the knife is applied to some sound and
                healthy part of the body, that is the act of an executioner and mere inhumanity.
                Those are the men who really apply healing remedies to the republic, who cut out
                some pestilence as if it were a wen on the person of the state. <milestone n="136"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But in order that my speech may have some termination, and that I may cease speaking
                before you are weary of listening to me with attention, I will finish my argument
                about the party of the best men and about their leaders and about those who are the
                chief defenders of the republic. I will stir you up, O young men, especially you who
                are of noble birth, to the imitation of your ancestors and I will exhort you who
                have the opportunity of arriving at high rank by the exercise of genius and virtue
                to adopt that line of conduct by which many new men have become crowned with honour
                and glory. <milestone n="137" unit="section"/>This, believe me, is the only path to
                praise, and dignity and honour,—to be praised and beloved by men who are wise and
                good, and endowed with good dispositions by nature; to <pb n="220"/> become
                acquainted with the constitution of the state, as it has been most wisely
                established by our ancestors, who, when they could no longer endure the power of a
                king, created annual magistrates on the principle of making the senate the perpetual
                supreme council of the republic, and of allowing men to be elected into that body by
                the whole people, and of opening the road to that supreme order to the industry and
                virtue of all the citizens. They established the senate as the guardian, and
                president, and protector of the republic; they chose the magistrates to depend on
                the authority of this order, and to be as it were the ministers of this most
                dignified council; and they contrived that the senate itself should be strengthened
                by the high respectability of those ranks which came nearest to it, and so be able
                to defend and promote the liberties and interests of the common people. <milestone
                    n="66" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="138" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Those who defend these institutions with all their might are the best men, of
                whatever rank they are; and they who chiefly support all these offices and the
                republic on their necks as it were, are accounted the chiefs of the party of the
                best men,—the chief advisers and preservers of the state. I confess that there are,
                as I have said before, many adversaries and enemies to, and enviers of, this class
                of men, that there are many dangers in their path, that many injuries are heaped
                upon them, that many labours have necessarily to be experienced and undergone by
                them. But all my speech is addressed to virtue, and not to sloth; to dignity, and
                not to luxury; to those men who look upon themselves as born for their country, for
                their fellow-citizens, for praise, for glory, not for sleep, for banquets, and soft
                delights. For if there be any men who are influenced wholly by pleasures, and who
                have given themselves entirely up to the seductions of vices and to the
                gratification of their desires, let them abandon all desire for honours; let them
                abstain from meddling with the republic; let them be satisfied with enjoying their
                ease, and owing it to the labour of virtuous and brave men. </p>
            <p><milestone n="139" unit="section"/>But they who desire the good report of good men,
                which is the only thing which is really entitled to be called glory, ought to seek
                ease and pleasures for others and not for themselves. They must toil for the common
                advantage; they must incur enmities, and often encounter tempests, for the sake of
                the republic; they must combat with many audacious and wicked <pb n="221"/>
                men,—sometimes even with men of great influence. This is what we have heard of the
                sentiments and actions of the most illustrious men; this is what tradition reports
                of them, and what we have read nor do we ever see those men loaded with praise who
                from time to time have stirred up the minds of men to sedition or who by bribery
                have corrupted the rich nations of the ignorant or who have brought brave and
                illustrious men, who have deserved well of the republic into odium and unpopularity.
                Our countrymen have always thought such men as those contemptible and audacious and
                wicked and mischievous citizens. But they who have checked the violence and the
                attempts of those men, they who by their authority, by their integrity, by their
                firmness and by their magnanimity have resisted the designs of audacious men, have
                been at all times considered wise and good men, the chiefs, and leaders and advisers
                of this order of this dignified body, and of the empire. <milestone n="67"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="140" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And let no one on account of what has happened to me, or perhaps to one or two others
                besides, fear to adopt this plan of life. One man in this state whom I can mention,
                a man who had done great services to the republic, Lucius Opimius, did fall in a
                most shameful manner. And if his grave is a deserted one on the shore of <placeName
                    key="tgn,7010750">Dyrrachium</placeName>, he has a most superb monument in our
                forum. And the Roman people itself at all times delivered him from danger, though he
                was exceedingly unpopular with the mob on account of the death of Caius Gracchus;
                and it was a storm coming from another quarter—from an iniquitous judicial derision
                which crushed that illustrious citizen. But the other men who have done good service
                to the state have either if for a while they have been stricken by any sudden
                violence or tempest of popular odium, been restored again and recalled by the people
                of its own accord, or else they have passed their whole lives without any such
                injuries or attacks. But they who have disregarded the wisdom of the senate, and the
                authority of good men, and the established rules of our ancestors, and have sought
                to become agreeable to an ignorant and excited multitude, have nearly all suffered
                just retribution and made atonement to the republic either by instant death, or
                shameful exile. <milestone n="141" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But it even among the Athenians, a nation of Greeks, far removed from the serious
                wisdom of our ancestors, there were <pb n="222"/> not wanting men to defend the
                republic against the rashness of the people;—though every one who ever did so was
                sure to be banished from the city;—if the great Themistocles, the preserver of his
                country, was not deterred from defending the republic, either by the calamity of
                Miltiades, who had saved that state only a little before, or by the banishment of
                Aristides, who is said to have been the greatest of all men: and if, after his time,
                many illustrious men of the same state, whom it is unnecessary for me to mention by
                name, in spite of the numerous instances of the popular ill-temper and fickleness
                which they had before them, still defended that republic of theirs; what ought we to
                do who, in the first place, have been born in that city which appears to me to be
                the very birth-place of wisdom and dignity and magnanimity; and who, in the second
                place, are raised on such a pinnacle of glory that all human things may well appear
                insignificant by the side of it; and who, lastly, have undertaken to uphold that
                republic, which is one of such dignity, that to slay a man who is defending it is no
                less a crime than to attack it and to endeavour to seize the supreme power?
                    <milestone n="68" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="142" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Those Greeks whom I have just mentioned, having been unjustly condemned and banished
                by their fellow-citizens, still, because they deserved well of their state, enjoy
                such renown at this present time, not in <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                    >Greece</placeName> alone, but among ourselves also, and in other lands, that no
                one ever mentions the names of those men by whom they were oppressed, and that every
                one prefers their disasters to the superior power of their enemies. Who of the
                Carthaginians was superior to Hannibal in wisdom, and valour, and actual
                achievements? a man who single-handed fought for so many years for empire and for
                glory with such numbers of our generals. His own fellow-citizens banished him from
                the city; but we see that he, though our enemy, is celebrated in the writings and
                recollection of our citizens. </p>
            <p><milestone n="143" unit="section"/> Let us then imitate our Bruti, our Camilli, and
                Ahalae our Decii, our Curius, and Fabricius, and Maximus, our Scipios, our Lentuli,
                our Aemilii, and countless others, who have given liberty to this republic; all of
                whom I consider deserving of being ranked among the company and number of the
                immortal gods. Let us love our country, let us obey the senate, let us consult the
                interests of the good; let us <pb n="223"/> disregard present rewards, and fix our
                eyes on the glory which we shall receive from posterity. Let us think that the most
                desirable conduct, which is the most upright; let us hope for whatever we choose,
                but bear whatever befalls us, let us consider, lastly, that the bodies of brave men
                and great citizens are mortal, but that the impulses of the mind and the glory of
                virtue are everlasting. And let us not if we see that the opinion is consecrated by
                the most holy example of the great Hercules, whose body indeed has been burnt but
                whose life and virtue are said to have received instant immortality, think any the
                less that they who by their counsels and labours have either increased the greatness
                or defended the safety, or preserved the existence of this great republic have
                acquired everlasting glory. <milestone n="69" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="144"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But suddenly, O judges, while speaking of the dignity and renown of those valiant and
                most illustrious citizens, and while I was preparing to say still more on that
                subject, I have been checked in the onward progress of my speech by the sight of
                these men. I see Publius Sestius the defender and upholder and chief maintainer of
                my safety and of your authority, and of the cause of the commonwealth on his trial
                as a criminal; I see his young son present here before you, gazing on me with
                tearful eyes, I see <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName> the vindicator of
                your liberty, the guardian of my safety the support and defence of the afflicted
                republic, the extinguisher of the piratical attempts of our domestic enemies, the
                repressor of daily bloodshed, the defender alike of the temples of the gods and of
                the houses of individuals the bulwark of the senate-house, in mourning apparel, and
                under a prosecution. I see Publius Lentulus, to whose father I pay my salutations as
                the protecting deity and parent of my fortune and my name, and of my brother, and of
                all my hopes and property in the miserable garb and squalid condition of an
                impeached man: I see the man who in the course of last year received the robe of
                manhood by the will of his father, and the purple robe by the deliberate choice<note
                    anchored="true">Publius Lentulus had been named one of the college of augurs, in
                    spite of his youth, which was a legal disqualification for such an office, in
                    compliment to his father.</note> of the people, now, in this year, in the same
                robe seeking to avert by his entreaties the sudden infliction of this most
                iniquitous decree, supplicating you on <pb n="224"/> behalf of his most gallant
                father, and your most illustrious citizen. <milestone n="145" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And these mourning robes of so many and of such illustrious citizens, and these signs
                of grief, and these tokens of abasement have all been put on for my single sake;
                because they defended me, because they grieve for my misfortune and for my grief,
                because, in compliance with the entreaties of all of you, they restored me to my
                mourning country, to the senate who demanded me back, and to <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> who entreated my recall. What great
                wickedness is imputed to me? What great crime did I commit on that day; on that day,
                I say, when I laid before you the proofs against, and the letters and confessions of
                those men who were seeking the general destruction; when I obeyed your commands?
                But, if it be a wicked thing to love one's country, still I have suffered punishment
                enough; my house has been pulled down, my property has been pillaged; my children
                have been scattered abroad, my wife has been insulted, my most excellent brother, a
                man of incredible affection and unheard-of devotion to me, has fallen, with all the
                emblems of most bitter grief, at the feet of my bitterest enemies; I have been
                driven from my altars, from my hearth, from my household gods; I have been separated
                from my friends and torn from my country, which (to say the very least) I had most
                undoubtedly shielded; I have endured the cruelty of my enemies, the wickedness of
                faithless men, and the dishonesty of envious ones. <milestone n="146" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>If this is not enough, because all this appears to be defaced by my return; it were
                better—it were far better, I say, for me, O judges, to fall back again into the same
                misfortune as before, than to bring such calamity on my defenders and preservers.
                Would it be possible for me to remain in this city after those men have been driven
                away from it, who alone enabled me again to enjoy this city? I cannot do so—it will
                not be possible for me, O judges,—nor shall this boy, who now, by his tears, shows
                how great his filial affection is, ever behold me in safety if he loses the presence
                of his father on account of his kindness to me; nor shall he, as often as he sees
                me, groan, and say that he beholds a man who has been the ruin of himself and of his
                father. I, in every fortune, whatever may befall me, will cling to you; nor shall
                    <pb n="225"/> any fortune ever separate me from those men whom you, O judges,
                behold in mourning apparel for my sake. Nor shall those nations to whom the senate
                recommended me, and to whom it gave thanks for their treatment of me, ever see this
                man as an exile on account of his conduct to me, without seeing me as his companion.
                    <milestone n="147" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But the immortal gods, who received me on my arrival in their temples, accompanied by
                these men and by Publius Lentulus the consul, and the republic itself, than which
                there is nothing more holy, have entrusted these things, O judges, to your power.
                You are able by your decision to encourage the minds of all virtuous men, and to
                check the designs of the wicked; you are able by your decision to avail yourselves
                of the services of the virtuous citizens, to strengthen me, and to renew the
                republic. Wherefore, I beseech and entreat you, if you wish for my safety, to save
                those men by whose instrumentality you have recovered me. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
