<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>In the Senate after his Return</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--   <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc> -->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-05-20" who="Lisa Cerrato">Review of EpiDoc and CTS work. Minor edits.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-17" who="Zach Himes">Changed section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi019.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
   <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO AFTER HIS RETURN. ADDRESSED TO THE SENATE.</head>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Cicero by his conduct in the conspiracy of Catiline had made many enemies, as there were many
    citizens of high rank and great influence more or less implicated in that treason. And besides
    those men, he had mortally offended a profligate senator, named Clodius, against whom he had
    appeared as a witness on a trial for impiety. Clodius, (by the assistance of Julius Caesar, who
    was offended with Cicero for refusing to support the measures of the triumvirate,) got adopted
    as a plebeian, in order to be made tribune of the people, so as to have the greater power to
    annoy Cicero. He was elected tribune A. U. C. 696. And the consuls, Lucius Calpurnius Piso
    Caesoninus and Aulus Gabinius, were also enemies to Cicero. After some preliminary laws, mostly
    aimed, in Cicero's opinion, at him, Clodius proposed a special law, “that whoever had taken
    away the life of a citizen uncondemned and without a trial, should be prohibited from fire and
    water.” This alluded especially to Cicero's having executed the accomplices of Catiline; and he
    accordingly changed his dress, as it was usual for people to do in the case of a public
    impeachment, and appeared in the streets in a mourning robe, and the whole body of the knights
    and the young nobility, to the number of twenty thousand, as he says himself in his speech to
    the people after his return, also changed their dress, and accompanied him about the city to
    protect him from the insults of Clodius's partisans, and to implore the assistance of the
    people. And all this body went to the consuls to implore their favour for Cicero; but Piso
    refused to see them, and Gabinius treated them with the greatest insolence, which caused such
    indignation in the assembly that Ninnius the tribune made a motion (which was carried
    unanimously) that the senate also should put on mourning robes. The consuls issued an edict
    forbidding them to do so. On one occasion Clodius with his slaves fell on Cicero's partisans
    and attacked them so violently that Hortensius was nearly killed and Vibienus, a senator, died
    of the wounds he received. Caesar openly espoused the cause of Clodius, declaring that he had
    always thought the proceedings against Lentulus and the rest irregular and illegal. And Pompey,
    who had at first espoused Cicero's cause began to be alarmed, and to avoid giving him any
    effectual assistance. And the disturbances in Rome rose to such a height, that Cicero, by the
    advice of his friends, and especially of Cato, Hortensius, and Atticus, went into voluntary
    exile.
   <milestone unit="para"/>As soon as he had departed, Clodius filled the forum with his own partisans and his slaves,
    and proposed a law in the following terms: “Whereas Marcus Tullius Cicero has put Roman
    citizens to death unheard and uncondemned; and for that end forged the authority and decree of
    the senate; may it please you to ordain that he be interdicted from fire and water; that nobody
    presume to harbour or receive him, on pain of death; and that whoever shall move, speak, vote,
    or take any step towards recalling him, shall be treated as a public enemy, unless those should
    first be recalled to life whom Cicero unlawfully put to death.” <note anchored="true">I take
     the terms of this law from Middleton's Life, from which indeed, I have abridged this argument;
     which is in some degree the argument of the three following speeches.</note> The name of
    Sedulius, one of the meanest of the people, was affixed to the law as if he had been its
    proposer, who afterwards declared that he was not in Rome at the time, and that he had known
    nothing about it.
   <milestone unit="para"/>Cicero went to Thessalonica. He had not been gone more than two months when Ninnius made a
    motion in the senate to recall him and to repeal the law which Clodius had enacted against him,
    and it would have been carried had not Aelius Ligur, one of the tribunes, interposed his veto.
    The senate, however, passed a resolution that no business should be proceeded with till the
    consuls had prepared a new law respecting Cicero's affairs. Pompey, too, began to feel the want
    of Cicero's assistance, and consulted Caesar as to the expediency of promoting his recall.
   <milestone unit="para"/>The new consuls were Publius Cornelius Lentulus, a warm friend of Cicero, and Quintus
    Metellus Nepos, who had been his enemy but who now, out of complaisance to the triumvirate,
    promised to assist in his restoration. One of the tribunes elect, whose name was Sextus, was
    also very eager in his cause; but Clodius bribed two of those who were coming into office,
    Servius Atilius Serranus and Numerius Quinctius Gracchus, to oppose all measures for his
    restoration. On the first of January the moment that the new consuls entered on their office,
    Lentulus made a motion in the senate for Cicero's recall; Metellus also spoke in favour of it,
    and Cotta, whose opinion was first asked declared that as Cicero had not been banished legally
    but had only retired from the city of his own accord for the sake of peace, there was <pb n="472"/> no law requisite for his recall; but that a vote of the senate would be sufficient.
    The motion would have passed at once had not Serranus interposed his veto. Great disturbances
    ensued in Rome; Fabricius, one of the tribunes favourable to Cicero, was attacked with a party
    of his friends by Clodius at the head of a band of gladiators, whom he had purchased; and great
    numbers of citizens were slain, so that Cicero says, (<bibl n="Cic. Sest. 35">Pro Sestio,
     35-38</bibl>,) that there had never been such bloodshed in Rome except in the time of Cinna.
    The senate passed a resolution that no business should be done till the vote for Cicero's
    recall was carried, and ordered the consuls to summon all the people of Italy who wished well
    to the state to come to the assistance and defence of Cicero. Pompey was at this time at Capua
    acting as chief magistrate of his new colony, where he presided in person at their making a
    decree in Cicero's honour, and took the trouble likewise of visiting all the other colonies and
    chief towns in those parts, to appoint them a day of general rendezvous at Rome to assist at
    the promulgation of the desired law. At last a decree to recall Cicero was carried, to the
    great joy of all the people; but for some time Clodius was enabled to prevent any regular law
    being passed to that effect, till at last all his partisans were afraid to stand by him any
    longer, and it was not until the fourth of August that the law was finally carried. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Cicero, in anticipation of it, had already embarked for Italy, and on the fifth of August he
    landed at Brundusium. He was received with the greatest honours by every town through which he
    passed on his way to Rome, and multitudes came from all quarters to see him and to escort him;
    and on his arrival in the city he was received with universal acclamations.
   <milestone unit="para"/>He arrived in the city on the fourth of September, and the next day the consuls summoned the
    senate to give him an opportunity of addressing that body, when he made the following
    speech.</p></div>
  
  
   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>If, O conscript fathers, I return you thanks in a very inadequate manner for your kindness to
    me, and to my brother, and to my children, (which shall never be forgotten by us,) I beg and
    entreat you not to attribute it so much to any coldness of my disposition, as to the magnitude
    of the service which you have done me. For what fertility of genius, what copiousness of
    eloquence can be so great, what language can be found of such divine and extraordinary power, as
    to enable any one, I will not say to do due honour to the universal kindness of you all towards
    us, but even to count up and enumerate all the separate acts of kindness which we have received
    from you? You have restored to me my brother; whom I have wished for above all things; you have
    restored me to my most affectionate brother; you have restored us parents to our children, and
    our children to us; you have restored to us our dignity, our rank, our fortunes, the republic,
    which we reverence above all things, and our country, than which nothing can be dearer to us;
    you have restored us, in short, to ourselves. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And if we ought to consider our parents most dear to us,
    because by them our life, our property, our freedom, and our rights as citizens have been given
    to us; if we love the immortal gods, by whose kindness we have preserved all those things, and
    have also had other benefits added to them; if we are most deeply attached to the Roman people
    owing to the honours paid to us by whom we have been placed in this most noble council, and in
    the very highest rank and dignity and in this citadel of the whole earth, if we are devoted to
    this order of the senate by which we have been frequently distinguished by most honourable
    decrees in our favour, surely it is a boundless and infinite obligation which we are under to
    you, who, by your singular zeal and unanimity an my behalf, have combined at one time the
    benefits done us by our parents, the bounty of the immortal gods, the honours conferred on us by
    the Roman people, and your own frequent decisions in my case; in such a manner that, owing, as
    we do, much to you, and great gratitude to the Roman people, and innumerable thanks to our
    parents, and everything to the immortal gods, the honours and enjoyments which we had separately
    before by their instrumentality, we have now recovered all together by your kindness. </p></div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, O conscript fathers, we seem by your agency to have obtained a species of
    immortality, a thing too great to be even wished for by men. For what time will there ever be in
    which the memory and fame of your kindnesses to me will perish? The memory of your kindness,
    who, at the very time that you were besieged by violence and arms and terror and threats, not
    long after my departure all agreed in recalling me, at the motion of Lucius Ninnius, a most
    fearless and virtuous man, the most faithful and (if it had come to a battle) the least timid
    defender of my safety that that fatal year could produce. After the honour of making a formal
    decree to that effect was refused to you by the means of that tribune of the people, who as he
    was unable of himself to injure the republic, destroyed it as far as he could by the wickedness
    of another, you never kept silence concerning me, you never ceased to demand my safety from
    those consuls who had sold it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, at last it was owing
    to your <pb n="474"/> authority and your zeal that that very year which I had preferred to have
    fatal to myself rather than to my country, elected these men as tribunes, who proposed a law
    concerning my safety, and constantly brought it under your notice. For the consuls being modest
    men, and having a regard for the laws, were hindered by a law, not by the one which had been
    passed concerning me, but by one respecting themselves, when my enemy had carried a clause, that
    when those men had come to life again who nearly destroyed the state, then I might return to the
    city. By which action he confessed two things—both that he longed for them to be living, and
    also that the republic would be in great peril, if either the enemies and murderers of the
    republic came to life again, or if I did not return. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, in that very year when I had departed, and when the chief man of the state was
    forced to defend his own life, not by the protection of the laws, but by that of his own
    walls,—when the republic was without consuls, and bereft, like an orphan, not only of its
    regular parents, but even of its annual guardians,—when you were forbidden to deliver your
    opinions,—when the chief clause of my proscription was repeatedly read,—still you never
    hesitated to consider my safety as united with the general welfare. </p></div><milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But when, by the singular and admirable virtue of Publius Lentulus the consul, you began on
    the first of January to see light arising in the republic out of the clouds and darkness of the
    preceding year,—when the great reputation of Quintus Metellus, that most noble and excellent
    man, and the virtue and loyalty of the praetors, and of nearly all the tribunes of the people,
    had likewise come to the aid of the republic,—when Cnaeus Pompeius, the greatest man for virtue,
    and glory, and achievements that any nation or any age has ever produced, the most illustrious
    man that memory can suggest thought that he could again come with safety into the senate,—then
    your unanimity with respect to my safety was so great that my body only was absent, my dignity
    had already returned to this country. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> And that month you were
    able to form an opinion as to what was the difference between me and my enemies. I abandoned my
    own safety, in order to save the republic from being (for my sake) stained with the blood of the
    citizens; they thought fit to hinder my return, not by the votes of the Roman people, but by a
    river of blood. Therefore, after those events, you gave no answers to the citizens, or the
    allies, or to kings; the judges gave no decisions; the people came to no vote on any matter;
    this body issued no declarations by its authority; you saw the forum silent the senate-house
    mute, the city dumb and dispirited. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> And then, too, when he had
    gone away, who, being authorized by you, had resisted murder and conflagration, you saw men
    rushing all over the city with sword and firebrand; you saw the houses of the magistrates
    attacked, the temples of the gods burnt, the <foreign xml:lang="lat">faces</foreign> of a most
    admirable man and illustrious consul burnt, the holy person of a most fearless and virtuous
    officer, a tribune of the people, not only laid hands on and insulted, but wounded with the
    sword and killed. And by that murder some magistrates were so alarmed, that partly out of fear
    of death, partly out of despair for the republic, they in some degree forsook my cause; but
    others remained behind, whom neither terror, nor violence, nor hope, nor fear, nor promises, nor
    threats, nor arms, nor firebrands, could influence so as to make them cease to stand by your
    authority, and the dignity of the Roman people, and my safety. </p></div><milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The chief of those men was Publius Lentulus, the parent and god of my life, and fortune, and
    memory, and name. He thought that the best proof that he could give of his virtue, the best
    indication that he could afford of his disposition, the greatest ornament with which he could
    embellish his consulship would be the restoration of me to myself, to my friends, to you, and to
    the republic. And as soon as ever he was appointed consul elect he never hesitated to express an
    opinion concerning my safety worthy both of himself and of the republic. When the veto was
    interposed by the tribune of the people,—when that admirable clause was read: “That no one
    should make any motion before you that no one should propose any decree to you that no one
    should raise any discussion, or make any speech or take any vote or frame any law;” he thought
    all that as I have said before, a proscription and not a law, by which a citizen who had
    deserved well of the republic was by name and without any trial, taken from the senate and the
    republic at the same time. But as soon as he entered on his office, I will not say what did he
    do before, but what else did he do at all, except labour by my preservation to establish your
    authority and <pb n="476"/> dignity on a firm basis for the future? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p> O ye immortal gods! what great kindness do you appear to have shown me, in
    making Publius Lentulus consul this year. How much greater still would your bounty bare been,
    had he been so the preceding year; for I should not have been in want of such medicine as a
    consul could give, unless I had fallen by a wound inflicted by a consul. I had been often told
    by one of the wisest of men and one of the most virtuous of citizens, Quintus Catulus, that it
    was not often that there was one wicked consul, but that there had never been two at the same
    time since the foundation of Rome, except in that terrible time of Cinna. Wherefore, he used to
    say that my interest would always be firmly secured, as long as there was even one virtuous
    consul in the republic. And he would have spoken the truth, if that state of things with respect
    to consuls could have remained lasting and perpetual, that, as there never had been two bad ones
    in the republic, so there never should be. But if Quintus Metellus had been at that time consul,
    who was then my enemy, do you doubt what would have been his feelings with regard to my
    preservation, when you see that he was a mover and seconder of the measure proposed for my
    restoration? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> But at that time there were two consuls, whose
    minds, narrow, contemptible, mean, groveling, dark, and dirty, were unable to look properly at,
    or to uphold, or to support the mere name of the consulship, much less the splendour of that
    honour, and the importance of that authority. They were not consuls, but dealers in provinces,
    and sellers of your dignity. One of whom demanded back from me, in the hearing of many,
    Catiline, his lover; the other reclaimed Cethegus, his cousin;—the two most wicked men in the
    memory of man, who (I will not call them consuls, but robbers) not only deserted, in a cause in
    which, above all others, the welfare of the republic and the dignity of the consulship was
    concerned, but betrayed me, and opposed me, and wished to see me stripped of all aid, not only
    from themselves, but also from you and from the other orders of the state. One of them, however,
    deceived neither me nor any one else. </p></div><milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For who ever could have any hope of any good existing in that man, the earliest period of
    whose life was made openly subservient to everyone's lusts; who had not the heart to repel the
    obscene impurity of men from the holiest portion of his person? who, after he had ruined his own
    estate with no less activity than he afterwards displayed in his endeavours to ruin the
    republic, supported his indigence and his luxury by every sort of pandering and infamy; who, if
    he had not taken refuge at the altar of the tribuneship, would not have been able to escape from
    the authority of the praetor, nor the multitude of his creditors, nor the seizure of his goods.
    And if he had not while in discharge of that office, passed that law about the piratical war,
    he, in truth, would have yielded to his own poverty and wickedness, and had recourse to piracy
    himself; and who would have done so with less injury to the republic than he did by remaining
    within our walls as an impious enemy and robber. It was he who was inspecting victims, and
    sitting in the discharge of that duty, when a tribune of the people procured a law to be passed
    that no regard should be had to the auspices,—that no one should on that account be allowed to
    interrupt the assembly or the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>, or to put his veto on
    the passing of a law; and that the Aelian and Fufian <note anchored="true">“The <foreign xml:lang="lat">Aelia lex</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">Rufia lex</foreign> were passed
     about the end of the sixth century of the city, and gave all magistrates the <foreign xml:lang="lat">obnuntiatio</foreign>, or power of preventing or dissolving the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> by observing the omens, and declaring them to be
     unfavourable.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 560, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Lex</foreign>.</note> laws
    should have no validity, which our ancestors had enacted, intending them to be the firmest
    protection of the republic against the insanity of the tribunes. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> And he also afterwards, when a countless multitude of virtuous men had come to
    him from the Capitol as suppliants, and in morning garments, and when all the most noble young
    men of Rome, and all the Roman knights, had thrown themselves at the feet of that most
    profligate pander, with what an expression of countenance did that curled and perfumed debauchee
    reject, not only the tears of the citizens, but even the prayers of his country! Nor was he
    content with that but he even went up to the assembly, and there said what even if his man
    Catiline had come to life again he would not have dared to say,—that he would make the Roman
    knights pay for the nones of December of my consulship, and for the Capitoline Hill; and he not
    only said this, but he even summoned those before him that suited him. And this imperious consul
    actually banished from the city Lucius Lamia, a Roman knight, a man of the highest character,
    and a very eager advocate of my safety, because of his intimacy with me, and very much attached
    to the state, as it was likely that a man of his fortune would be. And when you had passed a
    resolution to change your garments, and had changed them, and though, indeed, all virtuous men
    had already done the same thing, he, reeking with perfumes, clad in his <foreign xml:lang="lat">toga praetexta</foreign>, which all the praetors and aediles had at that time laid aside,
    derided your mourning garb, and the grief of a most grateful city, and did what no tyrant ever
    did,—he issued an edict that you should lament your disasters in secret and not presume openly
    to bewail the miseries of your country. </p></div><milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And when in the Circus Flaminius <note anchored="true">The Circus Flaminius was outside the
     walls of the city, and the assembly was held there to allow Caesar to be present, who, being
     now invested with a military command, could not come into the city.</note> (I will not say the
    consul had been conducted into the assembly by a tribune of the people, but) the archpirate had
    been brought in by another robber, he came first a man of what exceeding dignity, full of wine,
    sleep, and debauchery! with hair dripping with ointments, with carefully arranged locks, with
    heavy eyes, moist cheeks, a husky and drunken voice; and he, a grave authority, said that he was
    greatly displeased at citizens having been executed without having been formally condemned.
    Where is it that this great authority has lain hid so long out of our sight? Why has the
    extraordinary virtue of this ringletted dunce been wasted so long in scenes of debauchery and
    gluttony? For that other man, Caesoninus Calventius, from his youth up has been habituated to
    the forum, though, except his assumed and crafty melancholy, there was no single thing to
    recommend him,—no knowledge of the law, no skill in speaking, no knowledge of military affairs
    or of men, no liberality. And if, while passing him, you noticed how ungentlemanlike, and rough,
    and sulky he looked, though you might think him a barbarian and a boor, still you would not
    suppose him to be lascivious and profligate. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> You would think
    it made no difference whether you were standing in the forum with this man, or with a barbarian
    from Aethiopia; there he was, in that sense, without flavour, a mute, slow, uncivilized piece of
    goods. You would be apt to suppose him a Cappadocian just escaped out of a lot of slaves for
    sale. Then, again, how lustful was he at home,—how impure, how intemperate. He was not like a
    front-door, open for the reception of legitimate pleasures, but when he began to devote himself
    to literature, and, beastly rather a postern for all sorts of secret gratification. And glutton
    that he was, to learn philosophy with the Greeks, then he became an Epicurean, not because he
    was really much devoted to that sect such as it is, but because he was caught by that one
    expression about pleasure. And he has masters, none of those foolish fellows who go on for whole
    days discussing duty and virtue,—who exhort men to labour, to industry, to encounter dangers for
    the sake of their country, but men who argue that no hour ought to be unoccupied by pleasure;
    that in every part of the body there ought always to be some joy and delight to be perceived.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> He uses his masters as a sort of superintendents of his
    lusts; they seek out and scent out all sorts of pleasures; they are the seasoners and furnishers
    of his banquets they appraise and value the different pleasures, they give a formal decision and
    judgment as to how much indulgence ought to be allowed to each separate pleasure. He, becoming
    accomplished in all these arts, despised this most prudent city to such a degree that he thought
    that all his lusts and all his atrocities could be concealed, if he only thrust his ill-omened
    face into the forum. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>He deceived me, though I will not so much say me (for I know, from my connection with the
    Pisos how much the Transalpine blood on his mother's side had removed him from the qualities of
    that family) but he deceived you and the Roman people, not by his wisdom or his eloquence, as is
    often the case with many men, but by his wrinkled brow and solemn look. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> Lucius Piso, did you dare at that time with that eye (I will not say with that
    mind ) with that forehead (I will not say with what character,) and with that arrogance (for I
    cannot say, after such achievements,) to unite with Aulus Gabinius in forming plans for my ruin?
    Did not the odour of that man's perfumes, or his breath reeking with wine, or his forehead
    marked with the traces of the curling-iron, lead you to think that as you were like him in
    reality, you were no longer able to use the impenetrability of your countenance to conceal such
    enormous atrocities? Did you dare to continue with that man to abandon the consular dignity,—the
    existing condition of the republic,—the authority of the senate,—the fortunes of a citizen who
    had above all others deserved well of the republic, to the provinces? While you <pb n="480"/>
    were consul, according to your edicts and commands, it was not allowed to the Roman senate or
    people to come to the assistance of the republic, I will not say by their votes and their
    authority, but even by their grief and their mourning garb. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Did you think that you were consul at Capua, a city where there was once the abode of
    arrogance, or at Rome, where all the consuls that ever existed before you were obedient to the
    senate? Did you dare, when you were brought forward in the Flaminian Circus, with your
    colleague, to say that you had always been merciful? by which expression you declared that the
    senate and all virtuous men were cruel at the time that I warded off ruin from the republic. You
    were a merciful man when you handed me over,—me, your own relation,—me, whom at your <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> you had appointed as chief guardian of the prerogative tribe,
    whose opinions on the calends of January you had asked then, bound and helpless to the enemies
    of the republic! You repelled my son-in-law, your own kinsman; you repelled your own near
    relation, my daughter, with most haughty and inhuman language, from your knees; and you, also, O
    man of singular mercy and clemency, when I, together with the republic, had fallen, not by a
    blow aimed by a tribune, but by a wound inflicted by a consul, behaved with such wickedness and
    such intemperance, that you did not allow one single hour to elapse between the time of my
    disaster and your plunder; you did not allow even time for the lamentations and groans of the
    city to die away. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> It was not yet openly known that the
    republic had fallen, when you thought fit to arrange its interment. At one and the same moment
    my house was plundered and set on fire, my property from my house on the Palatine Hill was taken
    to the house of the consul who was my neighbour, the goods from my Tusculan villa were also
    taken to the house of my neighbour there, the other consul; when, while the same mob of artisans
    were giving their votes, the same gladiator proposing and passing laws, the forum being
    unoccupied, not only by virtuous men, but even by free citizens, and being entirely empty, the
    Roman people being utterly ignorant what was going on, the senate being beaten down and crushed,
    there being two wicked and impious consuls, the treasury, the prisoners, the legions, allies and
    military commands, were given away as they pleased. <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But the ruin wrought by these consuls you, O consuls, have prevented from spreading further by
    your virtue, being assisted as you have been by the admirable loyalty and diligence of the
    tribunes of the people and the praetors. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> What shall I say of
    that most illustrious man, Titus Annius? <note anchored="true">This was Titus Annius Milo, by
     which last name he is best known to us. He was tribune, and finding it impossible to bring
     Clodius to justice in the legal way, resolved to deal with him according to his own fashion,
     and bought a troop of gladiators, at the head of whom he had daily skirmishes with him in the
     streets.</note> or, who can ever speak of such a citizen in an adequate or worthy manner? For
    when he saw that a wicked citizen, or, it would be more correct to say, a domestic enemy,
    required (if it were only possible to employ the laws) to be crushed by judicial proceedings, or
    that if violence hindered and put an end to the courts of justice, in that case audacity must be
    put down by virtue, madness by courage, rashness by wisdom, hand by hand, violence by violence,
    he first of all prosecuted him for violence; when he saw that the very man whom he was
    prosecuting had destroyed the courts of justice, he took care that he should not be able to
    carry everything by violence. He taught us that neither private houses, nor temples, nor the
    forum, nor the senate-house could be defended from the bands of domestic robbers without the
    greatest gallantry, and large resources and numerous forces. He was the first man after my
    departure who relieved the virtuous from fear, and deprived the audacious of hope; who delivered
    this august body from alarm, and the city from slavery. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p> And
    Publius Sextius following the same line of conduct with equal virtue, courage, and loyalty,
    thought that there were no enmities, no efforts of violence, no attacks, no dangers even to his
    life, which it became him to shun, in defence of my safety, of your authority, and of the
    constitution of the state. He, by his diligence, so recommended the cause of the senate, thrown
    into disorder as it was by the harangues of wicked men, to the multitude, that your name soon
    became the most popular of all names, your authority the object of the greatest affection to all
    men. He defended me by every means that a tribune of the people could employ; and supported me
    by every sort of kind attention, just as if he had been my own brother; by his clients, and
    freedmen, and household, and resources, and letters, I was so much supported, that he seemed to
    be not only my assistant under, but my partner in calamity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>
    Now <pb n="482"/> you have seen the kindness and zeal of the others; how devoted to me was Caius
    Cestilius, how attached to you, how uniformly faithful to our cause. What did Marcus Cispius do?
    I know how much I owe to him and to his father and brother; and they, though they had some
    personal grudge against me on their own private account, still disregarded their private dislike
    out of recollection of my services to the state. Also, Titus Fadius, who was my quaestor, and
    Marcus Curtius, to whose father I was quaestor, cherished the memory of our connection with all
    zeal, and affection, and courage. Caius Messius made many speeches in my behalf, for the sake
    both of our friendship and of the republic. And he at the beginning proposed a special law
    respecting my safety. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p> If Quintus Fabricius could only have
    effected, in spite of violence and arms, what he endeavoured to do in my behalf, we should have
    recovered our position in the month of January. His own inclination prompted him to labour for
    my safety, violence checked him, your authority recalled him. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Of what disposition towards me the praetors were, you were able to form an opinion when Lucius
    Caecilius, in his private character, laboured to support me from his own resources, and in his
    public capacity proposed a law respecting my safety, in concert with all his colleagues, and
    refused the plunderers of my property permission to support their actions by legal proceedings.
    But Marcus Calidius, the moment he was elected, showed by his vote how dear my safety was to
    him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p> Caius Septimius, Quintus Valerius, Publius Crassus,
    Sextus Quintilius, and Caius Cornutus, all devoted all their energies to the promotion of my
    interests and those of the republic. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>And while I gladly make mention of these things, I am not unwilling to pass over the wicked
    actions done by some people with a view to injure me. It is not suited to my fortunes at present
    to remember injuries, which, even if I were able to revenge them, I still would rather forget.
    All my life is to be devoted to a different object: to that of showing my gratitude to those who
    have deserved well of me; to preserving those friendships which have been tried in the fire; to
    waging war against my open enemies; to pardoning my timid friends; to avoiding the showing those
    who deserted me any indignation at having been forced to leave the city; to console those who
    promoted my return by a proper display of my dignity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> And if
    I had no other duty before me for all the rest of my life, except to appear sufficiently
    grateful to the very originators and prime movers and authors of my safety, still I should think
    the period that remains to me of life too brief; I will not say for requiting, but even for
    enumerating the kindnesses which have been shown to me. For, when shall I, or when will all my
    relations, be able to show proper gratitude to this man and to his children? What memory, what
    force of genius, what amount of deference and respect will be a fit return for such numerous and
    immense services? He was the first man who held out to me the promise and faith of a consul when
    I was overwhelmed and miserable; he it was who recalled me from death to life, from despair to
    hope, from destruction to safety. His affection for me, his zeal for the republic, was so great,
    that he kept thinking how he might not only relieve my calamity, but how he might even make it
    honourable. For what could be more honourable, what could happen to me more creditable, than
    that which you decreed on his motion, that all people from all Italy, who desired the safety of
    the republic, should come forward for the sole purpose of supporting and defending me, a ruined
    and almost broken-hearted man? So that the senate summoned the citizens and the whole of Italy
    to come from all their lands and from every town to the defence of one man, with the very same
    force of expression which had never been used but three times before since the foundation of
    Rome, and at those times it was the consul who used it in behalf of the entire republic,
    addressing himself to those only who could hear his voice. </p></div><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What could I leave to my posterity more glorious than the fact, that the senate had declared
    its judgment that any citizen who did not defend me, did not desire the safety of the republic?
    Therefore your authority, and the preeminent dignity of the consul, had this great effect, that
    every one thought that he was committing a shameful crime if he did not come to that summons.
    And this same consul, when that incredible multitude, when Italy itself I might almost say, had
    come to Rome, summoned you repeatedly to the Capitol; and at that time you had an opportunity of
    seeing what great power excellence of natural disposition and true nobleness have. For Quintus
    Metellus, himself an enemy of mine, and a brother of an enemy of mine, as soon as he was assured
    of your inclinations, laid aside his own private dislike to me <pb n="484"/> and allowed Publius
    Servilius, a most illustrious man, and also a most virtuous one, and a most intimate friend of
    my own, to recall him, by what I may call the divine influence of his authority and eloquence,
    to the exploits and virtues of his race and of their common family, so as to take to his
    counsels his brother, in the shades below, the companion of my fortunes, and all the Metelli,
    those most admirable citizens, summoning them as it were from Acheron; and among them the great
    conqueror of Numidia, whose departure from his country formerly seemed grievous to all the
    citizens, but scarcely even vexatious to himself. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p> He,
    therefore, turns out now, not only a defender of my safety, having been previously to this one
    kindness of his always my enemy, but even the seconder of my restoration to my dignity. And on
    that day when you met in the senate to the number of four hundred and seventeen, and when all
    these magistrates were present one alone dissented; he who thought that the conspirators could
    by his law be awakened from the shades below. And on that day when in most weighty and copious
    language you delivered your decision, that the republic had been preserved by my counsels, he as
    consul again took care that the same things should be said by the chief men of the state in the
    assembly the next day; and he then spoke on my behalf with the greatest eloquence, and brought
    the assembly into such a state, all Italy standing by and listening, that no one would listen to
    the hateful and detested voice of any of my hired or profligate enemies. </p></div><milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>To these acts of his, being not only aids to my safety, but even ornaments of my dignity, you
    yourselves added the rest that was wanting. You decreed that no one should by any means whatever
    hinder that matter from proceeding; that if any one did try to interpose any obstacle, you would
    be very angry and indignant; that he would be acting in a manner contrary to the interests of
    the republic, and the safety of good men, and the unanimous wish of the citizens; and that such
    a man was instantly to be reported to you. And you passed a vote that if they persisted in
    interposing obstacles, I was to return in spite of them. Why need I tell how thanks were given
    to all those who had come up from the municipal towns; or that they were entreated to be present
    with equal eagerness on that day when the whole affair was consummated? Lastly, why need I tell
    what you did on that day which Publius Lentulus has made as a birthday to me, and to my brother,
    and to our children, to be recollected not only by us, who are now alive, but by all our race
    for ever? On which day, in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia centuriata</foreign>, which our
    ancestors rightly called and considered the real <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>, he
    summoned us back to our country, so that the same centuries which had made me consul should
    declare their approval of my consulship. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p> On that day what
    citizen was there who thought it right, whatever his age or state of health might be, to deny
    himself the opportunity of giving his vote for my safety? When did you ever see such a multitude
    assembled in the Campus, such a splendid show of all Italy and of all orders of men? when did
    you ever see movers, and tellers, and keepers of the votes all of such high rank? Therefore,
    through the active, and admirable, and godlike kindness of Publius Lentulus, we were not allowed
    to return to our country, as some most eminent citizens have been, but we were brought back in
    triumph, borne by white horses in a gilded car. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Can I ever appear grateful enough to Cnaeus Pompeius, who said, not only among you who all
    were of the same opinion, but also before the whole Roman people, that the safety of the
    republic had been preserved by me, and was inseparably connected with mine? who recommended my
    cause to the wise, and taught the ignorant, and at the same time checked the wicked by his
    authority, and encouraged the good; who not only exhorted the Roman people to espouse my cause,
    but even entreated them to do so, as if he were speaking for a brother or a parent; who, at a
    time when he was forced to keep within his house from fear of contests and bloodshed, begged
    even of the preceding tribunes to propose and carry a law respecting my safety; who in a colony
    lately erected, where he himself was discharging the duties of a magistrate in it, where there
    was no bribed interrupter, declared that the <foreign xml:lang="lat">privilegium</foreign>
    <note anchored="true">“A <foreign xml:lang="lat">Privilegium</foreign> signified an enactment
     that had for its object a single person, which is indicated by the form of the word <foreign xml:lang="lat">privae res</foreign>, being the same as <foreign xml:lang="lat">singulae
      res</foreign>. It might be beneficial to the party to whom it referred, or not; but it is
     generally used by Cicero in the unfavourable sense.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 500, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Lex</foreign>. “In the time of the republic it was not allowed to pass or to
     propose such a law.”—Riddle, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Privilegium</foreign>. But I do not know
     his authority for such a statement.</note> passed against me was violent and cruel, confirming
    that declaration by the authority of most <pb n="486"/> honourable men, and by public letters,
    and, being the chief man there, gave his opinion that it was becoming to implore the protection
    of all Italy for my safety; who, when he himself had always been a most firm friend to me,
    laboured also to make all his own friends also to me. </p></div><milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And by what services can I requite the kindness of Titus Annius to me? all whose actions, the
    whole of whose conduct and thoughts, the whole of whose tribuneship, in short, was nothing else
    except a consistent, continual, gallant, unwearied advocacy of my safety. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Why need I speak of Publius Sextius? who showed his good-will and faithful attachment to me,
    not only by his grief of mind, but even by the wounds which he received on his person. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>But to you, O conscript fathers, and to each individual of you, I have both declared, and I
    will continue to declare my gratitude. I declared it at the beginning to your whole body, as
    well as I could; to declare it with sufficient eloquence is what I am totally unable to do. And
    although I have received special favours from many persons, about which it is impossible for me
    to keep silence, still it is impossible at the present time, and with the apprehensions which I
    feel, to endeavour to enumerate the kindnesses which I have received from individuals. For it is
    difficult to avoid passing over some, and yet it would be impious to forget any one. I, O
    conscript fathers, ought to reverence every one of you as I do the immortal gods. But as, even
    in the case of the immortal gods themselves, we are wont not always to pay worship and to offer
    prayers to the same deities, but sometimes we pray to one and sometimes to another; so in the
    case of the men who have behaved to me with such godlike service, my whole life shall be devoted
    to celebrating their kindness towards me, and showing my reverent sense of it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p> But on this day I have thought that it became me to return thanks especially
    to the different magistrates by name, and also to one private individual, who for the sake of my
    safety, had visited all the municipal towns and colonies, had as a suppliant addressed his
    entreaties to the Roman people, and had declared that opinion which you followed when you
    restored me to my dignities. You always distinguished me when I was prosperous; when I was in
    distress you defended me to the extent of your power, by the change of your garments, and your
    general mourning, There have been times within our own recollection when senators did not dare
    to change their robes even in their own personal dangers; but in my danger the whole senate
    changed its garments as far as it was allowed to do without interruption from the edicts of
    those men who wished to deprive me in my peril not only of all protection from them, but of even
    the benefit of your prayers in my behalf. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And when I was in such circumstances as these, when I saw that I as a private individual had
    to contend with the same array which as consul I had defeated, using not arms but your
    authority, I deliberated much with myself. <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The consul had said that he would make the Roman knights pay for the scenes on the Capitoline
    Hill. Some were summoned by name, others were prosecuted, some were banished. All access to the
    temples was prevented, not merely by their being garrisoned or occupied with a strong force, but
    by their being demolished. The other consul, not content with only abandoning me and the
    republic, unless he could also betray us to the enemies of the republic, had bound those enemies
    to him by promising them the rewards which they coveted. There was another man at the gates with
    a command <note anchored="true">He means Julius Caesar, who had the command in Gaul as proconsul
     for five years.</note> given to him for many years, and with a large army. I do not say that he
    was an enemy of mine, but I do know that he did nothing when he was stated to be my enemy.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p> As there were thought to be two parties in the republic, the
    one was supposed, out of its enmity to me, to demand that I should be given up to it; the other,
    to defend me, but timidly out of fear of bloodshed. But those who seemed to require me to be
    given up to them increased the fear of a contest by their conduct as they never diminished the
    suspicions and anxieties of men by denying what they were suspected of. Wherefore, when I saw
    the senate deprived of leaders, and myself attacked by some of the magistrates, betrayed by
    some, and abandoned by others; when I saw that slaves were being enlisted by name under some
    pretence of forming guilds; <note anchored="true">“Clodius not only restored the old <foreign xml:lang="lat">collegia</foreign> or guilds, but formed some new ones of the very dregs of the
     city, and of the slaves; and this is alluded to in several of the subsequent
     orations.”—Manut.</note> that all the troops of Catiline were recalled to their original hopes
    of massacre and conflagration under <pb n="488"/> almost the same leaders as before; that the
    Roman knights were under the same fear of proscription as before; that the municipal towns were
    in dread of being pillaged, and every one in fear of his life; I might—I might, I say, O
    conscript fathers, still have been able to defend myself by force of arms, and many wise and
    brave men advised me to do so; nor was I wanting in the same courage which I had shown before,
    and which was not unknown to you. But I saw that if I defeated my present enemy, I had still too
    many others behind who must also be defeated; that if I were beaten myself; many virtuous men
    would fall for my sake, and with me, and even after me; and that the avengers of the blood of
    the tribunes were present, but that all satisfaction for my death must he exacted by the slow
    progress of the law, and reserved for posterity. </p></div><milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I did not choose, after I had as consul maintained the general safety of the state without
    having recourse to arms, to take arms as a private individual in my own cause; I preferred that
    virtuous men should grieve for my fortune rather than despair of their own; and if I were slain
    by myself; that I thought would be a shameful end for me; but if I were slain with many others,
    that I thought would be fatal to the republic. If I had supposed that eternal misery was before
    me, I would rather have endured death than everlasting agony. But I felt sure that I should not
    be absent from this city any longer than the constitution itself was, and, while that was
    banished, I thought it no longer desirable for myself that I should remain in it; and in
    accordance with my expectation, as soon as ever the constitution was restored, it brought me
    back in triumph as its companion. The laws were all banished as well as I, the courts of justice
    were banished as well as I; the prerogatives of the magistrates, the authority of the senate,
    the liberty of the citizens, even the fruitfulness of the land, all piety and all religion,
    whether it was with respect to men or gods, were all banished from the state when I was
    banished. And if they had been lost to you for ever, I should mourn over your fortunes rather
    than regret the loss of my home amongst you; but if they were ever restored, I was quite sure
    that I should be enabled to return with them. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And of these feelings of mine, he who was the protector of my life is also my most
    indisputable witness, namely Cnaeus Plancius, who, disregarding all the distinctions and
    emoluments which might have been derived from a province, devoted his whole quaestorship to
    supporting and preserving me. If he had been my quaestor when I was commander-in-chief; he would
    have stood in the relation of a son to me; now he surely shall be looked upon by me as a parent,
    since he has been my quaestor, not while in authority, but in grief. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, O conscript fathers, since I have been restored to the republic at the same time
    with the constitution of the republic, in whatever I do for the defence of it, I will not only
    not in the slightest degree abridge my former liberty, but I will even increase it. <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>In truth, if I defended the republic at a time when it was under some obligations to me, what
    ought I to do now when I owe everything to it? For what is there that can crush or even weaken
    my spirit, when you see that calamity itself is in my case not a witness of any error; but of
    most extraordinary services rendered to the republic? For these disasters were brought on me by
    my defence of the state; they were undergone by me of my own free will, in order that the
    republic which had been defended by me should not be brought into the very extremity of peril.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p> It was not in my case, as in that of Publius Popillius, a
    most noble man, my young sons, or a multitude of my relations that entreated the Roman people in
    my behalf; it was not in my case, as in the case of Quintus Metellus, a most admirable and most
    illustrious man, a youthful son of proved virtue who strove for me; it was not Lucius and Caius
    Metellus, men of consular rank, nor their sons; nor Quintus Metellus Nepos, who was at that very
    moment a candidate for the consulship, nor the Luculli or Servilii, or Scipios, sons of the
    Metelli, who with tears and in mourning garments addressed their supplications to the Roman
    people; but one single brother, who behaved to me with the dutiful affection of a son, who
    fortified me like a parent with his counsels, and loved me like a brother (as indeed he was), by
    his mourning robe and his tears and daily prayers kept alive the regret of me which existed, and
    the recollection of my name and services; and while he had made up his mind, that unless by your
    votes he could recover me here, he would encounter the same fortune himself, and choose the same
    abode both in life and death, still he never was alarmed either at the greatness of the
    business, or at his own <pb n="490"/> solitary and unassisted condition, nor at the violence and
    warlike measures of my adversaries. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>There was another upholder and assiduous defender of my fortunes, Caius Piso, my son-in-law, a
    man of the greatest virtue and piety, who disregarded the threats of my enemies, the hostility
    of my connection, and his own near relation, the consul; who, as quaestor, passed over Pontus
    and Bithynia for the sake of ensuring my safety. The senate never decreed anything respecting
    Publius Popillius; no mention was ever made in this assembly of Quintus Metellus. They were
    restored by motions made by the tribunes, after their enemies had been slain, and, above all,
    they were not restored by the interposition of any authority on the part of the senate, though
    one of them had done what he did in obedience to the senate, the other had fled from violence
    and bloodshed. For Caius Marius, the only man of consular dignity in the memory of man who was
    ever driven from the city in times of civil discord before me, was not only not restored by the
    senate, but by his return almost destroyed the senate. There was no unanimity of magistrates in
    their cases,—no summoning of the Roman people to come to the defence of the republic,—no
    commotion throughout Italy,—no decrees of municipalities and colonies in their favour.
    </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, since your authority has summoned me,—since the Roman people his recalled me,—since
    the republic has begged me to return,—since almost all Italy has brought me back in triumph on
    its shoulders, I will take care, O conscript fathers, now that those things have been restored
    to me, the restoration of which did not depend on myself, not to appear wanting in those
    qualities with which I can provide myself; I will take care, now that I have recovered those
    things which I had lost, never to lose my virtue and loyal attachment to you.</p></div>
  </div>
 </body></text>

</TEI>
