<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>In Defense of Lucius Flaccus</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--<encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>-->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-05-20" who="Lisa Cerrato">Review of EpiDoc and CTS work. Minor edits.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-16" who="Zach Himes">Changed section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi017.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
   <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF LUCIUS FLACCUS.</head>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>Lucius Valerius Flaccus had been praetor in Cicero's consulship, and had received the thanks
    of the senate for his zeal and vigour in the arrest of Catiline's accomplices; but he was now
    accused by Publius Lucius of rapine and oppression in the province of Asia, which had fallen to
    his lot after his praetorship. Part of the charge was on the ground that he had prohibited the
    Jews from carrying out of his province the gold which they used to collect annually throughout
    the empire for the temple at Jerusalem, and that he had seized it all, and remitted it to Rome.
    Hortensius was joined with Cicero in the defence; as is mentioned by Cicero in the last epistle
    of the second book of the Letters to Atticus; where he says, “With how much copiousness, with
    how much nobleness, with how much elegance, did your friend Hortensius <note anchored="true">But some editions read here <foreign xml:lang="la">Hortalus</foreign>.</note> extol me to the
    skies, both when he was speaking of the praetorship of Flaccus, and of the times of the
    Allobroges.” </p>
   <p>We may observe, since there has been some dispute as to the order in which this oration
    should be printed, that it cannot have been spoken before the year 695, A. U. C., in the
    consulship of Caius Julius Caesar and Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus, for Cicero's consulship took
    place A. U. C. 691, and after that Flaccus was occupied as propraetor for three years in Asia,
    and it could not have been before the expiration of his praetorship, and his return from it,
    that this prosecution was instituted. Flaccus was acquitted. </p>
   <p>This oration is imperfect and mutilated in some places.</p></div>
   
  
  
   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>When in the greatest perils of this city and empire, in the most important and terrible
    disasters of the republic, I was repelling slaughter from you, your wives, and your children,
    devastation from your temples, your altars, from the city and from Italy, with Lucius Flaccus,
    the companion and assistant of my counsels and my dangers, I used to hope, O judges, that I
    should some time or other be an assistant of Lucius Flaccus towards obtaining honour, rather
    than an advocate to defend him from calamity. For what reward of dignity could there be which
    the Roman people would deny to him, when it had always given them to his ancestors; when Lucius
    Flaccus had imitated the ancient glory of the Valerian family in delivering his country, nearly
    five hundred years after the existence of the republic? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>But if by chance there had existed at any time any detractor from this service, any enemy of
    this virtue, and envier of this renown, still I thought that Lucius Flaccus would have to
    encounter the judgment of an ignorant mob, (with no real danger, indeed,) rather than that of
    most wise and carefully chosen men. I never, indeed, imagined that any one would bring danger
    upon, or devise plots against, his fortunes, by means of those very men, by whose influence, and
    under whose protection, the safety, not only of all the citizens, but even of all nations, was
    at that time defended and preserved. And if it was fated ever to happen that any one should
    devise mischief to Lucius Flaccus, still I never thought, O judges, that Decimus Laelius, the
    son of a most virtuous man, himself a man of the fairest expectations and of the highest
    dignity, would adopt an accusation which is more suitable to the hatred and madness of wicked
    citizens than to his virtue and to the training of his early years. Indeed, as I had often seen
    well-founded enmities with citizens who had deserved well of their country, laid aside by the
    most illustrious men, I did not think that any friend of the republic, after the affection of
    Lucius Flaccus had been thoroughly tried, would take up a fresh quarrel against him without
    having received any injury.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But since, O judges, many things have deceived us, both in our
    own affairs and in those of the republic, those things which must be borne, we bear. This only
    we ask of you,—that you will consider that the whole strength of the republic,—the whole
    constitution of the state,—all the memory of past, and the safety of present and the hope of
    future time, hangs and depends upon your power, upon your votes, upon this single trial. If ever
    the republic has had need to <pb n="426"/> implore the wisdom, the gravity, the prudence and the
    foresight of her judges, she implores it now,—she implores it, I say, at this present time.
     <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You are not now about to decide on the constitution of Lydians, or Mysians, or Phrygians, who,
    under the influence of some compulsion or excitement have come before you; but on your own
    republic,—on the constitution of your own state,—on the common safety,—on the hope of all good
    men, if there is any such still remaining to support the minds and thoughts of brave citizens.
    Every other refuge of good men,—every other protection of innocent men,—every bulwark of the
    republic, wisdom, assistance, and laws, has failed. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> For whom
    else can I appeal to? whom can I cite? whom can I entreat? The senate? Nay; the senate itself
    implores assistance from you, and feels that the confirmation of its authority is submitted to
    your decision. The Roman knights? You yourselves, the fifty chief men of that body, will declare
    how far your sentiments are in unison with those of the rest. Shall I appeal to the Roman
    people? That body has delivered over to you all its power over us in our case. Wherefore, unless
    we can maintain in this place, and before you, and by your means, O judges, I will not say our
    authority, for that is lost but our safety, which hangs on a slender hope, and that hope our
    last, we have no place of refuge beyond to which we can betake ourselves. Unless perchance, O
    judges, you fail to see, as yet, what is the real object of this proceeding, what is really at
    stake, and what is the cause, the foundations of which are being now laid. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> The man has been condemned who slew Catiline when he was bearing his hostile
    standards against his country. What reason is there why he who drove Catiline from the city
    should be exempt from fear? That man is demanded for punishment who discovered the proofs of the
    common destruction of all which was then being planned. Why should he feel safe who took care to
    produce and divulge those proofs? The partners of his counsels, his ministers and comrades are
    harassed. What are the leaders, and chiefs, and principal men of his party to expect? We should
    then see whether at that time all good men were my guides or my companions in preserving the
    common safety of <gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="frBob1"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>He preferred saying they were strangled. <note anchored="true">These fragments are from a
     Vatican MS. first inserted in the text by Nobbe.</note>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="frBob2"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What did my friend Caetra wish? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="frBob3"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And what did Decianus? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="frBob4"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And I wish that my enemies, and those of all good men, would rather attack me; I wish it
    really was mine. The senate to a great extent <gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="frBob5"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>O ye immortal gods! that Lentulus <gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="frMed"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/> [What <note anchored="true">This passage is an addition of Beier from a Milan MS. inserted in
     the same way by Orellius.</note> was the use of bringing forward foreign evidence,] when his
    domestic life and his natural disposition was notorious? Therefore, I will not, O Decimus
    Laelius, allow you to assume this law and this condition as applicable to yourself and to the
    rest for the future, and to us at present; [so as to lay down a rule that we are to accommodate
    our defences to the will of the prosecutors, and not come to those assertions to which our cause
    of itself leads us.] 
   <milestone unit="para"/>When you have branded his youth, when you have stigmatized the rest of his life with stains of
    infamy, when you have brought forward the ruin of his private affairs and his disgrace in the
    city, and his vices and crimes in Spain and Gaul and Cilicia, and Crete, in which provinces he
    lived in no great obscurity, then we shall hear what the people of Tmolus and the Lorymeni think
    of Lucius Flaccus. But the man whom so many and such influential provinces wish to be
    saved,—whom many citizens from all parts of Italy defended, being bound to him by intimate
    connection and old friendship,—whom this the common country of us all holds fast in her embrace,
    on account of her fresh recollection of his great services,—him, even if all Asia demands him
    for punishment, I will defend,—his enemies I will resist. What if it is not all Asia that
    demands him, nor the best part of it nor even any part without bribery, nor of its own accord,
    nor rightly, nor in a manner according to custom, nor with truth, nor with any conscientious
    regard to justice or honesty? If it duly demands him because it has been persuaded, and tampered
    with, and excited, and compelled to do so,—if it has backed this prosecution with its name
    impiously, and rashly, and covetously, and with great inconsistency, speaking only by the mouth
    of the most needy witnesses, and if the province itself has no grounds to complain with truth of
    any injuries done by him; still, O judges, will these statements, <pb n="428"/> heard with
    reference to a very brief epoch diminish the credit due to actions which we really know,
    extending over a long period of time?
   <milestone unit="para"/>I, therefore, as his defender, will preserve this order which his enemy avoids; and I will
    pursue and follow up the prosecutor, and of my own accord I will demand the accusation from our
    adversary. What is it, O Laelius? Have you at any time been able to stigmatize the youth of
    Lucius Flaccus, who has passed his time, not in the shade, nor in the common pursuits and
    training of those his age? In truth, even as a boy he went with his father, the consul, to the
    wars; and yet, even as to this very fact you accused him of something because [something <note anchored="true">This passage is an addition of Beier from a Milan MS. inserted in the same way
     by Orellius.</note> appeared able to be said so as to excite suspicion.] </p></div>
    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>With what charges, then, O Laelius, do you attack my client being such a man as he is? He was
    in Cilicia a military tribune when Publius Servilius was the general; not a word is said about
    that. He was quaestor to Marcus Piso in Spain; not a word has been uttered about his
    quaestorship. He was present at the greater part of the Cretan war, and went through all its
    hardships in the company of that consummate general. The accusation is dumb with regard to this
    period. His discharge of his duties as judge during his praetorship,—a business of great
    intricacy, and affording numberless causes for suspicion and enmities, is not touched. Nay more,
    though it fell in a most critical and perilous time of the republic, it is praised even by his
    enemies. “Oh, but damaging evidence has been given against him.” Before I say by whom it was
    given, by what hopes, by what violence, by what means the witnesses were urged on, and what
    insignificant, needy, treacherous, audacious men they were, I will speak of their whole class,
    and of the condition in which all of us are placed. In the name of the immortal gods, O judges,
    will you ask of unknown witnesses in what way the man decided trials in Asia, who the year
    before had sat as judge at Rome? And will you yourselves form no conjectures on the subject? In
    a jurisdiction so various, many decrees were issued,—many desires of influential men were set at
    nought; and yet, what words, (I will not say of suspicion, for that is often false, but) of
    anger or indignation were ever once uttered against him?</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>And is that man to be put on his trial
    for covetousness, who, when employed on a business affording numerous opportunities for such
    conduct, shunned all base gain,—who, in a city much given to evil speaking, and in an office
    surrounded with suspicion avoided, not only all accusation, but even a single hard name? I pass
    over points which I ought not to pass over that in his private affairs no covetous action, no
    eagerness about money matters, no sordid conduct in the management of his estate can be alleged
    against him. By what witnesses, then, can I refute these men except by you? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> Shall that villager from near Tmolus,—a man not only a stranger to us, but not
    even known among his own neighbours,—teach you what sort of a man Lucius Flaccus is, whom you
    yourselves have known to be most modest as a youth, whom our most extensive provinces have found
    to be a most conscientious man and whom our armies know by experience to be a thoroughly brave
    soldier and vigilant general, and of a lieutenant and quaestor most moderate; whom you
    yourselves, being witnesses on the spot of his conduct, have judged to be a thoroughly wise and
    consistent senator, a most upright praetor, and a citizen wholly devoted to the republic.
     </p></div><milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Will you then listen to others as witnesses on those points, respecting which you yourselves
    ought rather to bear witness to others? And what witnesses are they? In the first place, I will
    say that they are Greeks, (that is the case of them all.) Not that I, for my own part, would be
    more inclined than others to refuse credit to that nation; for if ever there was any one of our
    countrymen not averse to that race of men, and proving himself so by zeal and good-will, I think
    that I am that man, and that I was so even more when I had more leisure; but there are in that
    body many virtuous, many learned, many modest men, and they have not been brought hither to this
    trial. There are also many impudent, illiterate, worthless persons, and those I see here,
    impelled by various motives. But I say this of the whole race of Greeks; I allow them learning,
    I allow them a knowledge of many arts; I do not deny them wit in conversation, acuteness of
    talents, and fluency in speaking; even if they claim praise for other sorts of ability, I will
    not make any objection; but a scrupulous regard to truth in giving their evidence is not a
    virtue that that nation has ever cultivated; they are utterly ignorant what is the meaning of
    that quality, they know nothing of its authority or of its weight. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> Where does that <pb n="430"/> expression, “Give evidence for me, and I will
    give evidence for you,” come from? is it supposed to be a phrase of the Gauls, or of the
    Spaniards? It belongs wholly to the Greeks; so that even those who do not understand Greek know
    what form of expression is used by the Greeks for this. Therefore, when they give their
    evidence, remark with what a countenance, with what confidence they give it; and then you will
    become aware how scrupulous they are as to what evidence they give. They never reply precisely
    to a question. They always answer an accuser more than he asks them. They never feel any anxiety
    to make what they say seem probable to any one; but are solicitous only how to get out what they
    have got to say. Marcus Lurco gave evidence against Flaccus, being angry (as he said himself)
    because his freedman had been condemned by a decision of his involving infamy. He said nothing
    which could injure him, though he was eager to do so; for his conscientious regard to his oath
    prevented him. And yet with what modesty, with what trembling
    and paleness did he say what he did! </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> How ready to give evidence was Publius Septimius; how angry
    was he about some former trial, and about his steward: yet he hesitated; yet his scrupulousness
    was at times at variance with his anger. Marcus Caelius was an enemy to Flaccus, because, as
    Flaccus had thought it wrong for one publican to decide on the case of another publican, though
    the case was ever so evident he had been removed from the list of judges. And yet he restrained
    himself; and brought nothing into the court which could injure Flaccus except his own
    inclination to do so. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>If these men had been Greeks, and if our habits and principles had not had more influence than
    indignation and hostility, they all would have said that they had been plundered, and harassed,
    and stripped of their fortunes. When a Greek witness comes forward with a desire to injure a
    man, he does not think of the words of his oath, but of what he can say to injure him. He thinks
    it a most shameful thing to be defeated, to be detected, to allow his enemy's innocence to be
    proved. That is the contest for which he prepares himself; he cares for nothing beyond.
    Therefore, it is not the best men, nor the wisest, but the most impudent and talkative men who
    are selected as witnesses. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> But you, even in private trials
    about the most trifling matters, carefully weigh the character of a witness; even if you know
    the person of the man, and his name and his tribe, still you think it right to inquire into his
    habits. And when a man of our citizens gives his evidence, how carefully does he restrain
    himself, how scrupulously does he regulate all his expressions, how fearful is he, and anxious
    not to say anything covetously or angrily,— not to say one word more or less than necessary! Do
    you think that those Greeks are so too? men to whom an oath is a joke, evidence a plaything,
    your opinion of them a shadow, men who place all their credit and profit and reputation, and
    triumph telling the most impudent lies. But I will not spin out what I have got to say. Indeed,
    my speech would be interminable if I were to take it into my head to unfold the faithlessness of
    the whole nation in giving evidence. But I will come nearer home; I will speak of these
    witnesses whom you have brought forward. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>We have got a most zealous prosecutor, O judges, and an enemy in every respect violent and
    furious against us. I trust that he may be of great use to his friends and to the republic; but
    at all events, he has undertaken this case and this prosecution, as if he were impelled by some
    most extraordinary eagerness. What a company attended him while pursuing his investigations!
    company, do I say? rather, what an army! what profusion! what expense! what prodigality was
    there! And though these statements are of service to my case, still I do not make them without
    apprehension lest Laelius should think that I am seeking by my oration to make him talked about,
    or to excite odium against him, in a business which he has undertaken for the sole object of
    acquiring credit. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, I will pass over all this part of the subject. I will only beg of you, O judges, if
    you have heard anything yourselves by common report and in ordinary conversation about force,
    and violence, and arms, and troops, to recollect it and to remember, because of the unpopularity
    of such conduct, that by this recent law, a certain number of companions has been fixed as the
    greatest number that ought to attend a man while prosecuting such an inquiry. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> However, to say nothing of violence, what conduct is this? which, since it was
    adopted according to the privileges and customs of prosecutors we cannot impeach, but still we
    are compelled to complain if it. I mean, first of all, the making a statement which has been
    bruited abroad over all Asia, (different people having had regular districts assigned to them,
    in which they were to <pb n="432"/> spread the report,) that Cnaeus Pompeius, because he is a
    most zealous enemy to Lucius Flaccus, had begged of Decimus Laelius, his father's and his own
    most intimate friend, to prosecute him on this charge, and that he placed at his disposal for
    the furtherance of this business, all his own authority, and influence, and resources, and
    riches. And this appeared all the more probable to the Greeks, because a little before they had
    seen Laelius in the same province with Flaccus, and on terms of great intimacy with him. And as
    the authority of Pompeius is great with every one, as indeed it ought to be, so especially is it
    predominant in that province which he has lately delivered from the war which pirates and kings
    were waging against it. He did this besides: those who did not wish to leave their homes he
    terrified with a summons to give their evidence; those who could not remain at home, he provided
    with a large and liberal sum for travelling expenses. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> And
    thus this young man, full of ability, worked on the wealthy by fear, on the poor by bribes, on
    the stupid by leading them into mistakes; and by these means he extorted those beautiful decrees
    which have been read to you,—decrees which were not passed by any formal vote or regular
    authority, nor under the sanction of an oath, but carried by holding up the hand, and by the
    loud shouts of an excited multitude. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>O for the admirable customs and principles which we received from our ancestors, if we could
    but keep them! but somehow or other they have slipped through our fingers. For our ancestors,
    those wise and upright men, would not permit the public assembly to have any authority to make
    laws; they chose that whatever the common people decided, or whatever the burgesses wished to
    enact should be ordered or forbidden, after the assembly was adjourned, and after all the parts
    had been properly arranged, by the different ranks, classes, and ages, distributed in their
    tribes and centuries, after having listened to the advocates of the proposal on which the vote
    was to be taken, and after the proposal itself had been for many days before the people, and had
    had its merits inquired into. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> But all the republics of the
    Greeks are governed by the rashness of the assembly while sitting. Therefore, to say no more of
    this Greece, which has long since been overthrown and crushed through the folly of its own
    counsels; that ancient country, which once flourished with riches, and rower, and glory, fell
    owing to that one evil, the immoderate liberty and licentiousness of the popular assemblies.
    When inexperienced men, ignorant and uninstructed in any description of business whatever, took
    their seats in the theatre, then they undertook inexpedient wars; then they appointed seditious
    men to the government of the republic; then they banished from the city the citizens who had
    deserved best of the state. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p> But if these things were
    constantly taking place at Athens, when that was the first city, not only in Greece, but in
    almost all the world, what moderation do you suppose there was in the assemblies in Phrygia and
    Mysia? It is usually men of those nations who throw our own assemblies into confusion; what do
    you suppose is the case when they are by themselves? Athenagoras, that celebrated man of Cyme,
    was beaten with rods, because, at a time of famine, he had ventured to export corn. An assembly
    was summoned at the request of Laelius. Athenagoras came forward, and, being a Greek among
    Greeks, he said a good deal, not about his fault, but in the way of complaining of his
    punishment. They voted by holding up their hands. A decree was passed. Is this evidence? The men
    of Pergamus, having been lately feasted, having been a little while before glutted with every
    sort of present,—I mean, all the cobblers and girdle-makers in Pergamus,—cried out whatever
    Mithridates (who governed that multitude, not by his authority, but by fattening them up) chose.
    Is this the testimony of that city? I brought witnesses from Sicily in pursuance of the public
    resolution of the island. But the evidence that I brought was the evidence not of an excited
    assembly, but of a senate on its oath. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> So that I am not now
    arguing against the reception of evidence; but you are to decide whether these statements are to
    be considered evidence. <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>A virtuous young man, born in an honourable rank, and eloquent, comes with a most numerous and
    splendidly appointed train into a town of the Greeks. He demands an assembly. He frightens
    wealthy men and men of authority from opposing him by summoning them to give evidence; he tempts
    the needy and worthless by the hope of being employed on the commission, and by a public grant
    for the expenses of their journey, and also by his own private liberality. What trouble is it to
    excite artisans, and shopkeepers, and all such dregs of a city, against any man, and especially
    against one who has lately had the supreme authority there, and could not possibly be very
    popular, on account of the odium attached to the very name of supreme power? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> And is it strange that those men who abominate the sight of our faces, who
    detest our name, who hate our tax on pastures, and our tenths, and our harbour dues, more than
    death itself, should gladly seize on every opportunity of injuring us that presents itself?
    Remember, therefore, that when you hear decrees you are not hearing evidence; that you are
    listening to the rashness of the common people; that you are listening to the assertions of all
    the most worthless men; that you are listening to the murmurs of the ignorant, to the voice of
    an inflamed assembly of a most worthless nation. Therefore examine closely into the nature and
    motive of all their accusations, and you will find no reason for them except the hopes by which
    they have been led on, or the terrors and threats by which they have been driven <gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div><milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The cities have nothing in the treasury, nothing in their revenues. There are two ways of
    raising money,—by tribute, or by loan. No lists of creditors are brought forward; no exaction of
    tribute is accounted for. But I pray you to remark how cheerfully they are in the habit of
    producing false accounts, and of entering in their accounts whatever suits them, forming your
    opinions by the letters of Cnaeus Pompeius to Hypsaeus, and of Hypsaeus to Pompeius. [The
    letters of Pompeius and of Hypsaeus are read.] Do not we appear to prove to you clearly enough,
    by the authority of these men, the profligate habits and impudent licentiousness of the Greeks?
    Unless, perchance, we suppose that those men who deceived Cnaeus Pompeius, and that too, when he
    was on the spot and when there was no one tempting them to do so, were likely now to be either
    timid or scrupulous, when Laelius urged them to bear witness against Lucius Flaccus in his
    absence. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p> But even suppose those documents were not tampered
    with in their own city, still what authority or what credit can they now have here? The law
    orders them to be brought to the praetor within three days, and to be sealed up with the seals
    of the judges; they are scarcely brought within thirty days. In order that the writings may not
    be easily tampered with, therefore the law orders that after they have been sealed up they shall
    be kept in a public office; but these are sealed up after they have been tampered with. What
    difference, then, does it make, whether they are brought to the judges so long after the proper
    time, or whether they are not brought at all? <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What shall we say if the zeal of the witnesses is in partnership, as it were, with the
    prosecutor? shall they still be considered witnesses? What then, is become of that expectation
    which ought to have a place in courts of justice? For formerly, when a prosecutor had said
    anything with bitterness and vehemence, and when the counsel for the defence had made a
    supplicatory and submissive reply, the third step expected was the appearance of the witnesses
    who either spoke without any partisanship at all, or else they in some degree concealed their
    desires. But what is the case here? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p> They are sitting with the
    prosecutor; they rise up from the prosecutor's bench; they use no concealment; they feel no
    apprehension. Do I complain of where they sit? They come with him from his house, if they trip
    at one word, they will have no place to return to. Can any one be a witness, when the prosecutor
    can examine him without any anxiety and have not the slightest fear of his giving him any answer
    which he is unwilling to hear? Where, then, is the oratorical skill, which formerly used to be
    looked for either in the prosecutor or in the counsel for the defence? “He examined the witness
    cleverly; he came up to him cunningly; he scolded him; he led him where he pleased; he convicted
    him and made him dumb.” </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p> Why need you ask a man questions,
    Laelius, who, even before you have pronounced the words “I ask you,” will pour out more
    assertions than you enjoined him before you left home? And why should I, the counsel for the
    defence, ask him questions, since the course to be taken with respect to witnesses is either to
    invalidate their testimony or to impeach their characters? But by what discussion can I refute
    the evidence of men who say “We gave,” and no more? Am I then to make a speech against the man,
    when my speech can find no room for argument? What can I say against an utter stranger? I must
    then be content with complaining and lamenting, as I have been some time doing, the general
    iniquity of the whole prosecution, and, in the first place, the whole class of witnesses; for
    that nation is the witness which is the least scrupulous of all in giving evidence. I come
    nearer;—I say that that is not evidence which you yourself call decrees; but that it is only the
    grumbling of needy men, and a sort of random movement of a miserable Greek <pb n="436"/>
    assembly. I will come in still further,—he who has done it is not present; he who is said to
    have paid the money is not brought hither; no private letters are produced; the public documents
    have been retained in the power of the prosecutors. The main point of my argument concerns the
    witnesses. These men are living with our enemies, they come into court with our adversaries,
    they are dwelling in the same house with our prosecutors. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> Do
    you think that this is an examination and an inquiry into the truth, or an endeavour to fix a
    stain, and bring ruin upon innocence? for there are many things of such a sort, O judges, that
    even if they deserve to be neglected, as far as the individual whom they more immediately affect
    is concerned, are still to be dreaded, because of the state of facts of which they betoken the
    existence, and because of the precedents which they afford. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>If I were defending a man of the lowest rank, of no splendour of reputation, and recommended
    by no innocence of character, still, relying on the rights of common humanity and mercy, I
    should beg from citizens, on behalf of another citizen, that you would not give up your
    fellow-citizen and your suppliant to witnesses who are strangers to you; who are urged on to
    give their evidence; who are the companions, and messmates, and comrades of the prosecutor; to
    men who from their fickleness are Greeks, but who, as far as cruelty goes, are barbarians: I
    should entreat you not to leave posterity so dangerous a precedent for their imitation.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> But when the interests of Lucius Flaccus are at stake, a man
    of whom I may say that the first man who was made consul of his family <note anchored="true">This is not quite true, for Cicero is referring to Publius Valerius, surnamed Publicola, and
     he was not the first consul; but was elected as a substitute for Collatinus, who, with Brutus,
     was the first consul.</note> was the first man that was ever consul in this city; a man by
    whose valour the kings were banished, and liberty was established in this republic; a family
    which has endured to this time with a continued series of honours and commands, and of glorious
    achievements; and when Lucius Flaccus has not only not degenerated from this everlasting and
    well-attested virtue of his ancestors, but as praetor has especially devoted himself to the
    glory of asserting the liberty of his country, seeing that that was the especial glory and
    characteristic of his family,—can I fear lest any mischievous precedent be established in the
    case of this defendant when, even if he had committed any slight fault, all good men would think
    that they ought rather to connive at it? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p> That, however, I not
    only do not request, but I beg and entreat you, O judges, to scrutinise the whole case most
    vigilantly, with all your eyes, as they say. None of the charges will be found borne witness to
    with conscientiousness, or founded in truth, or extorted by indignation; but, on the contrary,
    you will see that it is all redolent of lust, passion, party spirit, bribery, and perjury.
     </p></div><milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Now that the universal cupidity of those men is ascertained, I will proceed to the separate
    complaints and charges of the Greeks. They complain that money was levied from the cities under
    the name of money for a fleet. And we admit, O judges, that that was done. But if this be a
    crime, the guilt must consist either in the fact that it was not lawful so to levy money; or in
    the fact that the ships were not wanted; or in the third alternative, that no fleet put to sea
    while he was praetor. That you may see that this levy was lawful, listen, I pray you, to what
    the senate decreed, when I was consul, in which it did not depart at all from the former decrees
    of many years running. [The resolution of the senate is read.] The next thing is for us to
    inquire whether there was need of the fleet or not. Is it then the Greeks or any foreign nations
    who are to be judges of this, or your praetors, your generals, your commanders-in-chief? I
    indeed think that in a district and province of that sort which is surrounded by the sea, dotted
    all over with harbours, and girt with islands, a fleet is requisite not only for the sake of
    protection, but as an ornament of the empire. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p> For there were
    these principles and there was this greatness of mind in our ancestors, that while in their
    private affairs, and as to their own personal expenses, they lived contented with a little, and
    without the smallest approach to luxury; where the empire and the dignity of the state was
    concerned, they brought everything up to a high pitch of splendour and magnificence. For in a
    man's private affairs he desires the credit of moderation, but in public affairs dignity is the
    object aimed at. But even if he had a fleet for the sake of protection, who will be so unjust as
    to blame it?—“There were no pirates.” What? who could certify beforehand that there would be
    none? “You are taking away,” said he, “from the glory of Pompeius.” </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p> Say, rather, that you yourself are increasing his difficulties. For he
    destroyed the fleets of the pirates, their cities, and harbours, and places of refuge. By his
    surpassing valour and incredible rapidity of motion he established a maritime peace; but this he
    neither undertook nor ought to have undertaken,—namely, to submit to appear worthy of
    prosecution if a single pirate's boat was anywhere seen. Therefore he himself in Asia, when he
    had terminated every war, both by land and sea, nevertheless levied a fleet on those self-same
    cities. And if he then thought that step was necessary, when everything might have been safe and
    tranquil through fear of his name, while he was still in those countries, what do you think that
    Flaccus ought to have decided on and to have done after he had departed? </p></div><milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What? did not we decree, by the advice of Pompeius himself, in the consulship of Silanus and
    Murena, that a fleet should put to sea to sail round Italy? Did not we, at the very same time
    that Lucius Flaccus was levying sailors in Asia, exact four millions three hundred thousand
    sesterces for fleets to defend the Mediterranean and Adriatic? What did we do the year after?
    was not money exacted for the use of the fleet when Marcus Curius and Publius Sextilius were
    quaestors? What? were there not all this time cavalry on the sea-coast? for that is the
    surpassing glory of Pompeius,—first of all, that those pirates who, when the conduct of the
    maritime war was first entrusted to him, wandered about straggling over the whole sea, were soon
    reduced under our power; in the next place, that Syria is ours, that Cilicia is occupied by us,
    that Cyprus, through the instrumentality of king Ptolemaeus, is reduced to a state in which it
    can venture to do nothing; moreover, that Crete, owing to the valour of Metellus, is ours; that
    the pirates have now no ports from which they can set out none to which they can return; that
    all the bays, and promontories, and shores, and islands, and maritime cities, are now contained
    within the barriers of our empire.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/>But if, when Flaccus was praetor, there had been not one
    pirate at sea, still his diligence would not have deserved to be blamed. For I should think that
    the reason of there being no pirates at sea was, because he had a fleet. What will you say if I
    prove by the evidence of Lucius Oppius, of Lucius Agrius, of Caius Cestius, Roman knights, and
    also of this most industrious man here present, Cnaeus Domitius, who was an ambassador in Asia
    at the time, that at that very time in which you yourself affirm that there was no need of a
    fleet, numbers of men were taken prisoners by the pirates? Still, will the wisdom of Flaccus, as
    shown in raising crews for the fleet, be found fault with? What if a man of high rank, a citizen
    of Adramyttium, was even slain by the pirates,—a man whose name is known to nearly all of us,
    Atyanas the boxer, a victor at Olympia? and this victory is considered among the Greeks (since
    we are speaking of their wisdom) a greater and more glorious thing than to have had a triumph is
    reckoned at Rome. “But you took no prisoners.” How many most illustrious men have had the
    command of the sea-coast, who, though they had taken no pirate prisoner, still made the sea
    safe? For taking prisoners depends on chance, on place, on accident, on opportunity. And the
    caution which shows itself in defence has an easy task; being aided not only by lurking places
    in concealed spots, but by the sudden fall or change of winds and weather. </p></div><milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The last thing that we have to inquire into is, whether that fleet really sailed with oars and
    sails, or only on paper, and as far as the expense went. Can that then be denied, of which all
    Asia is witness, that the fleet was distributed into two divisions, so that one division should
    sail above Ephesus, the other below Ephesus? in the one fleet Marcus Crassus, that most noble
    man, sailed from Aenas to Asia, with the other division Flaccus sailed from Asia to Macedonia.
    In what then is it that we look in vain for the diligence of the praetor? Is it in the number of
    the ships or in the equal division of the expense? He demanded just one half the fleet which
    Pompeius required. Could he be more economical? And he divided the expense according to the
    proportions settled by Pompeius, which was adapted to the division made by Sulla, who, when he
    had arranged all the cities in Asia according to the proportion that they were to bear of the
    expense imposed on the whole provinces, adopted a rule which Pompeius and Flaccus followed in
    raising the necessary sums, and even to this day the whole sum is not collected. But he makes no
    return of it. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p> What does he gain by that? for when he takes on
    himself the burden of having levied the money, he avows what you wish to <pb n="440"/> have
    considered as a crime. How then can any one be induced to believe that by not returning an
    account of that money, he deserves to bring an accusation on himself, when there would be no
    crime at all in the business if he made the return? But you deny that my brother, who succeeded
    Lucius Flaccus, levied any money for the purpose of crews for the fleet. Indeed, I am delighted
    to hear this praise of my brother Quintus, but I am still more pleased at other and more
    important reasons for praise of him. He decided on a different course; he saw a different state
    of things. He thought that whenever any intelligence of pirates was received, he could get
    together a fleet as suddenly as he could wish. And lastly, my brother was the very first man in
    Asia who ventured to relieve the cities from this expense of furnishing crews. But it is usual
    to think that a crime, when any one establishes charges which had not been established before;
    not when a successor merely changes some of the charges established by his predecessors. Flaccus
    could not know what others would do after his time; he only saw what others had done. </p></div><milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But some mention has been made of charges brought by the common consent of all Asia; I will
    now touch on the cases of individual cities—and of them, the first that I will speak of shall be
    the city of Aemon. The crier with a loud voice calls for the deputies from Aemon; one comes
    forward, Asclepiades. Let them come forward. Have you compelled even the crier to proclaim a
    lie? I suppose this one deputy is a man who can support the dignity of his city by his sole
    authority;—a man condemned by decisions involving the greatest infamy in his own city;
    stigmatised in the public records; of whose disgraceful acts, and adulteries, and licentiousness
    there are letters of the people of Aemon in existence; which I think it better to pass over, not
    only on account of their length, but on account of the scandalous obscenity of the language. He
    said that two hundred and six thousand drachmas had been given to Flaccus at the public expense.
    He only said so—he produced no confirmation of his statement, no proof; but he added this,—which
    most certainly he ought to have proved, for it was a personal affair of his own,—that he, as a
    private individual, had paid two hundred and six thousand drachmas. The quantity that that most
    impudent man says was taken from him was a sum that he never even ventured to wish to be the
    possessor of. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p> He says that he gave it as a contribution from
    Aulus Sextilius, and from his own brothers. Sextilius was able to give such a sum; as for his
    own brothers, they are partners in his beggary. Let us then hear what Sextilius says; then let
    his brothers themselves come forward; let them lie as shamelessly as they please, and let them
    say that they gave what they never possessed; still, perhaps, when they are produced face to
    face with us, they will say something in which they may be detected. “I have not brought
    Sextilius with me as a witness,” says he. Give me the accounts then. “I have not brought them
    down.” At least produce your brothers. “I never summoned them.” Are we then to fear as an
    accusation or as a piece of evidence, what Asclepiades by himself affirms, a man needy as to
    fortune, infamous as to character, condemned by every one's opinion, relying on his own
    impudence and audacity, without any account-books or any one to support his evidence? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p> He also said that the panegyric which we mentioned as having been given
    by the men of Aemon to Flaccus, is false; a panegyric, says he, which we ought to be glad to be
    without. For when that admirable representative of his city beheld the public seal, he said that
    his own fellow-citizens and all the rest of the Greeks were accustomed to seal at the moment
    whatever required it. Then take that panegyric to yourself. For the life and character of
    Flaccus do not depend on the evidence of the citizens of Aemon. For you grant to me, (an
    admission which this cause especially requires,) that there is no authority, no consistency, no
    firm wisdom in the Greeks, and, above all, no proper regard to truth in giving their evidence;
    unless, indeed, henceforward there is to be this distinction made between the evidence and your
    speech, that the cities are to be said to have allowed something to Flaccus when absent but are
    to appear to have neither written nor sealed anything suited to the occasion, so as to save
    Laelius, though he was present, though he himself undertook the management of the business
    himself, and though he alarmed them and threatened them, availing himself of the power of the
    law, of the privileges of a prosecutor, and of all his own private resources. </p></div><milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>In truth, O judges, I have often seen important facts detected and discovered through mere
    trifles, as in the case of <pb n="442"/> this Asclepiades. This panegyric, which has been
    produced by us, had been sealed with that Asiatic chalk which is known to nearly all of us;
    which all men use not only on public but also on their private letters, and which we every day
    see used in letters sent by publicans, and in letters addressed to each individual among us. Nor
    indeed did the witness himself, when he saw the seal, say that we were producing a forged
    document, but he alleged the worthless character of all Asiatics,—a matter which we willingly
    and easily grant to him. Our panegyric then,—which he says was given to us because of that
    particular occasion, and by so saying in fact allows was given to us,—was sealed with chalk. But
    on that evidence, which is said to have been given to the prosecutor, we saw the seal was wax.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p> Here, O judges, if I thought that you were influenced by the
    decrees of the Aemonensians, and by the letters of the rest of the Phrygians, I should cry out,
    and argue with all the vigour of which I was master. I should call to witness the publicans; I
    should invoke the traders; I should implore the aid of your own consciences: the wax being seen,
    I should feel sure that the audacious forgery of the whole evidence was evidently detected and
    discovered, and laid bare to you. But at present I will not triumph too violently, nor be too
    much elated at this, nor will I inveigh against that trifler as if he were a witness, nor will I
    allow myself to be moved at all with respect to any part of this testimony of the Aemonensians,
    whether it has been forged here, as appears likely on the face of it, or whether it can really
    been sent from Aemon, as it is said to have been. In truth, I will not fear the evidence of the
    men to whom I make over that panegyric, since, as Asclepiades says, they are utterly
    insignificant. </p></div><milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I come now to the evidence of the people of Dorylaeum, who, when they were brought into court
    said that they had lost their public documents near some caverns. O the shepherds (I know not
    who they were), the literary shepherds! if they took nothing from those men except the letters!
    But we suspect that there is some other reason, and that we should not think those men quite
    destitute of all cunning. There is, I imagine, a heavier penalty at Dorylaeum than among other
    people, for forging or tampering with written documents. If they had produced the genuine
    letters, there was no accusation in them; if they produced forged ones, there was a penalty for
    such an act. They thought the finest thing they could do was to say that they were lost.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p> Let them be quiet then, and allow me to set this down as so
    much gain, said to turn to something else. They will not allow me to do so. For some one or
    other gives them a lift, and says that he, as a private person, had given him money. But this
    cannot possibly be endured. He who reads things from those public documents which have been in
    the power of the prosecutor, ought not to carry any weight with him; but, nevertheless, a formal
    trial appears to take place when the documents themselves, of whatever character they may be,
    are produced. But when a man, whom not one of you has ever seen, whom no living mortal has ever
    heard of only says, “I gave,” will you hesitate, O judges, to save a most noble citizen from
    this most unknown of Phrygians? And this very man was lately disbelieved by three honourable and
    worthy Roman knights, when in a case in which a man's liberty was at stake, he said that the man
    who was claimed was his own kinsman. How has it come about that the man who was not considered a
    trustworthy witness as to his own blood and family is a credible authority concerning a public
    injury? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p> And when this Dorylaean was lately carried out to
    burial in the presence of a great multitude and numerous assembly of you, Laelius tried to
    excite odium against Lucius Flaccus by imputing his death to him. You are acting unjustly, O
    Laelius, if you think that it is our risk whether your comrades live or die; especially as I
    think that this instance proceeded from your own carelessness. For you gave a Phrygian, a man
    who had never seen a fig-tree, a whole basket of figs; and his death was to some extent a relief
    to you, for you lost a very voracious guest. But what good did it to Flaccus, as he was well
    enough till he came forward here, and who died after he had put out his sting and delivered his
    evidence? But that prop of your cause, Mithridates, was retained as a witness by us and examined
    two whole days; and, after he had said all that he wished, departed reproved, convicted, and
    broken down, and now walks about in a breastplate. That learned and sagacious man is afraid that
    Lucius Flaccus may burden himself with a crime, now that he cannot escape him as a witness; so
    that he, who, before the evidence was given, restrained himself when he might have got something
    by the deed, is likely now to add the guilt of an enormous crime to the charge of covetousness,
     <pb n="444"/> which is only supported by false evidence. But since Quintus Hortensius has
    spoken at great length and with great acuteness concerning this witness, and respecting the
    whole charge which has reference to Mithridates, we, as we originally intended, will proceed to
    the other points. </p></div><milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The principal man in stirring up all the Greeks,—he who is sitting with the
    prosecutors,—Heraclides of Temnos, a silly chattering fellow, but (in his own opinion) so
    learned, that he calls himself even their tutor, and so ambitious, that he salutes all of you
    and of us every day. Old as he is, he has not yet been able to get admission into the senate of
    Temnos; and he, the man who professes himself able to teach the art of speaking to others, has
    himself been convicted in some very discreditable trials. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p> Of
    similar good fortune was Nicomedes, who came with him as a deputy, who was not allowed to enter
    the senate on any terms, but had been convicted of theft, and of defrauding his partner. For
    Lysanias, the chief man of the deputation, obtained the rank of senator; but as he showed
    himself rather too much devoted to the riches of the republic, he was convicted of peculation,
    and lost his property and his title of senator. These three men tried to render the accounts of
    even our own treasury false. For they returned themselves as having nine slaves, when they had
    in reality come without one single companion. I see at the first framing of the decree Lysanias
    was present, he, whose brother's property was sold by public order during the praetorship of
    Flaccus, because he did not pay what he owed to the people. Besides him there is Philippus, the
    son-in-law of Lysanias; and Hermobius, whose brother also, by name Poles, was convicted of
    embezzling the public money. </p></div><milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>These men say that they gave Flaccus and those who were with him fifteen thousand drachmas. I
    have to do with a most active city, and one which is an admirable hand at keeping its accounts;
    a city in which not a farthing can be disposed of without the intervention of five praetors,
    three quaestors, and four bankers, who are elected in that city by the burgesses. Of all that
    number not one has been brought hither as a witness; and when they return that money as having
    been given to Flaccus by name, they say that they gave him also a still larger sum, entered as
    having been given for the repair of a temple. But this is not a very consistent story; for
    either everything ought to have been kept secret or else everything ought to have been returned
    without any disguise. When they enter the money as having been given to Flaccus, naming him
    expressly, they fear nothing, they apprehend nothing. When they return the money as having been
    given for a public work, then all of a sudden those same men begin to be afraid of the very man
    whom they had despised before. If the praetor gave the money, as it is set down, he drew it from
    the quaestor, the quaestor from the public bank, the public bank derived it either from revenue
    or from tribute. All this will never be like a crime, unless you explain to me the whole
    business both with respect to the persons and to the accounts. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p> Or, as it is written in this same decree, that the most illustrious men of the city,—men who
    had had the highest honours of the state conferred on them,—were circumvented by him while he
    was praetor, why are they not present in court or why, at all events, are they not named in the
    decree? For I do not suppose that Heraclides, who is pricking up his head, is the person here
    intended. For is he one of the most eminent of the citizens, when Hermippus brought him here for
    trial? a man who did not even receive his present commission to come on this deputation from his
    fellow-citizens by their voluntary choice, but who went all the way from Tmolus to solicit it? a
    man on whom no honour was ever conferred in his own city; and the only business which ever has
    been entrusted to him, is one which is usually entrusted to the most insignificant people. He,
    in the praetorship of Titus Autidius, was appointed guardian of the public corn. And when he had
    received money from Publius Varinius the praetor for this purpose, he concealed it from his
    fellow-citizens, and charged the whole of the expense to them. And after this was made known and
    revealed at Temnos, by letters which were sent thither by Publius Varinius, and when Cnaeus
    Lentulus, he who was the censor, the patron of the people of Temnos, had sent letters on the
    same subject, no one ever afterwards saw that man Heraclides at Temnos. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p> And that you may be thoroughly aware of his impudence, listen, I entreat you,
    to the cause which excited the animosity of this most worthless man against Flaccus. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>He bought at Rome a farm in the district of Cyme, from a minor whose name was Meculonius.
    Having made himself out in words to be a rich man,—though he had in reality nothing beyond the
    stock of impudence which you <pb n="446"/> see,—he borrowed the money from Sextus Stola, one of
    our judges now present a man of the highest consideration, who is acquainted with the
    circumstances, and not unacquainted with the man; but who trusted him on the security of Publius
    Fulvius Veratius, a most unexceptionable man. And to pay this loan he borrowed money of Caius
    and Marcus Fufius, Roman knights, men of the highest character. Here, in truth, he caught a
    weasel asleep, as people say; for he cheated Hermippus, a learned man, his own fellow-citizen,
    who ought to have known him well enough; for on his security he borrowed money of the Fufii.
    Hermippus, without feeling any anxiety, goes away to Temnos, as he said that he would pay the
    Fufii the money which he had borrowed on his security, out of what he received from his pupils.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p> For he, as a rhetorician, had some rich men for pupils whom
    he was going to make as foolish again as they were when they came to him, (for they could
    acquire nothing from him, except an ignorance of every sort of learning;) but he could not
    infatuate any one to such an extent as to get him to lend him a single farthing. Therefore,
    having left Rome secretly, and cheated numbers of people by trifling loans, he came into Asia;
    and when Hermippus asked him what he had done about the bond given to the Fufii, he said that he
    paid the entire sum to the Fufii. In the mean time, not long afterwards, a freedman comes to
    Hermippus with letters from the Fufii. The money is demanded of Hermippus. Hermippus demands it
    of Heraclides; however, he himself satisfies the claim of the Fufii who are at a distance, and
    discharges the security which he had given. He then prosecutes Heraclides, in spite of all his
    fuming and shuffling, in a formal manner: the cause is tried before judges. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Do not fancy, O judges, that the impudence of cheats and repudiators is not one and the same
    in all places. This man did the very same things which debtors here are in the habit of doing.
    He denied that he had ever borrowed any money at all at Rome. He asserted that he had actually
    never heard the name of the Fufii; and he attacked Hermippus himself, a most modest and virtuous
    man, an ancient friend and hereditary connection of my own, the most eminent and accomplished
    man in his city, with every sort of reproach and abuse. But after this voluble gentleman had
    delivered himself in that fashion with a prodigious rapidity of eloquence for some time, all of
    a sudden, when the evidence of the Fufii and the items of their claim were read, though a most
    audacious man, he got alarmed; through a most talkative one, he became dumb. Therefore, the
    judges at the first trial gave a decision against him, in a matter which certainly did not admit
    of much doubt. As he did not comply with their decision, he was given up to Hermippus and put in
    prison by him. </p></div><milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Now you know the honesty of the man and the value of his evidence, and the whole reason of his
    enmity to Flaccus. Having been released by Hermippus after having sold him a few slaves, he came
    to Rome from thence he returned into Asia, when my brother Quintus had succeeded Flaccus in that
    government and went to him and related his story in this manner, saying that the judges being
    compelled and put in fear by the violence of Flaccus had given a false decision against their
    will. My brother as became his impartiality and prudence, decreed that if he demurred to the
    previous decision, he was to give security to double the amount; and that if he said that they
    were compelled by fear at the first trial, he should have the same judges again. He refused
    this, and as if there had been no trial and no decision, he began on the spot to demand back
    from Hermippus the slaves which he himself had sold him. Marcus Gratidius, the lieutenant,
    before whom he went refused to give him leave to proceed with the action, but declared that he
    should adhere to the decision already given. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus"><p> A second time,
    as he had no place anywhere where he could remain, he betook himself to Rome. Hermippus, who
    never yields to his impudence, follows him hither. Heraclides demands from Caius Plotius, a
    senator, a man of the highest character, who had served in Asia as lieutenant some slaves, which
    he said he had sold under compulsion, at a time when an unjust decision had been given against
    him. Quintus Naso, a most accomplished man, who had been praetor, is appointed judge; and when
    he showed that he was going to give sentence in favour of Plotius, Heraclides left the judge,
    and abandoned the whole cause as if he had not had a fair and legal trial. Do I appear to you, O
    judges, to be dwelling too much on each individual witness, and not to be discussing the whole
    class of witnesses, as I originally intended? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus"><p> I come now to
    Lysanias, of the same city,—your own especial witness, Decianus,—a <pb n="448"/> man whom you,
    as you had known him at Temnos when a youth, since he had pleased you when naked, wished to be
    always naked. You took him from Temnos to Apollonia. You lent money to him while quite a youth,
    at great interest, having taken good security for the loan. You say that the securities have
    been forfeited to you, and to this day you detain them and keep them in your possession. And you
    have compelled this man to come forward to give evidence as a witness by the hope of recovering
    his paternal estate. And as he has not yet given his evidence, I am waiting to see what it is
    that he will state. For I know the sort of men that they are,—I know their habits, I know their
    licentious ways. Therefore, although I am certain what he is prepared to state, still I will not
    argue against it before he has stated it; for if I do, he will alter it all and invent something
    else. Let him, then, keep what he has prepared; and I will keep myself fresh for whatever
    statements he makes. </p></div><milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I come now to that state to which I myself have shown great kindness and done many great
    services, and which my brother has shown the greatest attachment to and fondness for. And if
    that city had brought its complaints before you by the month of creditable and respectable men,
    I should be a little more concerned about it; but now what am I to think? Am I to think that the
    Trallians entrusted their cause to Maeandrius, a needy, sordid man, without honour, without
    character, without income? Where were the Pythodori, the Aetideni, the Lepisos, and the other
    men who are well known among us, and who are of high rank among their own people? where is their
    splendid and high-spirited display of the respectability of their city? Would they not have been
    ashamed, if they had been serious about this business, that Maeandrius should be called, I will
    not say their deputy, but even a Trallian at all? Would they ever have entrusted to this man as
    their deputy,—to this man as their public witness, Lucius Flaccus the hereditary patron of their
    city, whose father and ancestors had been so before him, to be ruined by the evidence of their
    city? This cannot be the fact, O judges; it never can be. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I myself lately saw in some trial a Trallian witness of the name of Philodorus, I saw
    Parrhasius, I saw Archidemus, when this identical man Maeandrius came to me as a sort of
    attorney, suggesting to me what I might say, if I pleased, against his own fellow-citizens and
    his own city. For there is nothing more worthless than that fellow,—nothing more needy, nothing
    more infamous. Wherefore, if the Trallians employ him as the relater of their indignation, and
    the keeper of their letters, and the witness of their injuries, and the utterer of their
    complaints, let them lower their high tone for the future, let them restrain their high spirit,
    let them bridle their arrogance, let them confess that the best representative of their city is
    to be found in the person of Maeandrius. But if they themselves have always thought this man a
    man to be buffeted and trampled upon at home, let them cease to think that there is any
    authority in that evidence which there is no respectable person to father. <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But I will explain what the facts of the case really are, that you may know why that city was
    neither severe in attacking Flaccus, nor very anxious to defend him. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus"><p> The city was offended with him on account of the affair of Castricius;
    concerning the whole of which Hortensius has made a sufficient reply. Very much against its
    will, it had paid Castricius some money which had long been due to him. Hence comes all its
    hatred to Flaccus, and this is his whole offence. And when Laelius had arrived in that city
    among a set of angry men, and had re-opened their indignation with respect to Castricius by
    mentioning the subject, the chief men jumped up and left the place, and refused to be present in
    that assembly, and would not assist in carrying the decree, or in framing the deposition. And to
    such an extent was that assembly deprived of the presence of the nobles of the city, that
    Maeandrius was the chief of the chief men present; and it was by his tongue, acting like a sort
    of fan of sedition, that assembly of needy men was ventilated. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, now learn the justice of the grief and complaints of a city, a moderate city, as I
    have always considered it, and a worthy one, as the citizens themselves wish it to be thought.
    They complain that the money which was deposited amongst them, in the name of Flaccus's
    father,—money which had been collected from different cities,—has been taken away from them. At
    another time I will inquire of them what power Flaccus had in the matter. At present I only ask
    the Trallians, whether they say the money, which they complain has been taken from them, was
    their own,—was a contribution from the other cities for their use. I wish to hear this. We do
    not <pb n="450"/> say so, says he. What then? We say that it was brought to us—entrusted to us
    in the name of Lucius Flaccus, the father of this man, for the days of festival and the games
    which were to be celebrated in his honour. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus"><p> What then? “This
    you had no right to touch.” Presently I will see to that; but first of all I will deal with
    this. A dignified, a wealthy, a noble city complains that it is not allowed to retain what does
    not belong to it. It says that it has been plundered, because it has not in its possession what
    never was its own. What can be said or imagined more shameless than this? A town was selected in
    which, above all others, the money contributed by all Asia for the honours of Lucius Flaccus
    should be deposited. All this money was transferred from the purpose of doing him honour, and
    employed in gainful traffic and usury. Many years afterwards it was recovered. </p></div><milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What injury was done to the city? “But the city is very indignant at it.” I dare say. For the
    profit is wrenched from it contrary to its hopes, which had already been devoured in
    expectation. “But it complains;” and a most impudent complaint it is. For we cannot reasonably
    complain of everything at which we are annoyed. “But it accuses him in the severest language.”
    Not the city, but ignorant men do so, who have been stirred up by Maeandrius. And while on this
    topic I beg you over and over again to recollect how great is the rashness of a multitude,—how
    great the peculiar levity of Greeks,—and how great is the influence of a seditious speech in a
    public assembly. Even here, in this most dignified and well-regulated of cities, when the forum
    is full of courts of justice, full of magistrates, full of most excellent men and citizens,—when
    the senate-house, the chastiser of rashness, the directress in the path of duty, commands and
    surveys the rostra, still what storms do we see excited in the public assemblies? What do you
    think is the case at Tralles? is it the same as is the case at Pergamus? Unless, perchance,
    these cities wish it to be believed that they could more easily be influenced by one letter of
    Mithridates, and impelled to violate the claims of their friendship with the Roman people, and
    their own plighted faith, and all the rights and duties of humanity, than to injure by their
    evidence the son of a man whom they had thought it necessary to drive from their walls by force
    of arms. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus"><p> Do not, then, oppose to me the names of those noble
    cities, for those whom this family has scorned as enemies, it will never be afraid of as
    witnesses. But you must confess, if your cities are governed by the counsels of your chief men,
    that it was not by the rashness of the multitude, but by the deliberate counsel of the nobles,
    that war was undertaken by those cities against the Roman people; or if that disturbance was at
    that time caused by the rashness of the ignorant mob, then permit me to separate the errors of
    the Roman people from the general cause. </p></div><milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>“But he had no right to lay hands on that money.” Had his father Flaccus a right to touch it
    or not? If he had a right, as he undoubtedly had, to take money which had been contributed for
    the purposes of his honours, then the son did right in taking away the money belonging to his
    father from those men from whom he on his own account took nothing; but if the father Flaccus
    had not a right to take it, still after his death, not only his son, but any heir, must have had
    a perfect right to take it. And at that time, indeed, the Trallians, as they themselves had been
    for many years putting out that money at high interest nevertheless obtained from Flaccus all
    that they desired; nor were they so shameless as to venture to say what Laelius said,—namely,
    that Mithridates had taken this money from them. For who was there who did not know that
    Mithridates was more anxious about adorning Tralles than plundering it? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus"><p> And if I were to speak of these matters as they ought to be spoken of, I
    should, O judges, press more strongly than I have as yet done, the point of how much credit it
    was reasonable for you to give Asiatic witnesses. I should recall your recollections to the time
    of the Mithridatic war, to that miserable and inhuman massacre of all the Roman citizens, in so
    many cities, at one and the same moment. I should remind you of our praetors who were
    surrendered, of our ambassadors who were thrown into prison, of almost all memory of the Roman
    name and every trace of its empire effaced, not only from the habitations of the Greeks, but
    even from their writings. They called Mithridates a god, they called him their father and the
    preserver of Asia, they called him Evius, Nysius, Bacchus, Liber. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus"><p> It was the same time, when all Asia shut its gates against Lucius Flaccus, the
    consul, and not only received that Cappadocian into their cities, but even spontaneously invited
    him. Let us be allowed, if not to forget these things, at least <pb n="452"/> to be silent
    respecting them. Let me be allowed rather to complain of the inconstancy of the Greeks than of
    their cruelty. Are these two men to have influence with a people which they wished utterly to
    destroy? For whomsoever they could they slew while in the garb of peace; as far as depended on
    them they annihilated the name of Roman citizens. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Shall they then give themselves airs in a city which they hate? among those people whom, if
    they had their will, they would not look upon? in that republic to the destruction of which it
    was their power that was unequal, and not their inclination? Let them behold this noble body of
    ambassadors and panegyrists of Flaccus who have come from the real honest Greece. Then let them
    weigh themselves in the balance, let them compare themselves with these men; then, if they dare, let them compare their dignity with that of these men.  </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus"><p> 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Athenians are here, citizens of that city from which civilization, learning, religion, corn,
    laws, and institutions are supposed to have arisen, and to have been disseminated over the whole
    earth—that city, for the possession of which there is said to have been, by reason of its
    beauty, a contest even among the gods: a city which is of that antiquity that she is said to
    have produced her citizens from her own womb, so that the same land is called the parent, and
    nurse, and country of her people. And she is of such authority that the name of Greece, now
    enfeebled and almost broken, rests upon the glory of this city. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Lacedaemonians are here; men of that city, whose tried and glorious virtue is considered not
    only to be implanted in them by nature, but also to be fortified by discipline. The only men in
    the whole world who have been living for now seven hundred years and more under one system, and
    under laws which have never been altered. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Many deputies are here from all Achaia, Boeotia, and Thessaly, places in which Lucius Flaccus
    has lately been in command as lieutenant under Metellus as commander-in-chief. Nor do I pass you
    over, O Marseilles, you who have known Lucius Flaccus as soldier and as quaestor,—a city, the
    strict discipline and wisdom of which I do not know whether I might not say was superior, not
    only to that of Greece, but to that of any nation whatever; a city which, though so far
    separated from the districts of all the Greeks, and from their fashions and language, and though
    placed in the extremity of the world and surrounded by tribes of Gauls, and washed with the
    waves of barbarism, is so regulated and governed by the counsels of its chief men, that there is
    no nation which does not find it easier to praise its institutions than to imitate them.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus"><p> Flaccus has these states as his panegyrists and as witnesses
    of his innocence, so that we may resist the covetousness of some Greeks by the assistance of
    others. <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Although, who is there who is ignorant, provided he has only taken the most ordinary trouble
    to make himself acquainted with these matters, that there are in reality three different races
    of Greeks; of which the Athenians are one, being considered an Ionic nation; the Aeolians are
    another; the third were called Dorians. And the whole of this land of Greece, which flourished
    so greatly with fame, with glory, with learning, and many arts, and even with wide dominion and
    military renown, occupies as you know, and always has occupied, but a small part of Europe. It
    surrounded the seacoast of Asia with cities after it had subdued it in war; not in order to
    increase the prosperity of Asia by fortifying it with colonies, but in order to keep its hold
    upon it by placing it in a state of siege. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus"><p> Wherefore I
    beseech you, O you Asiatic witnesses, that, when you wish to recollect with accuracy what amount
    of authority you bring into a court of justice, you would yourselves describe Asia, and
    remember, not what foreigners are accustomed to say of you, but what you yourselves affirm of
    your own races. For, as I think, the Asia that you talk of consists of Phrygia, Mysia, Caria,
    and Lydia. Is it then a proverb of ours or of yours that a Phrygian is usually made better by
    beating? What more? Is not this a common saying of you all with respect to the whole of Caria,
    if you wish to make any experiment accompanied with danger, that you had better try it on a
    Carian? Moreover what saying is there in Greek conversation more ordinary and well known, than,
    when any one is spoken of contemptuously, to say that he is the very lowest of the Mysians? For
    why should I speak of Lydia? What Greek ever wrote a comedy in which the principal slave was not
    a Lydian? What injury, then, is done to you, if we decide that we are to adhere to the judgment
    which you have formed of yourselves? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus"><p> In truth, I think that I
    have said enough and more than enough of the whole race of witnesses from Asia. But still it is
    your duty, O judges, to weigh in your minds and thoughts everything which can be said against
    the insignificance, the inconstancy, and the covetousness of the men, even if these points are
    not sufficiently enlarged upon by me. <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The next thing is that charge about the Jewish gold. And this, forsooth, is the reason why
    this cause is pleaded near the steps of Aurelius. It is on account of this charge, O Laelius,
    that this place and that mob has been selected by you. You know how numerous that crowd is, how
    great is its unanimity, and of what weight it is in the popular assemblies. I will speak in a
    low voice, just so as to let the judges hear me. For men are not wanting who would be glad to
    excite that people against me and against every eminent man; and I will not assist them and
    enable them to do so more easily. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus"><p> As gold, under pretence of
    being given to the Jews, was accustomed every year to be exported out of Italy and all the
    provinces to Jerusalem, Flaccus issued an edict establishing a law that it should not be lawful
    for gold to be exported out of Asia. And who is there, O judges, who cannot honestly praise this
    measure? The senate had often decided, and when I was consul it came to a most solemn resolution
    that gold ought not to be exported. But to resist this barbarous superstition were an act of
    dignity, to despise the multitude of Jews, which at times was most unruly in the assemblies in
    defence of the interests of the republic, was an act of the greatest wisdom. “But Cnaeus
    Pompeius, after he had taken Jerusalem, though he was a conqueror, touched nothing which was in
    that temple.” </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus"><p> In the first place, he acted wisely, as he did
    in many other instances, in leaving no room for his detractors to say anything against him, in a
    city so prone to suspicion and to evil speaking. For I do not suppose that the religion of the
    Jews, our enemies, was any obstacle to that most illustrious general, but that he was hindered
    by his own modesty. Where then is the guilt? Since you nowhere impute any theft to us, since you
    approve of the edict, and confess that it was passed in due form, and did not deny that the gold
    was openly sought for and produced the facts of the case themselves show that the business was
    executed by the instrumentality of men of the highest character. There was a hundredweight of
    gold, more or less openly seized at Apamea, and weighed out in the forum at the feet of the
    praetor, by Sextus Caesius, a Roman knight, a most excellent and upright man; twenty pounds
    weight or a little more were seized at Laodicea, by Lucius Peducaeus, who is here in court, one
    of our judges; some was seized also at Adramyttium, by Cnaeus Domitius, the lieutenant, and a
    small quantity at Pergamus. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus"><p> The amount of the gold is known;
    the gold is in the treasury; no theft is imputed to him; but it is attempted to render him
    unpopular. The speaker turns away from the judges, and addresses himself to the surrounding
    multitude. Each city, O Laelius, has its own peculiar religion we have ours. While Jerusalem was
    flourishing, and while the Jews were in a peaceful state, still the religious ceremonies and
    observances of that people were very much at variance with the splendour of this empire and the
    dignity of our name and the institutions of our ancestors. And they are the more odious to us
    now because that nation has shown by arms what were its feelings towards our supremacy. How dear
    it was to the immortal gods is proved by its having been defeated, by its revenues having been
    farmed out to our contractors, by its being reduced to a state of subjection. </p></div><milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, since you see that all that which you wished to impute to him as a crime is turned
    to his credit, let us now come to the complaints of the Roman citizens. And let the first be
    that of Decianus. What injury, then, O Decianus, has been done to you? You are trading in a free
    city. First of all, allow me to be a little curious. How long shall you continue to live there
    as a trader, especially since you are born of such a rank as you are? You have now for thirty
    years been frequenting the forum,—the forum, I mean, of Pergamus. After a very long interval, if
    at any time is convenient to you to travel, you come to Rome. You bring a new face, an old name;
    Tyrian garments, in which respect I envy you, that with only one cloak you look so smart for
    such a length of time. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus"><p> However, be it so. You like to
    practise commerce. Why not at Pergamus? at Smyrna? at Tralles? where there are many Roman
    citizens, and where magistrates of our own preside in the courts of justice. You are fond of
    ease: lawsuits, crowds, and praetors are odious to you. You delight in the freedom of the
    Greeks. Why, then, do you alone treat the people of Apollonides, the allies who of all others
    are the most attached to the Roman people and the most faithful, in a more miserable manner than
    either <pb n="456"/> Mithridates, or than your own father ever treated them? Why do you prevent
    them from enjoying their own liberty? why do you prevent them from being free? They are of all
    Asia the most frugal, the most conscientious men, the most remote from the luxury and
    inconstancy of the Greeks; they are fathers of families, are content with their own, farmers,
    country-people. They have lands excellent by nature, and improved by diligence and cultivation.
    In this district you wished to have some farms. I should greatly prefer, (and it would have been
    more for your interest too, if you wanted some fertile lands,) that you should have got some
    here somewhere in the district of Crustumii, or in the Capenate country. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus"><p> However, be it so. It is an old saying of Cato's,—“that money is balanced by
    distance.” It is a very long way from the Tiber to the Caicus,—a place in which Agamemnon
    himself would have lost his way, if he had not found Telephus for his guide. However, I give up
    all that. You took a fancy to the town. The country delighted you. You might have bought it.
     <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Amyntas is by birth, by rank, by universal opinion, and by his riches, the first man of that
    state. Decianus brought his mother-in-law, a woman of weak mind, and tolerably rich, over to his
    side, and, while she was ignorant of what his object was, he established his household in the
    possession of her estates. He took away from Amyntas his wife, then in a state of pregnancy, who
    was confined with a daughter in Decianus's house, and to this very day both the wife and
    daughter of Amyntas are in Decianus's house. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus"><p> Is there any one
    of all these circumstances invented by me, O Decianus? —All the nobles know these facts—virtuous
    men are acquainted with them—our own citizens are acquainted with them—all the merchants of
    ordinary consequence are acquainted with them. Rise, Amyntas: demand back from Decianus, not
    your money, not your estates; let him even keep your mother-in-law for himself; but let him
    restore your wife, let him restore the daughter to her miserable father: for the limbs which he
    has weakened with stones, with sticks, with weapons, the hands which he has crushed, the fingers
    which he has broken, the sinews which he has cut through, those he cannot restore. The
    daughter,—restore the daughter, I say, O Decianus, to her unhappy father. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74" resp="perseus"><p> Do you wonder that you could not get Flaccus to approve of this conduct? I
    should like to know who you did persuade to approve of it? You contrived fictitious purchases,
    you put up advertisements of estates in concert with some wretched women,—open frauds. According
    to the laws of the Greeks it was necessary to name a guardian to look after these matters. You
    named Polemocrates a hired slave and minister of your designs. Polemocrates was prosecuted by
    Dion for treachery and fraud on account of this very guardianship. What a crowd was there from
    all the neighbouring towns on every side! What was their indignation! How universal were their
    complaints! Polemocrates was convicted by every single vote; the sales were annulled, the
    advertisements were canceled. Do you restore the property? You bring to the men of Pergamus, and
    beg them to enter in their public registers, those beautiful advertisements and purchases of
    yours. They refuse, they reject them. And yet who were the men who did so? The men of Pergamus,
    your own panegyrists. For you appear to me to boast as much of the panegyric of the citizens of
    Pergamus, as if you had arrived at all the honours which had been attained by your ancestors.
    And you thought yourself in this respect better off than Laelius, that the city of Pergamus
    praised you. Is the city of Pergamus more honourable than that of Smyrna? Even the men of
    Pergamus themselves do not assert that. </p></div><milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I wish that I had leisure enough to read the decree of the Smyrnaeans, which they made
    respecting the dead Castricius. In the first place, that he was to be brought into the city,
    which is an honour not granted to others; in the next place, that young men should bear his
    coffin; and lastly, that a golden crown should be put upon the dead body. These honours were not
    paid to that most illustrious man, Publius Scipio, when he had died at Pergamus. But what
    language, O ye immortal gods, do they use concerning him, calling him “the glory of his country,
    the ornament of the Roman people, the flower of the youth.” Wherefore, O Decianus, if you are
    desirous of glory, I advise you to seek other distinctions. The men of Pergamus laughed at you.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76" resp="perseus"><p> What? Did you not understand that you were being made sport
    of, when they read those words to you, “most illustrious man, of most extraordinary wisdom, of
    singular ability.” I assure you they were joking with you. But when they put a golden crown at
    the head of their letters, in reality they did not entrust you with more gold than they would
    trust to a jackdaw; could you not even perceive the neatness and facetiousness of the men? They,
    then,—those men of Pergamus,—repudiated the advertisements which you produced. Publius Orbius, a
    man both prudent and incorruptible, gave every decision that he did give against you. <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You received more favour from Publius Globulus, an intimate friend of mine. I wish that
    neither he nor I may repent it? <note anchored="true">There are a few words here hopelessly
     corrupt which are omitted in the translation. Orellius prints it—<foreign xml:lang="la">Flaccum
      in curia decrevissent veridicas. Adjungis</foreign>, etc., and in a note gives up the whole
     passage as corrupt. Nobbe puts the stop before <foreign xml:lang="la">veridicas</foreign>.</note><gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77" resp="perseus"><p> You add real causes of the enmity between you, that your
    father as tribune of the people prosecuted the father of Lucius Flaccus when he was curule
    aedile. But that ought not to have been very annoying even to Flaccus's father himself;
    especially as he, who was prosecuted, was afterwards made praetor and consul, and the man who
    prosecuted him could not even remain in the city as a private individual. But if you thought
    that a reasonable ground for enmity, why, when Flaccus was military tribune, did you serve as a
    soldier in his legion, when by the military law you might have avoided the injustice of the
    tribune? And why did the praetor summon you, his hereditary enemy, to his counsels? And how
    sacredly such obligations are accustomed to be observed, you all know. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78" resp="perseus"><p> At present we are prosecuted by men who were our counselors. “Flaccus issued a
    decree.” Did he issue a different decree from what he ought? “against freemen.” Was it contrary
    to the resolution to which the senate had come? “He issued this decree against an absent man.”
    When you were in the same race, and when you refused to come forward, that is a different thing
    from being absent. [The resolution of the senate and the decree of Flaccus are read.]<milestone unit="para"/>What next?
    suppose he had not made a decree, but had only issued an edict, who could have found fault with
    him with truth? Are you going to find fault with the letters of my brother, full of humanity and
    equity. The same <note anchored="true">This passage is given up by every commentator as
     irretrievably corrupt.</note> letters which, having been given by me <gap reason="lost"/>Read
    the letters of Quintus Cicero. [The letters of Quintus Cicero are read.]</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79" resp="perseus"><p>What? did the people of
    Apollonides, when they had an opportunity, report these things to Flaccus? Were they not argued in court before Orbius? Were they not reported to Orbius?
    Did not the deputies of Apollonia report to our senate in my consulship all the demands which
    they had to make respecting the injuries which they had received from this one man, Decianus? 
   <milestone unit="para"/>“Oh, but you gave in an estimate of these farms also at the census.” I say nothing of their
    being other people's property; I say nothing of their having been got possession of by violence;
    I say nothing of the conviction by the Apollonidians that ensued; I say nothing of the business
    having been repudiated by the people of Pergamus; I say nothing of the fact that restitution of
    the whole was compelled by our magistrates; I say nothing of the fact that neither by law, nor
    in fact, nor even by the right of occupation, did they belong to you. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80" resp="perseus"><p> I only ask this; whether those farms can be bought and sold by the civil law;
    whether they come under the provisions of the civil law, whether or no they are freehold,
    whether they can be registered at the treasury and before the censor? Lastly, in what tribe did
    you register those farms? You managed it so, that if any serious emergency had arisen, tribute
    might have been levied on the same farms both at Apollonides and at Rome. However, be it so; you
    were in a boastful humour. You wanted a great amount of land to be registered as yours, and of
    that land too, which cannot be distributed among the Roman people. Besides that, you were
    registered as possessed of' money in hand, cash to the amount of a hundred and thirty thousand
    sesterces. I do not suppose that you counted that money; but I pass over all these things. You
    registered the slaves of Amyntas; and, in that respect you did not wrong; for Amyntas is the
    owner of those slaves. And at first indeed he was alarmed when he heard that you had registered
    his slaves. He consulted lawyers. It was decreed by all of them that if Decianus could make
    other people's property his by registering it as such, he would have very great <gap reason="lost"/>
    </p></div><milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You now know the cause of the enmity by which Decianus was excited to communicate to Laelius
    this grand accusation against Flaccus. For Laelius framed his complaint in this way, when he was
    speaking of the perfidy of Decianus: “He, who was my original informant; who communicated the
    facts of the case; whom I have followed, he has been bribed by Flaccus, he has deserted and
    abandoned me.” Have you, then, been the prime mover in bringing that man into peril of all his;
    fortunes, whose counselor you had been, with whom you had preserved all the privileges of your
    rank, a most virtuous man, a man born of a most noble family, a man who had done great services
    to the republic? Forsooth, I will defend Decianus, who has become suspected by you through no
    fault of his own. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82" resp="perseus"><p> Believe me, he was not bribed; for what was
    there which could have been got by bribing him? Could he have contrived for the trial to last
    longer? Why, the law only allows six hours altogether. How much would Decianus rather have taken
    away from those six hours, if he had wished to serve you. In truth, that is what he himself
    suspects,—you envied the ingenuity of your junior counsel. Because he discharged the part which
    he had undertaken with wit, and examined the witnesses cleverly, <note anchored="true">What
     follows here in the text is quite unintelligible, and is given up by Orellius as hopelessly
     corrupt; and probably there is some corruption for the next few lines which I have attempted to
     translate.</note><gap reason="lost"/> But if this be probable, at all events it is not very
    probable that Decianus was bribed by Flaccus. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83" resp="perseus"><p> And the rest of
    the case is just as improbable, as is what Lucceius says, that Lucius Flaccus had wished to give
    him two millions of sesterces to induce him to break his word. And do you accuse that man of
    avarice who you say was willing to abstain from taking two millions of sesterces? For when he
    was buying you, what was it that he was buying? Was it your desertion to his side? If you did
    come over to us, what share in the cause were we to give you? were we to allot to you the part
    of explaining the designs of Laelius? of saying what witnesses proceeded from his house? What?
    did not we ourselves see that they were living together? Who is there who does not know that? Is
    there the slightest doubt that the documents were in Laelius's power? or, was he bribing you not
    to accuse him with vigour and with eloquence? Now you give cause for suspicion; for you spoke in
    such a manner that some point or other does seem to have been carried with you. </p></div><milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>“But a great and intolerable injury was done to Andrus Sextilius.” As, when his wife Valeria
    had died without a will, Flaccus managed the business in such a way as if the inheritance
    belonged to himself. And in that I should be glad to know what you find fault with,—is it, that
    he asserted anything which was false? How do you prove it? “She was,” says he, “a person of good
    family.” O man, learned in the law! What? cannot inheritances legally come from women of good
    family? “She was,” says he, “under the power of her husband.” Now I understand you; but was she
    so by use <note anchored="true">The marriage <foreign xml:lang="la">per coemptionem</foreign>
     has already been explained. “Marriage was also effected by <foreign xml:lang="la">usus</foreign>, if a woman lived with a man for a whole year as his wife.” Smith, Dict, Ant.
     p. 604 v. <title>Marriage</title>, q. v. </note> or by purchase? It could not be by use for
    legitimate guardianship cannot be annulled except by the consent of all the guardians. By
    purchase? Then it must have been with the consent of all of them; and certainly you will not say
    that that of Flaccus was obtained. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85" resp="perseus"><p> That alternative remains
    which he did not cease asserting loudly; “that Flaccus ought not, when he was praetor, to have
    attended to his own private concerns, or to have made any mention of the inheritance.” I hear, O
    Lucius Lucullus, that very great inheritances came to you, to you who are about to decide as
    judge on the case of Lucius Flaccus, on account of your exceeding liberality and of the great
    services which you had done your friends, during the time that you were governing the province
    of Asia with consular power. If any one had said that those inheritances belonged to him, would
    you have given them up? You, O Titus Vettius, if any inheritance in Africa comes to you, will
    you abandon it? or, will you retain it as your own, without being liable to the imputation of
    avarice, without any sacrifice of your dignity? “But the possession of the inheritance of which
    we are speaking was demanded in the name of Flaccus, when Globulus was praetor.” Well then, it
    was not any sudden violence, nor the idea of any favourable opportunity, nor force, nor any
    peculiarity of time, nor the possession of command and of the forces which induced Flaccus to
    commit this injury. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And, therefore, it is to this point that Marcus Lurco also, a most excellent man, and a great
    friend of mine, has especially addressed the sting of his evidence. He said, that it was not
    becoming for a praetor in his province to claim money from a private individual. Why, I should
    like to know, O Lurco, is it not becoming? It is not becoming to force or extort money, or to
    receive money contrary to the laws; but you will never convince me that it is not becoming to
    claim it, unless you can show that it is not lawful to do so. Is it right to accept of honorary
    lieutenancies for the sake of exacting what is one's due, as you yourselves have done lately,
    and as many good men have often done, (and I, indeed, find no fault with such conduct; I see
    that our allies complain of it;) and, do you think a praetor, if he, being in his province, does
    not abandon an inheritance which comes to him, is not only to be blamed but even to be
    condemned? <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="para"/>“But Valeria,” says he, “had given up all her money
    as dower to her husband.” None of those assertions can be admitted, unless you prove that she
    was not under the guardianship of Flaccus. If she was, whatever money on her marriage was
    assigned to her husband without his consent, the assignment is null. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87" resp="perseus"><p> But still you saw that Lurco was angry with Flaccus, although out of regard to
    his own dignity he was guided by some moderation in giving his evidence. For he did not conceal,
    or think it at all necessary to be silent about the cause of his anger. He complained that his
    freedman had been condemned by Flaccus when he was praetor. O how miserable is the condition of
    those who have the government of provinces! in which diligence is sure to bring enmity;
    carelessness is sure to incur reproach; severity is dangerous; liberality meets only with
    ingratitude. The conversation addressed to one is insidious; the flattery with which one is
    courted is mischievous; the countenance which every one wears towards you is friendly; the
    disposition of numbers is hostile; dislikes are secret; caresses are open; they wait with
    eagerness for the coming praetors, they fawn on those who are present, they abandon and betray
    those who are departing. But let us give over complaining, lest we should seem to be extolling
    our own wisdom in declining all provinces. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>He sent letters about the steward of Publius Septimius, a man of great accomplishments, which
    steward had committed murder. You might have seen Septimius burning with anger. He allowed (in
    accordance with his edict) an action against a freedman of Lurco to proceed. Lurco is his enemy.
    What then? Was Asia to be abandoned to the freedmen of influential and powerful men? or has
    Flaccus any personal hostility of any sort with your freedmen? or do you hate his severity when
    displayed in your own causes, and in those of your freedmen, though you praise impartiality when
    it is we who are on our trial? <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But that man Andro, who was stripped of all his property, as you say, has not come forward to
    give his evidence. What if he had? Suppose he had come. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89" resp="perseus"><p> Caius
    Caecilius was the arbitrator of the settlement come to in that case. How noble, how upright, how
    conscientious a man! Caius Sextilius was a witness to it, the son of Lurco's sister—a modest,
    and consistent, and sensible man. If there was any violence employed in the business, any fraud,
    any fear, any trickery, still who compelled any arrangement to be made at all? who compelled the
    parties to have recourse to an arbitrator? What will you say, if all that money was restored to
    this young man by Lucius Flaccus? if it was claimed by him? if it was collected for him? and if
    this was done through the agency of this Antiochus who is here in court the freedman of this
    youth's father, and a man most highly esteemed by the elder Flaccus? Do we not then seem not
    only to escape from the charge of covetousness, but even to deserve the credit of very
    extraordinary liberality? For he gave up to the young man his relation the whole of their joint
    inheritance, which by law ought to have belonged to both of them in equal shares; and he himself
    touched none of Valeria's property. What he had resolved to do, being influenced by the young
    man's amiable character, and not by the great amount of his patrimony, that he not only did, but
    did most liberally and courteously. From which it ought to be understood that he had not taken
    the money in violation of the laws, when he was so very liberal in abandoning the inheritance.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But the charge respecting Falcidius is a serious one. He says that he gave fifty talents to
    Flaccus. Let us hear the man himself. He is not here. How then does he say it? His mother
    produces one letter, and his sister produces a second; and they say that he had written to them
    to say that he had given this large sum to Flaccus. Therefore he, whom, if he were to swear
    while holding by the altar, no one would believe, is to be allowed to prove whatever he pleases
    by a letter without being put on his oath at all! And what a man he is! how unfriendly to his
    fellow-citizens; a man who preferred squandering a sufficiently ample patrimony, which he might
    have spent among us here, in Grecian banquets! </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91" resp="perseus"><p> What was his
    object in leaving this city? in depriving himself of the glorious liberty existing here? in
    undergoing all the danger of a voyage? just as if he might not have devoured his property here
    at Rome. Now at last this jolly son writes to <pb n="464"/> his mother, an old woman not very
    likely to suspect him, and clears himself by a letter, in order to appear not to have spent all
    that money with which he had crossed the sea, but to have given it to Flaccus. <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But those crops of the Trallians had been sold when Globulus was praetor. Falcidius had bought
    them for nine hundred thousand sesterces. If he gives so much money to Flaccus, he assuredly
    gives it to secure the ratification of that purchase. He then buys something which certainly was
    worth a great deal more than he gave for it; he pays for it out of his profit; he never touches
    his capital. Therefore he makes the less profit. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92" resp="perseus"><p> Why does he
    order his Alban farm to be sold? Why, besides, does he caress his mother in this way? Why does
    he try to overreach the imbecility of his sister and mother by letters? Lastly, why do we not
    hear the man's own statement? He is detained, I suppose, in the province. His mother says he is
    not. “He would have come,” says the prosecutor, “if he had been summoned.” You certainly would
    have compelled him to come, if you had thought your statement would receive any real
    confirmation from his appearing as a witness. But you were unwilling to take the man away from
    his business. There was an arduous contest before him; a very severe battle with the Greeks;
    who, however, as I think, are defeated and overthrown. For he by himself beat all Asia in the
    size of his cups, and in his power of drinking. But still, who was it, O Laelius, who gave you
    information about those letters? The women say that they do not know. Who is it then? Did the
    man himself tell you that he had written to his sister and mother? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93" resp="perseus"><p> or did he write at your entreaty? But do you put no questions to Marcus
    Aebutius, a most sensible and virtuous man, a relation of Falcidius? Do you decline to examine
    Caius Manilius his son-in-law, a man of equal integrity? men who certainly must have heard
    something of so large a sum of money, if it had been given. Did you, O Decianus, think that you
    were going to prove so heavy a charge, by reading these letters, and bringing forward these
    women, while the author whom you were quoting was kept at a distance? Especially when you
    yourself, by not producing Falcidius, declared your own opinion that a forged letter would have
    more weight than the feigned voice and simulated indignation of the man himself if present.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But why keep on so long discussing and expostulating about the letters of Falcidius, or about
    Andron Sextilius, or about the income of Decianus, and say nothing about the safety of fortunes
    of the state, and the general interests of the republic? the whole of which are at stake in this
    trial, and are resting on your shoulders,—on yours, I say, you who are our judges. You see in
    what critical times, in what uncertain and variable circumstances, we are all at present placed.
     <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>There are certain men who are planning many other things, and who are labouring most
    especially to cause your inclinations, your formal decisions and sentences to appear in a most
    unfavourable and odious light to all the most respectable citizen. You have given many important
    decisions in a manner suited to the dignity of the republic and particularly you have given many
    respecting the guilt of the conspirators. They do not think that the republic has been turned
    upside down enough unless they can overwhelm citizens who have deserved well of the republic
    with the same punishment as that with which this impious man Caius Antonius has been crushed.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95" resp="perseus"><p> Be it so. He had some particular misdeeds of his own to bear
    up against. And yet even he (I say this on my own responsibility) would never have been
    condemned if you had been his judges, he, a man by whose condemnation the tomb of Catiline was
    decked with flowers and the sepulchres of all those most audacious men and domestic enemies were
    honoured with assemblies and banquets, and by which the shade of Catiline was appeased. Now an
    expiation for the death of Lentulus is sought to be obtained at Flaccus's expense, and by your
    instrumentality. What victim can you offer more acceptable to the manes of Publius Lentulus,—who
    intended, after you had been all murdered amid the embraces of your children and your wives, to
    bury you beneath the burning ruins of your country,—than you will offer, if you satiate his
    impious hatred towards all of us in the blood of Lucius Flaccus? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96" resp="perseus"><p> Let us then offer a sacrifice to Lentulus, let us make atonement to Cethegus,
    let us recall the exiles, let us in our turn, if you, O judges, think fit, suffer the punishment
    due to too great piety, and to the greatest possible affection towards our country. At this
    moment we are being mentioned by name by the informers; accusations are being invented against
    us; dangers are being prepared for us. And if they did these things by the instrumentality of
    others,—if, in short, by using the name of the people, they had excited a mob of ignorant
    citizens, we could bear it with more equanimity. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>But this can never be borne, that they should think that, by means of senators and knights of
    Rome, who have done all these things with a view to the safety of all the citizens, by their
    common decision, animated with one idea, and inspired with one and the same virtue, the prime
    movers, and leaders, and chief actors in these transactions, can be deprived of all their
    fortunes, and be expelled from the city. In truth, they are acquainted with the feelings and
    inclinations of the Roman people; by every means which it is master of, the Roman people
    indicates what are its opinions and feelings; there is no diversity of opinion, or of
    inclination, or of language. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97" resp="perseus"><p> Wherefore, if any one summons
    me, I come. I not only do not object to the Roman people as arbitrators in my cause, but I even
    demand them. Let there be no violence; let weapons and stones be kept at a distance let the
    artisans depart; let the slaves be silent. No one who hears me will be so unjust, if he be only
    a free man and a citizen, as not to think that he ought rather to think of rewards for me than
    of punishment. <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>O ye immortal got! what can be more miserable than this? We who wrested fire and sword out of
    the hands of Publius Lentulus, are trusting now to the judgment of an ignorant multitude, and
    are in dread of the sentence of chosen men and most honourable citizens. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98" resp="perseus"><p> Our fathers by their decision delivered Marcus Aquillius, who had been
    convicted of many charges of avarice, proved by abundant evidence, because he had behaved
    gallantly in the Servile war. I, when consul, lately defended Cnaeus Piso; who, because he had
    been a gallant and fearless consul, was preserved to the republic uninjured. I, when consul,
    defended also Lucius Murena, the consul elect. Not one of the judges in that case—though they
    were most eminent men who were the prosecutors—thought that they ought to entertain for one
    moment the accusation of bribery, because, while Catiline was still waging war against the
    republic, they agreed with me that it was necessary for them to have two consuls on the first of
    January. Aulus Thermius, an innocent and virtuous man, and one adorned with every sort of
    distinction, has been twice acquitted this year, when I have defended him. How great was the
    joy, how great were the congratulations of the Roman people at that event, for the sake of the
    republic! Wise and grave judges have always, when deciding in criminal trials, considered what
    the interests of the state, and the general safety, and the present necessities of the republic
    required. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99" resp="perseus"><p> When the voting tablets are given to you, O judges,
    it will not be Flaccus alone who will be interested in their verdict; the generals and all those
    who are leaders in the preservation of the city will all be interested; all good men will be
    interested; you yourselves will be interested; your children, your own lives, your country, the
    general safety, will all be interested in your vote. In this cause you are not determining about
    foreign nations, or about the allies; you are deciding on the welfare of your own selves and
    your own republic. </p></div><milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="100" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And if the consideration of the provinces has more weight with you than that of your own
    interests, I not only do not object, but I even demand that you should be influenced by the
    authority of the provinces. In truth, we will oppose to the province of Asia first of all a
    great part of the same province, which has sent deputies and panegyrists to stand up and defend
    this man from danger; in the next place we will set against it the province of Gaul, the
    province of Cilicia, the province of Spain, and the province of Crete; and against Greeks,
    whether they be Lydians, Mysians, or Phrygians, shall be set the men of Massilia, the Rhodians,
    the Lacedaemonians, the Athenians, and all Achaia, Thessaly, and Boeotia. Septimius and Caelius,
    the witnesses for them, shall be balanced by Publius Servilius and Quintus Metellus, as
    witnesses of this man's moderation and integrity. The Asiatic jurisdiction shall be replied to
    by the jurisdiction of the city; and the whole conduct and entire life of Lucius Flaccus shall
    defend him from accusations brought against him, all relying on the transactions of a single
    year.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="101" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And if, O judges, it ought to avail Lucius Flaccus that, as
    tribune of the soldiers, as quaestor, as lieutenant to the most illustrious generals, he has
    behaved among the most distinguished armies, and in the most important provinces, in a manner
    worthy of his ancestors; let it also avail him, that before your own eyes, at a time of general
    danger to you all, he united his fate to mine, and shared my danger; let the panegyrics of most
    honourable municipalities and colonies avail him; let the most glorious and genuine praise of
    the Roman senate and Roman people avail him. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="102" resp="perseus"><p>
    <pb n="468"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Oh that night, that night which nearly brought eternal darkness on this city, when the Gauls
    were invited to war, when Catiline was invited into the city, when the conspirators were invited
    to bring fire and sword upon us all; when I, O Flaccus, invoking heaven and night, was with
    tears entreating your aid, and you in tears were listening to me; when I commended to your
    honest and well-proved loyalty the safety of the city and of the citizens. You, O Flaccus, being
    at that time praetor, took the messengers of the general destruction; it was you who arrested
    that plague <note anchored="true">He refers to the ambassadors of the Allobroges, and to the
     letters from Lentulus, etc., which were found in their possession. See the Arguments to the
     Catilinarian orations.</note> of the republic which was contained in letters;
      you brought the proofs of our danger, you brought the aid that was to secure our safety to me
      and to the senate. What thanks were then given you by me! how did the senate, how did all good
      men thank you! Who would then have thought that any good man would ever refuse to Caius
      Pomptinus, that bravest of men, or to you, I will not say safety, but any imaginable honour?
      Oh those nones of December; what a time was that when I was consul! a day that I may fairly
      call the birthday of this city, or at all events its day of salvation. </p></div><milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="103" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/>Oh that night which that day followed!
       happy was it for this city; but, wretched man that I am, I fear it may still prove disastrous
       to me myself. What spirit was then shown by Lucius Flaccus! (for I will say nothing about
       myself,) what devotion to his country, what virtue, what firmness! But why do I speak of
       those things which then, at the time that they happened, were extolled to the skies by the
       cordial agreement of all men, by the unanimous voice of the Roman people, by the testimony in
       their favour of the whole world? Now I fear, not only that they may be no advantage to my
       client, but that they may even be some injury to him. Indeed, I sometimes fancy that the
       memory of bad men is much more lively than that of good men. It is I, if any disaster happens
       to you, O Flaccus, it is I who shall have betrayed you; it is that pledge of mine which will
       be in fault, that promise of mine, that undertaking of mine, when I promised, that if we by
       our joint efforts could preserve the republic, you, as long as you lived, should not only be
       defended, but also honoured by the espousal of your cause by all virtuous men. I did think, O
       judges, I did hope that, even if our honour appeared to you a consideration of no importance
       at all events you would take care of our safety. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="104" resp="perseus"><p> But if,
       O judges, this terrible injury should overwhelm Lucius Flaccus (may the immortal gods avert
       the omen!) still he will never repent of having provided for your safety, of having consulted
       the interests of you, and of your wives, and of your children, and your entire welfare. It
       will always be his feeling that he owed such sentiments to the nobleness of his race, and to
       his religion, and to his country; you, O judges, take care that you have no cause to repent
       of not having spared such a citizen. For how few are they who adopt these principles in the
       republic; who desire only to please you and men like you; who think the authority of every
       virtuous and honourable man and body of men of the greatest weight, seeing that that path is
       both the one which leads most easily to honours and everything which they desire. <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="para"/>But let everything else belong to our adversaries: let them
       keep to themselves power, and honours, and all the best opportunities of attaining all other
       advantages let it be allowed to those men who have striven to preserve all these things, to
       be at least safe themselves. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="105" resp="perseus"><p> Do not think, O judges, that
       they, who are now starting fresh who have not as yet arrived at honours, are not looking
       anxiously for the result of this trial. If the exceeding affection of Lucius Flaccus for all
       good men, and his great devotion to the republic turns out an injury to him, who do you
       expect will in future be so insane, as not to think that path of life which he has hitherto
       been accustomed to consider slippery and dangerous preferable to this level and steady one?
       But if you, O judges, are tired of such citizens declare it; those who can will change their
       opinions, those who have their path still to choose will soon make up their minds what to do
       we who have advanced as far as we have must bear this result of our rashness. If you wish as
       many as possible to be of this opinion, you will declare by this decision what your
       sentiments are. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="106" resp="perseus"><p> By your decision in this case, O judges,
       you will give this unhappy suppliant to you and to your children—precepts by which to
       regulate his life. If you preserve his father to him, you will prescribe to him what sort of
       citizen he himself ought to be. If you take his father from him, you will show that there is
       no reward held out by you to virtuous and wise and consistent conduct. And he now, (since he
       is of that age that he is able to feel for his father's agony, but not yet to be any
       assistance to his father in his dangers,) he, I say, entreats you not to add his father's
       tears to his sorrow, or his weeping to his father's misery. He fixes his eyes on me also, he
       implores me by his looks, he, as I may say, appeals to my good faith, and claims of me that
       honour for his father which I once promised him in return for the safety of his country. Pity
       his family, O judges; pity that most gallant father; pity the son: preserve to the republic
       that most noble and glorious name, either for the sake of the blood, or of the antiquity of
       the family, or else for the sake of the individual.</p></div>
  </div>
 </body></text>

</TEI>
