<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>In Defense of L. Murena</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--<encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>-->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-04-20" who="Lisa Cerrato">Minor edits and review of CTS and EpiDoc work.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-15" who="Zach Himes">Converted section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi014.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
    
   <head>THE ORATION OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF L. MURENA, PROSECUTED FOR BRIBERY.</head>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">   
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>Lucius Murena was one of the consuls elect; the other being Silanus, the brother-in-law of
    Cato. Cato, however, instigated Sulpicius, one of the most eminent lawyers in Rome, and a
    defeated competitor for the consulship, to prosecute Murena for bribery, under the new law
    passed by Cicero, (mentioned in the argument to the first oration against Catiline,) though he
    brought no charge against Silanus, who was as guilty as Murena, if there was any guilt at all.
    Murena had served as lieutenant to Lucullus in the Mithridatic war. Murena was defended by
    Crassus, Hortensius, and Cicero. We have neither of the speeches of his other advocates; and
    even the speech of Cicero is not in a perfect state. Murena was unanimously acquitted, partly
    perhaps from consideration of the argument which Cicero dwelt upon very earnestly, of what
    great importance it was, at such a perilous time, (for this oration was spoken in the interval
    between the flight of Catiline to the camp of Manlius, and the final detection and condemnation
    of the conspirators who remained behind,) to have a consul of tried bravery and military
    experience. It is remarkable that Sulpicius, the prosecutor, was a most intimate friend of
    Cicero, who had exerted all his influence to procure his election in this very contest for the
    consulship; and so also was Cato; nor did the opposition which Cicero made to them in this case
    cause any interruption to their intimacy, and we shall find, in the Philippics, Cicero exerting
    himself to procure public funeral honours for Sulpicius.</p></div>
   
 
   <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   What I entreated of the immortal gods, O judges, according to the manners and institutions of
    our ancestors, on that day when, after taking the auspices in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia
     centuriata</foreign>, <note anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia
      centuriata</foreign>, or as they were sometimes called <foreign xml:lang="lat">majora</foreign>, were the assembly in which the people gave their votes according to the
     classification instituted by Servius Tullius; they were held in the Campus Martius without the
     city, and in reference to their military organization they were summoned by the sound of the
     horn, not by the voice of the lictor. All magistrates were elected in these <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>.</note> I declared Lucius Murena to have been elected
    consul,—namely, that that fact might turn out gloriously and happily for me and for my office,
    and for the Roman nation and people,—that same thing do I now pray for from the same immortal
    gods, that the consulship may be obtained by that same man with safety, and that your
    inclinations and opinions may agree with the wishes and suffrages of the Roman people, and that
    that fact may bring to you and to the Roman people peace, tranquillity, ease, and unanimity. And
    if that solemn prayer of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>, consecrated under the
    auspices of the consul, has as much power and holy influence as the dignity of the republic
    requires, I pray also that the matter may turn out happily, fortunately, and prosperously to
    those men to whom the consulship was given when I presided over the election. </p></div>
   
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>
And as this is the case, O judges, and as all the power of the immortal gods is either
    transferred to, or at all events is shared with you, the same consul recommends him now to your
    good faith who before recommended him to the immortal gods; so that he being both declared
    consul and being defended by the voice of the same man, may uphold the kindness of the Roman
    people to your safety and that of all the citizens. And since in this duty which I have
    undertaken the zeal of my defence has been found fault with by the accusers, and even the very
    fact of my having undertaken the cause at all, before I begin to say anything of Lucius Murena,
    I will say a few words on behalf of myself; not because at this time the defence of my duty
    seems to me more important than that of his safety, but in order that, when what I have done is
    approved of by you, I may be able with the greater authority to repel the attacks of his enemies
    upon his honour, his reputation, and all his fortunes. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
   And first of all I will answer Marcus Cato a man who directs his life by a certain rule and
    system and who most carefully weighs the motives of every duty about my own duty. Cato says it
    is not right that I who have been consul and the very passer <note anchored="true">There had
     been several previous laws against bribery and corruption (<foreign xml:lang="lat">de
      ambitu</foreign>). The <foreign xml:lang="lat">Lex Acilia</foreign>, passed B.C. <date when="-0067">67</date>, imposed a fine on the offending party, with exclusion from the senate
     and from all public offices. The <foreign xml:lang="lat">Lex Tullia</foreign>, passed in
     Cicero's consulship, added banishment for ten years; and, among other restrictions, forbade any
     one to exhibit gladiators within two years of his being a candidate, unless he was required to
     do so on a fixed day by a testator's will.</note> of the law of bribery and corruption and who
    behaved so rigorously in my own consulship should take up the cause of Lucius Murena and his
    reproach has great weight with me and makes me desirous to make not only <pb n="332"/> you, O
    judges, whom I am especially bound to satisfy, but also Cato himself, a most worthy and upright
    man, approve the reasons of my action. By whom then, O Marcus Cato, is it more just that a
    consul should be defended than by a consul? Who can there be, who ought there to be, dearer to
    me in the republic, than he to whom the republic which has been supported by my great labours
    and dangers is delivered by me alone to be supported for the future? For if, in the demanding
    back things which may be alienated, he ought to incur the hazard of the trial who has bound
    himself by a legal obligation, surely still more rightly in the trial of a consul elect, that
    consul who has declared him consul ought most especially to be the first mover of the kindness
    of the Roman people, and his defender from danger. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> And if, as is accustomed to be done in some states, an
    advocate were appointed to this cause by the public, that man would above all others be assigned
    to one invested with honours as his defender, who having himself enjoyed the same honour,
    brought to his advocacy no less authority than ability. But if those who are being wafted from
    the main into harbour are wont with the greatest care to inform those who are sailing out of
    harbour, of the character of storms, and pirates, and of places, because nature prompts us to
    favour those who are entering on the same dangers which we have passed through, of what
    disposition ought I to be, who after having been much tossed about am now almost in sight of
    land, towards him by whom I see the greatest tempests of the republic about to be encountered?
    Wherefore, if it is the part of a virtuous consul not only to see what is being done, but to
    foresee what is likely to happen, I will show in another place how much it is for the interest
    of the common safety that there should be two consuls in the republic on the first of January.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> And if that be the case, then it is not so much my duty which
    ought to summon me to defend the fortunes of a man who is my friend, as the republic which ought
    to invite the consul to the defence of the common safety. 
    <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
   For as to my having passed a law concerning bribery and corruption, certainly I passed it so
    as not to abrogate that law which I have long since made for myself concerning defending my
    fellow-citizens from dangers. If, indeed, I confessed that a largess had been distributed, and
    were to defend it as having been rightly done, I should be acting wrongly, even if another had
    passed the law; but when I am saving in defence that nothing has been done contrary to law; then
    what reason is there that my having passed the law should he an obstacle to my undertaking the
    defence? </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>
   
  He says that it does not belong to the same severity of character, to have banished from the
    city by words, and almost by express command, Catiline, when planning the destruction of the
    republic within its very walls, and now to speak on behalf of Lucius Murena. But I have always
    willingly acted the part of lenity and clemency which nature itself has taught me but I have not
    sought the character of severity and rigour, but I have supported it when imposed upon me by the
    republic as the dignity of this empire required at the time of the greatest peril to the
    citizens. But if then, when the public required vigour and severity, I overcame my nature, and
    was as severe as I was forced to be not as I wished to be; now, when all causes invite me to
    mercy and humanity, with what great zeal ought I to obey my nature and my usual habits? and
    concerning my duty of defending, and your method of prosecuting, perhaps I shall have again to
    speak in another part of my speech. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
     But, O judges, the complaint of Servius Sulpicius, a most wise and accomplished man, moved me
    no less than the accusation of Cato; for he said that he was exceedingly and most bitterly vexed
    that I had forgotten my friendship and intimacy with him, and was defending the cause of Lucius
    Murena against him. I wish, O judges, to satisfy him, and to make you arbitrators between us.
    For as it is a sad thing to be accused with truth in a case of friendship, so, even if you be
    falsely accused, it is not to be neglected. I, O Servius Sulpicius, both allow that according to
    my intimacy with you I did owe you all my zeal and activity to assist you in your canvass, and I
    think I displayed it when you stood for the consulship, nothing on my part was wanting to you
    which could have been expected either from a friend, or from an obliging person, or from a
    consul. That time has gone by,—the case is changed. I think, and am persuaded, that I owed you
    as much aid as ever you have ventured to require of me against the advancement of Lucius Murena
    but no aid at all against his safety. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> Nor does it follow,
    because I stood by you when you were a candidate for the consulship, that on that account I
    ought now to be an assistant to you in the same <pb n="334"/> way, when you are attacking Murena
    himself. And this it not only not praiseworthy,—it is not even allowable, that we may not defend
    even those who are most entirely strangers to us when our friends accuse them. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
  But in truth, there is, O judges, between Murena and myself an ancient and great friendship,
    which shall not be overwhelmed in a capital trial by Servius Sulpicius, merely because it was
    overcome by superior considerations when he was contesting an honorable office with that same
    person. And if this cause had not existed, yet the dignity of the man, and the honourable nature
    of that office which he has obtained, would have branded me with the deepest reproach of pride
    and cruelty, if in so great a danger I had repudiated the cause of a man so distinguished by his
    own virtues and by the honours paid him by the Roman people. For it is not now in my power,—it
    is not possible, for me to shrink from devoting my labour to alleviate the dangers of others.
    For when such rewards have been given me for this diligence of mine, such as before now have
    never been given to any one, to abandon those labours by which I have earned them, as soon as I
    have received them, would be the act of a crafty and ungrateful man. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   If, indeed, I may rest from my labours,—if you advise me that I can do so,—if no reproach of
    indolence, none of unworthy arrogance, none of inhumanity is incurred by so doing, in good truth
    I will willingly rest. But if flying from toil convicts me of laziness,—if rejection of
    suppliants convicts me of arrogance,—if neglect of my friends is a proof of worthlessness, then,
    above all others, this cause is such an one as no industrious, or merciful, or obliging man can
    abandon. And you may easily form your opinion of this matter, O Servius, from your own pursuits.
    For if you think it necessary to give answers to even the adversaries of your friends when they
    consult you about law, and if you think it shameful, when you have been retained as an advocate
    for him in whose cause you have come forward, to fail; be not so unjust; as, when your springs
    are open even to your enemies, to think it right that our small streams should be closed even
    against our friends. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p>
Indeed, if my intimacy with you had prevented my appearing in this cause, and if the same
    thing had happened to Quintus Hortensius and Marcus Crassus, most honourable men, and to others
    also by whom I know that your affection is greatly esteemed, the consul elect would have had no
    defender in that city in which our ancestors intended that even the lowest of the people should
    never want an advocate. But I, O judges, should think myself wicked if I had failed my
    friend,—cruel if I had failed one in distress,—arrogant if I had failed the consul. So that what
    ought to be given to friendship shall be abundantly given by me, so that I will deal with you, O
    Servius, as if my brother, who is the dearest of all men to me, stood in your place. What ought
    to be given to duty, to good faith, to religion, that I will so regulate as to recollect that I
    am speaking contrary to the wish of one friend to defend another friend from danger. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>
   I understand, O judges, that this whole accusation is divided into three parts, and that one
    of them refers to find my fault with Murena's habits of life, another to his contest for the
    dignity, and a third to charges of bribery and corruption. And of these three divisions, that
    first which ought to have been the weightiest of all, was so weak and trifling, that it was
    rather some general rule of accusing, than any real occasion for finding fault, which prompted
    them to say anything about the way of life of Lucius Murena. For Asia has been mentioned as a
    reproach to him, which was not sought by him for the sake of pleasure and luxury, but was
    traversed by him in the performance of military labours; but if he while a young man had not
    served under his father when general, he would have seemed either to have been afraid of the
    enemy, or of the command of his father, or else to have been repudiated by his father. Shall we
    say that, when all the sons who wear the <foreign xml:lang="lat">praetexta</foreign>
    <note anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="lat">toga praetexta</foreign> was a robe bordered
     with purple worn by the higher magistrates, and by freeborn children till they arrived at the
     age of manhood.</note> are accustomed to sit on the chariot of those who are celebrating a
    triumph, this man ought to have shunned adorning the triumph of his father with military gifts,
    so as almost to share his fathers triumph for exploits which they had performed in common?
     </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>
But this man, O judges, both was in Asia and was a great assistance to that bravest of men his
    own father in his dangers, a comfort to him in his labours a source of congratulation to him in
    his victory. And if Asia does carry with it a suspicion of luxury, surely it is a praiseworthy
    thing, <pb n="336"/> not never to have seen Asia, but to have lived temperately in Asia. So that
    the name of Asia should not have been objected to Lucius Murena, a country whence renown was
    derived for his family, lasting recollection for his race, honour and glory for his name, but
    some crime or disgrace, either incurred in Asia, or brought home from Asia. But to have served
    campaigns in that war which was not only the greatest, but the only war which the Roman people
    was waging at that time, is a proof of valour; to have served most willingly under his father,
    who was commander-in-chief, is a proof of piety; that the end of his campaign was the victory
    and triumph of his father, is a proof of good fortune. There is, therefore, no room in these
    matters for speaking ill of him, because praise takes up the whole room. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>
   Cato calls Lucius Murena a dancer. If this be imputed to him truly, it is the reproach of a
    violent accuser; but if falsely, it is the abuse of a scurrilous railer. Wherefore, as you are a
    person of such influence, you ought not, O Marcus Cato, to pick up abusive expressions out of
    the streets, or out of some quarrel of buffoons; you ought not rashly to call a consul of the
    Roman people a dancer; but to consider with what other vices besides that man must be tainted to
    whom that can with truth be imputed. For no man, one may almost say, ever dances when sober,
    unless perhaps he be a madman, nor in solitude, nor in a moderate and sober party; dancing is
    the last companion of prolonged feasting, of luxurious situation, and of many refinements. You
    charge me with that which must necessarily be the last of all vices, you say nothing of those
    things without which this vice absolutely cannot exist: no shameless feasting, no improper love,
    no carousing, no lust no extravagance is alleged; and when those things which have the name of
    pleasure, and which are vicious, are not found, do you think that you will find the shadow of
    luxury in that man in whom you cannot find the luxury itself? </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>
    Can nothing, therefore, be said against the life of Lucius Murena? Absolutely nothing, I say,
    O judges. The consul elect is defended by me on this ground, that no fraud of his, no avarice,
    no perfidy, no cruelty, no wanton word can be alleged against him in his whole life. It is well.
    The foundations of the defence are laid; for we are not as yet defending this virtuous and
    upright man with my own panegyric, which I will employ presently, but almost by the confession
    of his adversaries. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   And now that this is settled, the approach to the contest for this dignity, which was the
    second part of the accusation, is more easy to me.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> I see that there is in you, O Servius
    Sulpicius, the greatest dignity of birth, of integrity, of industry, and of all the other
    accomplishments which a man ought to rely on when he offers himself as a candidate for the
    consulship. I know that all those qualities are equal in Lucius Murena, and so equal that he can
    neither be surpassed in worth by you, nor can himself surpass you in worth. You have spoken
    slightingly of the family of Lucius Murena, you have extolled your own; but if you dwell on this
    topic so as to allow no one to be considered as born of a good family, unless he be a patrician,
    you will compel the common people again to secede to the Aventine Hill. <note anchored="true">This refers to the time of Appius the <foreign xml:lang="lat">decemvir</foreign>, when the
     soldiers, at the call of Virginius, after the death of Virginia, occupied the Aventine, and
     were joined by great part of the plebs, demanding the abolition of the decemvirate.</note> But
    if there are honourable and considerable families among the plebeians,—both the
    great-grandfather of Lucius Murena, and his grand-father, were praetors; and his father, when he
    had triumphed most splendidly and honourably for exploits performed in his praetorship, left the
    steps towards the acquisition of the consulship more easy, because that honour which was due to
    the father was demanded by the son. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p>
    But your nobility, O Servius Sulpicius, although it is most eminent yet it is known rather to
    men versed in literature and history, but not much so to the people and to the voters. For your
    father was in the rank of the knights, your grandfather was renowned for no conspicuous action.
    So that the recollection of your nobility is to be extracted not from the modern conversation of
    men, but from the antiquity of annals. So that I also am accustomed to class you in our number,
    because you by your own virtue and industry, though you are the son of a Roman knight, have yet
    earned the being considered worthy of the very highest advancement. Nor did it ever seem to me
    that there was less virtue in Quintus Pompeius, a new man and a most brave man, than in that
    most high-born man, Marcus Aemilius. Indeed, it is a proof of the same spirit and genius, to
    hand down to his <pb n="338"/> posterity, as Pompeius did, an honourable name, which he had not
    received from his ancestors; and, as Scaurus did, to renew the recollection of his family which
    was almost extinct. <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>
    Although I now thought, O judges, that it had been brought about by my labours, that a want of
    nobleness of birth should not be objected to many brave men, who were neglected, though men were
    praising not only the Curii, the Catos, the Pompeii, those ancient new but most distinguished
    men, but also, these more modern new men, the Marii, and Didii, and Coelii. But when I, after so
    great an interval, had broken down those barriers of nobility, so that entrance to the
    consulship should hereafter be opened, as it was in the time of I our ancestors, not more to
    high birth than to virtue, I did not think when a consul-elect of an ancient and illustrious
    family was being defended by the son of a Roman knight himself a consul, that the accusers would
    say anything about newness of family. In truth it happened to me myself to stand against two
    patricians, one a most worthless and audacious man, the other a most modest and virtuous one;
    yet I surpassed Catiline in worth, Galba in popularity. But if that ought to have been imputed
    as a crime to a new man, forsooth, I should have wanted neither enemies nor detractors.
     </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p>
    Let us, therefore, give up saying anything about birth, the dignity of which is great in both
    the candidates; let us look at the other points. He stood for the quaestorship at the same time
    with me, and I was appointed first. We need not answer every point; for it cannot escape the
    observation of any one of you, when many men are appointed equal in dignity, but only one can
    obtain the first place, that the order of the dignity and of the declaration of it are not the
    same, because the declaration has degrees, but the dignity of all is usually the same. But the
    quaestorship of each was, given them by almost an equal decision of the lots: the one had by the
    Titian law a quiet and orderly province; you had that, one of Ostia, at the name of which, when
    the quaestors distribute the provinces by lot, a shout, is raised,—a province not so much
    pleasant and illustrious as troublesome and vexatious. The name of each was together in the
    quaestorship. For the drawing of the lots gave you no field on which your virtue could display
    itself and make itself known. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> The remaining space of time is
    dedicated to the contest. It was employed by each in a very dissimilar fashion. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   Servius <pb n="339"/> adopted the civil service, full of anxiety and annoyance, of answering,
    writing, cautioning; he learned the civil law; he worked early and late, he toiled, he was
    visible to every one, he endured the folly of crowds, he tolerated their arrogance, he bore all
    sorts of difficulties, he lived at the will of others, not at his own. It is a great credit a
    thing pleasing to men, for one man to labour hard in that science which will profit many.
     </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    What has Murena been doing in the meantime? He was lieutenant to Lucius Lucullus, a very brave
    and wise man, and a consummate general; and in this post he commanded an army, he fought a
    battle, he engaged the enemy, he routed numerous forces of the enemy, he took several cities,
    some by storm, some by blockade. He traversed that populous and luxurious Asia you speak of; in
    such a manner as to leave in it no trace either of his avarice or of his luxury; in a most
    important war he so behaved himself that he performed many glorious exploits without the
    commander-in-chief; but the commander-in-chief did nothing without him. And all these things,
    although I am speaking in the presence of Lucius Lucullus, yet that we may not appear to have a
    licence of invention granted us by him on account of the danger we are in, we are borne witness
    to in the public despatches; in which Lucius Lucullus gives him such praise as no ambitious nor
    envious commander-in-chief could have given another while dividing with him the credit of his
    exploits. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>
There is in each of the rivals the greatest honesty, the greatest worth; which I, if Servius
    will allow me, will place in equal and in the same panegyric. But he will not let me; he
    discusses the military question; he attacks the whole of his services as lieutenant; he thinks
    the consulship is an office requiring diligence and all this daily labour. “Have you been,” says
    he, “so many years with the army? you can never have been near the forum. Have you been away so
    long? and then, when after a long interval you arrive, will you contend in dignity with those
    who have made their abode in the forum?” First of all, as to that assiduity of ours, O Servius,
    you know not what disgust, what satiety, it sometimes causes men; it was, indeed, exceedingly
    advantageous for me myself that my influence was in the sight of all men; but I overcame the
    weariness of me by my own great labour; and you, perhaps, have done the same thing, but yet a
    regret at our absence would have been no injury to either of us. <pb n="340"/>
    </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
But to say no more of this, and to return to the contest of studies and pursuits; how can it
    be doubted that the glory of military exploits contributes more dignity to aid in the
    acquisition of the consulship, than renown for skill in civil law? Do you wake before the night
    is over in order to give answers to those who consult you? He has done so in order to arrive
    betimes with his army at the place to which he is marching. The cook-crow wakens you, but the
    sound of the trumpet rouses him: you conduct an action; he is marshaling an army: you take care
    lest your clients should be convicted; he lest his cities or camp be taken. He occupies posts,
    and exercises skill to repel the troops of the enemy, you to keep out the rain; he is practised
    in extending the boundaries of the empire, you in governing the present territories; and in
    short, for I must say what I think, preeminence in military skill excels all other virtues.
     <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
   It is this which has procured its name for the Roman people; it is this which has procured
    eternal glory for this city; it is this which has compelled the whole world to submit to our
    dominion; all domestic affairs, all these illustrious pursuits of ours, and our forensic renown,
    and our industry, are safe under the guardianship and protection of military valour. As soon as
    the first suspicion of disturbance is heard of, in a moment our arts have not a word to say for
    themselves.</p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p> And since you seem to me to embrace that knowledge of the
    law which you have, as if it were a darling daughter, I will not permit you to lie, under such a
    mistake as to think that whatever it may be, which you have so thoroughly learnt anything very
    preeminent. For your other virtues of continence, of gravity, of justice, of good faith, and all
    other good qualities, I have always considered you very worthy of the consulship and of all
    honour; but as for your having learnt civil law, I will not say you have wasted your pains, but
    I will say that there is no way made to lead to the consulship by that profession; for all arts
    which can conciliate for us the good-will of the Roman people ought to possess both an admirable
    dignity, and a very delightful utility. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>
  The highest dignity is in those men who excel in military glory. For all things which are in
    the empire and in the constitution of the state, are supposed to be defended and strengthened by
    them. There is also the greatest usefulness in them, since it is by their wisdom and their
    danger that we can enjoy both the republic and also our own private possessions. The power of
    eloquence also is no doubt valuable and full of dignity, and it has often been of influence in
    the election of a consul to be able by wisdom and oratory to sway the minds of the senate and
    the people, and those who decide on affair. A consul is required who may be able sometimes to
    repress the madness of the tribunes, who may be able to bend the excited populace, who may
    resist corruption. It is not strange, if, on account of this faculty, even men who were not
    nobly born have often obtained the consulship; especially when this same quality procures a man
    great gratitude, and the firmest friendship, and the greatest zeal in his behalf; but! of all
    this there is nothing, O Sulpicius, in your profession. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p>
   First of all, what dignity can there be in so limited a science? For they are but small
    matters, conversant chiefly about single letters and punctuation between words. Secondly, if in
    the time of our ancestors there was any inclination to marvel at that study of yours, now that
    all your mysteries are revealed, it is wholly despised and disregarded. At one time few men knew
    whether a thing might be lawfully done or not; for men ordinarily had no records; those were
    possessed of great power who were consulted, so that even days for consultation were begged of
    them beforehand, as from the Chaldean astrologers. A certain notary was found, by name Cnaeus
    Flavius, who could deceive <note anchored="true">The Latin strictly is, “pierce the eyes of
     ravens.” It was a proverbial expression.</note> the most wary, and who set the people records
    to be learnt by heart each day, and who pilfered their own learning from the profoundest
    lawyers. So they, being angry because they were afraid, lest, when their daily course of action
    was divulged and understood, people would be able to proceed by law without their assistance,
    adopted a sort of cipher, in order to make their presence necessary in every cause. <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>
   When this might have been well transacted thus—“The Sabine farm is mine.” “No; it is
    mine:”—then a trial; they would not have it so. “The farm,” says he, “which is in the territory
    which is called Sabine:”—verbose enough—well, what next? “That farm, I say, is mine according to
    the rights of Roman citizens.” What then?—“and <pb n="342"/> therefore I summon you according to
    law, seizing you by the hand.”
   <milestone unit="para"/>The man of whom the field was demanded did not know how to answer one who was so talkatively
    litigious. The same lawyer goes across, like a Latin flute-player,—says he, “In the place from
    whence you summoned me having seized me by the hand, from thence I recall you there.” In the
    meantime, as to the praetor, lest he should think himself a fine fellow and a fortunate one, and
    himself say something of his own accord, a form of words is composed for him also, absurd in
    other points, and especially in this: “Each of them being alive and being present I say that
    that is the way.” “Enter on the way.” That wise man was at hand who was to show them the way.
    “Return on your path.” They returned with the same guide. These things, I may well suppose,
    appeared ridiculous to full-grown men; that men when they have stood rightly and in their proper
    place should be ordered to depart, in order that they might immediately return again to the
    place they had left. Everything was tainted with the same childish folly. “When I behold you in
    the power of the law.” And this—“But do you say this who claim the right?” And while all this
    was made a mystery of, they who had the key to the mystery were necessarily sought after by men;
    but as soon as these things were revealed, and were bandied about and sifted in men's hands,
    they were found to be thoroughly destitute of wisdom, but very full of fraud and folly.
     </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>
   For though many things have been excellently settled by the laws, yet most of them have been
    depraved and corrupted by the genius of the lawyers. Our ancestors determined that all women, on
    account of the inferiority of their understanding, should be under the protection of trustees.
    These men have found out classes of trustees, whose power is subordinate to that of the women.
    The one party did not wish the domestic sacrifices to be abolished in families; by the ingenuity
    of the others old men were found to marry by the form called <foreign xml:lang="lat">coemptio</foreign>, <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Coemptio</foreign> was “a
     ceremony of marriage consisting in a mock sale, whereby the bride and bridegroom sold
     themselves to each other.” Riddle in voce. “<foreign xml:lang="lat">Coemptio</foreign> was
     effected by <foreign xml:lang="lat">mancipatio</foreign>, and consequently the wife was in
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">mancipio</foreign>.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 603, § v., v.
      <title>Marriage</title>, (Roman.)</note> for the sake of' getting rid of these sacred
    ceremonies. Lastly, in every part of the civil law they neglected equity itself, but adhered to
    the letter of the law; as for instance, because in somebody's books they found the name of Caia,
    they thought that all the women who had married by <foreign xml:lang="lat">coemptio</foreign>
    were called Caias. And that often appears marvellous to me, that so many men of such ability
    should now for so many years have been unable to decide whether the proper expressions to use be
    the day after tomorrow or the third day, a judge or an arbiter, a cause or a proceeding.
     <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>
   Therefore, as I said before, the dignity of a consul has never been consistent with that
    science; being one consisting wholly of fictitious and imaginary formulas. And its right to
    public gratitude was even much smaller. For that which is open to every one, and which is
    equally accessible to me and to my adversary, cannot be considered as entitled to any gratitude.
    And therefore you have now, not only lost the hope of conferring a favour, but even the
    compliment that used to be paid to you by men asking your permission to consult you. No one can
    be considered wise on account of his proficiency in that knowledge which is neither of any use
    at all out of Rome, nor at Rome either during the vacations. Nor has any one any right to be
    considered skillful in law, because there cannot be any difference between men in a branch of
    knowledge with which they are all acquainted. And a matter is not thought the more difficult for
    being contained in a very small number of very intelligible documents. Therefore, if you excite
    my anger, though I am excessively busy, in three days I will profess myself a lawyer. In truth,
    all that need be said about the written law is contained in written books; nor is there anything
    written with such precise accuracy, that I cannot add to the formula, “which is the matter at
    present in dispute.” If you answer what you ought, you will seem to have made the same answer as
    Servius; if you make any other reply, you will seem to be acquainted with and to know how to
    handle disputed points. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>
   Wherefore, not only is the military glory which you slight to be preferred to your formulas
    and legal pleas; but even the habit of speaking is far superior, as regards the attainment of
    honours, to the profession to the practice of which you devote yourself. And therefore many men
    appear to me to have preferred this at first; but afterwards, being unable to attain eminence in
    this profession, they have descended to <pb n="344"/> the other. Just as men say, when talking
    of Greek practitioners, that those men are flute-players who cannot become harp-players, so we
    see some men, who have not been able to make orators, turn to the study of the law. There is
    great labour in the practice of oratory. It is an important business, one of great dignity, and
    of most exceeding influence. In truth, from you lawyers men seek some degree or advantage; but
    from those who are orators they seek actual safety. In the next place, your replies and your
    decisions are constantly overturned by eloquence, and cannot be made firm except by the advocacy
    of the orator; in which if I had made any great proficiency myself; I should be more sparing
    while speaking in its praise; but at present I am saying nothing about myself; but only about
    those men who either are or have been great in oratory. <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>
   There are two occupations which can place men in the highest rank of dignity; one, that of a
    general the other, that of an accomplished orator. For by the latter the ornaments of peace are
    preserved, by the former the dangers of war are repelled. But the other virtues are of great
    importance from their own intrinsic excellence, such as justice, good faith, modesty,
    temperance; and in these, O Servius, all men know that you are very eminent. But at present I am
    speaking of those pursuits calculated to aid men in the attainment of honours, and not about the
    intrinsic excellency of each pursuit. For all those occupations are dashed out of our hands at
    once, the moment the slightest new commotion begins to have a warlike sound. In truth, as an
    ingenious poet and a very admirable author says, the moment there is a mention of battle, “away
    is driven” not only your grandiloquent pretences to prudence, but even that mistress of all
    things, “wisdom. Everything is done by violence. The orator,” not only he who is troublesome in
    speaking, and garrulous, but even “the good orator is despised; the horrid soldier is loved.”
    But as for your profession, that is trampled under foot; “men seek their rights not by law, but
    hand to hand by the sword,” says he. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>And if that be the case, then I think, O Sulpicius, the forum must yield to the camp; peace
    must yield to war, the pen to the sword, and the shade to the sun. That in fact must be the
    first thing in the city, by means of which the city itself is the first of all cities.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p> But Cato is busy proving that we are making too much of all
    these things in our speech; and that we have forgotten that that Mithridatic war was carried on
    against nothing better than women. However, my opinion is very different, O judges; and I will
    say a little on that subject; for my cause does not depend on that. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>For if all the wars which we have carried on against the Greeks are to be despised, then let
    the triumph of Marcus Curius over king Pyrrhus be derided; and that of Titus Flamininus over
    Philip; and that of Marcus Fulvius over the Aetolians; and that of Lucius Paullus over king
    Perses; and that of Quintus Metellus over the false Philip; and that of Lucius Mummius over the
    Corinthians. But, if all these wars were of the greatest importance, and if our victories in
    them were most acceptable, then why are the Asiatic nations and that Asiatic enemy despised by
    you? But, from our records of ancient deeds; I see that the Roman people carried on a most
    important war with Antiochus; the conqueror in which war, Lucius Scipio, who had already gained
    great glory when acting in conjunction with his brother Publius, assumed the same honour himself
    by taking a surname from Asia, as his brother did, who, having subdued Africa, paraded his
    conquest by the assumption of the name of Africanus. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p> And in
    that war the renown of your ancestor Marcus Cato was very conspicuous; but he, if he was, as I
    make no doubt that he was, a man of the same character as I see that you are, would never have
    gone to that war, if he had thought that it was only going to be a war against women. Nor would
    the senate have prevailed on Publius Africanus to go as lieutenant to his brother, when he
    himself; a little while before, having forced Hannibal out of Italy, having driven him out of
    Africa, and having crushed the power of Carthage, had delivered the republic from the greatest
    dangers, if that war had not been considered an important and formidable war. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
    But if you diligently consider what the power of Mithridates was, and what his exploits were,
    and what sort or a man he was himself; you will in truth prefer this king to all the kings with
    whom the Roman people has ever waged war;—a man whom Lucius Sulla,—not a very inexperienced
    general, to say the least of it—at the head of a numerous and powerful army, after a severe
    battle, allowed to depart having made peace with him, though he had overrun all Asia with war:
    whom Lucius Murena, my client's father, after having <pb n="346"/> warred against him with the
    greatest vigour and vigilance, left greatly checked indeed, but not overwhelmed: a king, who,
    having taken several years to perfect his system and to strengthen his warlike resources, became
    so powerful and enterprising that he thought himself able to unite the Atlantic to the Black
    Sea, and to combine the forces of Sertorius with his own. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p> And
    when two consuls had been sent to that war, with the view of one pursuing Mithridates, and the
    other protecting Bithynia, the disasters which befell one of them by land and sea greatly
    increased the power and reputation of the king. But the exploits of Lucius Lucullus were such
    that it is impossible to mention any war which was more important, or in which greater abilities
    and valour were displayed. For when the violence of the entire war had broken against the walls
    of Cyzicus, and as Mithridates thought that he should find that city the door of Asia, and that
    if that were once broken down and forced, the whole province would be open to him, everything
    was so managed by Lucullus that the city of our most faithful allies was defended, and all the
    forces of the king were wasted away by the length of the siege, what more need I say? Do you
    think that that naval battle at Tenedos, when the enemy's fleet were hastening on with rapid
    course and under most eager admirals towards Italy, full of hope and courage, was a trifling
    engagement—an insignificant contest? I will say nothing of battles; I pass over the sieges of
    towns. Being at length expelled from his kingdom, still his wisdom and his influence were so
    great that combining his forces with those of the king of Armenia, he reappeared with new armies
    and new resources of every kind. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
   And if it wore my business now to speak of the achievements of our army and of our general, I
    might mention many most important battles. But that is not the present question. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p> This I do say:—If this war, and this enemy,—if that king was a proper
    object for contempt the senate and Roman people would not have thought it one to be undertaken
    with such care, nor would they have carried it on for so many years, nor would the glory of
    Lucullus be as great as it is. Nor would the Roman people have entrusted the care of putting a
    finishing stroke to it to Cnaeus Pompeius; though of all his battles, numberless as they are,
    that appears to me to have been the most desperate and to have been maintained on both sides
    with the greatest vigour, which he fought against the king. And when Mithridates had escaped
    from that battle, and had fled to the Bosphorus, a place which no army could approach, still,
    even in the extremity of his fortunes, and as a fugitive, he retained the name of a king.
    Therefore, Pompeius himself; having taken possession of his kingdom, having driven the enemy
    away from all his coasts, and from all his usual places of resort still thought that so much
    depended on his single life, that though, by his victory, he had got possession of everything
    which he had possessed, or had approached, or even had hoped for, still he did not think the war
    entirely over till he drove him from life also. And do you, O Cato, think lightly of this man as
    an enemy, when so many generals warred against him for so many years, with so long a series of
    battles? when, though driven out and expelled from his kingdom, his life was still thought of
    such importance, that it was not till the news arrived of his death, that we thought the war
    over? We then say in defence of Lucius Murena, that as a lieutenant in this war he approved
    himself a man of the greatest courage, of singular military skill, and of the greatest
    perseverance; and that all his conduct at that time gave him no less a title to obtain the
    consulship than this forensic industry of ours gave us. <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p>
   “But in the standing for the praetorship, Servius was elected first.” Are you going (as if you
    were arguing on some written bond) to contend with the people that whatever place of honour they
    have once given any one, that same rank they are bound to give him in all other honours? For
    what sea, what Euripus do you think exists, which is liable to such commotions,—to such great
    and various agitations of waves, as the storms and tides by which the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> are influenced? The interval of one day,—the lapse of one night—often throws
    everything into confusion. The slightest breeze of rumour sometimes changes the entire opinions
    of people. Often, even, everything is done without any apparent cause, in a manner entirely at
    variance with the opinions that have been expressed, or that indeed, are really entertained; so
    that sometimes the people marvels that that has been done which has been done, as if it were not
    itself that has done it. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p> Nothing is more uncertain than the
    common people,—nothing more obscure than men's wishes,—nothing more treacherous <pb n="348"/>
    than the whole nature of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>. Who expected that Lucius
    Philippus, a man of the greatest abilities, and industry, and popularity, and nobleness of
    birth, could be beaten by Marcus Herennius? who dreamt of Quintus Catulus, a man eminent for all
    the politer virtues, for wisdom and for integrity, being beaten by Cnaeus Mallius? or Marcus
    Scaurus, a man of the highest character, an illustrious citizen, a most intrepid senator, by
    Quintus Maximus? Not only none of all these things were expected to happen, but not even when
    they had happened could anyone possibly make out why they had happened. For as storms arise,
    often being heralded by some well-known token in the heavens, but often also quite unexpectedly
    from no imaginable reason, but from some unintelligible cause; so in the popular tempests of the
     <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> you may often understand by what signs a storm was
    first raised, but often, too, the cause is so obscure, that the tempest appears to have been
    raised by chance. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p>
   But yet if an account of them must be given, two qualities were particularly missed in the
    praetorship, the existence of which in Murena now was of the greatest use to him in standing for
    the consulship: one was the expectation of a largess, which had got abroad through some rumour,
    and owing to the zeal and conversation of some of his competitors; the other, that those men who
    had been witnesses of all his liberality and virtue in the province and in the discharge of his
    office as lieutenant, had not yet left Rome. Fortune reserved each of these advantages for him,
    to aid him in his application for the consulship. For the army of Lucius Lucullus, which had
    come hither for his triumph, was also present at the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> in
    aid of Lucius Murena, and his praetorship afforded a most splendid proof of his liberality, of
    which there was no mention when he was standing for the praetorship. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p> Do these things appear to you trifling supports and aids towards obtaining the
    consulship? Is the good-will of the soldiery a trifle? who are both intrinsically powerful
    through their own numbers, and also by their influence among their connections, and who in
    declaring a consul have great weight among the entire Roman people. Are the votes of the army a
    trifle? No; for it is generals, and not interpreters of words, who are elected at the consular
     <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>. Most influential, then, is such a speech as this—“He
    refreshed me when I was wounded. He gave me a share of the plunder. He was the general when we
    took that camp—when we fought that battle. He never imposed harder work on the soldier than he
    underwent himself. He was as fortunate as he is brave.” What weight do you not suppose this must
    have to gaining a reputation and good-will among men? Indeed, if there is a sort of superstition
    in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>, that up to this time the omen to be drawn from
    the vote of the prerogative <note anchored="true">In the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia
      centuriata</foreign> the people voted in their centuries; the order in which the centuries
     voted was decided by lot, and that which gave it a vote first was called the <foreign xml:lang="lat">centuria praerogativa</foreign>. The question of a <foreign xml:lang="lat">tribus
      praerogativa</foreign> is a more disputed point; but on this see Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 997, v.
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">Tribus</foreign>, (Roman.)</note> tribe has always proved true, what
    wonder is there that in such a meeting the reputation of good fortune and such discourse as this
    has had the greatest weight? <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
   But if you think these things trifling, though they are most important; and if you prefer the
    votes of these quiet citizens to those of the soldiers; at all events, you cannot think lightly
    of the beauty of the games exhibited by this man, and the magnificence of his theatrical
    spectacles; and these things were of great use to him in this last contest. For why need I tell
    you that the people and the great mass of ignorant men are exceedingly taken with games? It is
    not very strange. And that is a sufficient reason in this case; for the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> are the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> of the people and the
    multitude. If, then, the magnificence of games is a pleasure, to the people, it is no wonder
    that it was of great service to Lucius Murena with the people. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p> But if we ourselves, who, from our constant business, have but little time for amusement, and
    who are able to derive many pleasures of another sort from our business itself; are still
    pleased and interested by exhibitions of games, why should you marvel at the ignorant multitude
    being so? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p> Lucius Otho, <note anchored="true">This refers to
     the law of Lucius Roscius Otho, (called <foreign xml:lang="lat">Roscia Lex</foreign> by Horace,)
     by which the fourteen rows of seats next to those of the senators were reserved for the
     knights.</note> a brave man, and an intimate friend of mine, restored not only its dignity, but
    also its pleasure to the equestrian order; and, therefore, this law which relates to the games
    is the most acceptable of all laws, because by it that most honourable order of men is restored
    not only to its honours, but also to the enjoyment of its amusements. Games, then, believe me,
    are a great delight to men, even to those who are ashamed to own it, and not to <pb n="350"/>
    those only who confess it as I found to be the case in my contest for the consulship; for we
    also had a theatrical representation as our competitor. But if I who, as aedile, had exhibited
    those shows of games, was yet influenced by the games exhibited by Antonius, do you not suppose
    that that very silver stage exhibited by this man, which you laugh at was a serious rival to
    you, who, as it happened, had never given any games at all? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p>
    But in truth, let us allow that these advantages are all equal,—let exertions displayed in the
    forum be allowed to be equal to military achievements,—let the votes of the quiet citizens be
    granted to be of equal weight with those of the I soldiers,—let it be of equal assistance to a
    man to have I exhibited the most magnificent games, and never to have exhibited any at all; what
    then? Do you think that in the praetorship itself there was no difference between your lot and
    that of my client Murena? <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
   His department was that which we and all your friends desired for you; that namely, of
    deciding the law; a business in which the importance of the business transacted procures great
    credit for a man, and the administration of justice earns him popularity; for which department a
    wise praetor, such as Murena was, avoids giving offence by impartiality in his decisions, and
    conciliates good-will by his good temper in hearing the cases brought before him. It is a very
    creditable employment and very well adapted to gain a man the consulship, being one in which the
    praise of justice, integrity and affability is crowned at the last by the pleasure of the games
    which he exhibits. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus"><p> What department was it that your lot gave
    you? A disagreeable and odious one. That of inquiry into peculation, pregnant on the one side
    with the tears and mourning apparel of the accused, full on the other side of imprisonment and
    informers. In that department of justice judges are forced to act against their will, are
    retained by force contrary to their inclination. The clerk is hated, the whole body is
    unpopular. The gratifications given by Sulla are found fault with. Many brave men,—indeed, a
    considerable portion of the city is offended; damages are assigned with severity. The man who is
    pleased with the decision soon forgets it; he who loses his cause is sure to remember it.
    Lastly, you would not go to your province. I cannot find fault with that resolution in you,
    which, both as praetor and consul, I have adopted in my own case. But still Lucius Murena's
    conduct in his province procured him the affection of many influential men, and a great
    accession of reputation. On his road he held a levy of troops in Umbria. The republic enabled
    him to display his liberality, which he did so effectually as to engage in his interest many
    tribes which are connected with the municipalities of that district. And in Gaul itself, he
    contrived by his equity and diligence to enable many of our citizens to recover debts which they
    had entirely despaired of. In the meantime you were living at Rome, ready to help your friends.
    I confess that—but still recollect this, that the inclinations of some friends are often cooled
    towards those men by whom they see that provinces are despised. <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p>
   And since I have proved, O judges, that in this con-test for the consulship Murena had the
    same claims of worth that Sulpicius had, accompanied with a very different fortune as respects
    the business of their respective provinces, I will say more plainly in what particular my friend
    Servius was inferior; and I will say those things while you are now hearing me,—now that the
    time of the elections is over—which I have often said to him by himself before the affair was
    settled. I often told you, O Servius, that you did not know how to stand for the consulship;
    and, in respect to those very matters which I saw you conducting and advocating in a brave and
    magnanimous spirit, I often said to you that you appeared to me to be a brave senator rather
    than a wise candidate. For, in the first place, the terrors and threats of accusations which you
    were in the habit of employing every day, are rather the part of a fearless man; but they have
    an unfavourable effect on the opinion of the people as regards a man's hopes of getting anything
    from them, and they even disarm the zeal of his friends. Somehow or other, this is always the
    case; and it has been noticed, not in one or two instances only, but in many; so that the moment
    a candidate is seen to turn his attention to provocations, he is supposed to have given up all
    hopes of his election. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>
   What, then, am I saying? Do I mean that a man is not to prosecute another for any injury which
    he may have received? Certainly I mean nothing of the sort. But the times for prosecuting and
    for standing for the consulship are different. I consider that a candidate for any office,
    especially for the consulship, ought to come down into the forum and <pb n="352"/> into the
    Campus Martius with great hopes, with great courage, and with great resources. But I do not like
    a candidate to be looking about for evidence—conduct which is a sure forerunner of a repulse. I
    do not like his being anxious to marshal witnesses rather than voters. I do not fancy threats
    instead of caresses,—declamation where there should be salutation; especially as, according to
    the new fashion now existing, all candidates visit the houses of nearly all the citizens, and
    from their countenances men form their conjectures as to what spirits and what probabilities of
    success each candidate has. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p> “Do you see how gloomy that man
    looks? how dejected? He is out of spirits; he thinks he has no chance; he has laid down his
    arms.” Then a report gets abroad—“Do you know that he is thinking of a prosecution? He is
    seeking for evidence against his competitors; he is hunting for witnesses. I shall vote for some
    one else, as he knows that he has no chance.” The most intimate friends of such candidates as
    that are dispirited and disarmed, they abandon all anxiety in the matter,—they give up a
    business which is so manifestly hopeless, or else they reserve all their labour and influence to
    countenance their friend in the trial and prosecution which he is meditating. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
   And, besides all this, the candidate himself cannot devote his whole thoughts, and care, and
    attention, and diligence to his own election; for he has also in his mind the thoughts of his
    prosecution—a matter of no small importance, but in truth of the very greatest. For it is a very
    serious business to be preparing measures by which to deprive a man, especially one who is not
    powerless or without resources—of his rights as a citizen; one who is defended both by himself
    and by his friend,—yes, and perhaps also by strangers. For we all of us naturally hasten to save
    any one from danger; and, if we are not notoriously enemies to them, we tender, even to utter
    strangers, when menaced by danger affecting their station as citizens, the services and zeal
    which are strictly speaking due only to the causes of our friends.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p> On which account I, who know
    by experience the troubles attending on standing for office, on defending and accusing
    prisoners, consider that the truth in respect of each business stands thus,—that in standing for
    an office, eagerness is the chief thing; in defending a man, a regard for one's duty is the
    principal thing shown; in accusing a man, the labour is greatest.
    And therefore I say decidedly that it is quite impossible for the same man to
    do justice properly to the part of an accuser and a candidate for the consulship. Few can play
    either part well; no one can do justice to both. Did you, when you turned aside out of the
    course prescribed for you as a candidate, and when you had transferred your attention to the
    task of prosecuting, think that you could fulfil all the requirements of both? You were greatly
    mistaken if you did; for what day was there after you once entered on that prosecution, that you
    did not devote the whole of it to that occupation? <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
   You demanded a law about bribery, though there was no deficiency of laws on that matter, for
    there was the Calpurnian law, framed with the greatest severity. Your inclinations and your wish
    procured compliance with your demand; but the whole of that law might perhaps have armed your
    accusation, if you had had a guilty defendant to prosecute; but it has been of great injury to
    you as a candidate. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p> A more severe punishment for the common
    people was demanded by your voice. The minds of the lower orders were agitated. The punishment
    of an exile was demanded in the case of any one of our order being convicted. The senate granted
    it to your request; but still it was with no good will that they established a more severe
    condition for our common fortunes at your instigation. Punishment was imposed on any one who
    made the excuse of illness. The inclinations of many men were alienated by this step, as by it
    they were forced either to labour to the prejudice of their health, or else through the distress
    of illness they were compelled to abandon the other enjoyments of life. What then, are we to say
    of this? Who passed this law? He, who, in so doing, acted in obedience to the senate, and to
    your wish. He, in short, passed it to whom it was not of the slightest personal advantage. Do
    you think that those proposals which, with my most willing consent, the senate rejected in a
    very full house, were but a slight hindrance to you? You demanded the confusion of the votes of
    all the centuries, the extension of the Manilian law, <note anchored="true">This was not the
     Manilian law, in support of which Cicero spoke to confer the command in Asia on Pompeius; but a
     law enacting that the votes should be counted without any regard to the centuries in which they
     were given; but this law was repealed soon after its enactment. </note> the equalization or all
    interest and dignity, and <pb n="354"/> of all the suffrages. Honourable men, men of influence
    in their neighbourhoods and municipalities, were indignant that such a man should contend for
    the abolition of all degrees in dignity and popularity. You also wished to have judges selected
    by the accuser at his pleasure, the effect of which would have been, that the secret dislikes of
    the citizens, which are at present confined to silent grumblings, would have broken out in
    attacks on the fortunes of every eminent man. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p>
   All these measures were strengthening your hands as a prosecutor, but weakening your chance as
    a candidate. And by them all a violent blow was struck at your hopes of success, as I warned
    you; and many very severe things were said about it by that most able and most eloquent man,
    Hortensius, owing to which my task of speaking now is the more difficult; as, after both he had
    spoken before me, and also Marcus Crassus, a man of the greatest dignity, and industry, and
    skill as an orator, I, coming in at the end, was not to plead some part of the cause, but to say
    with respect to the whole matter whatever I thought advisable. Therefore I am forced to recur to
    the same ideas, and to a great extent, O judges, I have to contend with a feeling of satiety on
    your part. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
   But still, O Servius, do you not see that you completely lay the axe to the root of your
    chance as a candidate, when you give the Roman people cause for apprehension that Catiline might
    be made consul through your neglect and, I may almost say, abandonment of your canvass, while
    you were intent on your prosecution? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p> In truth, men saw that
    you were hunting about for evidence; that you yourself looked gloomy, your friends out of
    spirits; they noticed your visits, your inquiries after proofs, your privy meetings with your
    witnesses, your conferences with your junior counsel; all which matters are certainly apt to
    make the countenance of a candidate look darker. Meantime they saw Catiline cheerful and joyous,
    accompanied by a band of youths, with a bodyguard of informers and assassins, elated by the
    hopes which he placed in the soldiers, and, as he himself said, by the promises of my
    colleagues; surrounded, too, with a numerous body of colonists from Arretium and Faesulae—a
    crowd made conspicuous by the presence of men of a very different sort in it, men who had been
    ruined by the disasters in the time of Sulla. His own countenance was full of fury; his eyes
    glared with wickedness; his discourse breathed nothing but arrogance. You might have thought
    that he had assured himself of the consulship, and that he had got it locked up at home. Murena
    he despised. Sulpicius he considered as his prosecutor, not as a competitor. He threatened him
    with violence; he threatened the republic. <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus"><p>
   And I need not remind you with what terror all good men were seized in consequence of these
    occurrences, and how entirely they would all have despaired of the republic if he had been made
    consul. All this you yourselves recollect; for you remember, when the expressions of that wicked
    gladiator got abroad, which he was said to have used at a meeting at his own house, when he said
    that it was impossible for any faithful defender of the miserable citizens to be found, except a
    man who was himself miserable; that men in an embarrassed and desperate condition ought not to
    trust the promises of men of a flourishing and fortunate estate; and therefore that those who
    were desirous to replace what they had spent, and to recover what they had lost, had better
    consider what he himself owed, what he possessed, and what he would dare to do; that that man
    ought to be very fearless and thoroughly overwhelmed by misfortune, who was to be the leader and
    standard-bearer of unfortunate men. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus"><p> Then, therefore, when
    these things had been heard, you recollect that a resolution of the senate was passed, on my
    motion, that the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> should not be held the next day, in
    order that we might be able to discuss these matters in the senate. Accordingly, the next day,
    in a full meeting of the senate, I addressed Catiline himself; and desired him, if he could, to
    some explanation of these reports which had been brought to me. And he—for he was not much
    addicted to disguising his intentions—did not attempt to clear himself; but openly avowed and
    adopted the statements. For he said then, that there were two bodies of the republic,—the one
    weak with a weak head, the other powerful without a head,—and that, as this last had deserved
    well of him, it should never want a head as long as he lived. The whole senate groaned at
    hearing itself addressed in such language, and passed a resolution not severe enough for such
    unworthy conduct; for some of them were against too rigorous a resolution, because they had no
    fear; and some, because they had a great deal. Then he rushed forth from the senate, triumphing
    and exulting,—a man who never ought to have been allowed to leave it alive, <pb n="356"/>
    especially as that very same man in the same place had made answer to Cato, that gallant man who
    was threatening him with a prosecution, a few days before, that if any fire were kindled against
    his own fortunes, he would put it out not with water, but by the general ruin. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p>
   Being influenced then by these facts, and knowing that men who were already associated in a
    conspiracy were being brought down by Catiline into the Campus Martius, armed with swords, I
    myself descended into the campus with a guard of brave men, and with that broad and shining
    breastplate, not in order to protect me, (for I knew that Catiline would aim at my head and
    neck, not at my chest or body,) but in order that all good men might observe it, and, when they
    saw their consul in fear and in danger, might as they did, throng together for my assistance and
    protection. Therefore, as, O Servius, men thought you very remiss in prosecuting the contest,
    and saw Catiline inflamed with hope and desire, all who wished to repel that pest from the
    republic immediately joined the party of Murena. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p> And in the
    consular <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign> the sudden inclination of men's feelings is
    often of great weight, especially as, in this case, it took the direction of a very gallant man,
    who was assisted by many other concurrent aids in his application for the office. He was born or
    a most honourable father and ancestors; he had passed his youth in a most modest manner; he had
    discharged the office of a lieutenant with great credit; he had been praetor, as such he had
    been approved as a judge; he had been popular through his liberality; be had been highly
    honoured in his province; he had been very diligent in his canvass, and had carried it on so as
    neither to give way if any one threatened him, nor to threaten any one himself. Can we wonder
    that the sudden hope which Catiline now entertained of obtaining the consulship was a great
    assistance to this man? </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus"><p>
   The third topic which I have got to speak about refers to the charge of bribery; which has
    been already entirely refuted by those who have spoken before me, but which must still be
    discussed by me, since such is the will of Murena. And while speaking on this point, I will
    reply to what Postumius, my own intimate friend, a most accomplished man, has said about the
    trials of agents, and about sums of money which he asserts have been found; and to what Servius
    Sulpicius, that able and virtuous young man, has said about the centuries of the knights; and to
    what Marcus Cato, a man eminent in every kind of virtue, has said about his own accusation,
    about the resolution of the senate, and about the republic in general. <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p>
   But first of all I will say a little, which has just occurred to me, about the hard fortune of
    Lucius Murena. For I have often before now, O judges, judging both by the miseries of others,
    and by my own daily cares and labours, considered those men fortunate, who, being at a distance
    from the pursuits of ambition, have addicted themselves to ease and tranquillity of life; and
    now especially I am so affected by these serious and unexpected dangers of Lucius Murena, that I
    am unable adequately to express my pity for the common condition of all of us, or for his
    particular state and fortune; who while, after an uninterrupted series of honours attained by
    his family and his ancestors, he was endeavouring to mount one step higher in dignity, has
    incurred the danger of losing both the honours bequeathed to him by his forefathers, and those
    too which have been acquired by himself, and now, on account of his pursuit of this new honour,
    is brought into the danger of losing his ancient fortune also. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus"><p> And as these are weighty considerations, O judges, so is this the most serious matter of all,
    that he has men for accusers who, instead of proceeding to accuse him on account of their
    private enmity against him, have become his personal enemies, being carried away by their zeal
    for their accusation. For, to say nothing of Servius Sulpicius, who, I am aware, is influenced
    not by any wrong done by Lucius Murena, but only by the party spirit engendered by the contest
    for honour, his father's friend, Cnaeus Postumius, is his accuser, an old neighbour and intimate
    friend of his own, as he says himself; who has mentioned many reasons for his intimacy with him,
    while he has not been able to mention one for any enmity towards him. Servius Sulpicius accuses
    him, the companion of his son,—he, by whose genius all the friends of his father ought to be
    only the more defended. Marcus Cato accuses him, who, though he has never been in any matter
    whatever at variance with Murena, yet was born in this city under such circumstances that his
    power and genius ought to be a protection to many who were even entire strangers to him, and
    ought to be the ruin of hardly any personal enemy. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus"><p>
   In the first instance then I will reply to Cnaeus Postumius, <pb n="358"/> who, somehow or
    other, I know not how, while a candidate for the praetorship, appears to me to be a straggler
    into the course marked out for the candidates for the consulship, as the horse of a vaulter
    might escape into the course marked out for the chariot races. And if there is no fault whatever
    to be found with his competitors, then he has made a great concession to their worth in
    desisting from his canvass. But if any one of them has committed bribery, then he must look for
    some friend who will be more inclined to prosecute an injury done to another than one done to
    himself. <gap reason="lost"/> [On the Charges of Postumius and of Servius.] <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus"><p>
   I come now to Marcus Cato, who is the mainstay and prop of the whole prosecution; who is,
    however, so zealous and vehement a prosecutor, that I am much more afraid of the weight of his
    name, than of his accusation. And with respect to this accuser, O judges, first of all I will
    entreat you not to let Cato's dignity, nor your expectation of his tribuneship, nor the high
    reputation and virtue of his whole life, be any injury to Lucius Murena. Let not all the honours
    of Marcus Cato, which he has acquired in order to be able to assist many men, be an injury to my
    client alone. Publius Africanus had been twice consul, and had destroyed those two terrors of
    this empire, Carthage and Numantia, when he prosecuted Lucius Cotta. He was a man of the most
    splendid eloquence, of the greatest good faith, of the purest integrity; his authority was as
    great almost as that of the Roman people itself, in that empire which had been mainly saved by
    his means. I have often heard old men say that this very extraordinarily high character of the
    accuser was of the greatest service to Lucius Cotta. Those wise men who then were the judges in
    that cause, did not like any one to be defeated in a trial, if he was to appear overwhelmed only
    by the excessive influence of his adversary. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus"><p> What more shall
    I say? Did not the Roman people deliver Sergius Galba (the fact is preserved in the recollection
    of every one) from your grandfather, that most intrepid and prosperous man, Marcus Cato, who was
    zealously seeking his ruin? At all times in this city the whole people, and also the judges,
    wise men, looking far into futurity, have resisted the overweening power of prosecutors. I do
    not like an accuser bringing his personal power, or any predominant influence, or his own
    eminent authority, or his own excessive popularity, into a court of justice. Let all these
    things have weight to ensure the safety of the innocent, to aid the weak, to succour the
    unfortunate. But in a case where the danger and ruin of citizens may ensue, let them be
    rejected. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus"><p> For if perchance any one should say that Cato would
    not have come forward as an accuser if he had not previously made up his mind about the justice
    of the cause, he will then be laying down a most unjust law, O judges, and establishing a
    miserable condition for men in their danger, if he thinks that the opinion of an accuser is to
    have against a defendant the weight of a previous investigation legally conducted. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
   I, O Cato, do not venture to find fault with your intentions, by reason of my extraordinarily
    high opinion of your virtue; but in some particulars I may perhaps be able slightly to amend and
    reform them. “You are not very wrong,” said an aged tutor to a very brave man; “but if you are
    wrong, I can set you right.” But I can say with the greatest truth that you never do wrong, and
    that your conduct is never such in any point as to need correction, but only such as
    occasionally to require being guided a little. For nature has herself formed you for honesty,
    and gravity, and moderation, and magnanimity, and justice; and for all the virtues required to
    make a great and noble man. To all these qualities are added an education not moderate, nor
    mild, but as it seems to me, a little harsh and severe, more so than either truth or nature
    would permit. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus"><p> And since we are not to address this speech
    either to an ignorant multitude, or to any assembly of rustics, I will speak a little boldly
    about the pursuits of educated men, which are both well known and agreeable to you, O judges,
    and to me. Learn then, O judges, that all these good qualities, divine and splendid as they are,
    which we behold in Marcus Cato, are his own peculiar attributes. The qualities which we
    sometimes wish for in him, are not all those which are implanted in a man by nature, but some of
    them are such as are derived from education. For there was once a man of the greatest genius,
    whose name was Zeno, the imitators of whose example are called Stoics. His opinions and precepts
    are of this sort: that a wise man is never influenced by interest; never pardons any man's
    fault; that no one is merciful except a fool and a trifler; that it is not the part of a man to
    be moved or pacified by entreaties; that wise men, let them be ever so deformed, are <pb n="360"/> the only beautiful men; if they be ever such beggars, they are the only rich men; if they be
    in slavery, they are kings. And as for all of us who are not wise men, they call away slaves,
    exiles, enemies, lunatics. They say that all offenses are equal; that every sin is an
    unpardonable crime; and that he does not commit a less crime who kills a cock if there was no
    need to do so, than the man who strangles his father. They say that a wise man never feels
    uncertain on any point never repents of anything, is never deceived in anything, and never
    alters his opinion. <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus"><p>
   All these opinions that most acute man, Marcus Cato, having been induced by learned advocates
    of them has embraced; and that, not for the sake of arguing about them as is the case with most
    men, but of living by them. Do the Publicans ask for anything? “Take care that their influence
    has no weight.” Do any suppliants, miserable and unhappy men, come to us? “You will be a wicked
    and infamous man if you do anything from being influenced by mercy.” Does any one confess that
    he has done wrong, and beg pardon for his wrong doing? “To pardon is a crime of the deepest
    dye.”—“But it is a trifling offence.” “All offences are equal.” You say something. “That is a
    fixed and unalterable principle.” “You are influenced not by the facts, but by your opinion.” “A
    wise man never forms mere opinions.” “You have made a mistake in some point.” He thinks that you
    are abusing him.—And in accordance with these principles of his are the following assertions: “I
    said in the senate, that I would prosecute one of the candidates for the consulship.” “You said
    that when you were angry.” “A wise man never is angry.” “But you said it for some temporary
    purpose.” “It is the act,” says he, “of a worthless man to deceive by a lie; it is a disgraceful
    act to alter one's opinion; to be moved by entreaties is wickedness; to pity any one is an
    enormity.” </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus"><p> But our philosophers, (for I confess, O Cato, that
    I too, in my youth, distrusting my own abilities, sought assistance from learning,) our
    philosophers, I say, men of the school of Plato and Aristotle, men of soberness and moderation,
    say that private interest does sometimes have weight even with a wise man. They say that it does
    become a virtuous man to feel pity; that there are different gradations of offences, and
    different degrees of punishment appropriate to each; that a man with every proper regard for
    firmness may pardon offences; that even the wise man himself has sometimes nothing more than
    opinion to go upon, without absolute certainty, that he is sometimes angry, that he is sometimes
    influenced and pacified by entreaty that he sometimes does change an opinion which he may have
    expressed when it is better to do so, that he sometimes abandons his previous opinions
    altogether, and that all his virtues are tempered by a certain moderation <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus"><p>
   If any chance, O Cato, had conducted endowed with your existing natural disposition to those
    tutors, you would not indeed have been a better man than you are, not a braver one, nor more
    temperate, nor more just than you are, (for that is not possible,) but you would have been a
    little more inclined to lenity; you would not when you were not induced by any enmity, or
    provoked by any personal injury, accuse a most virtuous man, a man of the highest rank and the
    greatest integrity; you would consider that as fortune had entrusted the guardianship of the
    same year to you <note anchored="true">Cato was tribune elect.</note> and to Murena, that you
    were connected with him by some certain political union; and the severe things which you have
    said in the senate you would either not have said, or you would have guarded against their being
    applied to him, or you would have interpreted them in the mildest sense. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus"><p> And even you yourself, (at least that is my opinion and expectation,) excited
    as you are at present by the impetuosity of your disposition and elated as you are both by the
    vigour of our natural character and by your confidence in your own ability, and inflamed as you
    are by your recent study of all these precepts, will find practice modify them and time and
    increasing years soften and humanise you. In truth, those tutors and teachers of virtue, whom
    you think so much of appear to me themselves to have carried their definitions of duties
    somewhat further than is agreeable to nature, and it would be better if, when we had in theory
    pushed our principles to extremities, yet in practice we stopped at what was expedient. “Forgive
    nothing.” Say rather, forgive some things, but not everything. “Do nothing for the sake of
    private influence.” Certainly resist private influence when virtue and good faith require you to
    do so. “Do not be moved by pity.” Certainly if it is to extinguish all impartiality;
    nevertheless, there is some credit due to humanity. “Abide by your own opinion.” </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus"><p> Very true, unless some other sounder opinion convinces you. That great
     <pb n="362"/> Scipio was a man of this sort, who had no objection to do the same thing that you
    do; to keep a most learned man, a man of almost divine wisdom, in his house; by whose
    conversation and precepts, although they were the very same that you are so fond of; he was
    nevertheless not made more severe, but (as I have heard said by old men) he was rendered most
    merciful. And who was more mild in his manners than Caius Lucius? who was more agreeable than
    he? (devoted to the same studies as you;) who was more virtuous or more wise than he? I might
    say the same of Lucius Philus, and of Caius Gallus; but I will conduct you now into your own
    house. Do you think that there was any man more courteous, more agreeable; any one whose conduct
    was more completely regulated by every principle of virtue and politeness, than Cato, your
    great-grandfather? And when you were speaking with truth and dignity of his virtue, you said
    that you had a domestic example to imitate. That indeed is an example set up for your imitation
    in your own family; and the similarity of nature ought rather to influence you who are descended
    from him than any one of us; but still that example is as much an object for my imitation as for
    yours. But if you were to add his courtesy and affability to your own wisdom and impartiality, I
    will not say that those qualities which are now most excellent will be made intrinsically
    better, but they will certainly be more agreeably seasoned. <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus"><p>
   Wherefore, to return to the subject which I began to speak of; take away the name of Cato out
    of the cause; remove and leave out of the question all mention of authority, which in courts of
    justice ought either to have no influence at all, or only influence to contribute to someone's
    safety; and discuss with me the charges themselves. What do you accuse him of, Cato? What action
    of his is it that you bring before the court? What is your charge? Do you accuse him of bribery?
    I do not defend bribery. You blame me because you say I am defending the very conduct which I
    brought in a law to punish. I punished bribery, not innocence. And any real ease of bribery I
    will join you in prosecuting if you please. You have said that a resolution of the senate was
    passed, on my motion, “that if any men who had been bribed had gone to meet the candidates, if
    any hired men followed them, if places were given men to see the shows of gladiators according
    to their tribes, and also, if dinners were given to the common people, that appeared to be a
    violation of the Calpurnian law.” Therefore the senate decides that these things were done in
    violation of the Calpurnian law if they were done at all it decides what there is not the least
    occasion for out of complaisance for the candidates. For there is a great question whether such
    things have been done or not. That if they have been done, they were done in violation of the
    law, no one can doubt. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus"><p> It is, therefore ridiculous to leave
    that uncertain which was doubtful but to give a positive decision on that point which can be
    doubtful to no one. And that decree is passed at the request of all the candidates; in order
    that it might be quite impossible to make out from the resolution of the senate whose interests
    were consulted, or against whose interests it was passed. Prove, then, that these actions have
    been done by Lucius Murena and then I will grant to you that they have been done in violation of
    the law. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
   “Many men went to meet him as he was departing from his province, when he was a candidate for
    the consulship.” That is a very usual thing to do. Who is there whom people do not go out to
    meet on his return home? “What a number of people they were.” In the first place, if I am not
    able to give you any exact account of it what wonder is it if many men did go out to meet such a
    man on his arrival, being a candidate for the consulship? If they had not done so, it would have
    appeared much more strange. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus"><p> What then? Suppose I were even to
    add, what there would be nothing unusual in, that many had been asked to go? Would that be
    matter of accusation, or at all strange, that in a city in which we, when we are asked, often
    come to escort the sons of even the lowest rank, almost before the night is over, from the
    furthest part of the city, men should not mind going at the third hour into the Campus Martius,
    especially when they have been invited in the name of such a man as Murena? What then? What if
    all the societies had come to meet him, of which bodies many are sitting here as judges? What if
    many men of our own most honourable order had come? What then? What if the whole of that most
    officious body of candidates, which will not suffer any man to enter the city except in an
    honourable manner, had come, or even our prosecutor himself—if Postumius had come to meet him
    with a numerous crowd of his dependents? What is there strange in such a multitude? I say
    nothing of his clients, his neighbours, his tribesmen, or the whole army of Lucullus, which,
    just at that time, had come to Rome to his triumph; I say <pb n="364"/> this, that that crowd,
    paying that gratuitous mark or respect was never backward in paying respect not only to the
    merit of any one, but even to his wishes. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus"><p>
   “But a great many people followed him.” Prove that it was for hire, and I will admit that that
     was a crime: but if the fact of hire be absent, what is there that you object to? <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
  “What need is there,” says he, “of an escort?” Are you asking me what is the need of that
    which we have always availed ourselves of? Men of the lower orders have only one opportunity of
    deserving kindness at the hands of our order, or of requiting services,—namely, this one
    attention of escorting us when we are candidates for offices. For it is neither possible, nor
    ought we or the Roman knights to require them to escort the candidates to whom they are attached
    for whole days together; but if our house is frequented by them, if we are sometimes escorted to
    the forum, if we are honoured by their attendance for the distance of one piazza, we then appear
    to be treated with all due observance and respect; and those are the attentions of our poorer
    friends who are not hindered by business, of whom numbers are not wont to desert virtuous and
    beneficent men. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus"><p> Do not then, O Cato, deprive the lower class
    of men of this power of showing their dutiful feelings; allow these men, who hope for everything
    from us, to have something also themselves, which they may be able to give us. If they have
    nothing beyond their own vote, that is but little; since they have no interest which they can
    exert in the votes of others. They themselves, as they are accustomed to say, cannot plead for
    us, cannot go bail for us, cannot invite us to their houses; but they ask all these things of
    us, and do not think that they can requite the services which they receive from us by anything
    but by their attentions of this sort. Therefore they resisted the Fabian law, which regulated
    the number of an escort and the resolution of the senate, which was passed in the consulship of
    Lucius Caesar. For there is no punishment which can prevent the regard shown by the poorer
    classes for this description of attention. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus"><p> “But spectacles
    were exhibited to the people by their tribes, and crowds of the common people were invited to
    dinner.” Although this, O judges, was not done by Murena at all, but done in accordance with all
    usage and precedent by his friends, still, being reminded of the fact, I recollect how many
    votes these investigations held in the senate have lost us, O Servius. For what time was there
    ever, either within our own recollection or that of our fathers, in which this, whether you call
    it ambition or liberality, did not exist to the extent of giving a place in the circus and in
    the forum to one's friends, and to the men of one's own tribe? The men of the poorer classes
    first, who had not yet obtained from those of their own tribe <gap reason="lost"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>[A considerable break in the text.] <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus"><p>
   <gap reason="lost"/> that the prefect of the carpenters <note anchored="true">Besides the
     classes into which the centuries were divided and the four supernumerary centuries of <foreign xml:lang="lat">accensi</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">velati</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="lat">proletarii</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">capite censi</foreign>, there
     were three centuries classed according to their occupation. The <foreign xml:lang="lat">fabri</foreign>, or carpenters, who were attached to the centuries of the first class; the
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">cornicines</foreign>, or hornblowers, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">liticines</foreign>, or trumpeters, who were reckoned with the fourth class. </note> once
    gave a place to the men of his own tribe. What will they decide with respect to the eminent men
    who have erected regular stalls in the circus for the sake of their own tribesmen? All these
    charges of escort of spectacles of dinners, are brought forward by the multitude, O Servius, as
    proofs of your over-scrupulous diligence but still as to those counts of the indictment Murena
    is defended by the authority of the senate. And why not? Does the senate think it a crime to go
    to meet a man? No but it does, if it be done for a bribe. Prove that it was so. Does the senate
    think it a crime for many men to follow him? No, but it does, if they were hired. Prove it. Or
    to give a man a place to see the spectacles? or to ask a man to dinner? Not by any means; but to
    give every one a seat to ask everyone one meets to dinner. “What is every one?” Why, the whole
    body of citizens. It then, Lucius Natta, a young man of the highest rank, as to whom we see
    already of what sort of disposition he is, and what sort of man he is likely to turn out wished
    to be popular among the centuries of the knights, both because of his natural connection with
    them, and because of his intentions as to the future, that will not be a crime in, or matter of
    accusation against his stepfather; nor, if a vestal virgin, my client's near relation, gave up
    her place to see the spectacle in his favour, was that any other than a pious action nor is he
    liable to any charge on that ground. All these are the kind offices of intimate friends the
    services done to the poorer classes, the regular privileges of candidates. </p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74" resp="perseus"><p>
   But I must change my tone for Cato argues with me on rigid and stoic principles. He says that
    it is not true that good-will is conciliated by food. He says that men's <pb n="366"/>
    judgments, in the important business of electing to magistracies, ought not to be corrupted by
    pleasures. Therefore, if any one, to promote his canvass, invites another to supper, he must be
    condemned. “Shall you,” says he, “seek to obtain supreme power, supreme authority, and the helm
    of the republic, by encouraging men's sensual appetites, by soothing their minds, by tendering
    luxuries to them? Are you asking employment as a pimp from a band of luxurious youths, or the
    sovereignty of the world from the Roman people?” An extraordinary sort of speech! but our
    usages, our way of living, our manners, and the constitution itself rejects it. For the
    Lacedaemonians, the original authors of that way of living and of that sort of language, men who
    lie at their daily meals on hard oak benches, and the Cretans, of whom no one ever lies down to
    eat at all, have neither of them preserved their political constitutions or their power better
    than the Romans, who set apart times for pleasure as well as times for labour; for one of those
    nations was destroyed by a single invasion of our army, the other only preserves its discipline
    and its laws by means of the protection afforded to it by our supremacy. <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75" resp="perseus"><p>
   Do not, then, O Cato, blame with too great severity of language the principles of our
    ancestors, which facts, and the length of time that our power has flourished under them,
    justify. There was, in the time of our ancestors, a learned man of the same sect an honourable
    citizen, and one of high rank, Quintus Tubero. He, when Quintus Maximus was giving a feast to
    the Roman people, in the name of his uncle Africanus, was asked by Maximus to prepare a couch
    for the banquet as Tubero was a son of the sister of the same Africanus. And he, a most learned
    man and a Stoic, covered for that occasion some couches made in the Carthaginian fashion, with
    skins of kids, and exhibited some Samian <note anchored="true">Samian vessels were made of an
     inferior earthenware; Carthaginian couches were very low and narrow.</note> vessels, as if
    Diogenes the Cynic had been dead, and not as if he were paying respect to the obsequies of that
    godlike Africanus; a man with respect to whom Maximus, when he was pronouncing his funeral
    panegyric on the day of his death, expressed his gratitude to the immortal gods for having
    caused that man to be born in this republic above all others, for that it was quite inevitable
    that the sovereignty of the world must belong to that state of which be was a citizen. At the
    celebration of the obsequies of such a man the Roman people was very indignant at the perverse
    wisdom of Tubero, </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76" resp="perseus"><p> and therefore he, a most upright man, a
    most virtuous citizen, though he was the grandson of Lucius Paullus, the sister's son, as I have
    said before, of Publius Africanus, lost the praetorship by his kid skins. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>The Roman people disapproves of private luxury, but admires public magnificence. It does not
    love profuse banquets, still less does it love sordid and uncivilized behaviour. It makes a
    proper distinction between different duties and different seasons; and allows of vicissitudes of
    labour and pleasure. For as to what you say, that it is not right for men's minds to be
    influenced, in appointing magistrates, by any other consideration than that of the worth of the
    candidates, this principle even you yourself—you, a man of the greatest worth—do not in every
    case adhere to. For why do you ark any one to take pains for you, to assist you? You ask me to
    make you governor over myself to entrust myself to you. What is the meaning of this? Ought I to
    be asked this by you, or should not you rather be asked by me to undertake labour and danger for
    the sake of my safety? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77" resp="perseus"><p> Nay more, why is it that you have a
    nomenclator <note anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="lat">nomenclator</foreign> was a slave
     who accompanied the candidate in going his rounds, and told him the name of every one he met,
     so that he might be able to accost them as if they were personally known to himself.</note>
    with you? for in so doing, you are practicing a trick and a deceit. For if it be an honourable
    thing for your fellow-citizens to be addressed by name by you, it is a shameful thing for them
    to be better known to your servant than to yourself. If though you know them yourself it seems
    better to use a prompter, why do you sometimes address them before he has whispered their names
    in your ear? Why, again, when he has reminded you of them, do you salute them as if you knew
    them yourself? And why, after you are once elected, are you more careless about saluting them at
    all? If you regulate all these things by the usages of the city, it is all right; but if you
    choose to weigh them by the precepts of your sect they will be found to be entirely wrong. Those
    enjoyments, then, of games, and gladiators, and banquets, all which things our ancestors
    desired, are not to be taken away from the Roman people, nor ought candidates to be forbidden
    the exercise of that kindness which is liberality rather than bribery. <pb n="368"/>
    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78" resp="perseus"><p>
   Oh, but it is the interest of the republic that has induced you to become a prosecutor. I do
    believe, O Cato, that you have come forward under the influence of those feelings and of that
    opinion. But you err out of ignorance. That which I am doing, O judges, I am doing out of regard
    to my friendship for Lucius Murena and to his own worth, and I also do assert and call you all
    to witness that I am doing it for the sake of peace, of tranquillity, of concord, of liberty, of
    safety,—yes, even for the sake of the lives of us all. Listen, O judges, listen to the consul,—I
    will not speak with undue arrogance, I will only say, who devotes all his thoughts day and night
    to the republic. Lucius Catiline did not despise and scorn the republic to such a degree as to
    think that with the forces which he took away with him he could subdue this city. The contagion
    of that wickedness spreads more widely than any one believes: more men are implicated in it than
    people are aware of. It is within the city,—the Trojan horse, I say, is within the city; but you
    shall never be surprised sleeping by that while I am consul. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79" resp="perseus"><p>
    You ask of me why I am afraid of Catiline? I am not; and I have taken care that no one should
    have any reason to be afraid of him; but I do say that those soldiers of his, whom I see present
    here, are objects of fear: nor is the army which Lucius Catiline now has with him as formidable
    as those men are who are said to have deserted that army; for they have not deserted it but they
    have been left by him as spies, as men placed in ambuscade, to threaten our lives and liberties.
    Those men are very anxious that an upright consul and an able general—a man connected both by
    nature and by fortune with the safety of the republic, should by your decision be removed from
    the office of protecting the city, from the guardianship of the state. Their swords and their
    audacity I have procured the rejection of in the campus, I have disarmed them in the forum, I
    have often checked them at my own house; but if you now give them up one of the consuls, they
    will have gained much more by your votes than by their own swords. That which I, in spite of the
    resistance of many, have managed and carried through, namely, that on the first of January there
    should be two consuls in the republic, is of great consequence, O judges. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80" resp="perseus"><p> Do not think that they should exploit ordinary counsels or the ordinary modes
    of proceeding <gap reason="lost"/> It is not some unjust law, some mischievous bribery, or
    some improprieties in the republic that have just been heard of; that are the real objects for
    your inquiry now. Plans have been formed in this state, O judges, for destroying the city, for
    massacring the citizens, for extinguishing the Roman name. They are citizens,—citizens, I say,
    (if indeed it is lawful to call them by this name,) who are forming and have formed these plans
    respecting their own country. Every day I am counteracting their designs, disarming their
    audacity, resisting their wickedness. But I warn you, O judges; my consulship is now just at an
    end. Do not refuse me a successor in my diligence; do not refuse me him, to whom I am anxious to
    deliver over the republic in a sound condition, that he may defend it from these great dangers.
     <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81" resp="perseus"><p>
   And do you not see, O judges, what other evil there is added to these evils? I am addressing
    you,—you, O Cato. Do you not foresee a storm in your year of office? for in yesterday's assembly
    there thundered out the mischievous voice of a tribune <note anchored="true">He means Quintus
     Metellus Nepos, the same man who afterwards prevented his making an address to the people on
     his resigning his consulship.</note> elect one of your own colleagues; against whom your own
    mind took many precautions, and so too did all good men, when they invited you to stand for the
    tribuneship. Everything which has been plotted for the last three years, from the time when you
    know that the design of massacring the senate was first formed by Lucius Catiline and by Cnaeus
    Piso, is now breaking out on these days, in these months, at this time. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82" resp="perseus"><p> What place is there, O judges, what time, what day, what night is there, that
    I have not been delivered and escaped from their plots and attacks, not only by my own prudence,
    but much more by the providence of the gods? It was not that they wished to slay me as an
    individual, but that they wished to get rid of a vigilant consul, and to remove him from the
    guardianship of the republic; and they would be just as glad, O Cato, to remove you too, if they
    could by any means contrive to do so; and believe me, that is what they are wishing and planning
    to do. They see how much courage, how much ability, how much authority, how much protection for
    the republic there is in you; but they think that, when they have once seen the power of the
    tribunes stripped of the support which it derives <pb n="370"/> from the authority and
    assistance of the consuls, they will then find it easier to crush you when you are deprived of
    your arms and vigour. For they have no fear of another consul being elected in the place of this
    one; they see that that will depend upon your colleagues; they hope that Silanus, any colleague;
    and that so will you without any consul; and that so will the republic without any protector.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83" resp="perseus"><p> When such an illustrious man, will be exposed to their
    attacks without are our circumstances, and such our perils, it becomes you, O Marcus Cato, who
    have been born, not for my good, nor for your own good, but for that of your country, to
    perceive what are their real objects; to retain as your assistant and defender, and partner in
    the republic, a consul who has no private desires to gratify, a consul (as this season
    particularly requires) formed by fortune to court ease, but by knowledge to carry on war, and by
    courage and practice to discharge in a proper manner whatever business you can impose upon him.
    <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
   Although the whole power of providing for this rests with you, O judges,—you, in this cause,
    are the masters and directors of the whole republic,—if Lucius Catiline, with his council of
    infamous men whom he took out with him, could give his decision in this case, he would condemn
    Lucius Murena; if he could put him to death, he would. For his plans require the republic to be
    deprived of every sort of aid; they require the number of generals who may be opposed to his
    frenzy to be diminished; they require that greater power should be given to the tribunes of the
    people, when they have driven away their adversary, to raise sedition and discord. Will, then,
    thoroughly honourable and wise men, chosen out of the most dignified orders of the state, give
    the same decision that most profligate gladiator, the enemy of the republic, would give?
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84" resp="perseus"><p> Believe me, O judges, in this case you are deciding not only
    about the safety of Lucius Murena, but also on your own. We are in a situation of extreme
    danger; there is no means now of repairing the losses which we have already, sustained, or of
    recovering the ground which we have lost. We must take care not only not to diminish the
    resources which we still have, but to provide ourselves with additional ones if that be
    possible. For the enemy is not on the Anio, which in the time of the Punic war appeared a most
    terrible thing, but he is in the city, in the forum; (O ye immortal gods! this cannot be said
    without a groan;) there are even some enemies in this sacred temple of the republic, in the very
    senate-house itself. May the gods grant that my colleague, that most gallant man, may be able in
    arms to overtake and crush this impious piratical war of Catiline's. I, in the garb of peace,
    with you and all virtuous men for my assistants, will endeavour by my prudence to divide and
    destroy the dangers which the republic is pregnant with and about to bring forth. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85" resp="perseus"><p> But still, what will be the consequences if these things slip through
    our hands and remain in vigour till the ensuing year? There will be but one consul; and he will
    have sufficient occupation, not in conducting a war, but in managing the election of a
    colleague. Those who will hinder him <gap reason="lost"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>That intolerable pest, <gap reason="lost"/> will break forth wherever it can find room; and
    even now it is threatening the Roman people; soon it will descend upon the suburban districts;
    frenzy will range at large among the camp, fear in the senate-house, conspiracy in the forum, an
    army in the Campus Martius, and devastation all over the country. In every habitation, and in
    every place, we shall live in fear of fire and sword. And yet all these evils, which have been
    so long making ready against us, if the republic is fortified by its natural means of
    protection, will be easily put down by the counsels of the magistrates and the diligence of
    private individuals. <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/></p></div>
    <milestone unit="para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86" resp="perseus"><p>
   And as this is the case, O judges, in the first place for the sake of the republic, than which
    nothing ought to be of more importance in the eyes of every one, I do warn you, as I am entitled
    to do by my extreme diligence in the cause of the republic, which is well known to all of you,—I
    do exhort you, as my consular authority gives me a right to do,—I do entreat you, as the
    magnitude of the danger justifies me in dying, to provide for the tranquillity, for the peace,
    for the safety, for the lives of yourselves and of all the rest of your fellow-citizens. In the
    next place I do appeal to your good faith, O judges, (whether you may think that I do so in the
    spirit of an advocate or a friend signifies but little,) and beg of you, not to overwhelm the
    recent exaltation of Lucius Murena, an unfortunate man, of one oppressed both by bodily disease
    and by vexation of mind, by a fresh cause for morning. He has been lately distinguished by the
    greatest kindness of the Roman people, and has seemed fortunate in being <pb n="372"/> the first
    man to bring the honours of the consulship into an old family, and a most ancient municipality.
    Now, in a mourning and unbecoming gait, debilitated by sickness, worn out with tears and grief,
    he is a suppliant to you, O judges, invoking your good faith, imploring your pity, fixing all
    his hopes on your power and your assistance. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87" resp="perseus"><p> Do not, in the
    name of the immortal gods, O judges, deprive him not only of that office which he thought
    conferred additional honour on him, and at the same time of all the honours which he had gained
    before, and of all his dignity and fortune. And, O judges, what Lucius Murena is begging and
    entreating of you is no more than this; that if he has done no injury unjustly to any one, if he
    has offended no man's ears or inclination, if he has never (to say the least) given any one
    reason to hate him either at home or when engaged in war, he may in that case find among you
    moderation in judging, and a refuge for men in dejection, and assistance for modest merit. The
    deprivation of the consulship is a measure calculated to excite great feelings of pity, O
    judges. For with the consulship everything else is taken away too. And at such times as these
    the consulship itself is hardly a thing to envy a man. For it is exposed to the harangues of
    seditious men, to the plots of conspirators, to the attacks of Catiline. It is opposed
    single-handed to every danger, and to every sort of unpopularity. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88" resp="perseus"><p> So that, O judges, I do not see what there is in this beautiful consulship
    which need be grudged to Murena, or to any other man among us. But those things in it which are
    calculated to make a man an object of pity, are visible to my eyes, and you too can clearly see
    and comprehend them. <milestone unit="para"/><milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
  If (may Jupiter avert the omen) you condemn this man by your decision, where is the unhappy
    man to turn? Home? What that he may see that image of that most illustrious man his father,
    which a few days ago he beheld crowned with laurel when men were congratulating him on his
    election, now in mourning and lamentation at his disgrace? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89" resp="perseus"><p> Or
    to his mother, who, wretched woman, having lately embraced her son as consul, is now in all the
    torments or anxiety, lest she should but a short time afterwards behold that same son stripped
    of all his dignity? But why do I speak of his home or of his mother, when the new punishment of
    the law deprives him of home, and parent, and of the intercourse with and sight of all his
    relations? Shall the <pb n="373"/> wretched man then go into banishment? Whither shall he go?
    Shall he go to the east, where he was for many years lieutenant, where he commanded armies, and
    performed many great exploits? But it is a most painful thing to return to a place in disgrace,
    from which you have departed in honour. Shall he hide himself in the opposite regions of the
    earth, so as to let Transalpine Gaul see the same man grieving and mourning, whom it lately saw
    with the greatest joy, exercising the highest authority? In that same province, moreover, with
    what feelings will he behold Caius Murena, his own brother? What will be the grief of the one
    what will be the agony of the other? What will be the lamentations of both? How great will the
    vicissitudes of fortune appear and what a change will there be in every one's conversation when
    in the very places in which a few days before messengers and letters had repeated, with every
    indication of joy that Murena had been made consul in the very places from which his own friends
    and his hereditary connections flocked to Rome for the purpose of congratulating him he himself
    arrives on a sudden as the messenger of his own misfortune. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90" resp="perseus"><p>
    And if these things seem bitter and miserable and grievous if they are most foreign to your
    general clemency and merciful disposition, O judges, then maintain the kindness done to him by
    the Roman people restore the consul to the republic grant this to his own modesty, grant it to
    his dead father, grant it to his race and family, grant it also to Lanuvium, that most
    honourable municipality, the whole population of which you have seen watching this cause with
    tears and mourning. Do not tear from his ancestral sacrifices to Juno Sospita, to whom all
    consuls are hound to offer sacrifice, a consul who is so peculiarly her own. Him, if my
    recommendation has any weight if my solemn assertion has any authority, I now recommend to you,
    O judges—I the consul recommend him to you as consul, promising and undertaking that he will
    prove most desirous of tranquillity, most anxious to consult the interests of virtuous men, very
    active against sedition, very brave in war, and an irreconcilable enemy to this conspiracy,
    which is at this moment seeking to undermine the republic.</p></div>
   </div>
  
 </body>
 </text>

</TEI>
