<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight books - 1</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight Books</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1857</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/4/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1" xml:id="p.1"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="book">
                <head>THE HISTORY OF ROME. BOOK I.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> The coming of Aeneas into Italy, and his achievements there; the reign of
                        Ascanius in Alba, and of the other Sylvian kings. Romulus and Remus born.
                        Amulius killed. Romulus builds Rome; forms a senate; makes war upon the
                        Sabines; presents the <foreign xml:lang="la">opima spolia</foreign> to
                        Jupiter Feretrius; divides the people into <foreign xml:lang="la"
                            >curiae;</foreign> his victories; is deified. Numa institutes the rites
                        of religious worship; builds a temple to Janus; and having made peace with
                        all his neighbours, closes it for the first time; enjoys a peaceful reign,
                        and is succeeded by Tullus Hostilius. War with the Albans; combat of the
                        Horatii and Curiatii. Alba demolished, and the Albans made citizens of Rome.
                        War declared against the Sabines: Tullus killed by lightning. Ancus Marcius
                        renews the religious institutions of Numa; conquers the Latins, confers on
                        them the right of citizenship, and assigns them the Aventine hill to dwell
                        on; adds the hill Janiculum to the city; enlarges the bounds of the empire.
                        In his reign Lucumo comes to Rome; assumes the name of Tarquinius; and,
                        after the death of Ancus, is raised to the throne. He increases the senate,
                        by adding to it a hundred new senators; defeats the Latins and Sabines;
                        augments the centuries of knights; builds a wall round the city; makes the
                        common sewers; is slain by the sons of Ancus after a reign of thirty-eight
                        years; and is succeeded by Servius Tullius. He institutes the census; closes
                        the lustrum, in which eighty thousand citizens are said to have been
                        enrolled; divides the people into classes and centuries; enlarges the
                        Pomaerium, and adds the Quirinal, Viminal, and Esquiline hills to the city;
                        after a reign of forty years, is murdered by L. Tarquin, afterwards surnamed
                        Superbus. He usurps the crown. Tarquin makes war on the Volsci, and, with
                        the plunder taken from them, builds a temple to Jupiter Capitolinus. By a
                        stratagem of his son, Sextus Tarquin, he reduces the city of Gabii; after a
                        reign of twenty-five years is dethroned and banished, in consequence of the
                        forcible violation of the person of Lucretia by his son Sextus. L. Junius
                        Brutus and L. Tarquinius Collatinus first created consuls. </p>
                </argument>
                <pb n="2" xml:id="p.2"/>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> WHETHER in tracing the history of the Roman
                    people, from the foundation of the city, I shall employ myself to a useful
                    purpose, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Employ myself to a useful purpose,</quote> — <hi rend="italics"
                            >facere operae pretium,</hi>
                        <quote>to do a thing that is worth the trouble,</quote> — <quote>to employ
                            oneself to a good purpose.</quote> —See Scheller's Lat. Lexicon. </note>
                    I am neither very certain, nor, if I were, dare I say: inasmuch as I observe,
                    that it is both an old and hackneyed practice, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote>A practice,</quote> — <hi rend="italics">rem.</hi> —Some, as Baker,
                        refer it to <hi rend="italics"> res populi R. <foreign xml:lang="la">Others,
                                as Stroth, to</foreign> res pop. Rom. perscribere. </hi>
                    </note> later authors always supposing that they will either adduce something
                    more authentic in the facts, or, that they will excel the less polished ancients
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> in their style of writing. Be that as it
                    may, it will, at all events, be a satisfaction to me, that I too have
                    contributed my share <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>My share,</quote> — <hi rend="italics">pro virili parte,</hi> or,
                            <quote>to the best of my ability.</quote>
                    </note> to perpetuate the achievements of a people, the lords of the world; and
                    if, amidst so great a number of historians, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Historians.</quote> —Those mentioned by Livy himself are Q. Fabius
                        Pictor, Valerius Antias, L. Piso, Q. Aelius Tubero, C. Licinius Macer,
                        Cœlius, Polybius, etc. </note> my reputation should remain in obscurity, I
                    may console myself with the celebrity and lustre of those who shall <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> stand in the way of my fame. Moreover, the subject is
                    both of immense labour, as being one which must be traced back for more than
                    seven hundred years, and which, having set out from small beginnings, has
                    increased to such a degree that it is now distressed by its own magnitude. And,
                    to most readers, I doubt not but that the first origin and the events
                    immediately succeeding, will afford but little pleasure, while they will be
                    hastening to these later times, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Hastening to these later times.</quote> —The history of the recent
                        civil wars would possess a more intense interest for the Romans of the
                        Augustan age. </note> in <pb n="3" xml:id="p.3"/> which the strength of this
                    overgrown people has for <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> a long period been
                    working its own destruction. I, on the contrary, shall seek this, as a reward of
                    my labour, viz. to withdraw myself from the view of the calamities, which our
                    age has witnessed for so many years, so long as I am reviewing with my whole
                    attention these ancient times, being free from every care <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> "From every care, —the fear of giving offence by
                        expressing his opinions freely, and the sorrow which, as a patriot, he could
                        not but feel in recording the civil wars of his countrymen. </note> that may
                    distract a writer's <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> mind, though it cannot
                    warp it from the truth. The traditions which have come down to us of what
                    happened before the building of the city, or before its building was
                    contemplated, as being suitable rather to the fictions of poetry than to the
                    genuine records of history, I have no intention either to affirm or refute. This
                    indulgence is conceded to antiquity, that by blending things human with divine,
                    it <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> may make the origin of cities appear more
                    venerable: and if any people might be allowed to consecrate their origin, and to
                    ascribe it to the gods as its authors, such is the renown of the Roman people in
                    war, that when they represent Mars, in particular, as their own parent and that
                    of their founder, the nations of the world may submit to <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> this as patiently as they submit to their sovereignty. —But
                    in whatever way these and such like matters shall be attended to, or judged of,
                    I shall not deem of great importance. I would have every man apply his mind
                    seriously to consider these points, viz. what their life and what their manners
                    were; through what men and by what measures, both in peace and in war, their
                    empire was acquired <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Acquired.</quote> —This refers to the whole period antecedent to the
                        time when Ap. Claudius carried the Roman arms beyond Italy against the
                        Carthaginians; (2) <hi rend="italics">extended,</hi> from that time till the
                        fall of Carthage; (3) <hi rend="italics">sinking,</hi> the times of the
                        Gracchi; (4) <hi rend="italics">gave way more and more,</hi> those of Sulla;
                        (5) <hi rend="italics">precipitate,</hi> those of Caesar; (6) <hi
                            rend="italics">the present times,</hi> those of Augustus after the
                        battle of Actium. — <hi rend="italics">Stocker.</hi>
                    </note> and extended; then, as discipline gradually declined, let him follow in
                    his thoughts their morals, at first as slightly giving way, anon how they sunk
                    more and more, then began to fall headlong, until he reaches the present
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> times, when we can neither endure our
                    vices, nor their remedies. This it is which is particularly salutary and
                    profitable in the study of history, that you behold instances of every variety
                    of conduct displayed <pb n="4" xml:id="p.4"/> on a conspicuous monument; that
                    from thence you may select for yourself and for your country that which you may
                    imitate; thence <hi rend="italics">note</hi> what is shameful in <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> the undertaking, and shameful in the result, which
                    you may avoid. But either a fond partiality for the task I have undertaken
                    deceives me, or there never was any state either greater, or more moral, or
                    richer in good examples, nor one into which luxury and avarice made their
                    entrance so late, and where poverty and frugality were so much and so long
                    honoured; so that the less wealth there was, the less desire was there. Of late,
                    riches have introduced avarice, and excessive pleasures a longing for them,
                    amidst luxury <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and a passion for ruining
                    ourselves and destroying every thing else. But let complaints, which will not be
                    agreeable even then, when perhaps they will be also necessary, be kept aloof at
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> least from the first stage of commencing
                    so great a work. We should rather, if it was usual with us (historians) as it is
                    with poets, begin with good omens, vows and prayers to the gods and goddesses to
                    vouchsafe good success to our efforts in so arduous an undertaking. </p>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now first of all it is sufficiently
                    established that, Troy having been taken, the utmost severity was shown to all
                    the other Trojans; but that towards two, Aeneas and Antenor, the Greeks forbore
                    all the rights of war, both in accordance with an ancient tie of hospitality,
                    and because they had ever been the advisers of peace, and of the restoration of
                    Helen —then <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that Antenor after various
                    vicissitudes came into the innermost bay of the Adriatic Sea, with a body of the
                    Heneti, who having been driven from Paphlagonia in consequence of a civil
                    commotion, were in quest both of a settlement and a leader, their king
                    Pylaemenes having been lost at Troy; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that
                    the Heneti and Trojans, having expelled the Euganei, who dwelt between the sea
                    and the Alps, took possession of <pb n="5" xml:id="p.5"/> the country; and the
                    place where they first landed is called Troy; from whence also the name of
                    Trojan is given to the canton; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but the nation
                    in general is called Veneti: that Aeneas was driven from home by a similar
                    calamity, but the fates leading him to the founding of a greater empire, he came
                    first to Macedonia: that he sailed from thence to Sicily in quest of a
                    settlement: that from Sicily he made for the Laurentine territory; this place
                    also has the name of Troy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the Trojans,
                    having disembarked there, were driving plunder from the lands, —as being persons
                    to whom, after their almost immeasurable wandering, nothing was left but their
                    arms and ships, —Latinus the king, and the Aborigines, who then occupied those
                    places, assembled in arms from the city and country to repel the violence of the
                    new-comers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On this point the tradition is
                    two-fold: some say, that Latinus, after being overcome in battle, made first a
                    peace, and then an alliance with Aeneas: others, that when the armies were drawn
                    out in battle-array, before the signals were sounded, Latinus advanced to the
                    front of the troops and invited the leader of the adventurers to a conference.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That he then inquired who they were,
                    whence (they had come), or by what casualty they had left their home, and in
                    quest of what they had landed on the Laurentine territory: <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> after he heard that the host were Trojans, their chief
                    Aeneas, the son of Anchises and Venus, and that, driven from their own country
                    and their homes, which had been destroyed by fire, they were seeking a
                    settlement and a place for building a town, struck with admiration of the noble
                    origin of the nation and of the hero, and their spirit, alike prepared for peace
                    or war, he confirmed the assurance of future friendship by giving his right
                    hand: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that upon this a compact was struck
                    between the chiefs, and mutual greetings passed between the armies: that Aeneas
                    was hospitably entertained by Latinus: that Latinus, in the presence of his
                    household gods, added a family league to the public one, by giving Aeneas his
                    daughter in marriage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This event confirms the
                    Trojans in the hope of at length terminating their wanderings by a fixed and
                    permanent settlement. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They build a town.
                    Aeneas calls it Lavinium, after the name of his wife. In a short time, too, a
                    son was the issue of the new marriage, to whom his parents gave the name of
                    Ascanius. <pb n="6" xml:id="p.6"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Aborigines and Trojans were soon after
                    attacked together in war. Turnus, king of the Rutulians, to whom Lavinia had
                    been affianced before the coming of Aeneas, enraged that a stranger had been
                    preferred to himself, made war on Aeneas and Latinus together. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Neither side came off from that contest with cause for
                    rejoicing. The Rutulians were vanquished; the victorious Aborigines and Trojans
                    lost their leader Latinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Upon this Turnus
                    and the Rutulians, diffident of their strength, have recourse to the flourishing
                    state of the Etruscans, and their king Mezentius; who holding his court at Cœre,
                    at that time an opulent town, being by no means pleased, even from the
                    commencement, at the founding of the new city, and then considering that the
                    Trojan power was increasing much more than was altogether consistent with the
                    safety of the neighbouring states, without reluctance joined his forces in
                    alliance with the Rutulians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Aeneas, in order
                    to conciliate the minds of the Aborigines to meet the terror of so serious a
                    war, called both nations Latins, so that they might all be not only under the
                    same laws, but also the same name. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor after
                    that did the Aborigines yield to the Trojans in zeal and fidelity towards their
                    king Aeneas; relying therefore on this disposition of the two nations, who were
                    now daily coalescing more and more, although Etruria was so powerful, that it
                    filled with the fame of its prowess not only the land, but the sea also, through
                    the whole length of Italy, from the Alps to the Sicilian Strait, though he might
                    have repelled the war by means of fortifications, yet he led out his forces to
                    the field. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Upon this a battle ensued
                    successful to the Latins, the last also of the mortal acts of Aeneas. He was
                    buried, by whatever name human and divine laws require him to be called, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Aeneas, being now deified, could not be
                        called by his human name; and in speaking of his being buried, it would be
                        improper to name him by his divine title. — — <hi rend="italics"
                            >Indigetem.</hi> He is called by Dionysius <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >xqo/nios Qeo/s.</foreign>
                    </note> on the banks of the river Numicius. They call him Jupiter Indiges. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ascanius, the son of Aeneas, was not yet old
                    enough to take the government upon him; that government, however, remained
                    secure for him till the age of maturity. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In
                    the interim, the Latin state and the kingdom of his grandfather <pb n="7"
                        xml:id="p.7"/> and father was secured for the boy under the regency of his
                    mother (such capacity was there in Lavinia). I have some doubts (for who can
                    state as certain a matter of such antiquity) whether this was the Ascanius, or
                    one older than he, born of Creusa before the fall of Troy, and the companion of
                    his father in his flight from thence, the same whom, being called Iulus, the
                    Julian family call the author of their name. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    This Ascanius, wheresoever and of whatever mother born, (it is at least certain
                    that he was the son of Aeneas,) Lavinium being overstocked with inhabitants,
                    left that flourishing and, considering these times, wealthy city to his mother
                    or stepmother, and built for himself a new one at the foot of Mount Alba, which,
                    being extended on the ridge of a hill, was, from its situation, called Longa
                    Alba. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Between the founding of Lavinium and the
                    transplanting this colony to Longa Alba, about thirty years intervened. Yet its
                    power had increased to such a degree, especially after the defeat of the
                    Etrurians, that not even upon the death of Aeneas, nor after that, during the
                    regency of Lavinia, and the first essays of the young <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> prince's reign, did Mezentius, the Etrurians, or any other
                    of its neighbours dare to take up arms against it. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> A peace had been concluded between the two nations on these
                    terms, that the river Albula, now called Tiber, should be the common boundary
                    between the Etrurians and Latins. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After him
                    Sylvius, the son of Ascanius, born by some accident in a wood, ascends the
                    throne. He was the father of Aeneas Sylvius, who afterwards begot Latinus
                    Sylvius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By him several colonies, called the
                    ancient Latins, were transplanted. From this time, all the princes, who reigned
                    at Alba, had the surname of Sylvius. From Latinus sprung Alba; from Alba, Atys;
                    from Atys, Capys; from Capys, Capetus; from Capetus, Tiberinus, who, being
                    drowned in crossing the river Albula, gave it a name famous with posterity.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then Agrippa, the son of Tiberinus; after
                    Agrippa, Romulus Silvius ascends the throne, in succession to his father. The
                    latter, having been killed by a thunderbolt, left the kingdom to Aventinus, who
                    being buried on that hill, which is now part of the city of Rome, gave his name
                    to it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After him reigns Proca; he begets
                    Numitor and Amulius. To Numitor, his eldest son, he bequeaths the ancient
                    kingdom of the Sylvian family. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But force
                    prevailed <pb n="8" xml:id="p.8"/> more than the father's will or the respect
                    due to seniority: for Amulius, having expelled his brother, seizes the kingdom;
                    he adds crime to crime, murders his brother's male issue; and under pretence of
                    doing his brother's daughter, Rhea Sylvia, honour, having made her a vestal
                    virgin, by obliging her to perpetual virginity he deprives her of all hopes of
                    issue. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But, in my opinion, the origin of so great a
                    city, and the establishment of an empire next in power to that of the gods, was
                    due to the Fates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The vestal Rhea, being
                    deflowered by force, when she had brought forth twins, declares Mars to be the
                    father of her illegitimate offspring, either because she believed it to be so,
                    or because a god was a more creditable author of her offence. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But neither gods nor men protect her or her children from
                    the king's cruelty: the priestess is bound and thrown into prison; the children
                    he commands to be thrown into the current of the river. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> By some interposition of providence, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Forte quâdam divinitus.</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="greek">qei/a| tini tu/xh|.</foreign> Plut. </note> the
                    Tiber having overflowed its banks in stagnant pools, did not admit of any access
                    to the regular bed of the river; and the bearers supposed that the infants could
                    be drowned in water however still; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> thus, as if
                    they had effectually executed the king's orders, they expose the boys in the
                    nearest land-flood, where now stands the ficus Ruminalis (they say that it was
                    called Romularis). The country thereabout was then a vast wilderness. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The tradition is, that when the water, subsiding, had
                    left the floating trough, in which the children had been exposed, on dry ground,
                    a thirsty she-wolf, coming from the neighbouring mountains, directed her course
                    to the cries of the infants, and that she held down her dugs to them with so
                    much gentleness, that the keeper of the king's flock found her licking the boys
                    with her tongue. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It is said his name was
                    Faustulus; and that they were carried by him to his homestead to be nursed by
                    his wife Laurentia. Some are of opinion that she was called Lupa among the
                    shepherds, from her being a common prostitute, and that this gave rise to the
                    surprising story. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The children thus born and
                    thus brought up, when arrived at the years of manhood, did not loiter away their
                    time in tending the folds or following the flocks, but roamed and hunted in the
                    forests. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="9" xml:id="p.9"/> Having by this exercise improved their strength and
                    courage, they not only encountered wild beasts, but even attacked robbers laden
                    with plunder, and afterwards divided the spoil among the shepherds. And in
                    company with these, the number of their young associates daily increasing, they
                    carried on their business and their sports. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They say, that the festival of the lupercal,
                    as now celebrated, was even at that time solemnized on the Palatine hill, which,
                    from Palanteum, a city of Arcadia, was first called Palatium, and afterwards
                    Mount Palatine. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There they say that Evander,
                    who belonged to the tribe of Arcadians, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Scil. <quote>The Pallantean.</quote>
                    </note> that for many years before had possessed that country, appointed the
                    observance of a feast, introduced from Arcadia, in such manner, that young men
                    ran about naked in sport and wantonness, doing honour to Pan Lycaeus, whom the
                    Romans afterwards called Inuus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the
                    robbers, through rage at the loss of their booty, having lain in wait for them
                    whilst intent on this sport, as the festival was now well known, whilst Romulus
                    vigorously defended himself, took Remus prisoner; that they delivered him up,
                    when taken, to king Amulius, accusing him with the utmost effrontery. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> They principally alleged it as a charge against them,
                    that they had made incursions upon Numitor's lands, and plundered them in a
                    hostile manner, having assembled a band of young men for the purpose. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Upon this Remus was delivered to Numitor to be
                    punished. Now, from the very first, Faustulus had entertained hopes that the
                    boys whom he was bringing up were of the blood royal; for he both knew that the
                    children had been exposed by the king's orders, and that the time at which he
                    had taken them up agreed exactly with that period: but he had been unwilling
                    that the matter, as not being yet ripe for discovery, should be disclosed, till
                    either a fit opportunity or necessity should arise. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Necessity came first; accordingly, compelled by fear, he
                    discovers the whole affair to Romulus. By accident also, whilst he had Remus in
                    custody, and had heard that the brothers were twins, on comparing their age, and
                        <hi rend="italics">observing</hi> their turn of mind entirely free from
                    servility, the recollection of his grand-children struck Numitor; and on making
                        <pb n="10" xml:id="p.10"/> inquiries <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> By all his inquiries he arrived at the same conclusion
                        as before, viz. that they were his grand-children. </note> he arrived at the
                    same conclusion, so that he was well nigh recognising Remus. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Thus a plot is concerted for the king on all sides.
                    Romulus, not accompanied by a body of young men, (for he was unequal to open
                    force,) but having commanded the shepherds to come to the palace by different
                    roads at a fixed time, forces his way to the king; and Remus, with another party
                    from Numitor's house, assists his brother, and so they kill the king. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Numitor, at the beginning of the fray, having
                    given out that enemies had invaded the city, and assaulted the palace, after he
                    had drawn off the Alban youth to secure the citadel with a garrison and arms,
                    when he saw the young men, after they had killed the king, advancing to
                    congratulate him, immediately called an assembly of the people, and represented
                    to them the unnatural behaviour of his brother towards him, the extraction of
                    his grand-children, the manner of their birth and education, and how they came
                    to be discovered; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> then he informed them of the
                    king's death, and that he was killed by his orders. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When the young princes, coming up with their band through
                    the middle of the assembly, saluted their grandfather king, an approving shout,
                    following from all the people present, ratified to him both that title and the
                    sovereignty. Thus the government of Alba being committed to Numitor, a desire
                    seized Romulus and Remus to build a city on the spot where they had been exposed
                    and brought up. And there was an overflowing population of Albans and of Latins.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The shepherds too had come into that
                    design, and all these readily inspired hopes, that Alba and Lavinium would be
                    but petty places in comparison with the city which they intended to build. But
                    ambition of the sovereignty, the bane of their grandfather, interrupted these
                    designs, and thence arose a shameful quarrel from a beginning sufficiently
                    amicable. For as they were twins, and the respect due to seniority could not
                    determine the point, they agreed to leave to the tutelary gods of the place to
                    choose, by augury, which should give a name to the new city, which govern it
                    when built. <pb n="11" xml:id="p.11"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Romulus chose the Palatine and Remus the
                    Aventine hill as their stands to make their observations. It is said, that to
                    Remus an omen came first, six vultures; and now, the omen having been declared,
                    when double the number presented itself to Romulus, his own party saluted each
                    king; the former claimed the kingdom on the ground of priority of time, the
                    latter on account of the number of birds. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Upon
                    this, having met in an altercation, from the contest of angry feelings they turn
                    to bloodshed; there Remus fell from a blow received in the crowd. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> A more common account is, that Remus, in derision of
                    his brother, leaped over his new-built wall, and was, for that reason, slain by
                    Romulus in a passion; who, after sharply chiding him, added words to this
                    effect: <quote>So shall every one fare, who shall dare to leap over my
                        fortifications.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Cato, Rome was founded
                        on the day of the <hi rend="italics">Palilia,</hi> the 11th of the Calends
                        of May, in the first year of the 7th Olympiad, and 751 B. C. This is two
                        years short of Varro's computation. </note> Thus Romulus got the sovereignty
                    to himself; the city, when built, was called after the name of its founder.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His first work was to fortify the Palatine
                    hill where he had been educated. To the other gods he offers sacrifices
                    according to the Alban rite; to Hercules, according to the Grecian rite, as they
                    had been instituted by Evander. There is a tradition, that Hercules, having
                    killed Geryon, drove his oxen, which were extremely beautiful, into those
                    places; and that, after swimming over the Tiber, and driving the cattle before
                    him, being fatigued with travelling, he laid himself down on the banks of the
                    river, in a grassy place, to refresh them with rest and rich pasture. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> When sleep had overpowered him, satiated with food
                    and wine, a shepherd of the place, named Cacus, presuming on his strength, and
                    charmed with the beauty of the oxen, wished to purloin that booty, but because,
                    if he had driven them forward into the cave, their footsteps would have guided
                    the search of their owner thither, he therefore drew the most beautiful of them,
                    one by one, by the tails, backwards into a cave. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Hercules, awaking at daybreak, when he had surveyed his herd, and observed
                    that some of them were missing, goes directly to the nearest cave, to see if by
                    chance their footsteps would lead him thither. But when he observed that they
                    were all turned from it, and directed him no other way, confounded, and not
                    knowing what to do, he <pb n="12" xml:id="p.12"/> began to drive his cattle out
                    of that unlucky place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Upon this, some of the
                    cows, as they usually do, lowed on missing those that were left; and the lowings
                    of those that were confined being returned from the cave, made Hercules turn
                    that way. And when Cacus attempted to prevent him by force, as he was proceeding
                    to the cave, being struck with a club, he was slain, vainly imploring the
                    assistance of the shepherds. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At that time
                    Evander, who had fled from the Peloponnesus, ruled this country more by his
                    credit and reputation than absolute sway. He was a person highly revered for his
                    wondrous knowledge of letters, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">He
                        taught the Italians to read and write.</note> a discovery that was entirely
                    new and surprising to men ignorant of every art; but more highly respected on
                    account of the supposed divinity of his mother Carmenta, whom these nations had
                    admired as a prophetess, before the coming of the Sibyl into Italy. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> This prince, alarmed by the concourse of the
                    shepherds hastily crowding round the stranger, whom they charged with open
                    murder, after he heard the act and the cause of the act, observing the person
                    and mien of the hero to be larger, and his gait more majestic, than human, asked
                    who he was? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As soon as he was informed of his
                    name, his father, and his native country, he said, <quote> Hail! Hercules! son
                        of Jupiter, my mother, a truth-telling interpreter of the gods, has revealed
                        to me, that thou shalt increase the number of the celestials; <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> and that to thee an altar shall be dedicated
                        here, which some ages hence the most powerful people on earth shall call Ara
                        Maxima, and honour according to thy own institution. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hercules having given him his right hand,
                    said, <quote> That he accepted the omen, and would fulfil the predictions of the
                        fates, by building and consecrating an altar. </quote> There for the first
                    time a sacrifice was offered to Hercules of a chosen heifer, taken from the
                    herd, the Potitii and Pinarii, who were then the most distinguished families
                    that inhabited these parts, having been invited to the service and the
                    entertainment. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It so happened that the
                    Potitii were present in due time, and the entrails were set before them; when
                    they were eaten up, the Pinarii came to the remainder of the feast. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> From this time it was ordained, that while the
                    Pinarian family subsisted, none of them should eat of the entrails of the solemn
                    sacri- <pb n="13" xml:id="p.13"/> fices. The Potitii, being instructed by
                    Evander, discharged this sacred function as priests for many ages, until the
                    office, solemnly appropriated to their family, being delegated to public slaves,
                    their whole race became extinct. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This was the
                    only foreign religious institution which Romulus adopted, being even then an
                    abettor of immortality attained by merit, to which his own destinies were
                    conducting him. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The duties of religion having been duly
                    performed, and the multitude summoned to a meeting, as they could be
                    incorporated into one people by no other means than fixed rules, he gave them a
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> code of laws, and judging that these
                    would be best respected by this rude class of men, if he made himself dignified
                    by the insignia of authority, he assumed a more majestic appearance both in his
                    other appointments, and especially by taking twelve lictors to attend him.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some think that he chose this number of
                    officers from that of the birds, which in the augury had portended the kingdom
                    to him. I do not object to be of the opinion of those who will have it that the
                    apparitors (in general), and this particular class of them, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Apparitores hoc genus.</hi> There is something incorrect
                        in the language of the original here. In my version I have followed
                        Drakenborch. Walker, in his edition, proposes to read <hi rend="italics"
                            >ut</hi> for <hi rend="italics">et;</hi> thus, <hi rend="italics">
                            quibus ut apparitores et hoc genus ab Etruscis —numerum quoque ipsum
                            ductum placet, "who will have it, that as public servants of this kind,
                            so was their number also, derived from the Etrurians. </hi>
                    </note> and even their number, was taken from their neighbours the Etrurians,
                    from whom were borrowed the curule chair, and the gown edged with purple; and
                    that the Etrurians adopted that number, because their king being elected in
                    common from twelve states, each state assigned him one <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> lictor. Meanwhile the city increased by their taking in
                    various lots of ground for buildings, whilst they built rather with a view to
                    future numbers, than for the population <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The population at that time consisted of not more than
                        3,000 foot, and less than 300 horse. At the death of Romulus, it is said to
                        have amounted to 46,000 foot and almost 1,000 horse. </note> which they then
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> had. Then, lest the size of the city might
                    be of no avail, in order to augment the population, according to the ancient
                    policy of the founders of cities, who, after drawing together to them an obscure
                    and mean multitude, used to feign that their offspring sprung out of the earth,
                    he opened as a <pb n="14" xml:id="p.14"/> sanctuary, a place which is now
                    enclosed as you go down <quote> to the two <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        groves. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="greek"> to\ metacu\ xwri/on tou= te Kapitwli/on kai\ th=s
                            a)/kras o(/ kalei=tai nu=n kaia\ th\n *(rwmai/wn dia/lekton meqo/rion
                            duoi=n drumw=n. </foreign> Dio. ii. 15. </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Ex industria —deditâ operâ</hi> — <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">apo\ paraskeuh=s.</foreign>
                    </note> Hither fled from the neighbouring states, without distinction whether
                    freemen or slaves, crowds of all sorts, desirous of change: and this was the
                    first accession of strength to <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> their rising
                    greatness. When he was now not dissatisfied with his strength, he next sets
                    about forming some means of directing that strength. He creates one hundred
                    senators, either because that number was sufficient, or because there were only
                    one hundred who could name their fathers. They certainly were called Fathers,
                    through respect, and their descendants, Patricians. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And now the Roman state was become so
                    powerful, that it was a match for any of the neighbouring nations in war, but,
                    from the paucity of women, its greatness could only last for one age of man; for
                    they had no hope of issue at home, nor had they any intermarriages with their
                    neighbours. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Therefore, by the advice of the
                    Fathers, Romulus sent ambassadors to the neighbouring states to solicit an
                    alliance and the privilege of intermarriage for his new subjects. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That cities, like every thing else, rose from very humble beginnings.
                        That those which the gods and their own merit aided, gained great power and
                        high renown. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That he knew full well, both
                        that the gods had aided the origin of Rome, and that merit would not be
                        wanting. Wherefore that, as men, they should feel no reluctance to mix their
                        blood and race with men. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No where did the embassy obtain a favourable
                    hearing: so much did they at the same time despise, and dread for themselves and
                    their posterity, so great a power growing up in the midst of them. They were
                    dismissed by the greater part with the repeated question, <quote> Whether they
                        had opened any asylum for women also, for that such a plan only could obtain
                        them suitable matches? </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman youth resented this conduct
                    bitterly, and the matter unquestionably began to point towards violence.
                    Romulus, in order that he might afford a favourable time and place for this,
                    dissembling his resentment, purposely prepares games in honour of Neptunus
                    Equestris; he calls them Consualia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then
                        <pb n="15" xml:id="p.15"/> orders the spectacle to be proclaimed among their
                    neighbours; and they prepare for the celebration with all the magnificence they
                    were then acquainted with, or were capable of doing, that they might render the
                    matter famous, and an object of expectation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Great numbers assembled, from a desire also of seeing the new city; especially
                    their nearest neighbours, the Caeninenses, Crustumini, and Antemnates. Moreover
                    the whole multitude of the Sabines came, with their wives and children.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having been hospitably invited to the
                    different houses, when they had seen the situation, and fortifications, and the
                    city crowded with houses, they became astonished that the Roman power had
                    increased so rapidly. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the time of the
                    spectacle came on, and while their minds and eyes were intent upon it, according
                    to concert a tumult began, and upon a signal given the Roman youth ran different
                    ways to carry off the virgins by force. A great number were carried off at
                    hap-hazard, according as they fell into their hands. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Persons from the common people, who had been charged with
                    the task, conveyed to their houses some women of surpassing beauty, destined for
                    the leading senators. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They say that one, far
                    distinguished beyond the others for stature and beauty, was carried off by the
                    party of one Thalassius, and whilst many inquired to whom they were carrying
                    her, they cried out every now and then, in order that no one might molest her,
                    that she was being taken to Thalassius; that from this circumstance this term
                    became a nuptial one. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The festival being
                    disturbed by this alarm, the parents of the young women retire in grief,
                    appealing to the compact of violated hospitality, and invoking the god, to whose
                    festival and games they had come, deceived by the pretence of religion and good
                    faith. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Neither had the ravished virgins
                    better hopes of their condition, or less indignation. But Romulus in person went
                    about and declared, <quote> That what was done was owing to the pride of their
                        fathers, who had refused to grant the privilege of marriage to their
                        neighbours; but notwithstanding, they should be joined in lawful wedlock,
                        participate in all their possessions and civil privileges, and, than which
                        nothing can be dearer to the human heart, in their common children.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He begged them only to assuage the
                        fierceness of their anger, and cheerfully surrender their affections to
                        those to whom fortune had con <pb n="16" xml:id="p.16"/> signed their
                        persons. </quote> [He added,] <quote> That from injuries love and friendship
                        often arise; and that they should find them kinder husbands on this account,
                        because each of them, besides the performance of his conjugal duty, would
                        endeavour to the utmost of his power to make up for the want of their
                        parents and native country. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> To this the caresses of the husbands were
                    added, excusing what they had done on the plea of passion and love, arguments
                    that work most successfully on women's hearts. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The minds of the ravished virgins were soon
                    much soothed, but their parents by putting on mourning, and tears and
                    complaints, roused the states. Nor did they confine their resentment to their
                    own homes, but they flocked from all quarters to Titus Tatius, king of the
                    Sabines; and because he bore the greatest character in these parts, embassies
                    were sent to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Caeninenses, Crustumini,
                    and Antemnates were people to whom a considerable portion of the outrage
                    extended. To them Tatius and the Sabines seemed to proceed somewhat dilatorily.
                    Nor even do the Crustumini and Antemnates bestir themselves with sufficient
                    activity to suit the impatience and rage of the Caeninenses. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the state of the Caeninenses by itself makes an
                    irruption into the Roman territory. But Romulus with his army met them ravaging
                    the country in straggling parties, and by a slight engagement convinces them,
                    that resentment without strength is of no avail. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> He defeats and routs their army, pursues it when routed, kills and despoils
                    their king in battle, and having slain their general takes the city at the first
                    assault. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From thence having led back his
                    victorious army, and being a man highly distinguished by his exploits, and one
                    who could place them in the best light, went in state to the capitol, carrying
                    before him, suspended on a frame curiously wrought for that purpose, the spoils
                    of the enemy's general, whom he had slain, and there after he had laid them down
                    at the foot of an oak held sacred by the shepherds, together with the offering,
                    he marked out the bounds for a temple of Jupiter, and gave a surname to the god:
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Jupiter Feretrius,</quote> he says, <quote> I, king Romulus, upon my
                        victory, present to thee these royal arms, and to thee I dedicate a temple
                        within those regions which I have now marked out in my mind, as a receptacle
                        for the grand spoils, which my suc- <pb n="17" xml:id="p.17"/> cessors,
                        following my example, shall, upon their killing the kings or generals of the
                        enemy, offer to thee. </quote> This is the origin of that temple, the first
                    consecrated at Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It afterwards so pleased
                    the gods both that the declaration of the founder of the temple should not be
                    frustrated, by which he announced that his posterity should offer such spoils,
                    and that the glory of that offering should not be depreciated by the great
                    number of those who shared it. During so many years, and amid so many wars since
                    that time, grand spoils have been only twice gained, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Two, one by A. Cornelius Cossus for slaying L.
                        Tolumnius, king of Veii, U. C. 318, another by M. Claudius Marcellus, for
                        killing Viridomarus, king of the Gauls, U. C. 532. </note> so rare has been
                    the successful attainment of that honour. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans are achieving these
                    exploits, the army of the Antemnates, taking advantage of their absence, makes
                    an incursion into the Roman territories in a hostile manner. A Roman legion
                    being marched out in haste against these also, surprise them whilst straggling
                    through the fields. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly the enemy were
                    routed at the very first shout and charge: their town taken; and as Romulus was
                    returning, exulting for this double victory, his consort, Hersilia, importuned
                    by the entreaties of the captured women, beseeches him <quote> to pardon their
                        fathers, and to admit them to the privilege of citizens; that thus his power
                        might be strengthened by a reconciliation. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Her request was readily granted. After this he
                    marched against the Crustumini, who were commencing hostilities; but as their
                    spirits were sunk by the defeat of their neighbours, there was still less
                    resistance there. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Colonies were sent to both
                    places, but more were found to give in their names for Crustuminum, because of
                    the fertility of the soil. Migrations in great numbers were also made from
                    thence to Rome, chiefly by the parents and relatives of the ravished women.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The last war broke out on the part of the
                    Sabines, and proved by far the most formidable: for they did nothing through
                    anger or cupidity; nor did they make a show of war, before they actually began
                    it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To prudence stratagem also was added. Sp.
                    Tarpeius commanded the Roman citadel; Tatius bribes his maiden daughter with
                    gold, to admit armed soldiers into the citadel: she had gone by chance outside
                    the walls to fetch water for the sacrifice. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Those <pb n="18" xml:id="p.18"/> who were admitted crushed her to death by
                    heaping their arms upon her; either that the citadel might seem rather to have
                    been taken by storm, or for the purpose of establishing a precedent, that no
                    faith should, under any circumstances, be kept with a traitor. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A story is added, that the Sabines commonly wore on their
                    left arm golden bracelets of great weight, and large rings set with precious
                    stones, and that she bargained with them for what they had on their left hands;
                    hence that their shields were thrown upon her instead of the golden presents.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There are some who say that in pursuance
                    of the compact to deliver up what was on their left hands, she expressly
                    demanded their shields, and that appearing to act with treachery, she was killed
                    by the reward of her own choosing. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Sabines, however, kept possession of the
                    citadel, and on the day after, when the Roman army, drawn up in order of battle,
                    filled up all the ground lying between the Palatine and Capitoline hills, they
                    did not descend from thence into the plain, till the Romans, fired with
                    resentment, and with a desire of retaking the citadel, advanced to attack them.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two chiefs, one on each side, animated the
                    battle, viz. Mettus Curtius on the part of the Sabines, Hostus Hostilius on that
                    of the Romans. The latter, in the front ranks, supported the Roman cause by his
                    courage and bravery, on disadvantageous ground. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> As soon as Hostus fell, the Roman line immediately gave way and was beaten to
                    the old gate of the Palatium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Romulus, himself
                    too carried away with the general rout, raising his arms to heaven, says,
                        <quote> O Jupiter, commanded by thy birds, I here laid the first foundation
                        of the city on the Palatine hill. The Sabines are in possession of the
                        citadel, purchased by fraud. From thence they are now advancing hither,
                        sword in hand, having already passed the middle of the valley. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> But do thou, father of gods and men, keep back
                        the enemy at least from hence, dispel the terror of the Romans, and stop
                        their shameful flight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here I solemnly vow
                        to build a temple to thee as Jupiter Stator, as a monument to posterity,
                        that this city was saved by thy immediate aid. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having offered up this prayer, as if he had
                    felt that his prayers were heard, he cries out, <quote> At this spot, Romans,
                        Jupiter, supremely good and great, commands you to halt, and renew the
                        fight. </quote> The Romans halted as if they had been commanded by a <pb
                        n="19" xml:id="p.19"/> voice from heaven; Romulus himself flies to the
                    foremost ranks. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Mettus Curtius, on the part of
                    the Sabines, had rushed down at the head of his army from the citadel, and
                    driven the Romans in disorder over the whole ground now occupied by the forum.
                    He was already not far from the gate of the Palatium, crying out, <quote> We
                        have defeated these perfidious strangers, these dastardly enemies. They now
                        feel that it is one thing to ravish virgins, another far different to fight
                        with men. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On him, thus vaunting, Romulus makes an attack
                    with a band of the most courageous youths. It happened that Mettus was then
                    fighting on horseback; he was on that account the more easily repulsed: the
                    Romans pursue him when repulsed: and the rest of the Roman army, encouraged by
                    the gallant behaviour of their king, routs the Sabines. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Mettus, his horse taking fright at the din of his pursuers,
                    threw himself into a lake; and this circumstance drew the attention of the
                    Sabines at the risk of so important a person. He, however, his own party
                    beckoning and calling to him, acquires new courage from the affection of his
                    many friends, and makes his escape. The Romans and Sabines renew the battle in
                    the valley between the hills; but Roman prowess had the advantage. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this juncture the Sabine women, from the
                    outrage on whom the war originated, with hair dishevelled and garments rent, the
                    timidity of their sex being overcome by such dreadful scenes, had the courage to
                    throw themselves amid the flying weapons, and making a rush across, to part the
                    incensed armies, and assuage their fury; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    imploring their fathers on the one side, their husbands on the other, <quote>
                        that as fathers-in-law and sons-in-law they would not contaminate each other
                        with impious blood, nor stain their offspring with parricide, the one <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">Nepotum et liberûm progeniem</hi> = Nepotes et
                            liberos, — <foreign xml:lang="greek">u(/ies 'Axaiwn</foreign> = <foreign
                                xml:lang="greek">oi(/ 'Axaioi.</foreign>
                        </note> their grandchildren, the other their <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> children. If you are dissatisfied with the affinity between you, if with
                        our marriages, turn your resentment against us; we are the cause of war, we
                        of wounds and of bloodshed to our husbands and parents. It were better that
                        we perish than live widowed or fatherless without one or other of <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> you. </quote> The circumstance affects both the
                    multitude and the leaders. Silence and a sudden suspension ensue. Upon this the
                    leaders <pb n="20" xml:id="p.20"/> come forward in order to concert a treaty,
                    and they not only conclude a peace, but form one state out of <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> two. They associate the regal power, and transfer the
                    entire sovereignty to Rome. The city being thus doubled, that some compliment
                    might be paid to the Sabines, they were called Quirites, from <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Cures. As a memorial of this battle, they called the place
                    where the horse, after getting out of the deep marsh, first set Curtius in
                    shallow water, the Curtian Lake. This happy peace following suddenly a war so
                    distressing, rendered the Sabine women still dearer to their husbands and
                    parents, and above all to Romulus <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> himself.
                    Accordingly, when he divided the people into thirty curiae, he called the curiae
                    by their names. Since, without doubt, the number of the Sabine women was
                    considerably greater than this, it is not recorded whether those who were to
                    give their names to the curiae were selected on account of their age, or their
                    own or their husbands' rank, or by <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> lot. At the
                    same time three centuries of knights were enrolled, called Ramnenses, from
                    Romulus; Tatienses, from Titus Tatius. The reason of the name and origin of the
                    Luceres is uncertain. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thenceforward the two kings held the regal
                    power not only in common, but in concord also. Several years after, some
                    relatives of king Tatius beat the ambassadors of the Laurentes, and when the
                    Laurentes commenced proceedings according to the law <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> of nations, the influence of his friends and their
                    importunities had more weight with Tatius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                    therefore drew upon himself the punishment due to them; for he is slain at
                    Lavinium, in a tumult which arose on his going thither to an anniversary
                    sacrifice. They say that Romulus resented this with less severity than the case
                    required, either by reason of their association in the kingly power being devoid
                    of cordiality, or because he believed that he was justly killed. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> He therefore declined going to war; in order,
                    however, that the ill-treatment of the ambassadors and the murder of the king
                    might be expiated, the treaty was renewed between the cities of Rome and
                    Lavinium. With this party, indeed, peace continued, contrary to expectation;
                    another war broke out much nearer home, and almost at the very gates. The
                    Fidenates, thinking that a power too near to themselves was growing to a height,
                    resolve to make war, before their strength should become as great as it was
                    apparent it would <pb n="21" xml:id="p.21"/> be. An armed body of young men
                    being sent in, all the land is laid waste between the city and Fidenae.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then turning to the left, because the
                    Tiber confined them on the right, they continue their depredations to the great
                    consternation of the peasantry. The sudden alarm reaching the city from the
                    country, served as the first announcement. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Romulus, roused at this circumstance, (for a war so near home could not admit of
                    delay,) leads out his army: he pitches his camp a mile from Fidenae. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Having left there a small garrison, marching out with
                    all his forces, he commanded a party of his soldiers to lie in ambush in a place
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The original has undergone
                        various changes here: my version coincides with the reading, <hi
                            rend="italics">locis circà densa obsita virgulta obscuris.</hi>
                    </note> hidden by thick bushes which were planted around. Then advancing with
                    the greater part of the foot and all the horse, and riding up to the very gates
                    of the city in a disorderly and menacing manner, he drew out the enemy, the very
                    thing he wanted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The same mode of fighting on
                    the part of the cavalry likewise made the cause of the flight, which was to be
                    counterfeited, appear less surprising: and when, the horse seeming irresolute,
                    as if in deliberation whether to fight or fly, the infantry also retreated, the
                    enemy suddenly rushed from the crowded gates, after they had made an impression
                    on the Roman line, are drawn on to the place of ambuscade in their eagerness to
                    press on and pursue. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Upon this the Romans,
                    rising suddenly, attack the enemy's line in flank. The standards of those who
                    had been left behind on guard, advancing from the camp, further increase the
                    panic. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Fidenates, thus dismayed with
                    terrors from so many quarters, turn their backs almost before Romulus, and those
                    who had accompanied him on horseback, could wheel their horses round; and those
                    who a little before had pursued men pretending to fly, now ran back to the town
                    in much greater disorder, for their flight was in earnest. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They did not however get clear of the enemy: the Romans
                    pressing on their rear rush in as it were in one body before the gates could be
                    shut against them. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The minds of the Veientes being excited by the
                    contagious influence of the Fidenatian war, both from the tie of consanguinity,
                    for the Fidenates also were Etrurians, and because the very proximity of
                    situation, in case the Roman arms <pb n="22" xml:id="p.22"/> should be turned
                    against all their neighbours, urged them on, they made an incursion on the Roman
                    territories, more to commit depredations than after the manner of a regular war.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly, without pitching a camp, or
                    awaiting the approach of the enemy's army, they returned to Veii, carrying with
                    them the booty collected from the lands; the Roman army on the other side, when
                    they did not find the enemy in the country, being prepared for and determined on
                    a decisive action, cross the Tiber. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when
                    the Veientes heard that they were pitching a camp, and intended to advance to
                    the city, they came out to meet them, that they might rather decide the matter
                    in the open field, than be shut up and fight from their houses and walls.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here the Roman king obtained the victory,
                    his power not being aided by any stratagem, merely by the strength of his
                    veteran army: and having pursued the routed enemies to their walls, he made no
                    attempt on the city, strong as it was by its fortifications, and well defended
                    by its situation: on his return he lays waste their lands, rather from a desire
                    of revenge than booty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And the Veientes, being
                    humbled by that loss no less than by the unsuccessful battle, send ambassadors
                    to Rome to sue for peace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A truce for one
                    hundred years was granted them after they were fined a part of their land. These
                    are the principal transactions which occurred during the reign of Romulus, in
                    peace and war, none of which seem inconsistent with the belief of his divine
                    original, or of the deification attributed to him after death, neither his
                    spirit in recovering his <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> grandfather's
                    kingdom, nor his project of building a city, nor that of strengthening it by the
                    arts of war and peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For by the strength
                    attained from that outset under him, it became so powerful, that for forty years
                    after it enjoyed a profound peace. He was, however, dearer to the people than to
                    the fathers; but above all others he was most beloved by the soldiers. And he
                    kept three hundred of them armed as a body-guard not only in war but in peace,
                    whom he called Celeres. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After performing these immortal achievements,
                    while lie was holding an assembly of the people for reviewing his army, in the
                    plain near the lake of Capra, on a sudden a storm having arisen, with great
                    thunder and lightning, enveloped the king in so dense a mist, that it took all
                    sight of him from the assembly. Nor was Romulus after this <pb n="23"
                        xml:id="p.23"/> seen on earth. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    consternation being at length over, and fine clear weather succeeding so
                    turbulent a day, when the Roman youth saw the royal seat empty, though they
                    readily believed the fathers who had stood nearest him, that he was carried
                    aloft by the storm, yet, struck with the dread as it were of orphanage, they
                    preserved a sorrowful silence for a considerable time. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Then, a commencement having been made by a few, the whole
                    multitude salute Romulus a god, son of a god, the king and parent of the Roman
                    city; they implore his favour with prayers, that he would be pleased always
                    propitiously to preserve his own offspring. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I
                    believe that even then there were some, who silently surmised that the king had
                    been torn in pieces by the hands of the fathers; for this rumour also spread,
                    but was not credited; their admiration of the man, and the consternation felt at
                    the moment, attached importance to the other report. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> By the contrivance also of one individual, additional
                    credit is said to have been gained to the matter. For Proculus Julius, whilst
                    the state was still troubled with regret for the king, and felt incensed against
                    the senators, a person of weight, as we are told, in any matter however
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> important, comes forward to the
                    assembly, <quote>Romans,</quote> he says, <quote> Romulus, the father of this
                        city, suddenly descending from heaven, appeared to me this day at day-break.
                        While I stood covered with awe, and filled with a religious dread,
                        beseeching him to allow me to see him face to face, he said, Go tell the
                        Romans, that the gods so will, that my Rome should become the capitol of the
                        world. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Therefore let them cultivate the
                        art of war, and let them know and hand down to posterity, that no human
                        power shall be able to withstand the Roman arms. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Having said this, he ascended up to heaven. </quote> It
                    is surprising what credit was given to the man on his making this announcement,
                    and how much the regret of the common people and army, for the lids of Romulus,
                    was assuaged upon the assurance of his immortality. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile ambition and contention for the
                    throne actuated the minds of the fathers; factions had not yet sprung up from
                    individuals, because, among a new people, no one person was eminently
                    distinguished above the rest: the contest was carried on between the different
                    orders. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The descendants of the Sabines wished
                    a king to be elected <pb n="24" xml:id="p.24"/> out of their body, lest, because
                    there had been no king on their side since the death of Tatius, they might lose
                    their claim to the crown <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Although,
                        according to the terms of the alliance, the Sabines and the Romans were to
                        be in all respects on an equal footing. </note> according to the compact of
                    equal participation. The old Romans spurned the idea of a foreign prince.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Amid this diversity of views, however, all
                    were anxious that there should be a king, they not having yet tasted the sweets
                    of liberty. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fear then seized the senators,
                    lest the minds of the surrounding states being incensed against them, some
                    foreign power should attack the state, now without a government, and the army
                    without a leader. It was therefore their wish that there should be some head,
                    but no one could bring himself to give way to another. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Thus the hundred senators divide the government among them,
                    ten decuries being formed, and one selected from each decury, who was to have
                    the chief direction of affairs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Ten governed;
                    one only was attended with the insignia of authority and the lictors: their
                    power was limited to the space of five days, and it passed through all in
                    rotation, and the interval between a kingly government lasted a year. From the
                    circumstance it was called an Interregnum, a term which holds good even now.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the people began to murmur, that their
                    slavery was multiplied, and that they had got a hundred sovereigns instead of
                    one, and they seemed determined to bear no authority but that of a king, and
                    that one of their own choosing. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the
                    fathers perceived that such schemes were in agitation, thinking it advisable to
                    offer them, of their own accord, what they were sure to lose; they thus
                    conciliate the favour of the people by yielding to them the supreme power, yet
                    in such a manner as to grant them no greater privilege than they reserved to
                    themselves. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For they decreed, that when the
                    people should choose a king, the election should be valid, if the senate
                    approved. And <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The order of the people
                        still requires the sanction of the senate for its ratification: but that
                        sanction now being given beforehand, the order of the people is no longer
                        subject to the control of the senate, and therefore not precarious as
                        heretofore. </note> the same forms are observed at this day in passing laws
                    and electing magistrates, though their efficacy has been taken away; for before
                    the people begin to vote, the senators declare their approbation, whilst the
                    result of the elections is still uncertain. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="25" xml:id="p.25"/> Then the interrex, having called an assembly of the
                    people, addressed them in this manner: <quote> Do you, Romans, choose yourselves
                        a king, and may it prove fortunate, happy, and auspicious to you; so the
                        fathers have determined. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then, if you
                        choose a prince worthy to succeed Romulus, the fathers will confirm your
                        choice. </quote> This concession was so pleasing to the people, that, not to
                    be outdone in generosity, they only voted, and required that the senate should
                    determine who should be king of Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The justice and piety of Numa Pompilius was at
                    that time celebrated. He dwelt at Cures, a city of the Sabines, and was as
                    eminently learned in all laws human and divine, as any man could be in that age.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They falsely represent that Pythagoras of
                    Samos was his instructor in philosophy, because there appears no other person to
                    refer to. Now it is certain that this philosopher, in the reign of Servius
                    Tullius, more than a hundred years after this, held assemblies of young men, who
                    eagerly imbibed his doctrine, in the most distant part of Italy, about
                    Metapontus, Heraclea, and Croton. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics"> Ex quibus locis, quae fama in Sabinos, aut quo linguae
                            commercio —quenquam excivisset. </hi>
                        <quote> From which (remote) places, what high character of him (could have
                            reached) to the Sabines, or by what intercourse of language could such
                            high character of him have aroused any one to become a pupil? </quote>
                        Other editions read <hi rend="italics">quâ famâ;</hi> thus, from which
                        places by what high character for talent, or by what intercourse of
                        language, could he, Pythagoras, have aroused any one, etc.? </note> from
                    these places, even had he flourished at the same time, what fame of his
                    (extending) to the Sabines could have aroused any one to a desire of learning,
                    or by what intercourse of language (could such a thing have been effected)?
                    Besides, how could a single man have safely passed through so many nations
                    differing in language and <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> customs? I presume,
                    therefore, that his mind was naturally furnished with virtuous dispositions, and
                    that he was not so much versed in foreign sciences as in the severe and rigid
                    discipline of the ancient Sabines, than which class none was in former times
                    more <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> strict. The Roman fathers, upon hearing
                    the name of Numa, although they perceived that the scale of power would incline
                    to the Sabines if a king were chosen from them, yet none of them ventured to
                    prefer himself, or any other of his party, or any of the citizens or fathers, to
                    that person, but unanimously resolved that the kingdom should be conferred on
                    Numa <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Pompilius. Being <pb n="26" xml:id="p.26"
                    /> sent for, just as Romulus before the building of the city obtained the throne
                    by an augury, he commanded the gods to be consulted concerning himself
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> also. Upon this, being conducted into the
                    citadel by an augur, (to which profession that office was made a public one and
                    perpetual by way of honour,) he sat down on a stone facing the south: the augur
                    took his seat on his left hand with his head covered, holding in his right a
                    crooked wand free from knots, which they called <hi rend="italics">lituus;</hi>
                    then taking a view towards the city and country, after offering a prayer to the
                    gods, he marked out the regions from east to west, the parts towards the south
                    he called the right, those towards the north, the <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> left; and in front of him he set out in his mind a sign as
                    far as ever his eye could reach. Then having shifted the lituus into his left
                    hand, placing his right hand on the head of Numa, he prayed in this <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> manner: <quote> O father Jupiter, if it is thy will
                        that this Numa Pompilius, whose head I hold, should be king of Rome, I
                        beseech thee to give sure and evident signs of it within those bounds which
                        I have <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> marked. </quote> Then he stated in
                    set terms the omens which he wished to be sent; and on their being sent, Numa
                    was declared king and came down from the stand. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having thus obtained the kingdom, he sets
                    about establishing anew, on the principles of laws and morals, the city recently
                    established by violence and arms. When he saw that their minds, as having been
                    rendered ferocious by military life, could not be reconciled to those principles
                    during the continuance of wars, considering that a fierce people should be
                    mollified by the disuse of arms, he erected at the foot of Argiletum a temple of
                    Janus, as an index of peace and war; that when open, it might show the state was
                    engaged in war, and when shut, that all the neighbouring nations were at peace
                    with it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Twice only since the reign of Numa
                    hath this temple been shut; once when T. Manlius was consul, at the end of the
                    first Punic war; and a second time, which the gods granted our age to see, by
                    the emperor Augustus Caesar, after the battle of Actium, peace being established
                    by sea and land. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This being shut, after he had
                    secured the friendship of the neighboring states around by alliance and
                    treaties, all anxiety regarding dangers from abroad being removed, lest their
                    minds, which the fear of enemies and military discipline had kept in check,
                    should become licentious by tranquillity, he <pb n="27" xml:id="p.27"/>
                    considered, that, first of all, an awe of the gods should be instilled into
                    them, a principle of the greatest efficacy with a multitude ignorant and
                    uncivilized as in those times. But as it could not sink deeply into their minds
                    without some fiction of a miracle, he pretends that he holds nightly interviews
                    with the goddess Egeria; that by her direction he instituted the sacred rites
                    which would be most acceptable to the gods, and appointed proper priests for
                    each of the deities. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And, first of all, he
                    divides the year into twelve months, according to the course of the moon; and
                    because the moon does not make up thirty days in each month, and some days are
                    wanting to the complete year as constituted by the solstitial revolution, he so
                    portioned it out by inserting intercalary months, that every twenty-fourth year,
                    the lengths of all the intermediate years being completed, the days should
                    correspond to the same place of the sun (in the heavens) whence they had set
                    out. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Romulus had made his year to
                        consist of ten months, the first month being March, and the number of days
                        in the year being only 304, which corresponded neither with the course
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> of the sun or moon. Numa, who added
                        the two months of January and February, divided the year into twelve months,
                        according to the course of the moon. This was the lunar Greek year, and
                        consisted of 354 days. Numa, however, adopted 355 days for his year, from
                        his partiality to odd numbers. The lunar year of 354 days fell short of the
                        solar year by 11 1/4 days; —this in 8 years amounted to (11 1/4 × 8) 90
                        days. These 90 days he divided into 2 months of 22 and 2 of 23 days,
                        (\overline(2 × 22) + \overline(2 × 23) = 90,) and introduced them
                        alternately every second year for two octennial periods: every third
                        octennial period, however, Numa intercalated only 66 days instead of 90
                        days, <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> he inserted 3 months of only 22 days
                        each. The reason was, because <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> he adopted
                        355 days as the length of his lunar year instead of 354, and this in 24
                        years (3 octennial periods) produced an error of 24 days; this error was
                        exactly compensated by intercalating only 66 days (90 —24) in the third
                        octennial period. The intercalations were generally made in the month of
                        February, after the 23rd of the month. Their management was left to the
                        pontiffs — <hi rend="italics">ad metam eandem solis unde orsi essent —dies
                            congruerent;</hi>
                        <quote> that the days might correspond to the same starting-point of the sun
                            in the heavens whence they had set out. </quote> That is, taking for
                        instance the tropic of Cancer for the place or starting-point of the sun any
                        one year, and observing that he was in that point of the heavens on
                        precisely the 21st of June, the object was so to dispense the year, that the
                        day on which the sun was observed to arrive at that same <hi rend="italics"
                            >meta</hi> or starting-point again, should also be called the 21st of
                        June: —such was the <hi rend="italics">congruity</hi> aimed <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> at by these intercalations. </note> He likewise
                    made a distinction of the days <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <cit>
                                <quote xml:lang="la">
                                    <l part="N">Ille nefastus erit per quem tria verba silentur;</l>
                                    <l part="N">Fastus erit, per quem lege licebit agi.</l>
                                </quote>
                                <bibl default="false">Ov. F. i. 47.</bibl>
                            </cit>
                        </quote>
                    </note> into pro- <pb n="28" xml:id="p.28"/> fane and sacred, because on some it
                    was likely to be expedient that no business should be transacted with the
                    people. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next he turned his attention to the
                    appointment of priests, though he performed many sacred rites himself,
                    especially those which now belong to the flamen of Jupiter. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But, as he imagined that in a warlike nation there would be
                    more kings resembling Romulus than Numa, and that they would go to war in
                    person, he appointed a residentiary priest as flamen to Jupiter, that the sacred
                    functions of the royal office might not be neglected, and he distinguished him
                    by a fine robe, and a royal curule chair. To him he added two other famines, one
                    for Mars, another for Quirinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He also
                    selected virgins for Vesta, a priesthood derived from Alba, and not foreign to
                    the family of the founder. That they might be constant attendants in the temple,
                    he appointed them salaries out of the public treasury; and by enjoining
                    virginity, and other religious observances, he made them sacred and venerable.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He selected twelve Salii for Mars
                    Gradivus, and gave them the distinction of an embroidered tunic, and over the
                    tunic a brazen covering for the breast. He commanded them to carry the celestial
                    shields called <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Ancilia,</hi> from <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >a)/gkulos.</foreign>
                    </note> Ancilia, and to go through the city singing songs, with leaping and
                    solemn dancing. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then he chose out of the
                    number of the fathers Numa Marcius, son of Marcus, as pontiff, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Pontificem,</hi> scil. Maximum. </note> and consigned to
                    him an entire system of religious rites written out and sealed, (showing) with
                    what victims, upon what days, and in what temples the sacred rites were to be
                    performed; and from what funds the money was to be taken for these expenses.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He placed all religious institutions,
                    public and private, under the cognisance of the pontiff, to the end that there
                    might be some place where the people should come to consult, lest any confusion
                    in the divine worship might be occasioned by neglecting the ceremonies of their
                    own country, and introducing foreign ones. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> (He
                    ordained) that the same pontiff should instruct the people not only in the
                    celestial ceremonies, but also in (the manner of performing) funeral
                    solemnities, and of appeasing the manes of the dead; and what prodigies sent by
                    lightning or any other phenomenon were to be attended to and expiated. <pb
                        n="29" xml:id="p.29"/> To elicit such knowledge from the divine mind, he
                    dedicated an altar on the Aventine to Jupiter <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote rend="blockquote">
                            <cit>
                                <quote xml:lang="la">
                                    <l part="N">Eliciunt caelo te, Jupiter: unde minores</l>
                                    <l part="N">Nunc quoque te celebrant, Eliciumque vocant.</l>
                                </quote>
                                <bibl default="false">Ov. F. iii. 327.</bibl>
                            </cit>
                        </quote>
                    </note> Elicius, and consulted the god by auguries as to what (prodigies) should
                    be expiated. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The whole multitude having been diverted from
                    violence and arms to the considering and adjusting these matters, both their
                    minds had been engaged in doing something, and the constant watchfulness of the
                    gods now impressed upon them, as the deity of heaven seemed to interest itself
                    in human concerns, had filled the breasts of all with such piety, that faith and
                    religious obligations governed the state, no less than fear of the laws and of
                    punishment. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And while <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cum ipsi se —formarent, turn initimi etiam,</hi> etc.
                        Some of the editors of Livy have remarked on this passage, that <hi
                            rend="italics">cum</hi> when answering to <hi rend="italics">tum</hi>
                        may be joined to a subjunctive, as here; the fact however is, that <hi
                            rend="italics">cum</hi> here does not answer to <hi rend="italics"
                            >tum</hi> at all; <hi rend="italics">cum</hi> is here
                            <quote>whilst,</quote> —and so necessarily requires the verb to be in
                        the subjunctive mood. </note> the people were moulding themselves after the
                    morals of the king, as their best example, the neighbouring states also, who had
                    formerly thought that it was a camp, not a city, situate in the midst of them to
                    disturb the general peace, were brought (to feel) such respect for them that
                    they considered it impious that a state, wholly occupied in the worship of the
                    gods, should <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> be molested. There was a grove,
                    the middle of which was irrigated by a spring of running water, issuing from a
                    dark grotto. As Numa went often thither alone, under pretence of conferring with
                    the goddess, he dedicated the place to the Muses, because their meetings with
                    his wife Egeria were <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> held there. He also
                    instituted a yearly festival to Faith alone, and commanded the priests to be
                    carried to her temple in an arched chariot drawn by two horses, and to perform
                    the divine service with their hands wrapt up to the fingers, intimating that
                    Faith ought to be protected, and that her seat ought to be sacred even in men's
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> right hands. He instituted many other
                    sacred rites, and dedicated places for performing them, which the priests call
                    Argei. But the greatest of all his works was his maintenance of peace, during
                    the whole period of his reign, no less than of his <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> royal prerogative. Thus two kings in succession, by
                    different me- <pb n="30" xml:id="p.30"/> thods, the one by war, the other by
                    peace, aggrandized the state. Romulus reigned thirty-seven years, Numa
                    forty-three: the state was both strong and well versed in the arts of war and
                    peace. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Upon the death of Numa, the administration
                    returned again to an interregnum. After that the people appointed as king,
                    Tullus Hostilius, the grandson of that Hostilius who had made the noble stand
                    against the Sabines at the foot of the citadel. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The fathers confirmed the choice. He was not only unlike the preceding king,
                    but was even of a more warlike disposition than Romulus. Both his youth and
                    strength, and the renown of his grandfather, stimulated his ambition. Thinking
                    therefore that the state was becoming languid through quiet, he every where
                    sought for pretexts for stirring up war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It
                    happened that some Roman and Alban peasants had mutually plundered each other's
                    lands. C. Cluilius at that time governed Alba. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    From both sides ambassadors were sent almost at the same time, to demand
                    restitution. Tullus ordered his to attend to nothing before their instructions.
                    He knew well that the Alban would refuse, and that so war might be proclaimed on
                    just grounds. Their commission was executed more remissly by the Albans.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For being courteously and kindly
                    entertained by Tullus, they politely avail themselves of the king's hospitality.
                    Meanwhile the Romans had both been first in demanding restitution, and, upon the
                    refusal of the Albans, had proclaimed war after an interval of thirty days: of
                    this they give Tullus notice. Upon this he granted the Alban ambassadors an
                    opportunity of stating what they came to demand. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> They, ignorant of all, waste some time in making apologies: <quote> That it
                        was with the utmost reluctance they should say any thing which was not
                        pleasing to Tullus; but they were compelled by their orders. That they had
                        come to demand restitution; and if this be not made, they were commanded to
                        declare war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this Tullus made answer, <quote> Go tell
                        your king, that the king of the Romans takes the gods to witness, which of
                        the two nations hath with contempt first dismissed the ambassadors demanding
                        restitution, that on it they may visit all the calamities of this war.
                    </quote> The Albans carry home these tidings. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> War was prepared for on both sides with the
                    utmost vigour, very like to a civil war, in a manner between parents <pb n="31"
                        xml:id="p.31"/> and children: both being Trojan offspring; for from Troy
                    came Lavinium, from Lavinium Alba, and the Romans were descended from the race
                    of Alban kings. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But the result of the war
                    rendered the quarrel less distressing, for they never came to any action; and,
                    when the houses only of one of the cities had been demolished, the two states
                    were incorporated into one. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Albans first
                    made an irruption into the Roman territories with a large army. They pitch their
                    camp not above five miles from the city, and surround it with a trench, which,
                    for several ages, was called the Cluilian trench, from the name of the general,
                    till, in process of time, the name, together with the thing itself, were both
                    forgotten. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In that camp Cluilius, the Alban
                    king, dies; the Albans create Mettus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Mettus.</hi> Gronovius and Bekker read <hi rend="italics"
                            >Mettius;</hi> Niebuhr also prefers <hi rend="italics">Mettius;</hi> he
                        conceives that the Latin <hi rend="italics">praenomina</hi> and the Roman
                            <hi rend="italics">nomina</hi> terminated in <hi rend="italics"
                            >ius.</hi>
                    </note> Fuffetius dictator. In the mean time, Tullus being in high spirits,
                    especially on the death of the king, and giving out that the supreme power of
                    the gods, having begun at the head, would take vengeance on the whole Alban
                    nation for this impious war, having passed the enemy's camp in the night-time,
                    marches with a hostile army into the Alban territory. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This circumstance drew out Mettus from his camp likewise;
                    he leads his forces as near as he can to the enemy; from thence he commands a
                    herald, despatched by him, to tell Tullus that a conference was expedient before
                    they came to an engagement; and that if he would give him a meeting, he was
                    certain he should adduce matters which concerned the interest of Rome not less
                    than that of Alba. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Tullus not slighting the
                    proposal, though the advances made were of little avail, draws out his men in
                    order of battle; the Albans on their part come out also. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As both armies stood in battle-array, the chiefs, with a
                    few of the principal officers, advance into the middle between them. Then the
                    Alban commences thus: <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Injuries et non redditas,</hi> etc. The construction is,
                            <hi rend="italics"> et ego videor audisse regem nostrum Cluilium (prae
                            se ferre) injuries et non redditas res...nec dubito te ferre eadem prae
                            te, Tulle. </hi>
                    </note>
                    <quote> That injuries and the non-restitution of property according to treaty,
                        when demanded, were the cause of this war, methinks I both heard our King
                        Cluilius (assert), and I doubt not, Tullus, but that you state the same
                        thing. But if the truth is to be told, rather than that which is plausible,
                        the <pb n="32" xml:id="p.32"/> desire of dominion stimulates two kindred and
                        neighbouring states to arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor do I take
                        upon myself to determine whether rightly or wrongly: be that his
                        consideration who commenced the war. The Albans have made me their leader
                        for carrying on the war. Of this, Tullus, I would wish to warn you; how
                        powerful the Etruscan state is around us, and round you particularly, you
                        know better (than we), inasmuch as you are nearer them. They are very
                        powerful by land, extremely so by sea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Recollect that, when you shall give the signal for battle, these two armies
                        will presently be a spectacle to them; and they may fall on us wearied and
                        exhausted, victor and vanquished together. Therefore, in the name of heaven,
                        since, not content with certain liberty, we are incurring the dubious risk
                        of sovereignty and slavery, let us adopt some method, whereby, without much
                        loss, without much blood of either nation, it may be decided which shall
                        rule the other. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> —The proposal is not displeasing to Tullus,
                    though both from the natural bent of his mind, as also from the hope of victory,
                    he was rather inclined to violence. After some consideration, a plan is adopted
                    on both sides, for which Fortune herself afforded the materials. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that there were in each of the two
                    armies three brothers <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Three brothers born at one birth.</hi> Dionys. iii. 14,
                        describes them as cousin-germans. Vid. Wachsmuth, p. 147. Niebuhr, i. p.
                        342. </note> born at one birth, unequal neither in age nor strength. That
                    they were called Horatii and Curiatii is certain enough; nor is there any
                    circumstance of antiquity more celebrated; yet in a matter so well ascertained,
                    a doubt remains concerning their names, to which nation the Horatii and to which
                    the Curiatii belonged. Authors claim them for both sides; yet I find more who
                    call the Horatii Romans. My inclination leads me to follow them. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The kings confer with the three brothers, that they
                    should fight with their swords each in defence of their respective country;
                    (assuring them) that dominion would be on that side on which victory should be.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> No objection is made; time and place are
                    agreed on. Before they engaged, a compact is entered into between the Romans and
                    Albans on these conditions, that the state whose champions should come off
                    victorious in that combat, should rule the other state without further dispute.
                    Different treaties are made on <pb n="33" xml:id="p.33"/> different terms, but
                    they are all concluded in the same general method. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> We have heard that it was then concluded as follows, nor is
                    there a more ancient record of any treaty. A herald asked king Tullus thus,
                        <quote> Do you command me, O king, to conclude a treaty with the pater
                        patratus of the Alban people? </quote> After the king had given command, he
                    said, <quote>I demand vervain of thee, O king.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To which the king replied, <quote>Take some
                        that is pure.</quote> The herald brought a pure blade of grass from the
                    citadel; again he asked the king thus, <quote> Dost thou, O king, appoint me the
                        royal delegate of the Roman people, the Quirites? <hi rend="italics"
                            >including</hi> my vessels and attendants? </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king answered, <quote> That which may be
                        done without detriment to me and to the Roman people, the Quirites, I do.
                    </quote> The herald was M. Valerius, who appointed Sp. Fusius pater patratus,
                    touching his head and hair with the vervain. The pater patratus is appointed
                        <quote>ad jusjurandum patrandum,</quote> that is, to ratify the treaty; and
                    he goes through it in a great many words, which, being expressed in a long set
                    form, it is not worth while repeating. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After
                    setting forth the conditions, he says, <quote> Hear, O Jupiter; hear, O pater
                        patratus of the Alban people, and ye, Alban people, hear. As those
                        (conditions), from first to last, have been recited openly from those
                        tablets or wax without wicked fraud, and as they have been most correctly
                        understood here this day, from those conditions the Roman people will not be
                        the first to swerve. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If they first swerve
                        by public concert, by wicked fraud, on that day do thou, O Jupiter, so
                        strike the Roman people, as I shall here this day strike this swine; and do
                        thou strike them so much the more, as thou art more able and more powerful. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When he said this, he struck the swine with a
                    flint stone. The Albans likewise went through their own form and oath by their
                    own dictator and priests. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The treaty being concluded, the twin-brothers,
                    as had been agreed, take arms. Whilst their respective friends exhortingly
                    reminded each party "that their country's gods, their country and parents, all
                    their countrymen both at home and in the army, had their eyes then fixed on
                    their arms, on their hands; naturally brave, and animated by the exhortations of
                    their friends, they advance into the midst between the two lines. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The two armies sat down before their respective
                    camps, free rather from present danger than from anxiety: for the sove- <pb
                        n="34" xml:id="p.34"/> reign power was at stake, depending on the valour and
                    fortune of so few. Accordingly, therefore, eager and anxious, they have their
                    attention intensely riveted on a spectacle far from pleasing. The signal is
                    given.: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the three youths on each side, as
                    if in battle-array, rush to the charge with determined fury, bearing in their
                    breasts the spirits of mighty armies: nor do the one or the other regard their
                    personal danger; the public dominion or slavery is present to their mind, and
                    the fortune <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The order is: <hi
                            rend="italics">fortuna patrice deindefutura ea quam ipsi f. (animo
                            obvers);</hi> the fortune of their country, the high or humble character
                        of which for the future depended on their exertions on that occasion.
                    </note> of their country, which was ever after destined to be such as they
                    should now establish it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As soon as their arms
                    clashed on the first encounter, and their burnished swords glittered, great
                    horror strikes the. spectators; and, hope inclining to neither side, their voice
                    and breath were suspended. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then having engaged
                    hand to hand, when not only the movements of their bodies, and the rapid
                    brandishings of their arms and weapons, but wounds also and blood were seen, two
                    of the Romans fell lifeless, one upon the other, the three Albans being wounded.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And when the Alban army raised a shout of
                    joy at their fall, hope entirely, anxiety however not yet, deserted the Roman
                    legions, alarmed for the lot of the one, whom the three Curiatii surrounded.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He happened to be unhurt, so that, though
                    alone he was by no means a match for them all together, yet he was confident
                    against each singly. In order therefore to separate their attack, he takes to
                    flight, presuming that they would pursue him with such swiftness as the wounded
                    state of his body would suffer each. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He had
                    now fled a considerable distance from the place where they had fought, when,
                    looking behind, he perceives them pursuing him at great intervals from each
                    other; and that one of them was not far from him. On him he turned round with
                    great fury. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And whilst the Alban army shouts
                    out to the Curiatii to succour their brother, Horatius, victorious in having
                    slain his antagonist, was now proceeding to a second attack. Then the Romans
                    encourage their champion with a shout such as is usually (given) by persons
                    cheering in consequence of unexpected success: he also hastens to put an end to
                    the combat. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Wherefore before the other, who
                    was not far off, could come <pb n="35" xml:id="p.35"/> up, he despatches the
                    second Curiatius also. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And now, the combat
                    being brought to an equality of numbers, one on each side remained, but they
                    were equal neither in hope nor in strength. The one his body untouched by a
                    weapon, and a double victory made courageous for a third contest: the other
                    dragging along his body exhausted from the wound, exhausted from running, and
                    dispirited by the slaughter of his brethren before his eyes, presents himself to
                    his victorious antagonist. Nor was that a fight. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman, exulting, says, <quote> Two I have offered to
                        the shades of my brothers: the third I will offer to the cause of this war,
                        that the Roman may rule over the Alban. </quote> He thrusts his sword down
                    into his throat, whilst faintly sustaining the weight of his armour: he strips
                    him as he lies prostrate. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans receive
                    Horatius with triumph and congratulation; with so much the greater joy, as
                    success had followed so close on fear. They then turn to the burial of their
                    friends with dispositions by no means alike; for the one side was elated with
                    (the acquisition of) empire, the other subjected to foreign jurisdiction:
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> their sepulchres are still extant in the
                    place where each fell; the two Roman ones in one place nearer to Alba, the three
                    Alban ones towards Rome; but distant in situation from each other, and just as
                    they fought. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The two Roman champions,
                        we have seen, fell in the one place, <hi rend="italics">super alium
                            alius;</hi> consequently were buried together; whilst the Curiatii fell
                        in different places, as Horatius contrived to separate them to avoid their
                        joint attack. </note>
                </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before they parted from thence, when Mettus,
                    in conformity to the treaty which had been concluded, asked what orders he had
                    to give, Tullus orders him to keep the youth in arms, that he designed to employ
                    them, if a war should break out with the Veientes. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> After this both armies returned to their homes. Horatius
                    marched foremost, carrying before him the spoils of the three brothers: his
                    sister, a maiden who had been betrothed to one of the Curiatii, met him before
                    the gate Capena: and having recognized her lover's military robe, which she
                    herself had wrought, on her brother's shoulders, she tore her hair, and with
                    bitter wailings called by name on her deceased lover. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The sister's lamentations in the midst of his own victory,
                    and of such great public rejoicings, raised the indignation of the excited <pb
                        n="36" xml:id="p.36"/> youth. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Having
                    therefore drawn his sword, he run the damsel through the body, at the same time
                    chiding her in these words: <quote> Go hence, with thy unseasonable love to thy
                        spouse, forgetful of thy dead brothers, and of him who survives, forgetful
                        of thy native country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So perish every
                        Roman woman who shall mourn an enemy. </quote> This action seemed shocking
                    to the fathers and to the people; but his recent services outweighed its guilt.
                    Nevertheless he was carried before the king for judgment. The king, that he
                    himself might not be the author of a decision so melancholy, and so disagreeable
                    to the people, or of the punishment consequent on that decision, having summoned
                    an assembly of the people, says, <quote> I appoint, according to law, duumvirs
                        to pass sentence on Horatius for <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">Perduellio,</hi> (duellum, bellum,) high treason
                            against the state or its sovereign; but in those times any offence
                            deserving capital punishment was included under that of treason, <hi
                                rend="italics">Qui Horatio perduellionem judicent,</hi> to pass
                            sentence on Horatius, as being manifestly guilty of murder; not to try
                            whether he was guilty or not. </note> treason. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The law was of dreadful import. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Duumviri, etc. Niebuhr considers these
                        to be the very words of the old formula. </note>
                    <quote> Let the duumvirs pass sentence for treason. If he appeal from the
                        duumvirs, let him contend by appeal; if they shall gain the cause, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> If the sentence (of the duumviri)
                            be confirmed by the people. </note> cover his head; hang him by a rope
                        from a gallows; scourge him either within the pomœrium or without the
                        pomœrium. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the duumvirs appointed by this law, who
                    did not consider that, according to the law, they could <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The letter of the law allowed of no justification or
                        extenuation of the fact. It left no alternative to the judge. </note> acquit
                    even an innocent person, had fond him guilty; one of them says, <quote> P.
                        Horatius, I judge thee guilty of treason. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Go, lictor, bind his hands. </quote> The lictor had approached him, and was
                    fixing the rope. Then Horatius, lay the advice of Tullus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> He kindly pointed out the loop-hole in the law, which
                        left an opening for the culprit's acquittal. </note> a favourable
                    interpreter of the law, says, <quote>I appeal.</quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly the matter was contested by appeal
                    to the people. On that trial persons were much affected, especially by P.
                    Horatius the father declaring, that he considered his daughter deservedly slain;
                    were it not so, that he would by his authority as a father have inflicted
                    punishment on his son. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> By the laws of
                        Romulus, a father had the power of life and death over his children. </note>
                    He then en- <pb n="37" xml:id="p.37"/> treated that they would not render
                    childless him whom but a little while ago they had beheld with a fine progeny.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During these words the old man, having
                    embraced the youth, pointing to the spoils of the Curiatii fixed up in that
                    place which is now called Pila Horatia, <quote>Romans,</quote> said he, <quote>
                        can you bear to see bound beneath a gallows amidst scourges and tortures,
                        him whom you just now beheld marching decorated (with spoils) and exulting
                        in victory; a sight so shocking as the eyes even of the Albans could
                        scarcely endure. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Go, lictor, bind those
                        hands, which but a little while since, being armed, established sovereignty
                        for the Roman people. Go, cover the head of the liberator of this city; hang
                        him on the gallows; scourge him, either within the pomœrium, so it be only
                        amid those javelins and spoils of the enemy; or without the pomœrium, only
                        amid the graves of the Curiatii. For whither can you bring this youth, where
                        his own glories must not redeem him from such ignominy of punishment? </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The people could not withstand the tears of
                    the father, or the resolution of the son, so undaunted in every danger; and
                    acquitted him more through admiration of his bravery, than for the justice of
                    his cause. But that so notorious a murder might be atoned for by some expiation,
                    the father was commanded to make satisfaction for the son at the public charge.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He, having offered certain expiatory
                    sacrifices, which were ever after continued in the Horatian family, and laid a
                    beam across the street, made his son pass under it as under a yoke, with his
                    head covered. This remains even to this day, being constantly repaired at the
                    expense of the public; they call it Sororium Tigillum. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> A tomb of square stone was erected to Horatia in the place
                    where she was stabbed and fell. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nor did the peace with Alba continue long. The
                    dissatisfaction of the populace, because the fortune of the state had been
                    hazarded on three soldiers, perverted the weak mind of the dictator; and because
                    honourable measures had not turned out well, he began to conciliate their
                    affections by perfidious means. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    as one formerly seeking peace in war, so now seeking war in peace, because he
                    perceived that his own state possessed more courage than strength, he stirs up
                    other nations to make war openly and by proclamation: <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The part which he reserves for himself and the Albans
                        is to play the traitors to Tullus in the hour of need, wearing meanwhile the
                        mark of friendship to Rome. </note>
                    <pb n="38" xml:id="p.38"/> for his own people he reserves treachery under the
                    mask of alliance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Fidenates, a Roman
                    colony, having gained over the Veientes as partisans in the confederacy, are
                    instigated to declare war and take up arms under a compact of desertion on the
                    part of the Albans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When Fidenae had openly
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The fact is, that the subject
                        population rose up against the Roman colonists, drove them out of the town,
                        and asserted their independence. Nieb. i. 24. 5. </note> revolted, Tullus,
                    after summoning Mettus and his army from Alba, marches against the enemy. When
                    he crossed the Anio, he pitches his camp at the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The Tiber and the Anio.</note> conflux of the rivers.
                    Between that place and Fidenae, the army of the Veientes had crossed the Tiber.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These, in line of battle, occupied the
                    right wing near the river; the Fidenates are posted on the left nearer the
                    mountains. Tullus stations his own men opposite the Veientian foe; the Albans he
                    opposes to the legion of the Fidenates. The Alban had not more courage than
                    fidelity. Neither daring therefore to keep his ground, nor to desert openly, he
                    files off slowly to the mountains. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After this,
                    when he supposed he had gone far enough, he <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Erigit</hi> — <quote>he makes it halt,</quote> from the
                        French <hi rend="italics">faire alte,</hi> or formerly <hi rend="italics"
                            >haut,</hi> because soldiers then stand upright and hold their spears
                        erect. </note> halts his entire army; and being still irresolute in mind, in
                    order to waste time, he opens his ranks. His design was, to turn his forces to
                    that side to which fortune should give <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    success. At first the Romans who stood nearest were astonished, when they
                    perceived their flanks were uncovered by the departure of their allies; then a
                    horseman in full gallop announces to the king that the Albans were moving off.
                    Tullus, in this perilous juncture, vowed twelve Salii, and temples to Paleness
                    and <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Panic. Rebuking the horseman in a loud
                    voice, so that the enemy might hear him, he orders him to return to the fight,
                        <quote> that there was no occasion for alarm; that by his order the Alban
                        army was marching round to fall on the unprotected rear of the <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Fidenates. </quote> He likewise commands him to
                    order the cavalry to raise their spears aloft; this expedient intercepted from a
                    great part of the Roman infantry the view of the Alban army retreating. Those
                    who <pb n="39" xml:id="p.39"/> saw it, believing what they had heard the king
                    say, fought with the greater ardour. The alarm is now transferred to the enemy;
                    they had both heard what had been pronounced so audibly, and a great part of the
                    Fidenates, as having been joined as colonists to the Romans, understood
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Latin. Therefore, that they might not be
                    intercepted from the town by a sudden descent of the Albans from the hills, they
                    take to flight. Tullus presses forward, and having routed the wing of the
                    Fidenates, returned with greater fury against the Veientes, disheartened by the
                    panic of the others: nor did they sustain his charge; but the river, opposed to
                    them behind, prevented a precipitate <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> flight.
                    Whither when their flight led, some, shamefully throwing down their arms, rushed
                    blindly into the river; others, while they linger on the banks, doubting whether
                    to fly or fight, were overpowered. Never before had the Romans a more desperate
                    battle. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the Alban army, that had been spectators
                    of the fight, was marched down into the plains. Mettus congratulates Tullus on
                    his defeat of the enemy; Tullus on his part addresses Mettus with great
                    civility. He orders the Albans to unite their camp with the Romans, which he
                    prayed might prove beneficial to both; and prepares a sacrifice of purification
                    for the next day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As soon as it was light, all
                    things being in readiness, according to custom, he commands both armies to be
                    summoned to an assembly. The heralds, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Praecones ab extremo.</hi> At the farther part of the
                        Roman camp, where it joined that of the Albans. </note> beginning at the
                    outside, summoned the Albans first. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They,
                    struck <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As well as by the orders issued
                        by Tullus.</note> too with the novelty of the thing, in order to hear the
                    Roman king harangue, crowded next to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    Roman legions, under arms, by concert surrounded them; a charge had been given
                    to the centurions to execute their orders without delay. Then Tullus begins as
                    follows: <quote> Romans, if ever before at any other time in any war there was
                        (an occasion) on which you should return thanks, first to the immortal gods,
                        next to your own valour, that occasion was yesterday's battle. For the
                        contest was not more with enemies than with the treachery and perfidy of
                        allies, a contest which is more serious and more dangerous. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> For that a false opinion may not influence you, the
                        Albans retired to the mountains without my orders, <pb n="40" xml:id="p.40"
                        /> nor was that my command, but a stratagem and the pretence of a command:
                        that so your attention might not be drawn away from the fight, you being
                        kept in ignorance that you were deserted, and that terror and dismay might
                        be struck into the enemy, conceiving themselves to be surrounded on the
                        rear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nor does that guilt, which I now
                        state, extend to all the Albans. They followed their leader; as you too
                        would have done, if I had wished my army to make a move to any other point
                        from thence. Mettus there is the leader of that march, the same Mettus is
                        the contriver of this war; Mettus is the violator of the treaty between Rome
                        and Alba. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Let another hereafter attempt
                        the like conduct, unless I now make of him a signal example to mankind.
                    </quote> The centurions in arms stand round Mettus, and the king proceeds with
                    the rest as he had commenced: <quote> It is my intention, and may it prove
                        fortunate, auspicious, and happy to the Roman people, to myself, and to you,
                        O Albans, to transplant all the inhabitants of Alba to Rome: to grant your
                        people the rights of citizenship, and to admit your nobles into the rank of
                        senators: to make one city, one republic; that as the Alban state was
                        formerly divided from one people into two, so it may now return into one. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On hearing this the Alban youth, unarmed,
                    surrounded by armed men, however divided in their sentiments, yet restrained by
                    the common apprehension, continue silent. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then
                    Tullus proceeded: <quote> If, Mettus Fuffetius, you were capable of learning
                        fidelity, and how to observe treaties, that lesson would have been taught
                        you by me, while still alive. Now, since your disposition is incurable, do
                        you at least by your punishment teach mankind to consider those things
                        sacred which have been violated by you. As therefore a little while since
                        you kept your mind divided between the interest of Fidenae and of Rome, so
                        shall you now surrender your body to be torn asunder in different
                        directions. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Upon this, two chariots drawn by four horses
                    being brought, he ties Mettus extended at full length to their carriages: then
                    the horses were driven on in different directions, carrying off the mangled body
                    on each carriage, where the limbs had been fastened by the cords. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> All turned away their eyes from so shocking a
                    spectacle. That was the first and last instance of a punishment among the Romans
                    regardless of the laws of humanity. In other cases we may <pb n="41"
                        xml:id="p.41"/> boast that no nation whatever adopted milder forms of
                    punishment. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these occurrences the cavalry had been
                    despatched onward to Alba to remove the multitude to Rome. The legions were next
                    led thither to demolish the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they
                    entered the gates, there was not indeed that tumult nor panic, such as usually
                    takes place with captured cities when the gates being burst open, or the walls
                    levelled by the ram, or the citadel taken by assault, the shouts of the enemy
                    and rush of armed men through the city throws every thing into confusion by fire
                    and sword: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but gloomy silence and speechless
                    sorrow so absorbed the minds of all, that, through fear, forgetting what they
                    should leave behind, what they should take with them, all concert failing them,
                    and frequently making inquiries of each other, they now stood at their
                    thresholds, now wandering about they strayed through their houses, doomed to see
                    them for that the last time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But as soon as
                    the shouts of the horsemen commanding them to depart now urged them on, the
                    crashing of the dwellings which were being demolished, was now heard in the
                    remotest parts of the city, and the dust, rising in distant places, had filled
                    every quarter as with a cloud spread over them; <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> hastily snatching up whatever each of them could, whilst they went forth
                    leaving behind them their guardian deity and household gods, and the homes in
                    which each had been born and brought up, a continued train of emigrants soon
                    filled the ways, and the sight of others through mutual commiseration renewed
                    their tears, and piteous cries too were heard, of the women more especially,
                    when they passed by their revered temples now beset with armed men, and left
                    their gods as it were in captivity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After the
                    Albans had evacuated the town, the Roman soldiery level all the public and
                    private edifices indiscriminately to the ground, and one short hour consigned to
                    demolition and ruin the work of four hundred years, during which Alba had stood.
                    The temples of the gods, however, for such had been the orders given by the
                    king, were spared. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time Rome increases by the
                    demolition of Alba. The number of citizens is doubled. The Cœlian mount is added
                    to the city, and in order that it might be inhabited more populously, Tullus
                    selects that situation for his <pb n="42" xml:id="p.42"/> palace and there took
                    up his abode. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The leading persons among the
                    Albans he enrols among the patricians, that that branch of the state also might
                    increase, the Julii, Servilii, Quinctii, Geganii, Curiatii, Clœlii; and as a
                    consecrated place of meeting for the order augmented by him he built a
                    senate-house, which was called Hostilia even down to the age of our fathers.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And that every rank might acquire some
                    additional strength from the new people, he formed ten troops of horsemen from
                    among the Albans: he likewise recruited the old, and raised new legions from the
                    same source. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Confiding in this increase of
                    strength, Tullus declares war against the Sabines, a nation at that time the
                    most powerful, next to the Etrurians, in men and in arms. Injuries had been done
                    on both sides, and restitution demanded in vain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Tullus complained that some Roman merchants had been seized in an open market
                    near the temple of Feronia; the Sabines, that some of their people had taken
                    refuge in the asylum, and were detained at Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> These were assigned as the causes of the war. The Sabines, holding in
                    recollection both that a portion of their strength had been fixed at Rome by
                    Tatius, and that the Roman power had also been lately increased by the accession
                    of the Alban people, began, on their part, to look around for foreign aid.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Etruria was in their neighbourhood; of the
                    Etrurians the Veientes were the nearest. From thence they drew some volunteers,
                    their minds being stirred up to a revolt, chiefly in consequence of the rankling
                    animosities from (former) wars. And pay also had its weight with some stragglers
                    belonging to the indigent population. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They
                    were assisted by no aid from the government, and the faith of the truce
                    stipulated with Romulus was strictly observed by the Veientes (for with respect
                    to the others it is less surprising). While they were preparing for war with the
                    utmost vigour, and the matter seemed to turn on this, which should first
                    commence hostilities, Tullus first passes into the Sabine territory. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> A desperate battle ensued at the wood called
                    Malitiosa, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Malitiosam.</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="greek">Thn u(/lhn kaloume/nhn Kakou=rgon.</foreign> Dio.
                        iii. </note> in which the Roman army was far superior, both by the strength
                    of their foot, and also by the recent augmentation of their cavalry. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The Sabine ranks were thrown into disorder by a
                    sudden charge of the cavalry, nor could either the fight be afterwards restored,
                    or a retreat accomplished without great slaughter. <pb n="43" xml:id="p.43"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the defeat of the Sabines, when the
                    government of Tullus and the whole Roman state was in high renown, and in a very
                    flourishing condition, word was brought to the king and senators, that it rained
                    stones on the Alban Mount. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As this could
                    scarcely be credited, on persons being sent to inquire into the prodigy, a thick
                    shower of stones fell from heaven in their sight, just as when hail collected
                    into balls is pelted down to the earth by the winds. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Besides, they imagined that they heard a loud voice from
                    the grove on the summit of the hill, requiring the Albans to perform their
                    religious service according to the rites of their native country, which they had
                    consigned to oblivion, as if their gods had been abandoned together with their
                    country; and they had either adopted the religion of Rome, or, as may happen,
                    enraged at their evil destiny, had renounced altogether the worship of the gods.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A festival of nine days was instituted
                    publicly by the Romans also on account of the same prodigy, either in obedience
                    to the heavenly voice sent from the Alban mount, (for that too is stated,) or by
                    the advice of the aruspices. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Certain it is, it
                    continued a solemn observance, that whenever the same prodigy was announced, a
                    festival for nine days was observed. Not long after, they were afflicted with a
                    pestilence; and though from this there arose an aversion to military service,
                    yet no respite from arms was granted by this warlike king, who considered that
                    the bodies of the young men were even more healthy abroad than at home, until he
                    himself also was seized with a lingering disease. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then, together with his body, those fierce spirits became
                    so broken, that he, who formerly considered nothing less worthy of a king than
                    to devote his mind to religion, suddenly became a slave to every form of
                    superstition, important and trifling, and filled the people's minds also with
                    religious scruples. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The generality of persons,
                    now wishing to recur to that state of things which had existed under king Numa,
                    thought that the only relief left for their sickly bodies was, if peace and
                    pardon could be obtained from the gods. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They
                    say that the king himself, turning over the commentaries of Numa, after he had
                    found therein that certain sacrifices of a secret and solemn nature had been
                    performed to Jupiter Elicius, shut himself up and set about the performance of
                    this solemnity; but that that rite was not duly undertaken or conducted, and
                    that not only no appearance of <pb n="44" xml:id="p.44"/> heavenly notification
                    was presented to him, but that he was struck with lightning and burnt to ashes,
                    together with his house, through the anger of Jupiter, exasperated at the
                    impropriety of the ceremony. Tullus reigned two-and-thirty years with great
                    military renown. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the death of Tullus the government devolved
                    once more upon the senate, and they nominated an interrex; and on his holding
                    the comitia, the people elected Ancus Marcius king. The fathers confirmed the
                    election. Ancus Marcius was the grandson of king Numa Pompilius by his daughter.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As soon as he ascended the throne,
                    reflecting on the renown of his grandfather, and that the late reign, glorious
                    in every other respect, in one particular had not been sufficiently prosperous,
                    the rites of religion having either been utterly neglected, or improperly
                    performed; deeming it of the highest importance to perform the public ceremonies
                    of religion as they had been instituted by Numa, he orders the pontiff, after he
                    had transcribed them all from the king's commentaries on white tables, to expose
                    them to public view. Hence, both his own subjects, desirous of peace, and the
                    neighbouring nations, entertained a hope that the king would conform to the
                    conduct and institutions of his grandfather. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly the Latins, with whom a treaty had been concluded in the reign of
                    Tullus, assumed new courage; and after they had made an incursion upon the Roman
                    lands, return a contemptuous answer to the Romans on their demanding
                    restitution, supposing that the Roman king would spend his reign in indolence
                    among chapels and altars. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The genius of Ancus
                    was of a middle kind, partaking both of that of Numa and of Romulus; and,
                    besides that, he thought that peace was more necessary in his grandfather's
                    reign, considering the people were but recent as well as uncivilized, he also
                    (considered) that he could not, without injury, preserve the tranquillity which
                    had fallen to his lot; that his patience was tried, and being tried, was now
                    despised; and that the times were more suited to a king Tullus than to a Numa.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In order, however, that as Numa had
                    instituted religious rites in peace, ceremonies relating to war might be
                    transmitted by him, and that wars might not only be waged, but proclaimed also
                    according to some rite, he borrowed from an ancient nation, the Aequicolae, the
                    form which the heralds still preserve, according to which restitution is <pb
                        n="45" xml:id="p.45"/> demanded. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    ambassador, when he comes to the frontiers of the people from whom satisfaction
                    is demanded, having his head covered with a fillet, (the fillet is of wool,)
                    says, <quote> Hear, O Jupiter, hear, ye confines, (naming the nation they belong
                        to,) let Justice hear. I am a public messenger of the Roman people; I come
                        justly and religiously deputed, and let my words gain credit. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then makes his demands; afterwards he makes
                    a solemn appeal to Jupiter, <quote> If I unjustly or impiously demand those
                        persons and those goods to be given up to me, the messenger of the Roman
                        people, then never permit me to enjoy my native country. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These words he repeats when he passes over the
                    frontiers; the same to the first man he meets; the same on entering the gate;
                    the same on entering the forum, some few words in the form of the declaration
                    and oath being changed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If the persons whom he
                    demands are not delivered up, on the expiration of thirty-three days, for so
                    many are enjoined by the rule, he declares war, thus: <quote> Hear, Jupiter, and
                        thou, Juno, Romulus, and all ye celestial, terrestrial, and infernal gods,
                        give ear! <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I call you to witness, that
                        this nation (naming it) is unjust, and does not act with equity; but we will
                        consult the fathers in our own country concerning these matters, and by what
                        means we may obtain our right. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After that the messenger returns to Rome to
                    consult: the king immediately used to consult the fathers almost in the
                    following words: <quote> Concerning such matters, differences, and quarrels, as
                        the pater patratus of the Roman people, the Quirites, has conferred with the
                        pater patratus of the ancient Latins, and with the ancient Latin people,
                        which matters ought to be given up, performed, discharged, which matters
                        they have neither given up, performed, nor discharged, declare, </quote>
                    says he to him, whose opinion he first asked, <quote>what think you?</quote>
                    Then he said, <quote> I think that they should be demanded by a just and
                        regularly declared war, therefore I consent, and vote for it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then the others were asked in order, and when
                    the majority of those present agreed in the same opinion, the war was resolved
                    on. It was customary for the fecialis to carry in his hand a javelin pointed
                    with steel, or burnt at the end and dipped in blood, to the confines of the
                    enemy's country, and in presence of at least three grown-up persons, <milestone
                        n="13??" unit="section"/> to say, <quote> Forasmuch as the states of the
                        ancient Latins, and the ancient Latin people, have offended against the
                        Roman people, the Quirites, <pb n="46" xml:id="p.46"/> forasmuch as the
                        Roman people, the Quirites, have ordered that there should be war with the
                        ancient Latins, and the senate of the Roman people, the Quirites, have given
                        their opinion, consented, and voted that war should be made with the ancient
                        Latins, on this account I and the Roman people declare and make war on the
                        states of the ancient Latins, and on the ancient Latin people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> After he had said that, he threw the spear
                    within their confines. After this manner restitution was demanded from the
                    Latins at that time, and war proclaimed: and that usage posterity have adopted. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ancus, having committed the care of sacred
                    things to the famines and other priests, set out with a new army, which he had
                    levied, and took Politorium, a city of the Latins, by storm; and following the
                    example of former kings, who had increased the Roman state by taking enemies
                    into the number of the citizens, he transplanted all the people to Rome.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And since the Sabines occupied the Capitol
                    and citadel, and the Albans the Cœlian mount around the Palatium, the residence
                    of the old Romans, the Aventine was assigned to the new people; not long after,
                    on Telleni and Ficana being taken, new citizens were added in the same quarter.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After this Politorium was taken a second
                    time by force of arms, because the ancient Latins had taken possession of it
                    when vacated. This was the cause of the Romans demolishing that city, that it
                    might not ever after serve as a receptacle to the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> At last, the whole war with the Latins being concentrated
                    in Medullia, they fought there with various fortune, sometimes the one and
                    sometimes the other gaining the victory; for the town was both well fortified by
                    works, and strengthened by a strong garrison, and the Latins, having pitched
                    their camp in the open fields, had several times fought the Romans in close
                    engagement. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last Ancus, making an effort
                    with all his forces, obtained a complete victory over them in a pitched battle,
                    and having got a considerable booty, returned thence to Rome; many thousands of
                    the Latins being then also admitted into the city, to whom, in order that the
                    Aventine might be joined to the Palatium, a settlement was assigned near the
                    temple of Murcia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Janiculum was likewise
                    added, not for want of room, but lest at any time it should become a lodgment
                    for the enemy. It was determined to join it to the city, not only by a wall, but
                    likewise, for the sake of the convenience of <pb n="47" xml:id="p.47"/> passage,
                    by a wooden bridge, then for the first time built across the Tiber. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The Fossa Quiritium, no inconsiderable defence
                    against the easy access to the city from the low grounds, is the work of king
                    Ancus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The state being augmented by such great
                    accessions, seeing that, amid such a multitude of persons, the distinction of
                    right and wrong being as yet confounded, clandestine crimes were committed, a
                    prison is built in the heart of the city, overlooking the forum, to intimidate
                    the growing licentiousness. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And not only was
                    the city increased under this king, but the territory also and the boundaries.
                    The Maesian forest was taken from the Veientes, the Roman dominion was extended
                    as far as the sea, and the city of Ostia built at the mouth of the Tiber;
                    salt-pits were formed around it, and, in consequence of the distinguished
                    success achieved in war, the temple of Jupiter Feretrius was enlarged. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the reign of Ancus, Lucumo, a rich and
                    enterprising man, came to settle at Rome, prompted chiefly by the desire and
                    hope of obtaining great preferment there, which he had no means of attaining at
                    Tarquinii (for there also he was descended from an alien stock). He was the son
                    of Demaratus, a Corinthian, who, flying his country for sedition, had happened
                    to settle at Tarquinii, and having married a wife there, had two sons by her.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their names were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Lucumones were a class of persons among the
                        Etrurians of a warlike sacerdotal character, patricians, not kings. Vid.
                        Niebuhr, i. p. 372. </note> Lucumo and Aruns. Lucumo survived his father,
                    and became heir to all his property. Aruns died before his father, leaving a
                    wife pregnant. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The father did not long survive
                    the son, and as he, not knowing that his daughter-in-law was pregnant, died
                    without taking any notice of his grandchild in his will, to the boy that was
                    born after the death of his grandfather, without having any share in his
                    fortune, the name of Egerius was given on account of his poverty. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> And when his wealth already inspired Lucumo, on the
                    other hand, the heir of all his father's wealth, with elevated notions,
                    Tanaquil, whom he married, further increased such feeling, she being descended
                    from a very high family, and one who would not readily brook the condition into
                    which she had married to be inferior to that in which she had been born.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As the Etrurians despised Lucumo, because
                    sprung from a foreign exile, she could not bear the affront, and regardless of
                    the innate love of her native country, provided <pb n="48" xml:id="p.48"/> she
                    might see her husband advanced to honours, she formed the determination to leave
                    Tarquinii. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rome seemed particularly suited for
                    her purpose. In this state, lately founded, where all nobility is recent and the
                    result of merit, there would be room for her husband, a man of courage and
                    activity. Tatius a Sabine had been king of Rome: Numa had been sent for from
                    Cures to reign there: Ancus was sprung from a Sabine mother, and rested his
                    nobility on the single statue of Numa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> She
                    easily persuades him, as being ambitious of honours, and one to whom Tarquinii
                    was his country only on the mother's side. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, removing their effects they set out together for Rome. They
                    happened to have reached the Janiculum; there, as he sat in the chariot with his
                    wife, an eagle, suspended on her wings, gently stooping, takes off his cap, and
                    flying round the chariot with loud screams, as if she had been sent from heaven
                    for the very purpose, orderly replaced it on his head, and then flew aloft.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Tanaquil is said to have received this
                    omen with great joy, being a woman well skilled, as the Etrurians generally are,
                    in celestial prodigies, and embracing her husband, bids him hope for high and
                    elevated fortune: that such bird had come from such a quarter of the heavens,
                    and the messenger of such a god: that it had exhibited the omen around the
                    highest part of man: that it had lifted the ornament placed on the head of man,
                    to restore it to the same, by direction of the gods. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Carrying with them these hopes and thoughts, they entered
                    the city, and having purchased a house there, they gave out the name of Lucius
                    Tarquinius Priscus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His being a stranger and
                    very rich, caused him to be taken notice of by the Romans. He also promoted his
                    own good fortune by his affable address, by the courteousness of his
                    invitations, and by conciliating those whom he could by acts of kindness;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> until a report of him reached even to the
                    palace; and by paying court to the king with politeness and address, he in a
                    short time so improved the acquaintance to the footing of intimate friendship,
                    that he was present at all public and private deliberations, foreign and
                    domestic; and being now tried in every trust, he was at length, by the king's
                    will, appointed guardian to his children. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ancus reigned twenty-four years, equal to any
                    of the former kings both in the arts and renown of war and peace. His <pb n="49"
                        xml:id="p.49"/> sons were now nigh the age of puberty, for this reason
                    Tarquin was more urgent that the assembly for the election of a king should be
                    held as soon as possible. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The assembly being
                    proclaimed, he sent away the boys to hunt towards the time of their meeting. He
                    is said to have been the first who earnestly sued for the crown, and to have
                    made a set speech for the purpose of gaining the affections of the people:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">he said</hi>
                    <quote> that he did not aim at any thing unprecedented; for that he was not the
                        first foreigner, (a thing at which any one might feel indignation or
                        surprise,) but the third who aspired to the sovereignty of Rome. That Tatius
                        not only from being an alien, but even an enemy, was made king: that Numa,
                        unacquainted with the city, and without soliciting it, had been voluntarily
                        invited by them to the throne. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That he, as
                        soon as he was his own master, had come to Rome with his wife and whole
                        fortune, and had there spent a greater part of that age, in which men are
                        employed in civil offices, than he had in his native country: <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> that he had both in peace and war thoroughly
                        learned the Roman laws and religious customs, under a master not to be
                        objected to, king Ancus himself; that he had vied with all in duty and
                        loyalty to his prince, and even with the king himself in his bounty to
                        others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While he was recounting these undoubted facts,
                    the people by a great majority elected him king. The same ambition which had
                    prompted Tarquin, in other respects an excellent man, to aspire to the crown,
                    followed him whilst on the throne. And being no less mindful of strengthening
                    his own power, than of increasing that of the commonwealth, he elected a hundred
                    into the fathers, who from that time were called Minorum Gentium, <hi
                        rend="italics">i. e.</hi> of the younger families: a party hearty in the
                    king's cause, by whose favour they had got into the senate. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The first war he waged was with the Latins, from whom he
                    took the town of Apiolae by storm, and having brought back thence more booty
                    than the character of the war would lead one to expect, he celebrated games with
                    more cost and magnificence than former kings. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The place for the circus, which is now called Maximus, was then first marked
                    out, and spaces were parted off for the senators and knights, where they might
                    each erect seats for themselves: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> they were
                    called fori (benches). They viewed the games from scaffolding which supported
                    seats <pb n="50" xml:id="p.50"/> twelve feet high from the ground. The show took
                    place; horses and boxers were sent for, chiefly from Etruria. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> These solemn games afterwards continued annual, being
                    variously called the Roman and Great (games). By the same king also spaces round
                    the forum were portioned off for private individuals to build on; porticoes and
                    shops were erected. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He was also preparing to surround the city
                    with a stone wall, when a Sabine war obstructed his designs. The matter was so
                    sudden, that the enemy had passed the Anio before the Roman army could meet and
                    stop them; great alarm therefore was produced at Rome. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And at first they fought with dubious success, but with
                    great slaughter on both sides. After this, the enemy's forces being led back
                    into their camp, and the Romans getting time to make new levies for the war,
                    Tarquin, thinking that the weakness of his army lay in the want of horse,
                    determined to add other centuries to the Ramnenses, the Titienses, and Luceres
                    which Romulus had appointed, and to leave them distinguished by his own name.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Because Romulus had done this by augury,
                    Attus Navius, at that time a celebrated soothsayer, insisted that no alteration
                    or new appointment of that kind could be made, unless the birds approved of it.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king, enraged at this, and, as it is
                    related, ridiculing the art, said, <quote>Come, thou diviner, tell me, whether
                        what I am thinking on can be done or not?</quote> When he had tried the
                    matter by divination, he affirmed it certainly could. <quote>But I was
                        thinking,</quote> says he, <quote> whether you could cut asunder this
                        whetstone with a razor. Take it, and perform what thy birds portend may be
                        done. </quote> Upon this, as they say, he immediately cut the whetstone in
                    two. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A statue of Attus, with his head veiled,
                    was erected in the comitium, upon the very steps on the left of the
                    senate-house, on the spot where the transaction occurred. They say that the
                    whetstone also was deposited in the same place, that it might remain a monument
                    of that miracle to posterity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There certainly
                    accrued so much honour to augury and the college of augurs, that nothing was
                    undertaken either in peace or war without taking the auspices. Assemblies of the
                    people, the summoning of armies, and affairs of the greatest importance were put
                    off, when the birds would not allow of them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Nor did Tarquin then make any other alteration in the centuries of horse, except
                    doubling the number of men in each of these <pb n="51" xml:id="p.51"/> corps, so
                    that the three centuries consisted of one thousand eight hundred knights.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those that were added were called
                        <quote>the younger,</quote> but by the same names with the former; which,
                    now that they have been doubled, they call six centuries. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This part of his forces being augmented, a
                    second battle is fought with the Sabines. But, besides that the Roman army was
                    thus reinforced, a stratagem also is secretly resorted to, persons having been
                    sent to throw into the river a great quantity of timber that lay on the banks of
                    the Anio, it being first set on fire; and the wood being further kindled by
                    favour of the wind, and the greater <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In my version of this passage I have followed the reading, <hi
                            rend="italics">et pleraque in ratibus, impacta sublicis quum
                            haererent,</hi> p. i. The burning logs were not sent down the river one
                        by one, but were placed on rafts, so that being incapable of passing on
                        between the piers of the bridge, they firmly stuck there, and burnt the
                        bridge. This mode of interpretation is confirmed by Dion. iii. 5, 6. The
                        bridge here meant is the one built by the Sabines at the confluence of the
                        Anio and the Tiber — —Another reading is, <hi rend="italics">pleraque in
                            ratibus impacta subliciis quam haererent,</hi>
                        <quote>most of them being driven against the boats, resting on piles, stuck
                            there,</quote> &amp;c. </note> part of it (being placed) on rafts, when
                    it stuck firmly impacted against the piers, sets the bridge <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> on fire. This accident struck terror into the Sabines
                    during the battle, and, after they were routed, impeded their flight; so that
                    many, who had escaped the enemy, perished in the river. Their arms floating down
                    the Tiber, and being recognised at the city, made known the victory, almost
                    before any account of it could be <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> carried
                    there. In that action the glory of the cavalry was prominent: they say that,
                    being posted in the two wings, when the centre of their own infantry was being
                    beaten, they charged so briskly in flank, that they not only checked the Sabine
                    legions who pressed hard on those who retired, but quickly put them <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> to flight. The Sabines made for the mountains with
                    great precipitation, yet few reached them; for, as we said before, the greatest
                    part were driven by the cavalry into <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the
                    river. Tarquin, thinking it advisable to pursue the enemy closely while in this
                    consternation, after sending the booty and the prisoners to Rome, piling up and
                    burning the spoils which he had vowed to Vulcan, proceeds to lead his army
                    onward into the <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sabine territory. And though
                    matters had turned out adversely, nor could they hope for better success; yet,
                    because the occasion did not allow <pb n="52" xml:id="p.52"/> time for
                    deliberation, the Sabines came out to meet him with a hastily raised army; and
                    being again defeated there, and matters having now become desperate, they sued
                    for peace. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Collatia and all the land about it was taken
                    from the Sabines, and Egerius, son to the king's brother, was left there with' a
                    garrison. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I understand that the people of
                    Collatia were thus surrendered, and that the form of the surrender was as
                    follows: the king asked them, <quote> Are ye ambassadors and deputies sent by
                        the people of Collatia to surrender yourselves and the people of Collatia? </quote>
                    <quote>We are.</quote>
                    <quote>Are the people of Collatia their own masters?</quote>
                    <quote>They are.</quote>
                    <quote> Do ye surrender yourselves and the people of Collatia, their city,
                        lands, water, boundaries, temples, utensils, and every thing sacred or
                        profane belonging to them, into my power, and that of the Roman people? </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>We do.</quote>
                    <quote>Then I receive them.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Sabine war being ended, Tarquin returned
                    in triumph to Rome. After that he made war upon the ancient Latins, where they
                    came on no occasion to a general engagement; yet by carrying about his arms to
                    the several towns, he subdued the whole Latin nation. Corniculum, old Ficulea,
                    Cameria, Crustumerium, Ameriola, Medullia, and Nomentum, towns which either
                    belonged to the ancient Latins, or which had revolted to them, were taken. Upon
                    this a peace was concluded. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The works of peace
                    were then set about with greater spirit, even than the efforts with which he had
                    conducted his wars; so that the people enjoyed no more ease and quiet at home,
                    than they had done abroad: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> for he both set
                    about surrounding the city with a stone wall, on the side where he had not
                    fortified it, the beginning of which work had been interrupted by the Sabine
                    war, and the lower parts of the city round the forum and the other valleys lying
                    between the hills, because they did not easily carry off the water from the flat
                    grounds, he drains by means of sewers drawn sloping downward into the Tiber.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Moreover he levels an area for founding a
                    temple to Jupiter in 'the Capitol, which he had vowed to him in the Sabine war;
                    his mind even then presaging the future grandeur of the place. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At that time, a prodigy occurred in the
                    palace, wonderful both in its appearance and in its result. They relate, that
                    the head of a boy, called Servius Tullius, as he lay fast asleep, blazed with
                    fire in the sight of many persons. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That <pb
                        n="53" xml:id="p.53"/> by the very great noise made at so miraculous a
                    phenomenon, the royal family were awakened; and when one of the servants was
                    bringing water to extinguish the flame, that he was kept back by the queen, and
                    after the confusion was over, that she forbade the boy to be disturbed till he
                    should awake of his own accord. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As soon as he
                    awoke the flame disappeared. Then Tanaquil, taking her husband into a private
                    place, said, <quote> Do you observe this boy whom we bring up in so mean a
                        style? Be assured that hereafter he will be a light to us in our adversity,
                        and a protector to our palace in distress. From henceforth let us, with all
                        our care, train up this youth, who is capable of becoming a great ornament
                        publicly and privately. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From this time the boy began to be treated as
                    their own son, and instructed in those arts by which men's minds are qualified
                    to maintain high rank. The matter was easily accomplished, because it was
                    agreeable to the gods. The young man turned out to be of a disposition truly
                    royal. Nor, when they looked out for a son-in-law for Tarquin, could any of the
                    Roman youth be compared to him in any accomplishment; therefore the king
                    betrothed his own daughter to him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This high
                    honour conferred upon him, from whatever cause, prevents us from believing that
                    he was the son of a slave, and that he had himself been a slave when young. I am
                    rather of the opinion of those who say that, on the taking of Corniculum, the
                    wife of Servius Tullius, who had been the leading man in that city, being
                    pregnant when her husband was slain, being known among the other female
                    prisoners, and, in consequence of her high rank, exempted from servitude by the
                    Roman queen, was delivered of a child at Rome, in the house of Tarquinius
                    Priscus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Upon this, that both the intimacy
                    between the ladies was improved by so great a kindness, and that the boy, having
                    been brought up in the house from his infancy, was beloved and respected; that
                    his mother's lot, in having fallen into the hands of the enemy, caused him to be
                    considered the son of a slave. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the thirty-eighth year of Tarquin's
                    reign, Servius Tullius was in the highest esteem, not only with the king, but
                    also with the senate and people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At this time
                    the two sons of Ancus, though they had before that always considered it the
                    highest indignity that they had been deprived of their father's crown by the
                    treachery of their guardian, that a <pb n="54" xml:id="p.54"/> stranger should
                    be king of Rome, who was not only not of a civic, but not even of an Italian
                    family, yet now felt their indignation rise to a still higher pitch at the
                    notion that the crown would not only not revert to them after Tarquin, but would
                    descend even lower to a slave, so that in the same state about the hundredth
                    year <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">The hundredth year.</hi> 138 years had elapsed since the
                        death of Romulus: they diminish the number of years designedly, to make the
                        matter appear still worse. </note> after Romulus, descended from a deity,
                    and a deity himself, occupied the throne as long as he lived, a slave, and one
                    born of a slave, should now possess it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That
                    it would be a disgrace both common to the Roman name, and more especially to
                    their family, if, whilst there was male issue of king Ancus still living, the
                    sovereignty of Rome should be accessible not only to strangers, but even to
                    slaves. They determine therefore to prevent that disgrace by the sword.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But both resentment for the injury done to
                    them incensed them more against Tarquin himself, than against Servius; and (the
                    consideration) that a king was likely to prove a more severe avenger of the
                    murder, if he should survive, than a private person; and moreover, in case of
                    Servius being put to death, whatever other person he might select as his
                    son-in-law, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Son-in-law.</hi> Why not one of his two sons, Lucius and
                        Aruns? Dio. iv. 1. If these were not his grandchildren rather, they must
                        have been infants at the time. Dio. iv. 4, 6. —At this time infants could
                        not succeed to the throne. — <hi rend="italics">Ruperti.</hi>
                    </note> it seemed likely that he would adopt as his successor on the throne.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This sentence has given some
                        trouble to the commentators. —Some will have it that three distinct reasons
                        are given for assassinating Tarquinius rather than Servius Tullius, and that
                        these are severally marked and distinguished by <hi rend="italics">et —et
                            —trum,</hi> the second only having <hi rend="italics">quia.</hi> —Stroth
                        will have it that only two reasons are assigned, one, why the king should be
                        killed, and the other, why Servius Tullius should not be killed, arising
                        from the danger and uselessness of the act —the former has not a <hi
                            rend="italics">quia,</hi> because it was a fact, ( <hi rend="italics">et
                            injuriae dolor,</hi> &amp;c.,) while the latter has it in the first part
                        (the danger, <hi rend="italics">et quia gravior,</hi> &amp;c., <hi
                            rend="italics">quia</hi> being understood also before the other, the
                        uselessness, <hi rend="italics">turn, Servio occiso,</hi> &amp;c.) because
                        it contained the reasoning of the youths. Doering says there were only two
                        powerful reasons, revenge and fear, and a ratio probabilis introduced by <hi
                            rend="italics">tum;</hi> which has the force of insuper. According to
                        Dr. Hunter, there are two formal assertions, one, that resentment stimulated
                        the sons of Ancus against the king himself; the other, that the plot is laid
                        for the king himself upon two considerations, of reason and policy. </note>
                    For these reasons the <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> plot is laid against <pb
                        n="55" xml:id="p.55"/> the king himself. Two of the most ferocious of the
                    shepherds being selected for the daring deed, with the rustic implements to
                    which each had been accustomed, by conducting themselves in as violent a manner
                    as possible in the porch of the palace, under pretence of a quarrel, draw the
                    attention of all the king's attendants to themselves; then, when both appealed
                    to the king, and their clamour reached even the interior of the palace, they are
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> called in and proceed before the king. At
                    first both bawled aloud, and vied in interrupting each other by their clamour,
                    until being restrained by the lictor, and commanded to speak in turns, they at
                    length cease railing. According to <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> concert,
                    one begins to state the matter. When the king, attentive to him, had turned
                    himself quite that way, the other, raising up his axe, struck it into his head,
                    and leaving the weapon in the wound, they both rush out of the house. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When those who were around had raised up the
                    king in a dying state, the lictors seize on the men who were endeavouring to
                    escape. Upon this followed an uproar and concourse of people, wondering what the
                    matter was. Tanaquil, during the tumult, orders the palace to be shut, thrusts
                    out all who were present: at the same time she sedulously prepares every thing
                    necessary for dressing the wound, as if a hope still remained; at the same time,
                    in case her hopes should disappoint her, she projects other means of safety.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Sending immediately for Servius, after she
                    had showed to him her husband almost expiring, holding his right hand, she
                    entreats him not to suffer the death of his father-in-law to pass unavenged, nor
                    his mother-in-law to be an object of insult to their enemies. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Servius,</quote> she said, <quote> if you are a man, the kingdom is
                        yours, not theirs, who, by the hands of others, have perpetrated the worst
                        of crimes. Exert yourself, and follow the guidance of the gods, who
                        portended that this head would be illustrious by having formerly shed a
                        blaze around it. Now let that celestial flame arouse you. Now awake in
                        earnest. We, too, though foreigners, have reigned. Consider who you are, not
                        whence you are sprung. If your own plans are not matured by reason of the
                        suddenness of this event, then follow mine. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the uproar and violence of the multitude
                    could scarcely be withstood, Tanaquil addresses the populace from the upper part
                    of the palace through the windows facing the new street (for the royal family
                    resided near the temple of <pb n="56" xml:id="p.56"/> Jupiter Stator). She bids
                    them <quote> be of good courage; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that the king
                        was stunned by the suddenness of the blow; that the weapon had not sunk deep
                        into his body; that he was already come to himself again; that the wound had
                        been examined, the blood having been wiped off; that all the symptoms were
                        favourable; that she hoped they would see him very soon; and that, in the
                        mean time, he commanded the people to obey the orders of Servius Tullius.
                        That he would administer justice, and would perform all the functions of the
                        king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Servius comes forth with the trabea and
                    lictors, and seating himself on the king's throne, decides some cases, with
                    respect to others pretends that he will consult the king. Therefore, the death
                    being concealed for several days, though Tarquin had already expired, he, under
                    pretence of discharging the duty of another, strengthened his own interest. Then
                    at length the matter being made public, and lamentations being raised in the
                    palace, Servius, supported by a strong guard, took possession of the kingdom by
                    the consent of the senate, being the first who did so without the orders of the
                    people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The children of Ancus, the instruments
                    of their villany having been already seized, as soon as it was announced that
                    the king still lived, and that the power of Servius was so great, had already
                    gone into exile to Suessa Pometia. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And now Servius began to strengthen his power,
                    not more by public <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> By <hi
                            rend="italics">public —private.</hi> The <quote>public</quote> were the
                        steps taken by Servius to establish his political ascendency, whilst the
                            <quote>private</quote> refer to those intended to strengthen his family
                        connexions. </note> than by private measures; and lest the feelings of the
                    children of Tarquin might be the same towards himself as those of the children
                    of Ancus had been towards Tarquin, he unites his two daughters in marriage to
                    the young princes, the Tarquinii, Lucius and <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Aruns. Nor yet did he break through the inevitable decrees of fate by human
                    measures, so that envy of the sovereign power should not produce general
                    treachery and animosity even among the members of his own family. Very
                    opportunely for maintaining the tranquillity of the present state, a war was
                    commenced with the Veientes (for the truce had now expired <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">The truce had now expired.</hi> If the truce concluded
                        with them by Romulus be here meant, it was long since expired, since about
                        140 years had now elapsed. It is probable, however, that it was renewed in
                        the reign of Tullius. </note> ) and with the other <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="57" xml:id="p.57"/> Etrurians. In that war, both the valour and good
                    fortune of Tullius were conspicuous, and he returned to Rome, after routing a
                    great army of the enemy, now unquestionably king, whether he tried the
                    dispositions of the fathers or the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> people. He
                    then sets about a work of peace of the utmost importance; that, as Numa had been
                    the author of religious institutions, so posterity might celebrate Servius as
                    the founder of all distinction among the members of the state, and of those
                    orders by which a limitation is established between the degrees of rank and
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> fortune. For he instituted the census, a
                    most salutary measure for an empire destined to become so great, according to
                    which the services of war and peace were to be performed, not by every person,
                    (indiscriminately,) as formerly, but in proportion to the amount of property.
                    Then he formed, according to the census, the classes and centuries, and the
                    arrangement as it now exists, eminently suited either to peace or war. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Of those who had an estate of a hundred
                    thousand asses or more, he made eighty centuries, forty of seniors and forty of
                    juniors. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> All these were called the first
                    class, the seniors were to be in readiness to guard the city, the juniors to
                    carry on war abroad. The arms enjoined them were a helmet, a round shield,
                    greaves, and a coat of mail, all of brass; these were for the defence of their
                    body; their weapons of offence were a spear and a sword. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To this class were added two centuries of mechanics, who
                    were to serve without arms; the duty imposed upon them was to carry the military
                    engines. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The second class comprehended all
                    whose estate was from seventy-five to a hundred thousand asses, and of these,
                    seniors and juniors, twenty centuries were enrolled. The arms enjoined them were
                    a buckler instead of a shield, and except a coat of mail, all the rest were the
                    same. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He appointed the property of the third
                    class to amount to fifty thousand asses; the number of centuries was the same,
                    and formed with the same distinction of age, nor was there any change in their
                    arms, only greaves were taken from them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In
                    the fourth class, the property was twenty-five thousand asses, the same number
                    of centuries was formed: the arms were changed, nothing was given them but a
                    spear and a long javelin. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The fifth class was
                    increased, thirty centuries were formed; these carried slings and stones for
                    throwing. Among them <pb n="58" xml:id="p.58"/> were reckoned the horn-blowers,
                    and the trumpeters, distributed into three centuries. This whole class was rated
                    at eleven thousand asses. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Property lower than
                    this comprehended all the rest of the citizens, and of them one century was made
                    up which was exempted from serving in war. Having thus divided and armed the
                    infantry, he levied twelve centuries of knights from among the chief men of the
                    state. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Likewise out of the three centuries,
                    appointed by Romulus, he formed other six under the same names which they had
                    received at their first institution. Ten thousand asses were given them out of
                    the public revenue, for the buying of horses, and widows were assigned them, who
                    were to pay two thousand asses yearly for the support of the horses. All these
                    burdens were taken off the poor and laid on the rich. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Then an additional honour was conferred upon them; for the
                    suffrage was not now granted promiscuously to all, as it had been established by
                    Romulus, and observed by his successors, to every man with the same privilege
                    and the same right, but gradations were established, so that no one might seem
                    excluded from the right of voting, and yet the whole power might reside in the
                    chief men of the state. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For the knights were
                    first called, and then the eighty centuries of the first class; and if they
                    happened to differ, which was seldom the case, those of the second were called:
                    and they seldom ever descended so low as to come to the lowest class. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Nor need we be surprised, that the present
                    regulation, which now exists, since the tribes were increased to thirty-five,
                    should not agree in the number of centuries of juniors and seniors with the
                    amount instituted by Servius Tullius, they being now double of what they were at
                    that time. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For the city being divided into
                    four parts, according to the regions and hills which were then inhabited, he
                    called these divisions tribes, as I think, from the tribute. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Varro, de L. L. iv. 36, thinks, on the
                        contrary, that <hi rend="italics">tributum</hi> was so called, as being paid
                        by the <hi rend="italics">tribes.</hi>
                    </note> For the method of levying taxes rateably according to the value of
                    estates was also introduced by him; nor had these tribes any relation to the
                    number and distribution of the centuries. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The census being now completed, which he had
                    expedited by the terror of a law passed on those not rated, with threats of
                    imprisonment and death, he issued a proclamation that all the Roman citizens,
                    horse and foot, should attend at <pb n="59" xml:id="p.59"/> the dawn of day in
                    the Campus Martius, each in his century. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There
                    he drew up his army and performed a lustration of it by the sacrifices called
                    suovetaurilia, and that was called the closing of the lustrum, because that was
                    the conclusion of the census. Eighty thousand citizens are said to have been
                    rated in that survey. Fabius Pictor, the oldest of our historians, adds, that
                    such was the number of those who were able to bear arms. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To accommodate that number the city seemed to require
                    enlargement. He adds two hills, the Quirinal and Viminal; then in continuation
                    he enlarges the Esquiliae, and takes up his own residence there, in order that
                    respectability might attach to the place. He surrounds the city with a rampart,
                    a moat, and a wall: thus he enlarges the pomœrium. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They who regard only the etymology of the word, will have
                    the pomœrium to be a space of ground without the walls; but it is rather a space
                    on each side the wall, which the Etrurians in building cities consecrated by
                    augury, reaching to a certain extent both within and without in the direction
                    they intended to raise the wall; so that the houses might not be joined to it on
                    the inside, as they commonly are now, and also that there might be some space
                    without left free from human occupation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                    space, which it was not lawful to till or inhabit, the Romans called the
                    pomœrium, not for its being without the wall, more than for the wall's being
                    without it: and in enlarging the city, as far as the walls were intended to
                    proceed outwards, so far these consecrated limits were likewise extended. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The state being increased by the enlargement
                    of the city, and every thing modelled at home and abroad for the exigencies both
                    of peace and war, that the acquisition of power might not always depend on mere
                    force of arms, he endeavoured to extend his empire by policy, and at the same
                    time to add some ornament to the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Temple of Diana.</hi> Built on the summit of the Aventine
                        mount towards the Tiber. On its brazen pillar were engraved the laws of the
                        treaty, and which were still extant in the time of Augustus. </note> The
                    temple of Diana at Ephesus was at that time in high renown; fame represented it
                    to have been built by all the-states of Asia, in common. When Servius, amid some
                    grandees of the Latins with whom he had taken pains to form connexions of
                    hospitality and friendship, extolled in high terms such concord and associa- <pb
                        n="60" xml:id="p.60"/> tion of their gods, by frequently insisting on the
                    same subject, he at length prevailed so far as that the Latin states agreed to
                    build a temple to Diana at Rome, in conjunction with the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This was an acknowledgment that Rome was
                    the head of both nations, concerning which they had so often disputed in arms.
                    Though that object seemed to have been left out of consideration by all the
                    Latins, in consequence of the matter having been so often attempted
                    unsuccessfully by arms, fortune seemed to present one of the Sabines with an
                    opportunity of recovering the superiority to his country by his own address.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A cow is said to have been calved to a
                    certain person, the head of a family among the Sabines, of surprising size and
                    beauty. Her horns, which were hung up in the porch of the temple of Diana,
                    remained, for many ages, a monument of this wonder. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The thing was looked upon as a prodigy, as it was, and the
                    soothsayers declared, that sovereignty would reside in that state of which a
                    citizen should immolate this heifer to Diana. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    This prediction had also reached the ears of the high priest of Diana. The
                    Sabine, when he thought the proper time for offering the sacrifice was come,
                    drove the cow to Rome, led her to the temple of that goddess, and set her before
                    the altar. The Roman priest, struck with the uncommon size of the victim, so
                    much celebrated by fame, thus accosted the Sabine: <quote>What intendest thou to
                        do, stranger?</quote> says he. <quote> Is it with impure hands to offer a
                        sacrifice to Diana? Why dost not thou first wash thyself in running water?
                        The Tiber runs along in the bottom of that valley. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The stranger, being seized with a scruple of
                    conscience, and desirous of having every thing done in due form, that the event
                    might answer the prediction, from the temple went down to the Tiber. In the mean
                    time the priest sacrificed the cow to Diana, which gave great satisfaction to
                    the king, and to the whole state. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Servius, though he had now acquired an
                    indisputable right to the kingdom by long possession, yet as he heard that
                    expressions were sometimes thrown out by young Tarquin, importing, <quote>That
                        he held the crown without the consent of the people,</quote> having first
                    secured their good will by dividing among them, man by man, the lands taken from
                    their enemies, he ventured to propose the question to the people, whether they
                        <quote>chose and ordered that he should be king,</quote> and was <pb n="61"
                        xml:id="p.61"/> declared king with such unanimity, as had not been observed
                    in the election of any of his predecessors. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But this circumstance diminished not Tarquin's hope of obtaining the throne;
                    nay, because he had observed that the question of the distribution of land to
                    the people <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is noticed as the
                        first trace of the Agrarian division by Niebuhr, i. p. 161. </note> was
                    carried against the will of the fathers, he felt so much the more satisfied that
                    an opportunity was now presented to him of arraigning Servius before the
                    fathers, and of increasing his own influence in the senate, he being himself
                    naturally of a fiery temper, and his wife, Tullia, at home stimulating his
                    restless temper. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For the Roman palace also
                    afforded an instance of tragic guilt, so that through their disgust of kings,
                    liberty might come more matured, and the throne, which should be attained
                    through crime, might be the last. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This L.
                    Tarquinius (whether he was the son or grandson of Tarquinius Priscus is not
                    clear; with the greater number of authorities, however, I would say, his son
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">His son.</hi> Dionysius will have it that he was the
                        grandson. See Nieb. i. p. 367. </note> ) had a brother, Aruns Tarquinius, a
                    youth of a mild disposition. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To these two, as
                    has been already stated, the two Tulliae, daughters of the king, had been
                    married, they also being of widely different tempers. It had so happened that
                    the two violent dispositions were not united in marriage, through the good
                    fortune, I suspect, of the Roman people, in order that the reign of Servius
                    might be more protracted, and the morals of the state be firmly established.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The haughty Tullia was chagrined, that
                    there was no material in her husband, either for ambition or bold daring.
                    Directing all her regard to the other Tarquinius, him she admired, him she
                    called a man, and one truly descended of royal blood; she expressed her contempt
                    of her sister, because, having got a man, she was deficient in the spirit
                    becoming a woman. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Similarity of mind soon
                    draws them together, as wickedness is in general most congenial to wickedness.
                    But the commencement of producing general confusion originated with the woman.
                    She, accustomed to the secret conversations of the other's husband, refrained
                    not from using the most contumelious language of her husband to his brother, of
                    her sister to (her sister's) husband, and contended, that it were <pb n="62"
                        xml:id="p.62"/> better that she herself were unmarried, and he single, than
                    that they should be matched unsuitably, so that they must languish away through
                    life by reason of the dastardly conduct of others. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> If the gods had granted her the husband of whom she was
                    worthy, that she should soon see the crown in her own house, which she now saw
                    at her father's. She soon inspires the young man with her own daring notions.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Aruns Tarquinius and the younger Tullia,
                    when they had, by immediate successive deaths, made their houses vacant for new
                    nuptials, are united in marriage, Servius rather not prohibiting than approving
                    the measure. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then indeed the old age of Servius began to be
                    every day more disquieted, his reign to be more unhappy. For now the woman
                    looked from one crime to another, and suffered not her husband to rest by night
                    or by day, lest their past murders might go for nothing. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That what she had wanted was not a person whose wife she might be
                        called, or one with whom she might in silence live a slave; what she had
                        wanted was one who would consider himself worthy of the throne; who would
                        remember that he was the son of Tarquinius Priscus; who would rather possess
                        a kingdom than hope for it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If you, to
                        whom I consider myself married, are such a one, I address you both as
                        husband and king; but if not, our condition has been changed so far for the
                        worse, as in that person crime is associated with meanness. Why not prepare
                        yourself? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is not necessary for you, as
                        for your father, (coming here) from Corinth or Tarquinii, to strive for
                        foreign thrones. Your household and country's gods, the image of your
                        father, and the royal palace, and the royal throne in that palace,
                        constitute and call you king. Or if you have too little spirit for this, why
                        do you disappoint the nation? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Why do you
                        stuffer yourself to be looked up to as a prince? Get hence to Tarquinii or
                        Corinth. Sink back again to your (original) race, more like your brother
                        than your father. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By chiding him in these and other terms, she
                    spurs on the young man; nor can she herself rest; (indignant) that when
                    Tanaquil, a foreign woman, could achieve so great a project, as to bestow two
                    successive thrones on her husband, and then on her son-in-law, she, sprung from
                    royal blood, should have no weight in bestowing and taking away a kingdom.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Tarquinius, driven on by these frenzied
                    instigations of the woman, began <pb n="63" xml:id="p.63"/> to go round and
                    solicit the patricians, especially those of the younger families; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Younger families.</hi> These had been brought into the
                        senate, as we have seen, by Tarquinius Priscus, and consequently favoured
                        the Tarquinian interest. Nieb. i. p. 372. </note> reminded them of his
                    father's kindness, and claimed a return for it; enticed the young men by
                    presents; increased his interest, as well by making magnificent promises on his
                    own part, as by inveighing against the king at every opportunity. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> At length, as soon as the time seemed convenient for
                    accomplishing his object, he rushed into the forum, accompanied by a party of
                    armed men; then, whilst all were struck with dismay, seating himself on the
                    throne before the senate-house, he ordered the fathers to be summoned to the
                    senate-house by the crier to attend king Tarquinius. They assembled immediately,
                    some being already prepared for the occasion, some through fear, lest their not
                    having come might prove detrimental to them, astounded at the novelty and
                    strangeness of the matter, and considering that it was now all over with
                    Servius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then Tarquinius, commencing his
                    invectives against his immediate ancestors: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    "that a slave, and born of a slave, after the untimely death of his parent,
                    without an interregnum being adopted, as on former occasions, without any
                    comitia (being held), without the suffrages of the people, or the sanction of
                    the fathers, he had taken possession of the kingdom as the gift of a woman.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That so born, so created king, ever a
                    favourer of the most degraded class, to which he himself belongs, through a
                    hatred of the high station of others, he had taken their land from the leading
                    men of the state and divided it among the very meanest; that he had laid all the
                    burdens, which were formerly common, on the chief members of the community;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> that he had instituted the census, in
                    order that the fortune of the wealthier citizens might be conspicuous to
                    (excite) public envy, and that all was prepared whence he might bestow largesses
                    on the most needy, whenever he might please. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Servius, aroused by the alarming
                    announcement, came in during this harangue, immediately from the porch of the
                    senate-house, he says with a loud voice, <quote> What means this, Tarquin? by
                        what audacity hast thou dared to summon the fathers, while I am still alive?
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> or to sit on my throne? </quote> To
                    this, when he fiercely replied <quote> that he, the <pb n="64" xml:id="p.64"/>
                        son of a king, occupied the throne of his father, a much fitter successor to
                        the throne than a slave; that he (Servius) had insulted his masters full
                        long enough by his arbitrary shuffling, </quote> a shout arises from the
                    partisans of both, and a rush of the people into the senate-house took place,
                    and it became evident that whoever came off victor would have the throne.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then Tarquin, necessity itself now
                    obliging him to have recourse to the last extremity, having much the advantage
                    both in years and strength, seizes Servius by the middle, and having taken him
                    out of the senate-house, throws him down the steps to the bottom. He then
                    returns to the senate-house to assemble the senate. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The king's officers and attendants fly. He himself, almost
                    lifeless, when he was returning home with his royal retinue frightened to death,
                    and had arrived at the top of the Cyprian street, is slain by those who had been
                    sent by Tarquin, and had overtaken him in his flight. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> As the act is not inconsistent with her other marked
                    conduct, it is believed to have been done by Tullia's advice. Certain it is,
                    (for it is readily admitted,) that driving into the forum in her chariot, and
                    not abashed by the crowd of persons there, she called her husband out of the
                    senate-house, and was the first to style him king; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and when, on being commanded by him to withdraw from such a
                    tumult, she was returning home, and had arrived at the top of the Cyprian
                    street, where Diana's temple lately was, as she was turning to the right to the
                    Orbian hill, in order to arrive at the Esquiline, the person who was driving,
                    being terrified, stopped and drew in the reins, and pointed out to his mistress
                    the murdered Servius as he lay. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On this
                    occasion a revolting and inhuman crime is stated to have been committed, and the
                    place is a monument of it. They call it the Wicked Street, where Tullia, frantic
                    and urged on by the furies of her sister and husband, is reported to have driven
                    her chariot over her father's body, and to have carried a portion of her
                    father's body and blood to her own and her husband's household gods, herself
                    also being stained and sprinkled with it; through whose vengeance results
                    corresponding to the wicked commencement of the reign were soon to follow.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Tullius reigned forty-four years in such a
                    manner that a competition with him would prove difficult even for a good and
                    moderate successor. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But this also has been an
                    accession to his glory, that with him <pb n="65" xml:id="p.65"/> perished all
                    just and legitimate reigns. This authority, so mild and so moderate, yet,
                    because it was vested in one, some say that he had it in contemplation to
                    resign, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">To resign.</hi> Niebuhr is of opinion that what is said
                        regarding the Commentaries of Servius Tullius, chap. 60, has reference to
                        this. </note> had not the wickedness of his family interfered with him
                    whilst meditating the liberation of his country. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this period Tarquin began his reign,
                    whose actions procured him the surname of the Proud, for he refused his
                    father-in-law burial, alleging, that even Romulus died without sepulture.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He put to death the principal senators,
                    whom he suspected of having been in the interest of Servius. Then, conscious
                    that the precedent of obtaining the crown by evil means might be adopted from
                    him against himself, he surrounded his person with <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> armed men, for he had no claim to the kingdom except force,
                    inasmuch as he reigned without either the order of the people or the sanction of
                    the senate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To this was added (the fact) that,
                    as he reposed no hope in the affection of his subjects, he found it necessary to
                    secure his kingdom by terror; and in order to strike this into the greater
                    number, he took cognizance of capital cases solely by himself without assessors;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and under that pretext he had it in his
                    power to put to death, banish, or fine, not only those who were suspected or
                    hated, but those also from whom he could obtain nothing else but plunder.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The number of the fathers more especially
                    being thus diminished, he determined to elect none into the senate, in order
                    that the order might become contemptible by their very paucity, and that they
                    might feel the less resentment at no business being transacted by them.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For he was the first king who violated the
                    custom derived from his predecessors of consulting the senate on all subjects;
                    he administered the public business by domestic counsels. War, peace, treaties,
                    alliances, he contracted and dissolved with whomsoever he pleased, without the
                    sanction of the people and senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The nation
                    of the Latins in particular he wished to attach to him, so that by foreign
                    influence also he might be more secure among his own subjects; and he contracted
                    not only ties of hospitality but affinities also with their leading men.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To Octavius Mamilius of Tusculum he gives
                    his daughter in marriage; (he was by far the most eminent of the Latin name,
                    being de <pb n="66" xml:id="p.66"/> scended, if we believe tradition, from
                    Ulysses and the goddess Circe, and by this match he attaches to himself his
                    numerous kinsmen and friends). </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The influence of Tarquin among the chief men
                    of the Latins was now considerable, when he issues an order that they should
                    assemble on a certain day at the grove of Ferentina; that there was business
                    about which he wished to confer with them touching their common interest.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They assemble in great numbers at the
                    break of day. Tarquinius himself observed the day indeed, but he came a little
                    before sun-set. Many matters were there canvassed in the meeting in various
                    conversations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Turnus Herdonius, from Aricia,
                    inveighed violently against Tarquin for his absence. <quote>That it was no
                        wonder the cognomen of Proud was given him at Rome;</quote> for they now
                    called him so secretly and in whispers, but still generally. <quote> Could any
                        thing be more proud than thus to trifle with the entire nation of the
                        Latins? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After their chiefs had been called
                        at so great a distance from home, that he who summoned the meeting did not
                        attend; that no doubt their patience was tried, in order that if they
                        submitted to the yoke, he may crush them when at his mercy. For to whom did
                        it not plainly appear that he was aiming at sovereignty over the Latins?
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But if his own countrymen did well in
                        intrusting it to him, or if it was intrusted, and not seized on by means of
                        murder, that the Latins also ought to intrust him (though <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> not even so, inasmuch as he was a foreigner). But if
                        his own subjects are dissatisfied with him, (seeing that they are butchered
                        one upon another, driven into exile, and deprived of their property,) what
                        better prospects are held out to the Latins? If they follow his advice, that
                        they would depart thence, each to his own home, and take no more notice of
                        the day of meeting than the person who appointed it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this man, turbulent and daring, and one
                    who had attained influence at home by these means, was pressing these and other
                    observations having the same tendency, Tarquin came in. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> This put a conclusion to his harangue. All turned away from
                    him to salute Tarquin, who, on silence being enjoined, being advised by those
                    next him to apologize for having come at that time, says, that he had been
                    chosen arbiter between a father and a son; that, frown his anxiety to reconcile
                    them, he had delayed; and because that circum- <pb n="67" xml:id="p.67"/> stance
                    had consumed that day, that on the morrow he would transact the business which
                    he had determined on. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They say that he did not
                    make even that observation without a remark from Turnus; <quote> that no
                        controversy was shorter than one between a father and son, and that it might
                        be decided in a few words, —unless he submitted to his father, that he must
                        prove unfortunate. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Arician withdrew from the meeting,
                    uttering these reflections against the Roman king. Tarquin, feeling the matter
                    much more acutely than he appeared to do, immediately sets about planning the
                    death of Turnus, in order that he might inspire into the Latins the same terror
                    with which he had crushed the spirits of his own subjects at home; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> and because he could not be put to death openly, by
                    virtue of his authority, he accomplished the ruin of this innocent man by
                    bringing a false accusation against him. By means of some Aricians of the
                    opposite faction, he bribed a servant of Turnus with gold, to suffer a great
                    number of swords to be introduced privately into his lodging. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When this had been completed in the course of one night,
                    Tarquin, having summoned the chiefs of the Latins to him a little before day, as
                    if alarmed by some strange occurrence, says, <quote> that his delay of
                        yesterday, having been occasioned as it were by some providential care of
                        the gods, had been the means of preservation to him and them; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> that it was told to him that destruction was
                        prepared by Turnus for him and the chiefs of the Latins, that he alone might
                        obtain the government of the Latins. That he was to have made the attempt
                        yesterday at the meeting; that the matter was deferred, because the person
                        who summoned the meeting was absent, whom he chiefly aimed at. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> That thence arose that abuse of him for being
                        absent, because he disappointed his hopes by delaying. That he had no doubt,
                        but that if the truth were told him, he would come at the break of day, when
                        the assembly met, attended with a band of conspirators, and with arms in his
                        hands. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That it was said that a great
                        number of swords had been conveyed to his house. Whether that be true or
                        not, might be known immediately. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                        requested that they would accompany him thence to Turnus. </quote> Both the
                    daring temper of Turnus, and his harangue of yesterday, and the delay of
                    Tarquin, rendered the matter suspicious, because it seemed possible that the
                    murder might <pb n="68" xml:id="p.68"/> have been put off in consequence of it.
                    They proceed then with minds inclined indeed to believe, yet determined to
                    consider every thing false, unless the swords were detected. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When they arrived there, Turnus is aroused from sleep, and
                    guards are placed around him; and the servants, who, from affection to their
                    master, were preparing to use force, being secured, when the swords, which had
                    been concealed, were drawn out from all parts of the lodging, then indeed the
                    whole matter appeared manifest, and chains were placed on Turnus; and forthwith
                    a meeting of the Latins was summoned amid great confusion. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> There, on the swords being brought forward in the midst,
                    such violent hatred arose against him, that without being allowed a defence, by
                    a novel mode of death, being thrown into the reservoir of the. water of
                    Ferentina, a hurdle <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Hurdle,</hi> a mode of punishment in use among the
                        Carthaginians. See Tac. Germ. 12. Similar to the Greek, <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">katapontismo/s.</foreign>
                    </note> being placed over him, and stones being thrown into that, he was
                    drowned. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tarquin, having recalled the Latins to the
                    meeting, and applauded those who had inflicted well-merited punishment on
                    Turnus, as one convicted of parricide, by his attempting a change of government,
                    spoke as follows: <quote> That he could indeed proceed by a long-established
                        right; because, since all the Latins were. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        sprung from Alba, they were included in that treaty by which the entire
                        Alban nation, with their colonies, fell under the dominion of Rome, under
                        Tullus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, for the sake of the
                        interest of all parties, he thought rather, that that treaty should be
                        renewed; and that the Latins should, as participators, enjoy the prosperity
                        of the Roman people, rather than that they should be constantly either
                        apprehending or suffering the demolition of their town and the devastations
                        of their lands, which they suffered formerly in the reign of Ancus,
                        afterwards in the reign of his own father. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Latins were persuaded without any
                    difficulty, though in that treaty the advantage lay on the side of Rome; but
                    they both saw that the chiefs of the Latin nation sided and concurred with the
                    king, and Turnus was a recent instance of his danger to each, if he should make
                    any opposition. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thus the treaty was renewed,
                    and notice was given to the young men of the Latins, that, according to the
                    treaty, they should attend in considerable numbers in arms, on a certain <pb
                        n="69" xml:id="p.69"/> day, at the grove of Ferentina. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> And when they assembled from all the states according to
                    the edict of the Roman king, in order that they should neither have a general of
                    their own, nor a separate command, or their own standards, he compounded
                    companies of Latins and Romans, so as to make one out of two, and two out of
                    one; the companies being thus doubled, he appointed centurions over them. </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nor was Tarquin, though a tyrannical prince in
                    peace, a despicable general in war; nay, he would have equalled his predecessors
                    in that art, had not his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">His degeneracy —degeneratum.</hi> This use of the passive
                        participle is of frequent occurrence in Livy. </note> degeneracy in other
                    respects likewise detracted from his merit <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    here. He began the war against the Volsci, which lasted two hundred years after
                    his time, and took from them Suessa Pometia by <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    storm; and when by the sale of the spoils he had amassed forty talents of silver
                    and of gold, he designed such magnificence for a temple to Jupiter, as should be
                    worthy of the king of gods and men, of the Roman empire, and of the majesty of
                    the place itself: for the building of this temple he set apart the money arising
                    from the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> spoils. Soon after a war came upon
                    him, more tedious than he expected, in which, having in vain attempted to storm
                    Gabii, a city in his neighbourhood, when being repulsed from the walls all hopes
                    of taking it by siege also was taken from him, he assailed it by fraud and
                    stratagem, arts by no means <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Roman. For when,
                    as if the war was laid aside, he pretended to be busily taken up with laying the
                    foundation of the temple, and with his other works in the city, Sextus, the
                    youngest of his three sons, according to concert, fled to Gabii, complaining of
                    the inhuman cruelty of his father, <quote> that he had turned his tyranny from
                        others <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> against his own family, and was
                        uneasy at the number of his own children, intending to make the same
                        desolations in his own house which he had made in the senate, in order that
                        he might leave behind him no issue, nor heir to his <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> kingdom. That for his own part, as he had escaped from
                        amidst the swords and other weapons of his father, he was persuaded he could
                        find no safety any where but among the enemies of L. Tarquin. And, that they
                        might not be led astray, that the war, which it is now pretended has been
                        given up, still lies in reserve, and that he would attack them when off
                        their guard on <pb n="70" xml:id="p.70"/> the occurrence of an <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> opportunity. But if there be no refuge for
                        suppliants among them, that he would traverse all Latium, and would apply to
                        the Volscians, and Aequians, and Hernicians, until he should come to those
                        who knew how to protect children from the impious and cruel persecution of
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> parents. That perhaps he would find
                        some ardour also to take up arms and wage war against this proud king and
                        his haughty <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> subjects. </quote> As he
                    seemed a person likely to go further onward, incensed with anger, if they paid
                    him no regard, he is received by the Gabians very kindly. They bid him not to be
                    surprised, if he were at last the same to his children as he had been to his
                    subjects and <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> allies; —that he would
                    ultimately vent his rage on himself if other objects failed him; —that his
                    coming was very acceptable to them, and they thought that it would come to pass
                    that by his aid the war would be transferred from the gates of Gabii to the
                    walls of Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Upon this he was admitted into their public
                    councils, where though, with regard to other matters, he professed to submit to
                    the judgment of the old inhabitants of Gabii, to whom they were better known,
                    yet he every now and then advised them to renew the war; to that he pretended to
                    a superior knowledge, because he was well acquainted with the strength of both
                    nations, and knew that the king's pride was decidedly become hateful to his
                    subjects, which not even his own children could now endure. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As he thus by degrees stirred up the nobles of the Gabians
                    to renew the war, went himself with the most active of their youth on plundering
                    parties and expeditions, and ill-grounded credit was attached to all his words
                    and actions, framed as they were for deception, he is at length chosen
                    general-in-chief in the war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There when, the
                    people being still ignorant of what was really going on, several skirmishes with
                    the Romans took place, wherein the Gabians generally had the advantage, then all
                    the Gabians, from the highest to the lowest, were firmly persuaded, that Sextus
                    Tarquinius had been sent to them as their general, by the special favour of the
                    gods. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By his exposing himself to fatigues and
                    dangers, and by his generosity in dividing the plunder, he was so beloved by the
                    soldiers, that Tarquin the father had not greater power at Rome than the son at
                    Gabii. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When he saw he had got sufficient
                    strength collected to support him in any under- <pb n="71" xml:id="p.71"/>
                    taking, he sent one of his confidants to Rome to ask his father what he wished
                    him to do, seeing the gods had granted him the sole management of all affairs at
                    Gabii. To this courier no answer by word of mouth was given, because, I suppose,
                    he appeared of questionable fidelity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king
                    going into a garden of the palace, as it were to consider of the matter,
                    followed by his son's messenger; walking there for some time in silence, he is
                    said to have struck off the heads of the tallest poppies with his staff.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The messenger, wearied with demanding and
                    waiting for an answer, returned to Gabii as if without having accomplished his
                    object, and told what he had said himself; and what he had observed, adding,
                        <quote> that Tarquin, either through passion, aversion to him, or his innate
                        pride, had not spoke a word. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as it became evident to Sextus what
                    his father wished, and what conduct he recommended by those silent intimations,
                    he put to death the most eminent men of the city, accusing some of them to the
                    people, and others who were exposed by their own unpopularity. Many were
                    executed publicly, and some, against whom an impeachment was likely to prove
                    less specious, were secretly assassinated. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Means of escape were to some allowed, and others were banished, and their
                    estates, as well as the estates of those who were put to death, publicly
                    distributed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By the sweets of corruption,
                    plunder, and private advantage resulting from these distributions, the sense of
                    the public calamities became extinguished in them, till the state of Gabii,
                    destitute of counsel and assistance, was delivered without a struggle into the
                    hands of the Roman king. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tarquin, thus put in possession of Gabii, made
                    peace with the Aequians, and renewed the treaty with the Etrurians. Then he
                    turned his thoughts to the business of the city. The chief whereof was that of
                    leaving behind him the temple of Jupiter on the Tarpeian mount, as a monument of
                    his name and reign; [since posterity would remember] that of two Tarquinii, both
                    kings, the father had vowed, the son completed it. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And that the area, excluding all other forms of worship,
                    might be entirely appropriated to Jupiter, and his temple, which was to be
                    erected upon it, he resolved to unhallow several small temples and chapels,
                    which had been vowed first by king Tatius, in the heat of the battle against
                    Romulus, and which he afterwards consecrated and dedicated. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="72" xml:id="p.72"/> In the very beginning of founding this work it is
                    said that the gods exerted their divinity to presage the future greatness of
                    this empire; for though the birds declared for the unhallowing of all the other
                    temples, they did not admit of it with respect to that of Terminus. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This omen and augury were taken to import that
                    Terminus's not changing his residence, and being the only one of the gods who
                    was not called out of the places devoted to their worship, presaged the duration
                    and stability of their empire. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This being
                    deemed an omen of the perpetuity, there followed another portending the
                    greatness of the empire. It is reported that the head of a man, with the face
                    entire, appeared to the workmen when digging the foundation of the temple.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The sight of this phenomenon unequivocally
                    presaged that this temple should be the metropolis of the empire, and the head
                    of the world; and so declared the soothsayers, both those who were in the city,
                    and those whom they had sent for from Etruria, to consult on this subject.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The king was encouraged to enlarge the
                    expense; so that the spoils of Pometia, which had been destined to complete the
                    work, scarcely sufficed for laying the foundation. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On this account I am more inclined to believe Fabius
                    Pictor, besides his being the more ancient historian, that there were only forty
                    talents, than Piso, who says that forty thousand pounds weight of silver were
                    set apart for that purpose; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> a sum of money
                    neither to be expected from the spoils of any one city in those times, and one
                    that would more than suffice for the foundation of any structure, even though
                    exhibiting the magnificence of modern structures. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tarquin, intent upon finishing this temple,
                    having sent for workmen from all parts of Etruria, employed on it not only the
                    public money, but the manual labour of the people; and when this labour, by no
                    means inconsiderable in itself, was added to their military service, still the
                    people murmured less at their building the temples of the gods with their own
                    hands; they were afterwards transferred to other works, which, whilst less in
                    show, (required) still greater toil: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> such as
                    the erecting benches in the circus, and conducting under ground the principal
                    sewer, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">The principal sewer</hi> —the <hi rend="italics">cloaca
                            maxima.</hi> This is attributed to Tarquinius Priscus by several
                        writers. Dio. iii. 67, states that it was he commenced it. See Plin. H. N.
                        xxxvi. Nieb. i. p. 385. </note> the receptacle of all the <pb n="73"
                        xml:id="p.73"/> filth of the city; to which two works even modern splendour
                    can scarcely produce any thing <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> equal. The
                    people having been employed in these works, because he both considered that such
                    a multitude was a burden to the city when there was no employment for them, and
                    further, he was anxious that the frontiers of the empire should be more
                    extensively occupied by sending colonists, he sent colonists to Signia and
                    Circeii, to serve as defensive barriers hereafter to the city by land and
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> sea. While he was thus employed a
                    frightful prodigy appeared to him. A serpent sliding out of a wooden pillar,
                    after causing dismay and a run into the palace, not so much struck the king's
                    heart with sudden terror, as filled him with anxious <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> solicitude. Accordingly when Etrurian soothsayers only were
                    employed for public prodigies, terrified at this as it were domestic apparition,
                    he determined on sending persons to Delphos to the most celebrated oracle in the
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> world; and not venturing to intrust the
                    responses of the oracle to any other person, he despatched his two sons to
                    Greece through lands unknown at that time, and seas still more so. Titus and
                    Aruns were the two who <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> went. To them were
                    added, as a companion, L. Junius Brutus, the son of Tarquinia, sister to the
                    king, a youth of an entirely different quality of mind from that the disguise of
                    which he had assumed. Brutus, on hearing that the chief men of the city, and
                    among others his own brother, had been put to death by his uncle, resolved to
                    leave nothing in his intellects that might be dreaded by the king, nor any thing
                    in his fortune to be coveted, and thus to be secure in contempt, where there was
                    but little protection in <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> justice. Therefore
                    designedly fashioning himself to the semblance of foolishness, after he suffered
                    himself and his whole estate to become a prey to the king, he did not refuse to
                    take even the surname of Brutus, that, concealed under the cover of such a
                    cognomen, that genius that was to liberate the Roman people might await its
                    proper <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> time. He, being brought to Delphos by
                    the Tarquinii rather as a subject of sport than as a companion, is said to have
                    brought with him as an offering to Apollo a golden rod, enclosed in a staff of
                    cornel-wood hollowed out for the purpose, a mystical emblem of his own
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> mind. When they arrived there, their
                    father's commission being executed, a desire seized the young men of inquiring
                    on which of them the sovereignty <pb n="74" xml:id="p.74"/> of Rome should
                    devolve. They say that a voice was returned from the bottom of the cave, <quote>
                        Young men, whichever of you shall first kiss his mother shall enjoy the
                        sovereign power at <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Rome. </quote> The
                    Tarquinii order the matter to be kept secret with the utmost care, that Sextus,
                    who had been left behind at Rome, might be ignorant of the response, and have no
                    share in the kingdom; they cast lots among themselves, as to which of them
                    should first kiss his mother, after they had returned to <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Rome. Brutus, thinking that the Pythian response had
                    another meaning, as if he had stumbled and fallen, touched the ground with his
                    lips; she being, forsooth, the common mother of all <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> mankind. After this they all returned to Rome, where
                    preparations were being made with the greatest vigour for a war against the
                    Rutulians. </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Rutulians, a nation very wealthy,
                    considering the country and age they lived in, were at that time in possession
                    of Ardea. Their riches gave occasion to the war; for the king of the Romans,
                    being exhausted of money by the magnificence of his public works, was desirous
                    both to enrich himself, and by a large booty <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    to soothe the minds of his subjects, who, besides other instances of his
                    tyranny, were incensed against his government, because they were indignant that
                    they had been kept so long a time by the king in the employments of mechanics,
                    and in labour fit for slaves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> An attempt was
                    made to take Ardea by storm; when that did not succeed, the enemy began to be
                    distressed by a blockade, and by works raised around them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As it commonly happens in standing camps, the war being
                    rather tedious than violent, furloughs were easily obtained, more so by the
                    officers, however, than the common soldiers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The young princes sometimes spent their leisure hours in feasting and
                    entertainments. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> One day as they were drinking
                    in the tent of Sextus Tarquin, where Collatinus Tarquinius, the son of Egerius,
                    was also at supper, mention was made of wives. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Every one commended his own in an extravagant manner, till a dispute arising
                    about it, Collatinus said, <quote> There was no occasion for words, that it
                        might be known in a few hours how far his Lucretia excelled all the rest. If
                        then, added he, we have any share of the vigour of youth, let us mount our
                        horses and examine the behaviour of our wives; that must be most
                        satisfactory to every one, which shall meet his eyes on the unexpected
                        arrival of <pb n="75" xml:id="p.75"/> the husband. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were heated with wine; <quote>Come on,
                        then,</quote> say all. They immediately galloped to Rome, where they arrived
                    in the dusk of the evening. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From thence they
                    went to Collatia, where they find Lucretia, not like the king's
                    daughters-in-law, whom they had seen spending their time in luxurious
                    entertainments with their equals, but though at an advanced time of night,
                    employed at her wool, sitting in the middle of the house amid her maids working
                    around her. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The merit of the contest
                    regarding the ladies was assigned to Lucretia. Her husband on his arrival, and
                    the Tarquinii, were kindly received; the husband, proud of his victory, gives
                    the young princes a polite invitation. There the villanous passion for violating
                    Lucretia by force seizes Sextus Tarquin; both her beauty, and her approved
                    purity, act as incentives. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And then, after
                    this youthful frolic of the night, they return to the camp. </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days after, without the knowledge of
                    Collatinus, Sextus came to Collatia with one attendant only; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> where, being kindly received by them, as not being aware of
                    his intention, after he had been conducted after supper into the guests'
                    chamber, burning with passion, when every thing around seemed sufficiently
                    secure, and all fast asleep, he comes to Lucretia, as she lay asleep, with a
                    naked sword, and with his left hand pressing down the woman's breast, he says,
                        <quote> Be silent, Lucretia; I am Sextus Tarquin; I have a sword in my hand;
                        you shall die, if you utter a word. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When awaking terrified from sleep, the woman
                    beheld no aid, impending death nigh at hand; then Tarquin acknowledged his
                    passion, entreated, mixed threats with entreaties, tried the female's mind in
                    every possible way. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he saw her
                    inflexible, and that she was not moved even by the terror of death, he added to
                    terror the threat of dishonour; he says that he will lay a murdered slave naked
                    by her side when dead, so that she may be said to have been slain in infamous
                    adultery. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When by the terror of this disgrace
                    his lust, as it were victorious, had overcome her inflexible chastity, and
                    Tarquin had departed, exulting in having triumphed over a lady's honour,
                    Lucretia, in melancholy distress at so dreadful a misfortune, despatches the
                    same messenger to Rome to her father, and to Ardea to her husband, that they
                    would come each with one trusty friend; that it was necessary to do so, and that
                        <pb n="76" xml:id="p.76"/> quickly. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">To do so, and that quickly,</hi>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> —a use of the participles <hi
                            rend="italics">facto</hi> and <hi rend="italics">maturato</hi> similar
                        to that already noticed in chap. 53, <hi rend="italics">degeneratum.</hi>
                    </note> Sp. Lucretius comes with P. Valerius, the son of Volesus, Collatinus
                    with L. Junius Brutus, with whom, as he was returning to Rome, he happened to be
                    met by his wife's messenger. They find Lucretia sitting in her chamber in
                    sorrowful <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> dejection. On the arrival of her
                    friends the tears burst from her eyes; and to her husband, on his inquiry
                        <quote>whether all was right,</quote> she says, <quote> By no means, for
                        what can be right with a woman who has lost her honour? The traces of
                        another man are on your bed, Collatinus. But the body only has been
                        violated, the mind is guiltless; death shall be my witness. But give me your
                        right hands, and your honour, that the adulterer shall not come off
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> unpunished. It is Sextus Tarquin, who,
                        an enemy in the guise of a guest, has borne away hence a triumph fatal to
                        me, and to himself, if you are <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> men.
                    </quote> They all pledge their honour; they attempt to console her, distracted
                    as she was in mind, by turning away the guilt from her, constrained by force, on
                    the perpetrator of the crime; that it is the mind sins, not the body; and that
                    where intention was wanting guilt could not <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    be. <quote>It is for you to see,</quote> says she, <quote> what is due to him.
                        As for me, though I acquit myself of guilt, from punishment I do not
                        discharge myself; nor shall any woman survive her dishonour pleading the
                        example of <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Lucretia. </quote> The knife,
                    which she kept concealed beneath her garment, she plunges into her heart, and
                    falling forward on the wound, she dropped down <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> expiring. The husband and father shriek aloud. </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Brutus, while they were overpowered with
                    grief, having drawn the knife out of the wound, and holding it up before him
                    reeking with blood, said, <quote> By this blood, most pure before the pollution
                        of royal villany, I swear, and I call you, O gods, to witness my oath, that
                        I shall pursue Lucius Tarquin the Proud, his wicked wife, and all their
                        race, with fire, sword, and all other means in my power; nor shall I ever
                        suffer them or any other to reign at Rome. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then he gave the knife to Collatinus, and
                    after him to Lucretius and Valerius, who were surprised at such extraordinary
                    mind in the breast of Brutus. However, they all take the oath as they were
                    directed, and converting their sorrow into rage, follow Brutus as their leader,
                    who from that time ceased not to so- <pb n="77" xml:id="p.77"/> licit them to
                    abolish the regal power. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They carry Lucretia's
                    body from her own house, and convey it into the forum; and assemble a number of
                    persons by the strangeness and atrocity of the extraordinary occurrence, as
                    usually happens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They complain, each for
                    himself, of the royal villany and violence. Both the grief of the father moves
                    them, as also Brutus, the reprover of their tears and unavailing complaints, and
                    their adviser to take up arms against those who dared to treat them as enemies,
                    as would become men and Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Each most
                    spirited of the youth voluntarily presents himself in arms; the rest of the
                    youth follow also. From thence, after leaving an adequate garrison at the gates
                    at Collatia, and having appointed sentinels, so that no one might give
                    intelligence of the disturbance to the king's party, the rest set out for Rome
                    in arms under the conduct of Brutus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they
                    arrived there, the armed multitude cause panic and confusion wherever they go.
                    Again, when they see the principal men of the state placing themselves at their
                    head, they think that, whatever it may be, it was not without good reason.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor does the heinousness of the
                    circumstance excite less violent emotions at Rome than it had done at Collatia;
                    accordingly they run from all parts of the city into the forum, whither, when
                    they came, the public crier summoned them to attend the tribune of the celeres,
                    with which office Brutus happened to be at that time vested. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> There an harangue was delivered by him, by no means of that
                    feeling and capacity which had been counterfeited up to that day, concerning the
                    violence and lust of Sextus Tarquin, the horrid violation of Lucretia and her
                    lamentable death, the bereavement of Tricipitinus, to whom the cause of his
                    daughter's death was more exasperating and deplorable than the death itself.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To this was added the haughty insolence of
                    the king himself, and the sufferings and toils of the people, buried in the
                    earth in cleansing sinks and sewers; that the Romans, the conquerors of all the
                    surrounding states, instead of warriors had become labourers and stone-cutters.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The unnatural murder of king Servius
                    Tullius was dwelt on, and his daughter's driving over the body of her father in
                    her impious chariot, and the gods who avenge parents were invoked by him.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> By stating these and other, I suppose,
                    more exasperating circumstances, which though by no means easily detailed by
                    writers, the heinousness of the case suggested at <pb n="78" xml:id="p.78"/> the
                    time, he persuaded the multitude, already incensed, to deprive the king of his
                    authority, and to order the banishment of L. Tarquin with his wife and children.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He himself, having selected and armed
                    some of the young men, who readily gave in their names, set out for Ardea to the
                    camp to excite the army against the king: the command in the city he leaves to
                    Lucretius, who had been already appointed prefect of the city by the king.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> During this tumult Tullia fled from her
                    house, both men and women cursing her wherever she went, and invoking on her the
                    furies the avengers of parents. </p>
                <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> News of these transactions having reached the
                    camp, when the king, alarmed at this sudden revolution, was going to Rome to
                    quell the commotions, Brutus, for he had notice of his approach, turned out of
                    the way, that he might not meet him; and much about the same time Brutus and
                    Tarquin arrived by different routes, the one at Ardea, the other at Rome.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The gates were shut against Tarquin, and
                    an act of banishment passed against him; the deliverer of the state the camp
                    received with great joy, and the king's sons were expelled. Two of them followed
                    their father, and went into banishment to Caere, a city of Etruria. Sextus
                    Tarquin, having gone to Gabii, as to his own kingdom, was slain by the avengers
                    of the old feuds, which he had raised against himself by his rapines and
                    murders. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Lucius Tarquin the Proud reigned
                    twenty-five years: the regal form of government continued from the building of
                    the city to this period of its deliverance, two hundred and forty-four years.
                    Two consuls, viz. Lucius Junius Brutus and Lucius Tarquinius Collatinus, were
                    elected by the prefect of the city at the comitia by centuries, according to the
                    commentaries of Servius Tullius. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
