<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 1-2 - 1</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books I and II With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1919</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.3"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="book">
                <head>Livy from the Founding of the City: Book I</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="pr" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whether I am likely to accomplish anything
                    worthy of the labour, if I record the achievements of the Roman people from the
                    foundation of the city, I do not really know, nor if I knew would I dare to
                    avouch it; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> perceiving as I do that the theme
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Some scholars take <hi
                            rend="italics">rem</hi> to mean <quote>the practice,</quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi> of expressing confidence in one's ability.
                    </note> is not only old but hackneyed, through the constant succession of new
                    historians, who believe either that in their facts they can produce more
                    authentic information, or that in their style they will prove better than the
                    rude attempts of the ancients. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Yet, however
                    this shall be, it will be a satisfaction to have done myself as much as lies in
                    me to commemorate the deeds of the foremost people of the world; and if in so
                    vast a company of writers my own reputation should be obscure, my consolation
                    would be the fame and greatness of those whose renown will throw mine into the
                    shade. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Moreover, my subject involves infinite
                    labour, seeing that it must be traced back <pb n="p.5"/> above seven hundred
                    years, and that proceeding from slender beginnings it has so increased as now to
                    be burdened by its own magnitude; and at the same time I doubt not that to most
                    readers the earliest origins and the period immediately succeeding them will
                    give little pleasure, for they will be in haste to reach these modern times, in
                    which the might of a people which has long been very powerful is working its own
                    undoing. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I myself, on the contrary, shall seek
                    in this an additional reward for my toil, that I may avert my gaze from the
                    troubles which our age has been witnessing for so many years, so long at least
                    as I am absorbed in the recollection of the brave <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> days of old, free from every care which, even if it could
                    not divert the historian's mind from the truth, might nevertheless cause it
                    anxiety. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy refers to the
                        animosities inevitably aroused by writers who dealt with such thorny
                        subjects as the civil wars, during the lifetime of many who had taken part
                        in them. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such traditions as belong to the time before
                    the city was founded, or rather was presently to be founded, and are rather
                    adorned with poetic legends than based upon trustworthy historical proofs, I
                    purpose neither to affirm nor to refute. It is the privilege of antiquity to
                    mingle divine things with human, and so to add dignity to the beginnings of
                    cities; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and if any people ought to be allowed
                    to consecrate their origins and refer them to a divine source, so great is the
                    military glory of the Roman People that when they profess that their Father and
                    the Father of their Founder was none other than Mars, the nations of the earth
                    may well submit to this also with as good a grace as they submit to Rome's
                    dominion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But to such legends as these,
                    however they shall be regarded and judged, I shall, for my own part, attach no
                    great importance. Here are the questions to which I would have every reader <pb
                        n="p.7"/> give his close attention —what life and morals were like; through
                    what men and by what policies, in peace and in war, empire was established and
                    enlarged; then let him note how, with the gradual relaxation of discipline,
                    morals first gave way, as it were, then sank lower and lower, and finally began
                    the downward plunge <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The metaphor is
                        from a decaying building.</note> which has brought us to the present time,
                    when we can endure neither our vices nor their cure. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What chiefly makes the study of history
                    wholesome and profitable is this, that you behold the lessons of every kind of
                    experience set forth as on a conspicuous monument; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The monument Livy means is the body of a nation's
                        achievements ( <hi rend="italics">cf. res</hi> in § 1), the
                            <quote>history</quote> of a nation, in that objective sense of the word.
                        This he likens to a monument of stone on which men's deeds are recorded.
                    </note> from these you may choose for yourself and for your own state what to
                    imitate, from these mark for avoidance what is shameful in the conception and
                    shameful in the result. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For the rest, either
                    love of the task I have set myself deceives me, or no state was ever greater,
                    none more righteous or richer in good examples, none ever was where avarice and
                    luxury came into the social order so late, or where humble means and thrift were
                    so highly esteemed and so long held in honour. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> For true it is that the less men's wealth was, the less was their greed. Of
                    late, riches have brought in avarice, and excessive pleasures the longing to
                    carry wantonness and licence to the point of ruin for oneself and of universal
                    destruction. </p>
                <p> But complaints are sure to be disagreeable, even when they shall perhaps be
                    necessary; let the beginning, at all events, of so great an enterprise have
                    none. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> With good omens rather would we begin,
                    and, if historians had the same custom which poets have, <pb n="p.9"/> with
                    prayers and entreaties to the gods and goddesses, that they might grant us to
                    bring to a successful issue the great task we have undertaken. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> First of all, then, it is generally agreed
                    that when Troy was taken vengeance was wreaked upon the other Trojans, but that
                    two, Aeneas and Antenor, were spared all the penalties of war by the Achivi,
                    owing to long-standing claims of hospitality, and because they had always
                    advocated peace and the giving back of Helen. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    They then experienced various vicissitudes. Antenor, with a company of Eneti who
                    had been expelled from Paphlagonia in a revolution and were looking for a home
                    and a leader —for they had lost their king, Pylaemenes, at Troy <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See the <hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi>
                        v. 576. </note> —came to the inmost bay of the Adriatic. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There, driving out the Euganei, who dwelt between the sea
                    and the Alps, the Eneti and Trojans took possession of those lands. And in fact
                    the place where they first landed is called Troy, and the district is therefore
                    known as Trojan, while the people as a whole are called the Veneti. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Aeneas, driven from home by a similar misfortune, but
                    guided by fate to undertakings of greater consequence, came first to Macedonia;
                    thence was carried, in his quest of a place of settlement, to Sicily; and from
                    Sicily laid his course towards the land of Laurentum. This place too is called
                    Troy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Landing there, the Trojans, as men who,
                    after their all but immeasurable wanderings, had nothing left but their swords
                    and ships, were driving booty from the fields, when King Latinus and the
                    Aborigines, who then occupied that country, rushed down from their city and
                    their fields to repel with arms the violence of the invaders. From this point
                    the tradition follows two <pb n="p.11"/> lines. Some say that Latinus, having
                    been defeated in the battle, made a peace with Aeneas, and later an alliance of
                    marriage. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This, in a nutshell, is the
                        form of the legend on which Virgil based Books vii.-xii. of the <hi
                            rend="italics">Aeneid.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Others maintain that when the opposing lines
                    had been drawn up, Latinus did not wait for the charge to sound, but advanced
                    amidst his chieftains and summoned the captain of the strangers to a parley.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then inquired what men they were,
                    whence they had come, what mishap had caused them to leave their home, and what
                    they sought in landing on the coast of Laurentum. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He was told that the people were Trojans and their leader
                    Aeneas, son of Anchises and Venus; that their city had been burnt, and that,
                    driven from home, they were looking for a dwelling-place and a site where they
                    might build a city. Filled with wonder at the renown of the race and the hero,
                    and at his spirit, prepared alike for war or peace, he gave him his right hand
                    in solemn pledge of lasting friendship. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    commanders then made a treaty, and the armies saluted each other. Aeneas became
                    a guest in the house of Latinus; there the latter, in the presence of his
                    household gods, added a domestic treaty to the public one, by giving his
                    daughter in marriage to Aeneas. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This event
                    removed any doubt in the minds of the Trojans that they had brought their
                    wanderings to an end at last in a permanent and settled habitation. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> They founded a town, which Aeneas named Lavinium,
                    after his wife. In a short time, moreover, there was a male scion of the new
                    marriage, to whom his parents gave the name of Ascanius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> War was then made upon Trojans and Aborigines
                    alike. Turnus was king of the Rutulians, and to him Lavinia had been betrothed
                    before the coming <pb n="p.13"/> of Aeneas. Indignant that a stranger should be
                    preferred before him, he attacked, at the same time, both Aeneas and Latinus.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Neither army came off rejoicing from that
                    battle. The Rutulians were beaten: the victorious Aborigines and Trojans lost
                    their leader Latinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then Turnus and the
                    Rutulians, discouraged at their situation, fled for succour to the opulent and
                    powerful Etruscans and their king Mezentius, who held sway in Caere, at that
                    time an important town. Mezentius had been, from the very beginning, far from
                    pleased at the birth of the new city; he now felt that the Trojan state was
                    growing much more rapidly than was altogether safe for its neighbours, and
                    readily united his forces with those of the Rutulians. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Aeneas, that he might win the goodwill of the Aborigines to
                    confront so formidable an array, and that all might possess not only the same
                    rights but also the same name, called both nations Latins; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Virgil makes Jupiter grant, as a favour to Juno, that
                        the Trojan name shall be sunk in the Latin ( <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                        xii. 835). </note> and from that time on the Aborigines were no less ready
                    and faithful than the Trojans in the service of King Aeneas. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, trusting to this friendly spirit of the two
                    peoples, which were growing each day more united, and, despite the power of
                    Etruria, which had filled with the glory of her name not only the lands but the
                    sea as well, along the whole extent of Italy from the Alps to the Sicilian
                    Strait, Aeneas declined to defend himself behind his walls, as he might have
                    done, but led out his troops to battle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    fight which ensued was a victory for the Latins: for Aeneas it was, besides, the
                    last of his mortal labours. He lies buried, whether it is fitting and right <pb
                        n="p.15"/> to term him god or man, on the banks of the river Numicus; men,
                    however, call him Jupiter Indiges. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Indiges</hi> means <quote>of or belonging to a certain
                            place</quote> (Fowler, <hi rend="italics">Fest.</hi> p. 192). Dion. Hal.
                        i. 64, says that the Latins made a shrine to Aeneas with an inscription in
                        which he was called <foreign xml:lang="greek">path\r xqo/nios</foreign> (
                            <hi rend="italics">Pater Indiges</hi> ). He was also called <hi
                            rend="italics">Deus Indiges</hi> and <hi rend="italics">Aeneas
                            Indiges.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ascanius, Aeneas' son, was not yet ripe for
                    authority; yet the authority was kept for him, unimpaired, until he arrived at
                    manhood. Meanwhile, under a woman's regency, the Latin State and the kingdom of
                    his father and his grandfather stood unshaken —so strong was Lavinia's character
                    —until the boy could claim it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I shall not
                    discuss the question —for who could affirm for certain so ancient a matter?
                    —whether this boy was Ascanius, or an elder brother, born by Creusa while Ilium
                    yet stood, who accompanied his father when he fled from the city, being the same
                    whom the Julian family call lulus and claim as the author of their name.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This Ascanius, no matter where born, or of
                    what mother —it is agreed in any case that he was Aeneas' son —left Lavinium,
                    when its population came to be too large, for it was already a flourishing and
                    wealthy city for those days, to his mother, or stepmother, and founded a new
                    city himself below the Alban Mount. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This was
                    known from its position, as it lay stretched out along the ridge, by the name of
                    Alba Longa. From the settlement of Lavinium to the planting of the colony at
                    Alba Longa was an interval of some thirty years. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Yet the nation had grown so powerful, in consequence especially of the defeat
                    of the Etruscans, that even when Aeneas died, and even when a woman became its
                    regent and a boy began his apprenticeship as king, neither Mezentius and his
                    Etruscans nor any other neighbours dared to attack them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Peace had been agreed to on these terms, that the River
                    Albula, which men now call the Tiber, should be the boundary <pb n="p.17"/>
                    between the Etruscans and the Latins. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Next
                    Silvius reigned, son of Ascanius, born, as it chanced, in the forest. He begat
                    Aeneas Silvius, and he Latinus Silvius. By him several colonies were planted,
                    and called the Ancient Latins. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thereafter the
                    cognomen Silvius was retained by all who ruled at Alba. From Latinus came Alba,
                    from Alba Atys, from Atys Capys, from Capys Capetus, from Capetus Tiberinus.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This last king was drowned in crossing the
                    River Albula, and gave the stream the name which has been current with later
                    generations. Then Agrippa, son of Tiberinus, reigned, and after Agrippa Romulus
                    Silvius was king, having received the power from his father. Upon the death of
                    Romulus by lightning, the kingship passed from him to Aventinus. This king was
                    buried on that hill, which is now a part of the City of Rome, and gave his name
                    to the hill. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Proca ruled next. He begat
                    Numitor and Amulius; to Numitor, the elder, he bequeathed the ancient realm of
                    the Silvian family. Yet violence proved more potent than a father's wishes or
                    respect for seniority. Amulius drove out his brother and ruled in his stead.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Adding crime to crime, he destroyed
                    Numitor's male issue; and Rhea Silvia, his brother's daughter, he appointed a
                    Vestal under pretence of honouring, her, and by consigning her to perpetual
                    virginity, deprived her of the hope of children. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the Fates were resolved, as I suppose,
                    upon the founding of this great City, and the beginning of the mightiest of
                    empires, next after that of Heaven. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Vestal
                    was ravished, and having given birth to twin sons, named Mars as the father of
                    her doubtful offspring, whether actually so believing, or because it seemed less
                    wrong if a god <pb n="p.19"/> were the author of her fault. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But neither gods nor men protected the mother herself or
                    her babes from the king's cruelty; the priestess he ordered to be manacled and
                    cast into prison, the children to be committed to the river. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It happened by singular good fortune that the Tiber having
                    spread beyond its banks into stagnant pools afforded nowhere any access to the
                    regular channel of the river, and the men who brought the twins were led to hope
                    that being infants they might be drowned, no matter how sluggish the stream.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So they made shift to discharge the king's
                    command, by exposing the babes at the nearest point of the overflow, where the
                    fig-tree Ruminalis —formerly, they say, called Romularis —now stands. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> In those days this was a wild and uninhabited region.
                    The story persists that when the floating basket in which the children had been
                    exposed was left high and dry by the receding water, a she-wolf, coming down out
                    of the surrounding hills to slake her thirst, turned her steps towards the cry
                    of the infants, and with her teats gave them suck so gently, that the keeper of
                    the royal flock found her licking them with her tongue. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Tradition assigns to this man the name of Faustulus, and
                    adds that he carried the twins to his hut and gave them to his wife Larentia to
                    rear. Some think that Larentia, having been free with her favours, had got the
                    name of <quote>she-wolf</quote> among the shepherds, and that this gave rise to
                    this marvellous story. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The word <hi
                            rend="italics">lupa</hi> was sometimes used in the sense of
                            <quote>courtesan.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The boys, thus born and reared, had no sooner
                    attained to youth than they began —yet without neglecting the farmstead or the
                    flocks —to range the glades of the mountains for game. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Having in this way gained both strength and resolution,
                    they would now not <pb n="p.21"/> only face wild beasts, but would attack
                    robbers laden with their spoils, and divide up what they took from them among
                    the shepherds, with whom they shared their toils and pranks, while their band of
                    young men grew larger every day. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They say that the Palatine was even then the
                    scene of the merry festival of the Lupercalia which we have to-day, and that the
                    hill was named Pallantium, from Pallanteum, an Arcadian city, and then Palatium.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The derivation here given is
                        fanciful. The word is probably akin to <hi rend="italics">palus,</hi>
                        <quote>pale,</quote> and meant a <quote>fenced place.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There Evander, an Arcadian of that stock, who
                    had held the place many ages before the time of which I am writing, is said to
                    have established the yearly rite, derived from Arcadia, that youths should run
                    naked about in playful sport, doing honour to Lycaean Pan, whom the Romans
                    afterwards called Inuus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the young men
                    were occupied in this celebration, the rite being generally known, some robbers
                    who had been angered by the loss of their plunder laid an ambush for them, and
                    although Romulus successfully defended himself, captured Remus and delivered up
                    their prisoner to King Amulius, even lodging a complaint against him. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The main charge was that the brothers made raids on
                    the lands of Numitor, and pillaged them, with a band of young fellows which they
                    had got together, like an invading enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So
                    Remus was given up to Numitor to be punished. From the very beginning Faustulus
                    had entertained the suspicion that they were children of the royal blood that he
                    was bringing up in his house; for he was aware both that infants had been
                    exposed by order of the king, and that the time when he had himself taken up the
                    children exactly coincided with that event. But he had been unwilling that the
                        <pb n="p.23"/> matter should be disclosed prematurely, until opportunity
                    offered or necessity compelled. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Necessity came
                    first; accordingly, driven by fear, he revealed the facts to Romulus. It chanced
                    that Numitor too, having Remus in custody, and hearing that the brothers were
                    twins, had been reminded, upon considering their age and their far from servile
                    nature, of his grandsons. The inquiries he made led him to the same conclusion,
                    so that he was almost ready to acknowledge Remus. Thus on every hand the toils
                    were woven about the king. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Romulus did not
                    assemble his company of youths —for he was not equal to open violence —but
                    commanded his shepherds to come to the palace at an appointed time, some by one
                    way, some by another, and so made his attack upon the king; while from the house
                    of Numitor came Remus, with another party which he had got together, to help his
                    brother. So Romulus slew the king. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the fray Numitor exclaimed
                    that an enemy had invaded the city and attacked the palace, and drew off the
                    active men of the place to serve as an armed garrison for the defence of the
                    citadel; and when he saw the young men approaching, after they had dispatched
                    the king, to congratulate him, he at once summoned a council, and laid before it
                    his brother's crimes against himself, the parentage of his grandsons, and how
                    they had been born, reared, and recognised. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                    then announced the tyrant's death, and declared himself to be responsible for
                    it. The brothers advanced with their band through the midst of the crowd, and
                    hailed their grandfather king, whereupon such a shout of assent arose from the
                    entire throng as confirmed the new monarch's title and authority. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.25"/>
                <p> The Alban state being thus made over to Numitor, Romulus and Remus were seized
                    with the desire to found a city in the region where they had been exposed and
                    brought up. And in fact the population of Albans and Latins was too large;
                    besides, there were the shepherds. All together, their numbers might easily lead
                    men to hope that Alba would be small, and Lavinium small, compared with the city
                    which they should build. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These considerations
                    were interrupted by the curse of their grandsires, the greed of kingly power,
                    and by a shameful quarrel which grew out of it, upon an occasion innocent
                    enough. Since the brothers were twins, and respect for their age could not
                    determine between them, it was agreed that the gods who had those places in
                    their protection should choose by augury who should give the new city its name,
                    who should govern it when built. Romulus took the Palatine for his augural
                    quarter, Remus the Aventine. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Remus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753</note> is said to have been the
                    first to receive an augury, from the flight of six vultures. The omen had been
                    already reported when twice that number appeared to Romulus. Thereupon each was
                    saluted king by his own followers, the one party laying claim to the honour from
                    priority, the other from the number of the birds. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They then engaged in a battle of words and, angry taunts
                    leading to bloodshed, Remus was struck down in the affray. The commoner story is
                    that Remus leaped over the new walls in mockery of his brother, whereupon
                    Romulus in great anger slew him, and in menacing wise added these words withal, <quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">So</hi> perish whoever else shall leap over my walls! </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A form of the legend preserved by
                        Dion. Hal. i. 87, and Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Fasti,</hi> iv. 843, names
                        Celer, whom Romulus had put in charge of the rising wall, as the slayer of
                        Remus. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thus Romulus acquired sole power, and the
                    city, thus founded, was called by its founder's name. </p>
                <pb n="p.27"/>
                <p> His first act was to fortify the Palatine, on which <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753</note> he had himself been
                    reared. To other gods he sacrificed after the Alban custom, but employed the
                    Greek for Hercules, according to the institution of Evander. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The story is as follows: Hercules, after slaying Geryones,
                    was driving off his wondrously beautiful cattle, when, close to the river Tiber,
                    where he had swum across it with the herd before him, he found a green spot,
                    where he could let the cattle rest and refresh themselves with the abundant
                    grass; and being tired from his journey he lay down himself. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> When he had there fallen into a deep sleep, for he was
                    heavy with food and wine, a shepherd by the name of Cacus, who dwelt hard by and
                    was insolent by reason of his strength, was struck with the beauty of the
                    animals, and wished to drive them off as plunder. But if he had driven the herd
                    into his cave, their tracks would have been enough to guide their owner to the
                    place in his search; he therefore chose out those of the cattle that were most
                    remarkable for their beauty, and turning them the other way, dragged them into
                    the cave by their tails. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At daybreak Hercules
                    awoke. Glancing over the herd, and perceiving that a part of their number was
                    lacking, he proceeded to the nearest cave, in case there might be foot-prints
                    leading into it. When he saw that they were all turned outward and yet did not
                    lead to any other place, he was confused and bewildered, and made ready to drive
                    his herd away from that uncanny spot. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As the
                    cattle were being driven off, some of them lowed, as usually happens, missing
                    those which had been left behind. They were answered with a low by the cattle
                    shut up in the cave, and this made Hercules turn back. When he came towards the
                        <pb n="p.29"/> cave, Cacus would have prevented his approach with <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753</note> force, but
                    received a blow from the hero's club, and calling in vain upon the shepherds to
                    protect him, gave up the ghost. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Evander, an
                    exile from the Peloponnese, controlled that region in those days, more through
                    personal influence than sovereign power. He was a man revered for his wonderful
                    invention of letters, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Evander is said
                        to have invented the Roman alphabet.</note> a new thing to men unacquainted
                    with the arts, and even more revered because of the divinity which men
                    attributed to his mother Carmenta, whom those tribes had admired as a prophetess
                    before the Sibyl's coming into Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Now this
                    Evander was then attracted by the concourse of shepherds, who, crowding
                    excitedly about the stranger, were accusing him as a murderer caught red-handed.
                    When he had been told about the deed and the reason for it, and had marked the
                    bearing of the man and his figure, which was somewhat ampler and more august
                    than a mortal's, he inquired who lie was. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Upon learning his name, his father, and his birth-place, he exclaimed, <quote>
                        Hail, Hercules, son of Jupiter! You are he, of whom my mother, truthful
                        interpreter of Heaven, foretold to me that you should be added to the number
                        of the gods, and that an altar should be dedicated to you here which the
                        nation one day to <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> be the most powerful on
                        earth should call the Greatest Altar, and should serve according to your
                        rite. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hercules gave him his hand, and declared that
                    he accepted the omen, and would fulfil the prophecy by establishing and
                    dedicating an altar. Then and there men took a choice victim from the herd, and
                    for the first time made sacrifice to Hercules. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> For the ministry and the banquet they employed the Potitii and the Pinarii,
                    being the families <pb n="p.31"/> of most distinction then living in that
                    region. It so <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        753</note> fell out that the Potitii were there at the appointed time, and
                    to them were served the inwards; the Pinarii came after the inwards had been
                    eaten, in season for the remainder of the feast. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Thence came the custom, which persisted as long as the
                    Pinarian family endured, that they should not partake of the inwards at that
                    sacrifice. The Potitii, instructed by Evander, were priests of this cult for
                    many generations, until, having delegated to public slaves the solemn function
                    of their family, the entire stock of the Potitii died out. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> This was the only sacred observance, of all those of
                    foreign origin, which Romulus then adopted, honouring even then the immortality
                    won by worth to which his own destiny was leading him. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For the story of Cacus and the origin of the Ara Maxima
                        see also Virgil, <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi> viii. 182-279; Prop. iv. 9;
                        Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Fasti,</hi> i. 543-586. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Romulus had duly attended to the worship
                    of the gods, he called the people together and gave them the rules of law, since
                    nothing else but law could unite them into a single body politic. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> But these, he was persuaded, would only appear
                    binding in the eyes of a rustic people in case he should invest his own person
                    with majesty, by adopting emblems of authority. He therefore put on a more
                    august state in every way, and especially by the assumption of twelve lictors.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The lictors carried axes in
                        bundles of rods, in readiness to execute the king's sentence of scourging
                        and decapitation. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some think the twelve birds which had given
                    him an augury of kingship led him to choose this number. For my part, I am
                    content to share the opinion of those who derive from the neighbouring Etruscans
                    (whence were borrowed the curule chair and purple-bordered toga) not only the
                    type of attendants but their number as well —a number which the Etruscans
                    themselves are thought to have chosen because each <pb n="p.33"/> of the twelve
                    cities which united to elect the king <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 753</note> contributed one lictor. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the City was expanding and reaching
                    out its walls to include one place after another, for they built their defences
                    with an eye rather to the population which they hoped one day to have than to
                    the numbers they had then. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next, lest his big
                    City should be empty, Romulus resorted to a plan for increasing the inhabitants
                    which had long been employed by the founders of cities, who gather about them an
                    obscure and lowly multitude and pretend that the earth has raised up sons to
                    them. In the place which is now enclosed, between the two groves as you go up
                    the hill, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Capitoline. </note> he opened a sanctuary.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thither fled, from the surrounding
                    peoples, a miscellaneous rabble, without distinction of bond or free, eager for
                    new conditions; and these constituted the first advance in power towards that
                    greatness at which Romulus aimed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He had now
                    no reason to be dissatisfied with his strength, and proceeded to add policy to
                    strength. He appointed a hundred senators, whether because this number seemed to
                    him sufficient, or because there were no more than a hundred who could be
                    designated Fathers. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As being heads of
                        clans, <hi rend="italics">patresfamiliarum.</hi>
                    </note> At all events, they received the designation of Fathers from their rank,
                    and their descendants were called patricians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Rome was now strong enough to hold her own
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note>
                    in war with any of the adjacent states; but owing to the want of women a single
                    generation was likely to see the end of her greatness, since she had neither
                    prospect of posterity at home nor the right of intermarriage with her
                    neighbours. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> So, on the advice of the senate,
                    Romulus sent envoys round among all the neighbouring nations to solicit for the
                    new people <pb n="p.35"/> an alliance and the privilege of intermarrying. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Cities, they argued, as well as all other
                    things, take their rise from the lowliest beginnings. As time goes on, those
                    which are aided by their own worth and by the favour of Heaven achieve great
                    power and renown. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They said they were well
                    assured that Rome's origin had been blessed with the favour of Heaven, and that
                    worth would not be lacking; their neighbours should not be reluctant to mingle
                    their stock and their blood with the Romans, who were as truly men as they were.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nowhere did the embassy obtain a friendly
                    hearing. In fact men spurned, at the same time that they feared, both for
                    themselves and their descendants, that great power which was then growing up in
                    their midst; and the envoys were frequently asked, on being dismissed, if they
                    had opened a sanctuary for women as well as for men, for in that way only would
                    they obtain suitable wives. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This was a bitter
                    insult to the young Romans, and the matter seemed certain to end in violence.
                    Expressly to afford a fitting time and place for this, Romulus, concealing his
                    resentment, made ready solemn games in honour of the equestrian Neptune, which
                    he called Consualia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Consualia
                        was a harvest festival, held on August 21. Consus, the true name of the god,
                        is from <hi rend="italics">condere,</hi>
                        <quote>to store up.</quote> From the association of the festival with horses
                        came the later identification of the god with <hi rend="italics">Neptunus
                            Equester.</hi> See Fowler, <hi rend="italics">Fest.</hi> pp. 206-9. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then bade proclaim the spectacle to the
                    surrounding peoples, and his subjects prepared to celebrate it with all the
                    resources within their knowledge and power, that they might cause the occasion
                    to be noised abroad and eagerly expected. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Many
                    people —for they were also eager to see the new city —gathered for the festival,
                    especially those who lived nearest, the inhabitants of Caenina, Crustumium, and
                    Antemnae. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Sabines, <pb n="p.37"/> too,
                    came with all their people, including their <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> children and wives.
                    They were hospitably entertained in every house, and when they had looked at the
                    site of the City, its walls, and its numerous buildings, they marvelled that
                    Rome had so rapidly grown great. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the
                    time came for the show, and people's thoughts and eyes were busy with it, the
                    preconcerted attack began. At a given signal the young Romans darted this way
                    and that, to seize and carry off the maidens. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    In most cases these were taken by the men in whose path they chanced to be.
                    Some, of exceptional beauty, had been marked out for the chief senators, and
                    were carried off to their houses by plebeians to whom the office had been
                    entrusted. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> One, who far excelled the rest in
                    mien and loveliness, was seized, the story relates, by the gang of a certain
                    Thalassius. Being repeatedly asked for whom they were bearing her off, they kept
                    shouting that no one should touch her, for they were taking her to Thalassius,
                    and this was the origin of the wedding-cry. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Rom.</hi> 15, also gives
                        the story, and observes that the Romans used <quote>Talasius</quote> as the
                        Greeks did <quote>Hymenaeus.</quote> See also Catullus, lxi. 134. </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The sports broke up in a panic, and the
                    parents of the maidens fled sorrowing. They charged the Romans with the crime of
                    violating hospitality, and invoked the gods to whose solemn games they had come,
                    deceived in violation of religion and honour. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    The stolen maidens were no more hopeful of their plight, nor less indignant. But
                    Romulus himself went amongst them and explained that the pride of their parents
                    had caused this deed, when they had refused their neighbours the right to
                    intermarry; nevertheless the daughters should be wedded and become co-partners
                    in all the possessions of the Romans, in their citizenship and, dearest
                    privilege of all to the human race, in their children; <pb n="p.39"/> only let
                    them moderate their anger, and give their <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> hearts to those to
                    whom fortune had given their persons. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A sense
                    of injury had often given place to affection, and they would find their husbands
                    the kinder for this reason, that every man would earnestly endeavour not only to
                    be a good husband, but also to console his wife for the home and parents she had
                    lost. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> His arguments were seconded by the
                    wooing of the men, who excused their act on the score of passion and love, the
                    most moving of all pleas to a woman's heart. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The resentment of the brides was already much
                    diminished at the very moment when their parents, in mourning garb and with
                    tears and lamentations, were attempting to arouse their states to action. Nor
                    did they confine their complaints to their home towns, but thronged from every
                    side to the house of Titus Tatius, king of the Sabines; and thither, too, came
                    official embassies, for the name of Tatius was the greatest in all that country.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The men of Caenina, Crustumium, and
                    Antemnae, were those who had had a share in the wrong. It seemed to them that
                    Tatius and the Sabines were procrastinating, and without waiting for them these
                    three tribes arranged for a joint campaign. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But even the Crustuminians and Antemnates moved too slowly to satisfy the
                    burning anger of the Caeninenses, and accordingly that nation invaded alone the
                    Roman territory. But while they were dispersed and engaged in pillage, Romulus
                    appeared with his troops and taught them, by an easy victory, how ineffectual is
                    anger without strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their army he broke
                    and routed, and pursued it as it fled; their king he killed <pb n="p.41"/> in
                    battle and despoiled; their city, once their leader <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> was slain, he captured
                    at the first assault. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then led his
                    victorious army back, and being not more splendid in his deeds than willing to
                    display them, he arranged the spoils of the enemy's dead commander upon a fame,
                    suitably fashioned for the purpose, and, carrying it himself, mounted the
                    Capitol. Having there deposited his burden, by an oak which the shepherds held
                    sacred, at the same time as he made his offering he marked out the limits of a
                    temple to Jupiter, and bestowed a title upon him. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Jupiter Feretrius,</quote> he said, <quote> to thee I, victorious
                        Romulus, myself a king, bring the panoply of a king, and dedicate a sacred
                        precinct within the bounds which I have even now marked off in my mind, to
                        be a seat for the spoils of honour which men shall bear hither in time to
                        come, following my example, when they have slain kings and commanders of the
                        enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This was the origin of the first temple that
                    was consecrated in Rome. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Jupiter
                        Feretrius (etymology unknown) was the pure Italian Jupiter, whose worship
                        was later overshadowed by the Etruscan god of the great temple on the
                        Capitol. See Fowler, <hi rend="italics">Fest.</hi> p. 229. </note> It
                    pleased Heaven, in the sequel, that while the founder's words should not be in
                    vain, when he declared that men should bring spoils thither in the after time,
                    yet the glory of that gift should not be staled by a multitude of partakers.
                    Twice only since then, in all these years with their many wars, have the spoils
                    of honour been won; so rarely have men had the good fortune to attain to that
                    distinction. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The other instances were
                        the victories of Cossus over Tolumnius, king of Veii (iv. 20), and of
                        Marcellus over Virdomarus, king of the Insubrian Gauls. Propertius tells the
                        three stories in iv. 10. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the Romans were thus occupied in the
                    City, the army of the Antemnates seized the opportunity afforded by their
                    absence, and made an inroad upon their territory; but so swiftly was the Roman
                        <pb n="p.43"/> levy led against them that they, too, were taken off <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> their
                    guard while scattered about in the fields. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    They were therefore routed at the first charge and shout, and their town was
                    taken. As Romulus was exulting in his double victory, his wife Hersilia, beset
                    with entreaties by the captive women, begged him to forgive their parents and
                    receive them into the state; which would, in that case, gain in strength by
                    harmony. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He readily granted her request. He
                    then set out to meet the Crustuminians, who were marching to attack him. They
                    offered even less resistance than their allies had done, for their ardour had
                    been quenched by the defeats of the others. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Colonies were sent out to both places, though most of the colonists preferred to
                    enrol for Crustumium on account of the fertility of its soil. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On the other hand, many persons left Crustumium and came to
                    live in Rome, chiefly parents and kinsmen of the captured women. </p>
                <p> The last to attack Rome were the Sabines, and this war was by far the gravest of
                    all, for passion and greed were not their motives, nor did they parade war
                    before they made it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To their prudence they
                    even added deception. Spurius Tarpeius commanded the Roman citadel. This man's
                    maiden daughter was bribed with gold by Tatius to admit armed men into the
                    fortress: she happened at that time to have gone outside the walls to fetch
                    water for a sacrifice. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As a vestal,
                        she had to draw water from the spring of the Camenae. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Once within, they threw their shields upon her
                    and killed her so, whether to make it appear that the citadel had been taken by
                    assault, or to set an example, that no one might anywhere keep faith with a
                    traitor. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There is also a legend that because
                    most of the Sabines wore heavy golden <pb n="p.45"/> bracelets on their left
                    arms and magnificent jewelled <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> rings, she had stipulated for what they
                    had on their left arms, and that they had therefore heaped their shields upon
                    her, instead of gifts of gold. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some say that,
                    in virtue of the compact that they should give her what they wore on their arms,
                    she flatly demanded their shields and, her treachery being perceived, forfeited
                    her life to the bargain she herself had struck. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> According to Dion. Hal. ii. 38, this was the version
                        given by L. Calpurnius Piso. Propertius wrote the best of his aetiological
                        poems (iv. 5) about Tarpeia. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Be that as it may, the Sabines held the
                    citadel. Next day the Roman army was drawn up, and covered the ground between
                    the Palatine Hill and the Capitoline, but the Sabines would not come down till
                    rage and eagerness to regain the citadel had goaded their enemy into marching up
                    the slope against them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two champions led the
                    fighting, the Sabine Mettius Curtius on the one side, and the Roman Hostius
                    Hostilius on the other. Hostius held the Romans firm, despite their disadvantage
                    of position, by the reckless courage he displayed in the thick of the fray.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But when he fell, the Roman line gave way
                    at once and fled towards the old gate of the Palatine. Romulus himself was swept
                    along in the crowd of the fugitives, till lifting his sword and shield to
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> heaven, he cried, <quote> O Jupiter, it
                        was thy omen that directed me when I laid here on the Palatine the first
                        foundations of my City. The fortress is already bought by a crime and in the
                        possession of the Sabines, whence they are come, sword in hand, across the
                        valley to seek us here. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But do thou,
                        father of gods and men, keep them back from this spot at least; deliver the
                        Romans from their terror, and stay their shameful flight! <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> I here vow to thee, Jupiter the Stayer, a temple, to be
                        a <pb n="p.47"/> memorial to our descendants how the City was saved <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> by
                        thy present help. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having uttered this prayer he exclaimed, as if
                    he had perceived that it was heard, <quote>Here, Romans, Jupiter Optimus Maximus
                        commands us to stand and renew the fight!</quote> The Romans did stand, as
                    though directed by a voice from Heaven, Romulus himself rushing into the
                    forefront of the battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Mettius Curtius, on
                    the Sabine side, had led the charge down from the citadel, and driven the Romans
                    in disorder over all that ground which the Forum occupies. He was not now far
                    from the gate of the Palatine, shouting, <quote> We have beaten our faithless
                        hosts, our cowardly enemies! They know now how great is the difference
                        between carrying off maidens and fighting with men! </quote> While he
                    pronounced this boast a band of gallant youths, led on by Romulus, assailed him.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It chanced that Mettius was fighting on
                    horseback at the time, and was therefore the more easily put to flight. As he
                    fled, the Romans followed; and the rest of their army, too, fired by the
                    reckless daring of their king, drove the Sabines before them. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Mettius plunged into a swamp, his horse becoming
                    unmanageable in the din of the pursuit, and even the Sabines were drawn off from
                    the general engagement by the danger to so great a man. As for Mettius,
                    heartened by the gestures and shouts of his followers and the encouragement of
                    the throng, he made his escape; and the Romans and the Sabines renewed their
                    battle in the valley that lies between the two hills. But the advantage rested
                    with the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the Sabine women, whose wrong had given
                    rise to the war, with loosened hair and torn <pb n="p.49"/> garments, their
                    woman's timidity lost in a sense of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> their misfortune, dared to go amongst the
                    flying missiles, and rushing in from the side, to part the hostile forces and
                    disarm them of <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> their anger, beseeching their
                    fathers on this side, on that their husbands, that fathers-in-law and
                    sons-in-law should not stain themselves with impious bloodshed, nor pollute with
                    parricide the suppliants' children, grandsons to one party and sons to the
                    other. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>If you regret,</quote> they continued, <quote> the relationship that
                        unites you, if you regret the marriage-tie, turn your anger against us; we
                        are the cause of war, the cause of wounds, and even death to both our
                        husbands and our parents. It will be better for us to perish than to live,
                        lacking either of you, as widows or as orphans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was a touching plea, not only to the rank
                    and file, but to their leaders as well. A stillness fell on them, and a sudden
                    hush. Then the leaders came forward to make a truce, and not only did they agree
                    on peace, but they made one people out of the two. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> They shared the sovereignty, but all authority was
                    transferred to Rome. In this way the population was doubled, and that some
                    concession might after all be granted the Sabines, the citizens were named
                    Quirites, from the town of Cures. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Quirites</hi> probably comes not from Cures, nor (as
                        Varro thought) from the Sabine word <hi rend="italics">quiris (curis),</hi>
                        <quote>spear,</quote> but from <hi rend="italics">curia</hi> ( <hi
                            rend="italics">cf.</hi> next section); it would then mean
                            <quote>wardsmen.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As a reminder of this battle they gave the
                    name of Curtian Lake to the pool where the horse of Curtius first emerged from
                    the deep swamp and brought his rider to safety. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For another explanation of the name see vii. 6. Varro,
                            <hi rend="italics">L. L.</hi> v. 14 ff., assigns this version of the
                        story to Piso, the other to Procilius, adding a third, on the authority of
                        Cornelius and Lutatius, to the effect that the Lacus Curtius was a place
                        which had been struck by lightning in the consulship of a Curtius. </note>
                </p>
                <p> The sudden exchange of so unhappy a war for a joyful peace endeared the Sabine
                    women even more to their husbands and parents, and above all to <pb n="p.51"/>
                    Romulus himself. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And so, when he divided the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note>
                    people into thirty <hi rend="italics">curiae,</hi> he named these wards after
                    the women. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics"
                            >curia</hi> was a political unit the members of which had certain
                        religious rites in common. </note> Undoubtedly the number of the women was
                    somewhat greater than this, but tradition does not tell whether it was their
                    age, their own or their husbands' rank, or the casting of lots, that determined
                    which of them should give their names to the wards. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time there were formed three centuries of
                    knights: the Ramnenses were named after Romulus; the Titienses after Titus
                    Tatius; the name and origin of the Luceres are alike obscure. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> All three names are obscure, but it is
                        not improbable that they represent a Roman, a Sabine, and an Etruscan
                        element in the population. </note> From this time forth the two kings ruled
                    not only jointly but in harmony. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some years later the kinsmen of King Tatius
                    maltreated the envoys of the Laurentians, and when their fellow-citizens sought
                    redress under the law of nations, Titus yielded to his partiality for his
                    relations and to their entreaties. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In
                    consequence of this he drew down their punishment upon himself, for at Lavinium,
                    whither he had gone to the annual sacrifice, a mob came together and killed him.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This act is said to have awakened less
                    resentment than was proper in Romulus, whether owing to the disloyalty that
                    attends a divided rule, or because he thought Tatius had been not unjustly
                    slain. He therefore declined to go to war; but yet, in order that he might atone
                    for the insults to the envoys and the murder of the king, he caused the covenant
                    between Rome and Lavinium to be renewed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thus with the Laurentians peace was preserved
                    against all expectation; but another war broke out, much nearer, and indeed
                    almost at the city gates. The men of Fidenae, perceiving the growth of a power
                    which they thought too near themselves for <pb n="p.53"/> safety, did not wait
                    till its promised strength should <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> be realized, but began war themselves.
                    Arming the young men, they sent them to ravage the land between the City and
                    Fidenae. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thence they turned to the left —for
                    the Tiber stopped them on the right —and by their devastations struck terror
                    into the farmers, whose sudden stampede from the fields into the City brought
                    the first tidings of war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Romulus led forth
                    his army on the instant, for delay was impossible with the enemy so near, and
                    pitched his camp a mile from Fidenae. Leaving there a small guard, he marched
                    out with all his forces. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A part of his men he
                    ordered to lie in ambush, on this side and on that, where thick underbrush
                    afforded cover; advancing with the greater part of the infantry and all the
                    cavalry, and delivering a disorderly and provoking attack, in which the horsemen
                    galloped almost up to the gates, he accomplished his purpose of drawing out the
                    enemy. For the flight, too, which had next to be feigned, the cavalry engagement
                    afforded a favourable pretext. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And when not
                    only the cavalry began to waver, as if undecided whether to fight or run, but
                    the infantry also fell back, the city gates were quickly thronged by the enemy,
                    who poured out and hurled themselves against the Roman line, and in the ardour
                    of attack and pursuit were drawn on to the place of ambuscade. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> There the Romans suddenly sprang out and assailed the
                    enemy's flanks, while, to add to their terror, the standards of the detachment
                    which had been left on guard were seen advancing from the camp; thus threatened
                    by so many dangers the men of Fidenae scarcely afforded time for Romulus and
                    those whom they had seen riding off with him to wheel about, before they <pb
                        n="p.55"/> broke and ran, and in far greater disorder than that <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 753-717</note> of the
                    pretended fugitives whom they had just been chasing —for <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> the flight was a real one this time — sought to regain the
                    town. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But the Fidenates did not escape their
                    foes; the Romans followed close upon their heels, and before the gates could be
                    shut burst into the city, as though they both formed but a single army. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From Fidenae the war-spirit, by a kind of
                    contagion, spread to the Veientes, whose hostility was aroused by their kinship
                    with the Fidenates, Etruscans like themselves, and was intensified by the danger
                    which lay in their very proximity to Rome, if her arms should be directed
                    against all her neighbours. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They made an
                    incursion into Roman territory which more resembled a marauding expedition than
                    a regular campaign; and so, without having entrenched a camp or waited for the
                    enemy's army, they carried off their booty from the fields and brought it back
                    to Veii. The Romans, on the contrary, not finding their enemy in the fields,
                    crossed the Tiber, ready and eager for a decisive struggle. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When the Veientes heard that they were making a camp, and
                    would be advancing against their city, they went out to meet them, preferring to
                    settle the quarrel in the field of battle rather than to be shut up and
                    compelled to fight for their homes and their town. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Without employing strategy to aid his forces, the Roman
                    king won the battle by the sheer strength of his seasoned army, and routing his
                    enemies, pursued them to their walls. But the city was strongly fortified,
                    besides the protection afforded by its site, and he refrained from attacking it.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their fields, indeed, he laid waste as he
                    returned, more in <pb n="p.57"/> revenge than from a desire for booty, and this
                    disaster, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        753-717</note> following upon their defeat, induced the Veientes to send
                    envoys to Rome and sue for peace. They were deprived of a part of their land,
                    and a truce was granted them for a hundred years. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Such were the principal achievements of the
                    reign of Romulus, at home and in the field, nor is any of them incompatible with
                    the belief in his divine origin and the divinity which was ascribed to the king
                    after his death, whether one considers his spirit in recovering the kingdom of
                    his ancestors, or his wisdom in founding the City and in strengthening it by
                    warlike and peaceful measures. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For it was to
                    him, assuredly, that Rome owed the vigour which enabled her to enjoy an
                    untroubled peace for the next forty years. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Nevertheless, he was more liked by the commons than by the senate, and was
                    preeminently dear to the hearts of his soldiers. Of these he had three hundred
                    for a bodyguard, to whom he gave the name of Celeres, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Literally, <quote>the .Swift.</quote>
                    </note> and kept them by him, not only in war, but also in time of peace. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these deathless deeds had been done,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 716</note> as
                    the king was holding a muster in the Campus Martius, near the swamp of Capra,
                    for the purpose of reviewing the army, suddenly a storm came up, with loud claps
                    of thunder, and enveloped him in a cloud so thick as to hide him from the sight
                    of the assembly; and from that moment Romulus was no more on earth. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the deification <hi rend="italics"
                            >cf.</hi> Cic. <hi rend="italics">de Rep.</hi> ii. 17; Dion. Hal. ii.
                        56; Plut. <hi rend="italics">Rom.</hi> xxvii. Ovid also tells the story in
                            <hi rend="italics">Fasti,</hi> ii. 491 ff., and <hi rend="italics"
                            >Met.</hi> xiv. 806 ff. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Roman soldiers at length recovered from
                    their panic, when this hour of wild confusion had been succeeded by a sunny
                    calm; but when they saw that the royal seat was empty, although they readily
                    believed the assertion of the senators, who had been standing next to Romulus,
                        <pb n="p.59"/> that he had been caught up on high in the blast, they <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 716</note>
                    nevertheless remained for some time sorrowful and silent, as if filled with the
                    fear of orphanhood. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then, when a few men had
                    taken the initiative, they all with one accord hailed Romulus as a god and a
                    god's son, the King and Father of the Roman City, and with prayers besought his
                    favour that he would graciously be pleased forever to protect his children.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There were some, I believe, even then who
                    secretly asserted that the king had been rent in pieces by the hands of the
                    senators, for this rumour, too, got abroad, but in very obscure terms; the other
                    version obtained currency, owing to men's admiration for the hero and the
                    intensity of their panic. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And the shrewd
                    device of one man is also said to have gained new credit for the story.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This was Proculus Julius, who, when the
                    people were distracted with the loss of their king and in no friendly mood
                    towards the senate, being, as tradition tells, weighty in council, were the
                    matter never so important, addressed the assembly as follows: <quote> Quirites,
                        the Father of this City, Romulus, descended suddenly from the sky at dawn
                        this morning and appeared to me. Covered with confusion, I stood reverently
                        before him, praying that it might be vouchsafed me to look upon his face
                        without sin. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The Romans regularly
                            prayed with the head cloaked.</note>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> 'Go,' said he, 'and declare to the Romans
                        the will of Heaven that my Rome shall be the capital of the world; so let
                        them cherish the art of war, and let them know and teach their children that
                        no human strength can resist Roman arms.' <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        So saying, </quote> he concluded, <quote>Romulus departed on high.</quote>
                    It is wonderful what credence the people placed in that man's tale, and how the
                    grief for the loss of Romulus, which the plebeians <pb n="p.61"/> and the army
                    felt, was quieted by the assurance of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 716</note> his immortality. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senators meanwhile were engaged in a
                    struggle for the coveted kingship. So far it had not come to a question of any
                    one person, for nobody stood out with special prominence in the new nation;
                    instead, a strife of factions was waging between the two stocks. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Those of Sabine origin, having had no king on their
                    side since the death of Tatius, feared that despite their equal rights they
                    might lose their hold upon the sovereign power, and hence desired that the king
                    should be chosen from their own body. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    original Romans spurned the idea of an alien king. Various, however, as were
                    men's inclinations, to be ruled by a king was their universal wish, for they had
                    not yet tasted the sweetness of liberty. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then
                    the senators became alarmed, lest the state wanting a ruler and the army a
                    leader, and many neighbouring states being disaffected, some violence might be
                    offered from without. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> All therefore were
                    agreed that there should be some head, but nobody could make up his mind to
                    yield to his fellow. And so the hundred senators shared the power among
                    themselves, establishing ten decuries and appointing one man for each decury to
                    preside over the administration. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Ten men
                    exercised authority; only one had its insignia and lictors. Five days was the
                    period of his power, which passed in rotation to all; and for a year the
                    monarchy lapsed. This interval was called, as it was, an interregnum, a name
                    which even yet obtains. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Murmurs then arose
                    among the plebs that their servitude had been multiplied; that a hundred masters
                    had been given them instead of <pb n="p.63"/> one. No longer, it seemed, would
                    they endure <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        716</note> anything short of a king, and a king, too, of their own choosing.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Perceiving that such ideas were in the
                    wind, the senators thought it would be well to proffer spontaneously a thing
                    which they were on the verge of losing, and obtained the favour of the people by
                    granting them supreme power on such terms as to part with no greater prerogative
                    than they retained. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For they decreed that when
                    the people should have named a king, their act should only be valid in case the
                    senators ratified it. Even now, in voting for laws and magistrates, the same
                    right is exercised, but is robbed of its significance; before the people can
                    begin to vote, and when the result of the election is undetermined, the Fathers
                    ratify it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the present occasion the
                    interrex summoned the assembly and spoke as follows: <quote> May prosperity,
                        favour, and fortune attend our action! Quirites, choose your king. Such is
                        the pleasure of the Fathers, who, in their turn, if your choice fall upon
                        one worthy to be called Romulus' successor, will confirm your election. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This so pleased the plebs, that, unwilling to
                    appear outdone in generosity, they merely resolved and ordered that the senate
                    should decree who should be king in Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A great reputation for justice and piety was
                    enjoyed in those days by Numa Pompilius. Cures, a town of the Sabines, was his
                    home, and he was deeply versed, so far as anyone could be in that age, in all
                    law, divine and human. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The teacher to whom he
                    owed his learning was not, as men say, in default of another name, the Samian
                    Pythagoras; for it is well established that Servius Tullius was king at Rome,
                    more than a hundred years after this <pb n="p.65"/> time, when Pythagoras
                    gathered about him, on the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 716</note> farthest coasts of Italy, in the neighbourhood
                    of Metapontum, Heraclea, and Croton, young men eager to share his studies. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was about <date when="-0530">530
                            B.C.</date> when Pythagoras settled in Croton. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And from that country, even if he had been
                    contemporary, how could his fame have reached the Sabines? Again, in what common
                    language could he have induced anyone to seek instruction of him? Or under whose
                    protection could a solitary man have made his way through so many nations
                    differing in speech and customs? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was Numa's
                    native disposition, then, as I incline to believe, that tempered his soul with
                    noble qualities, and his training was not in foreign studies, but in the stern
                    and austere discipline of the ancient Sabines, a race incorruptible as any race
                    of the olden time. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Numa's name had been
                    proposed, the Roman senators perceived that the Sabines would gain the
                    ascendancy if a king were to be chosen from that nation; yet nobody ventured to
                    urge his own claims in preference to those of such a man, nor the claim of any
                    other of his faction, nor those, in short, of any of the senators or citizens.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And so they unanimously voted to offer the
                    sovereignty to Numa Pompilius. Being summoned to Rome he commanded that, just as
                    Romulus had obeyed the augural omens in building his city and assuming regal
                    power, so too in his own case the gods should be consulted. Accordingly an augur
                    (who thereafter, as a mark of honour, was made a priest of the state in
                    permanent charge of that function) conducted him to the citadel and caused him
                    to sit down on a stone, facing the south. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    augur seated himself on Numa's left, having his head covered, and holding his in
                    right hand the crooked staff without a knot <pb n="p.67"/> which they call a <hi
                        rend="italics">lituus.</hi>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then, looking out over the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 716</note> City and
                    the country beyond, he prayed to the gods, and marked off the heavens by a line
                    from east to west, designating as ' right' the regions to the south, as 'left'
                    those to the north, and fixing in his mind a landmark opposite to him and as far
                    away as the eye could reach; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> next shifting the
                    crook to his left hand and, laying his right hand on Numa's head, he uttered the
                    following prayer: <quote> Father Jupiter, if it is Heaven's will that this man
                        Numa Pompilius, whose head I am touching, be king in Rome, do thou exhibit
                        to us unmistakable signs within those limits which I have set. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He then specified the auspices which he
                    desired should be sent, and upon their appearance Numa was declared king, and so
                    descended from the augural station. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had thus obtained the kingship, he
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 715-672</note>
                    prepared to give the new City, founded by force of arms, a new foundation in
                    law, statutes, and observances. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And perceiving
                    that men could not grow used to these things in the midst of wars, since their
                    natures grew wild and savage through warfare, he thought it needful that his
                    warlike people should be softened by the disuse of arms, and built the temple of
                    Janus at the bottom of the Argiletum, as an index of peace and war, that when
                    open it might signify that the nation was in arms, when closed that all the
                    peoples round about were pacified. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Twice since
                    Numa's reign has it been closed: once in the consulship of Titus Manlius, after
                    the conclusion of the First Punic War; the second time, which the gods permitted
                    our own generation to witness, was after the battle of Actium, when the emperor
                    Caesar Augustus had brought about peace on land and <pb n="p.69"/> sea. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was evidently written before <date
                            when="-0025">25 B.C.</date> , when the temple was again closed by
                        Augustus. But it was not written before 27, for it was not until that year
                        that the title of Augustus was conferred upon the emperor. We thus arrive at
                        an approximate date for the beginning of Livy's history. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Numa closed the temple after first securing
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 715-672</note>
                    good will of all the neighbouring tribes by alliances and treaties. And fearing
                    lest relief from anxiety on the score of foreign perils might lead men who had
                    hitherto been held back by fear of their enemies and by military discipline into
                    extravagance and idleness, he thought the very first thing to do, as being the
                    most efficacious with a populace which was ignorant and, in those early days,
                    uncivilized, was to imbue them with the fear of Heaven. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> As he could not instil this into their hearts without
                    inventing some marvellous story, he pretended to have nocturnal meetings with
                    the goddess Egeria, and that hers was the advice which guided him in the
                    establishment of rites most approved by the gods, and in the appointment of
                    special priests for the service of each. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And first of all he divided the year into
                    twelve months, according to the revolutions of the moon. But since the moon does
                    not give months of quite thirty days each, and eleven days are wanting to the
                    full complement of a year as marked by the sun's revolution, he inserted
                    intercalary months in such a way that in the twentieth year the days should fall
                    in with the same position of the sun from which they had started, and the period
                    of twenty years be rounded out. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He also
                    appointed days when public business might not be carried on, and others when it
                    might, since it would sometimes be desirable that nothing should be brought
                    before the people. </p>
                <pb n="p.71"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He then turned his attention to the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 715-672</note>
                    appointment of priests, although lie performed very many priestly duties
                    himself, especially those which now belong to the Flamen Dialis. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> But inasmuch as he thought that in a warlike nation
                    there would be more kings like Romulus than like Numa, and that they would take
                    the field in person, he did not wish the sacrificial duties of the kingly office
                    to be neglected, and so appointed a flamen for Jupiter, as his perpetual priest,
                    and provided him with a conspicuous dress and the royal curule chair. To him he
                    added two other flamens, one for Mars, the other for Quirinus. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In like manner he designated virgins for Vesta's service —a
                    priesthood, this, that derived from Alba and so was not unsuited to the
                    founder's stock. That they might be perpetual priestesses of the temple, he
                    assigned them a stipend from the public treasury, and by the rule of virginity
                    and other observances invested them with awe and sanctity. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He likewise chose twelve Salii for Mars Gradivus, and
                    granted them the distinction of wearing the embroidered tunic and over it a
                    bronze breastplate, and of bearing the divine shields which men call <hi
                        rend="italics">ancilia,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The original <hi rend="italics"
                            >ancile</hi> was a shield fabled to have fallen from heaven. To lessen
                        the chance of its being stolen, eleven others were .made exactly like it. It
                        was of a peculiar shape, something like a violin. See Fowler, <hi
                            rend="italics">Fest.</hi> p.42. </note> while they proceeded through the
                    City, chanting their hymns to the triple beat of their solemn dance. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> He next chose as pontifex Numa Marcius, son of
                    Marcus, one of the senators, and to him he intrusted written directions, full
                    and accurate, for performing the rites of worship; with what victims, on what
                    days, in what temple, sacrifices should be offered, and from what sources money
                    was to be disbursed to pay their costs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All
                    other public and private sacrifices lie likewise made subject to the decrees of
                    the pontifex, that there <pb n="p.73"/> might be someone to whom the commons
                    could <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        715-672</note> come for advice, lest any confusion should arise in the
                    religious law through the neglect of ancestral rites and the adoption of strange
                    ones. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And not merely ceremonies relating to
                    the gods above, but also proper funeral observances and the propitiation of the
                    spirits of the dead were to be taught by the pontifex as well, and also what
                    prodigies manifested by lightning or other visible sign were to be taken in hand
                    and averted. With the purpose of eliciting this knowledge from the minds of the
                    gods, Numa dedicated an altar on the Aventine to Jupiter Elicius, and consulted
                    the god by augury, that he might learn what portents were to be regarded. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consideration and disposal of these
                    matters diverted the thoughts of the whole people from violence and arms. Not
                    only had they something to occupy their minds, but their constant preoccupation
                    with the gods, now that it seemed to them that concern for human affairs was
                    felt by the heavenly powers, had so tinged the hearts of all with piety, that
                    the nation was governed by its regard for promises and oaths, rather than by the
                    dread of laws and penalties. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And while Numa's
                    subjects were spontaneously imitating the character of their king, as their
                    unique exemplar, the neighboring peoples also, who had hitherto considered that
                    it was no city but a camp that had been set up in their midst, as a menace to
                    the general peace, came to feel such reverence for them, that they thought it
                    sacrilege to injure a nation so wholly bent upon the worship of the gods.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was a grove watered by a perennial
                    spring which flowed through the midst of it, out of a dark cave. Thither <pb
                        n="p.75"/> Numa would often withdraw, without witnesses, as <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 715-672</note> if to
                    meet the goddess; so he dedicated the grove to the Camenae, alleging that they
                    held counsel there with his wife Egeria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He
                    also established an annual worship of Faith, to whose chapel he ordered that the
                    flamens should proceed in a two-horse hooded carriage, and should wrap up their
                    arms as far as the fingers before sacrificing, as a sign that faith must be
                    kept, and that even in men's clasped hands her seat is sacred. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He established many other rites, as well as places of
                    sacrifice, which the pontiffs called <hi rend="italics">Argei.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> There were six of these shrines or
                        chapels in each of the four regions of the Servian city. A procession made
                        the round of the <hi rend="italics">Argei</hi> on March 17; and on May 15
                        rush puppets, also called <hi rend="italics">Argei,</hi> and probably
                        corresponding to the shrines in number, were thrown into the Tiber by the
                        Vestal Virgins, in the presence of the priestess of Jupiter, who was dressed
                        in mourning. The meaning of both ceremonies is obscure. See Fowler, <hi
                            rend="italics">Fest.</hi> pp. 54 and 111. </note> But of all his
                    services the greatest was this, that throughout his reign he guarded peace no
                    less jealously than his kingdom. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus two
                    successive kings in different ways, one by war, the other by peace, promoted the
                    nation's welfare. Romulus ruled thirty-seven years, Numa forty-three. The state
                    was not only strong, but was also well organized in the arts both of war and of
                    peace. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Numa's death the state reverted to an <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note>
                    interregnum. Then Tullus Hostilius, grandson of that Hostilius who had
                    distinguished himself in the battle with the Sabines at the foot of the citadel,
                    was declared king by the people, and the senate confirmed their choice.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This monarch was not only unlike the last,
                    but was actually more warlike than Romulus had been. Besides his youth and
                    strength, the glory of his grandfather was also an incentive to him. So,
                    thinking that the nation was growing decrepit from inaction, he everywhere
                    sought excuses for stirring up war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It
                    happened that the Roman rustics were <pb n="p.77"/> driving off cattle from
                    Alban territory, while the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> Albans were treating the Romans in the
                    same way. The man who was then in power in Alba was Gaius Cluilius. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Each side, at about the same time, sent envoys to
                    demand restitution. Tullus had commanded his envoys to do nothing else till they
                    had carried out his orders; he felt convinced that the Albans would refuse his
                    demands, in which case he could declare war with a good conscience. The Alban
                    representatives proceeded rather laxly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Received by Tullus with gracious and kindly hospitality, they attended in a
                    friendly spirit the banquet which he gave in their honour. Meanwhile the Romans
                    had been beforehand with them in seeking redress, and, being denied it by the
                    Alban leader, had made a declaration of war, to take effect in thirty days.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Returning, they reported these things to
                    Tullus, who thereupon invited the Alban envoys to inform him of the object of
                    their mission. They, knowing nothing of what had happened, at first spent some
                    time in apologies. They said they should be sorry to utter anything which might
                    give offence to Tullus, but that they were compelled to do so by their orders;
                    they had come to seek restitution; if it should be denied them they were
                    commanded to declare war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To this Tullus
                    replied: <quote> Tell your king the Roman king calls the gods to witness which
                        people first spurned the other's demand for redress and dismissed its
                        envoys, that they may call down upon the guilty nation all the disasters of
                        this war. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With this answer the Albans returned to their
                    city, and both sides prepared for war with the greatest energy —a civil war, to
                    all intents and purposes, almost as if fathers were arrayed against sons; <pb
                        n="p.79"/> for both were of Trojan ancestry, since Lavinium had <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> been
                    planted from Troy, Alba from Lavinium, and from the line of the Alban kings had
                    come the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Still, the issue of the war
                    made the struggle less deplorable, for no battle was fought, and when only the
                    buildings of one of the cities had been destroyed, the two peoples were fused
                    into one. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Albans were first in the field,
                    and with a great army invaded the Roman territory. Their camp they pitched not
                    more than five miles from the City, and surrounded it with a trench. (This was
                    known for some centuries as the Cluilian Trench, from the name of the general,
                    until in the course of time both trench and name disappeared.) <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In this camp Cluilius the Alban king died, and the Albans
                    chose as dictator Mettius Fufetius. Meantime Tullus, emboldened principally by
                    the death of the king, and asserting that Heaven's great powers would take
                    vengeance upon all of the Alban name, beginning with their king himself, for
                    their unscrupulous war, made a night march past the enemy's camp and led his
                    army into the country of the Albans. This move drew Mettius out from his
                    fortifications. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Leading his troops the
                    shortest way towards the enemy, he sent an envoy on ahead to say to Tullus that
                    before they fought it was well that they should confer together; if Tullus would
                    meet him he was confident he had that to say which would be of no less moment to
                    the Roman state than to the Alban. Without rejecting this suggestion, Tullus
                    nevertheless drew up his men in line of battle, in case the proposals should
                    prove impracticable. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the other side the
                    Albans also formed up. When both armies had been marshalled, the leaders, <pb
                        n="p.81"/> attended by a few of their nobles, advanced to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> the
                    middle of the field. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then the Alban began as
                    follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <quote> Pillage and failure to make the amends demanded in accordance with our
                        treaty I think I have myself heard named by our king, Cluilius, as the
                        occasion of this war, and I doubt not, Tullus, but you make the same
                        contention. But if truth is to be spoken, rather than sophistries, it is
                        greed for dominion that is goading two kindred and neighbouring peoples into
                        war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Whether rightly or wrongly I do not
                        attempt to determine; that is a question that may well have been considered
                        by him who undertook the war; I am only the general appointed by the Albans
                        to prosecute that war. But this is the point, Tullus, which I wish to
                        suggest to you: Of the magnitude of the Etruscan power which encompasses us,
                        and you especially, you are better aware than we, in proportion as you are
                        nearer to that people. Great is their strength on land, exceedingly great on
                        the sea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> You must consider that the
                        instant you give the signal for battle, the Tuscans will be watching our two
                        armies, so that, when we have become tired and exhausted, they may attack at
                        once the victor and the vanquished. In Heaven's name, therefore, since we
                        are not content with unquestioned liberty, but are proceeding to the
                        doubtful hazard of dominion or enslavement, let us adopt some plan by which
                        we may decide the question which nation shall rule the other, without a
                        great disaster and much carnage on both sides. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Tullus made no objection, though inclined to
                    war by nature no less than by his anticipation of victory. While both parties
                    were considering what to do, a plan was hit upon for the execution of which
                    Fortune herself supplied the means. </p>
                <pb n="p.83"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It chanced that there were in each of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> these
                    armies triplet brothers, not ill-matched either in age or in physical prowess.
                    That they were Horatii and Curiatii is generally allowed, and scarcely any other
                    ancient tradition is better known; yet, in spite of the celebrity of the affair,
                    an uncertainty persists in regard to the names —to which people, that is, the
                    Horatii belonged, and to which the Curiatii. The writers of history are divided.
                    Still, the majority, I find, call the Roman brothers Horatii, and theirs is the
                    opinion I incline to adopt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To these young men
                    the kings proposed a combat in which each should fight for his own city, the
                    dominion to belong with that side where the victory should rest. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> No objection was raised, and time and place were
                    agreed on. Before proceeding with the battle, a treaty was made between the
                    Romans and the Albans, providing that the nation whose citizens should triumph
                    in this contest should hold undisputed sway over the other nation. One treaty
                    differs from another in its terms, but the same procedure is always employed.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the present occasion we are told that
                    they did as follows, nor has tradition preserved the memory of any more ancient
                    compact. The fetial <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi
                            rend="italics">fetiales</hi> (related to <hi rend="italics">facio,</hi>
                        <quote>do</quote> ) were a college of priests whose duties were to represent
                        the state in declaring war, making peace, entering into treaties, etc. <hi
                            rend="italics">The pater</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">patratus</hi> (from <hi rend="italics">patro,</hi>
                        <quote>accomplish</quote> or <quote>bring about</quote> ) was the spokesman
                        of the deputation. </note> asked King Tullus, <quote> Dost thou command me,
                        King, to make a treaty with the <hi rend="italics">pater patratus</hi> of
                        the Alban People? </quote> Being so commanded by the king, he said, <quote>I
                        demand of thee, King, the sacred herb.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The king replied, <quote>Thou shalt take it
                        untainted.</quote> The fetial brought from the citadel an untainted plant.
                    After this he asked the king, <quote> Dost thou grant me, King, with my emblems
                        and my companions, the royal sanction, to <pb n="p.85"/> speak for the Roman
                        People of the Quirites? </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> king made answer, <quote> So far as may be
                        without prejudice to myself and the Roman People of the Quirites, I grant
                        it. </quote> The fetial was Marcus Valerius; he made Spurius Fusius <hi
                        rend="italics">pater patratus,</hi> touching his head and hair with the
                    sacred sprig. The <hi rend="italics">pater patratus</hi> is appointed to
                    pronounce the oath, that is, to solemnize the pact; and this he accomplishes
                    with many words, expressed in a long metrical formula which it is not worth
                    while to quote. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The conditions being then
                    recited, he cries, <quote> Hear, Jupiter; hear, <hi rend="italics">pater
                            patratus</hi> of the Alban People: hear ye, People of Alba: From these
                        terms, as they have been publicly rehearsed from beginning to end, without
                        fraud, from these tablets, or this wax, and as they have been this day
                        clearly understood, the Roman People will not be the first to depart.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If it shall first depart from them, by
                        general consent, with malice aforethought, then on that day do thou, great
                        Diespiter, so smite the Roman People as I shall here to-day smite this pig:
                        and so much the harder smite them as thy power and thy strength are greater. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When Spurius had said these words, he struck
                    the pig with a flint. In like manner the Albans pronounced their own forms and
                    their own oath, by the mouth of their own dictator and priests. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the treaty had been established, the
                    brothers armed themselves, in accordance with the agreement. On either side the
                    soldiers urged on their champions. They reminded them that their fathers' gods,
                    their native land, their parents, and all their countrymen, whether at home or
                    with the army, had their eye only on their swords and their right hands.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Eager for the combat, as well owing to
                    their <pb n="p.87"/> native spirit as to the shouts of encouragement which <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> filled
                    their ears, the brothers advanced into the space between the two lines of
                    battle. The two armies were drawn up, each in front of its own camp, no longer
                    in any immediate danger, but their concern as great as ever; and no wonder,
                    since empire was staked on those few men's valour and good fortune! <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Alert, therefore, and in suspense, they concentrated
                    their attention upon this unpleasing spectacle. The signal was given, and with
                    drawn steel, like advancing battle-lines, the six young men rushed to the
                    charge, breathing the courage of great armies. Neither side thought of its own
                    danger, but of the nation's sovereignty or servitude, and how from that day
                    forward their country must experience the fortune they should themselves create.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The instant they encountered, there was a
                    clash of shields and a flash of glittering blades, while a deep shudder ran
                    through the onlookers, who, as long as neither side had the advantage, remained
                    powerless to speak or breathe. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, in the
                    hand-to-hand fight which followed, wherein were soon exhibited to men's eyes not
                    only struggling bodies and the play of the sword and shield, but also bloody
                    wounds, two of the Romans fell, fatally wounded, one upon the other, while all
                    three of the Albans were wounded. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At the fall
                    of the Romans a shout of joy burst from the Alban army, while the Roman levies
                    now bade farewell to all their hopes; but not to their anxiety, for they were
                    horror-stricken at the plight of the single warrior whom the three Curiatii had
                    surrounded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He happened to have got no hurt,
                    and though no match for his enemies together, was ready to fight them one at a
                    time. So, to divide their attack, he <pb n="p.89"/> fled, thinking that each of
                    them would pursue him <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 672-640</note> with what speed his wounds permitted. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He had already run some little distance from the spot where
                    they had fought, when, looking back, he saw that they were following at wide
                    intervals and that one of them had nearly overtaken him. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Facing about, he ran swiftly up to his man, and while the
                    Alban host were calling out to the Curiatii to help their brother, Horatius had
                    already slain him, and was hastening, flushed with victory, to meet his second
                    antagonist. Then with a cheer, such as is often drawn from partisans by a sudden
                    turn in a contest, the Romans encouraged their champion, and he pressed on to
                    end the battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And so, before the third
                    Curiatius could come up —and he was not far off —Horatius dispatched the second.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They were now on even terns, one soldier
                    surviving on each side, but in hope and vigour they were far from equal. The
                    one, unscathed and elated by his double victory, was eager for a third
                    encounter. The other dragged himself along, faint from his wound and exhausted
                    with running; he thought how his brothers had been slaughtered before him, and
                    was a beaten man when he faced his triumphant foe. What followed was no combat.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Roman cried exultantly, <quote> Two
                        victims I have given to the shades of my brothers: the third I will offer up
                        to the cause of this war, that Roman may rule Alban. </quote> His adversary
                    could barely hold up his shield. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> With a
                    downward thrust Horatius buried his sword in the Alban's throat, and despoiled
                    him where he lay. The Romans welcomed their hero with jubilations and
                    thanksgivings, and their joy was all the greater that they had come near
                    despairing. The burial of their dead then claimed the attention <pb n="p.91"/>
                    of the two armies, —with widely different feelings, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> since one nation was
                    exalted with imperial power, the other made subject to a foreign sway.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The graves may still be seen where each
                    soldier fell: two Roman graves in one spot, nearer Alba; those of the three
                    Albans towards Rome, but separated, just as they had fought. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before they left the field Mettius asked, in
                    pursuance of the compact, what Tullus commanded him to do, and the Roman ordered
                    him to hold his young men under arms, saying that he should employ their
                    services, if war broke out with the Veientes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The armies then marched home. In the van of the Romans came Horatius, displaying
                    his triple spoils. As he drew near the Porta Capena he was met by his unwedded
                    sister, who had been promised in marriage to one of the Curiatii. When she
                    recognized on her brother's shoulders the military cloak of her betrothed, which
                    she herself had woven, she loosed her hair and, weeping, called on her dead
                    lover's name. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It enraged the fiery youth to
                    hear his sister's lamentations in the hour of his own victory and the nation's
                    great rejoicing. And so, drawing his sword and at the same time angrily
                    upbraiding her, he ran her through the body. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Begone</quote> he cried, <quote> to your betrothed, with your ill-timed
                        love, since you have forgot your brothers, both the dead and the living, and
                        forgot your country! <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So perish every Roman
                        woman who mourns a foe! </quote>
                </p>
                <p> Horrid as this deed seemed to the Fathers and the people, his recent service was
                    an off-set to it; nevertheless he was seized and brought before the king for
                    trial. The king, that he might not take upon himself the responsibility for so
                    stern and unpopular a judgement, and for the punishment which must follow <pb
                        n="p.93"/> sentence, called together the council of the people <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> and
                    said: <quote> In accordance with the law I appoint duumvirs to pass judgement
                        upon Horatius for treason. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> By taking it upon himself to punish
                        his sister, Horatius had usurped a function of the state, and so was guilty
                        of treason. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The dread formula of the law ran thus: <quote>
                        Let the duumvirs pronounce him guilty of treason; if he shall appeal from
                        the duumvirs, let the appeal be tried; if the duumvirs win, let the lictor
                        veil his head; let him bind him with a rope to a barren tree; let him
                        scourge him either within or without the pomerium. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> I have adopted the view of Oldfather
                        ( <hi rend="italics">T.A.P.A.</hi> xxxix. pp. 49 ff.) that neither hanging
                        nor crucifixion is meant, but that the culprit was fastened to the tree and
                        scourged to death. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By the terms of this law duumvirs were
                    appointed. They considered that they might not acquit, under that act, even one
                    who was innocent, and having given a verdict of guilty, one of them pronounced
                    the words, <quote>Publius Horatius, I adjudge you a traitor; go, lictor, bind
                        his hands.</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The lictor had approached and was about to fit
                    the noose. Then Horatius, at the prompting of Tullus, who put a merciful
                    construction upon the law, cried, <quote>I appeal!</quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And so the appeal was tried before the people.
                    What influenced men most of all in that trial was the assertion of Publius
                    Horatius, the father, that his daughter had been justly slain; otherwise he
                    should have used a father's authority and have punished his son, himself. He
                    then implored them not to make him childless whom they had beheld a little while
                    before surrounded by a goodly offspring. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So
                    saying, the old man embraced the youth, and pointing to the spoils of the
                    Curiatii set up in the place which is now called <quote>the Horatian
                        Spears,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The name of the place which
                        commemorated the spoils reflects the tradition, rejected above by Livy, that
                        the Horatii were Albans, the Curiatii Romans. </note> he exclaimed, <quote>
                        This man you saw but lately advancing <pb n="p.95"/> decked with spoils and
                        triumphing in his victory; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> can you bear, Quirites, to see him
                        bound beneath a fork and scourged and tortured? Hardly could Alban eyes
                        endure so hideous a sight. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Go, lictor,
                        bind the hands which but now, with sword and shield, brought imperial power
                        to the Roman People! Go, veil the head of the liberator of this city! Bind
                        him to a barren tree! Scourge him within the pomerium, if you will —so it be
                        amidst yonder spears and trophies of our enemies —or outside the pomerium
                        —so it be amongst the graves of the Curiatii! For whither can you lead this
                        youth where his own honours will not vindicate him from so foul a
                        punishment? </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The people could not withstand the father's
                    tears, or the courage of Horatius himself, steadfast in every peril; and they
                    acquitted him, more in admiration of his valour than from the justice of his
                    cause. And so, that the flagrant murder might yet be cleansed away, by some kind
                    of expiatory rite, the father was commanded to make atonement for his son at the
                    public cost. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He therefore offered certain
                    piacular sacrifices, which were thenceforward handed down in the Horatian
                    family, and, erecting a beam across the street, to typify a yoke, he made his
                    son pass under it, with covered head. It remains to this day, being restored
                    from time to time at the state's expense, and is known as <quote>the Sister's
                        Beam.</quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Horatia's tomb, of hewn stone, was built on
                    the place where she had been struck down. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the peace with Alba did not last long. The
                    discontent of the people, who criticized the dictator for having confided the
                    nation's welfare to three soldiers, broke down his weak character, and since
                    honest measures had proved unsuccessful, <pb n="p.97"/> he resorted to evil ones
                    to regain the favour of his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> countrymen. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, just as in war he had sought peace, so now in
                    time of peace he desired war. But seeing that his own state was richer in
                    courage than in strength, he stirred up other tribes to make war openly after
                    due declaration; while for his own people he reserved the part of the traitor
                    under the disguise of friendship. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The men of
                    Fidenae, a Roman colony, and the Veientes, whom they admitted to a share in
                    their designs, were induced to commence hostilities by a promise that the Albans
                    would go over to their side. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fidenae having
                    openly revolted, Tullus summoned Mettius and his army from Alba, and led his
                    forces against the enemy. Crossing the Anio, he pitched his camp at the
                    confluence of the rivers. The Veientine army had crossed the Tiber between that
                    place and Fidenae. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These troops, drawn up next
                    the river, formed the right wing; on the left the Fidenates were posted, nearer
                    the mountains. Tullus marshalled his own men against the Veientine enemy; the
                    Albans he posted opposite the army of Fidenae. The Alban commander was as
                    wanting in courage as in loyalty. Not daring, therefore, either to hold his
                    ground or openly to desert, he drew off by imperceptible degrees in the
                    direction of the mountains. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then, when he
                    thought he had got near enough to them, he brought up his whole battle-line to
                    an elevated position, and still irresolute, deployed his ranks with the object
                    of consuming time. His purpose was to swing his forces to the side which fortune
                    favoured. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first the Romans posted next to
                    the Albans were amazed when they perceived that their flank was being uncovered
                    by the withdrawal of their allies; then a <pb n="p.99"/> horseman galloped up to
                    the king, and told him that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> the Albans were marching off. In this
                    crisis Tullus vowed to establish twelve Salian priests, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> These were the so-called <hi rend="italics"
                            >Collini,</hi> or <hi rend="italics">Agonales,</hi> and were associated
                        with Quirinus, as the <hi rend="italics">Palatini</hi> (chap. xx.) were with
                        Mars Gradivus. See also v. lii. 7. </note> and to build shrines to Pallor
                    and Panic. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The horseman he reprimanded in a
                    loud voice, that the enemy might overhear him, and ordered him to go back and
                    fight; there was no occasion for alarm; it was by his own command that the Alban
                    army was marching round, that they might attack the unprotected rear of the
                    Fidenates. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He also ordered the cavalry to
                    raise their spears. This manœuvre hid the retreat of the Alban army from a large
                    part of the Roman foot-soldiers; those who had seen it, believing what the king
                    had been heard to say, fought all the more impetuously. The enemy in their turn
                    now became alarmed; they had heard Tullus's loud assertion, and many of the
                    Fidenates, having had Romans among them as colonists, knew Latin. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> And so, lest the Albans should suddenly charge down
                    from the hills and cut them off from their town, they beat a retreat. Tullus
                    pressed them hard, and having routed the wing composed of the Fidenates,
                    returned, bolder than ever, to the Veientes, who were demoralized by the panic
                    of their neighbours. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They, too, failed to
                    withstand his attack, but their rout was stopped by the river in their rear When
                    they had fled thus far, some basely threw away their arms and rushed blindly
                    into the water, others hesitated on the bank and were overtaken before they had
                    made up their minds whether to flee or resist. Never before had the Romans
                    fought a bloodier battle. </p>
                <pb n="p.101"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the Alban army, which had been a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note>
                    spectator of the battle, was led down into the plain. Mettius congratulated
                    Tullus on the conquest of his enemies; Tullus replied kindly to Mettius, and
                    commanded the Albans in a good hour to join their camp to that of the Romans.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He then made preparations to perform, on
                    the morrow, a sacrifice of purification. At dawn, when all things were in
                    readiness, he issued to both armies the customary order, convoking them to an
                    assembly. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The heralds, beginning at the
                    outskirts of the camp, called out the Albans first, who being moved by the very
                    novelty of the occasion, took their stand close to the Roman king, that they
                    might hear him harangue his army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Roman
                    troops, by previous arrangement, were armed and disposed around them, and the
                    centurions were bidden to execute orders promptly. Then Tullus began as follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <quote> Romans, if ever anywhere in any war you have had reason to give thanks,
                        first to the immortal gods and then to your own valour, it was in the battle
                        of yesterday. For you fought not only against your enemies, but a harder and
                        more dangerous fight —against the treachery and the perfidy of your allies.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For, to undeceive you, I gave no
                        orders that the Albans should draw off towards the mountains. What you heard
                        was not my command, but a trick and a pretended command, devised in order
                        that you might not know you were being deserted, and so be distracted from
                        the fight; and that the enemy, thinking that they were being hemmed in on
                        the rear, might be panic-stricken and flee. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> And yet this guilt which I am charging does not attach to all the Albans;
                        they but followed <pb n="p.103"/> their general, as you, too, would have
                        done, had I <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            672-640</note> desired to lead you off anywhere. It is Mettius yonder
                        who led this march; Mettius, too, who contrived this war; Mettius who broke
                        the treaty between Roman and Alban. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Let
                        another dare such a deed hereafter if I do not speedily visit such a
                        punishment on him as shall be a conspicuous warning to all mankind. </quote>
                </p>
                <p> Thereupon the centurions, sword in hand, surrounded Mettius, while the king
                    proceeded: <quote> May prosperity, favour, and fortune be with the Roman people
                        and myself, and with you, men of Alba! I purpose to bring all the Alban
                        people over to Rome, to grant citizenship to their commons, to enroll the
                        nobles in the senate, to make one city and one state. As formerly from one
                        people the Alban nation was divided into two, so now let it be reunited into
                        one. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hearing these words the Alban soldiers,
                    themselves unarmed and fenced in by armed men, were constrained, however their
                    wishes might differ, by a common fear, and held their peace. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Then Tullus said: <quote> Mettius Fufetius, if you were
                        capable of learning, yourself, to keep faith and abide by treaties, you
                        should have lived that I might teach you this; as it is, since your
                        disposition is incurable, you shall yet by your punishment teach the human
                        race to hold sacred the obligations you have violated. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Accordingly, just as a little while ago your heart was
                        divided between the states of Fidenae and Rome, so now you shall give up
                        your body to be torn two ways, </quote> He then brought up two four-horse
                    chariots, and caused Mettius to be stretched out and made fast to them, after
                    which the horses were whipped up in opposite directions, and bore off in <pb
                        n="p.105"/> each of the cars fragments of the mangled body, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> where
                    the limbs held to their fastenings. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All eyes
                    were turned away from so dreadful a sight. Such was the first and last
                    punishment among the Romans of a kind that disregards the laws of humanity. In
                    other cases we may boast that with no nation have milder punishments found
                    favour. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this was going on, horsemen had already
                    been sent on to Alba to fetch the inhabitants to Rome, and afterwards the
                    legions were marched over to demolish the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> When they entered the gates there was not, indeed, the tumult and panic which
                    usually follow the capture of a city, when its gates have been forced or its
                    walls breached with a ram or its stronghold stormed, when the shouts of the
                    enemy and the rush of armed men through the streets throw the whole town into a
                    wild confusion of blood and fire. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But at Alba
                    oppressive silence and grief that found no words quite overwhelmed the spirits
                    of all the people; too dismayed to think what they should take with them and
                    what leave behind, they would ask each other's advice again and again, now
                    standing on their thresholds, and now roaming aimlessly through the houses they
                    were to look upon for that last time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when
                    at length the horsemen began to be urgent, and clamorously commanded them to
                    come out; when they could now hear the crash of the buildings which were being
                    pulled down in the outskirts of the city; when the dust rising in different
                    quarters had overcast the sky like a gathering cloud; then everybody made haste
                    to carry out what he could, and forth they went, abandoning their lares and
                    penates, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Each family had its <hi
                            rend="italics">lar,</hi> a special deity who protected the household,
                        and its <hi rend="italics">penates,</hi> guardians of the <hi rend="italics"
                            >penus</hi> (the family store of provisions). </note> and the houses
                    where they had been born and brought up. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And
                    now the streets were filled with an unbroken <pb n="p.107"/> procession of
                    emigrants, whose mutual pity, as they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> gazed at one another, caused their tears
                    to start afresh; plaintive cries too began to be heard, proceeding chiefly from
                    the women, when they passed the venerable temples beset by armed men, and left
                    in captivity, as it seemed to them, their gods. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> When the Albans had quitted the city, the Romans everywhere levelled with the
                    ground all buildings, both public and private, and a single hour gave over to
                    destruction and desolation the work of the four hundred years during which Alba
                    had stood. But the temples of the gods were spared, for so the king had decreed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Rome, meanwhile, was increased by Alba's
                    downfall. The number of citizens was doubled, the Caelian Hill was added to the
                    City, and, that it might be more thickly settled, Tullus chose it for the site
                    of the king's house and from that time onwards resided there. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The chief men of the Albans he made senators, that this
                    branch of the nation might grow too. Such were the Julii, the Servilii, the
                    Quinctii, the Geganii, the Curiatii, and the Cloelii. He also built, as a
                    consecrated place for the order he had enlarged, a senate-house, which continued
                    to be called the Curia Hostilia as late as the time of our own fathers. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> When Clodius was murdered, in <date
                            when="-0052">52 B.C.</date> , the mob burnt his body in the Curia
                        Hostilia, which caught fire and was destroyed. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And that all the orders might gain some
                    strength from the new people, he enrolled ten squadrons of knights <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Each squadron contained thirty men. The
                        total number was, therefore, the same as that of the three centuries of
                        Romulus. </note> from among the Albans, and from the same source filled up
                    the old legions and enlisted new ones. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Confiding in these forces, Tullus declared war
                    on <pb n="p.109"/> the Sabines, a nation second only at that time to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> the
                    Etruscans in its wealth of men and arms. On either side there had been
                    aggressions and refusals to grant satisfaction. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Tullus complained that at the shrine of Feronia, in a crowded fair, Roman
                    traders had been seized; the Sabines alleged that, before this, refugees from
                    their country had fled to the grove of sanctuary, and had been detained in Rome.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These were put forward as the causes of
                    war. The Sabines, not forgetting that a portion of their own forces had been
                    settled in Rome by Tatius and that the Roman state had recently been further
                    strengthened by the addition of the Alban people, began themselves to look about
                    for outside help. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Etruria was close by, and
                    the nearest of the Etruscans were the Veientes. There the resentment left over
                    from the wars was the strongest incentive to revolt, and procured them some
                    volunteers; while with certain vagrant and poverty-stricken plebeians even the
                    prospect of pay was effectual. Official aid there was none, and the Veientes
                    (for there is less to surprise us in the others) held firmly to the truce they
                    had agreed upon with Romulus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While
                    preparations for war were making on both sides with the greatest energy, and
                    success appeared to hinge upon which should first take the field, Tullus
                    anticipated his enemies and invaded the Sabine country. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> A desperate battle was fought near the Silva Malitiosa,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        <quote>Guileful Wood.</quote>
                    </note> where, owing partly, it is true, to the strength of their infantry, but
                    most of all to their newly augmented cavalry, the Roman army gained the mastery.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The cavalry made a sudden charge; the
                    ranks of the Sabines were thrown into disorder, and from that moment were
                    unable, without heavy loss, either to hold their own in the fight or to
                    extricate themselves by a retreat. </p>
                <pb n="p.111"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the defeat of the Sabines, when <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> King
                    Tullus and the entire Roman state were at a high pitch of glory and prosperity,
                    it was reported to the king and senators that there had been a rain of stones on
                    the Alban Mount. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As this could scarce be
                    credited, envoys were dispatched to examine the prodigy, and in their sight
                    there fell from the sky, like hail-stones which the wind piles in drifts upon
                    the ground, a shower of pebbles. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They thought
                    too that they heard a mighty voice issuing from the grove on the mountain-top,
                    which commanded the Albans to celebrate, according to the fashion of their
                    fathers, the sacrifices, which as though they had forsaken their gods along with
                    their city, they had given over to oblivion, either adopting Roman rites, or in
                    anger at their fortune, such as men sometimes feel, abandoning the worship of
                    the gods. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans also, in consequence of
                    the same portent, undertook an official nine days' celebration, whether so
                    commanded by the divine utterance from the Alban Mount —for this too is handed
                    down —or on the advice of soothsayers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At all
                    events it remained a regular custom that whenever the same prodigy was reported
                    there should be a nine days' observance. </p>
                <p> Not very long after this Rome was afflicted with a pestilence. This caused a
                    reluctance to bear arms, yet no respite from service was allowed by the warlike
                    king (who believed, besides, that the young men were healthier in the field than
                    at home) until he himself contracted a lingering illness. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then that haughty spirit was so broken, with the breaking
                    of his health, that he who had hitherto thought nothing less worthy of a king
                    than to devote his mind to sacred rites, suddenly became a prey to all sorts of
                        <pb n="p.113"/> superstitions great and small, and filled even the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 672-640</note> minds
                    of the people with religious scruples. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Men
                    were now agreed in wishing to recall the conditions which had obtained under
                    King Numa, believing that the only remedy left for their ailing bodies was to
                    procure peace and forgiveness from the gods. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The king himself, so tradition tells, in turning over the commentaries of Numa
                    discovered there certain occult sacrifices performed in honour of Jupiter
                    Elicius, and devoted himself in secret to those rites; but the ceremony was
                    improperly undertaken or performed, and not only was no divine manifestation
                    vouchsafed him, but in consequence of the wrath of Jupiter, who was provoked by
                    his faulty observance, he was struck by a thunderbolt and consumed in the flames
                    of his house. Tullus was greatly renowned in war and reigned thirty-two years. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the death of Tullus, the government <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 640-616</note>
                    reverted, in accordance with the custom established in the beginning, to the
                    senators, who named an interrex. This official called together the comitia, and
                    the people elected Ancus Marcius king, a choice which the Fathers ratified.
                    Ancus Marcius was a grandson, on the mother's side, of King Numa Pompilius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he began to rule he was mindful of
                    his grandfather's glory, and considered that the last reign, excellent in all
                    else, had failed to prosper in one respect, owing to neglect or misconduct of
                    religious observances. Deeming it therefore a matter of the utmost consequence
                    to perform the state sacrifices as Numa had established them, he bade the
                    pontifex copy out all these from the commentaries of the king and display them
                    in public on a whitened table. This act led the citizens, who were eager for
                    peace, <pb n="p.115"/> and also the neighbouring nations, to hope that he <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 640-616</note> would
                    adopt the character and institutions of his grandfather. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Hence the Latins, with whom a treaty had been made in the
                    time of Tullus, plucked up courage, and raided Roman territory, and when called
                    on by the Romans to make restitution, returned an arrogant answer, persuaded
                    that the Roman king would spend his reign in inactivity amid shrines and altars.
                    But the character of Ancus was well balanced, and he honoured the memory of
                    Romulus, as well as Numa. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And besides having a
                    conviction that peace had been more necessary to his grandfather's reign, when
                    the nation had been both young and mettlesome, he also believed that the
                    tranquillity, so free of attack, which had fallen to the lot of Numa would be no
                    easy thing for himself to compass; his patience was being tried, and when proved
                    would be regarded with contempt, and in short the times were better suited to
                    the rule of a Tullus than a Numa. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In order
                    however that, as Numa had instituted religious practices in time of peace, he
                    might himself give out a ceremonial of war, and that wars might not only be
                    waged but also declared with some sort of formality, he copied from the ancient
                    tribe of the Aequicoli the law, which the fetials now have, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The institution of the fetials was
                        ascribed in chap. xxiv. to Tullus (so also Cic. <hi rend="italics">Rep.</hi>
                        ii. 31). Livy is here following another authority, without taking the
                        trouble to remove the discrepancy. Other writers (Dion. ii. 72; Plut. <hi
                            rend="italics">Numa</hi> xii.) credit Numa with the institution. </note>
                    by which redress is demanded. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the envoy has arrived at the frontiers of
                    the people from whom satisfaction is sought, he covers his head with a bonnet
                    —the covering is of wool —and says: <quote>Hear, Jupiter; hear, ye boundaries
                        of</quote> —naming whatever nation they belong to; — <quote> let
                        righteousness hear! <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I am the public herald
                        of the Roman People; I come duly and religiously commissioned; let my words
                        be credited, </quote> Then he <pb n="p.117"/> recites his demands, after
                    which he takes Jupiter to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 640-616</note> witness: <quote> If I demand unduly and
                        against religion that these men and these things be surrendered to me, then
                        let me never enjoy my native land. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These words he rehearses when he crosses the
                    boundary line, the same to what man soever first meets him, the same when he
                    enters the city gates, the same when he has come into the market-place, with
                    only a few changes in the form and wording of the oath. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> If those whom he demands are not surrendered, at the end of
                    three and thirty days —for such is the conventional number —he declares war
                    thus: <quote> Hear, Jupiter, and thou, Janus Quirinus, and hear all heavenly
                        gods, and ye, gods of earth, and ye of the lower world; I call you to
                        witness that this people </quote> —naming whatever people it is — <quote> is
                        unjust, and does not make just reparation. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> But of these matters we will take counsel of the elders in our country,
                        how we may obtain our right. </quote> Then the messenger returns to Rome for
                    the consultation. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Immediately the king would
                    consult the Fathers, in some such words as these: <quote> Touching the things,
                        the suits, the causes, concerning which the <hi rend="italics">pater
                            patratus</hi> of the Roman People of the Quirites has made demands on
                        the <hi rend="italics">pater patratus</hi> of the Ancient Latins, and upon
                        the men of the Ancient Latins, which things they have not delivered, nor
                        fulfilled, nor satisfied, being things which ought to have been delivered,
                        fulfilled, and satisfied, speak, </quote> —turning to the man whose opinion
                    he was wont to ask first, — <quote>what think you?</quote> Then the other would
                    reply: <quote> I hold that those things ought to be sought in warfare just and
                        righteous; and so I consent and vote. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The others were then asked the question, in
                    their order, and when the majority <pb n="p.119"/> of those present went over to
                    the same opinion, war <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 640-616</note> had been agreed upon. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> It was customary for the fetial to carry to the bounds of the other nation a
                    cornet-wood spear, iron-pointed or hardened in the fire, and in the presence of
                    not less than three grown men to say: <quote> Whereas the tribes of the Ancient
                        Latins and men of the Ancient Latins have been guilty of acts and offences
                        against the Roman People of the Quirites; and whereas the Roman People of
                        the Quirites has commanded that war be made on the Ancient Latins, and the
                        Senate of the Roman People has approved, agreed, and voted a war with the
                        Ancient Latins; I therefore and the Roman People declare and make war on the
                        tribes of the Ancient Latins and the men of the Ancient Latins. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Having said this, he would hurl his spear
                    into their territory. This is the manner in which at that time redress was
                    sought from the Latins and war was declared, and the custom has been received by
                    later generations. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ancus delegated the care of the sacrifices to
                    the flamens and other priests, and having enlisted a new army proceeded to
                    Politorium, one of the Latin cities. He took this place by storm, and adopting
                    the plan of former kings, who had enlarged the state by making her enemies
                    citizens, transferred the whole population to Rome. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Palatine was the quarter of the original Romans; on the
                    one hand were the Sabines, who had the Capitol and the Citadel; on the other lay
                    the Caelian, occupied by the Albans. The Aventine was therefore assigned to the
                    newcomers, and thither too were sent shortly afterwards the citizens recruited
                    from the captured towns of Tellenae and Ficana. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Politorium was then attacked <pb n="p.121"/> a second time, for having been
                    left empty it had been <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 640-616</note> seized by the Ancient Latins, and this gave the Romans
                    an excuse for razing the town, lest it should serve continually as a refuge for
                    their enemies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the end the Latin levies
                    were all forced back upon Medullia, where for some time the fighting was
                    indecisive and victory shifted from one side to the other; for the city was
                    protected by fortifications and was defended by a strong garrison, and from
                    their camp in the open plain the Latin army several times came to close quarters
                    with the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last, throwing all his
                    troops into the struggle, Ancus succeeded first in defeating the enemy's army,
                    and then in capturing the town, whence he returned to Rome enriched with immense
                    spoils. On this occasion also many thousands of Latins were granted citizenship.
                    These people, in order that the Aventine might be connected with the Palatine,
                    were made to settle in the region of the Altar of Murcia. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Janiculum was also annexed to the city, not from any lack
                    of room, but lest it might some day become a stronghold of Rome's enemies. It
                    was decided not only to fortify it, but also to connect it with the City, for
                    greater ease in passing to and fro, by a bridge of piles, the first bridge ever
                    built over the Tiber. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This was the
                        famous Pons Sublicius, <quote>Pile Bridge,</quote> made of wood, without
                        metal of any sort. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Quirites' Ditch also, no small protection
                    on the more level and accessible side of town, was the work of King Ancus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When these enormous additions to the community
                    had been effected, it was found that in so great a multitude the distinction
                    between right and wrong had become obscured, and crimes were being secretly
                    committed. Accordingly, to overawe men's growing lawlessness, a prison was built
                    in <pb n="p.123"/> the midst of the city, above the Forum. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This prison, <hi rend="italics">the</hi> Carcer, may
                        still be seen at the foot of the Capitoline, between the Temple of Concord
                        and the Curia. It is thought to be as old as any structure in Rome. It was
                        used as a place of detention and execution for condemned criminals. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 640-616</note> this reign was a period of growth, not
                    only for the City, but also for her lands and boundaries. The Maesian Forest was
                    taken from the Veientes, extending Rome's dominion clear to the sea; at the
                    Tiber's mouth the city of Ostia was founded, and salt-works were established
                    near-by; while in recognition of signal success in war the temple of Jupiter
                    Feretrius was enlarged. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the reign of Ancus one Lucumo, a man of
                    energy and wealth, took up his residence in Rome, chiefly from ambition and the
                    hope that he might there achieve a station such as he had found no opportunity
                    of attaining in Tarquinii; for though he had been born there himself, his race
                    was alien to that place also. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He was the son
                    of Demaratus of Corinth, who had been driven from home by a political upheaval.
                    Happening to settle in Tarquinii, he had married there and had two sons, named
                    Lucumo and Arruns. Lucumo survived his father and inherited all his property;
                    Arruns died before his father, leaving his wife with child. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Demaratus did not long survive Arruns, and, unaware that
                    his son's wife was to become a mother, he died without making provision for his
                    grandson in his will. When the babe was born his grandfather was dead, and
                    having no share in the inheritance, he was given the name of Egerius, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        <quote>Necessitous.</quote>
                    </note> in consequence of his penniless condition. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Lucumo, on the other hand, was heir to the whole estate.
                    The self-confidence implanted in his bosom by his wealth was heightened by his
                    marriage with Tanaquil, who was a woman of the most exalted birth, and not of a
                    character lightly to endure a humbler rank in her new environment than she had
                        <pb n="p.125"/> enjoyed in the condition to which she had been born. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 640-616</note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Etruscans looked with disdain on Lucumo,
                    the son of a banished man and a stranger. She could not endure this indignity,
                    and forgetting the love she owed her native land, if she could only see her
                    husband honoured, she formed the project of emigrating from Tarquinii.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Rome appeared to be the most suitable
                    place for her purpose; amongst a new people, where all rank was of sudden growth
                    and founded on worth, there would be room for a brave and strenuous man; the
                    City had been ruled by Tatius the Sabine, it had summoned Numa to the
                    sovereignty from Cures, even Ancus was the son of a Sabine mother, and could
                    point to no noble ancestor but Numa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> She had
                    no trouble in persuading a man who was eager for distinction, to whom Tarquinii
                    was only his mother's birthplace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They
                    therefore gathered their possessions together and removed to Rome. They had
                    come, as it happened, as far as Janiculum, when, as they were sitting in their
                    covered waggon, an eagle poised on its wings gently descended upon them and
                    plucked off Lucumo's cap, after which, rising noisily above the car and again
                    stooping, as if sent from heaven for that service, it deftly replaced the cap
                    upon his head, and departed on high. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This
                    augury was joyfully accepted, it is said, by Tanaquil, who was a woman skilled
                    in celestial prodigies, as was the case with most Etruscans. Embracing her
                    husband, she bade him expect transcendent greatness: such was the meaning of
                    that bird, appearing from that quarter of the sky, and bringing tidings from
                    that god; the highest part of the man had been concerned in the omen; the eagle
                    had removed the adornment placed upon a mortal's head that it might <pb
                        n="p.127"/> restore it with the divine approbation. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Such were <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 640-616</note> their hopes and their reflections as they
                    entered the City. Having obtained a house, they gave out the name of Lucius
                    Tarquinius Priscus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Romans regarded him
                    with special interest, as a stranger and a man of wealth, and he steadily pushed
                    his fortune by his own exertions, making friends wherever possible, by kind
                    words, courteous hospitality, and benefactions, until his reputation extended
                    even to the palace. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He had not long been
                    known in this way to the king before the liberality and adroitness of his
                    services procured him the footing of an intimate friend. He was now consulted in
                    matters both of public and private importance, in time of war and in time of
                    peace, and having been tested in every way was eventually even named in the
                    king's will as guardian of his children. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ancus reigned four and twenty years, a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> king
                    inferior to none of his predecessors in the arts of peace and war and in the
                    reputation they conferred. By this time his sons were nearly grown. Tarquinius
                    was therefore all the more insistent in urging that the comitia should be held
                    without delay to choose a king. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the
                    meeting had been proclaimed, and the day drew near, he sent the boys away on a
                    hunting expedition. Tarcuinius was the first, they say, to canvass votes for the
                    kingship and to deliver a speech designed to win the favour of the commons.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He pointed out that it; was no new thing
                    he sought; he was not the first outsider to aim at the sovereignty in Rome —a
                    thing which might have occasioned indignation and astonishment, —but the third.
                    Tatius indeed, had been not merely an alien but an enemy when he was made king;
                    while Numa was a stranger <pb n="p.129"/> to the City, and, far from seeking the
                    kingship, had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        616-578</note> actually been invited to come and take it. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> As for himself, he had no sooner become his own master than
                    he had removed to Rome with his wife and all his property. For the greater part
                    of that period of life during which men serve the state he had lived in Rome,
                    and not in the city of his birth. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both in
                    civil life and in war he had had no mean instructor —King Ancus himself had
                    taught him Roman laws and Roman rites. In subordination and deference to the
                    king he had vied, he said, with all his hearers; in generosity to his
                    fellow-subjects he had emulated the king himself. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Hearing him advance these not unwarranted claims, the
                    people, with striking unanimity, named him king. The result was that the man, so
                    admirable in all other respects, continued even after he had obtained the
                    sovereignty to manifest the same spirit of intrigue which had governed him in
                    seeking it; and being no less concerned to strengthen his own power than to
                    enlarge the state, he added a hundred members to the senate, who were known
                    thenceforward as Fathers of the <quote>lesser families,</quote> and formed a
                    party of unwavering loyalty to the king, to whom they owed their admission to
                    the Curia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The senate had doubtless
                        shown its disapproval of the accession of Tarquinius, who now sought to
                        render its opposition futile by doubling the membership and appointing none
                        but his own supporters. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His first war was with the Latins, whose town
                    of Apiolae he took by storm. Returning thence with more booty than the rumours
                    about the war had led people to expect, he exhibited games on a more splendid
                    and elaborate scale than former kings had done. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> It was then that the ground was first marked out for the circus now called
                    Maximus. Places were divided amongst the Fathers and the knights where they
                    might each make seats for themselves; these were called 'rows.' <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> They got their view from seats <pb n="p.131"/> raised on
                    props to a height of twelve feet from the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> ground. The
                    entertainment was furnished by horses and boxers, imported for the most part
                    from Etruria. From that time the Games continued to be a regular annual show,
                    and were called indifferently the Roman and the Great Games. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> It was the same king, too, who apportioned building sites
                    about the Forum among private citizens, and erected covered walks and booths. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He was also preparing to build a stone wall
                    around the City, when a Sabine war interrupted his plans. And so sudden was the
                    invasion, that they had crossed the Anio before the Roman army was able to march
                    out and stop them, so that the City was thrown into a panic. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The first battle was indecisive, with heavy losses on both
                    sides. The enemy then withdrew into their camp, affording the Romans an
                    opportunity to renew their preparations for the war. Tarquinius believed that
                    cavalry was what he chiefly lacked. To the Ramnes, Titienses, and Luceres, the
                    centuries which Romulus had enrolled, he therefore determined to add others, and
                    to give them his own name as a permanent distinction. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But since this was a matter in which Romulus had obtained
                    the sanction of augury before acting, it was asserted by Attus Navius, a famous
                    augur of those days, that no change or innovation could be introduced unless the
                    birds had signified their approval. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king's
                    ire was aroused by this, and he is reported to have said, in derision of the
                    science, <quote> Come now, divine seer! Inquire of your augury if that of which
                        I am now thinking can come to pass. </quote> When Attus, having taken the
                    auspices, replied that it would surely come to pass, the king said, <quote> Nay,
                        but this is <pb n="p.133"/> what I was thinking of, that you should cleave a
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            616-578</note> whetstone with a razor. Take them, and accomplish what
                        your birds declare is possible! </quote> Whereupon, they say, the augur,
                    without a sign of hesitation, cut the whetstone in two. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There was a statue of Attus standing, with his head
                    covered, on the spot where the thing was done, in the comitium, even at the
                    steps on the left of the senate-house; tradition adds that the whetstone also
                    was deposited in the same place, to be a memorial of that miracle to posterity.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However this may be, auguries and the
                    augural priesthood so increased in honour that nothing was afterwards done, in
                    the field or at home, unless the auspices had first been taken: popular
                    assemblies, musterings of the army, acts of supreme importance —all were put off
                    when the birds refused their consent. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Neither
                    did Tarquinius at that time make any change in the organization of the centuries
                    of knights. Their numerical strength he doubled, so that there were now eighteen
                    hundred knights, in three centuries. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                    though enrolled under the old names, the new men were called the
                        <quote>secondary knights,</quote> and the centuries are now, because
                    doubled, known as the <quote>six centuries.</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this arm of the service had been
                    enlarged, a second battle was fought with the Sabines. And in this, besides
                    being increased in strength, the Roman army was further helped by a stratagem,
                    for men were secretly dispatched to light a great quantity of firewood lying on
                    the bank of the Anio, and throw it into the river. A favouring wind set the wood
                    in a blaze, and the greater part of it lodged against the boats and piles, where
                    it stuck fast and <pb n="p.135"/> set the bridge on fire. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This was another source of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> alarm to the Sabines
                    during the battle, and upon their being routed the same thing hindered their
                    flight, so that many of them escaped the Romans only to perish in the stream;
                    while their shields floated down the Tiber toward the City, and, being
                    recognized, gave assurance that a victory had been won almost sooner than the
                    news of it could be brought. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In this battle
                    the cavalry particularly distinguished themselves. They were posted on either
                    flank of the Romans, and when the centre, composed of infantry, was already in
                    retreat, they are said to have charged from both sides, with such effect that
                    they not only checked the Sabine forces, which were pressing hotly forward as
                    their enemy gave way, but suddenly put them to flight. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Sabines made for the mountains in a scattered rout, and
                    indeed a few gained that refuge. Most of them, as has been said before, were
                    driven by the cavalry into the river. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Tarquinius thought it proper to follow up his victory while the other side was
                    panic-stricken; he therefore sent the booty and the prisoners to Rome, and after
                    making a huge pile of the captured arms and setting fire to it, in fulfilment of
                    a vow to Vulcan, pushed forward at the head of his army into the enemy's
                    country. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Although defeat had been the portion
                    of the Sabines, and another battle could not be expected to result in better
                    success, still, as the situation allowed no room for deliberation, they took the
                    field with what soldiers they could hastily muster, and being then routed a
                    second time and fairly reduced to extremities, they sued for peace. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Collatia, and what land the Sabines had on the
                    hither side of Collatia, was taken from <pb n="p.137"/> them, and Egerius, the
                    son of the king's brother, was <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> left in the town with a garrison.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The surrender of the Collatini took place,
                    I understand, in accordance with this formula: the king asked, <quote> Are you
                        the legates and spokesmen sent by the People of Collatia to surrender
                        yourselves and the People of Collatia? </quote>
                    <quote>We are.</quote>
                    <quote>Is the People of Collatia its own master?</quote>
                    <quote>It is.</quote>
                    <quote> Do you surrender yourselves and the People of Collatia, city, lands,
                        water, boundary marks, shrines, utensils, all appurtenances, divine and
                        human, into my power and that of the Roman People? </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>We do.</quote>
                    <quote>I receive the surrender.</quote> Upon the conclusion of the Sabine war
                    Tarquinius returned to Rome and triumphed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He
                    then made war against the Ancient Latins. In this campaign there was no general
                    engagement at any point, but the king led his army from one town to another
                    until he had subdued the entire Latin race. Corniculum, Ficulea Vetus, Cameria,
                    Crustumerium, Ameriola, Medullia, and Nomentum —these were the towns which were
                    captured from the Ancient Latins, or from those who had gone over to the Latins.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Peace was then made. </p>
                <p> From that moment the king devoted himself to peaceful undertakings with an
                    enthusiasm which was even greater than the efforts he had expended in waging
                    war, so that there was no more rest for the people at home than there had been
                    in the field. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For he set to work to encircle
                    the hitherto unfortified parts of the City with a stone wall, a task which had
                    been interrupted by the Sabine war; and he drained the lowest parts of the City,
                    about the Forum, and the other valleys between the hills, which were too flat to
                    carry off the flood-waters easily, by means of sewers so made as to slope down
                    toward the Tiber. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.139"/> Finally, with prophetic anticipation of the splendour <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> which
                    the place was one day to possess, he laid foundations for the temple of Jupiter
                    on the Capitol, which he had vowed in the Sabine war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this time there happened in the house of
                    the king a portent which was remarkable alike in its manifestation and in its
                    outcome. The story is that while a child named Servius Tullius lay sleeping, his
                    head burst into flames in the sight of many. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The general outcry which so great a miracle called forth brought the king and
                    queen to the place. One of the servants fetched water to quench the fire, but
                    was checked by the queen, who stilled the uproar and commanded that the boy
                    should not be disturbed until he awoke of himself. Soon afterwards sleep left
                    him, and with it disappeared the flames. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then,
                    taking her husband aside, Tanaquil said: <quote> Do you see this child whom we
                        are bringing up in so humble a fashion? Be assured he will one day be a lamp
                        to our dubious fortunes, and a protector to the royal house in the day of
                        its distress. Let us therefore rear with all solicitude one who will lend
                        high renown to the state and to our family. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is said that from that moment the boy began
                    to be looked upon as a son, and to be trained in the studies by which men are
                    inspired to bear themselves greatly. It was a thing easily accomplished, being
                    the will of Heaven. The youth turned out to be of a truly royal nature, and when
                    Tarquinius sought a son-in-law there was no other young Roman who could be at
                    all compared to Servius; and the king accordingly betrothed his daughter to him.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This great honour, for whatever cause
                    conferred on him, forbids us to suppose that <pb n="p.141"/> his mother was a
                    slave and that he himself had been <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> in a state of servitude as a child. I am
                    rather of the opinion of those who say, that on the capture of Corniculum, when
                    Servius Tullius, the chief man of that city, had been slain, his wife, who was
                    great with child, had been recognized amongst the other captive women, and on
                    the score of her unique nobility had been rescued from slavery by the Roman
                    queen, and had brought forth her child at Rome in the house of Priscus
                    Tarquinius; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> in the sequel this act of
                    generosity led to a growing intimacy between the women, and the boy, as one
                    reared from childhood in the palace, was held in affection and esteem; it was
                    his mother's misfortune, who by the capture of her native town came into the
                    power of its enemies, which gave rise to the belief that Servius was born of a
                    slave woman. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now about thirty-eight years since
                    Tarquinius had begun to reign, and not only the king, but the Fathers and the
                    commons too, held Servius Tullius in the very highest honour. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Now the two sons of Ancus had always considered it a great
                    outrage that they had been ousted from their father's kingship by the crime of
                    their guardian, and that Rome should be ruled by a stranger whose descent was
                    derived from a race not only remote but actually not even Italian. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> But their indignation was vastly increased by the
                    prospect that even after Tarquinius' death the sovereignty would not revert to
                    them, but, plunging down to yet baser depths, would fall into the hands of
                    slaves; so that where, a hundred years before, Romulus, a god's son and himself
                    a god, had borne sway, so long as he remained on earth, in that self-same state
                    a slave and <pb n="p.143"/> the son of a slave woman would be king. It would
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note>
                    be not only a general disgrace to the Roman name, but particularly to their own
                    house, if during the lifetime of Ancus' sons it should be open not only to
                    strangers, but even to slaves to rule over the Romans. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They therefore determined to repel that insult with the
                    sword. But resentment at their wrong urged them rather against Tarquinius
                    himself than against Servius, not only because the king, if he survived, would
                    be more formidable to avenge the murder than a subject would be, but because if
                    Servius should be dispatched it seemed probable that the kingdom would be
                    inherited by whomsoever else Tarquinius might choose to be his son-in-law. For
                    these reasons they laid their plot against the king himself. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Two very desperate shepherds were selected to do the deed.
                    Armed with the rustic implements to which they were both accustomed, they
                    feigned a brawl in the entrance-court of the palace and, making as much noise as
                    possible, attracted the attention of all the royal attendants; then they
                    appealed to the king, until their shouts were heard inside the palace and they
                    were sent for and came before him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At first
                    each raised his voice and tried to shout the other down. Being repressed by the
                    lictor and bidden to speak in turn, they finally ceased to interrupt each other,
                    and one of them began to state his case, as they had planned beforehand.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While the king, intent upon the speaker,
                    turned quite away from the other shepherd, the latter lifted his axe and brought
                    it down upon his head. Then, leaving the weapon in the wound, they both ran out
                    of doors. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dying Tarquinius had hardly been caught
                        <pb n="p.145"/> up in the arms of the bystanders when the fugitives <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 616-578</note> were
                    seized by the lictors. Then there was an uproar, as crowds hurried to the scene,
                    asking one another in amazement what the matter was. In the midst of the tumult
                    Tanaquil gave orders to close the palace, and ejected all witnesses. She busily
                    got together the remedies needful for healing a wound, as if there were still
                    hope, taking at the same time other measures to protect herself in case her hope
                    should fail her. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Having hastily summoned
                    Servius, she showed him her husband's nearly lifeless body, and grasping his
                    right hand, besought him not to suffer the death of his father-in-law to go
                    unpunished, nor his mother-in-law to become a jest to her enemies. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>To you, Servius,</quote> she cried, <quote> if you are a man, belongs
                        this kingdom, not to those who by the hands of others have committed a
                        dastardly crime. Arouse yourself and follow the guidance of the gods, who
                        once declared by the token of divine fire poured out upon this head that you
                        should be a famous man. Now is the time for that heaven-sent flame to
                        quicken you! Now wake in earnest! We, too, were foreigners, yet we reigned.
                        Consider what you are, not whence you were born. If your own counsels are
                        benumbed in this sudden crisis, at least use mine. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the shouting and pushing of the crowd
                    could hardly be withstood, Tanaquil went up into the upper storey of the house,
                    and through a window looking out upon the Nova Via —for the king lived near the
                    temple of Jupiter the Stayer — addressed the populace. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> She bade them be of good cheer: the king had been stunned
                    by a sudden blow; the steel had not sunk deep into his body; he had already
                    recovered consciousness; the blood had been <pb n="p.147"/> wiped away and the
                    wound examined; all the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 616-578</note> symptoms were favourable; she trusted that they would
                    soon see Tarquinius himself; meanwhile she commanded that the people should obey
                    Servius Tullius, who would dispense justice and perform the other duties of the
                    king. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Servius went forth in the royal robe,
                    accompanied by lictors, and sitting in the king's seat rendered judgment in some
                    cases, while in regard to others he gave out that he would consult the king. In
                    this way for several days after Tarquinius had breathed his last he concealed
                    his death, pretending that he was merely doing another's work, while he was
                    really strengthening his own position; then at last the truth was allowed to be
                    known, from the lamentations which arose within the palace. Servius surrounded
                    himself with a strong guard, and ruled at first without the authorization of the
                    people, but with the consent of the Fathers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The sons of Ancus, upon the arrest of the agents of their crime and the report
                    that the king was alive and that Servius was so strong, had already gone into
                    voluntary exile at Suessa Pometia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Servius now took steps to assure his <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note>
                    position by private as well as public measures. In order that the sons of
                    Tarquinius might not show the same animosity towards himself which the sons of
                    Ancus had felt towards Tarquinius, he married his two daughters to the young
                    princes, Lucius and Arruns Tarquinius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But he
                    could not break the force of destiny by human wisdom; and jealousy of his power,
                    even among the members of his household, created an atmosphere of treachery and
                    hostility. Most opportune for the tranquil preservation <pb n="p.149"/> of the
                    existing state of things was a war which was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> undertaken against the
                    people of Veii —for the truce <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps
                        a reference to the hundred years' truce with Romulus (xv. 5), for Livy has
                        not mentioned any war with Veii in the interval, though one is implied in
                        the statement (xxxiii. 9) that the Veientes surrendered the Maesian Forest,
                        in the reign of Ancus. </note> had now run out —and the other Etruscans.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In this war the bravery and good fortune
                    of Tullius were conspicuous; and when he had utterly defeated the vast army of
                    his enemies, he found on returning to Rome that his title to the kingship was no
                    longer questioned, whether he tested the feeling of the Fathers or that of the
                    commons. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then addressed himself to what is
                    by far the most important work of peace: as Numa had established religious law,
                    so Servius intended that posterity should celebrate himself as the originator of
                    all distinctions among the citizens, and of the orders which clearly
                    differentiate the various grades of rank and fortune. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> For he instituted the census, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The organisation now to be described was primarily
                        designed to increase the fighting strength of Rome. Formerly the right to
                        bear arms had belonged solely to the patricians. Now plebeians were to be
                        given a place in the army, which was to be reclassified according to every
                        man's property, <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> his ability to provide himself
                        a more or less complete equipment for the field. See Dion. Hal. iv. 16-21;
                        Cic. <hi rend="italics">Rep.</hi> ii. 39. </note> a most useful thing for a
                    government destined to such wide dominion, since it would enable the burdens of
                    war and peace to be borne not indiscriminately, as heretofore, but in proportion
                    to men's wealth. He then distributed the people into classes and centuries
                    according to the following scale, which was based upon the census and was
                    suitable either for peace or war: <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Out of those who had a rating of a hundred
                    thousand assess <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Capital, not income.
                        The <hi rend="italics">as</hi> was originally a rod of copper a foot long
                        and divided into twelve inches ( <hi rend="italics">unciae</hi> ). Some time
                        during the regal period weight was substituted for measure in appraising the
                            <hi rend="italics">as,</hi> and it began to be stamped with the figure
                        of an ox, which was the source of the Latin name for money, viz. <hi
                            rend="italics">pecunia.</hi> From being a full pound the <hi
                            rend="italics">as</hi> was gradually reduced, till, in the Second Punic
                        War, it came to weigh only one ounce. What its value may have been in the
                        time of Servius is a highly speculative question. See the note in the
                        edition of Book I. by H. J. Edwards (pp. 179 ff.). </note> or more he made
                    eighty <pb n="p.151"/> centuries, forty each of seniors and of juniors; these
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note>
                    were all known as the first class; the seniors were to be ready to guard the
                    city, the juniors to wage war abroad. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    armour which these men were required to provide consisted of helmet, round
                    shield, greaves, and breast-plate, all of bronze, for the protection of their
                    bodies; their offensive weapons were a spear and a sword. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There were added to this class two centuries of mechanics,
                    who were to serve without arms; to them was entrusted the duty of fashioning
                    siege-engines in war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The second class was
                    drawn up out of those whose rating was between a hundred thousand and
                    seventy-five thousand; of these, seniors and juniors, twenty centuries were
                    enrolled. The arms prescribed for them were an oblong shield in place of the
                    round one, and everything else, save for the breast-plate, as in the class
                    above. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He fixed the rating of the third class
                    at fifty thousand; a like number of centuries was formed in this class as in the
                    second, and with the same distinction of ages; neither was any change made in
                    their arms, except that the greaves were omitted. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> In the fourth class the rating was twenty-five thousand;
                    the same number of centuries was formed, but their equipment was changed,
                    nothing being given them but a spear and a javelin. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The fifth class was made larger, and thirty centuries were
                    formed. These men carried slings, with stones for missiles. Rated with them were
                    the horn-blowers and trumpeters, divided into two centuries. Eleven thousand was
                    the rating of this class. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those who were
                    assessed at less than this amount, being all the rest of the population, were
                    made into a single century, exempt from military service. When the <pb n="p.153"
                    /> equipment and distribution of the infantry had been <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> thus provided for,
                    Servius enrolled twelve centuries of knights out of the leading men of the
                    state. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He likewise formed six other centuries
                    —three had been instituted by Romulus —employing the same names which had been
                    hallowed to their use by augury. For the purchase of horses they were allowed
                    ten thousand asses each from the state treasury, and for the maintenance of
                    these horses unmarried women were designated, who had to pay two thousand asses
                    each, every year. All these burdens were shifted from the shoulders of the poor
                    to those of the rich. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The latter were then
                    granted special privileges: for manhood suffrage, implying equality of power and
                    of rights, was no longer given promiscuously to all, as had been the practice
                    handed down by Romulus and observed by all the other kings; but gradations were
                    introduced, so that ostensibly no one should be excluded from the suffrage, and
                    yet the power should rest with the leading citizens. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> For the knights were called upon to vote first; then the
                    eighty centuries of the first class: if there were any disagreement there, which
                    rarely happened, it was provided that the centuries of the second class should
                    be called; and they almost never descended so far as to reach the lowest
                    citizens. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Nor ought it to cause any surprise
                    that the present organization, which exists since the increase of the tribes to
                    thirty-five, and the doubling of their number in the matter of the junior and
                    senior centuries, does not correspond with the total established by Servius
                    Tullius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For, having divided the City
                    according to its inhabited regions and hills into four parts, he named them
                        <quote>tribes,</quote> a word <pb n="p.155"/> derived, I suppose, from
                        <quote>tribute</quote> ; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Tributum</hi> comes from <hi rend="italics">tribus</hi>
                        (not <hi rend="italics">vice versa,</hi> as Livy has it), which meant
                        originally <quote>third part,</quote> but lost the numerical force and
                        became simply <quote>part,</quote>
                        <quote>district,</quote> like the French <quote>
                            <hi rend="italics">quartier,</hi>
                        </quote> which Walde compares. </note> for this <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> likewise the same king
                    planned to have apportioned equitably, on the basis of the census; nor had these
                    tribes anything whatever to do with the distribution or the number of the
                    centuries. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Upon the completion of the census, which had
                    been expedited by fear of a law that threatened with death and imprisonment
                    those who failed to register, Servius issued a proclamation calling on all Roman
                    citizens, both horse and foot, to assemble at daybreak, each in his own century,
                    in the Campus Martius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There the whole army
                    was drawn up, and a sacrifice of a pig, a sheep, and a bull was offered by the
                    king for its purification. This was termed the <quote>closing of the
                        lustrum,</quote> because it was the last act in the enrolment. Eighty
                    thousand citizens are said to have been registered in that census; the most
                    ancient of the historians, Fabius Pictor, adds that this was the number of those
                    capable of bearing arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To meet the wants of
                    this population it was apparent that the City must expand, and so the king added
                    two hills, the Quirinal and the Viminal, after which he proceeded to enlarge the
                    Esquiline, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Dion. iv. 13, and Strabo,
                        v. 3, 7, make Servius the first to include the Esquiline in the City. Livy
                        appears to have thought of him as merely increasing the extent of that
                        district. Conway and Walters adopt <hi rend="italics">O'</hi> s <hi
                            rend="italics">Viminalemque, Viminalem,</hi> and Gronov's <hi
                            rend="italics">Esquiliis,</hi> thus reconciling Livy with Dion and
                        Strabo. </note> going there to live himself, that the place might obtain a
                    good reputation. He surrounded the City with a rampart, trenches, and a wall,
                    and so extended the <quote>pomerium.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This word is interpreted by those who look
                    only at its etymology as meaning <quote>the tract behind the wall,</quote> but
                    it signifies rather <quote>the tract on both sides of the wall,</quote> the
                    space which the Etruscans used formerly to consecrate with augural <pb n="p.157"
                    /> ceremonies, where they proposed to erect their wall, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> establishing definite
                    limits on either side of it, so that they might at the same time keep the walls
                    free on their inward face from contact with buildings, which now, as a rule, are
                    actually joined to them, and on the outside keep a certain area free from human
                    uses. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This space, which the gods forbade men
                    to inhabit or to till, was called <quote>pomerium</quote> by the Romans, quite
                    as much because the wall stood behind it as because it stood behind the wall;
                    and as the city grew, these consecrated limits were always pushed out for as
                    great a distance as the walls themselves were to be advanced. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Pomerium</hi> at first meant the boundary-line itself,
                        then the strip of land left free within the wall, and finally was loosely
                        used of the strip on both sides of the wall. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the king had promoted the grandeur of the
                    state by enlarging the City, and had shaped all his domestic policy to suit the
                    demands of peace as well as those of war, he was unwilling that arms should
                    always be the means employed for strengthening Rome's power, and sought to
                    increase her sway by diplomacy, and at the same time to add something to the
                    splendour of the City. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Even at that early date
                    the temple of Diana at Ephesus enjoyed great renown. It was reputed to have been
                    built through the cooperation of the cities of Asia, and this harmony and
                    community of worship Servius praised in superlative terms to the Latin nobles,
                    with whom, both officially and in private, he had taken pains to establish a
                    footing of hospitality and friendship. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By dint
                    of reiterating the same arguments he finally carried his point, and a shrine of
                    Diana was built in Rome by the nations of Latium conjointly with the Roman
                    People. This was an admission that Rome was the capital —a point which had so
                    often been disputed <pb n="p.159"/> with force of arms. But though it seemed
                    that the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        578-534</note> Latins had lost all interest in this contention after the
                    repeated failure of their appeals to war, there was one man amongst the Sabines
                    who thought that he saw an opportunity to recover the empire by a shrewd plan of
                    his own. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the Sabine country, on the farm of
                    a certain head of a family, there was born a heifer of extraordinary size and
                    beauty; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> a marvel to which the horns afterwards
                    bore testimony, for they were fastened up for many generations in the vestibule
                    of Diana's temple. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This heifer was regarded as
                    a prodigy, as indeed it was; soothsayers prophesied that the state whose
                    citizens should sacrifice the animal to Diana would be the seat of empire, and
                    this prediction had reached the ears of the priest of Diana's shrine. On the
                    earliest day which seemed suitable for the sacrifice, the Sabine drove the
                    heifer to Rome, and bringing her to the shrine of Diana, led her up to the
                    altar. There the Roman priest, moved by the great size of the victim, which had
                    been much talked of, and recalling the prophecy, asked the Sabine, <quote> What
                        is this that you are doing, stranger? Would you sacrifice, unpurified, to
                        Diana? Not so! First bathe in a running stream; the Tiber flows by in the
                        bottom of the valley. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The stranger, touched by a scruple and wishing
                    to do everything according to ritual, that the prodigy might be answered by the
                    event, at once descended to the Tiber. Meanwhile the Roman offered the heifer to
                    Diana, an act which was exceedingly acceptable to the king and the citizens. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Servius had by this time a definite
                    prescriptive right to the supreme power. Still, hearing <pb n="p.161"/> that the
                    young Tarquinius now and then threw out <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> a hint that he was
                    reigning without the consent of the people, he proceeded to gain the goodwill of
                    the commons by dividing among all the citizens the land obtained by conquest
                    from the enemy; after which he made bold to call upon the people to vote whether
                    he should be their ruler, and was declared king with such unanimity as none of
                    his predecessors had experienced. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Yet the
                    circumstance did not lessen Tarquinius's hopes of obtaining the kingship. On the
                    contrary, perceiving that the bestowal of land on the plebeians was in
                    opposition to the wishes of the senate, he felt that he had got the better
                    opportunity of vilifying Servius to the Fathers and of increasing his own
                    influence in the senate-house. He was a hot-headed youth himself, and he had at
                    hand, in the person of Tullia his wife, one who goaded on his restless spirit.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For the royal house of Rome produced an
                    example of tragic guilt, as others had done, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The reference is to the stories of Atreus and
                        Oedipus.</note> in order that loathing of kings might hasten the coming of
                    liberty, and that the end of reigning might come in that reign which was the
                    fruit of crime. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This Lucius Tarquinius
                    —whether he was the son or the grandson of King Tarquinius Priscus is uncertain;
                    but, following the majority of historians, I would designate him son —had a
                    brother, Arruns Tarquinius, a youth of a gentle disposition. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> These two, as has been said before, had married the two
                    Tullias, daughters of the king, themselves of widely different characters.
                    Chance had so ordered matters that the two violent natures should not be united
                    in wedlock, thanks doubtless to the good fortune of the Roman People, that the
                    reign of Servius might be prolonged and the traditions of <pb n="p.163"/> the
                    state become established. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was distressing
                    to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note>
                    the headstrong Tullia that her husband should be destitute of ambition and
                    enterprise. With her whole soul she turned from him to his brother; him she
                    admired, him she called a man and a prince: she despised her sister because,
                    having got a man for a mate, she lacked a woman's daring. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Their similarity soon brought these two together, as is
                    generally the case, for evil is strongly drawn to evil; but it was the woman who
                    took the lead in all the mischief. Having become addicted to clandestine
                    meetings with another's husband, she spared no terms of insult when speaking of
                    her own husband to his brother, or of her sister to that sister's husband. She
                    urged that it would have been juster for her to be unmarried and for him to lack
                    a wife than for them to be united to their inferiors and be compelled to
                    languish through the cowardice of others. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If
                    the gods had given her the man she deserved she would soon have seen in her own
                    house the royal power which she now saw in <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> her
                    father's. It was not long before she had inspired the young man with her own
                    temerity, and, having made room in their respective houses for a new marriage,
                    by deaths which followed closely upon one another, they were joined together in
                    nuptials which Servius rather tolerated than approved. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From that moment the insecurity of the aged
                    Tullius and the menace to his authority increased with each succeeding day. For
                    the woman was already looking forward from one crime to another, nor would she
                    allow her husband any rest by night or day, lest the murders they had done
                    before should be without effect. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> She had not
                    wanted a <pb n="p.165"/> man just to be called a wife, just to endure <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note>
                    servitude with him in silence; she had wanted one who should deem himself worthy
                    of the sovereignty, who bethought him that he was the son of Tarquinius Priscus,
                    who preferred the possession of the kingship to the hope of it. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>If you are he,</quote> she cried, <quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">whom</hi> I thought I was marrying, I call you both man
                        and king; if not, then I have so far changed for the worse, in that crime is
                        added, in your case, to cowardice. Come, rouse yourself! <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> You are not come, like your father, from Corinth or
                        Tarquinii, that you must make yourself king in a strange land; the gods of
                        your family and your ancestors, your father's image, the royal palace, with
                        its throne, and the name of Tarquinius create and proclaim you king. Else,
                        if you have no courage for this, why do you cheat the citizens? why do you
                        suffer yourself to be looked on as a prince? Away with you to Tarquinii or
                        Corinth! <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Sink back into the rank of your
                        family, more like your brother than your father! </quote> With these and
                    other taunts she excited the young man's ambition. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Nor could she herself submit with patience to the thought
                    that Tanaquil, a foreign woman, had exerted her spirit to such purpose as twice
                    in succession to confer the royal power —upon her husband first, and again upon
                    her son-in-law — if Tullia, the daughter of a king, were to count for nothing in
                    bestowing and withdrawing a throne. Inspired by this woman's frenzy Tarquinius
                    began to go about and solicit support, especially among the heads of the lesser
                    families, whom he reminded of his father's kindness to them, and desired their
                    favour in return; the young men he attracted by gifts; both by the great things
                    he promised to do <pb n="p.167"/> himself, and by slandering the king as well,
                    he <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note>
                    everywhere strengthened his interest. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At
                    length, when it seemed that the time for action was now come, he surrounded
                    himself with a body of armed men and burst into the Forum. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then, amidst the general consternation which ensued, he
                    seated himself on the throne in front of the Curia, and commanded, by the mouth
                    of a herald, that the senators should come to King Tarquinius at the
                    senate-house. They at once assembled: some of them already prepared beforehand,
                    others afraid that they might be made to suffer for it if they did not come; for
                    they were astounded at this strange and wonderful sight, and supposed that
                    Servius was utterly undone. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Tarquinius then
                    went back to the very beginning of Servius's family and abused the king for a
                    slave and a slave-woman's son who, after the shameful death of his own father,
                    Tarquinius Priscus, had seized the power; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    there had been no observance of the interregnum, as on former occasions; there
                    had been no election held; not by the votes of the people had sovereignty come
                    to him, not with the confirmation of the Fathers, but by a woman's gift.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such having been his birth, and such his
                    appointment to the kingship, he had been an abettor of the lowest class of
                    society, to which he himself belonged, and his hatred of the nobility possessed
                    by others had led him to plunder the leading citizens of their land and divide
                    it amongst the dregs of the populace. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> All the
                    burdens which had before been borne in common he had laid upon the nation's
                    foremost men. He had instituted the census that he might hold up to envy the
                    fortunes of the wealthy, and make them available, when he chose to draw upon
                    them, for largesses to the destitute. </p>
                <pb n="p.169"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the midst of this harangue Servius, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> who
                    had been aroused by the alarming news, came up and immediately called out in a
                    loud voice from the vestibule of the Curia: <quote> What means this, Tarquinius?
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With what assurance have you dared,
                        while I live, to convene the Fathers or to sit in my chair? </quote>
                    Tarquinius answered truculently that it was his own father's seat he occupied;
                    that the king's son was a fitter successor to his kingdom than a slave was; that
                    Tullius had long enough been suffered to mock his masters and insult them.
                    Shouts arose from the partisans of each, and the people began to rush into the
                    senate-house; it was clear that he would be king who won the day. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Tarquinius was now compelled by sheer necessity to go
                    on boldly to the end. Being much superior to Servius in youth and strength, he
                    seized him by the middle, and bearing him out of the senate-house, flung him
                    down the steps. He then went back into the Curia to hold the senate together.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king's servitors and companions fled.
                    The king himself, half fainting, was making his way home without the royal
                    attendants, when the men whom Tarquinius had sent in pursuit of the fugitive
                    came up with him and killed him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It is
                    believed, inasmuch as it is not inconsistent with the rest of her wickedness,
                    that this deed was suggested by Tullia. It is agreed, at all events, that she
                    was driven in her carriage into the Forum, and nothing abashed at the crowd of
                    men, summoned her husband from the Curia and was the first to hail him king.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Tarquinius bade her withdraw from so
                    turbulent a scene. On her way home she had got to the top of the Vicus Cyprius,
                    where the shrine of Diana recently stood, and was bidding her driver <pb
                        n="p.171"/> turn to the right into the Clivus Urbius, to take her <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 578-534</note> to the
                    Esquiline Hill, when the man gave a start of terror, and pulling up the reins
                    pointed out to his mistress the prostrate form of the murdered Servius.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Horrible and inhuman was the crime that is
                    said to have ensued, which the place commemorates —men call it the Street of
                    Crime —for there, crazed by the avenging spirits of her sister and her former
                    husband, they say that Tullia drove her carriage over her father's corpse, and,
                    herself contaminated and defiled, carried away on her vehicle some of her
                    murdered father's blood to her own and her husband's penates, whose anger was
                    the cause that the evil beginning of this reign was, at no long date, followed
                    by a similar end. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Servius Tullius had ruled forty-four years, so
                    well that even a good and moderate successor would have found it hard to emulate
                    him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But there was this to enhance his renown,
                    that just and lawful kingship perished with him. Yet, mild and moderate though
                    his sway was, some writers state that he had intended to resign it, as being a
                    government by one man, had not the crime of one of his family interrupted his
                    plans for the liberation of his country. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now began the reign of Lucius Tarquinius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    whose conduct procured him the surname of Superbus, or the Proud. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For he denied the rites of sepulture to his own
                    father-in-law, asserting that Romulus had also perished without burial. He put
                    to death the leading senators, whom he believed to have favoured the cause of
                    Servius and, conscious that a precedent for gaining the kingship by crime might
                    be found in his own career and turned against himself, he <pb n="p.173"/>
                    assumed a body-guard. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He had indeed no right
                    to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    the throne but might, since he was ruling neither by popular decree nor
                    senatorial sanction. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Moreover, as he put no
                    trust in the affection of his people, he was compelled to safeguard his
                    authority by fear. To inspire terror therefore in many persons, he adopted the
                    practice of trying capital causes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> causes affecting the <hi rend="italics"
                            >caput</hi> (which might mean either <quote>life</quote> or <quote>civic
                            rights</quote> ) of the accused. </note> by himself, without advisers;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and, under the pretext thus afforded, was
                    able to inflict death, exile, and forfeiture of property, not only upon persons
                    whom he suspected and disliked, but also in cases where he could have nothing to
                    gain but plunder. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was chiefly the senators
                    whose numbers were reduced by this procedure, and Tarquinius determined to make
                    no new appointments to the order, that it might be the more despised for its
                    very paucity, and might chafe less at being ignored in all business of state.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For this king was the first to break with
                    the custom handed down by his predecessors, of consulting the senate on all
                    occasions, and governed the nation without other advice than that of his own
                    household. War, peace, treaties, and alliances were entered upon or broken off
                    by the monarch himself, with whatever states he wished, and without the decree
                    of people or senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Latin race he strove
                    particularly to make his friends, that his strength abroad might contribute to
                    his security at home. He contracted with their nobles not only relations of
                    hospitality but also matrimonial connections. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    To Octavius Mamilius of Tusculum, a man by long odds the most important of the
                    Latin name, and descended, if we may believe report, from Ulysses and the
                    goddess Circe, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Circe bore to Ulysses
                        a son, Telegonus, who founded Tusculum. </note> he gave his daughter in
                    marriage, and in this way attached to himself the numerous kinsmen and friends
                    of the man. </p>
                <pb n="p.175"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tarquinius had already won great influence
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    with the Latin nobles, when he gave notice that they should assemble on a
                    certain day at the grove of Ferentina, saying that there were matters of common
                    interest which he wished to discuss. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    Latins gathered at daybreak in large numbers; Tarquinius himself, though he did
                    indeed keep the day, arrived but a little while before sundown. There had been
                    much talk in the council all day about various subjects. Turnus Herdonius of
                    Aricia had inveighed violently against the absent Tarquinius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He said it was no wonder he had been given the name of
                    Superbus at Rome —for that was the name by which they already called him,
                    secretly and in whispers, but still quite generally; —could anything be more
                    overbearing than to flout the whole Latin race as he was doing then? <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Their leaders had been summoned from distant homes,
                    and the very man who had called the council was not there. He was evidently
                    trying their patience, intending, if they submitted to the yoke, to use them as
                    his vassals. For who could fail to see that he was aiming at sovereignty over
                    the Latins? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If his own people had done well to
                    intrust this to him, if indeed it had been intrusted to him at all, and had not
                    been ravished by foul murder, then it was right that the Latins also should
                    intrust it to him —nay, <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> not even then, for he
                    was of foreign birth; but if his own subjects were weary of him, as men who, one
                    after another, were being made to suffer death, exile, confiscation, what better
                    prospect was held out to the Latins? If they were guided by the speaker they
                    would depart every man to his own home, nor observe the day of meeting more than
                    he who had proclaimed it was observing it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As
                    these <pb n="p.177"/> words and others of the same import were being <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    uttered by the factious and turbulent Latin, who owed to these qualities his
                    influence amongst his own people, Tarquinius came up. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> This was the end of the speech; all turned to salute
                    Tarquinius. Silence was commanded, and the king, being advised by those nearest
                    him to excuse himself for having come so late, declared that he had been chosen
                    arbiter between a father and his son, and had been delayed by his anxiety to
                    reconcile them. He added that since this business had used up that day, he would
                    take up on the morrow the matters which he had meant to bring before them.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They say that Turnus would not suffer even
                    this to go unchallenged, asserting that there was no question more quickly
                    settled than one betwixt father and son, for these few words were enough to end
                    it: <quote>Unless you obey your father it will be the worse for you.</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Girding thus against the Roman king, the
                    Arician quitted the council. Tarquinius was considerably more vexed than he
                    appeared to be, and at once looked about him for the means of destroying Turnus,
                    that he might inspire in the Latins the same terror with which he had broken the
                    spirit of the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And since he could not
                    openly put his man to death by virtue of sovereign right, he charged him with a
                    crime of which he was innocent, and so destroyed him. Through the agency of
                    certain men of the opposite party in Aricia, he bribed a slave of Turnus with
                    gold to allow a large quantity of swords to be brought secretly into his
                    master's lodging. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Having accomplished this in
                    a single night, Tarquinius, shortly before dawn, summoned the chief men of the
                    Latins to his quarters, pretending to <pb n="p.179"/> have received alarming
                    news, and informed them <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 534-510</note> that his tardiness on the preceding day, as though
                    somehow providentially occasioned, had been the means of saving himself and
                    them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For he was told that Turnus was plotting
                    his murder and that of the chief men of the different cities, that he might be
                    sole ruler over the Latins. He would have attacked them the day before in the
                    council, but had postponed the attempt because the summoner of the council, whom
                    he chiefly aimed at, was not there. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That was
                    the reason Turnus had railed at him in his absence, for his delay had balked the
                    Arician's expectation. Tarquinius said that he had no doubt, if his information
                    was true, that Turnus would come at dawn, when they had assembled in the
                    council, and would be armed and attended by a band of conspirators. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> It was said that a great quantity of swords had been
                    carried to his lodging; the falsity or truth of this could be ascertained
                    immediately, and he asked them to go with him to Turnus's quarters. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The charge was made plausible both by the aggressive
                    spirit of Turnus and his speech of the day before, and by Tarquinius's delay,
                    since it seemed that the massacre might have been postponed on that account. The
                    nobles went therefore with a disposition to believe the story, but still, if the
                    swords should not be found, they were prepared to conclude the other charges
                    false. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as they reached the place they
                    wakened Turnus from his sleep and surrounded him with guards; and having
                    overpowered the slaves, who out of affection for their master would have
                    resorted to force, they proceeded to pull out the hidden swords from every
                    corner of the inn. There was now no doubt that Turnus was <pb n="p.181"/> caught
                    in the act, and he was cast into chains, while <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note> the summons was
                    instantly sent out, amidst intense excitement, for a council of the Latins.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There such bitter resentment was aroused
                    by the public display of the swords, that the accused was not permitted to plead
                    his cause, but suffered a new kind of death, being plunged into the source of
                    the Ferentine Water and sunk beneath a wicker crate heaped up with stones. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tarquinius then called the Latins again to the
                    place of council, and praised them for the punishment which they had justly
                    meted out to the rebellious attempt of Turnus, in view of the treason in which
                    he had just been taken. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king then went on
                    to say that it was in his power to proceed according to an ancient right, since
                    all the Latins, having sprung from Alba, were included in that treaty by which,
                    from the time of Tullus, the whole Alban state, with its colonies, had come
                    under Rome's dominion. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the account
                        of this treaty at xxiv. 3 no Alban colonies are mentioned, nor do we know of
                        any. Conway and Walters, therefore, keep <hi rend="italics">colonis</hi> of
                        the MSS., but we should rather expect <hi rend="italics">civibus</hi> in
                        this context. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the advantage of all would be better
                    served, he thought, if that treaty were renewed and the good fortune of the
                    Roman people were thrown open to the participation of the Latins, than if they
                    were always to be dreading or enduring the razing of their cities and the
                    devastation of their lands which they had suffered first in Ancus's reign and
                    afterward in that of the speaker's father. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                    was not difficult to persuade the Latins, although the Roman interest
                    preponderated in this treaty. For the rest, they saw that the chiefs of the
                    Latin name stood with the king and took his view of the matter, and they had
                    just been given a demonstration of the danger they would each incur if they
                    opposed the project. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So the treaty was
                    renewed, and the Latin <pb n="p.183"/> juniors were commanded to present
                    themselves at <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        534-510</note> the grove of Ferentina on a certain day, armed and in full
                    force, as the treaty prescribed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they had
                    assembled, agreeably to the king's edict, from the different districts,
                    Tarquinius was unwilling that they should have their own leaders, or a separate
                    command, or their own standards; he therefore mingled Latins and Romans in the
                    maniples, making one maniple of two and two of one, and over the maniples thus
                    doubled he put centurions. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A Roman
                        maniple was divided into halves, and each half was combined with the half of
                        a Latin maniple, similarly divided, to form a new unit. The maniples were
                        not, strictly speaking, doubled. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But if the king was unjust in peace, yet he
                    was not a bad general in war. Indeed, he would have equalled in this art the
                    kings who had gone before him, if his degeneracy in other things had not also
                    dimmed his glory here. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was he who began the
                    war with the Volsci which was to last more than two hundred years after his
                    time, and took Suessa Pometia from them by storm. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There, having sold off the booty and raised forty talents
                    of silver, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As Livy gives the sum in
                        talents, it has been suggested that he may here be following Fabius Pictor,
                        whose history was written in Greek. The Euboic talent was worth roughly £220
                        or $1,060. </note> he conceived the project of a temple of Jupiter so
                    magnificent that it should be worthy of the king of gods and men, the Roman
                    empire, and the majesty of the site itself. The money from the captured city he
                    put aside to build this temple. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then engaged in an unexpectedly tedious war
                    with Gabii, a neighbouring town After first assaulting the place in vain, he
                    laid siege to it, but this attempt was as unsuccessful as the other, for he was
                    driven off from the walls; and he finally resorted to the policy, so unlike a
                    Roman, of deceit <pb n="p.185"/> and trickery. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For he pretended to have given up <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note> the war and to be engrossed in laying the
                    foundations of his temple and in other city works, arranging meanwhile to let
                    Sextus, who was the youngest of his three sons, desert to Gabii, and there
                    complain that his father was intolerably cruel to him. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> His father's pride, he said, was now diverted from
                    strangers upon his own family. Even his children were too many to please him,
                    and the solitude which he had caused in the senate-house he wished to bring to
                    pass in his own home also, that he might leave no descendant, no heir to his
                    kingdom. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The young man said that he had
                    himself escaped from amidst the swords and javelins of his father, and had made
                    up his mind that there was no safety for him anywhere save with the enemies of
                    Lucius Tarquinius. Let them not delude themselves, he said; the war which the
                    king pretended to have abandoned was still awaiting them, and when the chance
                    offered he would attack them unawares. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But if
                    they had no room for suppliants, he was prepared to wander all over Latium, and
                    thence seek out the Volsci and the Aequi and the Hernici, till at last he should
                    come to people who knew how to protect a son from the cruel and wicked tortures
                    inflicted on him by a father. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Possibly he
                    might even discover some enthusiasm for war and arms against the haughtiest of
                    kings and the most insolent of nations. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When
                    it appeared that if they were indifferent he would leave them in anger and
                    continue his flight, the Gabini bade him welcome. They told him not to be
                    surprised if the king had been the same to his children that he had been to his
                    subjects, to his allies; he would end by venting his cruelty upon <pb n="p.187"
                    /> himself if other objects failed him. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But
                    for their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        534-510</note> own part, they said, they were glad of his coming, and they
                    believed that in a short time, with his help, the seat of war would be shifted
                    from the gates of Gabii to the walls of Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Sextus next obtained admission to the Gabian
                    councils of state, where, on all subjects but one, he professed a deference for
                    the opinion of those who had long been citizens of Gabii and were better
                    acquainted with the facts. War, however, he did take it upon himself to urge,
                    again and again; and in so doing he assumed a special competence, as one who was
                    acquainted with the strength of both nations, and knew that the king's pride
                    must necessarily be hateful to all the citizens, since even his children had not
                    been able to put up with it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this way,
                    little by little, he stirred up the leaders of the Gabini to reopen the war. He
                    would himself take the boldest of the young men and go upon raids and forays.
                    All his words and acts were calculated to deceive, and their ill-grounded
                    confidence so increased that in the end he was chosen commander-in-chief.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The war began, and the people had no
                    suspicion of what was going forward. Skirmishes took place between Rome and
                    Gabii, in which, as a rule, the Gabini had the best of it. Thereupon their
                    citizens, both high and low, contended who should be loudest in expressing the
                    belief that in Sextus Tarquinius they had a heaven-sent leader. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> And the soldiers, seeing him ever ready to share in their
                    dangers and hardships, and ever lavish in distributing the plunder, came to love
                    him so devotedly that the elder Tarquinius was not more truly master <pb
                        n="p.189"/> in Rome than was his son in Gabii. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> And so, when <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note> Sextus saw that he had acquired strength
                    enough for any enterprise, he despatched one of his own followers to his father
                    in Rome, to ask what the king might please to have him do, since the gods had
                    granted that at Gabii all power in the state should rest with him alone.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To this messenger, I suppose because he
                    seemed not quite to be trusted, no verbal reply was given. The king, as if
                    absorbed in meditation, passed into the garden of his house, followed by his
                    son's envoy. There, walking up and down without a word, he is said to have
                    struck off the heads of the tallest poppies with his stick. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Tired of asking questions and waiting for an answer, the
                    messenger returned to Gabii, his mission, as he thought, unaccomplished. He
                    reported what he had said himself and what he had seen. Whether from anger, or
                    hatred, or native pride, the king, he said, had not pronounced a single word.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as it was clear to Sextus what his
                    father meant and what was the purport of his silent hints, he rid himself of the
                    chief men of the state. Some he accused before the people; against others he
                    took advantage of the odium they had themselves incurred. Many were openly
                    executed; some, whom it would not have looked well to accuse, were put to death
                    in secret. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some were permitted, if they chose,
                    to leave the country; or they were driven into banishment, and once out of the
                    way, their property was forfeited, just as in the case of those who had been put
                    to death. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thence came largesses and spoils,
                    and in the sweetness of private gain men lost their feeling for the wrongs of
                    the nation, until, deprived of counsel and aid, the state of Gabii was handed
                    over unresisting to the Roman king. </p>
                <pb n="p.191"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having got possession of Gabii, Tarquinius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    made peace with the Aequian nation and renewed the treaty with the Etruscans. He
                    next turned his attention to affairs in the city. Here his first concern was to
                    build a temple of Jupiter on the Tarpeian Mount <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Capitoline. So Propertius calls the
                        Capitoline Jupiter <quote>Tarpeius Pater</quote> (IV. i. 7). </note> to
                    stand as a memorial of his reign and of his name, testifying that of the two
                    Tarquinii, both kings, the father had made the vow and the son had fulfilled it.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And that the site might be free from all
                    other religious claims and belong wholly to Jupiter and his temple, which was
                    building there, he determined to annul the consecration of several fanes and
                    shrines which had been first vowed by King Tatius at the crisis of the battle
                    against Romulus, and had afterwards been consecrated and inaugurated. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> At the very time when he began this task the gods are
                    said to have exerted their power to show the magnitude of this mighty empire.
                    For whereas the birds permitted that the consecrations of all the other shrines
                    should be rescinded, they refused their consent for the shrine of Terminus.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This omen and augury was thus construed:
                    the fact that the seat of Terminus was not moved, and that of all the gods he
                    alone was not called away from the place consecrated to him, meant that the
                    whole kingdom would be firm and steadfast. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    When this auspice of permanence had been received, there followed another
                    prodigy foretelling the grandeur of their empire. A human head, its features
                    intact, was found, so it is said, by the men who were digging for the
                    foundations of the temple. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This appearance
                    plainly foreshowed that here was to be the citadel of the empire and the head of
                    the world, and such was the interpretation of the soothsayers, both those who
                    were in <pb n="p.193"/> the City and those who were called in from Etruria <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note> to
                    consider the matter. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This made the king all
                    the more ready to spend money on the work. Hence the Pometian spoils, which had
                    been destined to carry the building up to the roof, barely sufficed for the
                    foundations. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This disposes me to believe the
                    statement of Fabius (who is, besides, the earlier writer) that the spoils were
                    only forty talents, rather than Piso's, who writes that forty thousand pounds of
                    silver were put aside for this work. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So great
                    a sum of money could not be expected from the booty of a single city of that
                    time, and there is no building, even among those of our own day, for the
                    foundations of which it would not be more than enough. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Being intent upon completing the temple, the
                    king called in workmen from every quarter of Etruria, and used for this purpose
                    not only the state funds but labourers drawn from the commons. This work was far
                    from light in itself, and was added to their military service. Yet the plebeians
                    felt less abused at having to build with their own hands the temples of the
                    gods, than they did when they came to be transferred to other tasks also, which,
                    while less in show, were yet rather more laborious. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> I mean the erection of seats in the circus, and the
                    construction underground of the Great Sewer, as a receptacle for all the
                    offscourings of the City, —two works for which the new splendour of these days
                    has scarcely been able to produce a match. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    After making the plebeians toil at these hard tasks, the king felt that a
                    populace which had now no work to do was only a burden to the City; he wished,
                    moreover, by sending out settlers, to extend the frontiers of his dominions.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.195"/> He therefore sent colonists to Signia and Circei, to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    safeguard the City by land and sea. </p>
                <p> While he was thus occupied, a terrible portent appeared. A snake glided out of a
                    wooden pillar, causing fright and commotion in the palace. As for the king
                    himself, his heart was not so much struck with sudden terror as filled with
                    anxious forebodings. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Now for public prodigies
                    none but Etruscan soothsayers were wont to be employed, but this domestic
                    apparition, as he regarded it, so thoroughly alarmed him that he determined to
                    send to Delphi, the most famous oracle in the world; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and, not daring to trust the oracle's reply to anybody
                    else, he sent two of his sons, through strange lands, as they were then, and
                    over stranger seas, to Greece. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Titus and
                    Arruns were the ones who went; and, to bear them company, Lucius Junius Brutus
                    was sent too, the son of Tarquinia, sister of the king, a young man of a very
                    different mind from that which he pretended to bear. Having heard that the
                    leading men of the state, and among them his own brother, had been put to death
                    by his uncle, he determined to leave nothing in his disposition which the king
                    might justly fear, nor anything in his fortune to covet, resolving to find
                    safety in contempt, where justice afforded no protection. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore deliberately assumed the appearance of
                    stupidity, and permitted himself and his property to become the spoil of the
                    king; he even accepted the surname Brutus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Literally <quote>Dullard.</quote>
                    </note> that behind the screen afforded by this title the great soul which was
                    to free the Roman People might bide its time unseen. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He it was who was then taken by the Tarquinii to Delphi,
                    more as a butt than as a comrade; and he is said to have carried a golden staff
                    inclosed within one <pb n="p.197"/> of cornel wood, hollowed out to receive it,
                    as a gift <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        534-510</note> to Apollo, and a roundabout indication of his own character.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When they came there, and had carried out
                    their father's instructions, a desire sprang up in the hearts of the youths to
                    find out which one of them should be king at Rome. From the depths of the cavern
                    this answer, they say, was returned: <quote> The highest power at Rome shall be
                        his, young men, who shall be first among you to kiss his mother. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Tarquinii, anxious that Sextus, who had
                    been left in Rome, might know nothing of the answer and have no share in the
                    rule, gave orders that the incident should be kept strictly secret; as between
                    themselves, they decided by lot which should be first, upon their return to
                    Rome, to give their mother a kiss. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Brutus
                    thought the Pythian utterance had another meaning; pretending to stumble, he
                    fell and touched his lips to Earth, evidently regarding her as the common mother
                    of all mortals. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They then returned to Rome,
                    where preparations for war with the Rutuli were being pushed with the greatest
                    vigour. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ardea belonged to the Rutuli, who were a
                    nation of commanding wealth, for that place and period. This very fact was the
                    cause of the war, since the Roman king was eager not only to enrich himself,
                    impoverished as he was by the splendour of his public works, but also to appease
                    with booty the feeling of the common people; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    who, besides the enmity they bore the monarch for other acts of pride, were
                    especially resentful that the king should have kept them employed so long as
                    artisans and doing the work of slaves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> An
                    attempt was made to capture Ardea by assault. Having failed in this, the Romans
                    invested <pb n="p.199"/> the place with intrenchments, and began to beleaguer
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here in their permanent camp, as is
                    usual with a war not sharp but long drawn out, furlough was rather freely
                    granted, more freely however to the leaders than to the soldiers; the young
                    princes for their part passed their idle hours together at dinners and drinking
                    bouts. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It chanced, as they were drinking in
                    the quarters of Sextus Tarquinius, where Tarquinius Collatinus, son of Egerius,
                    was also a guest, that the subject of wives came up. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Every man fell to praising his own wife with enthusiasm,
                    and, as their rivalry grew hot, Collatinus said that there was no need to talk
                    about it, for it was in their power to know, in a few hours' time, how far the
                    rest were excelled by his own Lucretia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Come! If the vigour of youth is in us let us mount our horses and see
                        for ourselves the disposition of our wives. Let every man regard as the
                        surest test what meets his eyes when the woman's husband enters unexpected.
                    </quote> They were heated with wine. <quote>Agreed!</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> they all cried, and clapping spurs to their
                    horses were off for Rome. Arriving there at early dusk, they thence proceeded to
                    Collatia, where Lucretia was discovered very differently employed from the
                    daughters-in-law of the king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These they had
                    seen at a luxurious banquet, whiling away the time with their young friends; but
                    Lucretia, though it was late at night, was busily engaged upon her wool, while
                    her maidens toiled about her in the lamplight as she sat in the hall of her
                    house. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A similar scene is imagined by
                        Tibullus, I. iii. 83 ff. (p. 211 of the volume in this series). </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The prize of this contest in womanly virtues
                    fell to Lucretia. As Collatinus and the Tarquinii approached, they were
                    graciously received, and the victorious husband courteously invited the young
                    princes to his table. It was there <pb n="p.201"/> that Sextus Tarquinius was
                    seized with a wicked desire <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note> to debauch Lucretia by force; not only her
                    beauty, but her proved chastity as well, provoked him. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> However, for the present they ended the boyish prank of the
                    night and returned to the camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When a few days had gone by, Sextus
                    Tarquinius, without letting Collatinus know, took a single attendant and went to
                    Collatia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Being kindly welcomed, for no one
                    suspected his purpose, he was brought after dinner to a guest-chamber. Burning
                    with passion, he waited till it seemed to him that all about him was secure and
                    everybody fast asleep; then, drawing his sword, he came to the sleeping
                    Lucretia. Holding the woman down with his left hand on her breast, he said,
                        <quote> Be still, Lucretia! I am Sextus Tarquinius. My sword is in my hand.
                        Utter a sound, and you die! </quote> In affright the woman started out of
                    her sleep. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> No help was in sight, but only
                    imminent death. Then Tarquinius began to declare his love, to plead, to mingle
                    threats with prayers, to bring every resource to bear upon her woman's heart.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he found her obdurate and not to be
                    moved even by fear of death, he went farther and threatened her with disgrace,
                    saying that when she was dead he would kill his slave and lay him naked by her
                    side, that she might be said to have been put to death in adultery with a man of
                    base condition. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At this dreadful prospect her
                    resolute modesty was overcome, as if with force, by his victorious lust; and
                    Tarquinius departed, exulting in his conquest of a woman's honour. Lucretia,
                    grieving at her great disaster, dispatched the same message to her father in
                    Rome and to her husband at Ardea: <pb n="p.203"/> that they should each take a
                    trusty friend and come; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 534-510</note> that they must do this and do it quickly, for a
                    frightful thing had happened. Spurius Lucretius came with Publius Valerius,
                    Volesus' son. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Collatinus brought Lucius Junius
                    Brutus, with whom he chanced to be returning to Rome when he was met by the
                    messenger from his wife. Lucretia they found sitting sadly in her chamber. The
                    entrance of her friends brought the tears to her eyes, and to her husband's
                    question, <quote>Is all well?</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> she replied, <quote> Far from it; for what can
                        be well with a woman when she has lost her honour? The print of a strange
                        man, Collatinus, is in your bed. Yet my body only has been violated; my
                        heart is guiltless, as death shall be my witness. But pledge your right
                        hands and your words that the adulterer shall not go unpunished. Sextus
                        Tarquinius is he that last night returned hostility for hospitality, and
                        armed with force brought ruin on me, and on himself no less —if you are men
                        —when he worked his pleasure with me. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They give their pledges, every man in turn.
                    They seek to comfort her, sick at heart as she is, by diverting the blame from
                    her who was forced to the doer of the wrong. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    They tell her it is the mind that sins, not the body; and that where purpose has
                    been wanting there is no guilt. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>It is for you to determine,</quote> she answers, <quote> what is due to
                        him; for my own part, though I acquit myself of the sin, I do not absolve
                        myself from punishment; not in time to come shall ever unchaste woman live
                        through the example of Lucretia. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Taking a knife which she had concealed
                    beneath her dress, she plunged it into her heart, and sinking forward upon the
                    wound, died as she fell. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The wail for the
                    dead was raised by her husband and her father. </p>
                <pb n="p.205"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Brutus, while the others were absorbed in
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 534-510</note>
                    grief, drew out the knife from Lucretia's wound, and holding it up, dripping
                    with gore, exclaimed, <quote> By this blood, most chaste until a prince wronged
                        it, I swear, and I take you, gods, to witness, that I will pursue Lucius
                        Tarquinius Superbus and his wicked wife and all his children, with sword,
                        with fire, aye with whatsoever violence I may; and that I will suffer
                        neither them nor any other to be king in Rome! </quote> The knife he then
                    passed to Collatinus, and from him to Lucretius and Valerius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They were dumbfounded at this miracle. Whence came this new
                    spirit in the breast of Brutus? As he bade them, so they swore. Grief was
                    swallowed up in anger; and when Brutus summoned them to make war from that very
                    moment on the power of the kings, they followed his lead. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They carried out Lucretia's corpse from the house and bore
                    it to the market-place, where men crowded about them, attracted, as they were
                    bound to be, by the amazing character of the strange event and its heinousness.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Every man had his own complaint to make of
                    the prince's crime and his violence. They were moved, not only by the father's
                    sorrow, but by the fact that it was Brutus who chid their tears and idle
                    lamentations and urged them .to take up the sword, as befitted men and Romans,
                    against those who had dared to treat them as enemies. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The boldest of the young men seized their weapons and
                    offered themselves for service, and the others followed their example. Then,
                    leaving Lucretia's father to guard Collatia, and posting sentinels so that no
                    one might announce the rising to the royal family, the rest, equipped for battle
                    and with Brutus in command, set out for Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Once there, wherever their armed <pb n="p.207"/> band advanced it brought terror
                    and confusion; but. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        534-510</note> again, when people saw that in the van were the chief men of
                    the state, they concluded that whatever it was it could be no meaningless
                    disturbance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And in fact there was no less
                    resentment at Rome when this dreadful story was known than there had been at
                    Collatia. So from every quarter of the City men came running to the Forum. No
                    sooner were they there than a crier summoned the people before the Tribune of
                    the Celeres, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the <hi
                            rend="italics">Celeres,</hi> see xv. 8 and note. H. J. Edwards ( <hi
                            rend="italics">ad</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">loc.</hi> ) thinks that the office comprised both
                        military and civil functions-the command of the cavalry ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >cf.</hi> the <hi rend="italics">Magister</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">Equitum</hi> in republican times) and the presidency (as
                        deputy of the king) of comitia and senate. </note> which office Brutus then
                    happened to be holding. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There he made a speech
                    by no means like what might have been expected of the mind and the spirit which
                    he had feigned up to that day. He spoke of the violence and lust of Sextus
                    Tarquinius, of the shameful defilement of Lucretia and her deplorable death, of
                    the bereavement of Tricipitinus, in whose eyes the death of his daughter was not
                    so outrageous and deplorable as was the cause of her death. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He reminded them, besides, of the pride of the king himself
                    and the wretched state of the commons, who were plunged into ditches and sewers
                    and made to clear them out. The men of Rome, he said, the conquerors of all the
                    nations round about, had been transformed from warriors into artisans and
                    stone-cutters. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He spoke of the shameful
                    murder of King Tullius, and how his daughter had driven her accursed chariot
                    over her father's body, and he invoked the gods who punish crimes against
                    parents. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> With these and, I fancy, even
                    fiercer reproaches, such as occur to a man in the very presence of an outrage,
                    but are far from easy for an historian to reproduce, he inflamed the people, and
                    brought them to abrogate the king's authority and to exile Lucius Tarquinius,
                    together with his wife and children. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Brutus
                    himself then enrolled the juniors, who <pb n="p.209"/> voluntarily gave in their
                    names, and arming them <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 534-510</note> set out for the camp at Ardea to arouse the troops
                    against the king. The command at Rome he left with Lucretius, who had been
                    appointed Prefect of the City by the king, some time before. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> During this confusion Tullia fled from her house, cursed
                    wherever she went by men and women, who called down upon her the furies that
                    avenge the wrongs of kindred. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of these events reached the
                    camp, the king, in alarm at the unexpected danger, set out for Rome to put down
                    the revolt. Brutus, who had perceived the king's approach, made a circuit to
                    avoid meeting him, and at almost the same moment, though by different roads,
                    Brutus reached Ardea and Tarquinius Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Against Tarquinius the gates were closed and exile was pronounced. The liberator
                    of the City was received with rejoicings in the camp, and the sons of the king
                    were driven out of it. Two of them followed their father, and went into exile at
                    Caere, in Etruria. Sextus Tarquinius departed for Gabii, as though it had been
                    his own kingdom, and there the revengers of old quarrels, which he had brought
                    upon himself by murder and rapine, slew him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Lucius Tarquinius Superbus ruled for five and
                    twenty years. The rule of the kings at Rome, from its foundation to its
                    liberation, lasted two hundred and forty-four years. Two consuls were then
                    chosen in the centuriate comitia, under the presidency of the Prefect of the
                    City, in accordance with the commentaries of Servius Tullius. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <quote>consuls,</quote> as they
                        were called from the time of the Decemvirate, were originally designated
                            <quote>praetors</quote> ; Livy is anachronistic. The <quote>centuriate
                            comitia</quote> was the assembly of the people by centuries, as
                        classified by Servius, primarily for military ends. It is more likely that
                        Lucretius presided over the election in the capacity of interrex (to which
                        office Dion. iv. 84 says Lucretius was appointed by Brutus) than in that of
                        prefect. </note> These were Lucius Junius Brutus and Lucius Tarquinius
                    Collatinus. </p>
                <pb n="p.211"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
