<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fescennine Verses in Honour of the Marriage of the Emperor Honorius</title>
            <author>Claudianus, Claudius</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. I</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date type="printing">1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian02clau#page/230/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">    
            <state unit="poem"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa007.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.231" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="poem" n="1" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>FESCENNINE VERSES I</head>
         <p>

Prince fairer than the day star who shootest thine
arrows with an aim more sure than the Parthian's
rider more daring than the Geloni, what praise 
shall match thy lofty mind, what praise thy brilliant 
beauty? Leda would rather have thee her son
than Castor ; Thetis counts thee dearer than her 
own Achilles ; Delos' isle admits thee Apollo's
victor ; Lydia puts Bacchus second to thee. When
in the heat of the chase thou guidest thy coursing
steed amid the towering holm-oaks and thy tossing 
locks stream out upon the wind, the beasts of their 
own accord will fall before thine arrows and the 
lion, right gladly wounded by a prince's sacred 
hand will welcome thy spear and be proud so to 
die. Venus scorns Adonis returned from the dead,
Diana disapproves Hippolytus recalled to life. </p>

<p>
When after thy toils thou seekest the shade of a
green plane-tree or  shunnest Sirius' extreme heat in some 
cool grot and freest thy wearied limbs in 
sleep, what a passion of love will inflame the Dryads'
hearts! how many a Naiad will steal up with trembling foot and snatch an unmarked kiss!
Who,

            <pb id="v.1.p.233"/>

though he be more uncivilized than the wild Scythians
and more cruel even than the beasts, but will, when
he has seen near at hand thy transcendent loveliness,
offer thee a ready servitude? Who will not
willingly seize the chains of slavery and demand
the yoke for a neck as yet free? Hadst thou o'er
the heights of snowy Caucasus gone against the cruel
Amazons in all thy beauty, that warrior band had
fled the fight and called to mind again their proper
sex; Hippolyte, amid the trumpets' din, forgetful
of her sire, had weakly laid aside her drawn battleaxe,
and with half-bared breast loosed the girdle
all Hercules' strength availed not to loose. Thy
beauty alone would have ended the war.
</p>
         <p>Blessed is she who will soon call thee husband and
unite herself to thee with the bonds of first love.

</p>
         <pb id="v.1.p..233" TEIform="pb"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="poem" n="2" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>FESCENNINE VERSES II </head>
         <p>
Come, earth, wreathed about with nuptial spring,
do honour to thy master's marriage-feast. Sing,
woods and rivers all, sing, deep of ocean. Give your
blessing, too, Ligurian plains and yours, Venetian
hills. Let Alpine heights on a sudden clothe themselves
with rose-bushes and the fields of ice grow
red. Let the Adige re-echo the sound of choric lays
and meandering Mincius whisper gently through his
<pb id="v.1.p.235"/>
reeds and Padus make answer with his amber-dripping
alders. Let Tiber's banks now ring with
the voices of Rome's full-fed citizens and the golden
city, rejoicing in her lord's marriage, crown her
seven hills with flowers.
</p>
         <p>Let Spain hear afar, Spain the cradle of the imperial
race, where is a house that is mother of
emperors, rich in crowns of laurel, whose triumphs
can scarce be numbered. Hence came the bride-groom's
sire, hence the bride's mother; from either
branch flows the blood of the Caesars, like twin
streams reunited. Let rich herbage clothe Baetis'
banks and Tagus swell his golden flood; may Ocean,
ancestor of the imperial race, make merry in his
crystal caves. Let East and West, the two brothers'
realms, join in their applause, and peace and joy
fill the cities illumined by the sun at his rising and
at his setting. Be still, ye storms of the north and
ye mad blasts of Caurus; sounding Auster, sink
to rest. Let Zephyrus have sole rule over this
year of triumph.
<pb id="v.1.p.237"/>
         </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p.." TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="poem" n="3" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>FESCENNINE VERSES III </head>
         <p>
Twine with a soft garland, Stilicho, the locks
whereon a helmet is wont to shine. Let the trumpets
of war cease and the propitious torch of marriage
banish savage Mars afar. Let regal blood unite once
more with regal blood. Perform a father's office
and unite these children with thine illustrious hand.
</p>
         <p>Thou didst marry an emperor's daughter, now, in
turn, thy daughter shall marry an emperor. What
room is here for the madness of jealousy? What
excuse for envy? Stilicho is father both of bride
and bridegroom.

         </p>
         </div1>
         <pb id="v.1.p" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="poem" n="4" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>FESCENNINE VERSES IV </head>
         <p>
Hesperus, loved of Venus, rises and shines for the
marriage with his Idalian 1  rays. Maiden shame now
overcomes the anxious bride; her veil now shows
traces of innocent tears. Hesitate not to be close
in thine attacks, young lover, e'en though she oppose
thee savagely with cruel finger-nail. None can
enjoy the scents of spring nor steal the honey of
Hybla from its fastnesses if he fears that thorns
may scratch his face. Thorns arm the rose and
bees find a defence for their honey. The refusals
of coyness do but increase the joy; the desire for
that which flies us is the more inflamed; sweeter is
the kiss snatched through tears. How oft wilt
thou say: <q direct="unspecified"> Better this than ten victories over the
yellow-haired Sarmatae</q>!
<pb id="v.1.p.239"/>


Breathe a new loyalty into your breasts and let
your senses kindle a flame that shall never be extinguished.
</p>
         <p>May your clasped hands form a bond
more close than that betwixt ivy and leafy oak
tree or poplar and pliant vine. Be the frequent
kisses that ye give and receive breathed more softly
than those of plaintive doves, and when lips have
united soul to soul let sleep still your throbbing
breath. Be the purple couch warm with your
princely wooing, and a new stain ennoble coverlets
ruddy with Tyrian dye. Then leap victorious from
the marriage-bed, scarred with the night's encounter.
</p>
         <p>All night long let the music of the flute resound
and the crowd, set free from law's harsh restraints,
with larger licence indulge the permitted jest.
</p>
         <p>Soldiers, make merry with your leaders, girls with
boys. Be this the cry that re-echoes from pole
to pole, among the peoples, over the seas: <q direct="unspecified">Fair
Honorius weds with Maria.</q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.241"/>
         </p>
            </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>