<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Sextus Roscius</title>
        <title>for Quintius, Sextus Roscius, Quintus Roscius, against Quintus Caecilius, and against
          Verres</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
        <editor role="translator" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
            <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
              Yonge</title><idno type="OCLC">4709897</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons</publisher>
              <date>1903</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>

      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>

      <!--<refsDecl>
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="text=Ver.">
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState delim=" " unit="actio"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="book"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="fre">French</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2016-02-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Moved front matter for more uniform treatment within series.</change>
      <change when="2016-01-27" who="Lisa Cerrato">CTS structure; sections as hierarchy; indicate resp for different structures</change>
      <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader.</change>
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to
        unicode</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2010-09-03">cleaned up log keyword</change>
      <change who="studentAD" when="2010-07-08">fixing place tags - AD</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-10-09">more reorganizing of texts module by
        collection</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed chunking for cic. ver. to
        text:actio:book:section in order for bibls to work</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2009-06-03">fixed bad bibls</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2006-05-05">fixed date tags</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2006-02-10">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2005-08-01">removed stray item tags</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2005-07-25">Converted to XML</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2003-10-10">fixed four random typos</change>
      <change who="yorkc" when="2003-07-01">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions;minor
        cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2002-10-02">fixed typo you have not this to you have not heard
        this</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="2000-03-04">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="1996-11-30">revised and proofread again</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="1999-10-14">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="1999-10-01">fixed valour for velour</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="1999-08-12">Fixed refsDecl</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Minor tagging changes.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Lisa's edits.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-09-01">Added sections.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Changed Quint. abbreviation to Quinct.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Added to repository. Passes TEI parsing.</change>
      <change when="1997-03-19" who="DAS">ed.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text xml:lang="eng">

    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi002.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
        <head>THE ORATION FOR SEXTUS ROSCIUS OF AMERIA.</head>
        <div type="commentary" resp="ed">
          <head>The Argument</head>
          <p>Cicero himself in this speech calls this trial the first public, that is criminal cause
            in which he was engaged; and many critics consider it an earlier speech than the preceding
            one for Quinctius. The case was this: The father of Sextus Roscius had been slain during
            the proscriptions of Sulla, and his estate, which was very large, had been sold for a very
            trifling sum to Lucius Cornelius Chrysogonus, a favourite slave to whom Sulla had given
            his freedom; and Chrysogonus, to secure possession of it, persuaded a man named Caius
            Erucius to accuse Roscius of having killed his father himself. Many lawyers refused to
            defend him, being afraid of Sulla, whose influence was openly used for his freedman.
            Roscius was acquitted. Cicero often refers with great complacency to his conduct in this
            suit, as a proof of his intrepidity, and of his resolute honesty in discharging the duties
            of an advocate without being dismayed at the opposition of the greatest men in <placeName
              key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. </p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="1" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/>
        <milestone unit="Para"/>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus">
        <p>I imagine that you, O judges, are marvelling why it is that when so many most eminent
          orators and most noble men are sitting still, I above all others should get up, who
          neither for age, nor for ability, nor for influence, am to be compared to those who are
          sitting still. For all these men whom you see present at this trial think that a man ought
          to be defended against all injury contrived against him by unrivalled wickedness; but
          through the sad state of the times they do not dare to defend him themselves. So it comes
          to pass that they are present here because they are attending to their business, but they
          are silent because they are afraid of danger.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>What then?
          Am I the boldest of all these men? By no means. Am I then so much more attentive to my
          duties than the rest? I am not so covetous of even that praise, as to wish to rob others
          of it. What is it then which has impelled me beyond all the rest to undertake the cause of
          Sextus Roscius? Because, if any one of those men, men of the greatest weight and dignity,
          whom you see present, had spoken, had said one word about public affairs, as must be done
          in this case, he would be thought to have said much more than he really had said.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>But if I should say all the things which must be said
          with ever so much freedom, yet my speech will never go forth or be diffused among the
          people in the same manner. Secondly, because anything said by the others cannot be
          obscure, because of their nobility and dignity, and cannot be excused as being spoken
          carelessly, on account of their age and prudence; but if I say anything with too much
          freedom, it may either be altogether concealed, because I have not yet mixed in public
          affairs, or pardoned on account of my youth; although not only the method of pardoning,
          but even the habit of examining into the truth is now eradicated from the State.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>There is this reason, also, that perhaps the request
          to undertake this cause was made to the others so that they thought they could comply or
          refuse without prejudice to their duty; but those men applied to me who have the greatest
          weight with me by reason of their friendship with me, of the kindnesses they have done me,
          and of their own dignity; whose kindness to me I could not be ignorant of whose authority
          I could not despise, whose desires I could not neglect.</p></div>
          <milestone n="2" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>On these accounts I have stood forward as the advocate in this cause, not as being the
          one selected who could plead with the greatest ability, but as the one left of the whole
          body who could do so with the least danger; and not in order that Sextus Roscius might he
          defended by a sufficiently able advocacy, but that he might not be wholly abandoned.
          Perhaps you may ask, What is that dread, and what is that alarm which hinders so many, and
          such eminent men, from being willing, as they usually are, to plead on behalf of the life
          and fortunes of another? And it is not strange that you are as yet ignorant of this,
          because all mention of the matter which has given rise to this trial has been designedly
          omitted by the accusers.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>What is that matter? The
          property of the father of this Sextus Roscius, which is six millions of <foreign
            xml:lang="la">sesterces</foreign>, which one of the most powerful young men of our city
          at this present time, Lucius Cornelius Chrysogonus, says he bought of that most gallant
          and most illustrious man Lucius Sulla, whom I only name to do him honour, for two thousand
            <foreign xml:lang="la">sesterces</foreign>. He, O judges, demands of you that, since he,
          without any right, has taken possession of the property of another, so abundant and so
          splendid, and as the life of Sextus Roscius appears to him to stand in the way of and to
          hinder his possession of that property, you will efface from his mind every suspicion, and
          remove all his fear. He does not think that, while this man is safe, he himself can keep
          possession of the ample and splendid patrimony of this innocent man; but if he be
          convicted and got rid of, he hopes he may be able to waste and squander in luxury what he
          has acquired by wickedness. He begs that you will take from his mind this uneasiness which
          day and night is pricking and harassing him, so as to profess yourselves his assistants in
          enjoying this his nefariously acquired booty.</p></div>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>If his
          demand seems to you just and honourable, O judges, I, on the other hand, proffer this
          brief request, and one, as I persuade myself, somewhat more reasonable still. 
            <milestone n="3" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            First of all, I ask of Chrysogonus to be content with our money and our fortunes, and not
          to seek our blood and our lives. In the second place, I beg you, O judges, to resist the
          wickedness of audacious men; to relieve the calamities of the innocent, and in the cause
          of Sextus Roscius to repel the danger which is being aimed at every one.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>But if any pretence for the accusation—if any suspicion of this act—if,
          in short, any, the least thing be found,—so that in bringing forward this accusation they
          shall seem to have had some real object,—if you find any cause whatever for it, except
          that plunder which I have mentioned, I will not object to the life of Sextus Roscius being
          abandoned to their pleasure. But if there is no other object in it, except to prevent
          anything being wanting to those men, whom nothing can satisfy, if this alone is contended
          for at this moment, that the condemnation of Sextus Roscius may be added as a sort of
          crown, as it were, to this rich and splendid booty,—though many things be infamous, still
          is not this the most infamous of all things, that you should be thought fitting men for
          these fellows now to expect to obtain by means of your sentences and your oaths, what they
          have hitherto been in the habit of obtaining by wickedness and by the sword; that though
          you have been chosen out of the state into the senate because of your dignity, and out of
          the senate into this body because of your inflexible love of justice—still assassins and
          gladiators should ask of you, not only to allow them to escape the punishment which they
          ought to fear and dread at your hands for their crimes, but also that they may depart from
          this court adorned and enriched with the spoils of Sextus Roscius?</p></div>
        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus">
        <p>Of such important and such atrocious actions, I am aware that I can neither speak with
          sufficient propriety, nor complain with sufficient dignity, nor cry out against with
          sufficient freedom. For my want of capacity is a hindrance to my speaking with propriety;
          my age, to my speaking with dignity; the times themselves are an obstacle to my speaking
          with freedom. To this is added great fear, which both nature and my modesty cause me, and
          your dignity, and the violence of our adversaries, and the danger of Sextus Roscius. On
          which account, I beg and entreat of you, O judges, to hear what I have to say with
          attention, and with your favourable construction.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus">
          <p>Relying on your integrity and wisdom, I have undertaken a greater burden than, I am well
          aware, I am able to bear. If you, in some degree, lighten this burden, O judges, I will
          bear it as well as I can with zeal and industry. But if, as I do not expect, I am
          abandoned by you, still I will not fail in courage, and I will bear what I have undertaken
          as well as I can. But if I cannot support it, I had rather be overwhelmed by the weight of
          my duty, than either through treachery betray, or through weakness of mind desert, that
          which has been once honestly entrusted to me.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>I also,
          above all things, entreat you, O Marcus Fannius, to show yourself at this present time
          both to us and to the Roman people the same man that you formerly showed yourself to the
          Roman people when you before presided at the trial in this same cause. <note
            anchored="true">Fannius had been praetor, and before a cause came to actual trial, in
            came before the praetor, who decided whether there were sufficient grounds for allowing
            the trial to proceed; much as our grand jury does now.</note>
          <milestone n="5" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          You see how great a crowd of men has come to this trial. You are aware how great is the
          expectation of men, and how great their desire that the decisions of the courts of law
          should be severe and impartial. After a long interval, this is the first cause about
          matters of bloodshed which has been brought into court, though most shameful and important
          murders have been committed in that interval. All men hope that while you are praetor,
          these trials concerning manifest crimes, and the daily murders which take place, will be
          conducted with no less severity than this one.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>We who
          are pleading this cause adopt the exclamations which in other trials the accusers are in
          the habit of using. We entreat of you, O Marcus Fannius, and of you, O judges, to punish
          crimes with the greatest energy; to resist audacious men with the greatest boldness; to
          consider that unless you show in this cause what your disposition is, the covetousness and
          wickedness, and audacity of men will increase to such a pitch that murders will take place
          not only secretly, but even here in the forum, before your tribunal, O Marcus Fannius;
          before your feet, O judges, among the very benches of the court.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>In truth, what else is aimed at by this trial, except that it may be
          lawful to commit such acts? They are the accusers who have invaded this man's fortunes. He
          is pleading his cause as defendant, to whom these men have left nothing except misfortune.
          They are the accusers, to whom it was an advantage that the father of Sextus Roscius
          should be put to death. He is the defendant, to whom the death of his father has brought
          not only grief, but also poverty. They are the accusers, who have exceedingly desired to
          put this man himself to death. He is the defendant who has come even to this very trial
          with a guard, lest he should be slain here in this very place, before your eyes. Lastly,
          they are the accusers whom the people demand punishment on, as the guilty parties.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>He is the defendant, who remains as the only one left
          after the impious slaughter committed by them. And that you may be the more easily able to
          understand, O judges, that what has been done is still more infamous than what we mention,
          we will explain to you from the beginning how the matter was managed, so that you may the
          more easily be able to perceive both the misery of this most innocent man, and their
          audacity, and the calamity of the republic.</p></div> 
        <milestone n="6" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>
         Sextus Roscius, the father of this man, was a citizen <note anchored="true">A <foreign
              xml:lang="la">municeps</foreign> was a citizen of a <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >municipium</foreign>. For a full explanation of these terms see Smith, Dict. Ant.
            p.259, v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Colonia</foreign>. </note> of <placeName
            key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>, by far the first man not only of his
          municipality, but also of his neighbourhood, in birth, and nobility and wealth, and also
          of great influence, from the affection and the ties of hospitality by which he was
          connected with the most noble men of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. For
          he had not only connections of hospitality with the Metelli, the Servilii, and the
          Scipios, but he had also actual acquaintance and intimacy with them; families which I
          name, as it is right I should, only to express my sense of their honour and dignity. And
          of all his property he has left this alone to his son,—for domestic robbers have
          possession of his patrimony, which they have seized by force the fame and life of this
          innocent man is defended by his paternal connections <note anchored="true">The Latin word
            is <foreign xml:lang="la">hospes</foreign>, answering to the Greek <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">ce/nos</foreign>.</note> and friends.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p>As he had at all times been a favourer of the side of the nobility, so, too, in this
          last disturbance, when the dignity and safety of all the nobles was in danger, he, beyond
          all others in that neighbourhood, defended that party and that cause with all his might,
          and zeal, and influence. He thought it right, in truth, that he should fight in defence of
          their honour, on account of whom he himself was reckoned most honourable among his
          fellow-citizens. After the victory was declared, and we had given up arms, when men were
          being proscribed, and when they who were supposed to be enemies were being taken in every
          district, he was constantly at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, and in the
          Forum, and was daily in the sight of every one; so that he seemed rather to exult in the
          victory of the nobility, than to be afraid lest any disaster should result to him from it.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"> <p>He had an ancient quarrel with two Roscii of
            <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>, one of whom I see sitting in the
          seats of the accusers, the other I hear is in possession of three of this man's farms; and
          if he had been as well able to guard against their enmity as he was in the habit of
          fearing it, he would be alive now. And, O judges, he was not afraid without reason. In
          these two Roscii, (one of whom is surnamed Capito; the one who is present here is called
          Magnus,) are men of this sort. One of them is an old and experienced gladiator, who has
          gained many victories, but this one here has lately betaken himself to him as his tutor:
          and though, before this contest, he was a mere tyro in knowledge, he easily surpassed his
          tutor himself in wickedness and audacity.</p></div> 
          <milestone n="7" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus">
        <p>For when this Sextus Roscius was at <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>,
          but that Titus Roscius at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; while the
          former, the son, was diligently attending to the farm, and in obedience to his father's
          desire had given himself up entirely to his domestic affairs and to a rustic life, but the
          other man was constantly at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, Sextus
          Roscius, returning home after supper, is slain near the 
          <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine</placeName> baths. I hope from this very fact, that it is not obscure on whom
          the suspicion of the crime falls; but if the whole affair does not itself make plain that
          which as yet is only to be suspected, I give you leave to say my client is implicated in
          the guilt.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"> <p>When Sextus Roscius was slain, the first
          person who brings the news to <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>, is a
          certain Mallius Glaucia, a man of no consideration, a freedman, the client and intimate
          friend of that Titus Roscius; and he brings the news to the house, not of the son, but of
          Titus Capito, his enemy, and though he had been slain about the first hour of the night,
          this messenger arrives at <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName> by the first
          dawn of day. In ten hours of the night he travelled fifty-six miles in a gig; not only to
          be the first to bring his enemy the wished-for news, but to show him the blood of his
          enemy still quite fresh, and the weapon only lately extracted from his body.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"> <p>Four days after this happened, news of the deed is brought to
          Chrysogonus to the camp of Lucius Sulla at Volaterra. The greatness of his fortune is
          pointed out to him, the excellence of his farms,—for he left behind him thirteen farms,
          which nearly all border on the Tiber—the poverty and desolate condition of his son is
          mentioned they point out that, as the father of this, man, Sextus Roscius a man so
          magnificent and so popular, was slain without any trouble this man, imprudent and
          unpolished as he was and unknown at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, might
          easily be removed. They promise their assistance for this business; not to detain you
          longer, O judges, a conspiracy is formed.</p></div> 
           <milestone n="8" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus">
        <p>As at this time there was no mention of a proscription, and as even those who had been
          afraid of it before, were returning and thinking themselves now delivered from their
          dangers, the name of Sextus Roscius, a man most zealous for the nobility, is proscribed
          and his goods sold; Chrysogonus is the purchaser; three of his finest farms, are given to
          Capito for his own, and he possesses them to this day; all the rest of his property that
          fellow Titus Roscius seizes in the name of Chrysogonus, as he says himself. This property,
          worth six millions of <foreign xml:lang="la">sesterces</foreign>, is bought for two
          thousand. I well know, O judges, that all this was done without the knowledge of Lucius
          Sulla;</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"> <p>and it is not strange that while he is surveying
          at the same time both the things which are past, and those which seem to be impending;
          when he alone has, the authority to establish peace, and the power of carrying on war;
          when all are looking to him alone, and he alone is directing all things; when he is
          occupied incessantly by such numerous and such important affairs that he cannot breathe
          freely, it is not strange, I say, if he fails to notice some things; especially when so
          many men are watching his, busy condition, and catch their opportunity of doing something
          of this sort the moment he looks away. To this is added, that although he is fortunate, as
          indeed he is, yet no man can have such good fortune, as in a vast household to have no
          one, whether slave or freedman, of worthless character.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus">
          <p>In the meantime Titus Roscius, excellent man, the agent of Chrysogonus, comes to
            <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>; he enters on this man's farm; turns
          this miserable man, overwhelmed with grief, who had not yet performed all the ceremonies
          of his father's funeral, naked out of his house, and drives him headlong from his paternal
          hearth and household gods; he himself becomes the owner of abundant wealth. He who had
          been in great poverty when he had only his own property, became, as is usual, insolent
          when in possession of the property of another; he carried many things openly off to his
          own house; he removed still more privily; he gave no little abundantly and extravagantly
          to his assistants; the rest he sold at a regular auction.</p></div> 
       <milestone n="9" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus">
        <p>Which appeared to the citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName> so
          scandalous, that there was weeping and lamentation over the whole city. In truth, many
          things calculated to cause grief were brought at once before their eyes; the most cruel
          death of a most prosperous man, Sextus Roscius, and the most scandalous distress of his
          son; to whom that infamous robber had not left out of so rich a patrimony even enough for
          a road to his father's tomb; the flagitious purchase of his property, the flagitious
          possession of it; thefts, plunders, largesses. There was no one who would not rather have
          had it all burnt, than see Titus Roscius acting as owner of and glorying in the property
          of Sextus Roscius, a most virtuous and honourable man.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p>
          Therefore a decree of their senate is, immediately passed, that the ten chief men <note
            anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="la">decuriones</foreign> were the senators in a
            colony. Only a <foreign xml:lang="la">decuric</foreign> could be a magistrate, and their
            body possessed whatever power had once belonged to the community. Smith, Dict. Ant. v.
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Colonia</foreign>.</note> should go to Lucius Sulla, and
          explain to him what a man Sextus Roscius had been; should complain of the wickedness and
          outrages of those fellows, should entreat him to see to the preservation both of the
          character of the dead man, and of the fortunes of his innocent son, And observe, I entreat
          you, this decree— [here the decree is read] —The deputies come to the camp. It is now
          seen, O judges, as I said before, that these crimes and atrocities were committed without
          the knowledge of Lucius Sulla. For immediately Chrysogonus himself comes to them, and
          sends some men of noble birth to them too, to beg them not to go to Sulla, and to promise
          them that Chrysogonus, will do everything which they wish.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>But to such a degree was he alarmed, that he would rather have died
          than have let Sulla be informed of these things. These old-fashioned men, who judged of
          others by their own nature, when he pledged himself to have the name of Sextus Roscius
          removed from the lists of proscription, and to give up the farms unoccupied to his son,
          and when Titus Roscius Capito, who was one of the ten deputies, added his promise that it
          should be so, believed him; they returned to <placeName key="perseus,Ameria"
            >Ameria</placeName> without presenting their petition. And at first those fellows began
          every day to put the matter off and to procrastinate; then they began to be more
          indifferent; to do nothing and to trifle with them; at last, as was easily perceived, they
          began to contrive plots against the life of this Sextus Roscius, and to think that they
          could no longer keep possession of another man's property while the owner was alive.</p></div>
            <milestone n="10" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus">
        <p>As soon as he perceived this, by the advice of his friends and relations he fled to
            <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, and betook himself to Caecilia, the
          daughter of Nepos, (whom I name to do her honour,) with whom his father had been
          exceedingly intimate; a woman in whom, O judges, even now, as all men are of opinion, as
          if it were to serve as a model, traces of the old-fashioned virtue remain. She received
          into her house Sextus Roscius, helpless, turned and driven out of his home and property,
          flying from the weapons and threats of robbers, and she assisted her guest now that he was
          overwhelmed and now that his safety was despaired of by every one. By her virtue and good
          faith and diligence it has been caused that he now is rather classed as a living man among
          the accused, than as a dead man among the proscribed.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus">
          <p>For after they perceived that the life of Sextus Roscius was protected with the greatest
          care, and that there was no possibility of their murdering him, they adopted a counsel
          full of wickedness and audacity, namely, that of accusing him of parricide; of procuring
          some veteran accuser to support the charge, who could say something even in a case in
          which there was no suspicion whatever; and lastly, as they could not have any chance
          against him by the accusation, to prevail against him on account of the time; for men
          began to say, that no trial had taken place for such a length of time, that the first man
          who was brought to trial ought to be condemned; and they thought that he would have no
          advocates because of the influence of Chrysogonus; that no one would say a word about the
          sale of the property and about that conspiracy; that because of the mere name of parricide
          and the atrocity of the crime he would be put out of the way, without any trouble, as he
          was defended by no one.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"> <p>With this plan, and urged on to
          such a degree by this madness, they have handed the man over to you to be put to death,
          whom they themselves, when they wished, were unable to murder. 
        <milestone n="11" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          What shall I complain of first? or from what point had I best begin, O judges? or what
          assistance shall I seek, or from whom? Shall I implore at this time the aid of the
          immortal gods, or that of the Roman people, or of your integrity, you who have the supreme
          power?</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>The father infamously murdered; the house
          besieged; the property taken away, seized and plundered by enemies; the life of the son,
          hostile to their purposes, attacked over and over again by sword and treachery. What
          wickedness does there seem to be wanting in these numberless atrocities? And yet they
          crown and add to them by other nefarious deeds, they invent an incredible accusation; they
          procure witnesses against him and accusers of him by bribery; they offer the wretched man
          this alternative, whether he would prefer to expose his neck to Roscius to be assassinated
          by him, or, being sewn in a sack, to lose his life with the greatest infamy. They thought
          advocates would be wanting to him; they are wanting. There is not wanting in truth, O
          judges, one who will speak with freedom, and who will defend him with integrity, which is
          quite sufficient in this cause, (since I have undertaken it).</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>And perhaps in undertaking this cause I may have acted rashly, in
          obedience to the impulses of youth; but since I have once undertaken it, although forsooth
          every sort of terror and every possible danger were to threaten me on all sides, yet I
          will support and encounter them. I have deliberately resolved not only to say everything
          which I think is material to the cause, but to say it also willingly, boldly, and freely.
          Nothing can ever be of such importance in my mind that fear should be able to put a
          greater constraint on me than a regard to good faith.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus">
          <p>Who, indeed, is of so profligate a disposition, as, when he sees these things, to be able
          to be silent and to disregard them? You have murdered my father when he had not been
          proscribed; you have classed him when murdered in the number of proscribed persons; you
          have driven me by force from my house; you are in possession of my patrimony. What would
          you more? have you not come even before the bench with sword and arms, that you may either
          convict Sextus Roscius or murder him in this presence?</p></div> 
          <milestone n="12" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus">
        <p>We lately had a most audacious man in this city, Caius Fimbria, a man, as is well known
          among all except among those who are mad themselves, utterly insane. He, when at the
          funeral of Caius Marius, had contrived that Quintus Scaevola, the most venerable and
          accomplished man in our city, should be wounded;—(a man in whose praise there is neither
          room to say much here, nor indeed is it possible to say more than the Roman people
          preserves in its recollection)—he, I say, brought an accusation against Scaevola, when he
          found that he might possibly live. When the question was asked him, what he was going to
          accuse that man of, whom no one could praise in a manner sufficiently suitable to his
          worth, they say that the man, like a madman as he was, answered, for not having received
          the whole weapon in his body. A more lamentable thing was never seen by the Roman people,
          unless it were the death of that same man, which was so important that it crushed and
          broke the hearts of all his fellow-citizens; for endeavouring to save whom by an
          arrangement, he was destroyed by them. <note anchored="true">Scaevola was trying to effect
            an accommodation between the parties of Sulla and Marius when he was murdered by them. </note></p></div>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p>Is not this case very like that speech and action of
          Fimbria? You are accusing Sextus Roscius. Why so? Because he escaped out of your hands;
          because he did not allow himself to be murdered. The one action, because it was done
          against Scaevola, appears scandalous; this one, because it is done by Chrysogonus, is
          intolerable. For, in the name of the immortal gods, what is there in this cause that
          requires a defence? What topic is there requiring the ability of an advocate, or even very
          much needing eloquence of speech? Let us, O judges, unfold the whole case, and when it is
          set before our eyes, let us consider it; by this means you will easily understand on what
          the whole case turns, and on what matters I ought to dwell, and what decision you ought to
          come to.</p></div> 
          <milestone n="13" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p>There are three things, as I think, which are at the present time hindrances to Sextus
          Roscius:—the charge brought by his adversaries, their audacity, and their power. Erucius
          has taken on himself the pressing of this false charge as accuser; the Roscii have claimed
          for themselves that part which is to be executed by audacity; but Chrysogonus, as being
          the person of the greatest influence, employs his influence in the contest. On all these
          points I am aware that I must speak.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>What then am I to
          say? I must not speak in the same manner on them all; because the first topic indeed
          belongs to my duty, but the two others the Roman people have imposed on you. I must efface
          the accusations; you ought both to resist the audacity, and at the earliest possible
          opportunity to extinguish and put down the pernicious and intolerable influence of men of
          that sort.</p></div>  
           <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p>Sextus Roscius is accused of having murdered
          his father. O ye immortal gods! a wicked and nefarious action, in which one crime every
          sort of wickedness appears to be contained. In truth, if, as is well said by wise men,
          affection is often injured by a look, what sufficiently severe punishment can be devised
          against him who has inflicted death on his parent, for whom all divine and human laws
          bound him to be willing to die himself, if occasion required?</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>In the case of so enormous, so atrocious, so singular a crime, as this
          one which has been committed so rarely, that, if it is ever heard of, it is accounted like
          a portent and prodigy—what arguments do you think, O Caius Erucius, you as the accuser
          ought to use? Ought you not to prove the singular audacity of him who is accused of it?
          and his savage manners, and brutal nature, and his life devoted to every sort of vice and
          crime, his whole character, in short, given up to profligacy and abandoned? None of which
          things have you alleged against Sextus Roscius, not even for the sake of making the
          imputation.</p></div>  
          <milestone n="14" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus">
        <p>Sextus Roscius has murdered his father. What sort of man is he? is he a young man,
          corrupted, and led on by worthless men? He is more than forty years old. Is he forsooth an
          old assassin, a bold man, and one well practised in murder? You have not heard this so
          much as mentioned by the accuser. To be sure; then, luxury, and the magnitude of his
          debts, and the ungovernable desires of his disposition, have urged the man to this
          wickedness? Erucius acquitted him of luxury, when he said that he was scarcely ever
          present at any banquet. But he never owed anything Further what evil desires could exist
          in that man who as his accuser himself objected to him has always lived in the country and
          spent his time in cultivating his land, a mode of life which is utterly removed from
          covetousness, and inseparably allied to virtue?</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p>What
          was it then which inspired Sextus Roscius with such madness as that? Oh, says he, he did
          not please his father. He did not please his father? For what reason? for it must have
          been both a just and an important and a notorious reason. For as this is incredible, that
          death should be inflicted on a father by a son, without many and most weighty reasons; so
          this, too, is not probable, that a son should be hated by his father, without many and
          important and necessary causes.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p>Let us return again to
          the same point, and ask what vices existed in this his only son of such importance as to
          make him incur the displeasure of his father. But it is notorious he had no vices. His
          father then was mad to bate him whom he had begotten, without any cause. But he was the
          most reasonable and sensible of men. This, then, is evident, that, if the father was not
          crazy, nor his son profligate, the father had no cause for displeasure, nor the son for
          crime.</p></div>  
         <milestone n="15" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus">
        <p>I know not, says he, what cause for displeasure there was; but I know that displeasure
          existed; because formerly, when he had two sons, he chose that other one, who is dead; to
          be at all times with himself, but sent this other one to his farms in the country. The
          same thing which happened to Erucius in supporting this wicked and trifling charge, has
          happened to me in advocating a most righteous cause. He could find no means of supporting
          this trumped-up charge; I can hardly find out by what arguments I am to invalidate and get
          rid of such trifling circumstances.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p>What do you say,
          Erucius? Did Sextus Roscius entrust so many farms, and such fine and productive ones to
          his son to cultivate and manage, for the sake of getting rid of and punishing him? What
          can this mean? Do not fathers of families who have children, particularly men of that
          class of municipalities in the country, do they not think it a most desirable thing for
          them that their sons should attend in a great degree to their domestic affairs, and should
          devote much of their labour and attention to cultivating their farms?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>Did he send him off to those farms that he might remain on the land and
          merely have life kept in him at this country seat? that he might be deprived of all
          conveniences? What? if it is proved that he not only managed the cultivation of the farms,
          but was accustomed himself to have certain of the farms for his own, even during the
          lifetime of his father? Will his industrious and rural life still be called removal and
          banishment? You see, O Erucius, how far removed your line of argument is from the fact
          itself, and from truth. That which fathers usually do, you find fault with as an
          unprecedented thing; that which is done out of kindness, that you accuse as having been
          done from dislike; that which a father granted his son as an honour, that you say he did
          with the object of punishing him.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p>Not that you are not
          aware of all this, but you are so wholly without any arguments to bring forward, that you
          think it necessary to plead not only against us, but even against the very nature of
          things, and against the customs of men, and the opinion of every one.
           <milestone n="16" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        Oh but, when he had two sons, he never let one be away from him, and he allowed the other
          to remain in the country. I beg you, O Erucius, to take what I am going to say in good
          part; for I am going to say it, not for the sake of finding fault, but to warn you.</p></div> 
           <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p>If fortune did not give to you to know the father
          whose son you are, so that you could understand what was the affection of fathers towards
          their children; still, at all events, nature has given you no small share of human
          feeling. To this is added a zeal for learning, so that you are not unversed in literature.
          Does that old man in Caecilius, (to quote a play,) appear to have less affection for
          Eutychus, his son, who lives in the country, than for his other one Chaerestratus? for
          that, I think, is his name; do you think that he keeps one with him in the city do him
          honour, and sends the other into the country in order to punish him?</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p>Why do you have recourse to such trifling? you will say. As if it were
          a hard matter for me to bring forward ever so many by name, of my own tribe, or my own
          neighbours, (not to wander too far off,) who wish those sons for whom they have the
          greatest regard, to be diligent farmers. But it is an odious step to quote known men, when
          it is uncertain whether they would like their names to be used; and no one is likely to be
          better known to you than this same Eutychus; and certainly it has nothing to do with the
          argument, whether I name this youth in a play, or some one of the country about <placeName
            key="perseus,Veii">Veii</placeName>. In truth, I think that these things are invented by
          poets in order that we may see our manners sketched under the character of strangers, and
          the image of our daily life represented under the guise of fiction.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p>Come now; turn your thoughts, if you please, to reality, and consider
          not only in <placeName key="tgn,7003125">Umbria</placeName> and that neighbourhood, but in
          these old municipal towns, what pursuits are most praised by fathers of families. You will
          at once see that, from want of real grounds of accusation, you have imputed that which is
          his greatest praise to Sextus Roscius as a fault and a crime. 
          <milestone n="17" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        But not only do children do this by the wish of their fathers, but I have myself known
          many men (and so, unless I am deceived, has every one of you) who are inflamed of their
          own accord with a fondness for what relates to the cultivation of land, and who think this
          rural life, which you think ought to be a disgrace to and a charge against a man, the most
          honourable and the most delightful.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p>What do you think
          of this very Sextus Roscius? How great is his fondness for, and shrewdness in rural
          affairs! As I hear from his relations, most honourable men, you are not more skillful in
          this your business of an accuser, than he is in his. But, as I think, since it seems good
          to Chrysogonus, who has left him no farm, he will be able now to forget this skill of his,
          and to give up this taste. And although that is a sad and a scandalous thing, yet he will
          bear it, O judges, with equanimity, if, by your verdict, he can preserve his life and his
          character; but this is intolerable, if he is both to have this calamity brought upon him
          on account of the goodness and number of his farms, and if that is especially to be
          imputed to him as a crime that he cultivated them with great care; so that it is not to be
          misery enough to have cultivated them for others not for himself, unless it is also to be
          accounted a crime that he cultivated them at all.</p></div>  
          <milestone n="18" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus">
        <p>In truth, O Erucius, you would have been a ridiculous accuser, if you had been born in
          those times when men were sent for from the plough to be made consuls. Certainly you, who
          think it a crime to have superintended the cultivation of a farm, would consider that
          Atilius, whom those who were sent to him found sowing seed with his own hand, a most base
          and dishonourable man. But, forsooth, our ancestors judged very differently both of him
          and of all other such men. And therefore from a very small and powerless state they left
          us one very great and very prosperous. For they diligently cultivated their own lands,
          they did not graspingly desire those of others; by which conduct they enlarged the
          republic, and this dominion, and the name of the Roman people, with lands and conquered
          cities, and subjected nations.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus"><p>Nor do I bring forward
          these instances in order to compare them with these matters which we are now
          investigating; but in order that that may be understood: that, as in the times of our
          ancestors, the highest and most illustrious men, who ought at all times to have been
          sitting at the helm of the republic, yet devoted much of their attention and time to the
          cultivation of their lands; that man ought to be pardoned, who avows himself a rustic, for
          having lived constantly in the country, especially when be could do nothing which was
          either more pleasing to his father, or more delightful to himself, or in reality more
          honourable.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p>The bitter dislike of the father to the
          son, then, is proved by this, O Erucius, that he allowed him to remain in the country. Is
          there anything else? Certainly, says he, there is. For he was thinking of disinheriting
          him. I hear you. Now you are saying something which may have a bearing on the business,
          for you will grant, I think, that those other arguments are trifling and childish. He
          never went to any feasts with his father. Of course not, as he very seldom came to town at
          all. People very seldom asked him to their houses. No wonder, for a man who did not live
          in the city, and was not likely to ask them in return.</p></div>  
          <milestone n="19" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus">
        <p>But you are aware that these things too are trifling. Let us consider that which we began
          with, than which no more certain argument of dislike can possibly be found. The father was
          thinking of disinheriting his son. I do not ask on what account. I ask how you know it?
          Although you ought to mention and enumerate all the reasons. And it was the duty of a
          regular accuser, who was accusing a man of such wickedness, to unfold all the vice and
          sins of a son had exasperated the father so as to enable him to bring his mind to subdue
          nature herself—to banish from his mind that affection so deeply implanted in it—to forget
          in short that he was a father; and all this I do not think could have happened without
          great errors on the part of the son.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus"><p>But I give you
          leave to pass over those things, which, as you are silent, you admit have no existence. At
          all events you ought to make it evident that he did intend to disinherit him. What then do
          you allege to make us think that that was the case? You can say nothing with truth. Invent
          something at least with probability in it; that you may not manifestly be convicted of
          doing what you are openly doing—insulting the fortunes of this unhappy man, and the
          dignity of these noble judges. He meant to disinherit his son. On what account? I don't
          know. Did he disinherit him? No. Who hindered him? He was thinking of it. He was thinking
          of it? Who did he tell? No one. What is abusing the court of justice, and the laws, and
          your majesty, O judges, for the purposes of gain and lust, but accusing men in this
          manner, and bringing imputations against them which you not only are not able to prove,
          but which you do not even attempt to?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p>There is not one
          of us, O Erucius, who does not know that you have no enmity against Sextus Roscius. All
          men see on what account you come here as his adversary. They know that you are induced to
          do so by this man's money. What then? Still you ought to have been desirous of gain with
          such limitations as to think that the opinion of all these men, and the Remmian <note
            anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="la">Remmia Lex</foreign> fixed the punishment for
              <foreign xml:lang="la">calumnia</foreign>; but it is not known when this law was
            passed, nor what were its penalties, Smith, Dict Ant. v. <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Calumnia</foreign>.</note> law ought to nave some weight.</p></div>  
              <milestone n="20" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus">
        <p>It is a useful thing for there to be many accusers in the city, in order that audacity
          may be kept in check by fear; but it is only useful with this limitation, that we are not
          to be manifestly mocked by accusers. A man is innocent. But although he is free from guilt
          he is not free from suspicion. Although it is a lamentable thing, still I can, to some
          extent, pardon a man who accuses him. For when be has anything which he can say, imputing
          a crime, or fixing a suspicion, he does not appear knowingly to be openly mocking and
          calumniating. On which account we all easily allow that there should be as many accusers
          as possible; because an innocent man, if he be accused, can be acquitted; a guilty man,
          unless or he be accused cannot be convicted. But it is more desirable that an innocent man
          should be acquitted, than that a guilty man should not be brought to trial. Food for the
          geese is contracted for at the public expense, and dogs are maintained in the Capitol, to
          give notice if thieves come. But they cannot distinguish thieves. Accordingly they give
          notice if any one comes by night to the Capitol; and because that is a suspicious thing,
          although they are but beasts, yet they oftenest err on that side which is the more prudent
          one. But if the dogs barked by day also, when any one came to pay honour to the gods, I
          imagine their legs would be broken for being active then also, when there was no
          suspicion. The notion of accusers is very much the same.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus"><p>Some of you are geese, who only cry out, and have no power to hurt, some are dogs who
          can both bark and bite. We see that food is provided for you; but you ought chiefly to
          attack those who deserve it. This is most pleasing to the people; then if you will, then
          you may bark on suspicion when it seems probable that some one has committed a crime. That
          may be allowed. But if you act in such a way as to accuse a man of having murdered his
          father, without being able to say why or how; and if you are only barking without any
          ground for suspicion, no one, indeed, will break your legs; but if I know these judges
          well, they will so firmly affix to your heads that letter <note anchored="true">The letter
            was K, which was branded on the forehead of those who were convicted of bringing false
            accusations, being the first letter of the word <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >kalumnia</foreign> as it was originally spelt. It was also the first letter of the
            word <foreign xml:lang="la">kalendae</foreign> and on the calends of each month debts
            were accustomed to be got in and bonds were liable to be paid.</note> to which you are
          so hostile that you hate all the Calends too, that you shall hereafter be able to accuse
          no one but your own fortunes.</p></div>  <milestone n="21" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus">
        <p>What have you given me to defend my client against, my good accuser? And what ground have
          you given these judges for any suspicion? He was afraid of being disinherited. I hear you.
          But no one says what ground he had for fear. His father had it in contemplation. Prove it.
          There is no proof; there is no mention of any one with whom he deliberated about it—whom
          he told of it; there is no circumstance from which it could occur to your minds to suspect
          it. When you bring accusations in this manner, O Erucius, do you not plainly say this? “I
          know what I have received, but I do not know what to say. I have had regard to that alone
          which Chrysogonus said, that no one would be his advocate; that there was no one who would
          dare at this time to say a word about the purchase of the property, and about that
          conspiracy.” This false opinion prompted you to this dishonesty. You would not in truth
          have said a word if you had thought that any one would answer you.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus"><p>It were worth while, if you have noticed it, O judges, to consider this
          man's carelessness in bringing forward his accusations. I imagine, when he saw what men
          were sitting on those benches, that he inquired whether this man or that man was going to
          defend him; that he never even dreamt of me, because I have never pleaded any public cause
          before. After he found that no one was going to defend him of those men who have the
          ability and are in the habit of so doing, he began to be so careless that, when it suited
          his fancy he sat down, then he walked about, sometimes he even called his boy, I suppose
          to give him orders for supper, and utterly overlooked your assembly and all this court as
          if it had been a complete desert.</p></div>  
         <milestone n="22" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus">
        <p>At length he summed up. He sat down. I got up. He seemed to breathe again because no one
          else rose to speak other than I. I began to speak. I noticed, O judges, that he was joking
          and doing other things, up to the time when I named Chrysogonus; but as soon as I touched
          him, my man at once raised himself up. He seemed to be astonished. I knew what had pinched
          him. I named him a second time, and a third. After, men began to run hither arid thither,
          I suppose to tell Chrysogonus that there was some one who dared to speak contrary to his
          will, that the cause was going on differently from what he expected, that the purchase of
          the goods was being ripped up; that the conspiracy was being severely handled; that his
          influence and power was being disregarded; that the judges were attending diligently; that
          the matter appeared scandalous to the people.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus"><p>And since
          you were deceived in all this, O Erucius, and since you see that everything is altered;
          that the cause on behalf of Sextus Roscius is argued, if not as it should be, at all
          events with freedom, since you see that be is defended whom you thought was abandoned,
          that those who you expected would deliver him up to you are judging impartially, give us
          again, at last, some of your old skill and prudence; confess that you came hither with the
          hope that there would he a robbery here, not a trial. A trial is held on a charge of
          parricide, and no reason is alleged by the accuser why the son has slain his father.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus"><p>That which, in even the least offences and in the
          more trifling crimes, which are more frequent and of almost daily occurrence, is asked
          most earnestly and as the very first question, namely what motive there was for the
          offence; that Erucius does not think necessary to be asked in a case of parricide. A
          charge which, O judges, even when many motives appear to concur, and to be connected with
          one another, is still not rashly believed, nor is such a case allowed to depend on slight
          conjecture, nor is any uncertain witness listened to, nor is the matter decided by the
          ability of the accuser. Many crimes previously committed must be proved, and a most
          profligate life on the part of the prisoner, and singular audacity, and not only audacity,
          but the most extreme frenzy and madness. When all these things are proved, still there
          must exist express traces of the crime: where, in what manner, by whose means, and at what
          time the crime was committed. And unless these proofs are numerous and evident—so wicked,
          so atrocious, so nefarious a deed cannot be believed.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus"><p>
          For the power of human feeling is great; the connection of blood is of mighty power;
          nature herself cries out against suspicions of this sort; it is a most undeniable portent
          and prodigy, for any one to exist in human shape, who so far outruns the beasts in
          savageness, as in a most scandalous manner to deprive those of life by whose means he has
          himself beheld this most delicious light of life; when birth, and bringing up, and nature
          herself make even beasts friendly to each other.</p></div>  
       <milestone n="23" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus">
        <p>Not many years ago they say that Titius Cloelius, a citizen of <placeName
            key="tgn,7006704">Terracina</placeName>, a well-known man, when, having supped, he had
          retired to rest in the same room with his two youthful sons, was found in the morning with
          his throat cut: when no servant could be found nor any free man, on whom suspicion of the
          deed could be fixed, and his two sons of that age lying near him said that they did not
          even know what had been done; the sons were accused of the parricide. What followed? it
          was, indeed, a suspicious business; that neither of them were aware of it, and that some
          one had ventured to introduce himself into that chamber, especially at that time when two
          young men were in the same place, who might easily have heard the noise and defended him.
          Moreover, there was no one on whom suspicion of the deed could fall.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus"><p>Still as it was plain to the judges that they were found sleeping with
          the door open, the young men were acquitted and released from all suspicion. For no one
          thought that there was any one who, when he had violated all divine and human laws by a
          nefarious crime, could immediately go to sleep; because they who have committed such a
          crime not only cannot rest free from care, but cannot even breathe without fear.</p></div>
            <milestone n="24" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus">
        <p>Do you not see in the case of those whom the poets have handed down to us, as having, for
          the sake of avenging their father, inflicted punishment on their mother, especially when
          they were said to have done so at the command and in obedience to the oracles of the
          immortal gods, how the furies nevertheless haunt them, and never suffer them to rest,
          because they could not be pious without wickedness. And this is the truth, O judges. The
          blood of one's father and mother has great power, great obligation, is a most holy thing,
          and if any stain of that falls on one, it not only cannot be washed out, but it drips down
          into the very soul, so that extreme frenzy and madness follow it.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus"><p>For do not believe, as you often see it written in fables, that they
          who have done anything impiously and wickedly are really driven about and frightened by
          the furies with burning torches. It is his own dishonesty and the terrors of his own
          conscience that especially harassed each individual; his own wickedness drives each
          criminal about and affects him with madness; his own evil thoughts, his own evil
          conscience terrifies him. These are to the wicked their incessant and domestic furies
          which night and day exact from wicked sons punishment for the crimes committed against
          their parents.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus"><p>This enormity of the crime is the cause
          why, unless a parricide is proved in a manner almost visible, it is not credible, unless a
          man's youth has been base, unless his life has been stained with every sort of wickedness,
          unless his extravagance has been prodigal and accompanied with shame and disgrace, unless
          his audacity has been violent, unless his rashness has been such as to be not far removed
          from insanity. There must be, besides a hatred of his father, a fear of his father's
          reproof—worthless friends, slaves privy to the deed, a convenient opportunity, a place
          fitly selected for the business. I had almost said the judges must see his hands stained
          with his father's blood, if they are to believe so monstrous, so barbarous, so terrible a
          crime.</p></div>  
           <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus"><p>On which account, the less credible it is unless
          it be proved, the more terribly is it to be punished if it be proved. 
          <milestone n="25" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          Therefore, it may be understood by many circumstances that our ancestors surpassed other
          nations not only in arms, but also in wisdom and prudence; and also most especially by
          this, that they devise a singular punishment for the impious. And in this matter consider
          how far they surpassed in prudence those who are said to have been the wisest of all
          nations.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus"><p>The state of the Athenians is said to have
          been the wisest while it enjoyed the supremacy. Moreover of that state they say that Solon
          was the wisest man, he who made the laws which they use even to this day. When he was
          asked why he had appointed no punishment for him who killed his father, he answered that
          he had not supposed that any one would do so. He is said to have done wisely in
          establishing nothing about a crime which had up to that time never been committed, lest he
          should seem not so much to forbid it as to put people in mind of it. How much more wisely
          did our ancestors act! for as they understood that there was nothing so holy that audacity
          did not sometimes violate it, they devised a singular punishment for parricides in order
          that they whom nature herself had not been able to retain in their duty, might be kept
          from crime by the enormity of the punishment. They ordered them to be sown alive in a
          sack, and in that condition to be thrown into the river.</p></div>  
            <milestone n="26" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus">
        <p>O singular wisdom, O judges! Do they not seem to have cut this man off and separated him
          from nature; from whom they took away at once the heaven, the sun, water and earth, so
          that he who had slain him, from whom he himself was horn, might be deprived of all those
          things from which everything is said to derive its birth. They would not throw his body to
          wild beasts, lest we should find the very beasts who had touched such wickedness, more
          savage; they would not throw them naked into the river, lest when they were carried down
          into the sea, they should pollute that also, by which all other things which have been
          polluted are believed to be purified. There is nothing in short so vile or so common that
          they left them any share in it.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus"><p>Indeed what is so
          common as breath to the living, earth to the dead, the sea to those who float, the shore
          to those who are cast up by the sea? These men so live, while they are able to live at
          all, that they are unable to draw breath from heaven; they so die that earth does not
          touch their bones; they are tossed about by the waves so that they are never washed;
          lastly, they are cast up by the sea so, that when dead they do not even rest on the rocks.
          Do you think, O Erucius, that you can prove to such men as these your charge of so
          enormous a crime, a crime to which so remarkable a punishment is affixed, if you do not
          allege any motive for the crime? If you were accusing him before the very purchasers of
          his property, and if Chrysogonus were presiding at that trial, still you would have come
          more carefully and with more preparation.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus"><p>Is it that
          you do not see what the cause really is, or before whom it is being pleaded? The cause in
          question is parricide; which cannot be undertaken without many motives; and it is being
          tried before very wise men, who are aware that no one commits the very slightest crime
          without any motive whatever.
          <milestone n="27" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              Be it so; you are unable to allege any motive. Although I ought at once to gain my cause,
          yet I will not insist on this, and I will concede to you in this cause what I would not
          concede in another, relying on this man's innocence. I do not ask you why Sextus Roscius
          killed his father; I ask you how he killed him? So I ask of you, O Caius Erucius, how, and
          I will so deal with you, that I will on this topic give you leave to answer me or to
          interrupt me, or even, if you wish to at all, to ask me questions.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74" resp="perseus"><p>How did he kill him? Did he strike him himself, or did he commit him to
          others to be murdered? If you say he did it himself, he was not at <placeName
            key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; if you say he did it by the instrumentality of
          others, I ask you were they slaves or free men? who were they? Did they come from the same
          place, from <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>, or were they assassins of
          this city? If they came from Ameria, who are they, why are they not named? If they are of
            <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, how did Roscius make acquaintance with
          them? who for many years had not come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>,
          and who never was there more than three days. Where did he meet them? with whom did he
          speak? how did he persuade them? Did he give them a bribe? to whom did he give it? by
          whose agency did he give it? whence did he get it, and how much did he giver? Are not
          these the steps by which one generally arrives at the main fact of guilt? And let it occur
          to you at the same time how you have painted this man's life; that you have described him
          as an unpolished and country-mannered man; that he never held conversation with any one,
          that he had never dwelt in the city.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75" resp="perseus"><p>And in this I pass
          over that thing which might be a strong argument for me to prove his innocence, that
          atrocities of this sort are not usually produced among country manners, in a sober course
          of life, in an unpolished and rough sort of existence. As you cannot find every sort of
          crop, nor every tree, in every field, so every sort of crime is not engendered in every
          sort of life. In a city, luxury is engendered; avarice is inevitably produced by luxury;
          audacity must spring from avarice, and out of audacity arises every wickedness and every
          crime. But a country life, which you call a clownish one, is the teacher of economy, of
          industry, and of justice.</p></div>  
        <milestone n="28" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76" resp="perseus">
        <p>But I will say no more of this. I ask then by whose instrumentality did this man, who, as
          you yourself say, never mixed with men, contrive to accomplish this terrible crime with
          such secrecy, especially while absent? There are many things, O judges, which are false,
          and which can still be argued so as to cause suspicion. But in this matter, if any grounds
          for suspicion can be discovered, I will admit that there is guilt. Sextus Roscius is
          murdered at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, while his son is at his farm
          at <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>. He sent letters, I suppose, to some
          assassin, he who knew no one at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. He sent
          for some one—but when? He sent a messenger—whom? or to whom? Did he persuade any one by
          bribes, by influence, by hope, by promises? None of these things can even be invented
          against him, and yet a trial for parricide is going on.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77" resp="perseus">
          <p>The only remaining alternative is that he managed it by means of slaves. Oh ye immortal
          gods, how miserable and disastrous is our lot. That which under such an accusation is
          usually a protection to the innocent, to offer his slaves to the question, that it is not
          allowed to Sextus Roscius to do. You, who accuse him, have all his slaves. There is not
          one boy to bring him his daily food left to Sextus Roscius out of so large a household. I
          appeal to you now, Publius Scipio, to you Metellus, while you were acting as his
          advocates, while you were pleading his cause, did not Sextus Roscius often demand of his
          adversaries that two of his father's slaves should be put to the question? Do you remember
          that you, O Titus Roscius, refused it? What? Where are those slaves? They are waiting on
          Chrysogonus, O judges; they are honoured and valued by him. Even now I demand that they be
          put to the question; he begs and entreats it.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78" resp="perseus"><p>What are
          you doing? Why do you refuse? Doubt now, O judges, if you can, by whom Sextus Roscius was
          murdered; whether by him, who, on account of his death, is exposed to poverty and
          treachery, who has not even opportunity allowed him of making inquiry into his father's
          death; or by those who shun investigation, who are in possession of his property, who live
          amid murder, and by murder. Everything in this cause, O judges, is lamentable and
          scandalous; but there is nothing which can be mentioned more bitter or more iniquitous
          than this. The son is not allowed to put his father's slaves to the question concerning
          his father's death. He is not to be master of his own slaves so long as to put them to the
          question concerning his father's death. I will come again, and that speedily, to this
          topic. For all this relates to the Roscii; and I have promised that I will speak of their
          audacity when I have effaced the accusations of Erucius.</p></div>  
           <milestone n="29" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79" resp="perseus">
        <p>Now, Erucius, I come to you. You must inevitably agree with me, if he is really
          implicated in this crime, that he either committed it with his own hand, which you deny,
          or by means of some other men, either freemen or slaves. Were they freemen? You can
          neither show that he had any opportunity of meeting them, nor by what means he could
          persuade them, nor where he saw them, nor by what agency he trafficked with them, nor by
          what hope, or what bribe he persuaded them. I show, on the other hand, not only that
          Sextus Roscius did nothing of all this, but that he was not even able to do anything,
          because he had neither been at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> for many
          years, nor did he ever leave his farm without some object. The name of slaves appeared to
          remain to you, to which, when driven from your other suspicions, you might fly as to a
          harbour, when you strike upon such a rock that you not only see the accusation rebound
          back from it, but perceive that every suspicion falls upon you yourselves.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80" resp="perseus"><p>What is it, then? Whither has the accuser betaken himself in his
          dearth of arguments? The time, says he, was such that men were constantly being killed
          with impunity; so that you, from the great number of assassins, could effect this without
          any trouble. Meantime you seem to me, O Erucius, to be wishing to obtain two articles for
          one payment; to blacken our characters in this trial, and to accuse those very men from
          whom you have received payment. What do you say? Men were constantly being killed? By
          whose agency? and by whom? Do you not perceive that you have been brought here by brokers?
          What next? Are we ignorant that in these times the same men were brokers of men's lives as
          well as of their possessions?</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81" resp="perseus"><p>Shall those men then, who
          at that time used to run about armed night and day, who spent all their time in rapine and
          murder, object to Sextus Roscius the bitterness and iniquity of that time? and will they
          think that troops of assassins, among whom they themselves were leaders and chiefs, can be
          made a ground of accusation against him? who not only was not at <placeName
            key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, but who was utterly ignorant of everything that was
          being done at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, because he was continually
              in the country, as you yourself admit.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82" resp="perseus"><p>I fear that I
          may be wearisome to you, O judges, or that I may seem to distrust your capacity, if I
          dwell longer on matters which are so evident. The whole accusation of Erucius, as I think,
          is at an end; unless perhaps you expect me to refute the charges which he has brought
          against us of peculation and of other imaginary crimes of that sort; charges unheard of by
          us before this time, and quite novel; which he appeared to me to be spouting out of some
          other speech which he was composing against some other criminal; so wholly were they
          unconnected with either the crime of parricide, or the man who is now on his trial. But as
          he accuses us of these things with his bare word, it is sufficient to deny them with our
          bare word. If there is any point which he is keeping back to prove by witnesses, there
          also, as in this cause, he shall find us more ready than he expected.</p></div>  
        <milestone n="30" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83" resp="perseus">
        <p>I come now to that point to which my desire does not lead me, but good faith towards my
          client. For if I wished to accuse men, I should accuse those men rather by accusing whom I
          might become more important, which I have determined not to do, as long as the
          alternatives of accusing and defending are both open to me. For that man appears to me the
          most honourable who arrives at a higher rank by his own virtue, not he who rises by the
          distress and misfortunes of another. Let us cease for awhile to examine into these matters
          which are unimportant; let us inquire where the guilt is, and where it can be detected. By
          this time you will understand, O Erucius, by how many suspicious circumstances a real
          crime must be proved, although I shall not mention every thing, and shall touch on every
          thing slightly. And I would not do even that if it were not necessary, and it shall be a
          sign that I am doing it against my will, that I will not pursue the point further than the
          safety of Roscius and my own good faith requires.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84" resp="perseus"><p>You
          found no motive in Sextus Roscius; but I do find one in Titus Roscius For I have to do
          with you now, O Titus Roscius, since you are sitting there and openly professing yourself
          an enemy. We shall see about Capito afterwards, if he comes forward as a witness as I hear
          he is ready to do then he shall hear of other victories of his, which he does not suspect
          that I ever even heard. That Lucius Cassius, whom the Roman people used to consider a most
          impartial and able judge, used constantly to ask at trials, “to whom it had been any
          advantage?” The life of men is so directed that no one attempts to proceed to crime
          without some hope of advantage.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85" resp="perseus"><p>Those who were about to
          be tried avoided and dreaded him as an investigator and a judge; because, although he was
          afraid of truth, he yet seemed not so much inclined by nature to mercy, as drawn by
          circumstances to severity. I, although a man is presiding at this trial who is both brave
          against audacity, and very merciful to innocence, would yet willingly suffer myself to
          speak in behalf of Sextus Roscius either before that very acute judge himself, or before
          other judges like him, whose very name those who have to stand a trial shudder at even
          now.</p></div>  
        <milestone n="31" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86" resp="perseus">
        <p>For when those judges saw in this cause that those men are in possession of abundant
          wealth, and that he is in the greatest beggary, they would not ask who had got advantage
          from the deed, but they would connect the manifest crime and suspicion of guilt rather
          with the plunder than with the poverty. What if this be added to that consideration that
          you were previously poor? what if it be added that you are avaricious? what if it be added
          that you are audacious? what if it be added that you were the greatest enemy of the man
          who has been murdered? need any further motive be sought for, which may have impelled you
          to such a crime? But which of all these particulars can be denied?</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87" resp="perseus"><p>The poverty of the man is such that it cannot be concealed, and it is
          only the more conspicuous the more it is kept out of sight. Your avarice you make a parade
          of when you form an alliance with an utter stranger against the fortunes of a
          fellow-citizen and a relation. How audacious you are (to pass over other points), all men
          may understand from this, that out of the whole troop, that is to say, out of so many
          assassins, you alone were found to sit with the accusers, and not only to show them your
          countenance, but even to volunteer it. You must admit that you had enmity against Sextus
          Roscius, and great disputes about family affairs.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88" resp="perseus"><p>It
          remains, O judges, that we must now consider which of the two rather killed Sextus
          Roscius; did he to whom riches accrued by his death, or did he to whom beggary was the
          result? Did he who, before that, was poor, or he, who after that became most indigent? Did
          he, who burning with avarice rushes in like an enemy against his own relations, or he who
          has always lived in such a manner as to have no acquaintance with exorbitant gains, or
          with any profit beyond that which he procured with toil? Did he who, of all the brokers
            <note anchored="true">There is a pun here on the word <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >sector</foreign>, which means not only a broker, but also a cut-throat, a
            murderer.</note> is the most audacious, or he who, because of the insolence of the forum
          and of the public courts, dreads not only the bench, but even the city itself? Lastly, O
          judges, what is most material of all to the argument in my opinion did his enemy do it or
          his son?</p></div>  
              <milestone n="32" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89" resp="perseus">
        <p>If you, O Erucius, had so many and such strong arguments against a criminal, how long you
          would speak; how you would plume yourself,—time indeed would fail you before words did. In
          truth, on each of these topics the materials are such that you might spend a whole day on
          each. And I could do the same; for I will not derogate so much from my own claims, though
          I arrogate nothing, as to believe that you can speak with more fluency than I can. But I,
          perhaps, owing to the number of advocates, may be classed in the common body; the battle
          of <placeName key="perseus,Cannae">Cannae</placeName>
          <note anchored="true">There is a little dispute as to Cicero's exact meaning here. Some
            think there is a sort of pun on the similarity of sound between <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Cannensis</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">Cinnanensis</foreign> and that
            allusion is intended to the destruction of Cinna's army, in which a great number of
            Roman knights were slain. Facciolati thinks that the battle of <placeName
              key="perseus,Cannae">Cannae</placeName> is mentioned, not on account of the battle
            itself but of what followed it; so that as, after the battle of <placeName
              key="perseus,Cannae">Cannae</placeName>, the dictator was forced to intrust arms even
            to slaves, now, after the proscriptions of Sulla, the most worthless men were allowed to
            put themselves forth as accusers.</note> has made you a sufficiently respectable
          accuser. We have seen many men slain, not at Thrasymenus, but at Servilius. <note
            anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="la">Lacus Servilius</foreign> was at <placeName
              key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, and was the place where Sulla murdered a great
            many Romans, and set up their heads, even the heads of senators, to public view; so that
                <persName><surname>Seneca</surname></persName> says of the lake, <foreign
              xml:lang="la">“id enim proscriptionis Sullanae spoliorum est.”</foreign>
          </note></p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90" resp="perseus"><p>
          <quote>
            <l>“Who was not wounded there with Phrygian<note anchored="true">This is a fragment of a
                play of Ennius; by the words, “Phrygian steel” he points out that these murders were
                chiefly committed by slaves, great numbers of whom had lately been imported from
                  <placeName key="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName>. Facciolati thinks too that
                allusion is made to the <placeName key="tgn,1001742">Oriental</placeName> and
                luxurious manners of Sulla.</note> steel?”</l>
          </quote> I need not enumerate all,—the Curtii, the Marii, the Mamerci, whom age now
          exempted from battles; and, lastly, the aged Priam himself, Antistius, <note
            anchored="true">In the <title>Brutus</title> Cicero speaks of Antistius as a tolerable
            speaker; he calls him here Priam, meaning that he acted as a sort of leader and king
            among the accusers. </note> whom not only his age, but even the laws excused from going
          to battle. There are now six hundred men, whom nobody even mentions by name because of
          their meanness, who are accusers of men on charges of murdering and poisoning; all of
          whom, as far as I am concerned, I hope may find a livelihood. For there is no harm in
          there being as many dogs as possible, where there are many men to be watched, and many
          things to be guarded.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91" resp="perseus"><p>But, as is often the case, the
          violence and tumultuous nature of war brings many things to pass without the knowledge of
          the generals. While he who was administering the main government was occupied in other
          matters, there were men who in the meantime were curing their own wounds; who rushed about
          in the darkness and threw everything into confusion as if eternal night had enveloped the
          whole Republic. And by such men as these I wonder that the courts of justice were not
          burnt, that there might be no trace left of any judicial proceedings; for they did destroy
          both judges and accusers. There is this advantage, that they lived in such a manner that
          even if they wished it, they could not put to death all the witnesses; for as long as the
          race of men exists, there will not be wanting men to accuse them: as long as the state
          lasts, trials will take place. But as I began to say, both Erucius, if he had these
          arguments to use which I have mentioned, in any cause Of his, would be able to speak on
          them as long as he pleased, and I can do the same. But I choose, as I said before, to pass
          by them lightly, and only just to touch on each particular, so that all men may perceive
          that I am not accusing men of my own inclination, but only defending my own client from a
          sense of duty.</p></div>  
          <milestone n="33" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92" resp="perseus">
        <p>I see therefore that there were many causes which urged that man to this crime. Let us
          now see whether he had any opportunity of committing it. Where was Sextus Roscius
          slain?—at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. What of you, O Roscius? Where
          were you at that time?—at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. But what is that
          to the purpose? many other men were there too. As if the point now were, who of so vast a
          crowd slew him, and as if this were not rather the question, whether it is more probable
          that he who was slain at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> was slain by that
          man who was constantly at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> at that time, or
          by him who for many years had never come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>
          at all?</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93" resp="perseus"><p>Come, let us consider now the other
          circumstances which might make it easy for him. There was at that time a multitude of
          assassins, as Erucius has stated, and men were being killed with impunity. What!—what was
          that multitude? A multitude, I imagine, either of those who were occupied in getting
          possession of men's property, or of those who were hired by them to murder some one. If
          you think it was composed of those who coveted other men's property, you are one of that
          number,—you who are enriched by our wealth; if of those whom they who call them by the
          lightest name call slayers, inquire to whom they are bound, and whose dependents they are,
          believe me you will find it is some one of your own confederacy, whatever you say to the
          contrary, compare it with our defence, and by this means the cause of Sextus Roscius will
          be most easily contrasted with yours.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94" resp="perseus"><p>You will say,
          “what follows if I was constantly at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>?” I
          shall answer, “But I was never there at all.” “I confess that I am a broker, but so are
          many other men also.” “But I, as you yourself accuse me of being, am a countryman and a
          rustic.” “It does not follow at once, because I have been present with a troop of
          assassins, that I am an assassin myself.” “But at all events I, who never had even the
          acquaintance of assassins, am far removed from such a crime.” There are many things which
          may be mentioned, by which it may be understood that you had the greatest facilities for
          committing this crime, which I pass over, not only because I do not desire to accuse, but
          still more on this account,—because if I were to wish to enumerate all the murders which
          were then committed on the same account as that on which Sextus Roscius was slain, I fear
          lest my speech would seem to refer to others also.</p></div>  
              <milestone n="34" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95" resp="perseus">
        <p>Let us examine now briefly, as we have done in the other particulars, what was done by
          you, O Titus Roscius, after the death of Sextus Roscius; and these things are so open and
          notorious, that by the gods, O judges, I am unwilling to mention them. For whatever your
          conduct may be, O Titus Roscius, I am afraid of appearing to be so eager to save my
          client, as to be quite regardless whether I spare you or not. And as I am afraid of this,
          and as I wish to spare you in some degree, as far as I can, saving my duty to my client, I
          will again change my purpose. For the thoughts on your countenance present here occur to
          my mind, that you when all the rest of your companions were flying and hiding themselves
          in order that this trial might appear to be not concerning their plunder, not concerning
          this man's crime, should select this part above all others for yourself, to appear at the
          trial and sit with the accuser, by which action you gain nothing beyond causing your
          impudence and audacity to be known to all mortals.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96" resp="perseus"><p>
          After Sextus Roscius is slain, who is the first to take the news to <placeName
            key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>? Mallius Glaneia, whom I have named before, your
          own client and intimate friend. What did it concern him above all men to bring the news of
          what, if you had not previously formed some plan with reference to his death and property,
          and had formed no conspiracy with any one else, having either the crime or its reward for
          its object, concerned you least of all men? Oh, Mallius brought the news of his own
          accord! What did it concern him, I beg? or, as he did not come to <placeName
            key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName> on account of this business, did it happen by
          chance that he was the first to tell the news which he had heard at <placeName
            key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>? On what account did he come to <placeName
            key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>? I cannot conjecture, says he. I will bring the
          matter to such a point that there shall be no need of conjecture. On what account did he
          announce it first to Roscius Capito? When the house, and wife, and children of Sextus
          Roscius were at <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName>; when he had so many
          kinsmen and relations on the best possible terms with himself, on what account did it
          happen that that client of yours, the reporter of your wickedness, did it to Titus Roscius
          Capito above all men?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97" resp="perseus"><p>He was slain returning home from
          supper. It was not yet dawn when it was known at <placeName key="perseus,Ameria"
            >Ameria</placeName>. Why was this incredible speed? What does this extraordinary haste
          and expedition intimate? I do not ask who struck the blow; you have nothing to fear, O
          Glaucia. I do not shake you to see if you have any weapon about you. I am not examining
          that point; I do not think I am at all concerned with that. Since I have found out by
          whose design he was murdered, by whose hand he was murdered I do not care. I assume one
          point, which your open wickedness and the evident state of the case gives me. Where, or
          from whom, did Glaucia hear of it? Who knew it so immediately? Suppose he did hear of it
          immediately; what was the affair which compelled to take so long a journey in one night?
          What was the great necessity which pressed upon him, so as to make him, if he was going to
            <placeName key="perseus,Ameria">Ameria</placeName> of his own accord, set out from
            <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> at that time of night, and devote no part
              of the night to sleep?</p></div>  
              <milestone n="35" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98" resp="perseus">
        <p>In a case so evident as this must we seek for arguments, or hunt for conjectures? Do you
          not seem, O judges, actually to behold with your own eyes what you have been hearing? Do
          you not see that unhappy man, ignorant of his fate, returning from supper? Do you not see
          the ambush that is laid? the sudden attack? Is not Glaucia before your eyes, present at
          the murder? Is not that Titus Roscius present? Is he not with his own hands placing that
          Automedon in the chariot, the messenger of his most horrible wickedness and nefarious
          victory? Is he not entreating him to keep awake that night? to labour for his honour? to
          take the news to <placeName key="tgn,2038075">Capito</placeName> as speedily as possible?</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99" resp="perseus"><p>Why was it that be wished
              <persName><surname>Capito</surname></persName> to be the first to know it? I do not
          know, only I see this, that <persName><surname>Capito</surname></persName> is a partner in
              this property. I see that, of thirteen farms, he is in possession of three of the finest.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="100" resp="perseus"><p>I hear besides, that this suspicion is not fixed
          upon <persName><surname>Capito</surname></persName> for the first time now; that he has
          gained many infamous victories; but that this is the first very splendid <note
            anchored="true">The Latin word is <foreign xml:lang="la">lemniscatus</foreign>,
            literally, adorned with ribbons hanging down all from a garland or crown. <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Palma lemniscata</foreign> is a palm branch (i.e. a token of victory,)
            given to a gladiator or general when the victory was very remarkable. Cicero understands
            it of a murder which was connected with very great gains. Riddle, Lat. Dict. v. <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Lemniscatus</foreign>.</note> one which he has gained at <placeName
            key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>; that there is no manner of committing murder in
          which he has not murdered many men; many by the sword, many by poison. I can even tell you
          of one man whom, contrary to the custom of our ancestors, he threw from the bridge into
          the <placeName key="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>, when he was not sixty years of age;
            <note anchored="true">There is a pun here on the word <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >pons</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="la">Pons</foreign> means not only a bridge, but
            also the platform over which men passed to give their votes at elections; and men above
            sixty had no votes, and all having none were called <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >depontati</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="la">dejecti de ponte</foreign>.</note> and
          if he comes forward, or when he comes forward, for I know that he will come forward, he
          shall hear of him.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="101" resp="perseus"><p>Only let him come; let him unfold
          that volume of his which I can prove that Erucius wrote for him, which they say that he
          displayed to Sextus Roscius, and threatened that he would mention everything contained in
          it in his evidence. O the excellent witness, O judges; O gravity worthy of being attended
          to; O honourable course of life! such that you may with willing minds make your oaths
          depend upon his testimony! In truth we should not see the crimes of these men so clearly
          if cupidity, and avarice, and audacity, did not render them blind.</p></div>  
        <milestone n="36" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="102" resp="perseus">
        <p>One of them sent a swift messenger from the very scene of murder to Ameria, to his
          partner and his tutor; so that if every one wished to conceal his knowledge of whom the
          guilt belonged to, yet he himself placed his wickedness visibly before the eyes of all
          men. The other (if the immortal gods will only let him) is going to give evidence also
          against Sextus Roscius. As if the matter now in question were, whether what he said is to
          be believed, or whether what he did is to be punished. Therefore it was established by the
          custom of our ancestors, that even in the most insignificant matters, the most honourable
          men should not be allowed to give evidence in their own cause.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="103" resp="perseus"><p>Africanus, who declares by his surname that he subdued a third part of
          the whole world, still, if a case of his own were being tried, would not give evidence.
          For I do not venture to say with respect to such a man as that, if he did give evidence he
          would not be believed. See now everything is altered and changed for the worse. When there
          is a trial about property and about murder, a man is going to give evidence, who is both a
          broker and an assassin; that is, he who is himself the purchaser and possessor of that
          very property about which the trial is taking place, and who contrived the murder of the
          man whose death is being inquired into.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="104" resp="perseus"><p>What do you
          want, O most excellent man? Have you anything to say? Listen to me. Take care not to be
          wanting to yourself; your own interest to a great extent is at stake. You have done many
          things wickedly, many things audaciously, many things scandalously; one thing foolishly,
          and that of your own accord, not by the advice of Erucius. There was no need for you to
          sit there. For no man employs a dumb accuser, or calls him as a witness, who rises from
          the accuser's bench. There must be added to this, that that cupidity of yours should have
          been a little more kept back and concealed. Now what is there that any one of you desire
          to hear, when what you do is such that you seem to have done them expressly for our
          advantage against your own interest?</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="105" resp="perseus"><p>Come now, let us
          see, O judges, what followed immediately after. <milestone n="37" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/></p>
        <p>The news of the death of Sextus Roscius is carried to Volaterra, to the camp of Lucius
          Sulla, to Chrysogonus, four days after he is murdered. I now again ask who sent that
          messenger. Is it not evident that it was the same man who sent the news to Ameria?
          Chrysogonus takes care that his goods shall be immediately sold; he who had neither his
          own the man nor his estate. But how did it occur to him to wish for the farms of a man who
          was unknown to him, whom he had never seen in his life? You are accustomed, O judges, when
          you hear anything of this sort to say at once, some fellow-citizen or neighbour must have
          told him; they generally tell these things; most men are betrayed by such. Here there is
          no ground for your entertaining this suspicion.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="106" resp="perseus"><p>I will
          not argue thus. It is probable that the Roscii gave information of that matter to
          Chrysogonus, for there was of old, friendship between them and Chrysogonus; for though the
          Roscii had many ancient patrons and friends hereditarily connected with them, they ceased
          to pay any attention and respect to them, and betook themselves to the protection and
          support of Chrysogonus.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="107" resp="perseus"><p>I can say all this with truth;
          for in this case I have no need to rely on conjecture. I know to a certainty that they
          themselves do not deny that Chrysogonus made the attack on this property at their
          instigation. If you see with your own eyes who has received a part of the reward for the
          information, can you possibly doubt, O judges, who gave the information? Who then are in
          possession of that property; and to whom did Chrysogonus give a share in it? The two
          Roscii!—Any one else? No one else, O judges. Is there then any doubt that they put this
          plunder in Chrysogonus's way, who have received from him a share of the plunder?</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="108" resp="perseus"><p>Come now let us consider the action of the Roscii by
          the judgment of Chrysogonus himself. If in that contest the Roscii had done nothing which
          was worth speaking of, on what account were they presented with such rewards by
          Chrysogonus? If they did nothing more than inform him of the fact, was it not enough for
          him to thank them? Why are these farms of such value immediately given to
              <persName><surname>Capito</surname></persName>? Why does that fellow Roscius possess
          all the rest in common property with Chrysogonus? Is it not evident, O judges, that
          Chrysogonus, understanding the whole business, gave them as spoils to the Roscii?</p></div> 
            <milestone n="38" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="109" resp="perseus">
        <p><persName><surname>Capito</surname></persName> came as a deputy to the camp, as one of
          the ten chief men of Ameria. Learn from his behaviour on this deputation the whole life
          and nature and manners of the man. Unless you are of opinion, O judges, that there is no
          duty and no right so holy and solemn that his wickedness and perfidy has not tampered with
          and violated it, then judge him to be a very excellent man.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="110" resp="perseus"><p>He is the hindrance to Sulla's being informed of this affair; he
          betrays the plans and intentions of the other deputies to Chrysogonus; he gives him
          warning to take care that the affair be not conducted openly; he points out to him, that
          if the sale of the property be prevented, he will lose a large sum of money, and that he
          himself will be in danger of his life. He proceeds to spur him on, to deceive those who
          were joined in the commission with him; to warn him continually to take care; to hold out
          treacherously false hopes to the others; in concert with him to devise plans against them,
          to betray their counsels to him; with him to bargain for his share in the plunder, and,
          relying constantly on some delay or other, to cut off from his colleagues all access to
          Sulla. Lastly, owing to his being the prompter, the adviser, the go-between, the deputies
          did not see Sulla; deceived by his faith, or rather by his perfidy, as you may know from
          themselves, if the accuser is willing to produce them <note anchored="true">In a question
            of fact the accuser alone was permitted to submit witnesses; the defendant could not do
            so.</note> as witnesses, they brought back home with a false hope instead of a reality.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="111" resp="perseus"><p>In private affairs if any one had managed a business
          entrusted to him, I will not say maliciously for the sake of his own gain and advantage,
          but even carelessly, our ancestors thought that he had incurred the greatest disgrace.
          Therefore, legal proceedings for betrayal of a commission are established, involving
          penalties no less disgraceful than those for theft. I suppose because, in cases where we
          ourselves cannot be present, the vicarious faith of friends is substituted; and he who
          impairs that confidence, attacks the common bulwark of all men, and as far as depends on
          him, disturbs the bonds of society. For we cannot do everything ourselves; different
          people are more capable in different matters. On that account friendships are formed, that
          the common advantage of all may be secured by mutual good offices.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="112" resp="perseus"><p>Why do you undertake a commission, if you are either going to neglect
          it or to turn it to your own advantage? Why do you offer yourself to me, and by feigned
          service hinder and prevent my advantage? Get out of the way, I will do my business by
          means of some one else. You undertake the burden of a duty which you think you are able to
          support; a duty which does not appear very heavy to those who are not very worthless
          themselves.
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        This fault therefore is very base, because it violates two most holy things, friendship
          and confidence; for men commonly do not entrust anything except to a friend, and do not
          trust any one except one whom they think faithful. It is therefore the part of a most
          abandoned man, at the same time to dissolve friendship and to deceive him who would not
          have been injured unless he had trusted him.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="113" resp="perseus"><p>Is it not
          so? In the most trifling affairs be who neglects a commission, must be condemned by a most
          dishonouring sentence; in a matter of this importance, when he to whom the character of
          the dead, the fortunes of the living have been recommended and entrusted, loads the dead
          with ignominy and the living with poverty, shall he be reckoned among honourable men,
          shall he even be reckoned a man at all? In trifling affairs, in affairs of a private
          nature, even carelessness is accounted a crime, and is liable to a sentence branding a man
          with infamy; because, if the commission be properly executed, the man who has given the
          commission may feel at his ease and be careless about it: he who has undertaken the
          commission may not. In so important an affair as this, which was done by public order and
          so entrusted to him, what punishment ought to be inflicted on that man who has not
          hindered some private advantage by his carelessness, but has polluted and stained by his
          treachery the solemnity of the very commission itself? or by what sentence shall he be
          condemned?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="114" resp="perseus"><p>If Sextus Roscius had entrusted this matter
          to him privately to transact and determine upon with Chrysogonus, and to involve his
          credit in the matter if it seemed to him to be necessary—if he who had undertaken the
          affair had turned ever so minute a point of the business to his own advantage, would he
          not, if convicted by the judge, have been compelled to make restitution, and would he not
          have lost all credit?</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="115" resp="perseus"><p>Now it is not Sextus Roscius who
          gave him this commission, but what is a much more serious thing, Sextus Roscius himself,
          with his character, his life, and all his property, is publicly entrusted by the senators
          to Roscius; and, of this trust, Titus Roscius has converted not some small portion to his
          own advantage, but has turned him entirely out of his property; he has bargained for three
          farms for himself; he has considered the intention of the senators and of all his
          fellow-citizens of just as much value as his own integrity.</p></div>  
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="116" resp="perseus">
        <p>Moreover, consider now, O judges, the other matters, that you may see that no crime can
          be imagined with which that fellow has not disgraced himself. In less important matters,
          to deceive one's partner is a most shameful thing, and equally base with that which I have
          mentioned before. And rightly; because he who has communicated an affair to another thinks
          that he has procured assistance for himself. To whose good faith, then, shall a man have
          recourse who is injured by the want of faith in the man whom he has trusted? But these
          offences are to be punished with the greatest severity which are guarded against with the
          greatest difficulty. We can be reserved towards strangers; intimate friends must see many
          things more openly; but how can we guard against a companion? for even to be afraid of him
          is to do violence to the rights of duty. Our ancestors therefore rightly thought that he
          who had deceived his companion ought not to be considered in the number of good men.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="117" resp="perseus"><p>But Titus Roscius did not deceive one friend alone
          in a money matter, (which, although it be a grave offence, still appears possible in some
          degree to be borne) but he led on, cajoled, and deserted nine most honourable men,
          betrayed them to their adversaries, and deceived them with every circumstance of fraud and
          perfidy. They who could suspect nothing of his wickedness, ought not to have been afraid
          of the partner of their duties; they did not see his malice, they trusted his false
          speech. Therefore these most honourable men are now, on account of his treachery, thought
          to have been incautious and improvident He who was at the beginning a traitor, then a
          deserter—who at first reported the counsels of his companions to their adversaries, and
          then entered into a confederacy with the adversaries themselves, even now terrifies us,
          and threatens us, adorned with his three farms, that is, with the prizes of his
          wickedness. In such a life as his, O judges, amid such numerous and enormous crimes, you
          will find this crime too, with which the present trial is concerned.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="118" resp="perseus"><p>In truth you ought to make investigation on this principle; where you
          see that many things have been done avariciously, many audaciously, many wickedly, many
          perfidiously, there you ought to think that wickedness also lies hid among so many crimes;
          although this indeed does not lie hid at all, which is so manifest and exposed to view,
          that it may be perceived, not by those vices which it is evident exist in him, but even if
          any one of those vices be doubted of, he may be convicted of it by the evidence of this
          crime. What then, I ask, shall we say, O judges? Does this gladiator seem entirely to have
          thrown off his former character? or does that pupil of his seem to yield but little to his
          master in skill? Their avarice is equal, their dishonesty similar, their impudence is the
          same; the audacity of the one is twin-sister to the audacity of the other.</p></div> 
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="119" resp="perseus">
        <p>Now forsooth, since you have seen the good faith of the master, listen to the justice of
          the pupil. I have already said before, that two slaves have been continually begged of
          them to be put to the question. You have always refused it, O Titus Roscius. I ask of you
          whether they who asked it were unworthy to obtain it? or had he, on whose behalf they
          asked it, no influence with you? or did the matter itself appear unjust? The most noble
          and respectable men of our state, whom I have named before, made the request, who have
          lived in such a manner, and are so esteemed by the Roman people, that there is no one who
          would not think whatever they said reasonable. And they made the request on behalf of a
          most miserable and unfortunate man, who would wish even himself to be submitted to the
          torture, provided the inquiry into his father's death might go on.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="120" resp="perseus"><p>Moreover, the thing demanded of you was such that it made no difference
          whether you refused it or confessed yourself guilty of the crime. And as this is the case,
          I ask of you why you refused it? When Sextus Roscius was murdered they were there. The
          slaves themselves, as far as I am concerned, I neither accuse nor acquit; but the point
          which I see you contending for, namely, that they be not submitted to the question, is
          full of suspicion. But the reason of their being held in such horror by you, must be that
          they know something, which, if they were to tell, will be pernicious to you. Oh, say you,
          it is unjust to put questions to slaves against their masters. Is any such question meant
          to be put? For Sextus Roscius is the defendant, and when inquiry is being made into his
          conduct, you do not say that you are their masters. Oh, they are with Chrysogonus. I
          suppose so; Chrysogonus is so taken with their learning and accomplishments, that be
          wishes these men—men little better than labourers from the training of a rustic master of
          a family at Ameria, to mingle with his elegant youths, masters of every art and every
          refinement—youths picked out of many of the politest households.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="121" resp="perseus"><p>That cannot be the truth, O judges; it is not probable that Chrysogonus
          has taken a fancy to their learning or their politeness, or that he should be acquainted
          with their industry and fidelity in the business of a household. There is something which
          is hidden; and the more studiously it is bidden and kept back by them, so much the more is
          it visible and conspicuous.</p></div>  
          <milestone n="42" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="122" resp="perseus"><p>What, then, are we to think? Is Chrysogonus unwilling that these men shall be put to the
          question for the sake of concealing his own crime? Not so, O judges; I do not think that
          the same arguments apply to every one. As far as I am concerned, I have no suspicion of
          the sort respecting Chrysogonus, and this is not the first time that it has occurred to me
          to say so. You recollect that I so divided the cause at the beginning; into the
          accusation, the whole arguing of which was entrusted to Erucius; and into audacity, the
          business of which was assigned to the Roscii;—whatever crime, whatever wickedness,
          whatever bloodshed there is, all that is the business of the Roscii. We say that the
          excessive interest and power of Chrysogonus is a hindrance to us, and can by no means be
          endured; and that it ought not only to be weakened, but even to be punished by you, since
          you have the power given to you.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="123" resp="perseus"><p>I think as follows;
          that he who wishes these men to be put to the question, whom it is evident were present
          when the murder was committed, is desirous to find out the truth; that he who refuses it,
          though he does not dare admit it in words, yet does in truth by his actions, confesses
          himself guilty of the crime. I said at the beginning, O judges, that I was unwilling to
          say more of the wickedness of those men than the cause required, and than necessity itself
          compelled me to say. For many circumstances can be alleged, and every one of them can be
          discussed with many arguments. But I cannot do for any length of time, nor diligently,
          what I do against my will, and by compulsion. Those things which could by no means be
          passed over, I have lightly touched upon, O judges; those things which depend upon
          suspicion, and which, if I begin to speak of them, will require a copious discussion, I
          commit to your capacities and to your conjectures.</p></div>  
              <milestone n="43" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="124" resp="perseus">
        <p>I come now to that golden name of Chrysogonus, <note anchored="true">This is a pun on the
            name of Chrysogonus, all derived from the Greek word <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >xruso/s</foreign>, gold; and <foreign xml:lang="grc">go/nos</foreign>, birth.</note>
          under which name the whole confederacy is set up, concerning whom, O judges, I am at a
          loss both how to speak and how to hold my tongue; for if I say nothing, I leave out a
          great part of my argument, and if I speak, I fear that not he alone (about whom I am not
          concerned), but others also may think themselves injured; although the case is such that
          it does not appear necessary to say much against the common cause of the brokers. For this
          cause is, in truth, a novel and an extraordinary cause. Chrysogonus is the purchaser of
          the property of Sextus Roscius.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="125" resp="perseus"><p>Let us see this first,
          on what pretence the property of that man was sold, or how they could be sold. And I will
          not put this question, O judges, so as to imply that it is a scandalous thing for the
          property of an innocent man to be sold at all. For if these things are to be freely
          listened to and freely spoken, Sextus Roscius was not a man of such importance in the
          state as to make us complain of his fortune more than of that of others. But I ask this,
          how could they be sold even by that very law which is enacted about prescriptions, whether
          it be the Valerian <note anchored="true">Valerius Flaccus had been created Interrex on the
            death of the two consuls, Marius and <persName><surname>Carbo</surname></persName>. He
            appointed Sulla dictator, and passed a law that whatever Sulla had done should be
            ratified; so that Cicero's meaning here is, that he does not know which was the nominal
            author of the law he is quoting, Valerius or Sulla.</note> or <placeName
            key="tgn,2257061">Cornelian</placeName> law,—for neither know nor understand which it
            is—but by that very law itself how could the property of Sextus Roscius be sold?</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="126" resp="perseus"><p>For they say it is written in it, “that the property
          of those men who have been proscribed is to be sold”; in which number Sextus Roscius is
          not one: “or of those who have been slain in the garrisons of the opposite party.” While
          there, were any garrisons, he was in the garrisons of Sulla; after they laid down their
          arms, returning from supper, he was slain at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>
          in a time of perfect peace. If he was slain by law, I admit that his property was sold by
          law too; but if it is evident that he was slain contrary to all laws, not merely to old
          laws, but to the new ones also, then I ask by what right, or in what manner, or by what
          law they were sold?</p></div>  
      <milestone n="44" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="127" resp="perseus">
        <p>You ask, against whom do I say this, O Erucius. Not against him whom you are meaning and
          thinking of; for both my speech from the very beginning, and also I is own eminent virtue,
          at all times has acquitted Sulla. I say that Chrysogonus did all this in order to tell
          lies; in order to make out Roscius to have been a bad citizen; in order to represent him
          as slain among the opposite party; in order to prevent Lucius Sulla from being rightly
          informed of these matters by the deputies from Ameria. Last of all, I suspect that this
          property was never sold at all; and this matter I will open presently, O judges, if you
          will give me leave.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="128" resp="perseus"><p>For I think it is set down in the
          law on what day these proscriptions and sales shall take place, forsooth on the first of
          January. Some months afterwards the man was slain, and his property is said to have been
          sold. Now, either this property has never been returned in the public accounts, and we are
          cheated by this scoundrel more cleverly than we think, or, if they were returned, then the
          public accounts have some way or other been tampered with, for it is quite evident that
          the property could not have been sold according to law. I am aware, O judges, that I am
          investigating this point prematurely, and that I am erring as greatly as if, while I ought
          to be curing a mortal sickness of Sextus Roscius, I were mending a whitlow; for he is not
          anxious about his money; he has no regard to any pecuniary advantage; he thinks he can
          easily endure his poverty, if he is released from this unworthy suspicion, from this false
          accusation.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="129" resp="perseus"><p>But I entreat you, O judges, to listen to
          the few things I have still to say, under the idea that I am speaking partly for myself,
          and party for Sextus Roscius. For the things which appear to me unworthy and intolerable,
          and which I think concern all men unless we are prudent, those things I now mention to you
          for my own sake, from the real feelings and indignation of my mind. What relates to the
          misfortunes of the life, and to the cause of my client, and what he wishes to be said for
          him, and with what condition he will be content, you shall hear, O judges, immediately at
          the end of my speech. I ask this of Chrysogonus of my own accord, leaving Sextus Roscius
          out of the question.</p></div>  
              <milestone n="45" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="130" resp="perseus">
        <p>First of all, why the property of a virtuous citizen was sold? Next, why the property of
          a man who was neither proscribed, nor slain in the garrisons of the opposite party, were
          sold; when the law was made against them alone? Next, why were they sold long after the
          day which is appointed by the law? Next, why were they sold for go little! And if he shall
          choose, as worthless and wicked freedmen are accustomed to do, to refer all this to his
          patrons, he will do himself no good by that For there is no one who does not know that on
          account of the immensity of his business, many men did many things of which Lucius Sulla
          knew very little.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="131" resp="perseus"><p>Is it right, then, that in these
          matters anything should be passed over without the ruler knowing it? It is not right, O
          judges, but it is inevitable. In truth, if the great and kind
              <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, by whose will and command the heaven,
          the earth, and the seas are governed, has often by too violent winds, or by immoderate
          tempests, or by too much heat, or by intolerable cold, injured men, destroyed cities, or
          ruined the crops; nothing of which do we suppose to have taken place, for the sake of
          causing injury, by the divine intention, but owing to the power and magnitude of the
          affairs of the world; but on the other hand we see that the advantages which we have the
          benefit of, and the light which we enjoy, and the air which we breathe, are all given to
          and bestowed upon us by him; how can we wonder that Lucius Sulla, when he alone was
          governing the whole republic, and administering the affairs of the whole world, and
          strengthening by his laws the majesty of the empire, which he had recovered by arms,
          should have been forced to leave some things unnoticed? Unless this is strange that human
          faculties have not a power which divine might is unable to attain to.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="132" resp="perseus"><p>But to say no more about what has happened already, cannot any one
          thoroughly understand from what is happening now, that Chrysogonus alone is the author and
          contriver of all this, and that it is he who caused Sextus Roscius to be accused? this
          trial in which Erucius says that he is the accuser out of regard for honour <gap
            reason="lost"/>
          <milestone n="46" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
       They think they are leading a convenient life, and one arranged rationally, who have a
          house among the Salentii or Brutii, from which they can scarcely receive news three times
          a year.</p></div> 
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="133" resp="perseus"><p>Another comes down to you from his palace on
          the <placeName key="tgn,2118187">Palatine</placeName>; he has for the purposes of
          relaxation to his mind a pleasant suburban villa, and many farms besides, and not one
          which is not beautiful and contiguous; a house filled with Corinthian and Delian vessels,
          among which is that celebrated stove which he has lately bought at so great a price, that
          passers by, who heard the money being counted out, thought that a farm was being sold.
          What quantities besides of embossed plate, of embroidered quilts; of paintings, of
          statues, and of marble, do you think he has in his house? All, forsooth, that in a time of
          disturbance and rapine can be crammed into one house from the plunder of many magnificent
          families. But why should I mention how vast a household too was his, and in what various
          trades was it instructed?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="134" resp="perseus"><p>I say nothing of those
          ordinary arts, cooks, bakers, and litter-bearers; he has so many slaves to gratify his
          mind and ears, that the whole neighbourhood resounds with the daily music of voices, and
          stringed instruments, and flutes. In such a life as this, O judges, how great a daily
          expense, and what extravagance do you think there must be? And what banquets? Honourable
          no doubt in such a house; if that is to be called a house rather than a workshop of
          wickedness, and a lodging for every sort of iniquity.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="135" resp="perseus">
          <p>In what a style he himself flutters through the forum, with his hair curled and perfumed,
          and with a great retinue of citizens, you yourselves behold, O judges; in truth you see
          how he despises every one, how he thinks no one a human being but himself, how he thinks
          himself the only happy, the only powerful man. But if I were to wish too mention what he
          does and what he attempts, O judges, I am afraid that some ignorant people would think
          that I wish to injure the cause of the nobility, and to detract from their victory;
          although I have a right to find fault if anything in that party displeases me. For I am
          not afraid that any one will suppose that I have a disposition disaffected to the cause of
          the nobility.</p></div>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="136" resp="perseus">
        <p>They who know me, know that I, to the extent of my small and insignificant power, (when
          that which I was most eager for could not be brought about, I mean an accommodation
          between the parties) laboured to ensure the victory of that party which got it. For who
          was there who did not see that meanness was disputing with dignity for the highest
          honours? a contest in which it was the part of an abandoned citizen not to unite himself
          to those, by whose safety dignity at home and authority abroad would be preserved. And
          that all this was done, and that his proper honour and rank was restored to every one, I
          rejoice, O judges, and am exceedingly delighted; and I know that it was all done by the
          kindness of the gods, by the zeal of the Roman people, by the wisdom and government, and
          good fortune <note anchored="true">Cicero dwells on the <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >felicitas</foreign> of Sulla, because <foreign xml:lang="la">Felix</foreign> was the
            name which Sulla himself assumed, priding himself especially on his good fortune.
          </note> of Lucius Sulla.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="137" resp="perseus"><p>I have no business to find
          fault with punishment having been inflicted on those who laboured with all their energies
          on the other side; and I approve of honours having been paid to the brave men whose
          assistance was eminent in the transaction of all these matters. And I consider that the
          struggle was to a great extent with this object, and I confess that I shared in that
          desire in the part I took. But if the object was, and if arms were taken with the view of
          causing the lowest of the people to be enriched with the property of others, and of
          enabling them to make attacks on the fortunes of every one, and if it is unlawful not only
          to hinder that by deed, but even to blame it in words, then the Roman people seems to me
          not to have been strengthened and restored by that war, but to have been subdued and
          crushed.</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="138" resp="perseus"><p>But the ease is totally different: nothing of
          this, O judges, is the truth: the cause of the nobility will not only not be injured if
          you resist these men, but it will even be embellished. 
              <milestone n="48" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
              In truth, they who are inclined to find fault with this complain that Chrysogonus has so
          much influence; they who praise it, declare that he has not so much allowed him. And now
          it is impossible for any one to be either so foolish or so worthless as to say: “I wish it
          were allowed me, I would have said...” You may say... “I would have done...” You may do...
          No one hinders you. “I would have decreed...” “Decree, only decree rightly, every one will
          approve.” “I should have judged...” All will praise you if you judge rightly and properly.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="139" resp="perseus"><p>While it was necessary and while the ease made it
          inevitable, one man had all the power, and after he created magistrates and established
          laws, his own proper office and authority was restored to every one. And if those who
          recovered it wish to retain it, they will be able to retain it for ever. But if they
          either participate in or approve of these acts of murder and rapine, these enormous and
          prodigal expenses—I do not wish to say anything too severe against them; not even as an
          omen; but this one thing I do say; unless those nobles of ours are vigilant, and virtuous,
          and brave, and merciful, they must abandon their honours to those men in whom these
          qualities do exist.</p></div>  
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="140" resp="perseus"><p>Let them, therefore, cease at
          least to say that a man speaks badly, if he speaks truly and with freedom; let them cease
          to make common cause with Chrysogonus; let them cease to think, if he be injured, that any
          injury has been done to them; let them see how shameful and miserable a thing it is that
          they, who could not tolerate the splendour of the knights, should be able to endure the
          domination of a most worthless slave—a domination, which, O judges, was formerly exerted
          in other matters, but now you see what a road it is making for itself, what a course it is
          aiming at, against your good faith, against your oaths, against your decisions, against
          almost the only thing which remains uncorrupted and holy in the state.</p></div>  
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="141" resp="perseus"><p>Does Chrysogonus think that in this particular too he has some
          influence? Does her even wish to be powerful in this? O miserable and bitter circumstance!
          Nor, in truth, am I indignant at this, because I am afraid that he may have some
          influence; but I complain of the mere fact of his having dared this, of his having hoped
          that with such men as these he could have any influence to the injury of an innocent man.
            <milestone n="49" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        Is it for this that the nobility has roused itself, that it has recovered the republic by
          arms and the sword—in order that freedmen and slaves might be able to maltreat the
          property of the nobles, and all your fortunes and ours, at their pleasure?</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="142" resp="perseus"><p>If that was the object, I confess that I erred in being anxious
          for their success. I admit that I was mad in espousing their party, although I espoused
          it, O judges, without taking up arms. But if the victory of the nobles ought to be an
          ornament and an advantage to the republic and the Roman people, then, too, my speech ought
          to be very acceptable to every virtuous and noble man. But if there be any one who thinks
          that he and his cause is injured when Chrysogonus is found fault with, he does not
          understand his cause, I may almost say he does not know himself. For the cause will be
          rendered more splendid by resisting every worthless man. The worthless favourers of
          Chrysogonus, who think that his cause and theirs are identical, are injured themselves by
          separating themselves from such splendour.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="143" resp="perseus"><p>But all
          this that I have been now saying, as I mentioned before, is said on my own account, though
          the republic, and my own indignation, and the injuries done by these fellows, have
          compelled me to say it. But Roscius is indignant at none of these things; he accuses no
          one; he does not complain of the loss of his patrimony; he, ignorant of the world, rustic
          and down that he is, thinks that all those things which you say were done by Sulla were
          done regularly, legally and according to the law of nations. If he is only exempted from
          blame and acquitted of this nefarious accusation, he will be glad to leave the court.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="144" resp="perseus"><p>If he is freed from this unworthy suspicion, he says
          that he can give up all his property with equanimity. He begs and entreats you, O
          Chrysogonus, if he has converted no part of his father's most ample possessions to his own
          use; if he has defrauded you in no particular; if he has given up to you and paid over and
          weighed out to you all his possessions with the most scrupulous faith; if he has given up
          to you the very garment with which he was clothed, and the ring off his finger; if he has
          stripped himself bare of everything, and has excepted nothing—he entreats you, I say, that
          he may be allowed to pass his life in innocence and indigence, supported by the assistance
          of his friends.</p></div>  
              <milestone n="50" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="145" resp="perseus">
        <p>“You are in possession of my farms,” says he; “I am living on the charity of others; I do
          not object to that, both because I have a calm mind, and because it is inevitable. My own
          house is open to you, and is closed against myself. I endure that. You are master of my
          numerous household; I have not one slave. I submit to that, and think it is to be borne.”
          What would you have more? What are you aiming at? Why are you attacking me now? In what
          point do you think your desires injured by me? In what point do I stand in the way of your
          advantage? In what do I hinder you? If you wish to slay the man for the sake of his
          spoils, you have despoiled him. What do you want more? If you want to slay him out of
          enmity, what enmity have you against him whose farms you took possession of before you
          knew himself? If you fear him, can you fear anything from him who you see is unable to
          ward off so atrocious an injury from himself? If, because the possessions which belonged
          to Roscius have become yours, on that account you seek to destroy his son, do you not show
          that you are afraid of that which you above all other men ought not to be afraid of;
          namely, that sometime or other their father's property may be restored to the children of
          proscribed persons?</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="146" resp="perseus"><p>You do wrong, O Chrysogonus, if
          you place greater hope of being able to preserve your purchase, than in those exploits
          which Lucius Sulla has performed But if you have no cause for wishing this unhappy man to
          be afflicted with such a grievous calamity; if he has given up to you everything but his
          life, and has reserved to himself nothing of his paternal property, not even as a memorial
          of his father—then, in the name of the gods, what is the meaning of this cruelty, of this
          savage and inhuman disposition? What bandit was ever so wicked, what pirate was ever so
          barbarous, as to prefer stripping off his spoils from his victim stained with his blood,
          which he might possess his plunder unstained, without blood?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="147" resp="perseus"><p>You know that the man has nothing, dares do nothing, has no power, has
          never harboured a thought against your estate; and yet you attack him whom you cannot
          fear, and ought not to hate; and when you see he has nothing left which you can take away
          from him—unless you are indignant at this, that you see him sitting with his clothes on in
          this court whom you turned naked out of his patrimony, as if off a wreck; as if you did
          not know that be is both fed and clothed by Caecilia, the daughter of Balearicus, <note
            anchored="true">In the tenth chapter she is called the daughter of Metellus Nepos; so,
            if the reading there be correct, it must be corrupt here, which is probably the case.
            According to Graevius, she was a woman held in such esteem that, in the Marsic war, the
            temple of Juno Sospita was restored by a decree of the senate in compliance with a dream
            seen by her, as Cicero records in the treatise <title>De Divinatione</title>.</note> the
          sister of Nepos, a most incomparable woman, who, though she had a most illustrious father,
          most honourable uncles, a most accomplished brother, yet, though she was a woman, carried
          her virtue so far, as to confer on them no less honour by her character than she herself
          received from their dignity.</p></div>  
          <milestone n="51" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/>
          <milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="148" resp="perseus">
        <p>Does it appear to you a shameful thing that he is defended with earnestness? Believe me,
          if, in return for the hospitality and kindness of his father, all his hereditary friends
          were to choose to be present and dared to speak with freedom, he would be defended
          numerously enough; and if because of the greatness of the injury, and because the
          interests of the whole republic are imperilled by his danger, they all were to punish this
          conduct, you would not in truth be able to sit in that place. Now he is defended so that
          his adversaries ought not to be indignant at it, and ought not to think that they are
          surpassed in power.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="149" resp="perseus"><p>What is done at home is done by
          means of Caecilia; the management of what takes place in the forum and court of justice,
          Messala, as you, O judges, see, has undertaken. And if he were of an age and strength
          equal to it, he would speak himself for Sextus Roscius. But since his age is an obstacle
          to his speaking, and also his modesty which sets off his age, he has entrusted the cause
          to me, who he knew was desirous of it for his sake, and who ought to be so, He himself, by
          his assiduity, by his wisdom, by his influence, and by his industry, has taken care that
          the life of Sextus Roscius, having been saved out of the bands of assassins, should be
          committed to the decisions of the judges. Of a truth, O judges, it was for this nobility
          that the greatest part of the city was in arms; this was all done that the nobles might be
          restored to the state, who would act as you see Messala acting; who would defend the life
          of an innocent man; who would resist injury; who would rather show what power they had in
          procuring the safety than the destruction of another. And if all who were born in the same
          rank did the same, the republic would be less harassed by them, and they themselves would
          be less harassed by envy.</p></div>  
            <milestone n="52" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="150" resp="perseus">
        <p>But if, O judges, we cannot prevail with Chrysogonus to be content with our money, and
          not to aim at our life; if he cannot be induced, when he has taken from us everything
          which was our private property, not to wish to take away this light of life also which we
          have in common with all the world; if he does not consider it sufficient to glut his
          avarice with money, if he be not also dyed with blood cruelly shed—there is one refuge, O
          judges; there is one hope left to Sextus Roscius, the same which is left to the
          republic—your ancient kindness and mercy; and if that remain, we can even yet be saved.
          But if that cruelty which at present stalks abroad in the republic has made your
          dispositions also more harsh and cruel, (but that can never be the case,) then there is an
          end of everything, O judges; it is better to live among brute beasts than in such a savage
          state of things as this.</p></div>  
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="151" resp="perseus"><p>Are you reserved for this?
          Are you chosen for this? to condemn those whom cut-throats and assassins have not been
          able to murder? Good generals are accustomed to do this when they engage in battle—to
          place soldiers in that spot where they think the enemy will retreat, and then if any
          escape from the battle they make an onset on them unexpectedly. I suppose in the same way
          those purchasers of property think that you, that such men as you, are sitting here to
          catch those who have escaped out of their hands. God forbid, O judges, that this which our
          ancestors thought fit to style the public council should now be considered a guard to
          brokers!</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="152" resp="perseus"><p>Do not you perceive, O judges, that the sole
          object of all this is to get rid of the children of proscribed persons by any means; and
          that the first step to such a proceeding is sought for in your oaths and in the danger of
          Sextus Roscius? Is there any doubt to whom the guilt belongs, when you see on one side a
          broker, an enemy, an assassin, the same being also now our accuser, and on the other side
          a needy man, the son of the murdered man, highly thought of by his friends, on whom not
          only no crime but no suspicion even can be fixed? Do you see anything else whatever
          against Roscius except that his father's property has been sold? </p></div> 
          <milestone n="53" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="153" resp="perseus"><p>And if you also undertake that cause; if you offer
          your aid in that business; if you sit there in order that the children of those men whose
          goods have been sold may be brought before you; beware, in God's name, O judges, lest a
          new and much more cruel proscription shall seem to have been commenced by you. Though the
          former one was directed against those who could take arms, yet the Senate would not adopt
          it lest anything should appear to be done by the public authority more severe than had
          been established by the usages of our ancestors. And unless you by your sentence reject
          and spurn from yourselves this one which concerns their children and the cradles of their
          infant babes, consider, in God's name, O judges, to what a state you think the republic
          will arrive.</p></div>  
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="154" resp="perseus"><milestone unit="Para"/>
        <p>It behoves wise men, and men endowed with the authority and power with which you are
          endowed, to remedy especially those evils by which the republic is especially injured.
          There is not one of you who does not understand that the Roman people, who used formerly
          to be thought extremely merciful towards its enemies, is at present suffering from cruelty
          exercised towards its fellow-citizens. Remove this disease out of the state, O judges! Do
          not allow it to remain any longer in the republic; having not only this evil in itself,
          that it has destroyed so many citizens in a most atrocious manner, but that through
          habituating them to sights of distress, it has even taken away clemency from the hearts of
          most merciful men. For when every hour we see or hear of something very cruel being done,
          even we who are by nature most merciful, through the constant repetition of miseries, lose
          from our minds every feeling of humanity. </p></div>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
