<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>For P. Quinctius</title>
        <title>For Quinctius, Sextus Roscius, Quintus Roscius, against Quintus Caecilius, and against
          Verres</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
        <editor role="translator" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor> <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder> 
      </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>  <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
            <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
              Yonge</title><idno type="OCLC">4709897</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons</publisher>
              <date>1903</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
      <cRefPattern n="section"
        matchPattern="(\w+)"
        replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
        <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
      </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      
      <!-- <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:milestone[@n='$1']/tei:milestone[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:milestone[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="chapter" delim="."/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
    <!--
      <refsDecl n="text=Ver.">
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState delim=" " unit="actio"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="book"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="fre">French</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2016-02-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Moved front matter for more uniform treatment within series.</change>
      <change when="2016-01-22" who="Lisa Cerrato">bumped urn; CTS work</change>
      <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2014-07" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2010-09-03">cleaned up log keyword</change>
      <change who="student_AD" when="2010-07-08"> fixing place tags - AD</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-10-09">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed 
chunking for cic. ver. to text:actio:book:section in order for bibls to work</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2009-06-03">fixed bad bibls</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2006-05-05">fixed date tags</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2006-02-10">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2005-08-01">removed stray item tags</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2005-07-25">Converted to XML</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2003-10-10">fixed four random typos</change>
      <change who="yorkc" when="2003-07-01">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions;
minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2002-10-02">fixed typo you have not this to you have not heard this</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="2000-03-04">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="1996-11-30">revised and proofread again</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="1999-10-14">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="1999-10-01">fixed valour for velour</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="1999-08-12">Fixed refsDecl</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Minor tagging changes.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Lisa's edits.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-09-01">Added sections.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Changed Quint. abbreviation to Quinct.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Added to repository. Passes TEI parsing.</change>
      <change when="1997-03-19" who="DAS">ed.</change>
    
    </revisionDesc>
    
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
<div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi001.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
  <head>The speech of M. T. Cicero as the advocate of P. Quinctius.</head>
  <div type="commentary" resp="ed">
    <head>The Argument</head>
    <p>Caius Quinctius and Sextus Naevius, one of the public criers, had been partners,
      having their chief business in Gallia Narbonensis—Caius died, and left his
      brother Publius his heir, between whom and Naevius there arose disputes concerning the
      division of the property of the partnership. Caius had left some debts, and Publius
      proposed to sell some lands which his brother had acquired as private property near
      <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbonne</placeName>, for the purpose of liquidating
      them. Naevius interposed difficulties in the way of his doing so, and by various
      artifices tried to make it appear that Quinctius had forfeited his recognizances;
      which would have given a different complexion to the whole case, as to forfeit one's
      recognizances was a crime liable to the punishment of <foreign xml:lang="la">infamia</foreign> at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. Cicero
      undertook the defence of Quinctius at the request of Roscius the
      actor—Naevius's cause was conducted by Hortensius, the greatest advocate at
      <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. It is doubtful whether this really
      was the first cause in which Cicero was engaged, as many think that he himself speaks
      in this oration of having been concerned in other trials previously, and that the
      speech for Sextus Roscius was his first. Quinctius gained the verdict.</p></div>
<milestone n="1" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus">
          <p>The two things which have the greatest influence in a state,—namely, the
            greatest interest, and eloquence, are both making against us at the present moment; and
            while I am awed <note anchored="true">The Latin is <foreign xml:lang="la">quorum alteram
                  <emph>vereor</emph>, alteram <emph>metuo</emph></foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="la">vereor</foreign> expressing a slighter degree of alarm than <foreign xml:lang="la">metuo</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="la">timeo</foreign>, and also one arising rather
              from the character and dignity of the adversary, than from any apprehension of
              consequences to oneself.</note> by the one, O Caius Aquillius, I am in fear of the
            other:—I am somewhat awed, apprehending that the eloquence of Quinctius
            Hortensius may embarrass me in speaking; but I am in no slight fear lest the interest of
            Sextus Naevius may injure Publius Quinctius.</p></div> 
  
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>And yet it
            would not seem so disastrous for us that these things should exist in the highest degree
            in the other party, if they existed also to a moderate extent in us; but the fact is,
            that I, who have neither sufficient experience nor much ability, am brought into
            comparison with a most eloquent advocate; and that Publius Quinctius, who has but small
            influence, no riches, and few friends, is contending with a most influential adversary.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>And, moreover, we have this additional disadvantage,
            that Marcus Junius, who has several times pleaded this cause before you, O Aquillius, a
            man practised in the conduct of other causes also, and much and frequently concerned in
            this particular one, is at this moment absent, being engaged on his new commission;
              <note anchored="true">It is not known what this <foreign xml:lang="la">legatio</foreign>
              was.</note> and so they have had recourse to me, who, even if I had all other
            requisite qualifications in ever so high a degree, have certainly scarcely had time
            enough to be able to understand so important a business, having so many points of
            dispute involved in it</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>so that also, which has been
            used to be an assistance to me in other causes, is wanting to me in this one; for in
            proportion to my want of ability, have I endeavoured to make amends for that want by
            industry, and unless time and space be given to one, it cannot be seen how great his
            industry is. But the greater our disadvantages, O Caius Aquillius, are, with so much the
            more favourable a disposition ought you, and those who are your colleagues in this
            trial, to listen to our words, that the truth, though weakened by many disadvantages,
            may be at last reestablished by the equity of such men as you.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>But if you, being the judge, shall appear to be no protection to a
            desolate and helpless condition against power and influence; if before this tribunal the
            cause is found to depend on interest, not on truth; then indeed there is nothing any
            longer holy and uncontaminated in the state—no hope that the firmness and
            virtue of the judge may counterbalance the lowly condition of any one. But undoubtedly
            before you and your colleagues truth will prevail, or else, if it be driven from this
            place by power and influence, it will not be able to find any place where it can stand.
<milestone n="2" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>I do not say this, O Caius Aquillius, because I have any doubt of your own good faith
            and constancy, or because Publius Quinctius ought not to have the greatest hopes from
            those whom you have called in as your assessors, being, as they are, among the most
            eminent <note anchored="true">Their names were Lucius Lucilius, Publius Quintilius, and
              Marcus Marcellus; “The <foreign xml:lang="la">judex</foreign> was generally
              aided by advisers learned in the law, (<foreign xml:lang="la">jurisconsulti</foreign>,)
              who were said <foreign xml:lang="la">in concilio adesse</foreign>, but the <foreign xml:lang="la">judex</foreign> alone was empowered to give judgment.” Smith,
              Dict. Ant. v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Judex</foreign>.</note> men in the state.</p></div> 
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>What then? In the first place, the magnitude of the danger
            causes a man the greatest fear, because he is staking all his fortunes on one trial; and
            while he is thinking of this, the recollection of your power does not occur to his mind
            less frequently than that of your justice; because all men whose lives are in another's
            hand more frequently think of what he, in whose power and under whose dominion they are,
            can do, than of what he ought to do,—</p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
            Secondly, Publius Quinctius has for his adversary, in name indeed, Sextus Naevius, but
            in reality, the most eloquent, the most gallant, the most accomplished men of our state,
            who are defending Sextus Naevius with one common zeal, and with all their power: if,
            indeed, defending means so to comply with the desire of another, that he may the more
            easily be able to overwhelm whomsoever he chooses by an unjust trial;</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>for what, O Caius Aquillius, can be mentioned or spoken of more
            unjust or more unworthy than this, that I who am defending the liberties, <note anchored="true">The Latin has <foreign xml:lang="la">caput</foreign>, which in a legal
              sense expresses not only a man's life, but also his status or civil condition; to be
              registered in the census was <foreign xml:lang="la">caput habere</foreign>; to change
              one's rank, <foreign xml:lang="la">capite, &amp;c. diminuere</foreign>. And so a trial
              which affected not only a citizen's life, but his rank or liberty, was called <foreign xml:lang="la">judicium capitale</foreign>.</note> the fame, and fortunes of another
            should be compelled to open the cause, especially when Quintus Hortensius, who in this
            trial fills the part of the accuser, is to speak against me; a man to whom nature has
            given the greatest possible fluency and energy in speaking? Matters are so managed, that
            I, who ought rather to ward off the darts of our adversary and to heal the wounds he has
            inflicted, am compelled to do so now, even when the adversary has cast no dart; and that
            that time is given to them to attack us when the power of avoiding their attacks is to
            be taken from us; and if in any particular they should (as they are well prepared to do)
            cast any false accusation like a poisoned arrow at us, there will be no opportunity for
            applying a remedy.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>That has happened through the
            injustice and wrong-doing of the praetor; first, because, contrary to universal custom,
            he has chosen that the trial as to honour or infamy <note anchored="true">Because if it
              were decided that Quinctius had forfeited his recognizances, <foreign xml:lang="la">infamia</foreign> was the consequence.</note> should take place before the one
            concerning the fact; secondly, because he has so arranged this very trial, that the
            defendant is compelled to plead his cause before he has heard a word of the accuser's;
            and this has been done because of the influence and power of those men who indulge the
            violence and covetousness of Sextus Naevius as eagerly as if their own property or
            honour were at stake, and who make experiment of their influence in such matters as
            this, in which the more weight they have through their virtue and nobility, the less
            they ought to make a parade of what influence they have.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p>Since Publius Quinctius, involved in and overwhelmed by such numerous
            and great difficulties, has taken refuge, O Caius Aquillius, in your good faith, in your
            truth, in your compassion; when, up to this time , owing to the might of his
            adversaries, no equal law could be found for him, no equal liberty of pleading, no just
            magistrate, when, through the greatest injustice, everything was unfavourable and
            hostile to him; he now prays and entreats you, O Caius Aquillius, and all of you who are
            present as assessors, to allow justice, which has been tossed about and agitated by many
            injuries, at length to find rest and a firm footing in this place.</p></div>

<milestone n="3" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>And that you may the more easily do this, I will endeavour to make you understand how this matter has been managed and carried out. Caius Quinctius was the brother of this
            Publius Quinctius; in other respects a sufficiently prudent and attentive head of a
            family, but in one matter a little less wise, inasmuch as he formed a partnership with
            Sextus Naevius, a respectable man, but one who had not been brought up so as to be
            acquainted with the rights of partnership, or with the duties of a head of an
            established family. <note anchored="true">The office of <foreign xml:lang="la">praeco</foreign> was so little reputable that before Cicero's death a law was
              passed to prevent all persons who had been <foreign xml:lang="la">praecones</foreign> from
              becoming <foreign xml:lang="la">decuriones</foreign> in the <foreign xml:lang="la">municipia</foreign>. Under the emperors, however it became very profitable.</note>
            Not that he was wanting in abilities; for Sextus Naevius as a buffoon was never
            considered without wit, nor as a crier was he reckoned unmannerly. What followed? As
            nature had given him nothing better than a voice, and his father had left him nothing
            besides his freedom, he made gain of his voice, and used his freedom for the object of
            being loquacious with impunity.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>So there was no
            reason in the world for your taking him as a partner, except that he might learn with
            your money what a harvest money can produce. Nevertheless, induced by acquaintance and
            intimacy with the man, Quinctius, as I have said, entered into a partnership with him as
            to those articles which were procured in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>.
            He had considerable property in cattle, and a well-cultivated and productive farm.
            Naevius is carried off from the halls of Licinius, <note anchored="true">The Hall of
              Licinius, i.e. Licinius Crassus, was the celebrated one where he erected four columns
              of Hymettian marble, for the theatrical shows in his aedileship, and was one of the
              common resorts of auctioneers and criers.</note> and from the gang of criers, into
              <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> and across the <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName>; there is a great change in his situation, <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la">Coelum non animum mutant qui trans mare
                currunt.</foreign> —<bibl n="Hor. Ep. 1.2.27">;Hor. Epist. 1, ii.
                27</bibl>.</note> none in his disposition; for he who from his boyhood had been
            proposing to himself gain without any outlay, as soon as he spent anything himself and
            brought it to the common stock, could not be content with a moderate profit.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>Nor is it any wonder if he, who had his voice for sale,
            thought that those things which he had acquired by his voice would be a great profit to
            him; so that without much moderation, he carried off whatever he could from the common
            stock to his private house for himself. And in this he was as industrious as if all who
            behaved in a partnership with exact good faith, were usually condemned in a trial before
            an arbitrator. <note anchored="true">The Latin has “arbitrium pro socio
              condemnari,” on which Graevius says, “<foreign xml:lang="la">Arbitrium
                pro socio</foreign>, is a formula of law, by which is signified an action and trial
              in a case of partnership if any one had cheated his partner; and Cicero means that
              Naevius was as industrious in cheating his partner, as if those who did not cheat were
              liable to be condemned, and not those who did cheat.”</note> But concerning
            these matters I do not consider it necessary to say what Publius Quinctius wishes me to
            mention; although the cause calls for it: yet as it only calls for it, and does not
            absolutely require it, <note anchored="true">The Latin has <foreign xml:lang="la">quia
                  <emph>postulat</emph> non <emph>flagitat</emph></foreign>, both words being nearly
              synonymous, but <foreign xml:lang="la">flagito</foreign> being evidently a stronger word
              than <foreign xml:lang="la">postulo</foreign>.</note> I will pass it over.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="4" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>When this partnership had now subsisted many years, and when Naevius had often been suspected by Quinctius, and was not able conveniently to give an account of the
            transactions which he had carried on according to his caprice, and not on any system,
            Quinctius dies in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, when Naevius was there
            too, and dies suddenly. By his will he left this Publius Quinctius his heir, in order
            that, as great grief would come to him by his death, great honour should also accrue to
            him.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>When he was dead, Publius Quinctius soon after
            goes into <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>. There he lives on terms of
            intimacy with that fellow Naevius. There they are together nearly a year, during which
            they had many communications with one another about their partnership, and about the
            whole of their accounts and their estate in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>; nor during that time did Naevius utter one single word about either
            the partnership owing him anything, or about Quinctius having owed him anything on his
            private account. As there was some little debt left behind, the payment of which was to
            be provided for at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, this Publius
            Quinctius issues notices that he shall put up to auction in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, at <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbonne</placeName>, those things
            which were his own private property.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p>On this, this
            excellent man, Sextus Naevius, dissuades the man by many speeches from putting the
            things up to auction, saying that he would not be able at that time to sell so
            conveniently what he had advertised. That he had a sum of money at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, which if Quinctius were wise he would consider
            their common property, from their brotherly intimacy, and also from his relationship
            with himself; for Naevius has married the cousin of Publius Quinctius, and has children
            by her. Because Naevius was saying just what a good man ought, Quinctius believed that
            he who imitated the language of good men, would imitate also their actions. He gives up
            the idea of having an auction; he goes to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; at the same time Naevius also leaves <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> for <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>As Caius Quinctius had owed money to Publius Scapula, Publius
            Quinctius referred it to you, O Caius Aquillius, to decide what he should pay his
            children. He preferred submitting to your decision in this matter, because, on account
            of the difference in the exchange, it was not sufficient to look in his books and see
            how much was owed, unless he had inquired at the temple of Castor <note anchored="true">Some have wished to alter <foreign xml:lang="la">ad Castoris</foreign> here to <foreign xml:lang="la">a quaestoribus</foreign>; but the temple of Castor was a place where much
              money was kept:—<foreign xml:lang="la">Æratâ</foreign>
              <quote xml:lang="la">
                <l>Æratâ multus in arca </l>
                <l>Fiscus et ad vigilem ponendi Castora nummi.</l>
              </quote>—<bibl n="Juv. 14.260">Juv. xiv. 260.</bibl> and the precincts were
              accordingly much frequented by men skillful in computing accounts, and the exchange of
              money.</note> how much was to be paid in Roman money. You decide and determine, on
            account of the friendship existing between you and the family of the Scapulae, what was
            to be paid to them to a penny.</p></div>
  <milestone n="5" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus">
          <p>All these things Quinctius did by the advice and at the instigation of Naevius: nor is
            there anything strange in his adopting the advice of the man whose assistance he thought
            at his service. For not only had he promised it in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, but every day he kept on saying at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> that he would pay the money as soon as he gave him a hint to do so.
            Quinctius moreover saw that he was able to do so. He knew that he ought; he did not
            think that he was telling lies, because there was no reason why he should tell lies. He
            arranged, therefore, that he would pay the Scapulae as if he had the money at home. He
            gives Naevius notice of it, and asks him to provide for the payment as he had said he
            would.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>Then that worthy man—I hope he will
            not think I am laughing at him if I call him again a most worthy man—as he
            thought that he was brought into a great strait, hoping to pin him down to his own terms
            at the very nick of time, says that he will not pay a penny, unless a decision is first
            come to about all the affairs and accounts of the partnership, and unless he knew that
            there would be no dispute between him and Quinctius. We will look into these matters at
            a future time, says Quinctius, but at present I wish you to provide, if you please, what
            you said you would. He says that he will not do so on any other condition; and that what
            he had promised no more concerned him, than it would if when he was holding a sale by
            auction, he had made any bidding at the command of the owner.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>Quinctius being perplexed at this desertion, obtains a few days'
            delay from the Scapulae; he sends into <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> to
            have those things sold which he had advertised; being absent, he sells them at a less
            favourable time than before; he pays the Scapulae with more disadvantage to himself than
            he would have done. Then of his own accord he calls Naevius to account, in order, since
            he suspected that there would be a dispute about something, to provide for the
            termination of the business as soon as possible, and with the smallest possible trouble.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>He appoints as his umpire his friend Marcus
            Trebellius; we name a common friend, a relation of our own, Sextus Alphenus, who had
            been brought up in his house, and with whom he was exceedingly intimate. No agreement
            could be come to; because the one was willing to put up with a slight loss, but the
            other was not content with a moderate booty.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>So from
            that time the matter was referred to legal decision. <note anchored="true">Lit.
              “recognizances were entered into.” When the praetor had granted an
              action, the plaintiff required the defendant to give security for his appearance
              before the praetor on a stated day, commonly the day but one after the <foreign xml:lang="la">in jus vocatio</foreign>.</note> After many delays, and when much time had
            been wasted in that business, and nothing had been done, Naevius appeared before the
            judge.</p> 
  <milestone n="6" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><p>I beseech you, O Caius Aquillius, and you the assessors in this suit, to observe
            carefully, in order that you may be able to understand the singular nature of this
            fraud, and the new method of trickery employed.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>He
            says that he had had a sale by auction in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>;
            that he had sold what he thought fit; that he had taken care that the partnership should
            owe him nothing; that he would have no more to do with summoning any one, or with giving
            security; if Quinctius had any business to transact with him, he had no objection. He,
            as he was desirous to revisit his farm in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>,
            does not summon the man at present; so he departs without giving security. After that,
            Quinctius remains at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> about thirty days.
            He gets any securities which he had given other people respited, so as to be able to go
            without hindrance into <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>He goes; he leaves <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> on
            the twenty-ninth of January, in the Consulship of Scipio and Norbanus;—I beg
            of you to remember the day. Lucius Albius the son of Sextus of the Quirine tribe, a good
            man and of the highest reputation for honour, set out with him. When they had come to
            the place called the fords of Volaterra, they see a great friend of Naevius, who was
            bringing him some slaves from <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> to be sold,
            Lucius Publicius by name, who when he arrived in <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> told Naevius in what place he had seen Quinctius; and unless this
            had been told Naevius by Publicius, the matter would not so soon have come to trial.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p>Then Naevius sends his slaves round to his friends;
            he summons himself all his associates from the halls of Licinius and from the jaws of
            the shambles, and entreats them to come to the booth of Sextus by the second hour of the
            next day. They come in crowds; he makes oath that Publius Quinctius has not appeared to
            his bail, and that he has appeared to his. A long protest to this effect is sealed with
            the seals of noble men. They depart: Naevius demands of Burrienus the praetor, that by
            his edict he may take possession of Quinctius's goods. <note anchored="true">If either
              party did not appear on the appointed day, he was said <foreign xml:lang="la">vadimonium
                deserere</foreign>, and the praetor gave to the other party the <foreign xml:lang="la">bonorum possessio</foreign>. Vide Smith's Dict. Ant. p. 9. v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Actio</foreign>.</note> He urged the confiscation of the property of that man with
            whom he had had intimacy, with whom he actually was in partnership, between whom and
            himself there was a relationship, which while his children lived could not possibly be
            annulled.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>From which act it could easily be perceived
            that there is no bond so holy and solemn, that avarice is not in the habit of weakening
            and violating it. In truth, if friendship is kept up by truth, society by good faith,
            relationship by affection, it is inevitable that he who has endeavoured to despoil his
            friend, his partner, and his relation of fame and fortune, should confess himself
            worthless and perfidious and impious.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>Sextus
            Alphenus, the agent of Publius Quinctius, the intimate friend and relation of Sextus
            Naevius, tears down the bills; carries off one little slave whom Naevius had laid hold
            of; gives notice that he is the agent, and that it is only fair that that fellow should
            consult the fame and fortunes of Publius Quinctius, and await his arrival. But if he
            would not do so, and believed that by such methods he could bring him into the
            conditions which he proposed, then he asked nothing as a favour, and if Naevius chose to
            go to law, he would defend him at the trial.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>While
            this is being done at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, meantime
            Quinctius, contrary to law and to custom, and to the edicts of the praetors, is driven
            by force by the slaves which belonged to both him and Naevius, as partners, from their
            common lands and estates.
<milestone n="7" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          Think, O Caius Aquillius, that Naevius did everything at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> with moderation and good sense, if this which was done in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> in obedience to his letters was done rightly and
            legally. Quinctius being expelled and turned out of his farm, having received a most
            notorious injury, flies to Caius Flaccus the general, who was at that time in the
            province; whom I name to do him honour as his dignity demands. How strongly he was of
            opinion that that action called for punishment you will be able to learn from his
            decrees.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>Meantime Alphenus was fighting every day at
              <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> with that old gladiator. He had the
            people indeed on his side, because that fellow never ceased to aim at the head. <note anchored="true">There is an allusion here to the fights of gladiators, in which the
              people disapproved of that gladiator who aimed too constantly at the vital parts of
              his adversary, so as to make the combat short. There is a pun here, <foreign xml:lang="la">caput</foreign> meaning the head or life of the gladiator, and also the condition
              of a citizen.</note> Naevius demanded that the agent should give security for payment
            on judgment being given. Alphenus says that it is not reasonable for an agent to give
            security, because the defendant would not be bound to give security if he were present
            himself. The tribunes are appealed to, and as a positive decision was demanded from
            them, the matter is terminated on the footing of Sextus Alphenus undertaking that
            Publius Quinctius should answer to his bail by the thirteenth of September.</p></div>
  <milestone n="8" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>Quinctius comes to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; he answers to his bail. That fellow, that most energetic man, the
            seizer of other men's goods, that invader, that robber, for a year and a half asks for
            nothing, keeps quiet, amuses Quinctius by proposals as long as he can, and at last
            demands of Cnaeus Dolabella, the praetor, that Quinctius should give security for
            payment on judgment being given, according to the formula, “Because he demands
            it of him whose goods he has taken possession of for thirty days, according to the edict
            of the praetor.” Quinctius made no objection to his ordering him to give
            security, if his goods had been possessed, in accordance with the praetor's edict. He
            makes the order; how just a one I do not say—this alone I do say, it was
            unprecedented: and I would rather not have said even this, since any one could have
            understood both its characters. He orders Publius Quinctius to give security to Sextus
            Naevius, to try the point whether his goods had been taken possession of for thirty
            days, in accordance with the edict of the praetor. The friends who were then with
            Quinctius objected to this: they showed that a decision ought to be come to as to the
            fact, so that either each should give security to the other, or else that neither
            should; that there was no necessity for the character of either being involved in the
            trial.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>Moreover, Quinctius himself cried out that he
            was unwilling to give security, lest by so doing he should seem to admit that his goods
            had been taken possession of in accordance with the edict: besides, if he gave a bond in
            that manner, he should be forced (as has now happened) to speak first in a trial
            affecting himself capitally. Dolabella (as high-born men are wont to do, who, whether
            they have begun to act rightly or wrongly, carry either conduct to such a height that no
            one born in our rank of life can overtake them) perseveres most bravely in committing
            injustice: he bids him either give security or give a bond; and meantime he orders our
            advocates, who objected to this, to be removed with great roughness.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="9" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>Quinctius departs much embarrassed; and no wonder, when so miserable a choice was
            offered him, and one so unjust, that he must either himself convict himself of a capital
            offence if he gave security, <note anchored="true">Because the giving security now would
              be an admission that he had forfeited his recognizances before; which was liable to be
              punished with <foreign xml:lang="la">infamia</foreign></note> or open the cause himself in
            a capital trial if he gave a bond. As in the one case there was no reason why he should
            pass an unfavourable sentence on himself (for sentence passed by oneself is the hardest
            sentence of all), but in the other case there was hope of coming before such a man as a
            judge, as would show him the more favour the more without interest he was, he preferred
            to give a bond. He did so. He had you, O Caius Aquillius, for the judge; he pleaded
            according to his bond; in what I have now mid consists the sum and the whole of the
            present trial. </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p>You see, O Caius Aquillius, that it is a trial
            touching not the property of Publius Quinctius, but his fame and fortunes. Though our
            ancestors have determined that he who is pleading for his life should speak last, you
            see that we, owing to this unprecedented accusation of the prosecutor's, are pleading
            our cause first. Moreover, you see that those who are more accustomed <note anchored="true">He means Hortensius.</note> to defend people are today acting as
            accusers; and that those talents are turned to do people injury, which have hitherto
            been employed in ministering to men's safety, and in assisting them. There remained but
            one thing more, which they put in execution yesterday,—namely, to proceed
            against you for the purpose of compelling you to limit the time allowed us for making
            our defence; and this they would easily have obtained from the praetor if you had not
            taught him what your rights and duties and business were.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p>Nor was there any longer any assistant left to us but yourself by
            whose means we could obtain our rights against them. Nor was it even enough for them to
            obtain that which might be justified to everybody; so trifling and insignificant a thing
            do they think power to be which is not exercised with injustice. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>But since Hortensius urges you to come to a decision, and requires of use that I should
            not waste time in speaking, and complains that when the former advocate was defending
            this action it never could be brought to a conclusion, I will not allow that suspicion
            to continue to exist, that we are unwilling for the matter to be decided, nor will I
            arrogate to myself a power of proving the case better than it has been proved before;
            nor yet will I make a long speech, because the cause has already been explained by him
            who has spoken before, and brevity, which is exceedingly agreeable to me, is required of
            me, who am neither able to devise <note anchored="true">He mentions in the Brutus that he
              was at this time in a very delicate state of health. <foreign xml:lang="la">Erat eo
                tempore in nobis summa gracilitas et infirmitas corporis</foreign>. <bibl n="Cic. ad Brut. 313">Brutus, 313.</bibl></note> nor to utter many arguments.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p>I will do what I have often observed you do, O
            Hortensius; I will distribute my argument on the entire cause into certain divisions.
            You always do so, because you are always able. I will do so in this cause, because in
            this cause I think I can. That power which nature gives you of being always able to do
            so, this cause gives me, so that I am able to do so today. I will appoint myself certain
            bounds and limits, out of which I cannot stray if I ever so much wish; so that both I
            may have a subject on which I may speak, and Hortensius may have allegations which he
            may answer, and you, O Caius Aquillius, may be able to perceive beforehand what topics
            you are going to hear discussed. We say, O Sextus Naevius, that you did not take
            possession of the goods of Publius Quinctius in accordance with the edict of the
            praetor.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>On that point the security was given. I will
            show first, that there was no cause why you should require of the praetor power to take
            possession of the goods of Publius Quinctius; in the second place, that you could not
            have taken possession of them according to the edict; lastly, that you did not take
            possession of them. I entreat you, O Caius Aquillius, and you too the assessors, to
            preserve carefully in your recollections what I have undertaken. You will more easily
            comprehend the whole business if you recollect this; and you will easily recall me by
            the expression of your opinion if I attempt to overstep those barriers to which I have
            confined myself. I say that there was no reason why he should make the demand; I say
            that he could not have taken possession according to the edict; I say that he did not
            take possession. When I have proved thee three things, I will sum up the whole.</p></div>
  
<milestone n="11" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus">
          <p>There was no reason why you should make the demand, How can this be proved? Because
            Quinctius owed nothing whatever to Sextus Naevius, neither on account of the
            partnership, nor from any private debt. Who is a witness of this? Why, the same man who
            is our most bitter enemy. In this matter I will cite you—you, I say, O
            Naevius, as our witness Quinctius was with you in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> a year, and more than that, after the death of Caius Quinctius.
            Prove that you ever demanded of him this vast sum of money, I know not how much; prove
            that you ever mentioned it, ever said it was owing, and I will admit that he owed it.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>Caius Quinctius dies; who, as you say, owed you a
            large sum for some particular articles. His heir, Publius Quinctius, comes into
              <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> to you, to your joint
            estate—comes to that place where not only the property was, but also all the
            accounts and all the books. Who would have been so careless in his private affairs, who
            so negligent, who so unlike you, O Sextus, us not, when the effects were gone from his
            hands who had contracted the debt, and had become the property of his heir, to inform
            the heir of it as soon as he saw him? to apply for the money? to give in his account?
            and if anything were disputed, to arrange it either in a friendly manner, or by the
            intervention of strict law? Is it not so? that which the best men do, those who wish
            their relations and friends to be affectionate towards them and honourable, would Sextus
            Naevius not do that, he who so burns, who is so hurried away by avarice, that he is
            unwilling to give up any part of his own property, lest he should leave some fraction to
            be any credit or advantage to this his near relation.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p>
            And would he not demand the money, if any were owing, who , because that was not paid
            which was never owed, seeks to take away not the money only, but even the life of his
            relation? You were unwilling, I suppose, to be troublesome to him whom you will not
            allow even to live as a free man! You were unwilling at that time modestly to ask that
            man for money, whom you now will nefariously to murder! I suppose so. You were
            unwilling, or you did not dare, to ask a man who was your relation, who had a regard for
            you, a good man, a temperate man, a man older than yourself. Often (as sometimes happens
            with men), when you had fortified yourself, when you had determined to mention the
            money, when you had come ready prepared and having considered the matter, you being a
            nervous man, of virgin modesty, on a sudden checked yourself, your voice failed you, you
            did not dare to ask him for money whom you wished to ask, lest he should be unwilling to
            hear you. No doubt that was it.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="12" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus">
          <p>Let us believe this, that Sextus Naevius spared the ears of the man whose life he is
            attacking! If he had owed you money, O Sextus, you would have asked for it at once; if
            not at once, at all events soon after; if not soon after, at least after a time; in six
            months I should think; beyond all doubt at the close of the year: but for a year and a
            half, when you had every day an opportunity of reminding the man of the debt, you say
            not one word about it; but now, when nearly two years have passed, you ask for the
            money. What profligate and extravagant spendthrift, even before his property is
            diminished, but while it is still abundant, would have been so reckless as Sextus
            Naevius was? When I name the man, I seem to myself to have said enough.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p>Caius Quinctius owed you money; you never asked for it: he
            died; his property came to his heir; though you saw him every day, you did not ask for
            it for two years; will any one doubt which is the more probable, that Sextus Naevius
            would instantly have asked for what was owed to him, or that be would not have asked for
            two years? Had he no opportunity of asking? Why, he lived with you more than a year:
            could no measures be taken in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>? But there
            was law administered in the province, and trials were taking place at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. The only alternative remaining is, either extreme
            carelessness prevented you, or extraordinary liberality. If you call it carelessness, we
            shall wonder; if you call it kindness, we shall laugh; and what else you can call it I
            know not; it is proof enough that nothing was owing to Naevius, that for such a length
            of time he asked for nothing.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="13" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus">
          <p>What if I show that this very thing which he is now doing is a proof that nothing is
            due? For what is Sextus Naevius doing now? About what is there a dispute? What is this
            trial on which we have now been occupied two years? What is the important business with
            which he is wearying so many eminent men? He is asking for his money. What now, at last?
            But let him ask; let us hear what he has to say.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p>He
            wishes a decision to be come to concerning the accounts and disputes of the partnership.
            It is very late. However, better late than never; let us grant it. Oh, says be, I do not
            want that now, O Caius Aquillius; and I am not troubling myself about that now: Publius
            Quinctius has had the use of my money for so many years; let him use it, I do not ask
            anything. What then are you contending for? is it with that object that you have often
            announced in many places—that he may no longer be a citizen? that he may not
            keep that rank which hitherto he has most honourably preserved? that be may not be
            counted among the living? that he may be in peril of his life and all his honours? that
            he may have to plead his cause before the plaintiff speaks, and that when he has ended
            his speech he may then hear the voice of his accuser? What? What is the object of this?
            That you may the quicker arrive at your rights? But if you wished that might be already
            done. That you may contend according to a more respectable form of procedure?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>But you cannot murder Publius Quinctius your own relation,
            without the greatest wickedness. That the trial may be facilitated I But neither does
            Caius Aquillius willingly decide on the life of another, nor has Quintus Hortensius been
            in the habit of pleading against a man's life. But what reply is made by us, O Caius
            Aquillius? He asks for his money: we deny that it is due. Let a trial take place
            instantly; we make no objection; is there anything more? If he is afraid that the money
            will not be forth coming when the decision is given let him take security that it shall
            be; and let him give security <note anchored="true">In many cases both plaintiff and
              defendant might be required to give security, (<foreign xml:lang="la">satis
              dare</foreign>.) Smith, Dict. Ant. p.10, V. <foreign xml:lang="la">Actio</foreign>.</note>
            for what I demand in the very same terms in which we give security.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p>The matter can be terminated at once, O Caius Aquillius You can at
            once depart, being delivered from an annoyance, I had almost said, no less than that
            Quinctius is exposed to. What are we doing, Hortensius? what are we to say of this
            condition? Can we, some time or other, laying aside our weapons, discuss the money
            matter without hazard of any one's fortunes? Can we so prosecute our business, as to
            leave the life of our relation in safety? Can we adopt the character of a plaintiff, and
            lay aside that of an accuser? Yes, says he, I will take security from you, but I will
            not give you security. <milestone n="14" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          But who is it that lays down for us these very reasonable conditions? who determines
            this—that what is just towards Quinctius is unjust towards Naevius? The goods
            of Quinctius, says he, were taken possession of in accordance with the edict of the
            praetor. You demand then, that I should admit that; that we should establish by our own
            sentence, as having taken place, that which we go to trial expressly to prove never did
            take place.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p>Can no means be found, O Caius Aquillius,
            for a man's arriving at his rights as expeditiously as maybe without the disgrace and
            infamy and ruin of any one else? Forsooth, if anything were owed, he would ask for it:
            he would not prefer that all sorts of trials should take place, rather than that one
            from which all these arise. He, who for so many years never even asked Quinctius for the
            money, when he had an opportunity of transacting business with him every day; he who,
            from the time when he first began to behave ill, has wasted all the time in adjournments
            and respiting the recognizances; he who, after he had withdrawn his recognizance drove
            Quinctius by treachery and violence from their joint estate; who, when he had ample
            opportunity, without any one's making objection, to try a civil action, <note anchored="true">With respect to its subject matter the <foreign xml:lang="la">actio</foreign> was divided into two great divisions, the <foreign xml:lang="la">in
                personam actio</foreign> and the <foreign xml:lang="la">in rem actio</foreign>. The
              former was against a person who was bound to the plaintiff by contract or delict the
              latter applied to those cases where a man claimed a property or a right. Smith, Dict.
              Ant. p.7.</note> chose rather a charge that involved infamy; who, when he is brought
            back to this tribunal, whence all these proceedings arise, repudiates the most
            reasonable proposals; confesses that he is aiming, not at the money, but at the life and
            heart's blood of his adversary;—does he not openly say, “if anything
            were owing to me, I should demand it, and I should long ago have obtained it;</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p>I would not employ so much trouble, so unpopular a course of
            legal proceeding, and such a band of favourers of my cause, if I had to make a just
            demand; I have got to extort money from one unwilling, and in spite of him; I have got
            to tear and squeeze out of a man what he does not owe; Publius Quinctius is to be cast
            down from all his fortune; every one who is powerful, or eloquent, or noble, must be
            brought into court with me; a force must be put upon truth, threats must be bandied
            about, dangers must be threatened; terrors must be brandished before his eyes, that
            being cowed and overcome by these things, he may at last yield of his own
            accord.” And, in truth, all these things, when I see who are striving against
            us, and when I consider the party sitting opposite to me, seem to be impending over, and
            to be present to us, and to be impossible to be avoided by any means. But when, O Caius
            Aquillius, I bring my eyes and my mind back to you, the greater the labour and zeal with
            which all these things are done, the more trifling and powerless do I think them.
            Quinctius then owed nothing, as you prove yourself.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p>
            But what if he had owed you anything? would that have at once been a reason for your
            requiring leave from the praetor to take possession of his goods? I think that was
            neither according to law, nor expedient for any one. What then does he prove? He says
            that he had forfeited his recognizances.</p> <milestone n="15" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><p>Before I prove that he had not done so, I choose, O Caius Aquillius, to consider both
            the fact itself and the conduct of Sextus Naevius, with reference to the principles of
            plain duty, and the common usages of men. He, as you say, had not appeared to his
            recognizances; he with whom you were connected by relationship, by partnership, by every
            sort of bond and ancient intimacy. Was it decent for you to go at once to the praetor?
            was it fair for you at once to demand to be allowed to take possession of his goods
            according to the edict? Did you betake yourself to these extreme measures and to these
            most hostile laws with such eagerness as to leave yourself nothing behind which you
            might be able to do still more bitter and cruel?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p>For,
            what could happen more shameful to any human being, what more miserable or more bitter
            to a man; what disgrace could happen so heavy, what disaster can be imagined so
            intolerable? If fortune deprived any one of money, or if the injustice of another took
            it from him, still while his reputation is unimpeached, honour easily makes amends for
            poverty. And some men, though stained with ignominy, or convicted in discreditable
            trials, still enjoy their wealth; are not forced to dance attendance (which is the most
            wretched of all states) on the power of another; and in their distresses they are
            relieved by this support and comfort; but he whose goods have been sold, who has seen
            not merely his ample estates, but even his necessary food and clothing put up under the
            hammer, with great disgrace to himself; he is not only erased from the list of men, but
            he is removed out of sight, if possible, even beneath the dead. An honourable <note anchored="true">Most of the commentators consider this passage corrupt, and propose
              various emendations of it. I have however thought it safer to adhere to the text of
              the MSS. as it stands in Orellius.</note> death forsooth often sets off even a base
            life, but a dishonoured life leaves no room to hope for even an honourable death.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus"><p>Therefore, in truth, when a man's goods are taken
            possession of according to the praetor's edict, all his fame and reputation is seized at
            the same time with his goods. A man about whom placards are posted in the most
            frequented places, is not allowed even to perish in silence and obscurity; a man who has
            assignees and trustees appointed to pronounce to him on what terms and conditions he is
            to be ruined; a man about whom the voice of the crier makes proclamation and proclaims
            his price,—he has a most bitter funeral procession while he is alive, if that
            may be considered a funeral in which men meet not as friends to do honour to his
            obsequies, but purchasers of his goods as executioners, to tear to pieces and divide the
            relics of his existence.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="16" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus">
          <p>Therefore our ancestors determined that such a thing should seldom happen; the praetors
            have taken care that it should only happen after deliberation; good men, even when fraud
            is openly committed, when there is no opportunity of trying the case at law, still have
            recourse to this measure timidly and hesitatingly; not till they are compelled by force
            and necessity, unwillingly, when the recognizances have often been forfeited, when they
            have been often deceived and outwitted. For they consider how serious a matter it is to
            confiscate the property of another. A good man is unwilling to slay another, even
            according to law; for he would rather say that he had saved when he might have
            destroyed, than that he had destroyed when he could have saved. Good men behave so to
            the most perfect strangers, aye, even to their greatest enemies, for the sake both of
            their reputation among men, and of the common rights of humanity; in order that, as they
            have not knowingly caused inconvenience to another, no inconvenience may lawfully befall
            them. He did not appear to his recognizances. Who? Your own relation. If that matter
            appeared of the greatest importance in itself, yet its magnitude would be lessened by
            the consideration of your relationship. He did not appear to his recognizances. Who?
            Your partner. You might forgive even a greater thing than this, to a man with whom
            either your inclination had connected you, or fortune had associated you.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p>He did not appear to his recognizances. Who? He who was always
            in your company. You therefore have hurled upon him, who allowed it to happen once that
            he was not in your company, all those weapons which have been forged against those who
            have done many things for the sake of malversation and fraud.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p>If your poundage was called in question, if in any trifling matter
            you were afraid of some trick, would you not have at once run off to Caius Aquillius, or
            to some other counsel? When the rights of friendship, of partnership, of relationship
            are at stake, when regard should have been had to your duty and your character, at that
            time you not only did not refer it to Caius Aquillius or to Lucius Lucilius, but you did
            not even consult yourself; you did not even say this to
            yourself—“The two hours are passed; Quinctius has not appeared to
            his recognizances; what shall I do?” If, in truth, you had said but these four
            words to yourself “What shall I do?” your covetousness and avarice
            would have had breathing time; you would have given some room for reason and prudence;
            you would have recollected yourself; you would not have come to such baseness as to be
            forced to confess before such men that in the same hour in which he did not appear to
            his recognizances you took counsel how utterly to ruin the fortunes of your relation.</p></div>
<milestone n="17" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus">
          <p>I now on your behalf consult these men, after the time has passed, and in an affair
            which is not mine, since you forgot to consult them in your own affair, and when it was
            the proper time. I ask of you, Caius Aquillius, Lucius Lucilius, Publius Quintilius, and
            Marcus Marcellus;—A certain partner and relation of mine has not appeared to
            his recognizances; a man with whom I have a long standing intimacy, but a recent dispute
            about money matters. Can I demand of the praetor to be allowed to take possession of his
            goods? Or must I, as he has a house, a wife, and children at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, not rather give notice at his house? What is your
            opinion in this matter? If, in truth, I have rightly understood your kindness and
            prudence, I am not much mistaken what you will answer if you are consulted. You will say
            at first that I must wait; then, if he seems to be shirking the business and to be
            trifling with it too long, that I must have a meeting of our friends; must ask who his
            agent is; must give notice at his house. It can hardly be told how many steps there are
            which you would make answer ought to be taken before having recourse to this extreme and
            unnecessary course.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p>What does Naevius say to all
            this? Forsooth, he laughs at our madness in expecting a consideration of the highest
            duty, or looking for the practices of good men in his conduct. What have I to do, says
            he, with all this sanctimoniousness and punctiliousness? Let good men, says he, look to
            these duties, but let them think of me thus; let them ask not what I have, but by what
            means I have acquired it, and in what rank I was born, and in what manner I was brought
            up. I remember, there is an old proverb about a buffoon; “that it is a much
            easier thing for him to become rich than to become the head of a family.”
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus"><p>This is what he says openly by his actions, if he
            does not dare to say it in words. If in truth he wishes to live according to the
            practices of good men, he has many things to learn and to unlearn, both which things are
            difficult to a man of his age. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>I did not hesitate, says he, when the recognizances were forfeited, to claim the
            confiscation of his goods. It was wickedly done; but since you claim this for yourself;
            and demand that it be granted to you, let us grant it. What if he has not forfeited his
            recognizances? if the whole of that plea has been invented by you with the most extreme
            dishonesty and wickedness? if there had actually been no securities given in any cause
            between you and Publius Quinctius? What shall we call you? Wicked? why, even if the
            recognizances had been forfeited, yet in making such a demand and confiscation of his
            goods, you were proved to be most wicked. Malignant? you do not deny it. Dishonest? you
            have already claimed that as your character, and you think it a fine thing. Audacious?
            covetous? perfidious? those are vulgar and worn-out imputations, but this conduct is
            novel and unheard-of.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus"><p>What then are we to say? I fear
            forsooth lest I should either use language severer than men's nature is inclined to
            bear, or else more gentle than the cause requires. You say that the recognizances were
            forfeited. Quinctius the moment he returned to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> asked you on what day the recognizances were drawn. You answered at
            once, on the fifth of February. Quinctius, when departing, began to recollect on what
            day he left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> for <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>: he goes to his journal, he finds the day of his
            departure set down, the thirty-first of January. If he was at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> on the fifth of February we have nothing to say
            against his having entered into recognizances with you.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus"><p>What then? how can this be found out? Lucius Albius went with him, a man of the
            highest honour; he shall give his evidence. Some friends accompanied both Albius and
            Quinctius; they also shall give their evidence. Shall the letters of Publius Quinctius,
            shall so many witnesses, all having the most undeniable reason for being able to know
            the truth, and no reason for speaking falsely, be compared with your witness to the
            recognizance?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus"><p>And shall Publius Quinctius be harassed
            in a cause like this? and shall he any longer be subjected to the misery of such fear
            and danger? and shall the influence of an adversary alarm him more than the integrity of
            the judge comforts him? For he always lived in an unpolished and uncompanionable manner;
            he was of a melancholy and unsociable disposition; he has not frequented the Forum, or
            the Campus, or banquets. He so lived as to retain his friends by attention, and his
            property by economy; he loved the ancient system of duty, all the splendour of which has
            grown obsolete according to present fashions. But if, in a cause where the merits were
            equal, he seemed to come off the worse, that would be in no small degree to be
            complained of; but now, when he is in the right, he does not even demand to come off
            best; he submits to be worsted, only with these limitations, that he is not to be given
            up with his goods, his character, and all his fortunes, to the covetousness and cruelty
            of Sextus Naevius.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="19" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus">
          <p>I have proved what I first promised to prove, O Caius Aquillius, that there was
            absolutely no cause why he should make this demand; that neither was any money owed, and
            that if it were owed ever so much, nothing had been done to excuse recourse being had to
            such measures as these. Remark now, that the goods of Publius Quinctius could not
            possibly have been taken possession of in accordance with the praetor's edict. Recite
            the edict. “He who for the sake of fraud has lain hid.” That is not
            Quinctius, unless they be hid who depart on their own business, leaving an agent behind
            them. “The man who has no heir.” Even that is not he. “The
            man who leaves the country in exile.” At what time, O Naevius, do you think
            Quinctius ought to have been defended in his absence, or how? Then, when you were
            demanding leave to take possession of his goods? No one was present, for no one could
            guess that you were going to make such a demand; nor did it concern any one to object to
            that which the praetor ordered not to be done absolutely, but to be done according to
            his edict.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus"><p>What was the first opportunity, then,
            which was given to the agent of defending this absent man? When you were putting up the
            placards. Then Sextus Alphenus was present: he did not permit it; he tore down the
            notices. That which was the first step of duty was observed by the agent with the
            greatest diligence. Let us see what followed on this. You arrest the servant of Publius
            Quinctius in public: you attempt to take him away. Alphenus does not permit it; he takes
            him from you by force; he takes care that he is led home to Quinctius. Here too is seen
            in a high degree the attention of an illustrious agent. You say that Quinctius is in
            your debt; his agent denies it. You wish security to he given; he promises it. You call
            him into court; he follows you. You demand a trial; he does not object. What other could
            be the conduct of one defending a man in his absence I do not understand.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus"><p>But who was the agent? I suppose it was some insignificant
            man, poor, litigious, worthless, who might be able to endure the daily abuse of a
            wealthy buffoon. Nothing of the sort: he was a wealthy Roman knight; a man managing his
            own affairs well: he was, in short, the man whom Naevius himself as often as he went
            into <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, left as his agent at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          And do you dare, O Sextus Naevius, to deny that Quinctius was defended in his absence,
            when the same man defended him who used to defend you? and when he accepted the trial on
            behalf of Quinctius, to whom when departing you used to recommend and entrust your own
            property and character? Do you attempt to say that there was no one who defended
            Quinctius at the trial?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus"><p>“I
            demanded,” says he, “that security should be given.” You
            demanded it unjustly. “The order was made.” Alphenus objected.
            “He did, but the praetor made the decree.” Therefore the tribunes
            were appealed to. “Here,” said he, “I have you: that is
            not allowing a trial, nor defending a man at a trial, when you ask assistance from the
            tribunes.” When I consider how prudent Hortensius is, I do not think that he
            will say this; but when I hear that he has said so before, and when I consider the cause
            itself I do not see what else he can say; for he admits that Alphenus tore down the
            bills, undertook to give security, did not object to go to trial in the very terms which
            Naevius proposed; but on this condition, that according to custom and prescription, it
            should be before that magistrate who was appointed in order to give assistance.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus"><p>You must either say that these things are not so;
            or that Caius Aquillius, being such a man as he is, on his oath, is to establish this
            law in the state: that he whose agent does not object to every trial which any one
            demands against him, whose agent dares to appeal from the praetor to the tribunes, is
            not defended at all, and may rightly have his goods taken possession of; may properly,
            while miserable, absent, and ignorant of it, have all the embellishments of his
            fortunes, all the ornaments of his life, taken from him with the greatest disgrace and
            ignominy. And this seems reasonable to no one.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus"><p>This
            certainly must be proved to the satisfaction of every one, that Quinctius while absent
            was defended at the trial. And as that is the ease, his goods were not taken possession
            of in accordance with the edict. But then, the tribunes of the people did not even hear
            his cause. I admit, if that be the case, that the agent ought to have obeyed the decree
            of the praetor. What; if Marcus Brutus openly said that he would intercede <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la">Intercedo</foreign> was the technical word for the
              interposition of the tribunes.</note> unless some agreement was come to between
            Alphenus himself and Naevius; does not the appeal to the tribunes seem to have been
            interposed not for the sake of delay but of assistance?</p></div> 
  <milestone n="21" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus">
          <p>What is done next? Alphenus, in order that all men might see that Quinctius was
            defended at the trial, that no suspicion might exist unfavourable either to his own
            duty, or to his principal's character, summons many excellent men, And, in the hearing
            of that fellow, calls them to witness that he begs this of him, in the first place, out
            of regard to their common intimacy, that he would not attempt to take any severe steps
            against Quinctius in his absence without cause; but if lie persevered in carrying on the
            contest in a most spiteful and hostile manner, that he is prepared by every upright and
            honourable method to defend him, and to prove that what he demanded was not owed, and
            that he accepted the trial which Naevius proposed.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus"><p>
            Many excellent men signed the document setting forth this fact and these conditions.
            While all matters are still unaltered, while the goods are neither advertised nor taken
            possession of, Alphenus promises Naevius that Quinctius should appear to his
            recognizances. Quinctius does appear to his recognizances. The matter lies in dispute
            while that fellow is spreading his calumnies for two years, until he could find out by
            what means the affair might be diverted out of the common course of proceeding, and the
            whole cause he confined to this single point to which it is now limited.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus"><p>What duty of an agent can possibly be mentioned, O Caius
            Aquillius, which seems to have been overlooked by Alphenus? What reason is alleged why
            it should be denied that Publius Quinctius was defended in his absence? Is it that which
            I suppose Hortensius will allege, because he has lately mentioned it, and because
            Naevius is always harping on it, that Naevius was not contending on equal terms with
            Alphenus, at such a time, and with such magistrates? And if I were willing to admit
            that, they will, I suppose, grant this, that it is not the case that no one was the
            agent of Publius Quinctius, but that he had one who was popular. But it is quite
            sufficient for me to prove that there was an agent, with whom he could have tried the
            matter. What sort of man he was, as long as he defended the man in his absence,
            according to law and before the proper magistrate, I think has nothing to do with the
            matter.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus"><p>“For he was,” says he,
            “a man of the opposite party.” No doubt; a man who had been brought
            up in your house, whom you from a youth had so trained up as not to favour any one of
            eminence, not even a gladiator. <note anchored="true">The text is undoubtedly corrupt
              here. Some read <foreign xml:lang="la">haereret</foreign>, some <foreign xml:lang="la">cederet</foreign>. I have adopted the text of Orellius; but the meaning is not very
              plain.</note> If Alphenus had the same wish as you always especially entertained, was
            not the contest between you on equal terms in that matter? “Oh,”
            says he, “he was an intimate friend of Brutus, and therefore he
            interposed.” You on the other hand were an intimate friend of Burrienus, who
            gave an unjust decision; and, in short, of all those men who at that time were both very
            powerful with violence and wickedness, and who dared do all that they could. Did you
            wish to overcome those men, who now are labouring with such zeal that you may be
            victorious? Dare to say that, not openly, but to these very men whom you have brought
            with you.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus"><p>Although I am unwilling to bring that
            matter up again by mentioning it, every recollection of which I think ought to be
            entirely effaced and destroyed. <milestone n="22" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          This one thing I say, if Alphenus was an influential man because of his party zeal,
            Naevius was most influential; if Alphenus, relying on his personal interest, made any
            rather unjust demand; Naevius demanded, and obtained too, things much more unjust. Nor
            was there, as I think, any difference between your zeal. In ability, in experience, in
            cunning, you easily surpassed him. To say nothing of other things, this is sufficient:
            Alphenus was ruined with those men, and for the sake of those men to whom he was
            attached; you, after those men who were your friends could not get the better, took care
            that those who did get the better should be your friends.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus"><p>But if you think you had not then the same justice as Alphenus,
            because it was in his power to appeal to some one against you; because a magistrate was
            found before whom the cause of Alphenus could be fairly heard; what is Quinctius to
            determine on at this time I—a man who has not as yet found any just
            magistrate, nor been able to procure the customary trial; <note anchored="true">“Because the matter in dispute was really a money matter, but the praetor
              ordered the trial to proceed <foreign xml:lang="la">de
              probro</foreign>.”—Hottoman.</note> in whose case no condition, no
            security, no petition has been interposed,—I do not say a just one, but none
            at all that had ever been heard of before that time. I wish to try an action about
            money. You cannot. But that is the point in dispute. It does not concern me; you must
            plead to a capital charges. Accuse me then, if it must be so. No says be, not unless
            you, in an unprecedented manner, first make your defence. You must plead; the time must
            be fixed at our pleasure; the judge himself shall be removed.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus"><p>What then? Shall you be able to find any advocate, a man of such
            ancient principles of duty as to despise our splendour and influence? Lucius Philippus
            will be my advocate; in eloquence, in dignity, and in honour, the most flourishing man
            in the states. Hortensius will speak for me; a man eminent for his genius, and nobility,
            and reputation; and other most noble and powerful men will accompany me into court, the
            number and appearance of whom may alarm not only Publius Quinctius, who is defending
            himself on a capital charge, but even any one who is out of danger.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus"><p>This really is what an unequal contest is; not that one in which you
            were skirmishing against Alphenus. You did not leave him any place where he could make a
            stand against you. You must therefore either prove that Alphenus denied he was his
            agent, did not tear down the bills, and refused to go to trial; or, if all this was
            done, you must admit that you did not take possession of the goods of Publius Quinctius
            in accordance with the edict. <milestone n="23" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          If, indeed, you did take possession of the things according to the edict, I ask you why
            they were not sold—why the others who were his securities and creditors did
            not meet together? Was there no one to whom Quinctius owed money? There were some, there
            were many such; because Caius, his brother, had left some amount of debt behind him.
            What then was the reason? They were all men entirely strangers to him, and he owed them
            money, and yet not one was found so notoriously infamous as to dare to attack the
            character of Publius Quinctius in his absences.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74" resp="perseus"><p>There
            was one man, his relation, his partner, his intimate friend, Sextus Naevius, who, though
            he himself was in reality in debt to him, as if some extraordinary prize of wickedness
            was proposed to him, strove with the greatest eagerness to deprive his own relation,
            oppressed and ruined by his means, not only of property which he had honestly acquired,
            but even of that light which is common to all men. Where were the rest of the creditors?
            Even now at this very time where are they? Who is there who says he kept out of the way
            for the sake of fraud? Who is there who denies that Quinctius was defended in his
            absence?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75" resp="perseus"><p>Not one is found But, on the other hand, all
            men who either have or have had any transactions with him are present on his behalf and
            are defending him; they are labouring that his good faith, known in many places, may not
            now be disparaged by the perfidy of Sextus Naevius. In a trial of this nature Naevius
            ought to have brought some witnesses out of that body, who could say; “He
            forfeited his recognizances in my case; he cheated me, he begged a day of me for the
            payment of a debt which he had denied; could not get him to trial; he kept out of the
            way; he left no agent:” none of all these things is said. Witnesses are being
            got ready to say it But we shall examine into that, I suppose, when they have said it:
            but let them consider this one thing, that they are of weight only so far, that they can
            preserve that weight, if they also preserve the truth; if they neglect that, they are so
            insignificant that all men may see that influence is of avail not to support a lie, but
            only to prove the truth.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="24" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76" resp="perseus">
          <p>I ask these two questions. First of all, on what account Naevius did not complete the
            business he had undertaken; that is, why he did not sell the goods which he had taken
            possession of in accordance with the edict: Secondly, why out of so many other creditors
            no one reinforced his demand; so that you must of necessity confess that neither was any
            one of them so rash, and that you yourself were unable to persevere in and accomplish
            that which you had most infamously begun. What if you yourself, O Sextus Naevius,
            decided that the goods of Publius Quinctius had not been taken possession of according
            to the edict? I conceive that your evidence, which in a matter which did not concern
            yourself would be very worthless, ought to be of the greatest weight in an affair of
            your own when it makes against you. You bought the goods of Sextus Alphenus when Lucius
            Sulla, the dictator, sold them. You entered Quinctius in your books as the partner in
            the purchase of these goods.<note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la">Nomen</foreign> is
              especially used in reference to debts, because not only the amount of the debts, but
              also the name of the debtor is entered in the account books. Riddle's Dict. in v.
                <foreign xml:lang="la">Nomen</foreign>.</note> I say no more. Did you enter into a
            voluntary partnership with that man who had cheated in a partnership to which he had
            succeeded by inheritance;</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77" resp="perseus"><p>and did you by your own
            sentence approve of the man who you thought was stripped of his character and of all his
            fortunes? I had fears indeed, O Caius Aquillius, that I could not stand my ground in
            this cause with a mind sufficiently fortified and resolute. I thought thus, that, as
            Hortensius was going to speak against me, and as Philip was going to listen to me
            carefully, I should through fear stumble in many particulars. I said to Quintus Roscius
            here, whose sister is the wife of Publius Quinctius, when he asked of me, and, with the
            greatest earnestness, entreated me to defend his relation, that it was very difficult
            for me, not only to sum up a cause against such orators, but even to attempt to speak at
            all. When he pressed it more eagerly, I said to the man very familiarly, as our
            friendship justified, that a man appeared to me to have a very brazen face, who, while
            he was present, could attempt to use action in speaking, but those who contended with
            him himself, even though before that they seemed to have any skill or elegance, lost it,
            and that I was afraid lest something of the same sort would happen to me when I was
            going to speak against so great an artist.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="25" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78" resp="perseus">
          <p>Then Roscius said many other things with a view to encourage me, and in truth, if he
            were to say nothing he would still move any one by the very silent affection and zeal
            which he felt for his relation. In truth, as he is an artist of that sort that he alone
            seems worthy of being looked at when he is on the stage, so he is also a man of such a
            sort that he alone seems to deserve never to go thither. “But what,”
            says he, “if you have such a cause as this, that you have only to make this
            plain, that there is no one in two or three days at most can walk seven hundred miles?
            Will you still fear that you will not be able to argue this point against
            Hortensius?”</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79" resp="perseus"><p>“No,” said
            I. “But what is that to the purpose?” “In
            truth,” said he, “that is what the cause turns upon.”
            “How so?” He then explains to me an affair of that sort, and at the
            same time an action of Sextus Naevius, which, if that alone were alleged, ought to be
            sufficient. And I beg of you, O Caius Aquillius, and of you the assessors, that you will
            attend to it carefully. You will see, in truth, that on the one side there were engaged
            from the very beginning covetousness and audacity, that on the other side truth and
            modesty resisted as long as they could. You demand to be allowed to take possession of
            his goods according to the edict. On what day I wish to hear you yourself, O Naevius. I
            want this unheard-of action to be proved by the voice of the very man who has committed
            it. Mention the day, Naevius. The twentieth of February. Right, how far is it from hence
            to your estate in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>? I ask you, Naevius.
            Seven hundred miles. Very well: Quinctius is driven off the estate. On what day? May we
            hear this also from you? Why are you silent? Tell me the day, I say.—He is
            ashamed to speak it. I understand; but he is ashamed too late, and to no purpose. He is
            driven off the estate on the twenty-third of February, O Caius Aquillius. Two days
            afterwards, or, even if any one had set off and run the moment he left the court, in
            under three days, he accomplishes seven hundred miles.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80" resp="perseus"><p>O incredible thing! O inconsiderate covetousness! O winged messenger! The agents and
            satellites of Sextus Naevius come from <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>,
            across the <placeName key="tgn,2066659">Alps</placeName>, among the Segusiani in two
            days. O happy man who has such messengers, or rather Pegasi. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          Here I, even if all the Crassi were to stand forth with all the Antonies, if you, O
            Lucius Philippus, who flourished among those men, choose to plead this cause, with
            Hortensius for your colleague, yet I must get the best of it. For everything does not
            depend, as you two think it does, on eloquence. There is still some truth so manifest
            that nothing can weaken it.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81" resp="perseus"><p>Did you, before you made
            the demand to be allowed to take possession of his goods, send any one to take care that
            the master should be driven by force off the estate by his own slaves? Choose whichever
            you like; the one is incredible; the other abominable; and both are unheard-of before
            this time. Do you mean that any one ran over seven hundred miles in two days? Tell me.
            Do you deny it? Then you sent some one beforehand. I had rather you did. For if you were
            to say that, you would be seen to tell an impudent lie: when you confess this, you admit
            that you did a thing which you cannot conceal even by a lies. Will such a design, so
            covetous, so audacious, so precipitate, be approved of by Aquillius and by such men as
            he is?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82" resp="perseus"><p>What does this madness, what does this baste,
            what does this precipitation intimate? Does it not prove violence? does it not prove
            wickedness? does it not prove robbery? does it not, in short, prove everything rather
            than right, than duty, or than modesty? You send some one without the command of the
            praetor. With what intention? You knew he would order it. What then? When he had ordered
            it, could you not have sent then? You were about to ask him. When? Thirty days after.
            Yes, if nothing hindered you; if the same intention existed; if you were well; in short,
            if you were alive. The praetor would have made the order, I suppose, if he chose, if he
            was well, if he was in court, if no one objected, by giving security according to his
            decree, and by being willing to stand a trial.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83" resp="perseus"><p>For,
            by the immortal gods, if Alphenus, the agent of Publius Quinctius, were then willing to
            give security and to stand a trial, and in short to do everything which you chose, what
            would you do? Would you recall him whom you had sent into <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>? But this man would have been already expelled from his farm,
            already driven headlong from his home, already (the most unworthy thing of all)
            assaulted by the hands of his own slaves, in obedience to your messenger and command.
            You would, forsooth, make amends for these things afterwards. Do you dare to speak of
            the life of any man, you who must admit this,—that you were so blinded by
            covetousness and avarice, that, though you did not know what would happen afterwards,
            but many things might happen, you placed your hope from a present crime in the uncertain
            event of the future? And I say this, just as if, at that very time when the praetor had
            ordered you to take possession according to his edict, you had sent any one to take
            possession, you either ought to, or could have ejected Publius Quinctius from
            possession.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="27" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84" resp="perseus">
          <p>Everything, O Caius Aquillius, is of such a nature that any one may be able to perceive
            that in this cause dishonesty and interest are contending with poverty and truth. How
            did the praetor order you to take possession? I suppose, in accordance with his edict.
            In what words was the recognizance drawn up? “If the goods of Publius
            Quinctius have been taken possession of in accordance with the praetor's
            edict.” Let us return to the edict. How does that enjoin you to take
            possession? Is there any pretence, O Caius Aquillius, if he took possession in quite a
            different way from that which the praetor enjoined, for denying that then he did not
            take possession according to the edict, but that I have beaten him in the trial? None, I
            imagine. Let us refer to the edict.—“They who in accordance with my
            edict have come into possession.” He is speaking of you, Naevius, as you
            think; for you say that you came into possession according to the edict. He defines for
            you what you are to do; he instructs you; he gives you precepts. “It seems
            that those ought to be in possession.” How? “That which they can
            rightly secure in the place where they now are, let them secure there; that which they
            cannot, they may carry or lead away.” What then? “It is not
            right,” says he, “to drive away the owner against his
            will.” The very man who with the object of cheating is keeping out of the way,
            the very man who deals dishonestly with all his creditors, he forbids to be driven off
            his farm against his will.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85" resp="perseus"><p>As you are on your way to
            take possession, O Sextus Naevius, the praetor himself openly says to
            you—“Take possession in such manner that Naevius may have possession
            at the same time with you; take possession in such a manner that no violence may be
            offered to Quinctius.” What? how do you observe that? I say nothing of his not
            having been a man who was keeping out of the way, of his being a man who had a house, a
            wife, children, and an agent at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; I say
            nothing of all this: I say this, that the owner was expelled from his farm; that hands
            were laid on their master by his own slaves, before his own household gods; I say <gap reason="lost"/>
            <milestone n="28" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          I say too that Naevius never even asked Quinctius for the money, when he was with him,
            and might have sued him every day; because he preferred that all the most perplexing
            modes of legal proceedings should take place, to his own great discredit, and to the
            greatest danger of Publius Quinctius, rather than allow of the simple trial about money
            matters which could have been got through in one day; from which one trial he admits
            that all these arose and proceeded. On which occasion I offered a condition, if he was
            determined to demand the money, that Publius Quinctius should give security to submit to
            the decision, if he also, if Quinctius had any demands upon him, would submit to the
            like conditions.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86" resp="perseus"><p>I showed how many things ought to be
            done before a demand was made that the goods of a relation should be taken possession
            of; especially when he had at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> his house,
            his wife, his children, and an agent who was equally an intimate friend of both. I
            proved that when he said the recognizances were forfeited, there were actually no
            recognizances at all; that on the day on which he says he gave him the promise, he was
            not even at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. I promised that I would make
            that plain by witnesses, who both must know the truth, and who had no reason for
            speaking falsely. I proved also that it was not possible that the goods should have been
            taken possession of according to the edict; because he was neither said to have kept out
            of the way for the purpose of fraud, nor to have left the country in banishment.
             </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87" resp="perseus"><p>The charge remains, that no one defended him at the
            trial. In opposition to which I argued that he was most abundantly defended, and that
            not by a man unconnected with him, nor by any slanderous or worthless person, but by a
            Roman knight, his own relation and intimate friend, whom Sextus Naevius himself had been
            accustomed previously to leave as his own agent. And that even if he did appeal to the
            tribunes, he was not on that account the less prepared to submit to a trial; and that
            Naevius had not had his rights wrested from him by the powerful interest of the agent;
            that on the other hand he was so much superior to us in interest that he now scarcely
            gives us the liberty of breathing.</p></div>
  <milestone n="29" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88" resp="perseus">
          <p>I asked what the reason was why the goods had not been sold, since they had been taken
            possession of according to the edict. Secondly, I asked this also, on what account not
            one of so many creditors either did the same thing then, why not one speaks against him
            now, but why they are all striving for Publius Quinctius? Especially when in such a
            trial the testimonies of creditors are thought exceedingly material. After that, I
            employed the testimony of the adversary, who lately entered as his partner the man who,
            according to the language of his present claim, <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la">Intentio</foreign> was the technical legal term for the claim made by the
              plaintiff.</note> he demonstrates was at that time not even in the number of living
            men. Then I mentioned that incredible rapidity, or rather audacity of his. I showed that
            it was inevitable, either that seven hundred miles had been run over in two days, or
            that Sextus Naevius had sent men to take possession many days before he demanded leave
            so to seize his goods.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89" resp="perseus"><p>After that I recited the
            edict, which expressly forbade the owner to be driven off his by which it was plain that
            Naevius had not taken possession according to the edict, as he confessed that Quinctius
            had been driven off his farm by force. But I thoroughly proved that the goods had
            actually not been taken possession of, because such a seizure of goods is looked at not
            as to part but with respect to everything which can be seized or taken possession of. I
            said that he had a house at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> which that
            fellow never even made an attempt on; that he had many slaves, of which he neither took
            possession of any, and did not even touch any; that there was one whom he attempted to
            touch; that he was forbidden to, and that he remained quiet.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90" resp="perseus"><p>You know also that Sextus Naevius never came on to the private farms
            of Quinctius even in <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>. Lastly I proved that
            the private servants of Quinctius were not all driven away from that very estate which
            he took possession of, having expelled his partner by force. From which, and from all
            the other sayings, and actions, and thoughts of Sextus Naevius, any one can understand
            that that fellow did nothing else, and is now doing nothing, but endeavouring by
            violence, by injustice, and by unfair means at this trial, to make the whole farm his
            own which belongs to both partners in common.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="30" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91" resp="perseus">
          <p>Now that I have summed up the whole cause the affair itself and the magnitude of the
            danger, O Caius Aquillius, seem to make it necessary for Publius Quinctius to solicit
            and entreat you and your colleagues, by his old age and his desolate condition, merely
            to follow the dictates or your own nature and goodness; so that as the truth is on his
            side, his necessitous state may move you to pity rather than the influence of the other
            party to cruelty.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92" resp="perseus"><p>From the self same day when we came
            before you as judges, we began to disregard all the threats of those men which before we
            were alarmed at. If cause was to contend with cause we are sure that we could easily
            prove ours to any one but as the course of life of the one was to be contested with the
            course of life of the other, we thought we had on that account even more need of you as
            our judge. For this is the very point now in question, whether the rustic and unpolished
            economy of my client can defend itself against the luxury and licentiousness of the
            other or whether, homely as it is, and stripped of all ornaments, it is to lie handed
            over naked to covetousness and wantonness.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93" resp="perseus"><p>Publius
            Naevius does not compare himself with you, O Sextus Naevius, he does not vie with you in
            riches or power. He gives up to you all the arts by which you are great; he confesses
            that he does not speak elegantly; that he is not able to say pleasant things to people;
            that he does not abandon a friendship when his friend is in distress, and fly off to
            another which is in flourishing circumstances; that he does not give magnificent and
            splendid banquets; that he has not a house closed against modesty and holiness, but open
            and as it were exposed to cupidity and debauchery; on the other hand he says that duty,
            good faith, industry and a life which has been always austere and void of pleasure has
            been his choice; he knows that the opposite course is more fashionable, and that by such
            habits people have more influence. What then shall be done?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94" resp="perseus"><p>They have not so much more influence, that those who, having
            abandoned the strict discipline of virtuous men, have chosen rather to follow the gains
            and extravagance of Gallonius,<note anchored="true">Gallonius was a crier also, branded
              by Horace as notorious for extravagance and luxury. <quote xml:lang="la">
                <l>Galloni praeconis erat acipensere mensa </l>
                <l>Infamis. </l>
              </quote>—<bibl n="Hor. Carm. 2.2.47">Hor. Sat. 2.2.47</bibl>.</note> and
            have even spent their liven in audacity and perfidy which were no part of his character,
            should have absolute dominion over the lives and fortunes of honourable men. If he may
            be allowed to live where Sextus Naevius does not wish to, if there is room in the city
            for an honest man against the will of Naevius; if Publius Quinctius may be allowed to
            breathe in opposition to the nod and sovereign power of Naevius; if under your
            protection, he can preserve in opposition to the insolence of his enemy the ornaments
            which he has acquired by virtue, there is hope that this unfortunate and wretched man
            may at last be able to rest in peace. But if Naevius is to have power to do everything
            he chooses, and if he chooses what is unlawful, what is to be done? What God is to be
            appealed to? The faith of what man can we invoke? What complaints, what lamentations can
            be devised adequate to so great a calamity.</p></div> 
  <milestone n="31" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95" resp="perseus">
          <p>It is a miserable thing to be despoiled of all one's fortunes; it is more miserable
            still to be so unjustly. It is a bitter thing to be circumvented by any one, more bitter
            still to be so by a relation. It is a calamitous thing to be stripped of one's goods,
            more calamitous still if accompanied by disgrace. It is an intolerable injury to be
            slain by a brave and honourable man, more intolerable still to be slain by one whose
            voice has been prostituted to the trade of a crier. It is an unworthy thing to be
            conquered by one's equal or one's superior, more unworthy still by one's inferior, by
            one lower than oneself. It is a grievous thing to be handed over with one's goods to
            another, more grievous still to be handed over to an enemy. It is a horrible thing to
            have to plead to a capital charge, more horrible still to have to speak in one's own
            defence before one's accuser speaks.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96" resp="perseus"><p>Quinctius has
            looked round on all sides, has encountered every danger. He was not only unable to find
            a praetor from whom he could obtain a trial, much less one from whom he could obtain one
            on his own terms, but he could not even move the friends of Sextus Naevius, at whose
            feet he often lay, and that for a long time, entreating them by the immortal Gods either
            to contest the point with him according to law, or at least, if they must do him
            injustice, to do it without ignominy.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97" resp="perseus"><p>Last of all he
            approached the haughty countenance of his very enemy; weeping he took the hand of Sextus
            Naevius, well practised in advertising the goods of his relations. He entreated him by
            the ashes of his dead brother by the name of their relationship, by his own wife and
            children to whom no one is a nearer relation than Publius Quinctius, at length to take
            pity on him, to have some regard, if not for their relationship, at least for his age,
            if not for a man, at least for humanity, to terminate the matter on any conditions as
            long as they were only endurable, leaving his character unimpeached.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98" resp="perseus"><p>Being rejected by him, getting no assistance from his friends being
            passed and frightened by every magistrate he has no one but you whom he can appeal to
            you he commends himself to you he commends all his property and fortunes to you he
            commends his character and his hopes for the remainder of his life. Harassed by much
            contumely suffered in under many injuries he flies to you not unworthy but unfortunate;
            driven out of a beautiful farm with his enemies attempting to fix every possible mark of
            ignominy on him, seeing his adversary the owner of his paternal property, while he
            himself is unable to make up a dowry for his marriageable daughter, he has still done
            nothing inconsistent with his former life.</p></div> 
           <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99" resp="perseus"><p>Therefore
            be begs this of you, O Caius Aquillius, that he may be allowed to carry with him out of
            this place the character and the probity which, now that his life is nearly come to an
            end, he brought with him before your tribunal. That he, of whose virtue no one ever
            doubted, may not in his sixtieth year be branded with disgrace, with stigma, and with
            the most shameful ignominy; that Sextus Naevius may not array himself in all his
            ornaments as spoils of victory; that it may not be owing to you that the character,
            which has accompanied Publius Quinctius to his old age, does not attend him to the
            tomb.</p></div>
            </div>

    </body>
      </text>
      </TEI>
