<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 7-9 - 7</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <biblStruct default="NO">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With An English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="NO">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="book">
                <head>Book VII</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="pr" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I think that enough has been said on the subject
of invention. For I have dealt not merely with the
methods by which we may instruct the judge, but
also with the means of appealing to his emotions.
But just as it is not sufficient for those who are
erecting a building merely to collect stone and timber
and other building materials, but skilled masons are
required to arrange and place them, so in speaking,
however abundant the matter may be, it will merely
form a confused heap unless arrangement be employed to reduce it to order and to give it connexion
and firmness of structure.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is it without good
reason that arrangement is treated as the second of
the five departments of oratory,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        vi. iv. 1. Invention, arrangement, style, memory,
delivery.
                    </note>
                    since without it the
first is useless. For the fact that all the limbs of a
statue have been cast does not make it a statue: they
must be put together; and if you were to interchange some one portion of our bodies or of those
of other animals with another, although the body
would be in possession of all the same members
                    <pb id="p.5"/>
                    as before, you would none the less have produced
a monster. Again even a slight dislocation will
deprive a limb of its previous use and vigour, and
disorder in the ranks will impede the movements of an army.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Nor can I regard as an error
the assertion that order is essential to the existence
of nature itself, for without order everything would
go to wrack and ruin. Similarly if oratory lack this
virtue, it cannot fail to be confused, but will be
like a ship drifting without a helmsman, will lack
cohesion, will fall into countless repetitions and
omissions, and, like a traveller who has lost his way
in unfamiliar country, will be guided solely by chance
without fixed purpose or the least idea either of
starting-point or goal.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The whole of this book, therefore, will be devoted
to arrangement, an art the acquisition of which would
never have been such a rarity, had it been possible to
lay down general rules which would suit all subjects.
Put since cases in the courts have always presented
an infinite variety, and will continue to do so, and
since through all the centuries there has never been
found one single case which was exactly like any
other, the pleader must rely upon his sagacity, keep
his eyes open, exercise his powers of invention and
judgment and look to himself for advice. On the
other hand, I do not deny that there are some points
which are capable of demonstration and which
accordingly I shall be careful not to pass by.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Division,</hi>
                    as I have already stated,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">v. x. 63.</note>
                    means the
division of a group of things into its component
parts,
                    <hi rend="italics">partition</hi>
                    is the separation of an individual
whole into its elements,
                    <hi rend="italics">order</hi>
                    the correct disposition
                    <pb id="p.7"/>
                    of things in such a way that what follows coheres
with what precedes, while
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    is the distribution of things and parts to the places which it is
expedient that they should occupy.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But we must
remember that
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    is generally dependent
on expediency, and that the same question will not
always be discussed first by both parties. An
example of what I mean, to quote no others, is
provided by Demosthenes and Aeschines, who adopt
a different order in the trial of Ctesiphon, since the
accuser begins by dealing with the legal question
involved, in which he thought he had the advantage,
whereas the advocate for the defence treats practically every other topic before coming to the question
of law, with a view to preparing the judges for a
consideration of the legal aspect of the case.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For
it will often be expedient for the parties to place
different points first; otherwise the pleading would
always be determined by the good pleasure of the
prosecution. Finally, in a case of mutual accusation,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III.
                        <hi rend="italics">x.</hi>
                        4.
                    </note>
                    where both parties have to defend themselves before
accusing their antagonist, the order of everything
must necessarily be different. I shall therefore set
forth the method adopted by myself, about which I
have never made any mystery: it is the result in
part of instruction received from others, in part of
my own reasoning.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    When engaged in forensic disputes I made it a
point to make myself familiar with every circumstance connected with the case.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp</hi>
                        iv. iv. 8; IV. ii. 28.
                    </note>
                    (In the schools,
of course, the facts of the case are definite and
limited in number and are moreover set out before
we begin to declaim: the Greeks call them
                    <hi rend="italics">themes,</hi>
                    which Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.,</hi>
                        21.
                    </note>
                    translates by
                    <hi rend="italics">propositions.</hi>
                    ) When I
                    <pb id="p.9"/>
                    had formed a general idea of these circumstances, I
proceeded to consider them quite as much from my
opponent's point of view as from my own.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The
first point which I set myself to determine (it is
easy enough to state, but is still all-important) was
what each party desired to establish and then what
means he was likely to adopt to that end. My
method was as follows. I considered what the
prosecutor would say first: his point must either be
admitted or controversial: if admitted, no question
could arise in this connexion.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    I therefore passed to
the answer of the defence and considered it from the
same standpoint: even there the point was sometimes one that was admitted. It was not until the
parties ceased to agree that any question arose.
'fake for example the following case.
                    <quote>You killed a man.</quote>
                    <quote>Yes, I killed him.</quote>
                    Agreed, I pass to
the defence,
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    which has to produce the motive for
the homicide.
                    <quote>It is lawful,</quote>
                    lie urges,
                    <quote>to kill an adulterer with his paramour.</quote>
                    Another admitted
point, for there is no doubt about the law. We
must look for a third point where the two parties are
at variance.
                    <quote>They were not adulterers,</quote>
                    say the
prosecution;
                    <quote>They were,</quote>
                    say the defence. Here
then is the question at issue: there is a doubt as to
the facts, and it is therefore a question of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecure.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        a question as to facts.
                        <hi rend="italics">cv.</hi>
                        VII. ii.
                    </note>
                    Sometimes even the third point may be admitted;
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    it is granted that they were adulterers.
                    <quote>But,</quote>
                    says
the accuser,
                    <quote>you had no right to kill them, for you were an exile</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>had forfeited your civil rights.</quote>
                    The question is now one of law. On the other
hand, if when the prosecution says,
                    <quote>You killed them,</quote>
                    the defence at once replies,
                    <quote>I did not,</quote>
                    the
issue is raised without more delay.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.11"/>
                <p>
                    If it requires some search to discover where the
dispute really begins, we must consider what constitutes the first question. The charge may be simple,
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    as for example
                    <quote>Rabirius killed Saturninus,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        v. xi. 6.
                    </note>
                    or
complex like the following:
                    <quote>
                        The offence committed
by Lucius Varenus falls under the law of assassination
for he procured the murder of Gaius Varenus, the
wounding of Gnaeus Varenus and also the murder
of Salarius.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        v. xiii. 38.
                    </note>
                    In the latter case there will be a
number of propositions, a statement which also
applies to civil suits as well. But in a complex case
there may be a number of
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    :
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 1
                        <hi rend="italics">sq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    for
instance the accused may deny one fact, justify
another and plead technical grounds to show
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 23 and 52.
                    </note>
                    that
a third fact is not actionable. In such cases the
pleader will have to consider what requires refutation
and where that refutation should be placed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the prosecutor, I do not altogether
disagree with Celsus, who, though no doubt in so
doing he is following the practice of Cicero, insists
with some vehemence on the view that the first
place should be given to some strong argument,
but that the strongest should be reserved to the end,
while the weaker arguments should be placed in the
middle, since the judge has to be moved at the beginning and forcibly impelled to a decision at the end.
But with the defence it is different:
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    the strongest
arguments as a rule require to be disposed of first,
for fear that the judge through having his thoughts
fixed on those arguments should regard the defence
of other points with disfavour. Sometimes, however,
this order is subject to alteration; for example if the
minor arguments are obviously false and the refutation of the most serious argument a matter of some
                    <pb id="p.13"/>
                    difficulty, we should attack it last of all, after discrediting the prosecution by demonstrating the falsity
of the former, thereby disposing the judges to believe that all their arguments are equally unreliable.
We shall, however, require to preface our remarks by
explaining why we postpone dealing with the most
serious charge, and by promising that we will deal
with it at a later stage: otherwise the fact that we do
not dispose of it at once may give the impression that
we are afraid of it.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Charges brought against the
past life of the accused should generally be dealt
with first in order that the judge may be well disposed to listen to our defence on that point on which
lie has to give his verdict. But Cicero in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Vareno</hi>
                    postpones his treatment of such charges to
the conclusion, being guided not by the general rule,
but by the special circumstances of the case.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    When the accusation is simple, we must consider
whether to give a single answer to the charge or
several. In the former case, we must decide
whether the question is one of fact or of law: if it is
one of fact, we must deny the fact or justify it: if, on
the other hand, it is a question of law, we must decide
on what special point the dispute arises and whether
the question turns on the letter or the intention of
the law.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    We shall do this by considering what the
law is which gives rise to the dispute, that is to say
under what law the court has been constituted. In
scholastic themes, for example, the laws are sometimes stated merely with a view to connecting the
arguments of the cases. Take the following case:
                    <quote>
                        A father who recognises a son whom he has exposed in infancy, shall only take him back after paying
for his keep. A disobedient son may be disinherited.
                        <pb id="p.15"/>
                        A man who took back a son whom he had exposed
orders him to marry a wealthy neighbour. The son
desires to marry the daughter of the poor man who
brought him up.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The law about children who have
been exposed affords scope for emotional treatment,
while the decision of the court turns on the law of
disinheritance.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The first law is strictly irrelevant to the case, but can
be employed by the son to stir the jury's emotions. He owes
a deep debt of gratitude to his poor foster-father, and his
love for his foster-sister is based on life-long acquaintance.
The father, on the other hand, will urge that his payment
for his son's nurture has discharged the debt due to the poor
man and that his son is once more under the
                        <hi rend="italics">patria potestas.</hi>
                        The introduction of the first law thus enables the pleader to
introduce fresh arguments and is thus said to link up the
arguments.
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, a question may
turn on more laws than one, as in cases of
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ntinomi/a</foreign>
                    or contradictory laws.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 46. and vii.
                    </note>
                    It is by consideration of such
points as these that we shall be able to determine
the point of law out of which the dispute arises.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    As an example of complex defence I may quote
the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Rabirio:</hi>
                    <quote>If he had killed him, he would have been justified in so doing: but he did not kill him.</quote>
                    But when we advance a number of points in
answer to a single proposition, we must first of all
consider everything that can be said on the subject,
and then decide which out of these points it is expedient to select and where to put them forward.
My views on this subject are not identical with
those which I admitted a little while ago
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 10.</note>
                    on the
subject of
                    <hi rend="italics">propositions</hi>
                    and on that of
                    <hi rend="italics">arguments</hi>
                    in
the section which I devoted to
                    <hi rend="italics">proofs,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">v. xii. 14.</note>
                    to the effect
that we may sometimes begin with the strongest.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    For when we are defending, there should always be an
increase of force in the treatment of questions and we
should proceed from the weaker to the stronger,
whether the points we raise are of the same or of a
different character.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Questions of law will often arise
from one ground of dispute after another, whereas
questions of fact are always concerned with one point;
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This statement amounts to no more than that there may
be infinite complication where questions of law are concerned, but questions of fact are simple and there is but one
point to be considered,
                        <quote>was such and such an act committed?</quote>
                    </note>
                    <pb id="p.17"/>
                    but the order to be followed is the same in both
cases. We must, however, deal first with points that
differ in character. In such cases the weakest
should always be handled first, for the reason that
there are occasions when after discussing a question
we make a concession or present of it to our opponents: for we cannot pass on to others without
dropping those which come first.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    This should be
done in such a way as to give the impression not
that we regard the points as desperate, but that we
have deliberately dropped them because we can
prove our case without them. Suppose that the
agent for a certain person claims the interest on a
loan as due under an inheritance. The question may
here arise whether such a claim can be made by an
agent.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See IV. iv. 6.</note>
                    Assume that, after discussing the question,
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    we drop it or that the argument is refuted. We
then raise the question whether the person in whose
name the action is brought has the right to employ
an agent. Let us yield this point also.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. 6, 8.
                    </note>
                    The case
will still admit of our raising the question whether
the person in whose name the suit is brought is
heir to the person to whom the interest was due
and again whether he is sole heir.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Grant these
points also and we can still raise the question whether
the sum is due at all? On the other hand, no one
will be so insane as to drop what he considers his
strongest point and pass to others of minor importance. The following case from a scholastic theme
is of a similar character.
                    <quote>
                        You may not disinherit
your adopted son. And if you may disinherit him
                        <hi rend="italics">quâ</hi>
                        adopted son, you may not disinherit one who is
so brave. And if you may disinherit one who is so
brave, you may not disinherit him because he has
                        <pb id="p.19"/>
                        not obeyed your every command; and if he was
bound to obey you in all else, you may not disinherit
him on the ground of his choice of a reward; and
even if the choice of a reward may give just ground
for disinheriting, that is not true of such a choice
as he actually made.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            The adopted son has done some heroic deed, bringing
him under the scholastic law
                            <hi rend="italics">vir fortis optet quod uolet,</hi>
                            <quote>Let a hero choose what reward he will</quote>
                            (
                            <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                            v. x. 97). A
scandalous choice might give ground for disinheriting him
(cp. § 24 below), but the choice in question is not
scandalous.
                        </note>
                        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    </quote>
                    Such is the nature of
dissimilarity where points of law are concerned.
Where, however, the question is one of fact, there
may be several points all tending to the same result,
of which some may be dropped as not essential to
the main issue, as for instance if a man accused of
theft should say to his accuser,
                    <quote>
                        Prove that you had
the property, prove that you lost it, prove that it
was stolen, prove that it was stolen by me.
                    </quote>
                    The
first three can be dropped, but not the last.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I used also to employ the following method.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    I
went back from the ultimate
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    (which generally
contains the vital point of the case) to the first
general question or descended from the
                    <hi rend="italics">genus</hi>
                    to the
ultimate
                    <hi rend="italics">species,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        v. x. 5, 6. The statement
                        <quote>man is an animal</quote>
                        is
insufficient as a definition,
                        <quote>animal</quote>
                        being the
                        <hi rend="italics">genus.</hi>
                        <quote>Man is mortal</quote>
                        introduces a
                        <hi rend="italics">species,</hi>
                        but one common to other
animals.
                        <quote>Man is rational</quote>
                        introduces the
                        <hi rend="italics">ultima species.</hi>
                    </note>
                    applying this method even to deliberative themes.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    For example, Numa is deliberating
whether to accept the crown offered him by the
Romans. First he considers the general question,
                    <quote>Ought I to be a king?</quote>
                    Then,
                    <quote>
                        Ought I to be
king in a foreign state? Ought I to be king at
Rome? Are the Romans likely to put up with such
a king as myself?
                    </quote>
                    So too in controversial themes.
Suppose a brave man to choose another man's wife
as his reward. The ultimate
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    is found in the
question whether lie is allowed to choose another
man's wife. The
                    <hi rend="italics">general</hi>
                    question is whether he
should be given whatever he chooses. Next come
questions such as whether he can choose his reward
from the property of private individuals, whether he
                    <pb id="p.21"/>
                    can choose a bride as his reward, and if so, whether
he can choose one who is already married.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    But in
our search for such questions we follow an order
quite different from that which we employ in actual
speaking.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. ix. 6.
                    </note>
                    For that which as a rule occurs to us first,
is just that which ought to come last in our speech:
as for instance the conclusion,
                    <quote>You have no right to choose another man's wife.</quote>
                    Consequently undue
haste will spoil our division of the subject. We
must not therefore be content with the thoughts
that first offer themselves, but should press our
inquiry further till we reach conclusions such as
that he ought not even to choose a widow: a further
advance is made when we reach the conclusion that
be should choose nothing that is private property, or
last of all we may go back to the question next in
order to the general question, and conclude that he
should choose nothing inequitable.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently
after surveying our opponent's proposition, an easy
task, we should consider, if possible, what it is most
natural to answer first. And, if we imagine the case
as being actually pleaded and ourselves as under the
necessity of making a reply, that answer will probably suggest itself. On the other hand,
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    if this is
impossible, we should put aside whatever first
                    <hi rend="italics">occurs</hi>
                    to us and reason with ourselves as follows:
                    <quote>What if this were not the case?</quote>
                    We must then repeat
the process a second and a third time and so on,
until nothing is left for consideration. Thus we
shall examine even minor points, by our treatment
of which we may perhaps make the judge all the
better disposed to us when we come to the main
issue.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    The rule that we should descend from the
                    <hi rend="italics">common</hi>
                    to the
                    <hi rend="italics">particular</hi>
                    is much the same, since
                    <pb id="p.23"/>
                    what is
                    <hi rend="italics">common</hi>
                    is usually
                    <hi rend="italics">general.</hi>
                    For example,
                    <quote>He killed a tyrant</quote>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italics">common,</hi>
                    while
                    <quote>A tyrant was killed by his son, by a woman or by his wife</quote>
                    are all
                    <hi rend="italics">particular.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    I used also to note down separately whatever was
admitted both by my opponent and myself, provided
it suited my purpose, and not merely to press any
admissions that he might make, but to multiply
them by partition, as for example in the following
controversial theme:—
                    <quote>
                        A general, who had stood
against his father as a candidate and defeated him,
was captured: the envoys who went to ransom him
met his father returning from the enemy. He said
to the envoys, 'You are too late.'
                        <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                        They searched
the father and found gold in his pockets. They
pursued their journey and found the general crucified. He cried to them, ' Beware of the traitor.'
The father is accused.
                    </quote>
                    What points are admitted
by both parties?
                    <quote>We were told that there had been treason and told it by the general.</quote>
                    We try
to find the traitor.
                    <quote>
                        You admit that you went to the
enemy, that you did so by stealth, that you returned
unscathed, that you brought back gold and had it
concealed about your person.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    For an act of the
accused may sometimes be stated in such a way as
to tell heavily against him, and if our statement
makes a real impression on the mind of the judge,
it may serve to close his ears to all that is urged by
the defence. For as a general rule it is of advantage
to the accuser to mass his facts together and to the
defence to separate them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I used also, with reference to the whole material
of the case, to do what I have already mentioned
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">V. x. 66.</note>
                    as being done with arguments, namely, after first
                    <pb id="p.25"/>
                    setting forth all the facts without exception, I then
disposed of all of them with the one exception
of the fact which I wished to be believed. For
example, in charges of collusion it may be argued
as follows.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        The means for securing the acquittal
of an accused person are strictly limited. His innocence may be established, some superior authority
may intervene, force or bribery may be employed,
his guilt may be difficult to prove, or there may be
collusion between the advocates. You admit that
he was guilty; no superior authority intervened, no
violence was used and you make no complaint that
the jury was bribed, while there was no difficulty
about proving his guilt. What conclusion is left to
us save that there was collusion?
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    If I could not
dispose of all the points against me, I disposed of
the majority.
                    <quote>
                        It is acknowledged that a man was
killed: but he was not killed in a solitary place,
such as might lead me to suspect that he was the
victim of robbers; he was not killed for the sake of
plunder, for nothing was taken from him; he was
not killed in the hope of inheriting his property, for
he was poor: the motive must therefore have been
hatred, since you are his enemy.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    The task not
merely of division, but of invention as well, is rendered materially easier by this method of examining
all possible arguments and arriving at the best by a
process of elimination. Milo is accused of killing
Clodius. Either he did or did not do the deed.
The best policy would be to deny the fact, but that
is impossible. It is admitted then that he killed
him. The act must then have been either right or
wrong. We urge that it was right. If so, the act
must have either been deliberate or under
                    <pb id="p.27"/>
                    compulsion of necessity, for it is impossible to plead
ignorance.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    The intention is doubtful, but as it is
generally supposed to have existed, some attempt
must he made to defend it and to show that it was
for the good of the state. On the other hand, if we
plead necessity, we shall argue that the fight was
accidental and unpremeditated. One of the two
parties then must have lain in wait for the other.
Which was it? Clodius without doubt. Do you
see how inevitably we are led to the right method
of defence by the logical necessity of the facts?
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    We
may carry the process further: either he wished to
kill Clodius, who lay in wait for him, or he did not.
The safer course is to argue that he did not wish
to kill him. It was then the slaves of Milo who did
the deed without Milo's orders or knowledge. But
this line of defence shows a lack of courage and
lessens the weight of our argument that Clodius
was rightly killed.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    We shall therefore add the
words,
                    <quote>As every man would have wished his slaves to do under similar circumstances.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">pro Mil.</hi>
                        x. 29.
V. iv. 8.
                    </note>
                    This method is
all the more useful from the fact that often we can
find nothing to say that really pleases us and yet
have got to say something. Let us therefore consider every possible point; for thus we shall discover what is the best line for us to pursue, or at
any rate what is least bad. Sometimes, as I have
already said in the appropriate context,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">pro Mil.</hi>
                        x. 29.
V. iv. 8.
                    </note>
                    we may
make good use of the statement of our opponent,
since occasionally it is equally to the purpose of
both parties.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I am aware that some authors have written
thousands of lines to show how we may discover
which party ought to speak first. But in the actual
                    <pb id="p.29"/>
                    practice of the courts this is decided either by some
brutally rigid formula, or by the character of the
suit, or finally by lot.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    In the schools, on the other
hand, such an enquiry is mere waste of time, since
the prosecution and the defence are indifferently
permitted to state a case and refute it in the same
declamation. But in the majority of controversial
themes it is not even possible to discover who
should speak first, as for instance in the following:
                    <quote>
                        A certain man had three sons, an orator, a
philosopher and a physician. In his will he divided
his property into four portions, three of which he
distributed equally among his sons, while the fourth
was to go to the son who rendered the greatest
service to his country.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    The sons dispute the point.
It is uncertain who should speak first, but our
course is clear enough. For we shall begin with the
son whose role we assume. So much for the general
rules by which we should be guided in making our
                    <hi rend="italics">division.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    But how shall we discover those
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    which
present abnormal difficulty? Just as we discover
reflexions, words, figures or the appropriate
                    <hi rend="italics">nuances</hi>
                    of style,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Or perhaps
                        <quote>glosses,</quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        the giving of a special aspect
to the case by skilful representation of facts.
                    </note>
                    namely by native wit, by study and by
practice. None the less it will be rare for anyone
who is not a fool to fail to discover them, so long as
he is content, as I have said,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 26.</note>
                    to accept nature for a
guide.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Many, however, in their passionate desire to
win a reputation for eloquence are content to produce
showy passages which contribute nothing to the
proof of their case, while others think that their
enquiry need not proceed further than that which
meets the eye.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To make my meaning clearer, I will cite a
                    <pb id="p.31"/>
                    solitary example from the controversial themes of
the schools; it is neither novel nor complicated.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        The man who refuses to appear in defence
of his father when accused of treason shall be
disinherited: the man who is condemned for treason
shall be banished together with his advocate. A
father accused of treason was defended by one
son who was a fluent speaker, while another son,
who was uneducated, refused to appear for him.
The father was condemned and banished with his
advocate. The uneducated son performed some
heroic act and demanded as a reward the restoration
of his father and brother. The father returned and
died intestate. The uneducated son claims a portion
of his estate, the orator claims the whole for himself.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    In this case those paragons of eloquence,
who laugh at us because we trouble our heads about
cases that rarely occur, will always assume the
popular rôle. They will defend the uneducated
against the eloquent son, the brave against the
coward, the son who secured the recall of his kin
against the ungrateful son, the son who is content
with a portion of the inheritance against the son
who would refuse his brother a share in their
patrimony.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    All these points are actually to be
found in the case and are of considerable importance, but they are not such as to render victory
a certainty. In such a case they will, as far as
possible, search for daring or obscure reflexions (for
to-day obscurity is accounted a virtue), and they
will think they have given the theme a brilliant
treatment by ranting and raving over it. Those, on
the other hand, whose ideals are higher, but who
restrict themselves merely to the obvious, will note
                    <pb id="p.33"/>
                    the following points, which are, however, purely
superficial.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    The uneducated son may be excused
for not appearing at the trial on the ground that he
could contribute nothing to his father's defence: but
even the orator has no claim on the gratitude of
the accused, since the latter was condemned:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Sc.</hi>
                        in spite of his own eloquence.
                    </note>
                    the
man who secured the recall of his kin deserves
to receive the inheritance, while the man who
refuses to divide it with his brother, more especially with a brother who has deserved so well
of him, is avaricious, unnatural and ungrateful:
they will further note that the first and essential
question is that which turns on the letter and intention of the law; unless this is first disposed of,
all subsequent arguments must fall to the ground.
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    He, however, who follows the guidance of nature
will assuredly reflect as follows: the first argument
of the uneducated son will be,
                    <quote>
                        My father died
intestate and left two sons, my brother and myself;
I claim a share in his estate by the law of nations.
                    </quote>
                    Who is so ignorant or so lacking in education as
not to make this his opening, even though he
does not know what is meant by a proposition?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See IV. iv.</note>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    He will then proceed to extol, though with due
moderation, the justice of this common law of
nations. The next point for our consideration is
what reply can be made to so equitable a demand?
The answer is clear:—
                    <quote>
                        There is a law which disinherits the man who fails to appear in his father's
defence when the latter is accused of treason, and
you failed to appear.
                    </quote>
                    This statement will be
followed by the necessary praise of the law and
denunciation of the man who failed to appear.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    So far we have been dealing entirely with
                    <pb id="p.35"/>
                    admitted facts. Let us now return to the claimant.
Unless he is hopelessly unintelligent, surely the
following argument will suggest itself:—
                    <quote>
                        If the law
bars the way, there is no ground for action and the
trial becomes a farce. But it is beyond question that
the law exists and that the uneducated son did
commit the offence for which it enacts a punishment.
                    </quote>
                    What then shall we say?
                    <quote>I had no education.</quote>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    But if the law applies to all men, it
will be of no avail to plead lack of education. We
must therefore try to discover whether there be not
some point on which the law can be invalidated.
We turn for guidance to nature (a point on which
I cannot insist too often); what does she suggest
save that when the letter of the law is against us,
we should discuss its intention? This introduces
the general question whether we are to stand by the
letter or the spirit. But if we argue this question
on general grounds with reference to law in the
abstract, we shall go on for ever; it is a question
that has never been decided. We must therefore
restrict our enquiry to the particular law on which
our case turns and try to find some argument
against adhesion to the strict letter.
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    Well, then, is
everyone who fails to appear in defence of his father
to be disinherited? Are there no exceptions to the
rule? At this point the following arguments will
spontaneously suggest themselves.
                    <quote>Is an infant liable to the law?</quote>
                    For we may imagine a case
where the son is an infant and has failed to appear
in his father's support. Again
                    <quote>
                        does the law apply
to a man who was away from home or absent on
military service or on an embassy?
                    </quote>
                    We have
gained a considerable amount of ground; for we
                    <pb id="p.37"/>
                    have established the fact that a man may fail to
appear for his father and still inherit.
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    Our declaimer,
who has thought out this line of argument, must now
pass over like a Latin flute-player, as Cicero says,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Pro Mur.</hi>
                        xii. 26. The flute-player went from one actor
to another, according as each required accompaniment.
                    </note>
                    to the side of the eloquent son and reply,
                    <quote>
                        Granted,
but you are not an infant, you were not away from
home nor absent on military service.
                    </quote>
                    Is there any
answer to this except the previous reply,
                    <quote>I am an uneducated man</quote>
                    ?
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    But to this there is the obvious
retort,
                    <quote>Even if you could not actually plead, you might have supported him by your presence,</quote>
                    which is no more than the simple truth. The uneducated son must therefore return to the intention
of the legislator.
                    <quote>He wished to punish unfilial conduct, but I am not unfilial.</quote>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    To this the
eloquent son will reply,
                    <quote>
                        The action whereby you
deserved disinheritance was unfilial, although penitence or desire for display may have subsequently
led you to choose this as your reward. Further,
it was owing to you that our father was condemned,
since by absenting yourself you appeared to imply
that you thought him guilty.
                    </quote>
                    The uneducated son
replies,
                    <quote>
                        Nay, you contributed to his condemnation, for you had given offence to many and made
our family unpopular.
                    </quote>
                    These arguments are based
on conjecture, as also will be the excuse put forward
by the uneducated son to the effect that his father
advised his absence, as he did not wish to emperil
his whole family. All these arguments are involved
in the preliminary question as to the letter and the
intention of the law.
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    Let us pursue the matter
further and see if we can discover any additional
arguments. How is that to be done? I am deliberately imitating the actual train of thought of one
                    <pb id="p.39"/>
                    who is engaged in such an enquiry with a view to
showing how such enquiry should be conducted. I
shall therefore put aside the more showy kind of
composition, and concern myself solely with such as
may be of real profit to the student.
                </p>
                <p>
                    So far we have derived all our questions from the
character of the claimant. But why should we not
make some enquiries into the character of the father?
Does not the law say that whoever fails to appear
for his father is to be disinherited?
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    Why should we
not try asking whether this means that he is to be
disinherited, whatever the character of the father
for whom he failed to appear? Such a course is
often adopted in those controversial themes in
which we demand that sons who fail to maintain
their parents should be cast into prison: take for
example the case of the mother who gave evidence
against her son when accused of being an alien, or
of the father who sold his son to a procurer. What,
then, is there in the present case that we lay hold of
as regards the character of the father?
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    He was
condemned. But does the law apply only to those
cases where the father is acquitted? At first sight
the question is difficult. But let us not despair. It
is probable that the intention of the legislator was
that innocent parents should secure the support of
their children. But the uneducated son will be
ashamed to produce this argument, since he acknowledges that his father was innocent.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    There is, however, another line of argument which may be drawn
from the enactment that the person condemned for
treason should be banished together with his
advocate. It seems almost impossible that in one
and the same case a son should incur a penalty,
                    <pb id="p.41"/>
                    both if he appeared in his father's defence and if
he did not appear. Further, exiles are outlaws.
Therefore the letter of the law cannot conceivably apply to the advocate of the condemned
man.
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    For how can an exile hold any property?
The uneducated son raises a doubt as to the interpretation both of the letter and the spirit of the law.
Tile eloquent son will cling to the strict letter of
tile law, which makes no exception, and will argue
that the reason for enacting a penalty against those
who fail to appear for their fathers was to prevent
their being deterred from the defence of their
fathers by the risk of banishment, and he will assert
that his brother failed to appear in defence of
his innocent father. It may therefore be worth
while pointing out that two
                    <hi rend="italics">general questions</hi>
                    may
arise out of one
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    —
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        III. vi. 1
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                        The
                        <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                        or main point on which the case
turns is that of the intention of the law (
                        <hi rend="italics">voluntas</hi>
                        ).
                    </note>
                    for we may ask,
                    <quote>Is everyone who fails to appear liable to disinheritance?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Is he bound to appear irrespective of the character of his father?</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    So far all our questions have been derived from
two of the persons involved.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        the father and the uneducated son.
                    </note>
                    With regard to the
third, this can give rise to no question, as there is
no dispute about his portion of the inheritance.
Still the time is not yet come to relax our
efforts: for so far all the arguments might have
been used even if the father had not been recalled
from exile. But we must not betake ourselves
at once to the obvious point that he was recalled
by the agency of the uneducated son. A little
ingenuity will lead us to look further a field:
for as
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    comes after
                    <hi rend="italics">genus,</hi>
                    so
                    <hi rend="italics">genus</hi>
                    precedes
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                        species.
                    </hi>
                    Let us therefore assume that the father
was recalled by someone else. This will give rise
                    <pb id="p.43"/>
                    to a question of the ratiocinative or syllogistic type,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 15, 43, 46, 51; vii. viii. 1.
                    </note>
                    namely whether recall from exile cancels the sentence of the court and is tantamount to the trial
never having taken place at all. The uneducated
son will therefore attempt to argue that, being
entitled to not more than one reward, there was no
means by which he could have secured the recall of
his kin save by the restoration of his father on the
same terms as if he had never been accused, and
that this fact carries with it the cancellation of the
penalty incurred by his advocate, as though he had
never defended his father at all.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The reward to be chosen, it is argued, covered the
recall of one person only. The only means by which
                        <hi rend="italics">both</hi>
                        father and son could be recalled was by the restoration of
the father, whose amnesty would
                        <hi rend="italics">ipso facto</hi>
                        extend to the son
as well.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    Our next point
will be that which first occurred to us, namely the
plea that he was recalled by the agency of the
uneducated son. At this point we are confronted
by the question whether the son who secured his
father's restoration is thereby to be regarded in the
light of an advocate, since he secured for him
precisely what his original advocate demanded for
him, and it is not an unreasonable claim to ask that
an action should be regarded as equivalent when it
is really more than equivalent.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    The remaining
points turn on questions of equity, for we ask which
of the two sons makes the juster claim. This
question admits of still further division. The claim
of the uneducated son would have been the juster
even if both had claimed the whole property. How
much more so when one claims only a half and the
other the whole to the exclusion of his brother.
And then, even after we have dealt with all these
points, an appeal to the memory of his father will
carry great weight with the judges, more especially
as the dispute is about the father's estate. This
will give rise to conjecture as to what the intentions
                    <pb id="p.45"/>
                    of the father were at the time of his dying intestate.
This conjecture, however, involves a question of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    and is employed in the service of a
different
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        qualitative,
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 43.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    As a rule questions of equity are
best introduced at the conclusion of a case, since
there is nothing to which the judges give more
ready hearing. Sometimes, however, the interests
of the case demand a change in this order; for
example if we regard our case as weak in point of
law, it will be well to secure the good-will of the
judge by dealing with the question of equity first.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    This concludes my general rules on this subject.
We will now proceed to consider the several parts
of forensic cases, and although I cannot follow them
to the
                    <hi rend="italics">ultimate species,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        VI. i. 23.
                    </note>
                    that is to say, I cannot deal
with individual suits and controversies, I shall be
able to discuss them on general lines in such a way
as to show what
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    most of them involve. And
since the first question naturally is whether an
alleged fact has taken place, I will begin with this.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    All conjecture is concerned either with facts
or intention. Each of these may occur in one of
three times, past, present or future. Questions
concerning facts are either general or definite, that
is to say, those which involve consideration of
persons and those which do not.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Concerning intentions there can be no questions which do not
involve some person and where the facts of the
case are not admitted. Therefore when the question
turns on some fact, the point on which doubt arises
is either what has been done, or what is being done,
or what is likely to be done. For example, in general
questions we discuss whether the universe
                    <hi rend="italics">has been</hi>
                    formed of a concourse of atoms, or
                    <hi rend="italics">is</hi>
                    governed by
                    <pb id="p.47"/>
                    providence, or
                    <hi rend="italics">is likely</hi>
                    some day to come to an end.
In definite questions, on the other hand, we discuss whether Roscius
                    <hi rend="italics">has</hi>
                    murdered his father,
whether Manlius
                    <hi rend="italics">is</hi>
                    aiming at making himself king,
or Quintus Caecilius
                    <hi rend="italics">will be</hi>
                    justified in appearing
as the accuser of Verres.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In the law courts past
time is of most importance, since all accusations
are concerned with what has actually been done,
while what is being done or is likely to be done is
inferred from the past. We also enquire into origins.
For instance, we enquire whether a pestilence be
due to the anger of heaven, the inclement weather,
the pollution of the water-supply, or the noxious
vapours emitted by the earth. Again, we seek for
the motives of an act. For example, we enquire
whether the fifty kings who sailed against Troy did
so because they were bound by their oath, or were
moved to do so by righteous indignation, or merely
desired to gratify the sons of Atreus. There is no
very great difference between these two classes of
question.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As regards facts falling within the present,
if they can be detected by the eye without any
reference to their logical antecedents being required,
there will be no need of conjecture: let us suppose,
for instance, that the Lacedaemonians are enquiring
whether the Athenians are erecting fortifications.
But although conjecture may seem entirely foreign
to this class of question, there are cases in which it
it necessary, as in questions of personal identity,
which may be illustrated by the action brought
against the heirs of Urbinia,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cv.</hi>
                        IV. i. 11 and VII. ii. 26.
                    </note>
                    where the question
was whether the man who claimed the property as
being the son of the deceased, was Figulus or Sosipater.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In this case the actual person was before the
                    <pb id="p.49"/>
                    eyes of the court, so that there could be no question
whether he existed (as there is, for instance, when
we ask whether there exists any land beyond the
Ocean)
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        viii. 16.
                    </note>
                    nor what he was nor of what kind. The
question was simply, who he was. But this kind of
dispute also depends on past time. The problem is
whether this man Clusinius Figulus
                    <hi rend="italics">was</hi>
                    born of
Urbinia. Such disputes have arisen even in our
own day, indeed I myself have pleaded in such.
On the other hand,
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    conjecture as to intention is
obviously concerned with all three times. We ask
with what purpose Ligarius
                    <hi rend="italics">went</hi>
                    to Africa, with
what purpose Pyrrhus
                    <hi rend="italics">is</hi>
                    asking for a treaty, and
how Caesar
                    <hi rend="italics">will</hi>
                    take it if Ptolemy kills Pompey.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. viii. 56.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    We may also employ conjecture to enquire into
quality in questions dealing with size, species and
number, such as whether the sun is greater than the
earth, whether the moon is spherical, flat or conical,
whether there is one universe or several, or,
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    to go
outside these physical speculations, whether the
Trojan or the Peloponnesian war was the greatest,
what was the nature of the shield of Achilles, or
whether there was more than one Hercules.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In forensic cases, however, which consist of
accusation and defence, there is one kind of conjecture by which we enquire both about an act
and about its author. This sometimes treats the two
questions together, as, for example, when both the
act and the identity of the author are denied, and
sometimes separately, as when the first enquiry,
whether the act was committed, is followed by a
second, where, the act being admitted, the question
is by whom it was committed.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The act itself again
sometimes involves a single question, as, for example,
                    <pb id="p.51"/>
                    whether a man is dead, and sometimes two, as, for
instance, whether he died of poison or of some internal
disease. Another form of conjecture is concerned
with the act alone, it being admitted that if the
act was really committed, there can be no doubt as
to its author. A third form is concerned solely with
the author, the act being admitted and the dispute
turning on the question as to who committed it.
This third form is complex.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For the accused either
confines himself to denying that he did it or accuses
another of having done it. Further, there is more
than one way of transferring the charge to another.
At times this results in
                    <hi rend="italics">mutual accusation,</hi>
                    which the
Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ntikathgori/a,</foreign>
                    and some of our own authors
                    <hi rend="italics">concertative accusation.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        mutual or reciprocal accusation, see VII. i. 3.
                    </note>
                    At times, on the other hand,
the charge is transferred to some person who
cannot be brought to trial, and may be either
known or unknown: again, if the person is known,
he may be someone outside the case or the victim
himself, who may be alleged to have committed
suicide.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    In such cases we compare characters,
motives and other circumstances in the same way
as in eases of mutual accusation. Cicero, for instance,
in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Vareno</hi>
                    diverts the charge from the
accused to the slaves of Ancharius and in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Scauro</hi>
                    throws the suspicion of Bostar's murder upon
his mother.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There is also a different form of comparison, which comes into play when both parties
claim the credit of some act, and yet another kind,
when the question is not as between two persons,
but as between two acts; that is to say, the
question is not which of the two committed an act,
but which of two acts was committed. Finally,
if the act and the identity of the author are both
                    <pb id="p.53"/>
                    admitted, we may still raise the question of his
intention.
                </p>
                <p>
                    I shall now proceed to detail. As an example of
joint denial covering both the act and the identity
of the author we may take the following statements,
                    <quote>I have not committed adultery,</quote>
                    <quote>I have not sought to establish myself as tyrant.</quote>
                    In cases of
murder or poisoning the denial is often divided as
follows:
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The act was not committed, and, if it was committed, it was not by me.</quote>
                    But if the
defence say,
                    <quote>Prove that the man was killed,</quote>
                    the
burden falls solely on the accuser, for the accused can
say nothing more against the charge except perhaps
in the way of casting certain suspicions, which he
should throw out in the vaguest terms, since if you
make one definite assertion, you will have to prove it
or run the risk of losing your case. For when the
question lies between our statement and that of our
opponent, one or other will be regarded as true.
Thus when the point on which we relied for our
defence is overthrown, there is nothing left but the
points that tell against us.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For example, when the
question turns on symptoms, which may point either
to poisoning or internal disease, there is no third
course left open and consequently each party sticks
to his statement. At times the question turns on
the nature of the fact, whether, for instance, death
was due to poisoning or internal disease, and arguments are introduced which are drawn from the
circumstances alone without any reference to the
person concerned.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For example, it makes a difference whether the deceased was cheerful or depressed,
had been working or taking his ease, had been awake
or sleeping previous to the festive gathering that
                    <pb id="p.55"/>
                    was followed by his death. The age of the deceased
is also an important factor, and it is desirable to
know whether he died suddenly or after a long
period of ill health. If the question turns only on
his sudden death, both parties will have still freer
scope for discussion.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    At times the character of the
accused may be adduced to prove the fact, and to
make it likely that it was or was not a case of
poisoning because the accused is or is not a likely
person to have committed such an act.
                </p>
                <p>
                    When, on the other hand, the enquiry concerns
both the accused and the act, the natural order for
the accuser to pursue is to commence by proving
that the act has been committed and then to go on
to show that it was committed by the accused. If,
however, proofs of the authorship of the crime are
more in number than the proofs of the commission,
this order may be reversed.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, the
accused will always begin by denying the act, since
if this can be successfully proved, there is no need
to say anything more, while if it is not proved, there
remain other means of defence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Similarly, when the dispute turns solely on the act
and, the act being proved, there can be no doubt as
to the author, arguments may be drawn in like
manner both from the person and the facts, although
with reference to the question of fact alone.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Take the
following controversial theme as an example, for it
is best to employ scholastic themes as illustrations
since they are more familiar to the student.
                    <quote>
                        A
man who had been disinherited by his father took
to the study of medicine. His father fell sick and,
his life being despaired of by the other doctors, the
son was called in, and said he would cure him if
                        <pb id="p.57"/>
                        he would take a draught prescribed by himself.
The father after drinking part of the draught said
that he had been poisoned: the son drank the
remainder of the draught. The father died and
the son is accused of parricide.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    There is no doubt
who administered the draught, and, if it was poison,
there is no question as to the author: but the
problem as to whether the draught was poison can
only be decided by arguments drawn from the
character of the accused.
                </p>
                <p>
                    There remains a third type of conjectural case
where the fact is admitted, and the only question
is as to the author. It is unnecessary for me to
quote examples, since such cases are of frequent
occurrence. For example, it may be clear that a
man has been killed or that sacrilege has been committed, but the person accused of the crime may
deny his guilt. It is from such circumstances that
cases of mutual accusation arise, where it is admitted
that the crime has been committed, but each party
charges the other with being the author.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to this class of case Celsus points out that they
cannot actually occur in the courts, a fact which I
imagine is familiar to all: for the jury is empanelled
to try one accused person only, and even though
the defence and the prosecution may accuse each
other of tile crime, the first case must be tried before
the second.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Apollodorus again stated that mutual
accusation involved two separate disputes, and this
is of course in conformity with the practice of the
courts, which insists on two separate trials. On the
other hand, mutual accusation is possible in cases
tried before the senate or the emperor, and even in
the courts the fact of mutual accusation will involve
                    <pb id="p.59"/>
                    no difference in the pleadings, since the same
methods will be required whether the verdict is
given on both charges simultaneously or only on
one.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    In such cases the defence must always come
first for three reasons. In the first place, we naturally prefer to secure our own safety than to injure
our opponent, while secondly, our accusation will
carry greater weight if we have first proved our
own innocence, and thirdly, we shall thus secure
a double line of defence. For the man who says,
                    <quote>I did not kill him,</quote>
                    is then free to go on to say,
                    <quote>You killed him,</quote>
                    whereas it is superfluous for the
man who says,
                    <quote>You killed him,</quote>
                    to go on to say,
                    <quote>I did not kill him.</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Further, such cases consist of comparison, which
may be effected in different ways. For we may either
compare our case in its entirety with that of our
adversary, or we may compare individual arguments.
The choice between these two methods can only
be determined by the requirements of the case. For
example, in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Vareno,</hi>
                    Cicero, in dealing with
the first charge, compares the individual arguments:
for it would have been rash in connexion with the
second charge to compare the position of a stranger
with that of a mother.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italics">pro Vareno</hi>
                        being lost, it is impossible to say to
what this refers, and for the same reason Halm's conjecture must be regarded as quite uncertain.
                    </note>
                    It is therefore best, if
possible, to refute argument by individual argument:
if, however, our individual arguments are weak, we
shall try to secure success by comparison of case
with case as a whole.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    But whether the case is
one of mutual accusation, or the accused throws
the guilt upon his opponent without making any
formal accusation (as Roscius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Roscius Amerinus, accused of parricide and defended by
Cicero.
                    </note>
                    did without indicting
                    <pb id="p.61"/>
                    his accusers), or the responsibility for the deed be
placed on the victims themselves, whom we allege
to have perished by their own hand, the arguments
for both sides of the case will be compared in
exactly the same way as in cases of mutual accusation.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    The class of case last mentioned by me is,
however, not merely of frequent occurrence in
the schools, but sometimes actually occurs in the
courts. For example, the sole question in the
case of Naevius of Arpinum was whether he threw
his wife out of the window or she threw herself.
My speech in this case is the only one of all my
pleadings that I have so far published, and I admit
that I was led to do so merely by a youthful
desire for glory. For the other speeches which
circulate as mine have little in them that actually
fell from my lips, having been corrupted by the
carelessness of the shorthand-writers who took
them down with a view to making money out of
them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    There is also another type of conjectural case
which, though it involves two questions, is different
from cases of mutual accusation; such cases are concerned with rewards and may be illustrated by the
following controversial theme.
                    <quote>
                        A tyrant, suspecting that his physician had given him poison, tortured
him and, since he persisted in denying that he had
done so, sent for a second physician. The latter
asserted that poison had been administered, but
that he would provide an antidote; he gave him a
draught: the tyrant drank it and died. Both
physicians claim a reward for slaying the tyrant.
                    </quote>
                    Now just as in cases of mutual accusation where each
party shifts the guilt to his opponent, so in this
                    <pb id="p.63"/>
                    case we compare the characters, motives, means,
opportunities, instruments and evidence of the
persons who claim the reward.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    There is yet another
type of case which, though not one of mutual
accusation, is treated in the same way: I mean a
case in which we enquire, without accusing anyone, which of two acts has taken place. For both
parties make and defend their own statement of
the case. Thus in the suit concerning the estate
of Urbinia
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        i. 11. and VII. ii. 4.
                    </note>
                    the claimant says that Clusinius Figulus,
the son of Urbinia, on the defeat of the army
in which he was serving, fled and after various
misfortunes, being even even kept in captivity by
the king, at length returned to Italy and his own
home in the Marrucine district, where he was recognised. To this Pollio replies that he had been a
slave to two masters at Pisaurum, that he had
practised medicine, and finally, after receiving his
freedom, inserted himself into a gang of slaves who
were for sale
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        For another meaning of
                        <hi rend="italics">venalis,</hi>
                        newly-bought, see VIII.
ii. 8.
                    </note>
                    and was at his own request purchased by himself.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Does not the whole suit consist
of comparison between the two cases and of two
different and opposite sets of conjecture? But the
method to be followed is identical whether the case
be one of accusation and defence or of claim and
denial of the claim.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Conjecture is, in the first place, based on what is
past, under which I include persons, causes and
intent. For in dealing with a case we first ask
what the accused intended to do, next what he was
in a position to do, and lastly what he actually did.
Consequently the first point on which we must fix
our attention is the character of the accused.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    It is
the business of the accuser to make any charge that
                    <pb id="p.65"/>
                    he may bring against the accused not merely discreditable, but as consistent as possible with the
crime for which he is arraigned. For example, if
he calls a man accused of murder a debauchee or
an adulterer, the discredit attaching to such charges
will no doubt tell against the accused, but will, on
the other hand, do less to prove the case than if
he shows him to be bold, insolent, cruel or reckless.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, counsel for the defence must,
as far as possible, aim at denying, excusing or
extenuating such charges, or, if that be impossible,
show that they are not relevant to the case. For
there are many charges which not only have no
mutual resemblance, but may even at times contradict each other, as for instance if a man accused
of theft is called prodigal or careless. For it is
not likely that one and the same man should at
once despise money and covet it.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    If such means
of defence are not available, we must take refuge
with the plea that the charges made are not
relevant to the case, that because a man has committed certain sins, it does not follow that he has
committed all, and that the accusers ventured to
make such false charges merely because they hoped
by injuring and insulting the accused to be able
to overwhelm him with the unpopularity thus
created.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    There are also other topics which arise
from and against the statement of the case by the
prosecution. The defence may begin by drawing
arguments from the person involved, and will at
times urge on general grounds that it is incredible
that a father has been killed by his son or that a
commander has betrayed his country to the enemy.
The answer to such arguments is easy, for we may
                    <pb id="p.67"/>
                    urge that bad men are capable of every crime, as
is shown by every-day occurrences, or that the
atrocious nature of a crime is but a poor argument
against its having been committed.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    At times we
may base our arguments on the special circumstances
of the person involved. This may be done in various
ways: rank, for example, may be pleaded in defence
of the accused, or at times, on the other hand, may
be employed to prove his guilt on the ground that
he trusted to his rank to secure impunity. Similarly
poverty, humble rank, wealth may be used as arguments for or against the accused according to the
talent of the advocate.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Upright character, however,
and the blamelessness of his past life are always of
the utmost assistance to the accused. If no charge
is made against his character, counsel for the defence
will lay great stress on this fact, while the accuser
will attempt to restrict the judge to the sole consideration of the actual issue which the court has
to decide, and will say that there must always be
a first step in crime and that a first offence is not
to be regarded as the occasion for celebrating a
feast in honour of the defendant's character.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    So
much for the methods of reply which will be employed by the prosecution. But he will also in his
opening speech endeavour to dispose the judges to
believe that it is not so much that he is unable,
as that he is unwilling to bring any charge against
the character of the accused. Consequently it is
better to abstain from casting any slur on the past
life of the accused than to attack him with slight
or frivolous charges which are manifestly false,
since such a proceeding discredits the rest of
our argument. Further, the advocate who brings
                    <pb id="p.69"/>
                    no charges against the accused may be believed to
have omitted all reference to past offences on the
ground that such reference was not necessary, while
the advocate who heaps up baseless charges thereby
admits that his only argument is to be found in the
past life of the accused, and that he has deliberately
preferred to risk defeat on this point rather than
say nothing at all about it.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the other
arguments derived from character, I have already
discussed them in connexion with
                    <quote>places</quote>
                    of
argument.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        v. x. 20, where
                        <hi rend="italics">argumentorum loci</hi>
                        are defined as "the
dwellings of arguments, where they hide and where we must
look for them.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The next type of proof is derived from causes or
motives, such as anger, hatred, fear, greed or hope,
since all motives can be classified as species of one
or other of these. If any of these motives can be
plausibly alleged against the accused, it is the duty
of the accuser to make it appear that such motives
may lead a man to commit any crime, and to exaggerate the particular motives which he selects for
the purpose of his argument.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    If no such motive can
be alleged, he must take refuge in suggesting that
there must have been some hidden motive, or in
asserting that, if he committed the act, all enquiry
into motive is irrelevant or that a motiveless crime
is even more abominable than one which has a
motive. Counsel for the defence, on the other hand,
will, wherever it be possible, emphasise the point
that it is incredible that any act should be committed
without a motive. Cicero develops this point with
great energy in a number of his speeches, but more
especially in his defence of Varenus, who had everything else against him and was as a matter of fact
condemned.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    But if the prosecution do allege some
motive, he will either say that the motive alleged is
                    <pb id="p.71"/>
                    false or inadequate or unknown to the accused. For
it is possible that a man may be quite ignorant of
motives imputed to him. He may not, for example,
have known whether the man whom he is accused
of having killed had appointed him his heir
or intended to prosecute him. All else failing,
we may urge that motives are not necessarily of
importance. For what man is there who is not
liable to the emotions of fear, hatred or hope, and
yet numbers of persons act on these motives without
committing crime?
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    Nor should we neglect the point
that all motives do not apply to all persons. For
example, although poverty may in certain cases be a
motive for theft, it will not have the same force with
men such as Curius or Fabricius.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    The question has been raised as to whether we
should deal first with persons or motives, and different
orators have given different answers: Cicero as a rule
prefers to treat motives first. For my own part, if
the circumstances of the case do not point strongly
in either direction, I consider that the most natural
course is to begin by dealing with persons. For the
enquiry whether any crime can credibly be imputed
to such a man as the accused is of a more general
character than the question whether some one
particular crime can be imputed, and in addition
involves a greater correctness in division.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    Still, in
many cases expediency may make it desirable to
reverse the order. Further, we have to seek not
merely motives affecting the will, but also causes
leading to error, such as drunkenness or ignorance.
For just as such considerations lessen the guilt of a
crime when regarded from the point of view of its
quality, so they tell heavily against the criminal as
                    <pb id="p.73"/>
                    far as the question of fact is concerned.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    I should
imagine that there could never be a case, or at any rate
an actual case in the courts, in which neither side said
anything about the character of the persons involved;
but this is not true of causes and motives, for it is
often wholly unnecessary to trouble ourselves about
them, as, for example, in cases of theft or adultery,
crimes which carry their motives on the face of them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    Next we must consider the intention, a term which
involves a number of questions, such as whether it is
probable that the accused hoped that he would be
able to carry such a crime into effect, or that it
would escape detection when committed, or that,
even if detected, it would be pardoned or punished
but lightly or after considerable lapse of time, or
that the inconvenience involved by the penalty
would be outweighed by the pleasure resulting from
the crime: or again, whether it was worth while
incurring the penalty;
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    and further, whether he could
have done the deed at some other time and in some
other way, or with greater ease or security, as Cicero
says in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Milone,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        c. xiv.
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    where he mentions the
numerous occasions when his client could have killed
Clodius with impunity. There is also the question
why the accused should have chosen that particular
place or time or means for the commission of the
crime, a topic to which Cicero gives a thorough
treatment in the same passage;
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    or whether, without
having the least reason for the deed, he was carried
away by the impulse of the moment and acted
without deliberate purpose (for it is a common
saying that crimes are irrational), or finally, whether
he was led astray by the fact that crime had become
a habit with him.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.75"/>
                <p>
                    Having dealt with the question whether he
intended to commit the crime, we proceed to the
question whether he was in a position to commit it.
Under this head we discuss the place and occasion of
the offence. For instance, in a case of theft we ask
whether it was committed in a secluded or frequented
spot, in the daytime, when witnesses are more
numerous, or by night, when success is more difficult.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently we shall consider all the circumstances
rendering the act difficult or easy of accomplishment;
these require no illustration, being numerous and
familiar. This second topic is of such importance
that, if it is impossible to give it satisfactory treatment, the case falls to the ground; if, however, we
succeed in dealing with it adequately, we must
proceed to consider whether the accused actually
committed the act. But this topic involves conjecture as to intention, for it is from these facts that
we infer whether he hoped for success or not.
Therefore we must also consider the question of
the means at his disposal, such, for example, as the
retinues of Clodius and Milo.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    The question whether he actually did the deed
belongs, in the first place, to the second division of
time, namely the present, and secondly to time that
is almost, though not actually contemporary: under
this latter head come circumstances such as noise,
cries or groans,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        x. 45.
                    </note>
                    while concealment, fear and the
like belong to subsequent time. To these must be
added indications, which we have already discussed
elsewhere,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">v. ch. ix.</note>
                    and words and acts antecedent or subsequent to the crime.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    These words and acts are either
our own or those of others. With regard to words,
our own do us greater harm and bring us less profit
                    <pb id="p.77"/>
                    than do those of others, while those of others bring
us greater profit and do us less harm than our own.
On the other hand, with regard to deeds, it is sometimes from our own and sometimes from those of
others that we derive the greatest advantage, as, for
example, when our opponent has done something
which tells in our favour: but our own acts are
always more injurious to our case than are those
of others.
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    Again, with regard to words, we must
distinguish between those whose meaning is clear
and those whose significance is doubtful. The latter
will necessarily give less assistance to either side, be
they our own words or another's. On the other hand,
any ambiguity in our own words will always tell
against us, as, for example, in the following controversial theme.
                    <quote>
                        A son, on being asked where his
father was, replied: 'Wherever he is, he is alive.'
But the father was found dead at the bottom of a
well.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    When the ambiguity lies in words used by
others, they can never do us any harm, unless he
who uttered them be unknown or dead; I will give
two illustrations of my meaning:
                    <quote>A cry was heard at night, 'Be on your guard against the establishment of a tyranny';</quote>
                    and,
                    <quote>on being asked who had poisoned him, he replied: 'It is not fit that you should know.'</quote>
                    For if the speaker is available for
examination, he will clear up the ambiguity.
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    Finally,
whereas our own words and deeds can only be justified by their intention, the deeds and words of others
can be disposed of in a number of different ways.
                </p>
                <p>
                    My remarks on this subject have, I think, been
confined to one very important class of conjectural
cases, but something of what I have said will apply
to all cases. For example, in cases concerned with
                    <pb id="p.79"/>
                    theft, deposits and loans, arguments are derived both
from possibilities (as when we enquire whether there
was any money to deposit), and from persons, as when
we raise the question whether it is credible that anyone deposited money with this man or trusted him
with a loan, or that the claimant is bringing a false
accusation, or that the accused repudiates his debt or
is a thief.
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    But even in the case of an accusation of
theft, just as in an accusation of murder, we enquire
both into the act and the author, while in cases
concerned with loans and deposits there are also
two questions (though these are always distinct
from one another), namely, whether the money was
delivered and whether it has been repaid. Cases of
adultery are marked by the following peculiarity,
that, as a rule, the safety of two persons is involved,
and it is necessary to say something of the past life
of both, although some have raised the question
whether both parties should be defended together.
The line to be taken must depend on the circumstances of the individual case: if the defence of one
party lends support to the defence of the other, I
should defend them conjointly; if the reverse is the
case, I should treat the two cases separately.
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    However, that no one may think me somewhat hasty in
saying that two persons are as a rule involved in
charges of adultery, I would point out that I would
not assert that this is always the case. The
woman alone may be accused of adultery with a
person unknown: we may say,
                    <quote>
                        Gifts were found
in the house, and money from some unknown source,
and love-letters whose destination cannot be ascertained.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    The case is similar in accusations of
forgery: for either there are several accused or only
                    <pb id="p.81"/>
                    one. The writer of a document always regards it as
necessary to support the signatory, but the signatory
does not always support the writer of the document,
for it is always possible that he has been deceived
on the matter.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The writer will always support the signatory's statement that he signed the document. The signatory will not
always support the writer;
                        <hi rend="italics">e.</hi>
                        g. he may not know the nature
of the document which he signed.
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, the man who is
said to have called in their services, and for whom
the document is alleged to have been written, will
always defend both writer and signatories. The
arguments employed in cases of treason or attempted
tyranny will be drawn from the same sources.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    But the custom prevalent in the schools of regarding everything not definitely stated in the theme as
being in the speaker's favour,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        IV. ii. 28. As the examples which follow show, the
declaimer assumes that his imaginary opponent has no good
evidence to support his case:
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        no witness, no informer,
no weapons, no bodyguard.
                    </note>
                    is likely to prove
harmful to students destined for practice in the
courts. You bring a charge of adultery.
                    <quote>Who is your witness? who is your informer?</quote>
                    You charge
me with treason.
                    <quote>What was my reward? who was my accomplice?</quote>
                    You charge me with poisoning.
                    <quote>
                        Where did I buy the poison, and from whom?
When did I buy it, what was the price, and whom
did I employ to administer it?
                    </quote>
                    Or in defence of
one charged with attempting to establish himself as
tyrant, the declaimer will cry,
                    <quote>Where are my weapons, and what bodyguards have I ever collected?</quote>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    I do not deny that these questions
should be asked, or that we should use them as
far as is permitted by the rôle which we have
assumed; for even in the courts I feel that it will
be desirable to put such questions, if my opponent
is not in a position to reply effectively; but we have
often felt the lack of such freedom in the courts,
whereas in the schools there is scarcely a case where
one or more examples of this method are not to be
found.
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    Similar to this is the practice which some
                    <pb id="p.83"/>
                    declaimers allow themselves in their perorations
of assigning children, parents and nurses to their
characters at will, though it is more reasonable to
call for evidence which is not explicitly mentioned
in the statement of the theme than to introduce it
ourselves.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        it is safer to ask the imaginary opponent
                        <quote>where is your evidence?</quote>
                        than to produce imaginary evidence
ourselves.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    With regard to the method to be followed when
we enquire into intention, I have said enough in
dividing the subject into three questions,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 27.</note>
                    namely,
whether the accused intended to do the deed,
whether he was in a position to do it and whether
he actually did it. For the method of enquiring
into the purpose with which an act was committed
is identical with that employed in enquiring whether
the deed was intended, since it amounts to asking
whether a criminal act was intended.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    Further, the
order in which the facts are stated may either contribute to or detract from the credibility of our case;
for consistency and the reverse depend to a very
great extent on the way the circumstances are
arranged. But we shall be unable to detect these
qualities unless we consider the circumstances in
connexion with the case as a whole. None the less,
it will always be necessary to consider what are best
suited to be placed together.
                </p>
                <p>
                    III.
                    <hi rend="italics">Conjecture</hi>
                    is followed by
                    <hi rend="italics">definition.</hi>
                    For the
man who cannot assert that he has done nothing,
must needs take refuge in the assertion that lie has
not committed the act which is alleged against him.
Consequently the laws which govern
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    are
for the most part the same as those which govern
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    the only difference lying in the method to be
employed in defence in cases such as those concerned
with theft, deposits or adultery. For just as we say,
                    <pb id="p.85"/>
                    <quote>I have not committed theft, I never received a deposit, I am not guilty of adultery,</quote>
                    so we say,
                    <quote>This is not theft, this is not a deposit, this is not adultery.</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes we may pass from
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    to
                    <hi rend="italics">definition,</hi>
                    as in actions concerned with lunacy, cruelty
and offences against the State. In such cases if it
is impossible to assert that the acts alleged were
right, we are left with such pleas as,
                    <quote>To use bad language to one's wife does not amount to cruelty.</quote>
                    Definition is the statement of the fact called in
question in appropriate, clear and concise language.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    As I have already said,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">V. x. 55.</note>
                    it consists mainly in the
statement of
                    <hi rend="italics">genus, species, difference</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">property.</hi>
                    For example, if you wish to define a horse (for I will
take a familiar example), the
                    <hi rend="italics">genus</hi>
                    is animal, the
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    mortal, the
                    <hi rend="italics">diffrence</hi>
                    irrational (since man also
is mortal) and the
                    <hi rend="italics">properly</hi>
                    neighing. Definition is
employed by the orator for a number of different
reasons.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For sometimes, though there may be no
doubt as to a term, there is a question as to what it
includes, or, on the other hand, there may be no
doubt about the thing, but no agreement as to the
term to be applied to it. When the term is agreed,
but the thing doubtful, conjecture may sometimes
come into play, as, for instance, in the question,
                    <quote>What is god?</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For the man who denies that god
is a spirit permeating all things, assuredly asserts
that the epithet
                    <quote>divine</quote>
                    is falsely applied to his
nature, like Epicurus, who gives him a human form
and makes him reside in the intermundane space.
While both use the same term
                    <hi rend="italics">god,</hi>
                    both have to employ conjecture to decide which of the two meanings
is consistent with fact.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes again we have
recourse to quality, as in the question,
                    <quote>
                        What is
                        <pb id="p.87"/>
                        rhetoric? Is it the power to persuade or the science
of speaking well?
                    </quote>
                    This form of question is of
frequent occurrence in the courts. For instance, the
question may arise whether a man caught in a
brothel with another man's wife is an adulterer.
Here there is no doubt about the name; it is the
significance of the act which is in doubt, since the
question is whether he has committed any sin at all.
For if he has sinned, his sin can only be adultery.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    There is a different type of question where the
dispute is concerned with the term to be applied,
which depends on the letter of the law: it is a form
of question which can only arise in the courts from
the actual words on which the dispute turns. Take
as examples the questions, whether suicide is a form
of homicide, or whether the man who forces a tyrant
to kill himself can be considered a tyrannicide, or
whether magical incantations are equivalent to the
crime of poisoning. In all these cases there is no
doubt about the facts, for it is well known that there
is a difference between killing oneself and killing
another, between slaying a tyrant and forcing him
to suicide, between employing incantations and
administering a deadly draught, but we enquire
whether we are justified in calling them by the
same name.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Though I hardly like to differ from Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 31.
                    </note>
                    who
follows many authorities in saying that definition is
concerned with identity and difference (since he
who denies the applicability of one term must always
produce another term which he regards as preferable), for my own part I consider that definition
falls into three types, which I may perhaps call
                    <hi rend="italics">species.</hi>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For at times it is convenient merely to
                    <pb id="p.89"/>
                    enquire whether one particular term is applicable to
a given thing, as in the question whether an act
committed in a brothel is adultery. If we deny
that it is adultery, there is no need to state what it
should be called, since we have given a total denial
to the charge. Secondly, there are occasions when
the question is which of two terms is to be applied
to a thing, as in the question whether an act is
theft or sacrilege. It may be sufficient for the
defence that it is not sacrilege, but it is still necessary
to show what else it is, and therefore we must define
both.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Thirdly, there are times when the question
concerns things which are different in species, and
we ask whether two different things are to be called
by the same name, in spite of the fact that each has
a special name of its own: for example, is tile same
name applicable both to a love-potion and a poison?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        VIII. V. 31.
                    </note>
                    But in all disputes of this kind the question is
whether one thing is another thing as well, since
the name in doubt does without question apply to
something else. It is sacrilege to steal a sacred
object from a temple; is it also sacrilege to steal
private property from a temple? It is adultery to
lie with another man's wile in one's own house; is
it adultery to do so in a brothel? It is tyrannicide
to slay a tyrant; is it tyrannicide to force him to
slay himself?
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently the syllogism, to which
I shall return later, is virtually a weaker form of
definition, since while definition seeks to determine
whether one thing has the same name as another,
syllogism seeks to determine whether one thing is
to be regarded as identical with another.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    There is
moreover great variety in definitions. For instance,
persons will give different verbal expression to
                    <pb id="p.91"/>
                    things about which they are really in agreement:
thus rhetoric is defined as the science of
                    <hi rend="italics">speaking well,</hi>
                    as the science of
                    <hi rend="italics">correct conception</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">correct expression</hi>
                    of what we have to say, as the science of
                    <hi rend="italics">speading in accordance with the excellence of an orator</hi>
                    and again of
                    <hi rend="italics">speaking to the purpose.</hi>
                    And we must
take care to discover how it is that definitions,
identical in meaning, differ in the form in which
they are expressed. However, this is a subject for
discussion and not for a quarrel.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Definition is sometimes required to explain rare or obscure words such
as
                    <hi rend="italics">clarigatio</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A formal demand for redress under threat of war.</note>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">erctum citum,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">An undivided inheritance.</note>
                    or again to explain
familiar words such as
                    <hi rend="italics">penus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Store of provisions.</note>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">litus.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Shore, see v. xiv. 34, where its derivation is explained
as qua fiuctus eludit.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    This variety in definition has caused some writers
to include it under conjecture, others under quality
and others again under legal questions.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Some, on
the other hand, entirely reject the elaborate and
formal methods of reasoning employed by dialectic,
regarding such ingenuity as suited rather to quibbles
over words in philosophical discussions than as likely
to carry much weight in the performance of the
duties of an orator. For though in dialogue definition may serve to fetter the person who has got
to reply in chains of his own making, or may force
him to silence, or even to reluctant confession of a
point which tells against himself, it is of less use in
forensic cases.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For there we have to persuade the
judge, who, even though he may be tied and bound
with our words, will still dissent in silence, unless he
is brought really into touch with the actual facts.
And what need has a pleader for such precision of
definition? Even if I do not say that man is an
animal, mortal and rational, surely I shall still be
able, by setting forth the numerous properties of his
                    <pb id="p.93"/>
                    body and mind in more general terms, to distinguish
him from gods or dumb beasts.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Again, may not the
same thing be defined in more than one way, as
Cicero does when he says,
                    <quote>What do we mean when we say' commonly ': surely we mean 'by all men'?</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Pro Mur.</hi>
                        xxxv. 73.
                    </note>
                    May it not be given a wide and varied treatment
such as is frequently employed by all orators? For
it is rare to find orators falling victims to that form
of slavery introduced from the practice of the philosophers and tying themselves down to certain
definite words; indeed it is absolutely forbidden by
Marcus Antonius in the
                    <hi rend="italics">de Oratore</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        II xxv. 108
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    of Cicero.
For it is a most dangerous practice, since,
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    if we make
a mistake in a single word, we are like to lose our
whole case, and consequently the compromise adopted
by Cicero in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Caecina</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">XV. 42.</note>
                    is the safest course to
follow; this consists in setting forth the facts without
running any risks over the exactness of our terminology. These are his words:
                    <quote>
                        Judges, the violence
which threatens our lives and persons is not the
only kind of violence: there is a much more serious
form which by the threat of death fills our minds
with panic and often turns them from their natural
condition of stability.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Or again, we may prove
before we define, as Cicero does in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Philippics,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IX. iii. 7.</note>
                    where he proves that Servius Sulpicius was killed by
Antony and introduces his definition at the conclusion in the following terms:—
                    <quote>For assuredly the murderer was he who was the cause of his death.</quote>
                    I would not, however, deny that such rules should be
employed, if it will help our case, and that, if we
can produce a definition which is at once strong and
concise, it will be not merely an ornament to our
speech, but will also produce the strongest
                    <pb id="p.95"/>
                    impression, provided always that it cannot be overthrown.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The order to be followed in definition is invariable.
We first ask
                    <hi rend="italics">what</hi>
                    a thing is, and then, whether it is
                    <hi rend="italics">this.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        the thing under consideration.
                    </note>
                    And there is generally more difficulty in the
establishment than in the application of a definition.
In determining what a thing is, there are two things
which require to be done: we must establish our
own definition and destroy that of our opponent.
Consequently in the schools,
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    where we ourselves
imagine our opponent's reply, we have to introduce
two definitions, which should suit the respective
sides of the case as well as it is in our power to
make them. But in the courts we must give careful
consideration to the question whether our definition
may not be superfluous and irrelevant or ambiguous
or inconsistent or even of no less service to our
opponents than to ourselves, since it will be the
fault of the pleader if any of these errors occur. On
the other hand, we shall ensure the right definition,
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    if we first make up our minds what it is precisely
that we desire to effect: for, this done, we shall be
able to suit our words to serve our purpose. To
make my meaning clearer, I will follow my usual
practice and quote a familiar example.
                    <quote>A man who has stolen private money from a temple is accused of sacrilege.</quote>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    There is no doubt about his
guilt; the question is whether the name given by
the law applies to the charge. It is therefore
debated whether the act constitutes sacrilege. The
accuser employs this term on the ground that the
money was stolen from a temple: the accused denies
that the act is sacrilege, on the ground that the
money stolen was private property, but admits that
                    <pb id="p.97"/>
                    it is theft. The prosecutor will therefore give the
following definitions,
                    <quote>It is sacrilege to steal anything from a sacred place.</quote>
                    The accused will reply
with another definition,
                    <quote>It is sacrilege to steal something sacred.</quote>
                    Each impugns the other's definition.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    A definition may be overthrown on two
grounds: it may be false or it may be too narrow.
There is indeed a possible third ground, namely
irrelevance, but this is a fault which no one save a
fool will commit.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    [It is a false definition if you say,
                    <quote>A horse is a rational animal,</quote>
                    for though the horse
is an animal, it is irrational. Again, a thing which
is common to something else cannot be a property
of the thing defined.] In the case under discussion,
then, the accused alleges that the definition given
by the accuser is false, whereas the accuser cannot
do the same by his opponent's definition, since to
steal a sacred object is undoubtedly sacrilege. He
therefore alleges that the definition is too narrow
and requires the addition of the words
                    <quote>or from a sacred place.</quote>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    But the most effective method of
establishing and refuting definitions is derived from
the examination of properties and differences, and
sometimes even from considerations of etymology,
while all these considerations will, like others, find
further support in equity and occasionally in conjecture.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Conjecture is here used in the ordinary sense, not the
technical.
                    </note>
                    Etymology is rarely of assistance, but the
following will provide an example of its use.
                    <quote>
                        For
what else is a 'tumult' but a disturbance of such
violence as to give rise to abnormal alarm? And
the name itself is derived from this fact.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italics">Phil.</hi>
                        VIII. i. 3.
                        <hi rend="italics">Tumultus</hi>
                        is here used by Cicero in
its special sense, civil war or Gallic invasion. He derives it
from
                        <hi rend="italics">timor multus.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Great
ingenuity may be exercised with regard to properties
and differences, as for instance in the question
whether a person assigned to his creditor for debt,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 25.
                    </note>
                    <pb id="p.99"/>
                    who is condemned by the law to remain in a state
of servitude until he has paid his debt, is actually a
slave. One party will advance the following definition,
                    <quote>A slave is one who is legally in a state of servitude.</quote>
                    The other will produce the definition,
                    <quote>
                        A slave is one who is in a state of servitude on
the same terms as a slave (or, to use the older
phrase, 'who serves as a slave').
                    </quote>
                    This definition,
though it differs considerably from the other, will be
quite useless unless it is supported by properties
and differences.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    For the opponent will say that the
person in question is actually serving as a slave or is
legally in a state of servitude. We must therefore
look for properties and differences, to which in
passing I devoted a brief discussion in my fifth book.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">V. x. 60.</note>
                    A slave when manumitted becomes a freedman: a
man who is assigned for debt becomes a free man on
the restoration of his liberty. A slave cannot acquire
his freedom without the consent of his master: a
man assigned for debt can acquire it by paying his
debt without the consent of his master being
necessary. A slave is outside the law; a man
assigned for debt is under the law. Turning to
properties, we may note the following which are
possessed by none save the free, the three names
(praenomen, nomen and cognomen) and membership
of a tribe, all of which are possessed by the man
assigned for debt.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    By settling what a thing is we have come near
to determining its identity, for our purpose is to
produce a definition that is applicable to our case.
Now the most important element in a definition is
provided by quality, as, for example, in the question
whether love be a form of madness. To this point
                    <pb id="p.101"/>
                    in our procedure belong those proofs which according
to Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxiii. 88.
                    </note>
                    are peculiar to definition, that is, proofs
drawn from antecedents, consequents, adjuncts, contraries, causes, effects and similarities, with the
nature of which I have already dealt.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">V. x. 73.</note>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    I will, however, quote a passage from the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Caecina</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">XV. 44.</note>
                    in which
Cicero includes brief proofs drawn from origins,
causes, effects, antecedents and consequents:
                    <quote>
                        Why
then did they fly? Because they were afraid. What
were they afraid of? Obviously of violence. Can you
then deny the beginning, when you have admitted
the end?
                    </quote>
                    But he also argued from similarity:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">XV. 43.</note>
                    <quote>Shall not that which is called violence in war be called violence in peace as well</quote>
                    Arguments may
also be drawn from contraries, as for instance in the
question whether a love-potion can be a poison, in
view of the fact that a poison is not a love-potion.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In order that my young students (and I call them
mine, because the young student is always dear to
me) may form a clearer conception of this second
kind of definition, I will once more quote a fictitious
controversial theme.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        Some young men who were
in the habit of making merry together decided to
dine on the sea-shore. One of their party failed
to put in an appearance, and they raised a tomb to
him and inscribed his name thereon. His father on
his return from overseas chanced to land at this
point of the shore, read the name and hung himself.
It is alleged that the youths were the cause of
his death.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    The definition produced by the accuser
will run as follows:
                    <quote>The man whose act leads to another's death is the cause of his death.</quote>
                    The
definition given by the accused will be,
                    <quote>
                        He who
wittingly commits an act which must necessarily lead
                        <pb id="p.103"/>
                        to another's death, is the cause of his death.
                    </quote>
                    Without any formal definition it would be sufficient for
the accuser to argue as follows:
                    <quote>
                        You were the
cause of his death, for it was your act that led
to his death: but for your act he would still be
alive.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    To which the accused might answer,
                    <quote>
                        It
does not necessarily follow that the man whose act
leads to another's death should be condemned forthwith. Were this so, the accuser, witnesses and
judges in a capital case would all be liable to
condemnation. Nor is the cause of death always a
guilty cause. Take for instance the case of a man
who persuades another to go on a journey or
sends for his friend from overseas, with the result
that the latter perishes in a shipwreck, or again the
case of a man who invites another to dine, with
the result that the guest dies of indigestion.
                        <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                        Nor
is the act of the young men to be regarded as
the sole cause of death. The credulity of the old
man and his inability to bear the shock of grief
were contributory causes. Finally, had lie been wiser
or made of sterner stuff, he would still be alive.
Moreover the young men acted without the least
thought of doing harm, and the father might have
suspected from the position of the tomb and the
traces of haste in its construction that it was not
a genuine tomb. What ground then is there for
condemning them, for everything else that constitutes
homicide is lacking save only the contributory act?
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes we have a settled definition on which
both parties are agreed, as in the following example
from Cicero:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Part. Or.</hi>
                        xxx. 105.
                        <hi rend="italics">maiestatem iminuere</hi>
                        = to commit
lèse-majesté or treason.
                    </note>
                    <quote>Majesty resides in the dignity of the Roman power and the Roman people.</quote>
                    The
question however, is, whether that majesty has been
                    <pb id="p.105"/>
                    impaired, as for example in the ease of Cornelius.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        No fragments of the
                        <hi rend="italics">pro Cornelio contain any trace of this.</hi>
                    </note>
                    But even although the case may seem to turn on
definition, the point for decision is one of quality,
since there is no doubt about the definition, and
must be assigned to the
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative basis.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See III. vi. 31,
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    It is a
mere accident that I have come to mention quality
at this moment, but in point of fact quality is the
matter that comes next in order for discussion.
                </p>
                <p>
                    IV. In speaking of quality we sometimes use
the word in its most general sense, which covers
a number of different questions. For we enquire
sometimes into the nature and form of things: as
for instance whether the soul is immortal or whether
god is to be conceived of in human form. Sometimes, on the other hand, the question turns on size
and number, as, for instance, what is the size of
the sun or whether there are more worlds than
one. In all these cases we arrive at our conclusions
by conjecture, yet each involves a question of quality.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Such questions are sometimes treated in deliberative themes: for example, if Caesar is deliberating
whether to attack Britain, he must enquire into the
nature of the Ocean, consider whether Britain is an
island (a fact not then ascertained), and estimate its
size and the number of troops which lie will require
for the invasion. Under the same head of quality
fall questions whether certain things should be done
or not and certain objects sought or avoided: such
topics are specially adapted for deliberative themes,
but occur with some frequency in controversial
themes as well, the only difference being that in
the latter we deal with what is past and in the
former with the future.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Similarly all the topics
of demonstrative
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See III. iv. 12
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    oratory involve a
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative basis.</hi>
                    <pb id="p.107"/>
                    The facts are admitted, and the question turns on
their quality, the dispute being entirely concerned
with rewards or penalties or their quantity. The
case is therefore of two kinds, simple or comparative, the former dealing with what is just, the latter
with what is juster, or most just. When the point
for decision is the penalty to be inflicted, the duty
of the pleader will be to defend, extenuate or excuse
the act on which the charge is based, or even,
according to some, to plead for mercy.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    By far the strongest line that can be taken in
defence is to assert that the act which forms the
subject of the charge is actually honourable. A
man is disinherited because he went on military
service, stood for office or married without his
father's consent. We defend this act. This form
of defence is called
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kat' a)nti/lhyin</foreign>
                    by the followers of
Hermagoras, that is, defence by objection, the term
being used with reference to the purport of the
defendant's plea.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)nti/lhyis</foreign>
                        is the technical term for this form of defence
which turns not on the facts, but on the justice of the case.
The meaning of
                        <hi rend="italics">ad intellectum id nomen referentes</hi>
                        is obscure.
If the words are correct (and no satisfactory correction seems
possible), their meaning must be that the defence turns not
on the act, but on its significance and equity. If any change
is made in the text, the simplest course is to delete the words
as a gloss which has crept into the text.
                    </note>
                    I can find no exact Latin translation of the term; we call it an absolute defence.
But in such cases the question is concerned with the
justice or injustice of the act alone.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Justice is
either natural or conventional. Natural justice is
found in actions of inherent worth.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Under this
head come the virtues of piety, loyalty, self-control
and the like. To these some add the rendering
of like for like. But this view must not be adopted
without consideration: for to retaliate, or meet
violence with violence on the one hand, does not
imply injustice on the part of the aggressor, while
on the other hand it does not follow that the first
act was just merely because the two acts were alike.
In cases where there is justice on both sides, the
                    <pb id="p.109"/>
                    two parties must both come under the same law
and the same conditions, and it would not perhaps
be untrue to say that things can never be spoken
of as like if there is any point in which they
are dissimilar. Convention, on the other hand, is
to be found in laws, customs, legal precedents and
agreements.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    There is another form of defence by which we
defend an act in itself indefensible by arguments
drawn from without.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        from motives derived from facts lying outside the
actual case.
                    </note>
                    This the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kat' a)nti/qesin</foreign>
                    by opposition. Here again there is no
Latin equivalent, since we call it defence by assumption.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The strongest line to take in this form
of defence is to defend the act forming the subject
of the charge by appealing to its motive. An
example of this is provided by the defence put
forward on behalf of Orestes, Horatius or Milo. The
term
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)nte/gklhma,</foreign>
                    or counter-accusation, is employed
when our defence consists entirely in accusing the
person whom our opponents are seeking to vindicate.
                    <quote>He was killed, but he was a robber; he was blinded, but he was a ravisher.</quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    There is another form
of defence based on an appeal to the motives of
the act which is the opposite of that which I have
just described It consists not in defending the act
                    <hi rend="italics">per se,</hi>
                    as we do when we employ the absolute
defence, nor in opposing another act to it, but
in appealing to the interests of the State, of a
number of persons, of our opponent himself or finally
at times of ourselves, provided always that the act
in question is such as we might lawfully do in our
own interests. If, however, the accuser is a stranger
and insists on the letter of the law, this form
of defence will invariably be useless, though it may
                    <pb id="p.111"/>
                    serve our turn if the dispute is of a domestic
character.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For example, in a suit concerned
with the question of disinheritance a father may,
without reflecting on himself, say to his sons that
his act was of importance to his own interests,
and the same plea may be urged by a husband
accused of cruelty by his wile or a son who
alleges that his father is insane. But in such cases
the position of the man who seeks to avoid
loss is stronger than that of him who aims at
positive advantage.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Precisely similar methods are
also employed in questions that occur in real life.
For the scholastic themes concerned with the disowning of children are on exactly the same footing
as the cases of sons disinherited by their parents
which are tried in the public courts, or of those
claims for the recovery of property which are tried
in the centum viral court: themes dealing with cruelty
find an actual parallel in those cases in which the
wife claims the restoration of her dowry, and the
question is whose fault it was that led to the divorce:
and again the theme where the son accuses his father
of madness has its analogy in cases where a suit is
brought for the appointment of a guardian.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Under
the same heading as the appeal to public or personal
interest comes the plea that the act in question
prevented the occurrence of something worse. For
in a comparison of evils the lesser evil must be
regarded as a positive good: for example, Mancinus
may defend the treaty made with the Numantines
on the ground that it saved the army from annihilation. This form of defence is called
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)nti/stasis</foreign>
                    by
the Greeks, while we style it defence by comparison.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Such are the methods by which we may
                    <pb id="p.113"/>
                    defend an act. If it is impossible to defend an
act either on its merits or with the assistance of
arguments from without, the next best course will
be to shift the charge, if possible, to another.
It is for this reason that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    has
been held to apply even to those who cannot
plead the letter of the law in this connexion.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i e.</hi>
                        there are no legal grounds for alleging that the court
is not competent to try the case, or the accuser to bring the
charge, etc. See III. vi. 53, 78.
                    </note>
                    In
some cases, then, the blame will be thrown on a
person: for example, Gracchus, when accused of
making the treaty with the Numantines (and it was
fear of this accusation that seems to have led him
to bring forward the democratic laws of his tribuneship) may plead that he made it as the representative of his commander-in-chief.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    At times, on the
other hand, the blame may be shifted to some
thing: for instance, a person who has failed to
comply with some testamentary injunction may plead
that the laws forbade such compliance. The Greek
term for such shifting is
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">meta/stasis.</foreign>
                </p>
                <p>
                    If these methods of defence are out of the
question, we must take refuge in making excuses.
We may plead ignorance. For example, if a man
has branded a runaway slave and the latter is
subsequently adjudged to be a free man, he may
deny that he was cognisant of the truth. Or
we may plead necessity; for instance, if a soldier
overstays his leave, he may plead that his return
was delayed by floods or ill health.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the
blame is often cast upon fortune, while sometimes
we assert that, although we undoubtedly did wrong,
we did so with the best intentions. Instances
of these two latter forms of excuse are, however,
so numerous and obvious that there is no need for
me to cite them here.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.115"/>
                <p>
                    If all the above-mentioned resources prove unavailable, we must see whether it may not be
possible to extenuate the offence. It is here that
what some call the
                    <hi rend="italics">quantitative basis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 23, 51, 53.
                    </note>
                    comes into
play.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But when quantity is considered in reference to punishment or reward, it is determined by
the quality of the act, and therefore in my opinion
comes under the
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative basis,</hi>
                    as also does quantity
which is used with reference to number by the
Greeks, who distinguish between
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">poso/ths</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">phliko/ths</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">poso/ths</foreign>
                        = quantity with reference to number;
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">phliko/ths</foreign>
                        = quantity with reference to magnitude.
                    </note>
                    : we, however, have only one name for
the two.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    In the last resort we may plead for mercy, a though
most writers deny that this is ever admissible in the
courts.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Pro Lig.</hi>
                        X. 30.
                    </note>
                    Indeed Cicero himself seems to support
this view in his defence of Quintus Ligarius where
he says,
                    <quote>
                        I have pleaded many causes, Caesar, some
of them even in association with yourself, so long as
your political ambitions prevented you from abandoning the bar, but never have I pleaded in words such
as these, ' Forgive him, gentlemen, he erred, he
made a slip, he did not think that it mattered, he
will never do it again,'
                    </quote>
                    and so on.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    On the other
hand, in addressing the senate, the people, the emperor or any other authority who is in a position to
show clemency, such pleas for mercy have a legitimate
place. In such cases there are three points based
on the circumstances of the accused which are most
effective. The first is drawn from his previous life, if
he has been blameless in his conduct and deserved
well of the state, or if there is good hope that his
conduct will be blameless for the future and likely
to be of some use to his fellow men; the second is
operative if it appears that he has been sufficiently
                    <pb id="p.117"/>
                    punished already on the ground that he has suffered
other misfortunes, or that his present peril is extreme,
or that he has repented of his sin; while thirdly we
may base his appeal on his external circumstances,
his birth, his rank, his connexions, his friendships.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    It is, however, on the judge that we shall pin our
highest hopes, if the circumstances be such that
acquittal will result in giving him a reputation for
clemency rather than for regrettable weakness. But
even in the ordinary courts appeals for mercy are
frequently employed to a large extent, although they
will not colour the whole of our pleading. For the
following form of division is common:—
                    <quote>Even if he had committed the offence, he would have deserved forgiveness,</quote>
                    a plea which has often
turned the balance in doubtful cases, while practically
all perorations contain such appeals.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes
indeed the whole case may rest on such considerations. For example, if a father has made an express
declaration that he has disinherited his son because
lie was in love with a woman of the town, will not
the whole question turn on the point whether it was
the father's duty to pardon such an offence and
whether it is the duty of the centumviral court
to overlook it? Nay, even in penal prosecutions
governed by strict forms of law we raise two separate
questions: first whether the penalty has been incurred,
and secondly whether, if so, it ought to be inflicted.
Still the view of the authorities to whom I have
referred that an accused person cannot be saved
from the clutches of the law by this method of
defence is perfectly correct.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to rewards, there are two questions
which confront us: namely, whether the claimant is
                    <pb id="p.119"/>
                    deserving of any reward, and, if so, whether he deserves so great a reward. If there are two claimants,
we have to decide which is the more worthy of the
two; if there are a number, who is the most worthy.
The treatment of these questions turns on the kind
of merit possessed by the claimants. And we must
consider not merely the act (whether it has merely
to be stated or has to be compared with the acts of
others), but the person of the claimant as well. For
it makes a great difference whether a tyrannicide be
young or old, man or woman, a stranger or a connexion.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    The place may also be discussed in a number
of ways: was the city in which the tyrant was killed
one inured to tyranny or one which had always been
free? was he killed in the citadel or in his own
house? The means, too, and the time call for consideration: was he killed by poison or the sword?
was he killed in time of peace or war, when he was
intending to lay aside his power or to venture on
some fresh crime?
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Further, in considering the
question of merit, the danger and difficulty of the act
will carry great weight, while with regard to liberality
it will similarly be of importance to consider the
character of the person from whom it proceeds. For
liberality is more pleasing in a poor man than in a
rich, in one who confers than in one who returns a
benefit, in a father than in a childless man. Again,
we must consider the immediate object of the gift,
the occasion and the intention, that is to say, whether
it was given in the hope of subsequent profit; and
so on with a number of similar considerations. The
question of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    therefore makes the highest
demands on the resources of oratory, since it affords
the utmost scope for a display of talent on either side,
                    <pb id="p.121"/>
                    while there is no topic in which the emotional appeal
is so
                    <hi rend="italics">effective.</hi>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    For conjecture has often to introduce
proofs from without and uses arguments drawn from
the actual subject matter, whereas the real task of
eloquence is to demonstrate
                    <hi rend="italics">quality:</hi>
                    there lies its
kingdom, there its power, and there its unique
victory.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Verginius includes under
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    cases concerned
with disinheritance, lunacy, cruelty to a wife, and
claims of female orphans to marry relatives. The
questions thus involved are, it is true, frequently questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    while some writers style them questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">moral obligation.</hi>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    But the laws governing
these cases sometimes admit of other
                    <hi rend="italics">bases.</hi>
                    For
example,
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    is involved in quite a number of
such cases, as when the accused urges either that he
did not commit the act or, if he did, acted with the
best intentions. I could quote many examples of
this kind. Again, it is definition which tells us what
precisely is meant by lunacy or cruelty to a wife.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The general sense of 25 and 26 is clear. These cases do
not always come under the
                        <hi rend="italics">status qualitatis:</hi>
                        they not infrequently come under the
                        <hi rend="italics">status coniecturalis</hi>
                        and
                        <hi rend="italics">finitivus.</hi>
                        They cannot however, strictly be said to come under the
                        <hi rend="italics">states legalis,</hi>
                        since although the
                        <hi rend="italics">leges</hi>
                        of such scholastic themes do
involve certain questions of law, these are not such as to constitute the
                        <hi rend="italics">status legally.</hi>
                        Still in the last resort such cases
may be argued on legal grounds. The text adopted for the
last sentence of 25 is that which involves the least change,
but it is highly obscure and the corruption may well lie
deeper still. For the whole question of
                        <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                        which is
highly technical, see III, vi.
                    </note>
                    For as a rule the laws cited in such themes involve
certain legal questions, though not to such an extent
as to determine the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the case.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    But this notwithstanding, if the actual fact cannot be defended,
we may in the last resort base our defence on legal
grounds, in which case we shall consider how many
and what cases there are in which a father may not
disinherit his son, what charges fail to justify an
action for cruelty, and under what circumstances a
son is not allowed to accuse his father of lunacy.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.123"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Disinheritance may be of two kinds. In the first
case it is for a completed crime: for example, the son
who is disinherited may be a ravisher or an adulterer:
in the second case it is for a crime which is still incomplete and terminable
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Literally
                        <hi rend="italics">conditional.</hi>
                        The sense, however, is that the disinheritance is only conditional on the disobedience being
continued.
                    </note>
                    ; an instance of this will
be the case where the son is disinherited because of
disobedience to his father. The first form of disinheritance always demands a certain harshness when
the father pleads his case, since the act is irrevocable,
whereas in the latter his pleading will be of a kindly
and almost persuasive nature, since he would prefer
not to disinherit him. On the other hand, the
pleading of the sons should in both cases be of a
subdued character and couched in a conciliatory
tone.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    I know that those who delight in making
covert attacks upon the father under the disguise
of some figure of speech will disagree with me:
and I would not deny that their procedure may
sometimes be justifiable, since the theme may conceivably be such as to demand it; but it is certainly
to be avoided wherever possible. However, I shall
deal with the whole question of figures in a later
book.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Book IX. See especially IX. ii. 65 sqq.</note>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    The treatment of the theme of cruelty to a
wife is not unlike that of the theme of disinheritance; for both demand a certain moderation on the
part of the accuser. Cases concerned with lunacy
arise either out of what has been done or out of
something which may or may not be done in the
future.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    In the former case the pleader is free to
attack as he will, but must none the less do so in
such a manner that, while denouncing the act, he
will yet express pity for the father on the ground
that he has erred by reason of his infirmity. On the
other hand, in the latter case, where the act has not
                    <pb id="p.125"/>
                    yet taken place and there is nothing to prevent the
father changing his purpose, he must begin by a
prolonged attempt to induce him to change his mind,
and then, and only then, complain that it is madness
and not depravity of character that prevents him
from listening to the voice of reason; and the more
he praises his past character, the easier will it be to
prove the change which it has undergone owing to
the inroads of the disease.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    The accused, wherever
possible, must assume a temperate tone in his defence, for the reason that as a rule anger and excitement are near akin to madness. All these cases
have this much in common, that the accused does not
always defend his act, but often pleads excuse and
asks for pardon. For these are domestic quarrels, in
which the fact that the offence is an isolated case,
due to error and of a less serious character than
alleged, will sometimes suffice to secure an acquittal.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    There are, however, a number of other controversial themes involving
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    as, for example,
cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">assault.</hi>
                    In these, although at times the
accused denies that he committed the assault, the
pleading as a rule is concerned with fact and intention.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Then there are cases concerned with the
                    <hi rend="italics">appointment of a prosecutor,</hi>
                    which are known as
                    <hi rend="italics">divinations.</hi>
                    In this connexion Cicero, who was indicting Verres on the instruction of our Sicilian allies,
adopts the following division-to the effect that the
main point for consideration is, by whom those the
redress of whose wrongs forms the subject of the
trial would prefer to be represented, and by whom
the accused would least desire them to be represented.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    But in the great majority of cases the
questions raised are, which claimant has the strongest
                    <pb id="p.127"/>
                    motives for undertaking the role of accuser, which is
likely to bring the greatest energy or talent to the
task, and which is likely to press the charge with
the greatest sincerity.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Next we may take cases
concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">guardianship,</hi>
                    in which it is usual
to enquire whether it is necessary to investigate
anything save the accounts, and whether anything
can be demanded of the guardian except the
honest execution of his trust; his sagacity and the
success of his administration being beside the mark.
Cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">fraud on the part of an agent,</hi>
                    which are
styled cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">conduct of business</hi>
                    when they occur in
the actual courts, are of a similar nature, since they
also are concerned with the administration of a
trust.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    In addition to these we have the fictitious
cases of the schools which deal with
                    <hi rend="italics">crimes not covered by the law,</hi>
                    where the question is as a rule either
whether the crime is really not covered by the law
or whether it is a crime, though on rare occasions
both questions are raised. Cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">misconduct on the part of an ambassador</hi>
                    are of frequent occurrence
among the Greeks, even in actual life: in these the
legal question is raised whether it is lawful to deviate
at all from one's instructions and for how long the
accused was technically an ambassador, since in some
cases the ambassador's duty is to convey a communication to a foreign power and in others to bring one
back. Take for example the case of Heius, who gave
evidence against Verres after performing his duties
as ambassador. But in such cases the most important
question turns on the nature of the deed complained
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    of Next come cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">action contrary to the interests of the state.</hi>
                    In these we meet with legal quibbles
as to what is the meaning of
                    <quote>
                        action contrary to the
                        <pb id="p.129"/>
                        interests of the state,
                    </quote>
                    and whether the action of
the accused was injurious or profitable, or whether
the interests of the state suffered at his hands or
merely on his account: but the most important
question is that of fact. There are also cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">ingratitude;</hi>
                    in these we raise the question whether
the accused has really received any kindness. It is
only rarely that the fact can be denied, as denial is
in itself a sign of ingratitude. But there are the
further questions as to the extent of the kindness
and whether it has been repaid.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    If it has not been
repaid, does this necessarily involve ingratitude?
Was it in his power to repay? Did he really owe
the return which was demanded of him? What is
his intention? Somewhat simpler are cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">unjust divorce,</hi>
                    a form of controversy which has this
peculiarity, that the accuser defends and the defendant accuses.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        the divorced wife defends her character, while the
husband attacks her character.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    Further there are cases where
a senator sets forth to the senate the
                    <hi rend="italics">reasons which determine him to commit suicide,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Based on a law of Massilia, where the state provided
poison for the would-be suicide, provided he could justify
himself before the senate.
                    </note>
                    in which there is one
                    <hi rend="italics">legal</hi>
                    question, namely, whether a man who desires to
kill himself in order to escape the clutches of the
law ought to be prevented from so doing, while the
remaining questions are all concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">quality.</hi>
                    There are also fictitious cases concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">wills,</hi>
                    in which the only question raised is one of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    as,
for instance, in the controversial theme quoted above,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">VII. i. 38.</note>
                    where the philosopher, physician and orator all
claim the fourth share which their father had left
to the most worthy of his sons. The same is true
of cases where suitors of equal rank claim the
hand of an orphan and the question confronting her
relatives is which is the most suitable.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    I do not,
however, intend to discuss every possible theme,
                    <pb id="p.131"/>
                    since fresh ones can always be invented, nor yet to
deal with all the questions to which they give rise,
since these vary with circumstances. But I cannot
help expressing my astonishment that Flavus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        Verginius mentioned in § 24.
                    </note>
                    for
whose authority I have the highest respect, restricted
the range of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    to such an extent in the text-book
which he composed for the special guidance of the
schools.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Quantity</hi>
                    also, as I have already stated,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 16.</note>
                    falls as a
rule, though not always, under the head of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    whether it is concerned with measure or number.
Measure, however, sometimes consists in the valuation
of a deed with a view to determining the amount
of guilt or the amount of benefit involved, while, on
the other hand, it sometimes turns on a point of
law, when the dispute is under what law a man
is to be punished or rewarded.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    For example is a
ravisher to pay 10,000 sesterces
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        IV. ii. 69.
                    </note>
                    because that is the
penalty appointed by law, or is he liable to capital
punishment as a murderer because his victim hanged
himself? In such cases those who plead as if there
were a question between two laws, are wrong: for
there is no dispute about the fine of 10,000,
since it is not claimed by the prosecution.
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    The
point on which judgment has to be delivered is
whether the accused is guilty of causing his victim's
death. The same type of case will also bring
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    into play, when, for example, the question
in dispute is whether the accused shall be punished
with banishment for life or for five years. For the
question then is whether he caused his death
willingly or not.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    Again, there are questions concerned with numerical quantity which turn on a
point of law, such as the questions whether thirty
                    <pb id="p.133"/>
                    rewards are due to Thrasybulus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        for his overthrow of the thirty tyrants;
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        II. vi. 26.
                    </note>
                    or whether, when
two thieves have stolen a sum of money, they are
each to be required to refund fourfold or twofold.
But in these cases, too, valuation of the act is
necessary, and yet the point of law also turns on
                    <hi rend="italics">quality.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    V. He who neither denies nor defends his act nor
asserts that it was of a different nature from that
alleged, must take his stand on some point of law
that tells in his favour, a form of defence which
generally turns on the legality of the action brought
against him.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This question is not, however, as some
have held, always raised before the commencement
of the trial, like the elaborate deliberations of the
praetor when there is a doubt as to whether the
prosecutor has any legal standing, but frequently
comes up during the course of the actual trial. Such
discussions fall into two classes, according as the point
in dispute arises from an argument advanced by the
prosecution or from some
                    <hi rend="italics">prescription</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 72.
                    </note>
                    (or demurrer)
put forward by the defence. There have indeed
been some writers who have held that there is a
special
                    <hi rend="italics">prescriptive basis;</hi>
                    but
                    <hi rend="italics">prescription</hi>
                    is covered
by precisely the same questions that cover all other
laws.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When the dispute turns on
                    <hi rend="italics">prescription,</hi>
                    there
is no need to enquire into the facts of the case
itself. For example, a son puts forward a demurrer
against his father on the ground that his father has
forfeited his civil rights. The only point which has
to be decided is whether the demurrer can stand.
Still, wherever possible, we should attempt to create
a favourable impression in the judge as to the facts
of the case as well, since, if this be done, he will be
all the more disposed to give an indulgent hearing
                    <pb id="p.135"/>
                    to our point of law: for example, in actions taking
the form of a wager and arising out of interdicts,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sponsio</hi>
                        (= wager) was a form of suit in which the litigant
promised to pay a sum of money if he lost his case. The
                        <hi rend="italics">interdict was</hi>
                        an order issued by the praetor commanding or
prohibiting certain action. It occurred chiefly in disputes
about property.
                    </note>
                    even though the question is concerned solely with
actual possession, the question as to tile right to
possession not being raised, it will be desirable to
prove not merely that the property was actually in
our possession, but that it was ours to possess.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    On
tile other hand, the question more frequently turns
on intention. Take the law
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        an imaginary law of the schools of rhetoric.
                    </note>
                    <quote>Let a hero choose what reward he will.</quote>
                    I deny that he is entitled to receive
whatever he chooses. I cannot put forward any
formal demurrer, but none the less I use the intention as against the letter of the law just as I should
use a demurrer. In both cases the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is the same.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover every law either gives or takes away
punishes or commands, forbids or permits, and
involves a dispute either on its own account or on
account of another law, while the question which it
involves will turn either on the letter or the intention.
The letter is either clear or obscure or ambiguous.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And what I say with reference to laws will apply
equally to wills, agreements, contracts and every
form of document; nay, it will apply even to verbal
agreements. And since I have classified such cases
under four
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    I will deal with each in
turn.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Lawyers frequently raise the question of the
letter and the intention of the law, in fact a large
proportion of legal disputes turn on these points.
We need not therefore be surprised that such
questions occur in the schools as well, where they
are often invented with this special purpose. One
form of this kind of question is found in cases where
tile enquiry turns both on the letter and the spirit
                    <pb id="p.137"/>
                    of a law.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Such questions arise when the law presents
some obscurity. Under these circumstances both
parties will seek to establish their own interpretation
of the passage and to overthrow that advanced by
their opponent. Take for example the following
case.
                    <quote>
                        A thief shall refund four times the amount
of his theft. Two thieves have jointly stolen 10,000
sesterces. 40,000 are claimed from each. They
claim that they are liable only to pay 20,000 each.
                    </quote>
                    The accuser will urge that the sum which he claims
is fourfold the amount stolen; the accused will urge
that the sum which they offer to pay is fourfold.
The intention of the law will be pleaded by both
parties.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, the dispute may turn
on a passage of the law which is clear in one sense
and doubtful in another.
                    <quote>
                        The son of a harlot shall
not address the people. A woman who had a son
became a prostitute. The youth is forbidden to
address the people.
                    </quote>
                    Here there is no doubt about
the son of one who was a prostitute before his birth,
but it is doubtful whether the law applies to the case
of one born before his mother became a prostitute.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Another question which is not infrequently raised is
as to the interpretation of the law forbidding an action
to be brought twice on the same dispute, the problem
being whether the word
                    <hi rend="italics">twice</hi>
                    refers to the prosecutor
or the prosecution. Such are the points arising out
of the obscurity of the law.
                </p>
                <p>
                    A second form of question turns on some passage
where the meaning is clear. Those who have given
exclusive attention to this class of question call it
the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis concerned with the obvious expression of the law and its intention.</hi>
                    In such circumstances one
party will rest their case on the letter, the other
                    <pb id="p.139"/>
                    on the intention of the law.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    There are three
different methods in which we may combat the letter.
The first comes into play where it is clear that it is
impossible always to observe the letter of the law.
                    <quote>Children shall support their parents under penalty of imprisonment.</quote>
                    It is clear, in the first place, that
this cannot apply to an infant. At this point we
shall turn to other possible exceptions and distinguish
as follows.
                    <quote>
                        Does this apply to everyone who refuses
to support his parent? Has this particular individual
incurred the penalty by this particular act?
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The
second arises in scholastic themes where no argument can be drawn from the particular law, but the
question is concerned solely with the subject of the
dispute.
                    <quote>
                        A foreigner who goes up on to the wall
shall be liable to capital punishment. The enemy
had scaled the wall and were driven back by a
foreigner. His punishment is demanded.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n=" 7" unit="section"/>
                    In this
case we shall not have two separate questions,
namely, whether every foreigner who goes up on
the wall is liable to the penalty, and whether this
particular foreigner is liable, since no more forcible
argument can be brought against the application of
the letter of the law than the fact in dispute, but the
only question to be raised will be whether a foreigner
may not go on to the wall even for the purpose of
saving the city. Therefore we shall rest our case on
equity and the intention of the law. It is, however,
sometimes possible to draw examples from other laws
to show that we cannot always stand by the letter,
as Cicero did in his defence of Caecina.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The third
method becomes operative when we find something
in the actual words of the law which enables us to
prove that the intention of the legislator was different.
                    <pb id="p.141"/>
                    The following theme will provide an example.
                    <quote>
                        Anyone who is caught at night with steel in his hands
shall be thrown into prison. A man is found wearing a steel ring, and is imprisoned by the magistrate.
                    </quote>
                    In this case the use of the word
                    <hi rend="italics">caught</hi>
                    is sufficient
proof that the word steel was only intended by the
law in the sense of a weapon of offence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But just as the advocate who rests his case on the
intention of the law must wherever possible impugn
the letter of the law, so he who defends the letter
of the law must also seek to gain support from the
intention. Again, in cases concerned with wills it
sometimes happens that the intention of the testator
is clear, though it has not been expressed in writing:
an example of this occurs in the trial of Curius, which
gave rise to the well-known argument between
Lucius Crassus and Scaevola.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    A second heir had
been appointed in the event of a posthumous son
dying while a minor. No posthumous son was born.
The next of kin claimed the property. Who could
doubt that the intention of the testator was that
the same man should inherit in the event of the
son not being born who would have inherited in the
event of his death? But he had not written this in
his will.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the opposite case, that is to say,
when what is written is obviously contrary to tile
intention of the writer, occurred quite recently. A
man who had made a bequest of 5000 sesterces, on
altering his will erased the word
                    <hi rend="italics">sesterces</hi>
                    and inserted
                    <hi rend="italics">pounds of silver.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">About 384 sesterces go to the pound of silver.</note>
                    But it was clear that he had meant
not 5000 but 5 pounds of silver, because the weight
of silver mentioned in the bequest was unparalleled
and incredible.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The same
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    includes such general
questions as to whether we should stand by the
                    <pb id="p.143"/>
                    letter or the intention of the document, and what
was the purpose of the writer, while for the treatment of such questions we must have recourse to
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    with which I think I have dealt
in sufficient detail.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The next subject which comes up for discussion is that of contrary laws.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. vi. 46.</note>
                    For all writers
of text-books are agreed that in such cases there
are two
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    involving the letter and the intention
of the law respectively. This view is justified by
the fact that, when one law contradicts another, both
parties attack the letter and raise the question of
intention, while the point in dispute, as regards each
law, is whether we should be guided by it at all.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But
it is clear to everybody that one law cannot contradict
another in principle (since if there were two different
principles, one law would cancel the other), and
that the laws in question are brought into collision
purely by the accidents of chance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    When two laws clash, they may be of a similar
nature, as for instance if we have to compare two
cases in which a tyrannicide and a brave man are
given the choice of their reward, both being granted
the privilege of choosing whatever they desire. In
such a case we compare the deserts of the claimants,
the occasions of the respective acts and the nature
of the rewards claimed.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Or the same law may be
in conflict with itself, as in the case where we have
two brave men,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Both claiming the reward allotted by the law.</note>
                    two tyrannicides
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Both claiming the reward allotted by the law.</note>
                    or two ravished
women,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Two women, both dishonoured by one man, put in
different claims, both of which are provided for as alternatives
in the same law.
                        <hi rend="italics">A.</hi>
                        demands the ravisher's death,
                        <hi rend="italics">B.</hi>
                        demands his hand in marriage.
                    </note>
                    when the question must turn either on
                    <hi rend="italics">time</hi>
                    (that is, whose claim has priority) or on
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    (that
is, whose claim is the more just). Again, we may
have a conflict between diverse, similar or dissimilar
laws.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Diverse</hi>
                    laws are those against which arguments
                    <pb id="p.145"/>
                    may be brought without reference to any contradictory law. The following theme will provide an
example.
                    <quote>
                        A magistrate shall not quit the citadel.
One who has rendered heroic service to his country
may choose what reward he pleases. A magistrate
who left his post and saved his country, demands an
amnesty for his conduct.
                    </quote>
                    In this case, even though
there be no other law covering the case, we may
raise the question whether a hero ought to be
granted anything he chooses to claim. Again, many
conclusive arguments may be brought against the
letter of the law restricting the movements of the
magistrate: for example, a fire may have broken out
in the citadel, or a sally against the enemy may have
been necessary.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Laws are styled
                    <hi rend="italics">similar</hi>
                    when nothing can be opposed to one except the other.
                    <quote>
                        Tyrannicides shall have their statues set up in the
gymnasium. A statue of a woman shall not be set
up in the gymnasium. A woman killed a tyrant.
                    </quote>
                    Here are two conflicting laws: for a woman's statue
cannot under any other circumstances be erected in
the gymnasium, while there is no other circumstance
which can bar the erection of the statue of a
tyrannicide in the gymnasium.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Laws are styled
                    <hi rend="italics">dissimilar</hi>
                    when many arguments can be urged against
one, while the only point which can be urged against
the other is the actual subject of dispute. An
example is provided by the case in which a brave
man demands the pardon of a deserter as his reward.
For there are many arguments, as I have shown
above, which can be urged against the law permitting
a hero to choose whatever reward he will, but
the letter of the law dealing with the crime of
desertion cannot be overthrown under any
                    <pb id="p.147"/>
                    circumstances save the choice of rewards to which I have
just referred.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the point of law is either admitted by
both parties or disputed. If it be admitted, the
questions which are raised will as a rule be such
as the following. Which of the two laws is the
most stringent? Does it concern gods or men, the
state or private individuals, reward or punishment,
great things or small? Does it permit, forbid or
command?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Another common question is which of
the two laws is the oldest; but the most important
question is which of the two laws will suffer less by
its contravention, as for example in the case of the
hero and the deserter just mentioned, in which case,
if the deserter is not put to death, the whole law is
ignored, whereas, if he be put to death, the hero
will still have another choice left open to him. It
is, however, of the utmost importance to consider
which course is best from the point of view of
morality and justice, a problem for the solution of
which no general rules can be laid down, as it will
depend on the special circumstances of the case.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    If,
on the other hand, the point of law is disputed, either
one party or both in turn will argue the point. Take
the following case as an example.
                    <quote>
                        A father shall
be empowered to arrest his son, and a patron to
arrest his freedman. Freedmen shall be transferred
to their patron's heir. A certain man appointed the
son of a freedman as his heir. The son of the freedman and the freedman himself both claim the right
to arrest the other.
                    </quote>
                    Here the father claims his right
over the son, while the son, in virtue of his new position
as patron, denies that his father possessed the rights
of a father, because he was in the power of his patron.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.149"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Laws containing two provisions may conflict with
themselves in exactly the same way as two laws may
conflict. The following will serve as an illustration.
                    <quote>
                        The bastard born before a legitimate son shall rank
as legitimate, the bastard born after the legitimate
son shall only rank as a citizen.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. vi. 96.</note>
                    All that I have
said about laws will also apply to decrees of the
senate. If decrees of the senate conflict with one
another or with the laws, the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    will be the same
as if laws only were concerned.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogistic basis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See III. vi. 43
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    has some resemblance
to the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    concerned with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter and intention of the law,</hi>
                    since whenever it comes into play, one party
rests his case on the letter: there is, however, this
difference between the two
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    that in the latter
we argue against the letter, in the present beyond
the letter, while in the latter the party defending
the letter aims at securing that in any case the letter
may be carried into effect, whereas in the present his
aim will be to prevent anything except the letter
being carried into effect. The
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism</hi>
                    is sometimes
employed in conjunction with
                    <hi rend="italics">definition:</hi>
                    for often if
the definition be weak it takes refuge in the syllogism.
Assume a law to run as follows:
                    <quote>
                        A woman who is
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        a poisoner shall be liable to capital punishment. A
wife gave her husband a love-potion to cure him of
his habit of beating her. She also divorced him.
On being asked by her relatives to return to him,
she refused. The husband hung himself. The
woman is accused of poisoning.
                    </quote>
                    The strongest
line for the accuser to take will be to assert that
the love-potion was a poison. This involves definition.
If it proves weak, we shall have recourse to the
syllogism, to which we shall proceed after virtually
                    <pb id="p.151"/>
                    dropping our previous argument, and which we shall
employ to decide the question whether she does not
deserve to be punished for administering the lovepotion no less than if she had caused her husband's
death by poison.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogistic basis,</hi>
                    then, deduces from the letter
of the law that which is uncertain; and since this
conclusion is arrived at by reason, the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is called
                    <hi rend="italics">ratiocinative.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">See</hi>
                        in. vi. 43, 61.
                    </note>
                    It may be subdivided into the following
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    of question. If it is right to do a thing
once, is it right to do it often? Example:
                    <quote>
                        A
priestess found guilty of unchastity is thrown from
the Tarpeian rock and survives. It is demanded
that she shall be thrown down again.
                    </quote>
                    If the law
grants a privilege with reference to one thing, does
it grant it with reference to a number? Example:
                    <quote>A man kills two tyrants together and claims two rewards.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    If a thing is legal before a certain
occurrence, is it legal after it? Example:
                    <quote>
                        The
ravisher took refuge in flight. His victim married.
The ravisher returned and the woman demands to
be allowed her choice.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        the death of the ravisher, see n. on VII. vii. 3.
                    </note>
                    Is that which is lawful
with regard to the whole, lawful with regard to a
part? Example:
                    <quote>It is forbidden to accept a plough as security. He accepted a ploughshare.</quote>
                    Is that
which is lawful with regard to a part, lawful with
regard to the whole? Example:
                    <quote>It is forbidden to export wool from Tarentum: he exported sheep.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In all these cases the syllogism rests on the letter of
the law as well: for the accuser urges that the
provisions of the law are precise. He will say,
                    <quote>I demand that the priestess who has broken her vows be cast down: it is the law,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>
                        The
ravished woman demands the exercise of the
                        <pb id="p.153"/>
                        choice permitted her by law,
                    </quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Wool grows on sheep,</quote>
                    and so on.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But to this we may reply,
                    <quote>
                        The law does not prescribe that the condemned
woman should be thrown down twice, that the
ravished woman should exercise her choice under
all circumstances, that the tyrannicide should receive
two rewards, while it makes no mention of ploughshares or of sheep.
                    </quote>
                    Thus we infer what is doubtful
from what is certain. It is a more difficult task to
deduce from the letter of the law that which is not
actually prescribed by the letter, and to argue because
that is the case, so also is this. Take the following
problems.
                    <quote>The man who kills his father shall be sewn up in a sack. He killed his mother,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>
                        It
is illegal to drag a man from his own house into the
court. He dragged him from his tent.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Under this
heading come questions such as the following: if
there is not a special law applicable to the case, ought
we to have recourse to an analogous law? is the
point in question similar to what is contained in the
letter of the law? Now it should be noted that what
is similar may be greater, equal or less. In the first
ease we enquire whether the provisions of the law
are sufficient, or, if they are insufficient, whether we
should have recourse to this other law. In both
cases it is a question of the intention of the legislator.
But the most effective form of treatment in such
cases will be to appeal to equity.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I turn to tile discussion of
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity,</hi>
                    which will
be found to have countless species: indeed, in the
opinion of certain philosophers, there is not a single
word which has not a diversity of meanings. There
are, however, very few
                    <hi rend="italics">genera,</hi>
                    since ambiguity must
occur either in a single word or in a group of words.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.155"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Single words give rise to error, when the same
noun applies to a number of things or persons (the
Greeks call this
                    <hi rend="italics">homonymy):</hi>
                    for example, it is uncertain with regard to the word
                    <hi rend="italics">gallus</hi>
                    whether it
means a cock or a Gaul or a proper name or an
emasculated priest of tybele; while Ajax may refer
either to the son of Telamon or the son of Oileus.
Again, verbs likewise may have different meanings,
as, for example, cerno.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <hi rend="italics">or</hi>
                        decide
                        <hi rend="italics">or</hi>
                        separate.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    This ambiguity crops up in
many ways, and gives rise to disputes, mole especially
in connexion with wills, when two men of the same
name claim their freedom or, it may be, an inheritance, or again, when the enquiry turns on the precise
nature of the bequest.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    There is another form of
ambiguity where a word has one meaning when
entire and another when divided, as, for example,
                    <hi rend="italics">ingenua, armameniam</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">Corvinum.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Inyenua,</hi>
                        a freeborn woman;
                        <hi rend="italics">in genua,</hi>
                        on to the knees.
                        <hi rend="italics">Armamentum,</hi>
                        equipment;
                        <hi rend="italics">arma mentum,</hi>
                        arms, chin.
                        <hi rend="italics">Corvinum,</hi>
                        ace. of name Corvinus;
                        <hi rend="italics">cor vimium,</hi>
                        heart, wine.
                    </note>
                    The disputes
arising from such ambiguities are no more than
childish quibbles, but nevertheless the Greeks are
in the habit of making them the subject for controversial themes, as, for example, in the notorious
case of the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">au)lhtri/s,</foreign>
                    when the question is whether
it is a hall which has fallen down three times (
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">au)/lh tri/s</foreign>
                    ) or a flute-player who fell down that is to be sold.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    A third form of ambiguity is caused by the use of
compound words; for example, if a man orders his
body to be buried in a cultivated spot, and should
direct, as is often done, a considerable space of land
surrounding his tomb to be taken from the land left
to his heirs with a view to preserving his ashes from
outrage, an occasion for dispute may be afforded by
the question whether the words mean
                    <quote>in a cultivated place</quote>
                    (
                    <hi rend="italics">in culto loco</hi>
                    ) or
                    <quote>in an uncultivated place</quote>
                    (
                    <hi rend="italics">inculto loco</hi>
                    ).
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Thus arises the Greek theme
                    <pb id="p.157"/>
                    about Leon and Pantaleon, who go to law because
the handwriting of a will makes it uncertain whether
the testator has left all his property to Leon or his
property to Pantaleon.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        whether he wrote
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">pa/nta *le/onti</foreign>
                        or
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">*pantale/onti.</foreign>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Groups of words give rise to more serious ambiguity. Such ambiguity may arise from doubt as
to a case, as in the following passage:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Enn.
                        <hi rend="italics">Ann.</hi>
                        186. An ambiguous oracle quoted by Cicero
(
                        <hi rend="italics">de Div.</hi>
                        II. lvi.). It might equally mean that Rome or
Pyrrhus would conquer. Cp. the oracle given to Croesus:
                        <quote>If thou cross the Halys, thou shalt destroy a mighty empire.</quote>
                    </note>
                    —
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">I say that you, O prince of Aeacus' line,</l>
                            <l part="I">Rome can o'erthrow.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Or it may arise from the arrangement of the words,
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    which makes it doubtful what the exact reference of
some word or words may be, more especially when
there is a word in the middle of the sentence which
may be referred either to what precedes or what
follows, as in the line of Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                        i. 477.
                    </note>
                    which describes
Troilus as
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">lora tenens tamen,</l>
                    </quote>
                    where it may be disputed whether the poet means
that he is still holding the reins, or that, although
he holds the reins, he is still dragged along.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The
controversial theme,
                    <quote>
                        A certain man in his will
ordered his heirs to erect
                        <hi rend="italics">statuam auream hastam tenentem,'</hi>
                    </quote>
                    turns on a similar ambiguity; for it raises
the question whether it is the statue holding the
spear which is to be of gold, or whether the spear
should be of gold and the statue of some other
material. The same result is even more frequently
produced by a mistaken inflexion of the voice, as in
the line:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            quinquaginta uhi erant centum inde occidit Achilles.
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                                <quote>Achilles slew fifty out of a hundred,</quote>
                                <hi rend="italics">or</hi>
                                <quote>a hundred out of fifty.</quote>
                                Translated from a Greek line in Arist.
                                <hi rend="italics">Soph. El.</hi>
                                i. 4. (
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">penth/kont' a)ndrw=n e(kato\n li/pe di=os</foreign>
                                ).
                                <hi rend="italics">Quinquaginta</hi>
                                is the object of
                                <hi rend="italics">occidit.</hi>
                                Faulty reading might
make it go with
                                <hi rend="italics">ubi erant,</hi>
                                leaving
                                <hi rend="italics">centum</hi>
                                as the object of
                                <hi rend="italics">occidit,</hi>
                                and making nonsense of the line.
                            </note>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    It is also often doubtful to which of two antecedents
a phrase is to be referred. Hence we get such
                    <pb id="p.159"/>
                    controversial themes as,
                    <quote>My heir shall be bound to give my wife a hundred pounds of silver according to choice,</quote>
                    where it is left uncertain which of the
two is to make the choice.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But in these examples of ambiguity, the first may
be remedied by a change of case, the second by
separating 1 the words or altering their position, the
third by some addition.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 11.</note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Ambiguity resulting from
the use of two accusatives may be removed by the
substitution of the ablative: for example,
                    <hi rend="italics">Lachetem audivi percussisse Demeam</hi>
                    (I heard that Demea struck
Laches,
                    <hi rend="italics">or</hi>
                    that L. struck D.) may be rendered clear
by writing
                    <hi rend="italics">a Lachete percussum Demeam</hi>
                    (that D. was
struck by L.). There is, however, a natural ambiguity in the ablative case itself, as I pointed out
in the first book.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">I. vii. 3.</note>
                    For example,
                    <hi rend="italics">caelo decurrit aperto</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Apparently a misquotation of Virg.
                        <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                        v. 212,
                        <hi rend="italics">pelago decurrit aperto.</hi>
                    </note>
                    leaves it doubtful whether the poet means he
hastened down
                    <quote>through the open sky,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>when the sky was opened for him to pass.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Words may
be separated by a breathing space or pause. We
may, for instance, say
                    <hi rend="italics">statuam,</hi>
                    and then, after a
slight pause, add
                    <hi rend="italics">auream hastam,</hi>
                    or the pause may
come between
                    <hi rend="italics">statuam auream</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">haslam.</hi>
                    The
addition referred to above would take the form
                    <hi rend="italics">quod elegerit ipse,</hi>
                    where
                    <hi rend="italics">ipse</hi>
                    will show that the reference
to the heir, or
                    <hi rend="italics">quod elegerit ipsa,</hi>
                    making the reference
to the wife. In cases where ambiguity is caused
by the addition of a word, the difficulty may be
eliminated by the removal of a word, as in the
sentence
                    <hi rend="italics">nos flentes illos deprehendimus.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Does this mean
                        <hi rend="italics">we found them weeping,</hi>
                        or
                        <hi rend="italics">we found them weeping for us?</hi>
                        The ambiguity is eliminated by the removal
of
                        <hi rend="italics">nos.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Where it
is doubtful to what a word or phrase refers, and the
word or phrase itself is ambiguous, we shall have to
alter several words, as, for example, in the sentence,
                    <quote>
                        My heir shall be bound to give him all his own
                        <pb id="p.161"/>
                        property,
                    </quote>
                    where
                    <quote>his own</quote>
                    is ambiguous. Cicero
commits the same fault when he says of Gaius
Fannius,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Brut.</hi>
                        xxvi. 101. The sentence continues,
                        <quote>
                            (an act of
which Laelius said by way of excuse that he had given the
augurship not to his younger son-in-law, but to his elder
daughter), Fannius, I say, despite his lack of affection for
Laelius, in obedience to his instructions attended the lectures
of Panaetius.
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        He following the instructions of his
father-in-law, for whom, because he had not been
elected to the college of augurs, he had no great
affection, especially as he had given Quintus Scaevola,
the younger of his sons-in-law, the preference over
himself. .
                    </quote>
                    For
                    <hi rend="italics">over himself</hi>
                    may refer either to his
father-in-law or to Fannius.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Again, another source
of ambiguity arises from leaving it doubtful in a
written document whether a syllable is long or short.
                    <hi rend="italics">Cato,</hi>
                    for example, means one thing in the nominative when its second syllable is short, and another in
the dative or ablative when the same syllable is long.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                        of the adjective catus, shrewd.
                    </note>
                    There are also a number of other forms of ambiguity
which it is unnecessary for me to describe at length.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Further, it is quite unimportant how ambiguity
arises or how it is remedied. For it is clear in all
cases that two interpretations are possible, and as
far as the written or spoken word is concerned,
it is equally important for both parties. It is
therefore a perfectly futile rule which directs us to
endeavour, in connexion with this
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    to turn the
word in question to suit our own purpose, since, if
this is feasible, there is no ambiguity.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    In cases of
ambiguity the only questions which confront us will
be, sometimes which of the two interpretations is
most natural, and always which interpretation is
most equitable, and what was the intention of the
person who wrote or uttered the words. I have,
however, given sufficient instructions in the course
of my remarks on
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    as to the
method of treating such questions, whether by the
prosecution or the defence.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.163"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    There is, however, a certain affinity between
all these
                    <hi rend="italics">bases.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">III. vi. 54.</note>
                    For in
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    we enquire into the
meaning of a term, and in the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism,</hi>
                    which is
closely connected with
                    <hi rend="italics">definition,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See ch. viii. 1.</note>
                    we consider what
was the meaning of the writer, while it is obvious
that in the case of contrary laws there are two
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    one concerned with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter,</hi>
                    and the other with
the
                    <hi rend="italics">intention.</hi>
                    Again,
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    is in itself a kind of
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity,</hi>
                    since it brings out two meanings in the
same term.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    concerned with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter</hi>
                    and
the
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    of the law involves a legal question as
regards the interpretation of the words, which is
identical with the question arising out of
                    <hi rend="italics">contrary laws.</hi>
                    Consequently some writers have asserted that
all these
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    may be resolved into those concerned
with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">intention,</hi>
                    while others hold that
in all cases where the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    of a
document have to be considered, it is
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity</hi>
                    that
gives rise to the question at issue. But all these
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    are really distinct, for an obscure point of law
is not the same as an ambiguous point of law.
                    <hi rend="italics">Definition,</hi>
                    then,
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    involves a general question as to
the actual nature of a term, a question which may
conceivably have no connexion whatsoever with the
content of the case in point. In investigations as
to the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">intention,</hi>
                    the dispute turns on
the provisions contained in the law, whereas the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism</hi>
                    deals with that which is not contained in
the law. In disputes arising out of
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity</hi>
                    we
are led from the ambiguous phrase to its conflicting
meanings, whereas in the case of
                    <hi rend="italics">contrary laws</hi>
                    the
fight starts from the conflict of their provisions.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The distinction between these
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    has therefore
been rightly accepted by the most learned of
                    <pb id="p.165"/>
                    rhetoricians, and is still adopted by the majority
and the wisest of the teachers of to-day.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It has not been possible in this connexion to give
instructions which will cover the arrangement to be
adopted in every case, though I have been able to
give some.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    There are other details concerning which
I can give no instructions without a statement of the
particular case on which the orator has to speak.
For not only must the whole case be analysed into
its component topics and questions, but these subdivisions themselves require to be arranged in the
order which is appropriate to them. For example,
in the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium</hi>
                    each part has its own special place,
first, second and third, etc., while each question and
topic requires to be suitably arranged, and the same
is true even of isolated
                    <hi rend="italics">general questions.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        II. iv. 24; III. v. 8.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    For it will
not, I imagine, be represented that sufficient skill
in division is possessed by the man who, after resolving a controversial theme into questions such as
the following, whether a hero is to be granted any
reward that he may claim, whether he is allowed to
claim private property, whether he may demand any
woman in marriage, whether he may claim to marry
a woman who already possesses a husband, or this
particular woman,
                    <hi rend="italics">then,</hi>
                    although it is his duty to
deal with the first question first, proceeds to deal
with them indiscriminately as each may happen to
occur to him, and ignores the fact that the first
point which should be discussed is whether we
should stand by the letter or the intention of the
law, and fails to follow the natural order,
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    which
demands that after beginning with this question he
should then proceed to introduce the subsidiary
questions, thereby making the structure of his speech
                    <pb id="p.167"/>
                    as regular as that of the human body, of which, for
example, the hand is a part, while the fingers are
parts of the hand, and the joints of the fingers.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">fecerit</hi>
                        and
                        <hi rend="italics">struxerit</hi>
                        are both negatived by the preceding
                        <hi rend="italics">non.</hi>
                        It is impossible to reproduce the conciseness of the
original.
                    </note>
                    It
is precisely this method of arrangement which it is
impossible to demonstrate except with reference to
some definite and specific case.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But it is clearly
useless to take one or two cases, or even a hundred
or a thousand, since their number is infinite. It is
the duty of the teacher to demonstrate daily in one
kind of case after another what is the natural order
and connexion of the parts, so that little by little
his pupils may gain the experience which will enable
them to deal with other cases of the same character.
For it is quite impossible to teach everything that
can be accomplished by art.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For example, what
painter has ever been taught to reproduce everything
in nature? But once he has acquired the general
principles of imitation, he will be able to copy whatever is given him. What vase-maker is there who
has not succeeded in producing a vase of a type
which he had never previously seen?
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    There are, however, some things which depend
not on the teacher, but on the learner. For example,
a physician will teach what treatment should be
adopted for different diseases, what the dangers are
against which he must be on his guard, and what
the symptoms by which they may be recognised. But
he will not be able to communicate to his pupil the
gift of feeling the pulse, or appreciating the variations
of colour, breathing and temperature: this will
depend on the talent of the individual. Therefore,
in most instances, we must rely on ourselves,
and must study cases with the utmost care, never
                    <pb id="p.169"/>
                    forgetting that men discovered our art before ever
they proceeded to teach it.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    For the most effective,
and what is justly styled most
                    <hi rend="italics">economical</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        III. iii. 9.
                    </note>
                    arrangement of a case as a whole, is that which cannot be
determined except when we have the specific facts
before us. It consists in the power to determine
when the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium</hi>
                    is necessary and when it should
be omitted; when we should make our statement of
facts continuous, and when we should subdivide it;
when we should begin at the very beginning, when,
like Homer, start at the middle or the end;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    when
we should omit the statement of facts altogether;
when we should begin by dealing with the arguments
advanced by our opponents, and when with our own;
when we should place the strongest proofs first and
when the weakest; in what cases we should prefix
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    to the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium,</hi>
                    and what preparation is
necessary to pave the way for these questions; what
arguments the judge will accept at once, and to
what he requires to be led by degrees; whether we
should refute our opponent's arguments as a whole
or in detail; whether we should reserve emotional
appeals for the peroration or distribute them throughout the whole speech; whether we should speak first
of law or of equity; whether we should first advance
(or refute) charges as to past offences or the charges
connected with the actual trial;
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    or, again, if the
case is complicated, what order we should adopt,
what evidence or documents of any kind should
be read out in the course of our speech, and what
reserved for a later stage. This gift of arrangement
is to oratory what generalship is to war. The skilled
commander will know how to distribute his forces
                    <pb id="p.171"/>
                    for battle, what troops he should keep back to
garrison forts or guard cities, to secure supplies, or
guard communications, and what dispositions to make
by land and by sea.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    But to possess this gift, our
orator will require all the resources of nature, learning
and industrious study. Therefore let no man hope
that he can acquire eloquence merely by the labour
of others. He must burn the midnight oil, persevere
to the end and grow pale with study: he must form
his own powers, his own experience, his own
methods: he must not require to hunt for his
weapons, but must have them ready for immediate
use, as though they were born with him and not
derived from the instruction of others.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The road
may be pointed out, but our speed must be our
own. Art has done enough in publishing the
resources of eloquence, it is for us to know how to
use them.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    And it is not enough merely to arrange
the various parts: each several part has its own
internal economy, according to which one thought
will come first, another second, another third, while
we must struggle not merely to place these thoughts
in their proper order, but to link them together and
give them such cohesion that there will be no trace
of any suture: they must form a body, not a congeries
of limbs.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    This end will be attained if we note what
best suits each position, and take care that the words
which we place together are such as will not clash,
but will mutually harmonise. Thus different facts
will not seem like perfect strangers thrust into
uncongenial company from distant places, but will
be united with what precedes and follows by an
intimate bond of union, with the result that our
                    <pb id="p.173"/>
                    speech will give the impression not merely of having
been put together, but of natural continuity. I fear,
however, that I have been lured on from one thing to
another and have advanced somewhat too far, since
I find myself gliding from the subject of arrangement to the discussion of the general rules of style,
which will form the opening theme of the next
book.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
