<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panegyric on the Third Consulship of the Emperor Honorius</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. I</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date type="printing">1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/claudian01clau#page/266/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa010.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.269" TEIform="pb"/>
         <div1 type="poem" n="praef" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PREFACE</head>
         <p>

Eagles may not rear their young without the sun's
permission and the goodwill of heaven. So soon as
the chicks have shattered their shells and issued
forth, after that the warmth of their mother's body
has cracked the opening egg, the father bird makes
haste to carry the unfledged nestlings aloft and bids
them gaze at the sun's fires with unblinking eye. He
takes counsel of those bright beams and under light's
schooling makes trial of the strength and temper of
his sons. The angry father strikes with pitiless
talons the degenerate who turns away his glance, but
he whose eye can bear the searching flame, who with
bolder sight can outstare the noonday sun, is brought
up a king of birds, heir to the thunderbolt, destined
to carry Jove's three-forked weapon. So mighty
Rome fears not to send me, oft tested e'er now in the
Muses' caverns, to face the emperor, her god. Now
have I won an emperor's ear, the entrance to an
emperor's palace and the emperor himself as judge
of my lyre's song.
<pb id="v.1.p.271"/>
         </p>
         <pb id="v.1.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="poem" n="1" id="poem.7" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PANEGYRIC</head>
         <p>

Let the consular fasces of Romulus open a third
year, and for the third time let the warlike procession
accompany thy curule litter. More festal in array
be the coming year, and let purple, folded in Gabine 1
guise, be proudly enriched with gems of Hydaspes;
let the cloak of peace succeed the arms of war;
let the lictor guard the consul's tent and the Latin
axes return to the standards.2 And do thou,
Honorius, who with thy brother, lord of the East,
governest with equal care a world that was once thy
sire's, go thy way with favourable omens and order
the sun's new course, thyself heaven's hope and
desire, palace-nurtured even from life's threshold,
to whom the camp, gleaming with drawn swords,
gave schooling among the laurels of victory. Thy
towering fortune has never known the condition of a
private citizen; when thou wast born thou wast born
a king. Power which was thine by birth received
thee, a precious pledge, amid the purple; soldiers
bearing victorious standards inaugurated thy birth
and set thy cradle in the midst of arms. When
thou wast born fierce Germany trembled along
<pb id="v.1.p.273"/>
the Rhine's full course, Caucasus shook his forests
in fear, and the people of Meroe, confessing thy
divinity, laid aside their quivers and drew the useless
arrows from their hair. As a child thou didst
crawl among shields, fresh-won spoils of monarchs
were thy playthings, and thou wert ever the first
to embrace thy stern father on his return from
rude battles, when that, reeking with the blood of
northern savages, he came home victorious from
his conquest over the tribes of the Danube. Then
wouldst thou demand thy share of the spoils, a
Scythian bow or a belt won from the Geloni, a Dacian
spear or Suabian bridle. Often would he smile on
thee and uplift thee, eager for the honour, on his
shining shield, and clasp thee to his still panting
bosom. Thou fearedst not his coat of mail nor the
dread gleam of his helmet but stretchedst out thy
hands to grasp its lofty plumes. Then in his joy
thy father cried: <q direct="unspecified">King of starry Olympus, may
this my son return in like manner from the lands of
conquered foes, rich with the spoils of Hyrcania or
proud with the slaughter of the Assyrians; his sword
thus red with blood, his countenance thus roughened
by the constant blasts and stained with the welcome
dust of heroic combat, may he bring back to his
happy father the arms of his conquered foes.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Soon when thou couldst stand upright and walk
with firm step thy sire forbade thee enervating sloth,
luxurious ease, time-wasting slumbers. He strengthened
thy young limbs with hard toils and rude was the
training wherewith he exercised thy tender powers.
</p>
         <p>Thou wert taught to bear winter's cruel cold, to
shrink not before storm and tempest, to face the heat
of summer, to swim across loud-roaring torrents, to
<pb id="v.1.p.275"/>
climb mountains, to run o'er the plain, to leap
ravines and hollows, to spend sleepless nights of
watching under arms, to drink melted snow from thy
casque, to shoot the arrow from the bow or hurl the
acorn-missiles with a Balearic sling. And the more
to inflame thy heart with love of battle he would
recount to thee the deeds of thy grandsire, object of
dread to Libya's sun-scorched shores and Thule
whither no ship can sail. He conquered the fleet
Moors and the well-named 1 Picts; his roaming sword
pursued the flying Scot; his adventurous oars broke
the surface of the northern seas. Crowned with the
spoils of triumphs won beneath the northern and the
southern sky he trod the wave-swept strand of either
Ocean. Thus did he spur thy courage, thus sow
the seeds of fame; these were the examples he gave.
</p>
         <p>Not more avidly did Achilles himself drink in the
Centaur's precepts when he learnt of him how to
wield the spear or play the lyre or discern healing
plants.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile the world forgot its loyalty: the
thunder of civil war sounded afresh and discord shook
the tottering earth. O ye guilty gods! O shame
everlasting! — a barbarian 2 exile had possessed himself
of the cities of Italy and had entrusted the
government of Rome to some low-born dependent.
</p>
         <p>But Theodosius was already afoot, rallying to his
standard the distant nations of the East, the dwellers
on the banks of flooding Euphrates, clear Halys, and
rich Orontes. The Arabs left their spicy groves, the
Medes the waters of the Caspian Sea, the Armenians
the river Phasis, the Parthians the Niphates.
</p>
         <p>What lust of battle then filled thy heart, what
longing to accompany thy father! What would not
<pb id="v.1.p.277"/>
thine eager spirit have given to hear the beloved
clarion's note and to revel in the bloody storm of
battle, trampling upon the slaughtered bodies of thy
foes! Like a young lion in a cave, accustomed to look
for nourishment to the teats of its tawny mother,
who, so soon as he finds talons beginning to grow
from out his paws and a mane sprout from his neck
and teeth arm his jaws, will have none of this inglorious
food but burns to leave his cavern home and
accompany his Gaetulian sire, to bring death upon
the herds and steep him in the gore of some tall
steer. But Theodosius said thee nay, and put
the reins of government into thy hands, crowning
thy head with the sacred diadem it wore so meetly.
</p>
         <p>And so did thy virtue show in earliest years, so did
thy soul out-range thy youth that all complained
that to thee empire was granted late.
</p>
         <p>Swiftly beneath thy auspices was victory achieved.
</p>
         <p>Both fought for us — thou with thy happy influence,
thy father with his strong right arm. Thanks to thee
the Alps lay open to our armies, nor did it avail
the careful foe to cling to fortified posts. Their
ramparts, and the trust they put therein, fell; the
rocks were torn away and their hiding-places exposed.
</p>
         <p>Thanks to thine influence the wind of the frozen North
overwhelmed the enemy's line with his mountain
storms, hurled back their weapons upon the throwers
and with the violence of his tempest drove back their
spears. Verily God is with thee, when at thy behest
Aeolus frees the armèd tempests from his cave, when
the very elements fight for thee and the allied winds
come at the call of thy trumpets. The Alpine snows
grew red with slaughter, the cold Frigidus, its waters
turned to blood, ran hot and steaming, and would
<pb id="v.1.p.279"/>
have been choked with the heaps of corpses had not
their own fast-flowing gore helped on its course.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile Arbogast, the cause of this wicked
war, had pierced his side deep not with a single
blade: two swords 1 reeked with his blood, and his
own hand, learning justice at last, had turned its
savage fury against himself. Thus was liberty
restored; but though Nature demanded the return
to heaven of divine Theodosius whose work was now
accomplished, though the sky threw open the golden
palaces of its starry vault and Atlas staggered
knowing the burden he was to bear, yet did the
emperor forbear to entrust him to expectant Olympus
until he could in thy presence hand over to thee a
world at peace. Straightway didst thou, Honorius,
leave the coasts of Thrace, and, braving the dangers of
the journey, pass without a tremor through the hordes
of barbarians. Thou leavest the rocks of Rhodope
to which Orpheus' lyre gave life; thou quittest the
heights of Oeta, scene of Hercules' ill-omened funeral
pyre; next thou climbest Pelion, famed for the
marriage of Peleus and Thetis. Fair Enipeus and
lofty Dodona look upon thee in amaze, and the oaks of
Chaonia, finding tongues once more, utter oracles in
thine honour. Thou skirtest the extreme coasts of
Illyria and, passing over Dalmatia's fields, dost
cross in turn the nine sources of Trojan Timavus.2
The high-walled cities of Italy rejoice in the blessings
of thy presence. Eridanus bows his head and
worships, bidding his waves flow gently to the sea;
and Phaethon's leafy sisters, that ever weep their
brother's death, check the flow of their dewy amber.
</p>
         <p>How many youths, how many matrons set modesty
aside in eagerness to behold thee! Austere grey-
<pb id="v.1.p.281"/>
beards struggle with boys for places whence to see
thee in the tender embraces of thy sire, borne
through the midst of Rome on a triumphal chariot
decked but with the shade of a simple laurel branch.
</p>
         <p>Who did not then think that he beheld the morning-
star together with the rosy sun, or the Thunderer
shine in concert with Bacchus? On every side
stretches the host of plumed warriors, each hymning
thy praises in his own tongue; the brightness of
bronze dazzles the eye and the martial glint of a
forest of unsheathed swords redoubles the light
of day. Some are decked with bows, others bristle
with far-flung javelins or pikes for fighting at close
quarters. These raise standards adorned with
flying eagles, or with embroidered dragons or
writhing serpents, that in their thousands seem to be
roused to angry life by the breath of the wind which,
as it blows them this way and that, causes them
to rustle with a sound like the hiss of a living snake.
</p>
         <p>When they reached the palace the emperor bade
all depart and thus unbidden addressed his son-in-law:
<q direct="unspecified">Victorious Stilicho, of whose courage in
war, of whose loyalty in peace I have made proof
— what warlike feat have I performed without
thine aid? What triumph have I won that thou
helpedst me not in the winning? Together we
caused Thracian Hebrus to run red with Getic blood,
together overthrew the squadrons of the Sarmatae,
together rested our weary limbs on the snows of
Mount Riphaeus and scarred the frozen Danube
with our chariot's wheel — come, therefore, since
heaven's halls claim me, do thou take up my
task; be thou sole guardian of my children, let
thy hand protect my two sons. I adjure thee by
<pb id="v.1.p.283"/>
that marriage that makes thee kin with me, by the
night that saw its consummation, by the torch
which at thy wedding-feast the queen carried in
her own hand when she led thy bride-elect from out
the imperial palace, take on thee a father's spirit,
guard the years of their childhood. Was not their sire
thy master and thy wife's father? Now, now I shall
mount untroubled to the stars for thou wilt watch over
them. Even should Typhoeus rend away the rocks
and leap forth, should Tityus free his captive limbs,
should Enceladus, hurling Etna from him, roar in
rage — each and all will fall before Stilicho's attack.</q>
         </p>
         <p>He spake no more but still in human form clove
a furrow of light through the clouds; he passes
to Luna's globe, leaves Mercury's threshold and
hastens to the gentle airs of Venus. Hence he traverses
Phoebus' path. Mars' baleful fires and Jupiter's
quiet quarters, and stands upon the very crown of
the sky, cold Saturn's frozen zone. Heaven's fabric
opens, unbidden the shining doors swing back.
</p>
         <p>Boötes prepares a place in the vault of the northern
sky, sword-girt Orion unbars the portals of the south;
they offer welcome to the new star, uncertain
each in turn to what region he will betake himself,
what constellation he will grace with his presence,
or in what quarter he will elect to shine alone.
O glory of heaven as once thou wert of earth, the
ocean that laves the shores of the land of thy birth
receives thee wearied with thy nightly course, Spain
bathes thee in thy natal waves. Happy father, when
first thou risest above the horizon thou lookest upon
Arcadius, when thou dippest to thy setting the sight
of Honorius delays thy westering fires. Through
whichever hemisphere thou takest thy wandering
<pb id="v.1.p.285"/>
journey, thou passest over the domains of sons who
with tranquil mind and ripe control rule over allied
peoples, who once again fashion the ages from a
nobler ore. Avarice is left to weep in Stygian
chains, mad Ambition and his gold banished afar.
</p>
         <p>Wealth does not hold sway; sense-corrupting gifts
are of no avail; virtue alone can purchase power.
</p>
         <p>Brothers twain, with the heart of one, brothers to
whose rule fate has entrusted sea and land, if there
is aught that has escaped your grandsire's conquering
hand, aught your father has left unsubdued, even
now Vulcan prepares the arms for their subjection
and Cyclops labours on the Sicilian anvil. Brontes
carves countless figures on the shield, Steropes hastes
to bend the lofty peak of the flashing helmet, Pyragmon
knits the coat of mail, smoky Lipare roars
throughout its fire-belching caves. 'Tis for you that
Neptune pastures in the sea-weed meadows of the
Ionian main green sea-horses who can fly o'er the
surface of the blue waters with so light a step that
their hoofs are unflecked with foam, and course o'er
fields of corn so delicately that the ears do not bend
beneath their weight. E'en now I see the sack of
Babylon and the Parthian driven to flight that is not
feigned, Bactria subjected to the Law, the fearful
pallor of the Ganges' servile banks, the humbled Persian
throwing off his gem-encrusted robes. Mount
to Tanais' source, explore the frozen North, traverse
sun-scorched Libya, o'ercome the fires of Titan and
surprise Nile's hidden spring; pass the Pillars of
Hercules, the bourne, too, whence Bacchus returned;
whatever heaven enfolds shall own your dominion.
</p>
         <p>To you the Red Sea shall give precious shells, India
her ivory, Panchaia perfumes, and China silk.
<pb id="v.1.p.287"/>
         </p>
                  </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>