<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.21/tei-epidoc.rng"
                         schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.21/tei-epidoc.rng"
                         schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
	           <title>Georgics</title>
	           <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	           <author n="Verg.">P. Vergilius Maro</author>
	           <editor role="editor" n="Greenough">J. B. Greenough</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
		          <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
		          <respStmt>
		             <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
		             <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
		             <name>William Merrill</name>
		             <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
		             <name>David Smith</name>
		          </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>about 147Kb</extent>
	        <publicationStmt>
		          <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
		          <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
		          <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
		       </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
	           <biblStruct>
	              <monogr>
	                 <author>Vergil</author>
	                 <title>Bucolics, Aeneid, and Georgics Of Vergil</title>
	                 <editor role="editor">J. B. Greenough</editor>
	                 <imprint>
	                    <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
	                    <publisher>Ginn &amp; Co.</publisher>
	                    <date>1900</date>
	                 </imprint>
	              </monogr>
	           </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
    
     <encodingDesc>
        <refsDecl n="NTS">
           <cRefPattern n="line" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']//tei:l[@n='$2'])">
              <p>This pointer pattern extracts book and line</p>
           </cRefPattern>
           <cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
              <p>This pointer pattern extracts book</p>
           </cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="card" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                <p>This pointer pattern extracts book and card</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                <p>This pointer pattern extracts book</p>
            </cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl n="TEI.2">
            <refState unit="book"/>
            <refState unit="card"/>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
    
     <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
           <language ident="eng">English</language>
        </langUsage>
     </profileDesc>
    
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2014-11-06" who="Thibault Clerice">Moving to Epidoc with new URN</change>
         <change when="2010-07-01" who="student">fixed place tags - zr</change>
         <change when="2009-12-09" who="rsingh04">moved more xml files around based on copyright status</change>
         <change when="2009-06-19" who="rsingh04">removed place name references to Neath</change>
         <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
         <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
         <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
         <change when="2004-04-02" who="mimno">added line 1 cards</change>
         <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
         <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
         <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Changed line tags to handle verse translation.</change>
         <change when="1999-08-04" who="textgod">Added ED=p to cards.</change>
         <change when="1997-09-24" who="textgod">Changed names and redid headers.</change>
         <change when="1997-07-01" who="WM">Lined up chunks of text with latin</change>
         <change when="1996-10-24" who="WM">Mark up public domain text downloaded from vatech; needs line nos.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0690.phi002.perseus-eng2">
         <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="1">
               <l n="1">What makes the cornfield smile; beneath what star</l>
               <l n="2">Maecenas, it is meet to turn the sod</l>
               <l n="3">Or marry elm with vine; how tend the steer;</l>
               <l n="4">What pains for cattle-keeping, or what proof</l>
               <l n="5">Of patient trial serves for thrifty bees;—</l>
               <l n="6">Such are my themes. O universal lights</l>
               <l n="7">Most glorious! ye that lead the gliding year</l>
               <l n="8">Along the sky, Liber and Ceres mild,</l>
               <l n="9">If by your bounty holpen earth once changed</l>
               <l n="10">Chaonian acorn for the plump wheat-ear,</l>
               <l n="11">And mingled with the grape, your new-found gift,</l>
               <l n="12">The draughts of Achelous; and ye Fauns</l>
               <l n="13">To rustics ever kind, come foot it, Fauns</l>
               <l n="14">And Dryad-maids together; your gifts I sing.</l>
               <l n="15">And thou, for whose delight the war-horse first</l>
               <l n="16">Sprang from earth's womb at thy great trident's stroke,</l>
               <l n="17">Neptune; and haunter of the groves, for whom</l>
               <l n="18">Three hundred snow-white heifers browse the brakes,</l>
               <l n="19">The fertile brakes of <placeName key="tgn,7010867">Ceos</placeName>; and clothed in power,</l>
               <l n="20">Thy native forest and Lycean lawns,</l>
               <l n="21">Pan, shepherd-god, forsaking, as the love</l>
               <l n="22">Of thine own Maenalus constrains thee, hear</l>
               <l n="23">And help, O lord of <placeName key="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName>! And thou, too,</l>
               <l n="24">Minerva, from whose hand the olive sprung;</l>
               <l n="25">And boy-discoverer of the curved plough;</l>
               <l n="26">And, bearing a young cypress root-uptorn,</l>
               <l n="27">Silvanus, and Gods all and Goddesses,</l>
               <l n="28">Who make the fields your care, both ye who nurse</l>
               <l n="29">The tender unsown increase, and from heaven</l>
               <l n="30">Shed on man's sowing the riches of your rain:</l>
               <l n="31">And thou, even thou, of whom we know not yet</l>
               <l n="32">What mansion of the skies shall hold thee soon,</l>
               <l n="33">Whether to watch o'er cities be thy will,</l>
               <l n="34">Great Caesar, and to take the earth in charge,</l>
               <l n="35">That so the mighty world may welcome thee</l>
               <l n="36">Lord of her increase, master of her times,</l>
               <l n="37">Binding thy mother's myrtle round thy brow,</l>
               <l n="38">Or as the boundless ocean's God thou come,</l>
               <l n="39">Sole dread of seamen, till far <placeName key="tgn,1016579">Thule</placeName> bow</l>
               <l n="40">Before thee, and Tethys win thee to her son</l>
               <l n="41">With all her waves for dower; or as a star</l>
               <l n="42">Lend thy fresh beams our lagging months to cheer,</l>
               <l n="43">Where 'twixt the Maid and those pursuing Claws</l>
               <l n="44">A space is opening; see! red Scorpio's self</l>
               <l n="45">His arms draws in, yea, and hath left thee more</l>
               <l n="46">Than thy full meed of heaven: be what thou wilt—</l>
               <l n="47">For neither Tartarus hopes to call thee king,</l>
               <l n="48">Nor may so dire a lust of sovereignty</l>
               <l n="49">E'er light upon thee, howso <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> admire</l>
               <l n="50">Elysium's fields, and Proserpine not heed</l>
               <l n="51">Her mother's voice entreating to return—</l>
               <l n="52">Vouchsafe a prosperous voyage, and smile on this</l>
               <l n="53">My bold endeavour, and pitying, even as I,</l>
               <l n="54">These poor way-wildered swains, at once begin,</l>
               <l n="55">Grow timely used unto the voice of prayer.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="43">
               <l n="56">In early spring-tide, when the icy drip</l>
               <l n="57">Melts from the mountains hoar, and Zephyr's breath</l>
               <l n="58">Unbinds the crumbling clod, even then 'tis time;</l>
               <l n="59">Press deep your plough behind the groaning ox,</l>
               <l n="60">And teach the furrow-burnished share to shine.</l>
               <l n="61">That land the craving farmer's prayer fulfils,</l>
               <l n="62">Which twice the sunshine, twice the frost has felt;</l>
               <l n="63">Ay, that's the land whose boundless harvest-crops</l>
               <l n="64">Burst, see! the barns. But ere our metal cleave</l>
               <l n="65">An unknown surface, heed we to forelearn</l>
               <l n="66">The winds and varying temper of the sky,</l>
               <l n="67">The lineal tilth and habits of the spot,</l>
               <l n="68">What every region yields, and what denies.</l>
               <l n="69">Here blithelier springs the corn, and here the grape,</l>
               <l n="70">There earth is green with tender growth of trees</l>
               <l n="71">And grass unbidden. See how from Tmolus comes</l>
               <l n="72">The saffron's fragrance, ivory from Ind,</l>
               <l n="73">From <placeName key="tgn,7016796">Saba</placeName>'s weakling sons their frankincense,</l>
               <l n="74">Iron from the naked Chalybs, castor rank</l>
               <l n="75">From <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>, from <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName> the prize-palms</l>
               <l n="76">O' the mares of <placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>. Such the eternal bond</l>
               <l n="77">And such the laws by Nature's hand imposed</l>
               <l n="78">On clime and clime, e'er since the primal dawn</l>
               <l n="79">When old Deucalion on the unpeopled earth</l>
               <l n="80">Cast stones, whence men, a flinty race, were reared.</l>
               <l n="81">Up then! if fat the soil, let sturdy bulls</l>
               <l n="82">Upturn it from the year's first opening months,</l>
               <l n="83">And let the clods lie bare till baked to dust</l>
               <l n="84">By the ripe suns of summer; but if the earth</l>
               <l n="85">Less fruitful just ere Arcturus rise</l>
               <l n="86">With shallower trench uptilt it—'twill suffice;</l>
               <l n="87">There, lest weeds choke the crop's luxuriance, here,</l>
               <l n="88">Lest the scant moisture fail the barren sand.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="71">
               <l n="89">Then thou shalt suffer in alternate years</l>
               <l n="90">The new-reaped fields to rest, and on the plain</l>
               <l n="91">A crust of sloth to harden; or, when stars</l>
               <l n="92">Are changed in heaven, there sow the golden grain</l>
               <l n="93">Where erst, luxuriant with its quivering pod,</l>
               <l n="94">Pulse, or the slender vetch-crop, thou hast cleared,</l>
               <l n="95">And lupin sour, whose brittle stalks arise,</l>
               <l n="96">A hurtling forest. For the plain is parched</l>
               <l n="97">By flax-crop, parched by oats, by poppies parched</l>
               <l n="98">In Lethe-slumber drenched. Nathless by change</l>
               <l n="99">The travailing earth is lightened, but stint not</l>
               <l n="100">With refuse rich to soak the thirsty soil,</l>
               <l n="101">And shower foul ashes o'er the exhausted fields.</l>
               <l n="102">Thus by rotation like repose is gained,</l>
               <l n="103">Nor earth meanwhile uneared and thankless left.</l>
               <l n="104">Oft, too, 'twill boot to fire the naked fields,</l>
               <l n="105">And the light stubble burn with crackling flames;</l>
               <l n="106">Whether that earth therefrom some hidden strength</l>
               <l n="107">And fattening food derives, or that the fire</l>
               <l n="108">Bakes every blemish out, and sweats away</l>
               <l n="109">Each useless humour, or that the heat unlocks</l>
               <l n="110">New passages and secret pores, whereby</l>
               <l n="111">Their life-juice to the tender blades may win;</l>
               <l n="112">Or that it hardens more and helps to bind</l>
               <l n="113">The gaping veins, lest penetrating showers,</l>
               <l n="114">Or fierce sun's ravening might, or searching blast</l>
               <l n="115">Of the keen north should sear them. Well, I wot,</l>
               <l n="116">He serves the fields who with his harrow breaks</l>
               <l n="117">The sluggish clods, and hurdles osier-twined</l>
               <l n="118">Hales o'er them; from the far Olympian height</l>
               <l n="119">Him golden Ceres not in vain regards;</l>
               <l n="120">And he, who having ploughed the fallow plain</l>
               <l n="121">And heaved its furrowy ridges, turns once more</l>
               <l n="122">Cross-wise his shattering share, with stroke on stroke</l>
               <l n="123">The earth assails, and makes the field his thrall.</l>
               <l n="124"> Pray for wet summers and for winters fine,</l>
               <l n="125">Ye husbandmen; in winter's dust the crops</l>
               <l n="126">Exceedingly rejoice, the field hath joy;</l>
               <l n="127">No tilth makes <placeName key="tgn,7016748">Mysia</placeName> lift her head so high,</l>
               <l n="128">Nor Gargarus his own harvests so admire.</l>
               <l n="129">Why tell of him, who, having launched his seed,</l>
               <l n="130">Sets on for close encounter, and rakes smooth</l>
               <l n="131">The dry dust hillocks, then on the tender corn</l>
               <l n="132">Lets in the flood, whose waters follow fain;</l>
               <l n="133">And when the parched field quivers, and all the blades</l>
               <l n="134">Are dying, from the brow of its hill-bed,</l>
               <l n="135">See! see! he lures the runnel; down it falls,</l>
               <l n="136">Waking hoarse murmurs o'er the polished stones,</l>
               <l n="137">And with its bubblings slakes the thirsty fields?</l>
               <l n="138">Or why of him, who lest the heavy ears</l>
               <l n="139">O'erweigh the stalk, while yet in tender blade</l>
               <l n="140">Feeds down the crop's luxuriance, when its growth</l>
               <l n="141">First tops the furrows? Why of him who drains</l>
               <l n="142">The marsh-land's gathered ooze through soaking sand,</l>
               <l n="143">Chiefly what time in treacherous moons a stream</l>
               <l n="144">Goes out in spate, and with its coat of slime</l>
               <l n="145">Holds all the country, whence the hollow dykes</l>
               <l n="146">Sweat steaming vapour?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="118">
               <l n="147">But no whit the more</l>
               <l n="148">For all expedients tried and travail borne</l>
               <l n="149">By man and beast in turning oft the soil,</l>
               <l n="150">Do greedy goose and Strymon-haunting cranes</l>
               <l n="151">And succory's bitter fibres cease to harm,</l>
               <l n="152">Or shade not injure. The great Sire himself</l>
               <l n="153">No easy road to husbandry assigned,</l>
               <l n="154">And first was he by human skill to rouse</l>
               <l n="155">The slumbering glebe, whetting the minds of men</l>
               <l n="156">With care on care, nor suffering realm of his</l>
               <l n="157">In drowsy sloth to stagnate. Before Jove</l>
               <l n="158">Fields knew no taming hand of husbandmen;</l>
               <l n="159">To mark the plain or mete with boundary-line—</l>
               <l n="160">Even this was impious; for the common stock</l>
               <l n="161">They gathered, and the earth of her own will</l>
               <l n="162">All things more freely, no man bidding, bore.</l>
               <l n="163">He to black serpents gave their venom-bane,</l>
               <l n="164">And bade the wolf go prowl, and ocean toss;</l>
               <l n="165">Shooed from the leaves their honey, put fire away,</l>
               <l n="166">And curbed the random rivers running wine,</l>
               <l n="167">That use by gradual dint of thought on thought</l>
               <l n="168">Might forge the various arts, with furrow's help</l>
               <l n="169">The corn-blade win, and strike out hidden fire</l>
               <l n="170">From the flint's heart. Then first the streams were ware</l>
               <l n="171">Of hollowed alder-hulls: the sailor then</l>
               <l n="172">Their names and numbers gave to star and star,</l>
               <l n="173">Pleiads and Hyads, and Lycaon's child</l>
               <l n="174">Bright Arctos; how with nooses then was found</l>
               <l n="175">To catch wild beasts, and cozen them with lime,</l>
               <l n="176">And hem with hounds the mighty forest-glades.</l>
               <l n="177">Soon one with hand-net scourges the broad stream,</l>
               <l n="178">Probing its depths, one drags his dripping toils</l>
               <l n="179">Along the main; then iron's unbending might,</l>
               <l n="180">And shrieking saw-blade,—for the men of old</l>
               <l n="181">With wedges wont to cleave the splintering log;—</l>
               <l n="182">Then divers arts arose; toil conquered all,</l>
               <l n="183">Remorseless toil, and poverty's shrewd push</l>
               <l n="184">In times of hardship. Ceres was the first</l>
               <l n="185">Set mortals on with tools to turn the sod,</l>
               <l n="186">When now the awful groves 'gan fail to bear</l>
               <l n="187">Acorns and arbutes, and her wonted food</l>
               <l n="188">
                  <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> gave no more. Soon, too, the corn</l>
               <l n="189">Gat sorrow's increase, that an evil blight</l>
               <l n="190">Ate up the stalks, and thistle reared his spines</l>
               <l n="191">An idler in the fields; the crops die down;</l>
               <l n="192">Upsprings instead a shaggy growth of burrs</l>
               <l n="193">And caltrops; and amid the corn-fields trim</l>
               <l n="194">Unfruitful darnel and wild oats have sway.</l>
               <l n="195">Wherefore, unless thou shalt with ceaseless rake</l>
               <l n="196">The weeds pursue, with shouting scare the birds,</l>
               <l n="197">Prune with thy hook the dark field's matted shade,</l>
               <l n="198">Pray down the showers, all vainly thou shalt eye,</l>
               <l n="199">Alack! thy neighbour's heaped-up harvest-mow,</l>
               <l n="200">And in the greenwood from a shaken oak</l>
               <l n="201">Seek solace for thine hunger.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="160">
               <l n="202">Now to tell</l>
               <l n="203">The sturdy rustics' weapons, what they are,</l>
               <l n="204">Without which, neither can be sown nor reared</l>
               <l n="205">The fruits of harvest; first the bent plough's share</l>
               <l n="206">And heavy timber, and slow-lumbering wains</l>
               <l n="207">Of the Eleusinian mother, threshing-sleighs</l>
               <l n="208">And drags, and harrows with their crushing weight;</l>
               <l n="209">Then the cheap wicker-ware of Celeus old,</l>
               <l n="210">Hurdles of arbute, and thy mystic fan,</l>
               <l n="211">Iacchus; which, full tale, long ere the time</l>
               <l n="212">Thou must with heed lay by, if thee await</l>
               <l n="213">Not all unearned the country's crown divine.</l>
               <l n="214">While yet within the woods, the elm is tamed</l>
               <l n="215">And bowed with mighty force to form the stock,</l>
               <l n="216">And take the plough's curved shape, then nigh the root</l>
               <l n="217">A pole eight feet projecting, earth-boards twain,</l>
               <l n="218">And share-beam with its double back they fix.</l>
               <l n="219">For yoke is early hewn a linden light,</l>
               <l n="220">And a tall beech for handle, from behind</l>
               <l n="221">To turn the car at lowest: then o'er the hearth</l>
               <l n="222">The wood they hang till the smoke knows it well.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="176">
               <l n="223">Many the precepts of the men of old</l>
               <l n="224">I can recount thee, so thou start not back,</l>
               <l n="225">And such slight cares to learn not weary thee.</l>
               <l n="226">And this among the first: thy threshing-floor</l>
               <l n="227">With ponderous roller must be levelled smooth,</l>
               <l n="228">And wrought by hand, and fixed with binding chalk,</l>
               <l n="229">Lest weeds arise, or dust a passage win</l>
               <l n="230">Splitting the surface, then a thousand plagues</l>
               <l n="231">Make sport of it: oft builds the tiny mouse</l>
               <l n="232">Her home, and plants her granary, underground,</l>
               <l n="233">Or burrow for their bed the purblind moles,</l>
               <l n="234">Or toad is found in hollows, and all the swarm</l>
               <l n="235">Of earth's unsightly creatures; or a huge</l>
               <l n="236">Corn-heap the weevil plunders, and the ant,</l>
               <l n="237">Fearful of coming age and penury.</l>
               <l n="238">Mark too, what time the walnut in the woods</l>
               <l n="239">With ample bloom shall clothe her, and bow down</l>
               <l n="240">Her odorous branches, if the fruit prevail,</l>
               <l n="241">Like store of grain will follow, and there shall come</l>
               <l n="242">A mighty winnowing-time with mighty heat;</l>
               <l n="243">But if the shade with wealth of leaves abound,</l>
               <l n="244">Vainly your threshing-floor will bruise the stalks</l>
               <l n="245">Rich but in chaff. Many myself have seen</l>
               <l n="246">Steep, as they sow, their pulse-seeds, drenching them</l>
               <l n="247">With nitre and black oil-lees, that the fruit</l>
               <l n="248">Might swell within the treacherous pods, and they</l>
               <l n="249">Make speed to boil at howso small a fire.</l>
               <l n="250">Yet, culled with caution, proved with patient toil,</l>
               <l n="251">These have I seen degenerate, did not man</l>
               <l n="252">Put forth his hand with power, and year by year</l>
               <l n="253">Choose out the largest. So, by fate impelled,</l>
               <l n="254">Speed all things to the worse, and backward borne</l>
               <l n="255">Glide from us; even as who with struggling oars</l>
               <l n="256">Up stream scarce pulls a shallop, if he chance</l>
               <l n="257">His arms to slacken, lo! with headlong force</l>
               <l n="258">The current sweeps him down the hurrying tide.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="204">
               <l n="259">Us too behoves Arcturus' sign observe,</l>
               <l n="260">And the Kids' seasons and the shining Snake,</l>
               <l n="261">No less than those who o'er the windy main</l>
               <l n="262">Borne homeward tempt the Pontic, and the jaws</l>
               <l n="263">Of oyster-rife <placeName key="perseus,Abydos,Mysia">Abydos</placeName>. When the Scales</l>
               <l n="264">Now poising fair the hours of sleep and day</l>
               <l n="265">Give half the world to sunshine, half to shade,</l>
               <l n="266">Then urge your bulls, my masters; sow the plain</l>
               <l n="267">Even to the verge of tameless winter's showers</l>
               <l n="268">With barley: then, too, time it is to hide</l>
               <l n="269">Your flax in earth, and poppy, Ceres' joy,</l>
               <l n="270">Aye, more than time to bend above the plough,</l>
               <l n="271">While earth, yet dry, forbids not, and the clouds</l>
               <l n="272">Are buoyant. With the spring comes bean-sowing;</l>
               <l n="273">Thee, too, Lucerne, the crumbling furrows then</l>
               <l n="274">Receive, and millet's annual care returns,</l>
               <l n="275">What time the white bull with his gilded horns</l>
               <l n="276">Opens the year, before whose threatening front,</l>
               <l n="277">Routed the dog-star sinks. But if it be</l>
               <l n="278">For wheaten harvest and the hardy spelt,</l>
               <l n="279">Thou tax the soil, to corn-ears wholly given,</l>
               <l n="280">Let Atlas' daughters hide them in the dawn,</l>
               <l n="281">The Cretan star, a crown of fire, depart,</l>
               <l n="282">Or e'er the furrow's claim of seed thou quit,</l>
               <l n="283">Or haste thee to entrust the whole year's hope</l>
               <l n="284">To earth that would not. Many have begun</l>
               <l n="285">Ere Maia's star be setting; these, I trow,</l>
               <l n="286">Their looked-for harvest fools with empty ears.</l>
               <l n="287">But if the vetch and common kidney-bean</l>
               <l n="288">Thou'rt fain to sow, nor scorn to make thy care</l>
               <l n="289">Pelusiac lentil, no uncertain sign</l>
               <l n="290">Bootes' fall will send thee; then begin,</l>
               <l n="291">Pursue thy sowing till half the frosts be done.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="231">
               <l n="292">Therefore it is the golden sun, his course</l>
               <l n="293">Into fixed parts dividing, rules his way</l>
               <l n="294">Through the twelve constellations of the world.</l>
               <l n="295">Five zones the heavens contain; whereof is one</l>
               <l n="296">Aye red with flashing sunlight, fervent aye</l>
               <l n="297">From fire; on either side to left and right</l>
               <l n="298">Are traced the utmost twain, stiff with blue ice,</l>
               <l n="299">And black with scowling storm-clouds, and betwixt</l>
               <l n="300">These and the midmost, other twain there lie,</l>
               <l n="301">By the Gods' grace to heart-sick mortals given,</l>
               <l n="302">And a path cleft between them, where might wheel</l>
               <l n="303">On sloping plane the system of the Signs.</l>
               <l n="304">And as toward <placeName key="tgn,6005315">Scythia</placeName> and Rhipaean heights</l>
               <l n="305">The world mounts upward, likewise sinks it down</l>
               <l n="306">Toward <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName> and the south, this pole of ours</l>
               <l n="307">Still towering high, that other, 'neath their feet,</l>
               <l n="308">By dark Styx frowned on, and the abysmal shades.</l>
               <l n="309">Here glides the huge Snake forth with sinuous coils</l>
               <l n="310">'Twixt the two Bears and round them river-wise—</l>
               <l n="311">The Bears that fear 'neath Ocean's brim to dip.</l>
               <l n="312">There either, say they, reigns the eternal hush</l>
               <l n="313">Of night that knows no seasons, her black pall</l>
               <l n="314">Thick-mantling fold on fold; or thitherward</l>
               <l n="315">From us returning Dawn brings back the day;</l>
               <l n="316">And when the first breath of his panting steeds</l>
               <l n="317">On us the Orient flings, that hour with them</l>
               <l n="318">Red Vesper 'gins to trim his 'lated fires.</l>
               <l n="319">Hence under doubtful skies forebode we can</l>
               <l n="320">The coming tempests, hence both harvest-day</l>
               <l n="321">And seed-time, when to smite the treacherous main</l>
               <l n="322">With driving oars, when launch the fair-rigged fleet,</l>
               <l n="323">Or in ripe hour to fell the forest-pine.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="257">
               <l n="324">Hence, too, not idly do we watch the stars—</l>
               <l n="325">Their rising and their setting-and the year,</l>
               <l n="326">Four varying seasons to one law conformed.</l>
               <l n="327">If chilly showers e'er shut the farmer's door,</l>
               <l n="328">Much that had soon with sunshine cried for haste,</l>
               <l n="329">He may forestall; the ploughman batters keen</l>
               <l n="330">His blunted share's hard tooth, scoops from a tree</l>
               <l n="331">His troughs, or on the cattle stamps a brand,</l>
               <l n="332">Or numbers on the corn-heaps; some make sharp</l>
               <l n="333">The stakes and two-pronged forks, and willow-bands</l>
               <l n="334">Amerian for the bending vine prepare.</l>
               <l n="335">Now let the pliant basket plaited be</l>
               <l n="336">Of bramble-twigs; now set your corn to parch</l>
               <l n="337">Before the fire; now bruise it with the stone.</l>
               <l n="338">Nay even on holy days some tasks to ply</l>
               <l n="339">Is right and lawful: this no ban forbids,</l>
               <l n="340">To turn the runnel's course, fence corn-fields in,</l>
               <l n="341">Make springes for the birds, burn up the briars,</l>
               <l n="342">And plunge in wholesome stream the bleating flock.</l>
               <l n="343">Oft too with oil or apples plenty-cheap</l>
               <l n="344">The creeping ass's ribs his driver packs,</l>
               <l n="345">And home from town returning brings instead</l>
               <l n="346">A dented mill-stone or black lump of pitch.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="276">
               <l n="347">The moon herself in various rank assigns</l>
               <l n="348">The days for labour lucky: fly the fifth;</l>
               <l n="349">Then sprang pale Orcus and the Eumenides;</l>
               <l n="350">Earth then in awful labour brought to light</l>
               <l n="351">Coeus, Iapetus, and Typhoeus fell,</l>
               <l n="352">And those sworn brethren banded to break down</l>
               <l n="353">The gates of heaven; thrice, sooth to say, they strove</l>
               <l n="354">Ossa on <placeName key="tgn,4008379">Pelion</placeName>'s top to heave and heap,</l>
               <l n="355">Aye, and on Ossa to up-roll amain</l>
               <l n="356">Leafy <placeName key="perseus,Olympos,Lycia">Olympus</placeName>; thrice with thunderbolt</l>
               <l n="357">Their mountain-stair the Sire asunder smote.</l>
               <l n="358">Seventh after tenth is lucky both to set</l>
               <l n="359">The vine in earth, and take and tame the steer,</l>
               <l n="360">And fix the leashes to the warp; the ninth</l>
               <l n="361">To runagates is kinder, cross to thieves.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="287">
               <l n="362">Many the tasks that lightlier lend themselves</l>
               <l n="363">In chilly night, or when the sun is young,</l>
               <l n="364">And Dawn bedews the world. By night 'tis best</l>
               <l n="365">To reap light stubble, and parched fields by night;</l>
               <l n="366">For nights the suppling moisture never fails.</l>
               <l n="367">And one will sit the long late watches out</l>
               <l n="368">By winter fire-light, shaping with keen blade</l>
               <l n="369">The torches to a point; his wife the while,</l>
               <l n="370">Her tedious labour soothing with a song,</l>
               <l n="371">Speeds the shrill comb along the warp, or else</l>
               <l n="372">With Vulcan's aid boils the sweet must-juice down,</l>
               <l n="373">And skims with leaves the quivering cauldron's wave.</l>
               <l n="374">But ruddy Ceres in mid heat is mown,</l>
               <l n="375">And in mid heat the parched ears are bruised</l>
               <l n="376">Upon the floor; to plough strip, strip to sow;</l>
               <l n="377">Winter's the lazy time for husbandmen.</l>
               <l n="378">In the cold season farmers wont to taste</l>
               <l n="379">The increase of their toil, and yield themselves</l>
               <l n="380">To mutual interchange of festal cheer.</l>
               <l n="381">Boon winter bids them, and unbinds their cares,</l>
               <l n="382">As laden keels, when now the port they touch,</l>
               <l n="383">And happy sailors crown the sterns with flowers.</l>
               <l n="384">Nathless then also time it is to strip</l>
               <l n="385">Acorns from oaks, and berries from the bay,</l>
               <l n="386">Olives, and bleeding myrtles, then to set</l>
               <l n="387">Snares for the crane, and meshes for the stag,</l>
               <l n="388">And hunt the long-eared hares, then pierce the doe</l>
               <l n="389">With whirl of hempen-thonged Balearic sling,</l>
               <l n="390">While snow lies deep, and streams are drifting ice.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="311">
               <l n="391">What need to tell of autumn's storms and stars,</l>
               <l n="392">And wherefore men must watch, when now the day</l>
               <l n="393">Grows shorter, and more soft the summer's heat?</l>
               <l n="394">When Spring the rain-bringer comes rushing down,</l>
               <l n="395">Or when the beards of harvest on the plain</l>
               <l n="396">Bristle already, and the milky corn</l>
               <l n="397">On its green stalk is swelling? Many a time,</l>
               <l n="398">When now the farmer to his yellow fields</l>
               <l n="399">The reaping-hind came bringing, even in act</l>
               <l n="400">To lop the brittle barley stems, have I</l>
               <l n="401">Seen all the windy legions clash in war</l>
               <l n="402">Together, as to rend up far and wide</l>
               <l n="403">The heavy corn-crop from its lowest roots,</l>
               <l n="404">And toss it skyward: so might winter's flaw,</l>
               <l n="405">Dark-eddying, whirl light stalks and flying straws.</l>
               <l n="406">Oft too comes looming vast along the sky</l>
               <l n="407">A march of waters; mustering from above,</l>
               <l n="408">The clouds roll up the tempest, heaped and grim</l>
               <l n="409">With angry showers: down falls the height of heaven,</l>
               <l n="410">And with a great rain floods the smiling crops,</l>
               <l n="411">The oxen's labour: now the dikes fill fast,</l>
               <l n="412">And the void river-beds swell thunderously,</l>
               <l n="413">And all the panting firths of Ocean boil.</l>
               <l n="414">The Sire himself in midnight of the clouds</l>
               <l n="415">Wields with red hand the levin; through all her bulk</l>
               <l n="416">Earth at the hurly quakes; the beasts are fled,</l>
               <l n="417">And mortal hearts of every kindred sunk</l>
               <l n="418">In cowering terror; he with flaming brand</l>
               <l n="419">
                  <placeName key="tgn,7002722">Athos</placeName>, or Rhodope, or Ceraunian crags</l>
               <l n="420">Precipitates: then doubly raves the South</l>
               <l n="421">With shower on blinding shower, and woods and coasts</l>
               <l n="422">Wail fitfully beneath the mighty blast.</l>
               <l n="423">This fearing, mark the months and Signs of heaven,</l>
               <l n="424">Whither retires him Saturn's icy star,</l>
               <l n="425">And through what heavenly cycles wandereth</l>
               <l n="426">The glowing orb Cyllenian. Before all</l>
               <l n="427">Worship the Gods, and to great Ceres pay</l>
               <l n="428">Her yearly dues upon the happy sward</l>
               <l n="429">With sacrifice, anigh the utmost end</l>
               <l n="430">Of winter, and when Spring begins to smile.</l>
               <l n="431">Then lambs are fat, and wines are mellowest then;</l>
               <l n="432">Then sleep is sweet, and dark the shadows fall</l>
               <l n="433">Upon the mountains. Let your rustic youth</l>
               <l n="434">To Ceres do obeisance, one and all;</l>
               <l n="435">And for her pleasure thou mix honeycombs</l>
               <l n="436">With milk and the ripe wine-god; thrice for luck</l>
               <l n="437">Around the young corn let the victim go,</l>
               <l n="438">And all the choir, a joyful company,</l>
               <l n="439">Attend it, and with shouts bid Ceres come</l>
               <l n="440">To be their house-mate; and let no man dare</l>
               <l n="441">Put sickle to the ripened ears until,</l>
               <l n="442">With woven oak his temples chapleted,</l>
               <l n="443">He foot the rugged dance and chant the lay.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="351">
               <l n="444">Aye, and that these things we might win to know</l>
               <l n="445">By certain tokens, heats, and showers, and winds</l>
               <l n="446">That bring the frost, the Sire of all himself</l>
               <l n="447">Ordained what warnings in her monthly round</l>
               <l n="448">The moon should give, what bodes the south wind's fall,</l>
               <l n="449">What oft-repeated sights the herdsman seeing</l>
               <l n="450">Should keep his cattle closer to their stalls.</l>
               <l n="451">No sooner are the winds at point to rise,</l>
               <l n="452">Than either Ocean's firths begin to toss</l>
               <l n="453">And swell, and a dry crackling sound is heard</l>
               <l n="454">Upon the heights, or one loud ferment booms</l>
               <l n="455">The beach afar, and through the forest goes</l>
               <l n="456">A murmur multitudinous. By this</l>
               <l n="457">Scarce can the billow spare the curved keels,</l>
               <l n="458">When swift the sea-gulls from the middle main</l>
               <l n="459">Come winging, and their shrieks are shoreward borne,</l>
               <l n="460">When ocean-loving cormorants on dry land</l>
               <l n="461">Besport them, and the hern, her marshy haunts</l>
               <l n="462">Forsaking, mounts above the soaring cloud.</l>
               <l n="463">Oft, too, when wind is toward, the stars thou'lt see</l>
               <l n="464">From heaven shoot headlong, and through murky night</l>
               <l n="465">Long trails of fire white-glistening in their wake,</l>
               <l n="466">Or light chaff flit in air with fallen leaves,</l>
               <l n="467">Or feathers on the wave-top float and play.</l>
               <l n="468">But when from regions of the furious North</l>
               <l n="469">It lightens, and when thunder fills the halls</l>
               <l n="470">Of Eurus and of Zephyr, all the fields</l>
               <l n="471">With brimming dikes are flooded, and at sea</l>
               <l n="472">No mariner but furls his dripping sails.</l>
               <l n="473">Never at unawares did shower annoy:</l>
               <l n="474">Or, as it rises, the high-soaring cranes</l>
               <l n="475">Flee to the vales before it, with face</l>
               <l n="476">Upturned to heaven, the heifer snuffs the gale</l>
               <l n="477">Through gaping nostrils, or about the meres</l>
               <l n="478">Shrill-twittering flits the swallow, and the frogs</l>
               <l n="479">Crouch in the mud and chant their dirge of old.</l>
               <l n="480">Oft, too, the ant from out her inmost cells,</l>
               <l n="481">Fretting the narrow path, her eggs conveys;</l>
               <l n="482">Or the huge bow sucks moisture; or a host</l>
               <l n="483">Of rooks from food returning in long line</l>
               <l n="484">Clamour with jostling wings. Now mayst thou see</l>
               <l n="485">The various ocean-fowl and those that pry</l>
               <l n="486">Round Asian meads within thy fresher-pools,</l>
               <l n="487">Cayster, as in eager rivalry,</l>
               <l n="488">About their shoulders dash the plenteous spray,</l>
               <l n="489">Now duck their head beneath the wave, now run</l>
               <l n="490">Into the billows, for sheer idle joy</l>
               <l n="491">Of their mad bathing-revel. Then the crow</l>
               <l n="492">With full voice, good-for-naught, inviting rain,</l>
               <l n="493">Stalks on the dry sand mateless and alone.</l>
               <l n="494">Nor e'en the maids, that card their nightly task,</l>
               <l n="495">Know not the storm-sign, when in blazing crock</l>
               <l n="496">They see the lamp-oil sputtering with a growth</l>
               <l n="497">Of mouldy snuff-clots.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="393">
               <l n="498">So too, after rain,</l>
               <l n="499">Sunshine and open skies thou mayst forecast,</l>
               <l n="500">And learn by tokens sure, for then nor dimmed</l>
               <l n="501">Appear the stars' keen edges, nor the moon</l>
               <l n="502">As borrowing of her brother's beams to rise,</l>
               <l n="503">Nor fleecy films to float along the sky.</l>
               <l n="504">Not to the sun's warmth then upon the shore</l>
               <l n="505">Do halcyons dear to Thetis ope their wings,</l>
               <l n="506">Nor filthy swine take thought to toss on high</l>
               <l n="507">With scattering snout the straw-wisps. But the clouds</l>
               <l n="508">Seek more the vales, and rest upon the plain,</l>
               <l n="509">And from the roof-top the night-owl for naught</l>
               <l n="510">Watching the sunset plies her 'lated song.</l>
               <l n="511">Distinct in clearest air is Nisus seen</l>
               <l n="512">Towering, and Scylla for the purple lock</l>
               <l n="513">Pays dear; for whereso, as she flies, her wings</l>
               <l n="514">The light air winnow, lo! fierce, implacable,</l>
               <l n="515">Nisus with mighty whirr through heaven pursues;</l>
               <l n="516">Where Nisus heavenward soareth, there her wings</l>
               <l n="517">Clutch as she flies, the light air winnowing still.</l>
               <l n="518">Soft then the voice of rooks from indrawn throat</l>
               <l n="519">Thrice, four times, o'er repeated, and full oft</l>
               <l n="520">On their high cradles, by some hidden joy</l>
               <l n="521">Gladdened beyond their wont, in bustling throngs</l>
               <l n="522">Among the leaves they riot; so sweet it is,</l>
               <l n="523">When showers are spent, their own loved nests again</l>
               <l n="524">And tender brood to visit. Not, I deem,</l>
               <l n="525">That heaven some native wit to these assigned,</l>
               <l n="526">Or fate a larger prescience, but that when</l>
               <l n="527">The storm and shifting moisture of the air</l>
               <l n="528">Have changed their courses, and the sky-god now,</l>
               <l n="529">Wet with the south-wind, thickens what was rare,</l>
               <l n="530">And what was gross releases, then, too, change</l>
               <l n="531">Their spirits' fleeting phases, and their breasts</l>
               <l n="532">Feel other motions now, than when the wind</l>
               <l n="533">Was driving up the cloud-rack. Hence proceeds</l>
               <l n="534">That blending of the feathered choirs afield,</l>
               <l n="535">The cattle's exultation, and the rooks'</l>
               <l n="536">Deep-throated triumph.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="424">
               <l n="537">But if the headlong sun</l>
               <l n="538">And moons in order following thou regard,</l>
               <l n="539">Ne'er will to-morrow's hour deceive thee, ne'er</l>
               <l n="540">Wilt thou be caught by guile of cloudless night.</l>
               <l n="541">When first the moon recalls her rallying fires,</l>
               <l n="542">If dark the air clipped by her crescent dim,</l>
               <l n="543">For folks afield and on the open sea</l>
               <l n="544">A mighty rain is brewing; but if her face</l>
               <l n="545">With maiden blush she mantle, 'twill be wind,</l>
               <l n="546">For wind turns Phoebe still to ruddier gold.</l>
               <l n="547">But if at her fourth rising, for 'tis that</l>
               <l n="548">Gives surest counsel, clear she ride thro' heaven</l>
               <l n="549">With horns unblunted, then shall that whole day,</l>
               <l n="550">And to the month's end those that spring from it,</l>
               <l n="551">Rainless and windless be, while safe ashore</l>
               <l n="552">Shall sailors pay their vows to Panope,</l>
               <l n="553">Glaucus, and Melicertes, Ino's child.</l>
               <l n="554">The sun too, both at rising, and when soon</l>
               <l n="555">He dives beneath the waves, shall yield thee signs;</l>
               <l n="556">For signs, none trustier, travel with the sun,</l>
               <l n="557">Both those which in their course with dawn he brings,</l>
               <l n="558">And those at star-rise. When his springing orb</l>
               <l n="559">With spots he pranketh, muffled in a cloud,</l>
               <l n="560">And shrinks mid-circle, then of showers beware;</l>
               <l n="561">For then the South comes driving from the deep,</l>
               <l n="562">To trees and crops and cattle bringing bane.</l>
               <l n="563">Or when at day-break through dark clouds his rays</l>
               <l n="564">Burst and are scattered, or when rising pale</l>
               <l n="565">Aurora quits Tithonus' saffron bed,</l>
               <l n="566">But sorry shelter then, alack I will yield</l>
               <l n="567">Vine-leaf to ripening grapes; so thick a hail</l>
               <l n="568">In spiky showers spins rattling on the roof.</l>
               <l n="569">And this yet more 'twill boot thee bear in mind,</l>
               <l n="570">When now, his course upon <placeName key="perseus,Olympos,Lycia">Olympus</placeName> run,</l>
               <l n="571">He draws to his decline: for oft we see</l>
               <l n="572">Upon the sun's own face strange colours stray;</l>
               <l n="573">Dark tells of rain, of east winds fiery-red;</l>
               <l n="574">If spots with ruddy fire begin to mix,</l>
               <l n="575">Then all the heavens convulsed in wrath thou'lt see—</l>
               <l n="576">Storm-clouds and wind together. Me that night</l>
               <l n="577">Let no man bid fare forth upon the deep,</l>
               <l n="578">Nor rend the rope from shore. But if, when both</l>
               <l n="579">He brings again and hides the day's return,</l>
               <l n="580">Clear-orbed he shineth,idly wilt thou dread</l>
               <l n="581">The storm-clouds, and beneath the lustral North</l>
               <l n="582">See the woods waving. What late eve in fine</l>
               <l n="583">Bears in her bosom, whence the wind that brings</l>
               <l n="584">Fair-weather-clouds, or what the rain South</l>
               <l n="585">Is meditating, tokens of all these</l>
               <l n="586">The sun will give thee. Who dare charge the sun</l>
               <l n="587">With leasing? He it is who warneth oft</l>
               <l n="588">Of hidden broils at hand and treachery,</l>
               <l n="589">And secret swelling of the waves of war.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="466">
               <l n="590">He too it was, when Caesar's light was quenched,</l>
               <l n="591">For <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> had pity, when his bright head he veiled</l>
               <l n="592">In iron-hued darkness, till a godless age</l>
               <l n="593">Trembled for night eternal; at that time</l>
               <l n="594">Howbeit earth also, and the ocean-plains,</l>
               <l n="595">And dogs obscene, and birds of evil bode</l>
               <l n="596">Gave tokens. Yea, how often have we seen</l>
               <l n="597">
                  <placeName key="tgn,7003867">Etna</placeName>, her furnace-walls asunder riven,</l>
               <l n="598">In billowy floods boil o'er the Cyclops' fields,</l>
               <l n="599">And roll down globes of fire and molten rocks!</l>
               <l n="600">A clash of arms through all the heaven was heard</l>
               <l n="601">By <placeName key="tgn,7000084">Germany</placeName>; strange heavings shook the Alps.</l>
               <l n="602">Yea, and by many through the breathless groves</l>
               <l n="603">A voice was heard with power, and wondrous-pale</l>
               <l n="604">Phantoms were seen upon the dusk of night,</l>
               <l n="605">And cattle spake, portentous! streams stand still,</l>
               <l n="606">And the earth yawns asunder, ivory weeps</l>
               <l n="607">For sorrow in the shrines, and bronzes sweat.</l>
               <l n="608">Up-twirling forests with his eddying tide,</l>
               <l n="609">Madly he bears them down, that lord of floods,</l>
               <l n="610">
                  <placeName key="tgn,7010018">Eridanus</placeName>, till through all the plain are swept</l>
               <l n="611">Beasts and their stalls together. At that time</l>
               <l n="612">In gloomy entrails ceased not to appear</l>
               <l n="613">Dark-threatening fibres, springs to trickle blood,</l>
               <l n="614">And high-built cities night-long to resound</l>
               <l n="615">With the wolves' howling. Never more than then</l>
               <l n="616">From skies all cloudless fell the thunderbolts,</l>
               <l n="617">Nor blazed so oft the comet's fire of bale.</l>
               <l n="618">Therefore a second time <placeName key="perseus,Philippi">Philippi</placeName> saw</l>
               <l n="619">The Roman hosts with kindred weapons rush</l>
               <l n="620">To battle, nor did the high gods deem it hard</l>
               <l n="621">That twice <placeName key="tgn,7002718">Emathia</placeName> and the wide champaign</l>
               <l n="622">Of <placeName key="tgn,7011635">Haemus</placeName> should be fattening with our blood.</l>
               <l n="623">Ay, and the time will come when there anigh,</l>
               <l n="624">Heaving the earth up with his curved plough,</l>
               <l n="625">Some swain will light on javelins by foul rust</l>
               <l n="626">Corroded, or with ponderous harrow strike</l>
               <l n="627">On empty helmets, while he gapes to see</l>
               <l n="628">Bones as of giants from the trench untombed.</l>
               <l n="629">Gods of my country, heroes of the soil,</l>
               <l n="630">And Romulus, and Mother Vesta, thou</l>
               <l n="631">Who Tuscan Tiber and Rome's Palatine</l>
               <l n="632">Preservest, this new champion at the least</l>
               <l n="633">Our fallen generation to repair</l>
               <l n="634">Forbid not. To the full and long ago</l>
               <l n="635">Our blood thy Trojan perjuries hath paid,</l>
               <l n="636">Laomedon. Long since the courts of heaven</l>
               <l n="637">Begrudge us thee, our Caesar, and complain</l>
               <l n="638">That thou regard'st the triumphs of mankind,</l>
               <l n="639">Here where the wrong is right, the right is wrong,</l>
               <l n="640">Where wars abound so many, and myriad-faced</l>
               <l n="641">Is crime; where no meet honour hath the plough;</l>
               <l n="642">The fields, their husbandmen led far away,</l>
               <l n="643">Rot in neglect, and curved pruning-hooks</l>
               <l n="644">Into the sword's stiff blade are fused and forged.</l>
               <l n="645">
                  <placeName key="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName> here, here <placeName key="tgn,7000084">Germany</placeName> new strife</l>
               <l n="646">Is stirring; neighbouring cities are in arms,</l>
               <l n="647">The laws that bound them snapped; and godless war</l>
               <l n="648">Rages through all the universe; as when</l>
               <l n="649">The four-horse chariots from the barriers poured</l>
               <l n="650">Still quicken o'er the course, and, idly now</l>
               <l n="651">Grasping the reins, the driver by his team</l>
               <l n="652">Is onward borne, nor heeds the car his curb.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="1">
               <l n="1">Thus far the tilth of fields and stars of heaven;</l>
               <l n="2">Now will I sing thee, Bacchus, and, with thee,</l>
               <l n="3">The forest's young plantations and the fruit</l>
               <l n="4">Of slow-maturing olive. Hither haste,</l>
               <l n="5">O Father of the wine-press; all things here</l>
               <l n="6">Teem with the bounties of thy hand; for thee</l>
               <l n="7">With viny autumn laden blooms the field,</l>
               <l n="8">And foams the vintage high with brimming vats;</l>
               <l n="9">Hither, O Father of the wine-press, come,</l>
               <l n="10">And stripped of buskin stain thy bared limbs</l>
               <l n="11">In the new must with me.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="9">
               <l n="12">First, nature's law</l>
               <l n="13">For generating trees is manifold;</l>
               <l n="14">For some of their own force spontaneous spring,</l>
               <l n="15">No hand of man compelling, and possess</l>
               <l n="16">The plains and river-windings far and wide,</l>
               <l n="17">As pliant osier and the bending broom,</l>
               <l n="18">Poplar, and willows in wan companies</l>
               <l n="19">With green leaf glimmering gray; and some there be</l>
               <l n="20">From chance-dropped seed that rear them, as the tall</l>
               <l n="21">Chestnuts, and, mightiest of the branching wood,</l>
               <l n="22">Jove's Aesculus, and oaks, oracular</l>
               <l n="23">Deemed by the Greeks of old. With some sprouts forth</l>
               <l n="24">A forest of dense suckers from the root,</l>
               <l n="25">As elms and cherries; so, too, a pigmy plant,</l>
               <l n="26">Beneath its mother's mighty shade upshoots</l>
               <l n="27">The bay-tree of <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>. Such the modes</l>
               <l n="28">Nature imparted first; hence all the race</l>
               <l n="29">Of forest-trees and shrubs and sacred groves</l>
               <l n="30">Springs into verdure. Other means there are,</l>
               <l n="31">Which use by method for itself acquired.</l>
               <l n="32">One, sliving suckers from the tender frame</l>
               <l n="33">Of the tree-mother, plants them in the trench;</l>
               <l n="34">One buries the bare stumps within his field,</l>
               <l n="35">Truncheons cleft four-wise, or sharp-pointed stakes;</l>
               <l n="36">Some forest-trees the layer's bent arch await,</l>
               <l n="37">And slips yet quick within the parent-soil;</l>
               <l n="38">No root need others, nor doth the pruner's hand</l>
               <l n="39">Shrink to restore the topmost shoot to earth</l>
               <l n="40">That gave it being. Nay, marvellous to tell,</l>
               <l n="41">Lopped of its limbs, the olive, a mere stock,</l>
               <l n="42">Still thrusts its root out from the sapless wood,</l>
               <l n="43">And oft the branches of one kind we see</l>
               <l n="44">Change to another's with no loss to rue,</l>
               <l n="45">Pear-tree transformed the ingrafted apple yield,</l>
               <l n="46">And stony cornels on the plum-tree blush.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="35">
               <l n="47">Come then, and learn what tilth to each belongs</l>
               <l n="48">According to their kinds, ye husbandmen,</l>
               <l n="49">And tame with culture the wild fruits, lest earth</l>
               <l n="50">Lie idle. O blithe to make all Ismarus</l>
               <l n="51">One forest of the wine-god, and to clothe</l>
               <l n="52">With olives huge Tabernus! And be thou</l>
               <l n="53">At hand, and with me ply the voyage of toil</l>
               <l n="54">I am bound on, O my glory, O thou that art</l>
               <l n="55">Justly the chiefest portion of my fame,</l>
               <l n="56">Maecenas, and on this wide ocean launched</l>
               <l n="57">Spread sail like wings to waft thee. Not that I</l>
               <l n="58">With my poor verse would comprehend the whole,</l>
               <l n="59">Nay, though a hundred tongues, a hundred mouths</l>
               <l n="60">Were mine, a voice of iron; be thou at hand,</l>
               <l n="61">Skirt but the nearer coast-line; see the shore</l>
               <l n="62">Is in our grasp; not now with feigned song</l>
               <l n="63">Through winding bouts and tedious preludings</l>
               <l n="64">Shall I detain thee.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="47">
               <l n="65">Those that lift their head</l>
               <l n="66">Into the realms of light spontaneously,</l>
               <l n="67">Fruitless indeed, but blithe and strenuous spring,</l>
               <l n="68">Since Nature lurks within the soil. And yet</l>
               <l n="69">Even these, should one engraft them, or transplant</l>
               <l n="70">To well-drilled trenches, will anon put of</l>
               <l n="71">Their woodland temper, and, by frequent tilth,</l>
               <l n="72">To whatso craft thou summon them, make speed</l>
               <l n="73">To follow. So likewise will the barren shaft</l>
               <l n="74">That from the stock-root issueth, if it be</l>
               <l n="75">Set out with clear space amid open fields:</l>
               <l n="76">Now the tree-mother's towering leaves and boughs</l>
               <l n="77">Darken, despoil of increase as it grows,</l>
               <l n="78">And blast it in the bearing. Lastly, that</l>
               <l n="79">Which from shed seed ariseth, upward wins</l>
               <l n="80">But slowly, yielding promise of its shade</l>
               <l n="81">To late-born generations; apples wane</l>
               <l n="82">Forgetful of their former juice, the grape</l>
               <l n="83">Bears sorry clusters, for the birds a prey.</l>
               <l n="84">Soothly on all must toil be spent, and all</l>
               <l n="85">Trained to the trench and at great cost subdued.</l>
               <l n="86">But reared from truncheons olives answer best,</l>
               <l n="87">As vines from layers, and from the solid wood</l>
               <l n="88">The Paphian myrtles; while from suckers spring</l>
               <l n="89">Both hardy hazels and huge ash, the tree</l>
               <l n="90">That rims with shade the brows of Hercules,</l>
               <l n="91">And acorns dear to the Chaonian sire:</l>
               <l n="92">So springs the towering palm too, and the fir</l>
               <l n="93">Destined to spy the dangers of the deep.</l>
               <l n="94">But the rough arbutus with walnut-fruit</l>
               <l n="95">Is grafted; so have barren planes ere now</l>
               <l n="96">Stout apples borne, with chestnut-flower the beech,</l>
               <l n="97">The mountain-ash with pear-bloom whitened o'er,</l>
               <l n="98">And swine crunched acorns 'neath the boughs of elms.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="73">
               <l n="99">Nor is the method of inserting eyes</l>
               <l n="100">And grafting one: for where the buds push forth</l>
               <l n="101">Amidst the bark, and burst the membranes thin,</l>
               <l n="102">Even on the knot a narrow rift is made,</l>
               <l n="103">Wherein from some strange tree a germ they pen,</l>
               <l n="104">And to the moist rind bid it cleave and grow.</l>
               <l n="105">Or, otherwise, in knotless trunks is hewn</l>
               <l n="106">A breach, and deep into the solid grain</l>
               <l n="107">A path with wedges cloven; then fruitful slips</l>
               <l n="108">Are set herein, and—no long time—behold!</l>
               <l n="109">To heaven upshot with teeming boughs, the tree</l>
               <l n="110">Strange leaves admires and fruitage not its own.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="83">
               <l n="111">Nor of one kind alone are sturdy elms,</l>
               <l n="112">Willow and lotus, nor the cypress-trees</l>
               <l n="113">Of Ida; nor of self-same fashion spring</l>
               <l n="114">Fat olives, orchades, and radii</l>
               <l n="115">And bitter-berried pausians, no, nor yet</l>
               <l n="116">Apples and the forests of Alcinous;</l>
               <l n="117">Nor from like cuttings are Crustumian pears</l>
               <l n="118">And Syrian, and the heavy hand-fillers.</l>
               <l n="119">Not the same vintage from our trees hangs down,</l>
               <l n="120">Which <placeName key="tgn,7002672">Lesbos</placeName> from <placeName key="perseus,Methymna">Methymna</placeName>'s tendril plucks.</l>
               <l n="121">Vines Thasian are there, Mareotids white,</l>
               <l n="122">These apt for richer soils, for lighter those:</l>
               <l n="123">Psithian for raisin-wine more useful, thin</l>
               <l n="124">Lageos, that one day will try the feet</l>
               <l n="125">And tie the tongue: purples and early-ripes,</l>
               <l n="126">And how, O Rhaetian, shall I hymn thy praise?</l>
               <l n="127">Yet cope not therefore with Falernian bins.</l>
               <l n="128">Vines Aminaean too, best-bodied wine,</l>
               <l n="129">To which the Tmolian bows him, ay, and king</l>
               <l n="130">Phanaeus too, and, lesser of that name,</l>
               <l n="131">Argitis, wherewith not a grape can vie</l>
               <l n="132">For gush of wine-juice or for length of years.</l>
               <l n="133">Nor thee must I pass over, vine of <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>,</l>
               <l n="134">Welcomed by gods and at the second board,</l>
               <l n="135">Nor thee, Bumastus, with plump clusters swollen.</l>
               <l n="136">But lo! how many kinds, and what their names,</l>
               <l n="137">There is no telling, nor doth it boot to tell;</l>
               <l n="138">Who lists to know it, he too would list to learn</l>
               <l n="139">How many sand-grains are by Zephyr tossed</l>
               <l n="140">On <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>'s plain, or wot, when Eurus falls</l>
               <l n="141">With fury on the ships, how many waves</l>
               <l n="142">Come rolling shoreward from the Ionian sea.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="109">
               <l n="143">Not that all soils can all things bear alike.</l>
               <l n="144">Willows by water-courses have their birth,</l>
               <l n="145">Alders in miry fens; on rocky heights</l>
               <l n="146">The barren mountain-ashes; on the shore</l>
               <l n="147">Myrtles throng gayest; Bacchus, lastly, loves</l>
               <l n="148">The bare hillside, and yews the north wind's chill.</l>
               <l n="149">Mark too the earth by outland tillers tamed,</l>
               <l n="150">And Eastern homes of Arabs, and tattooed</l>
               <l n="151">Geloni; to all trees their native lands</l>
               <l n="152">Allotted are; no clime but <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> bears</l>
               <l n="153">Black ebony; the branch of frankincense</l>
               <l n="154">Is <placeName key="tgn,7016796">Saba</placeName>'s sons' alone; why tell to thee</l>
               <l n="155">Of balsams oozing from the perfumed wood,</l>
               <l n="156">Or berries of acanthus ever green?</l>
               <l n="157">Of Aethiop forests hoar with downy wool,</l>
               <l n="158">Or how the Seres comb from off the leaves</l>
               <l n="159">Their silky fleece? Of groves which <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> bears,</l>
               <l n="160">Ocean's near neighbour, earth's remotest nook,</l>
               <l n="161">Where not an arrow-shot can cleave the air</l>
               <l n="162">Above their tree-tops? yet no laggards they,</l>
               <l n="163">When girded with the quiver! Media yields</l>
               <l n="164">The bitter juices and slow-lingering taste</l>
               <l n="165">Of the blest citron-fruit, than which no aid</l>
               <l n="166">Comes timelier, when fierce step-dames drug the cup</l>
               <l n="167">With simples mixed and spells of baneful power,</l>
               <l n="168">To drive the deadly poison from the limbs.</l>
               <l n="169">Large the tree's self in semblance like a bay,</l>
               <l n="170">And, showered it not a different scent abroad,</l>
               <l n="171">A bay it had been; for no wind of heaven</l>
               <l n="172">Its foliage falls; the flower, none faster, clings;</l>
               <l n="173">With it the Medes for sweetness lave the lips,</l>
               <l n="174">And ease the panting breathlessness of age.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="136">
               <l n="175">But no, not Mede-land with its wealth of woods,</l>
               <l n="176">Nor Ganges fair, and Hermus thick with gold,</l>
               <l n="177">Can match the praise of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; nor Ind,</l>
               <l n="178">Nor <placeName key="tgn,7016612">Bactria</placeName>, nor Panchaia, one wide tract</l>
               <l n="179">Of incense-teeming sand. Here never bulls</l>
               <l n="180">With nostrils snorting fire upturned the sod</l>
               <l n="181">Sown with the monstrous dragon's teeth, nor crop</l>
               <l n="182">Of warriors bristled thick with lance and helm;</l>
               <l n="183">But heavy harvests and the Massic juice</l>
               <l n="184">Of Bacchus fill its borders, overspread</l>
               <l n="185">With fruitful flocks and olives. Hence arose</l>
               <l n="186">The war-horse stepping proudly o'er the plain;</l>
               <l n="187">Hence thy white flocks, <placeName key="perseus,Clitumnus">Clitumnus</placeName>, and the bull,</l>
               <l n="188">Of victims mightiest, which full oft have led,</l>
               <l n="189">Bathed in thy sacred stream, the triumph-pomp</l>
               <l n="190">Of Romans to the temples of the gods.</l>
               <l n="191">Here blooms perpetual spring, and summer here</l>
               <l n="192">In months that are not summer's; twice teem the flocks;</l>
               <l n="193">Twice doth the tree yield service of her fruit.</l>
               <l n="194">But ravening tigers come not nigh, nor breed</l>
               <l n="195">Of savage lion, nor aconite betrays</l>
               <l n="196">Its hapless gatherers, nor with sweep so vast</l>
               <l n="197">Doth the scaled serpent trail his endless coils</l>
               <l n="198">Along the ground, or wreathe him into spires.</l>
               <l n="199">Mark too her cities, so many and so proud,</l>
               <l n="200">Of mighty toil the achievement, town on town</l>
               <l n="201">Up rugged precipices heaved and reared,</l>
               <l n="202">And rivers undergliding ancient walls.</l>
               <l n="203">Or should I celebrate the sea that laves</l>
               <l n="204">Her upper shores and lower? or those broad lakes?</l>
               <l n="205">Thee, Larius, greatest and, Benacus, thee</l>
               <l n="206">With billowy uproar surging like the main?</l>
               <l n="207">Or sing her harbours, and the barrier cast</l>
               <l n="208">Athwart the Lucrine, and how ocean chafes</l>
               <l n="209">With mighty bellowings, where the Julian wave</l>
               <l n="210">Echoes the thunder of his rout, and through</l>
               <l n="211">Avernian inlets pours the Tuscan tide?</l>
               <l n="212">A land no less that in her veins displays</l>
               <l n="213">Rivers of silver, mines of copper ore,</l>
               <l n="214">Ay, and with gold hath flowed abundantly.</l>
               <l n="215">A land that reared a valiant breed of men,</l>
               <l n="216">The Marsi and Sabellian youth, and, schooled</l>
               <l n="217">To hardship, the Ligurian, and with these</l>
               <l n="218">The Volscian javelin-armed, the Decii too,</l>
               <l n="219">The Marii and Camilli, names of might,</l>
               <l n="220">The Scipios, stubborn warriors, ay, and thee,</l>
               <l n="221">Great Caesar, who in <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s utmost bounds</l>
               <l n="222">With conquering arm e'en now art fending far</l>
               <l n="223">The unwarlike Indian from the heights of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</l>
               <l n="224">Hail! land of Saturn, mighty mother thou</l>
               <l n="225">Of fruits and heroes; 'tis for thee I dare</l>
               <l n="226">Unseal the sacred fountains, and essay</l>
               <l n="227">Themes of old art and glory, as I sing</l>
               <l n="228">The song of Ascra through the towns of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="177">
               <l n="229">Now for the native gifts of various soils,</l>
               <l n="230">What powers hath each, what hue, what natural bent</l>
               <l n="231">For yielding increase. First your stubborn lands</l>
               <l n="232">And churlish hill-sides, where are thorny fields</l>
               <l n="233">Of meagre marl and gravel, these delight</l>
               <l n="234">In long-lived olive-groves to Pallas dear.</l>
               <l n="235">Take for a sign the plenteous growth hard by</l>
               <l n="236">Of oleaster, and the fields strewn wide</l>
               <l n="237">With woodland berries. But a soil that's rich,</l>
               <l n="238">In moisture sweet exulting, and the plain</l>
               <l n="239">That teems with grasses on its fruitful breast,</l>
               <l n="240">Such as full oft in hollow mountain-dell</l>
               <l n="241">We view beneath us—from the craggy heights</l>
               <l n="242">Streams thither flow with fertilizing mud—</l>
               <l n="243">A plain which southward rising feeds the fern</l>
               <l n="244">By curved ploughs detested, this one day</l>
               <l n="245">Shall yield thee store of vines full strong to gush</l>
               <l n="246">In torrents of the wine-god; this shall be</l>
               <l n="247">Fruitful of grapes and flowing juice like that</l>
               <l n="248">We pour to heaven from bowls of gold, what time</l>
               <l n="249">The sleek Etruscan at the altar blows</l>
               <l n="250">His ivory pipe, and on the curved dish</l>
               <l n="251">We lay the reeking entrails. If to rear</l>
               <l n="252">Cattle delight thee rather, steers, or lambs,</l>
               <l n="253">Or goats that kill the tender plants, then seek</l>
               <l n="254">Full-fed <placeName key="tgn,7004100">Tarentum</placeName>'s glades and distant fields,</l>
               <l n="255">Or such a plain as luckless <placeName key="perseus,Mantua">Mantua</placeName> lost</l>
               <l n="256">Whose weedy water feeds the snow-white swan:</l>
               <l n="257">There nor clear springs nor grass the flocks will fail,</l>
               <l n="258">And all the day-long browsing of thy herds</l>
               <l n="259">Shall the cool dews of one brief night repair.</l>
               <l n="260">Land which the burrowing share shows dark and rich,</l>
               <l n="261">With crumbling soil—for this we counterfeit</l>
               <l n="262">In ploughing—for corn is goodliest; from no field</l>
               <l n="263">More wains thou'lt see wend home with plodding steers;</l>
               <l n="264">Or that from which the husbandman in spleen</l>
               <l n="265">Has cleared the timber, and o'erthrown the copse</l>
               <l n="266">That year on year lay idle, and from the roots</l>
               <l n="267">Uptorn the immemorial haunt of birds;</l>
               <l n="268">They banished from their nests have sought the skies;</l>
               <l n="269">But the rude plain beneath the ploughshare's stroke</l>
               <l n="270">Starts into sudden brightness. For indeed</l>
               <l n="271">The starved hill-country gravel scarce serves the bees</l>
               <l n="272">With lowly cassias and with rosemary;</l>
               <l n="273">Rough tufa and chalk too, by black water-worms</l>
               <l n="274">Gnawed through and through, proclaim no soils beside</l>
               <l n="275">So rife with serpent-dainties, or that yield</l>
               <l n="276">Such winding lairs to lurk in. That again,</l>
               <l n="277">Which vapoury mist and flitting smoke exhales,</l>
               <l n="278">Drinks moisture up and casts it forth at will,</l>
               <l n="279">Which, ever in its own green grass arrayed,</l>
               <l n="280">Mars not the metal with salt scurf of rust—</l>
               <l n="281">That shall thine elms with merry vines enwreathe;</l>
               <l n="282">That teems with olive; that shall thy tilth prove kind</l>
               <l n="283">To cattle, and patient of the curved share.</l>
               <l n="284">Such ploughs rich <placeName key="perseus,Capua">Capua</placeName>, such the coast that skirts</l>
               <l n="285">Thy ridge, <placeName key="tgn,1107763">Vesuvius</placeName>, and the Clanian flood,</l>
               <l n="286">Acerrae's desolation and her bane.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="226">
               <l n="287">How each to recognize now hear me tell.</l>
               <l n="288">Dost ask if loose or passing firm it be—</l>
               <l n="289">Since one for corn hath liking, one for wine,</l>
               <l n="290">The firmer sort for Ceres, none too loose</l>
               <l n="291">For thee, Lyaeus?—with scrutinizing eye</l>
               <l n="292">First choose thy ground, and bid a pit be sunk</l>
               <l n="293">Deep in the solid earth, then cast the mould</l>
               <l n="294">All back again, and stamp the surface smooth.</l>
               <l n="295">If it suffice not, loose will be the land,</l>
               <l n="296">More meet for cattle and for kindly vines;</l>
               <l n="297">But if, rebellious, to its proper bounds</l>
               <l n="298">The soil returns not, but fills all the trench</l>
               <l n="299">And overtops it, then the glebe is gross;</l>
               <l n="300">Look for stiff ridges and reluctant clods,</l>
               <l n="301">And with strong bullocks cleave the fallow crust.</l>
               <l n="302">Salt ground again, and bitter, as 'tis called—</l>
               <l n="303">Barren for fruits, by tilth untamable,</l>
               <l n="304">Nor grape her kind, nor apples their good name</l>
               <l n="305">Maintaining—will in this wise yield thee proof:</l>
               <l n="306">Stout osier-baskets from the rafter-smoke,</l>
               <l n="307">And strainers of the winepress pluck thee down;</l>
               <l n="308">Hereinto let that evil land, with fresh</l>
               <l n="309">Spring-water mixed, be trampled to the full;</l>
               <l n="310">The moisture, mark you, will ooze all away,</l>
               <l n="311">In big drops issuing through the osier-withes,</l>
               <l n="312">But plainly will its taste the secret tell,</l>
               <l n="313">And with a harsh twang ruefully distort</l>
               <l n="314">The mouths of them that try it. Rich soil again</l>
               <l n="315">We learn on this wise: tossed from hand to hand</l>
               <l n="316">Yet cracks it never, but pitch-like, as we hold,</l>
               <l n="317">Clings to the fingers. A land with moisture rife</l>
               <l n="318">Breeds lustier herbage, and is more than meet</l>
               <l n="319">Prolific. Ah I may never such for me</l>
               <l n="320">O'er-fertile prove, or make too stout a show</l>
               <l n="321">At the first earing! Heavy land or light</l>
               <l n="322">The mute self-witness of its weight betrays.</l>
               <l n="323">A glance will serve to warn thee which is black,</l>
               <l n="324">Or what the hue of any. But hard it is</l>
               <l n="325">To track the signs of that pernicious cold:</l>
               <l n="326">Pines only, noxious yews, and ivies dark</l>
               <l n="327">At times reveal its traces.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="259">
               <l n="328">All these rules</l>
               <l n="329">Regarding, let your land, ay, long before,</l>
               <l n="330">Scorch to the quick, and into trenches carve</l>
               <l n="331">The mighty mountains, and their upturned clods</l>
               <l n="332">Bare to the north wind, ere thou plant therein</l>
               <l n="333">The vine's prolific kindred. Fields whose soil</l>
               <l n="334">Is crumbling are the best: winds look to that,</l>
               <l n="335">And bitter hoar-frosts, and the delver's toil</l>
               <l n="336">Untiring, as he stirs the loosened glebe.</l>
               <l n="337">But those, whose vigilance no care escapes,</l>
               <l n="338">Search for a kindred site, where first to rear</l>
               <l n="339">A nursery for the trees, and eke whereto</l>
               <l n="340">Soon to translate them, lest the sudden shock</l>
               <l n="341">From their new mother the young plants estrange.</l>
               <l n="342">Nay, even the quarter of the sky they brand</l>
               <l n="343">Upon the bark, that each may be restored,</l>
               <l n="344">As erst it stood, here bore the southern heats,</l>
               <l n="345">Here turned its shoulder to the northern pole;</l>
               <l n="346">So strong is custom formed in early years.</l>
               <l n="347">Whether on hill or plain 'tis best to plant</l>
               <l n="348">Your vineyard first inquire. If on some plain</l>
               <l n="349">You measure out rich acres, then plant thick;</l>
               <l n="350">Thick planting makes no niggard of the vine;</l>
               <l n="351">But if on rising mound or sloping bill,</l>
               <l n="352">Then let the rows have room, so none the less</l>
               <l n="353">Each line you draw, when all the trees are set,</l>
               <l n="354">May tally to perfection. Even as oft</l>
               <l n="355">In mighty war, whenas the legion's length</l>
               <l n="356">Deploys its cohorts, and the column stands</l>
               <l n="357">In open plain, the ranks of battle set,</l>
               <l n="358">And far and near with rippling sheen of arms</l>
               <l n="359">The wide earth flickers, nor yet in grisly strife</l>
               <l n="360">Foe grapples foe, but dubious 'twixt the hosts</l>
               <l n="361">The war-god wavers; so let all be ranged</l>
               <l n="362">In equal rows symmetric, not alone</l>
               <l n="363">To feed an idle fancy with the view,</l>
               <l n="364">But since not otherwise will earth afford</l>
               <l n="365">Vigour to all alike, nor yet the boughs</l>
               <l n="366">Have power to stretch them into open space.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="288">
               <l n="367">Shouldst haply of the furrow's depth inquire,</l>
               <l n="368">Even to a shallow trench I dare commit</l>
               <l n="369">The vine; but deeper in the ground is fixed</l>
               <l n="370">The tree that props it, aesculus in chief,</l>
               <l n="371">Which howso far its summit soars toward heaven,</l>
               <l n="372">So deep strikes root into the vaults of hell.</l>
               <l n="373">It therefore neither storms, nor blasts, nor showers</l>
               <l n="374">Wrench from its bed; unshaken it abides,</l>
               <l n="375">Sees many a generation, many an age</l>
               <l n="376">Of men roll onward, and survives them all,</l>
               <l n="377">Stretching its titan arms and branches far,</l>
               <l n="378">Sole central pillar of a world of shade.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="298">
               <l n="379">Nor toward the sunset let thy vineyards slope,</l>
               <l n="380">Nor midst the vines plant hazel; neither take</l>
               <l n="381">The topmost shoots for cuttings, nor from the top</l>
               <l n="382">Of the supporting tree your suckers tear;</l>
               <l n="383">So deep their love of earth; nor wound the plants</l>
               <l n="384">With blunted blade; nor truncheons intersperse</l>
               <l n="385">Of the wild olive: for oft from careless swains</l>
               <l n="386">A spark hath fallen, that, 'neath the unctuous rind</l>
               <l n="387">Hid thief-like first, now grips the tough tree-bole,</l>
               <l n="388">And mounting to the leaves on high, sends forth</l>
               <l n="389">A roar to heaven, then coursing through the boughs</l>
               <l n="390">And airy summits reigns victoriously,</l>
               <l n="391">Wraps all the grove in robes of fire, and gross</l>
               <l n="392">With pitch-black vapour heaves the murky reek</l>
               <l n="393">Skyward, but chiefly if a storm has swooped</l>
               <l n="394">Down on the forest, and a driving wind</l>
               <l n="395">Rolls up the conflagration. When 'tis so,</l>
               <l n="396">Their root-force fails them, nor, when lopped away,</l>
               <l n="397">Can they recover, and from the earth beneath</l>
               <l n="398">Spring to like verdure; thus alone survives</l>
               <l n="399">The bare wild olive with its bitter leaves.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="315">
               <l n="400">Let none persuade thee, howso weighty-wise,</l>
               <l n="401">To stir the soil when stiff with Boreas' breath.</l>
               <l n="402">Then ice-bound winter locks the fields, nor lets</l>
               <l n="403">The young plant fix its frozen root to earth.</l>
               <l n="404">Best sow your vineyards when in blushing Spring</l>
               <l n="405">Comes the white bird long-bodied snakes abhor,</l>
               <l n="406">Or on the eve of autumn's earliest frost,</l>
               <l n="407">Ere the swift sun-steeds touch the wintry Signs,</l>
               <l n="408">While summer is departing. Spring it is</l>
               <l n="409">Blesses the fruit-plantation, Spring the groves;</l>
               <l n="410">In Spring earth swells and claims the fruitful seed.</l>
               <l n="411">Then Aether, sire omnipotent, leaps down</l>
               <l n="412">With quickening showers to his glad wife's embrace,</l>
               <l n="413">And, might with might commingling, rears to life</l>
               <l n="414">All germs that teem within her; then resound</l>
               <l n="415">With songs of birds the greenwood-wildernesses,</l>
               <l n="416">And in due time the herds their loves renew;</l>
               <l n="417">Then the boon earth yields increase, and the fields</l>
               <l n="418">Unlock their bosoms to the warm west winds;</l>
               <l n="419">Soft moisture spreads o'er all things, and the blades</l>
               <l n="420">Face the new suns, and safely trust them now;</l>
               <l n="421">The vine-shoot, fearless of the rising south,</l>
               <l n="422">Or mighty north winds driving rain from heaven,</l>
               <l n="423">Bursts into bud, and every leaf unfolds.</l>
               <l n="424">Even so, methinks, when Earth to being sprang,</l>
               <l n="425">Dawned the first days, and such the course they held;</l>
               <l n="426">'Twas Spring-tide then, ay, Spring, the mighty world</l>
               <l n="427">Was keeping: Eurus spared his wintry blasts,</l>
               <l n="428">When first the flocks drank sunlight, and a race</l>
               <l n="429">Of men like iron from the hard glebe arose,</l>
               <l n="430">And wild beasts thronged the woods, and stars the heaven.</l>
               <l n="431">Nor could frail creatures bear this heavy strain,</l>
               <l n="432">Did not so large a respite interpose</l>
               <l n="433">'Twixt frost and heat, and heaven's relenting arms</l>
               <l n="434">Yield earth a welcome.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="346">
               <l n="435">For the rest, whate'er</l>
               <l n="436">The sets thou plantest in thy fields, thereon</l>
               <l n="437">Strew refuse rich, and with abundant earth</l>
               <l n="438">Take heed to hide them, and dig in withal</l>
               <l n="439">Rough shells or porous stone, for therebetween</l>
               <l n="440">Will water trickle and fine vapour creep,</l>
               <l n="441">And so the plants their drooping spirits raise.</l>
               <l n="442">Aye, and there have been, who with weight of stone</l>
               <l n="443">Or heavy potsherd press them from above;</l>
               <l n="444">This serves for shield in pelting showers, and this</l>
               <l n="445">When the hot dog-star chaps the fields with drought.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="354">
               <l n="446">The slips once planted, yet remains to cleave</l>
               <l n="447">The earth about their roots persistently,</l>
               <l n="448">And toss the cumbrous hoes, or task the soil</l>
               <l n="449">With burrowing plough-share, and ply up and down</l>
               <l n="450">Your labouring bullocks through the vineyard's midst,</l>
               <l n="451">Then too smooth reeds and shafts of whittled wand,</l>
               <l n="452">And ashen poles and sturdy forks to shape,</l>
               <l n="453">Whereby supported they may learn to mount,</l>
               <l n="454">Laugh at the gales, and through the elm-tops win</l>
               <l n="455">From story up to story.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="362">
               <l n="456">Now while yet</l>
               <l n="457">The leaves are in their first fresh infant growth,</l>
               <l n="458">Forbear their frailty, and while yet the bough</l>
               <l n="459">Shoots joyfully toward heaven, with loosened rein</l>
               <l n="460">Launched on the void, assail it not as yet</l>
               <l n="461">With keen-edged sickle, but let the leaves alone</l>
               <l n="462">Be culled with clip of fingers here and there.</l>
               <l n="463">But when they clasp the elms with sturdy trunks</l>
               <l n="464">Erect, then strip the leaves off, prune the boughs;</l>
               <l n="465">Sooner they shrink from steel, but then put forth</l>
               <l n="466">The arm of power, and stem the branchy tide.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="371">
               <l n="467">Hedges too must be woven and all beasts</l>
               <l n="468">Barred entrance, chiefly while the leaf is young</l>
               <l n="469">And witless of disaster; for therewith,</l>
               <l n="470">Beside harsh winters and o'erpowering sun,</l>
               <l n="471">Wild buffaloes and pestering goats for ay</l>
               <l n="472">Besport them, sheep and heifers glut their greed.</l>
               <l n="473">Nor cold by hoar-frost curdled, nor the prone</l>
               <l n="474">Dead weight of summer upon the parched crags,</l>
               <l n="475">So scathe it, as the flocks with venom-bite</l>
               <l n="476">Of their hard tooth, whose gnawing scars the stem.</l>
               <l n="477">For no offence but this to Bacchus bleeds</l>
               <l n="478">The goat at every altar, and old plays</l>
               <l n="479">Upon the stage find entrance; therefore too</l>
               <l n="480">The sons of Theseus through the country-side—</l>
               <l n="481">Hamlet and crossway—set the prize of wit,</l>
               <l n="482">And on the smooth sward over oiled skins</l>
               <l n="483">Dance in their tipsy frolic. Furthermore</l>
               <l n="484">The Ausonian swains, a race from <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> derived,</l>
               <l n="485">Make merry with rough rhymes and boisterous mirth,</l>
               <l n="486">Grim masks of hollowed bark assume, invoke</l>
               <l n="487">Thee with glad hymns, O Bacchus, and to thee</l>
               <l n="488">Hang puppet-faces on tall pines to swing.</l>
               <l n="489">Hence every vineyard teems with mellowing fruit,</l>
               <l n="490">Till hollow vale o'erflows, and gorge profound,</l>
               <l n="491">Where'er the god hath turned his comely head.</l>
               <l n="492">Therefore to Bacchus duly will we sing</l>
               <l n="493">Meet honour with ancestral hymns, and cates</l>
               <l n="494">And dishes bear him; and the doomed goat</l>
               <l n="495">Led by the horn shall at the altar stand,</l>
               <l n="496">Whose entrails rich on hazel-spits we'll roast.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="397">
               <l n="497">This further task again, to dress the vine,</l>
               <l n="498">Hath needs beyond exhausting; the whole soil</l>
               <l n="499">Thrice, four times, yearly must be cleft, the sod</l>
               <l n="500">With hoes reversed be crushed continually,</l>
               <l n="501">The whole plantation lightened of its leaves.</l>
               <l n="502">Round on the labourer spins the wheel of toil,</l>
               <l n="503">As on its own track rolls the circling year.</l>
               <l n="504">Soon as the vine her lingering leaves hath shed,</l>
               <l n="505">And the chill north wind from the forests shook</l>
               <l n="506">Their coronal, even then the careful swain</l>
               <l n="507">Looks keenly forward to the coming year,</l>
               <l n="508">With Saturn's curved fang pursues and prunes</l>
               <l n="509">The vine forlorn, and lops it into shape.</l>
               <l n="510">Be first to dig the ground up, first to clear</l>
               <l n="511">And burn the refuse-branches, first to house</l>
               <l n="512">Again your vine-poles, last to gather fruit.</l>
               <l n="513">Twice doth the thickening shade beset the vine,</l>
               <l n="514">Twice weeds with stifling briers o'ergrow the crop;</l>
               <l n="515">And each a toilsome labour. Do thou praise</l>
               <l n="516">Broad acres, farm but few. Rough twigs beside</l>
               <l n="517">Of butcher's broom among the woods are cut,</l>
               <l n="518">And reeds upon the river-banks, and still</l>
               <l n="519">The undressed willow claims thy fostering care.</l>
               <l n="520">So now the vines are fettered, now the trees</l>
               <l n="521">Let go the sickle, and the last dresser now</l>
               <l n="522">Sings of his finished rows; but still the ground</l>
               <l n="523">Must vexed be, the dust be stirred, and heaven</l>
               <l n="524">Still set thee trembling for the ripened grapes.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="420">
               <l n="525">Not so with olives; small husbandry need they,</l>
               <l n="526">Nor look for sickle bowed or biting rake,</l>
               <l n="527">When once they have gripped the soil, and borne the breeze.</l>
               <l n="528">Earth of herself, with hooked fang laid bare,</l>
               <l n="529">Yields moisture for the plants, and heavy fruit,</l>
               <l n="530">The ploughshare aiding; therewithal thou'lt rear</l>
               <l n="531">The olive's fatness well-beloved of Peace.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="426">
               <l n="532">Apples, moreover, soon as first they feel</l>
               <l n="533">Their stems wax lusty, and have found their strength,</l>
               <l n="534">To heaven climb swiftly, self-impelled, nor crave</l>
               <l n="535">Our succour. All the grove meanwhile no less</l>
               <l n="536">With fruit is swelling, and the wild haunts of birds</l>
               <l n="537">Blush with their blood-red berries. Cytisus</l>
               <l n="538">Is good to browse on, the tall forest yields</l>
               <l n="539">Pine-torches, and the nightly fires are fed</l>
               <l n="540">And shoot forth radiance. And shall men be loath</l>
               <l n="541">To plant, nor lavish of their pains? Why trace</l>
               <l n="542">Things mightier? Willows even and lowly brooms</l>
               <l n="543">To cattle their green leaves, to shepherds shade,</l>
               <l n="544">Fences for crops, and food for honey yield.</l>
               <l n="545">And blithe it is Cytorus to behold</l>
               <l n="546">Waving with box, Narycian groves of pitch;</l>
               <l n="547">Oh! blithe the sight of fields beholden not</l>
               <l n="548">To rake or man's endeavour! the barren woods</l>
               <l n="549">That crown the scalp of <placeName key="tgn,1108814">Caucasus</placeName>, even these,</l>
               <l n="550">Which furious blasts for ever rive and rend,</l>
               <l n="551">Yield various wealth, pine-logs that serve for ships,</l>
               <l n="552">Cedar and cypress for the homes of men;</l>
               <l n="553">Hence, too, the farmers shave their wheel-spokes, hence</l>
               <l n="554">Drums for their wains, and curved boat-keels fit;</l>
               <l n="555">Willows bear twigs enow, the elm-tree leaves,</l>
               <l n="556">Myrtle stout spear-shafts, war-tried cornel too;</l>
               <l n="557">Yews into Ituraean bows are bent:</l>
               <l n="558">Nor do smooth lindens or lathe-polished box</l>
               <l n="559">Shrink from man's shaping and keen-furrowing steel;</l>
               <l n="560">Light alder floats upon the boiling flood</l>
               <l n="561">Sped down the <placeName key="tgn,7010018">Padus</placeName>, and bees house their swarms</l>
               <l n="562">In rotten holm-oak's hollow bark and bole.</l>
               <l n="563">What of like praise can Bacchus' gifts afford?</l>
               <l n="564">Nay, Bacchus even to crime hath prompted, he</l>
               <l n="565">The wine-infuriate Centaurs quelled with death,</l>
               <l n="566">Rhoetus and Pholus, and with mighty bowl</l>
               <l n="567">Hylaeus threatening high the Lapithae.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="458">
               <l n="568">Oh! all too happy tillers of the soil,</l>
               <l n="569">Could they but know their blessedness, for whom</l>
               <l n="570">Far from the clash of arms all-equal earth</l>
               <l n="571">Pours from the ground herself their easy fare!</l>
               <l n="572">What though no lofty palace portal-proud</l>
               <l n="573">From all its chambers vomits forth a tide</l>
               <l n="574">Of morning courtiers, nor agape they gaze</l>
               <l n="575">On pillars with fair tortoise-shell inwrought,</l>
               <l n="576">Gold-purfled robes, and bronze from Ephyre;</l>
               <l n="577">Nor is the whiteness of their wool distained</l>
               <l n="578">With drugs Assyrian, nor clear olive's use</l>
               <l n="579">With cassia tainted; yet untroubled calm,</l>
               <l n="580">A life that knows no falsehood, rich enow</l>
               <l n="581">With various treasures, yet broad-acred ease,</l>
               <l n="582">Grottoes and living lakes, yet Tempes cool,</l>
               <l n="583">Lowing of kine, and sylvan slumbers soft,</l>
               <l n="584">They lack not; lawns and wild beasts' haunts are there,</l>
               <l n="585">A youth of labour patient, need-inured,</l>
               <l n="586">Worship, and reverend sires: with them from earth</l>
               <l n="587">Departing justice her last footprints left.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="475">
               <l n="588">Me before all things may the Muses sweet,</l>
               <l n="589">Whose rites I bear with mighty passion pierced,</l>
               <l n="590">Receive, and show the paths and stars of heaven,</l>
               <l n="591">The sun's eclipses and the labouring moons,</l>
               <l n="592">From whence the earthquake, by what power the seas</l>
               <l n="593">Swell from their depths, and, every barrier burst,</l>
               <l n="594">Sink back upon themselves, why winter-suns</l>
               <l n="595">So haste to dip 'neath ocean, or what check</l>
               <l n="596">The lingering night retards. But if to these</l>
               <l n="597">High realms of nature the cold curdling blood</l>
               <l n="598">About my heart bar access, then be fields</l>
               <l n="599">And stream-washed vales my solace, let me love</l>
               <l n="600">Rivers and woods, inglorious. Oh for you</l>
               <l n="601">Plains, and Spercheius, and Taygete,</l>
               <l n="602">By Spartan maids o'er-revelled! Oh, for one,</l>
               <l n="603">Would set me in deep dells of <placeName key="tgn,7011635">Haemus</placeName> cool,</l>
               <l n="604">And shield me with his boughs' o'ershadowing might!</l>
               <l n="605">Happy, who had the skill to understand</l>
               <l n="606">Nature's hid causes, and beneath his feet</l>
               <l n="607">All terrors cast, and death's relentless doom,</l>
               <l n="608">And the loud roar of greedy Acheron.</l>
               <l n="609">Blest too is he who knows the rural gods,</l>
               <l n="610">Pan, old Silvanus, and the sister-nymphs!</l>
               <l n="611">Him nor the rods of public power can bend,</l>
               <l n="612">Nor kingly purple, nor fierce feud that drives</l>
               <l n="613">Brother to turn on brother, nor descent</l>
               <l n="614">Of Dacian from the Danube's leagued flood,</l>
               <l n="615">Nor <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>'s great State, nor kingdoms like to die;</l>
               <l n="616">Nor hath he grieved through pitying of the poor,</l>
               <l n="617">Nor envied him that hath. What fruit the boughs,</l>
               <l n="618">And what the fields, of their own bounteous will</l>
               <l n="619">Have borne, he gathers; nor iron rule of laws,</l>
               <l n="620">Nor maddened Forum have his eyes beheld,</l>
               <l n="621">Nor archives of the people. Others vex</l>
               <l n="622">The darksome gulfs of Ocean with their oars,</l>
               <l n="623">Or rush on steel: they press within the courts</l>
               <l n="624">And doors of princes; one with havoc falls</l>
               <l n="625">Upon a city and its hapless hearths,</l>
               <l n="626">From gems to drink, on Tyrian rugs to lie;</l>
               <l n="627">This hoards his wealth and broods o'er buried gold;</l>
               <l n="628">One at the rostra stares in blank amaze;</l>
               <l n="629">One gaping sits transported by the cheers,</l>
               <l n="630">The answering cheers of plebs and senate rolled</l>
               <l n="631">Along the benches: bathed in brothers' blood</l>
               <l n="632">Men revel, and, all delights of hearth and home</l>
               <l n="633">For exile changing, a new country seek</l>
               <l n="634">Beneath an alien sun. The husbandman</l>
               <l n="635">With hooked ploughshare turns the soil; from hence</l>
               <l n="636">Springs his year's labour; hence, too, he sustains</l>
               <l n="637">Country and cottage homestead, and from hence</l>
               <l n="638">His herds of cattle and deserving steers.</l>
               <l n="639">No respite! still the year o'erflows with fruit,</l>
               <l n="640">Or young of kine, or Ceres' wheaten sheaf,</l>
               <l n="641">With crops the furrow loads, and bursts the barns.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="519">
               <l n="642">Winter is come: in olive-mills they bruise</l>
               <l n="643">The Sicyonian berry; acorn-cheered</l>
               <l n="644">The swine troop homeward; woods their arbutes yield;</l>
               <l n="645">So, various fruit sheds Autumn, and high up</l>
               <l n="646">On sunny rocks the mellowing vintage bakes.</l>
               <l n="647">Meanwhile about his lips sweet children cling;</l>
               <l n="648">His chaste house keeps its purity; his kine</l>
               <l n="649">Drop milky udders, and on the lush green grass</l>
               <l n="650">Fat kids are striving, horn to butting horn.</l>
               <l n="651">Himself keeps holy days; stretched o'er the sward,</l>
               <l n="652">Where round the fire his comrades crown the bowl,</l>
               <l n="653">He pours libation, and thy name invokes,</l>
               <l n="654">Lenaeus, and for the herdsmen on an elm</l>
               <l n="655">Sets up a mark for the swift javelin; they</l>
               <l n="656">Strip their tough bodies for the rustic sport.</l>
               <l n="657">Such life of yore the ancient Sabines led,</l>
               <l n="658">Such Remus and his brother: Etruria thus,</l>
               <l n="659">Doubt not, to greatness grew, and <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> became</l>
               <l n="660">The fair world's fairest, and with circling wall</l>
               <l n="661">Clasped to her single breast the sevenfold hills.</l>
               <l n="662">Ay, ere the reign of Dicte's king, ere men,</l>
               <l n="663">Waxed godless, banqueted on slaughtered bulls,</l>
               <l n="664">Such life on earth did golden Saturn lead.</l>
               <l n="665">Nor ear of man had heard the war-trump's blast,</l>
               <l n="666">Nor clang of sword on stubborn anvil set.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="541">
               <l n="667">But lo! a boundless space we have travelled o'er;</l>
               <l n="668">'Tis time our steaming horses to unyoke.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="1">
               <l n="1">Thee too, great Pales, will I hymn, and thee,</l>
               <l n="2">Amphrysian shepherd, worthy to be sung,</l>
               <l n="3">You, woods and waves Lycaean. All themes beside,</l>
               <l n="4">Which else had charmed the vacant mind with song,</l>
               <l n="5">Are now waxed common. Of harsh Eurystheus who</l>
               <l n="6">The story knows not, or that praiseless king</l>
               <l n="7">Busiris, and his altars? or by whom</l>
               <l n="8">Hath not the tale been told of Hylas young,</l>
               <l n="9">Latonian Delos and Hippodame,</l>
               <l n="10">And Pelops for his ivory shoulder famed,</l>
               <l n="11">Keen charioteer? Needs must a path be tried,</l>
               <l n="12">By which I too may lift me from the dust,</l>
               <l n="13">And float triumphant through the mouths of men.</l>
               <l n="14">Yea, I shall be the first, so life endure,</l>
               <l n="15">To lead the Muses with me, as I pass</l>
               <l n="16">To mine own country from the Aonian height;</l>
               <l n="17">I, <placeName key="perseus,Mantua">Mantua</placeName>, first will bring thee back the palms</l>
               <l n="18">Of Idumaea, and raise a marble shrine</l>
               <l n="19">On thy green plain fast by the water-side,</l>
               <l n="20">Where Mincius winds more vast in lazy coils,</l>
               <l n="21">And rims his margent with the tender reed.</l>
               <l n="22">Amid my shrine shall Caesar's godhead dwell.</l>
               <l n="23">To him will I, as victor, bravely dight</l>
               <l n="24">In Tyrian purple, drive along the bank</l>
               <l n="25">A hundred four-horse cars. All <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> for me,</l>
               <l n="26">Leaving Alpheus and Molorchus' grove,</l>
               <l n="27">On foot shall strive, or with the raw-hide glove;</l>
               <l n="28">Whilst I, my head with stripped green olive crowned,</l>
               <l n="29">Will offer gifts. Even 'tis present joy</l>
               <l n="30">To lead the high processions to the fane,</l>
               <l n="31">And view the victims felled; or how the scene</l>
               <l n="32">Sunders with shifted face, and <placeName key="tgn,7008653">Britain</placeName>'s sons</l>
               <l n="33">Inwoven thereon with those proud curtains rise.</l>
               <l n="34">Of gold and massive ivory on the doors</l>
               <l n="35">I'll trace the battle of the Gangarides,</l>
               <l n="36">And our Quirinus' conquering arms, and there</l>
               <l n="37">Surging with war, and hugely flowing, the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>,</l>
               <l n="38">And columns heaped on high with naval brass.</l>
               <l n="39">And <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>'s vanquished cities I will add,</l>
               <l n="40">And quelled Niphates, and the Parthian foe,</l>
               <l n="41">Who trusts in flight and backward-volleying darts,</l>
               <l n="42">And trophies torn with twice triumphant hand</l>
               <l n="43">From empires twain on ocean's either shore.</l>
               <l n="44">And breathing forms of Parian marble there</l>
               <l n="45">Shall stand, the offspring of Assaracus,</l>
               <l n="46">And great names of the Jove-descended folk,</l>
               <l n="47">And father Tros, and <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>'s first founder, lord</l>
               <l n="48">Of Cynthus. And accursed Envy there</l>
               <l n="49">Shall dread the Furies, and thy ruthless flood,</l>
               <l n="50">Cocytus, and Ixion's twisted snakes,</l>
               <l n="51">And that vast wheel and ever-baffling stone.</l>
               <l n="52">Meanwhile the Dryad-haunted woods and lawns</l>
               <l n="53">Unsullied seek we; 'tis thy hard behest,</l>
               <l n="54">Maecenas. Without thee no lofty task</l>
               <l n="55">My mind essays. Up! break the sluggish bonds</l>
               <l n="56">Of tarriance; with loud din Cithaeron calls,</l>
               <l n="57">Steed-taming <placeName key="perseus,Epidauros">Epidaurus</placeName>, and thy hounds,</l>
               <l n="58">Taygete; and hark! the assenting groves</l>
               <l n="59">With peal on peal reverberate the roar.</l>
               <l n="60">Yet must I gird me to rehearse ere long</l>
               <l n="61">The fiery fights of Caesar, speed his name</l>
               <l n="62">Through ages, countless as to Caesar's self</l>
               <l n="63">From the first birth-dawn of Tithonus old.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="49">
               <l n="64">If eager for the prized Olympian palm</l>
               <l n="65">One breed the horse, or bullock strong to plough,</l>
               <l n="66">Be his prime care a shapely dam to choose.</l>
               <l n="67">Of kine grim-faced is goodliest, with coarse head</l>
               <l n="68">And burly neck, whose hanging dewlaps reach</l>
               <l n="69">From chin to knee; of boundless length her flank;</l>
               <l n="70">Large every way she is, large-footed even,</l>
               <l n="71">With incurved horns and shaggy ears beneath.</l>
               <l n="72">Nor let mislike me one with spots of white</l>
               <l n="73">Conspicuous, or that spurns the yoke, whose horn</l>
               <l n="74">At times hath vice in't: liker bull-faced she,</l>
               <l n="75">And tall-limbed wholly, and with tip of tail</l>
               <l n="76">Brushing her footsteps as she walks along.</l>
               <l n="77">The age for Hymen's rites, Lucina's pangs,</l>
               <l n="78">Ere ten years ended, after four begins;</l>
               <l n="79">Their residue of days nor apt to teem,</l>
               <l n="80">Nor strong for ploughing. Meantime, while youth's delight</l>
               <l n="81">Survives within them, loose the males: be first</l>
               <l n="82">To speed thy herds of cattle to their loves,</l>
               <l n="83">Breed stock with stock, and keep the race supplied.</l>
               <l n="84">Ah! life's best hours are ever first to fly</l>
               <l n="85">From hapless mortals; in their place succeed</l>
               <l n="86">Disease and dolorous eld; till travail sore</l>
               <l n="87">And death unpitying sweep them from the scene.</l>
               <l n="88">Still will be some, whose form thou fain wouldst change;</l>
               <l n="89">Renew them still; with yearly choice of young</l>
               <l n="90">Preventing losses, lest too late thou rue.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="72">
               <l n="91">Nor steeds crave less selection; but on those</l>
               <l n="92">Thou think'st to rear, the promise of their line,</l>
               <l n="93">From earliest youth thy chiefest pains bestow.</l>
               <l n="94">See from the first yon high-bred colt afield,</l>
               <l n="95">His lofty step, his limbs' elastic tread:</l>
               <l n="96">Dauntless he leads the herd, still first to try</l>
               <l n="97">The threatening flood, or brave the unknown bridge,</l>
               <l n="98">By no vain noise affrighted; lofty-necked,</l>
               <l n="99">With clean-cut head, short belly, and stout back;</l>
               <l n="100">His sprightly breast exuberant with brawn.</l>
               <l n="101">Chestnut and grey are good; the worst-hued white</l>
               <l n="102">And sorrel. Then lo! if arms are clashed afar,</l>
               <l n="103">Bide still he cannot: ears stiffen and limbs quake;</l>
               <l n="104">His nostrils snort and roll out wreaths of fire.</l>
               <l n="105">Dense is his mane, that when uplifted falls</l>
               <l n="106">On his right shoulder; betwixt either loin</l>
               <l n="107">The spine runs double; his earth-dinting hoof</l>
               <l n="108">Rings with the ponderous beat of solid horn.</l>
               <l n="109">Even such a horse was Cyllarus, reined and tamed</l>
               <l n="110">By Pollux of Amyclae; such the pair</l>
               <l n="111">In Grecian song renowned, those steeds of Mars,</l>
               <l n="112">And famed Achilles' team: in such-like form</l>
               <l n="113">Great Saturn's self with mane flung loose on neck</l>
               <l n="114">Sped at his wife's approach, and flying filled</l>
               <l n="115">The heights of <placeName key="tgn,4008379">Pelion</placeName> with his piercing neigh.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="95">
               <l n="116">Even him, when sore disease or sluggish eld</l>
               <l n="117">Now saps his strength, pen fast at home, and spare</l>
               <l n="118">His not inglorious age. A horse grown old</l>
               <l n="119">Slow kindling unto love in vain prolongs</l>
               <l n="120">The fruitless task, and, to the encounter come,</l>
               <l n="121">As fire in stubble blusters without strength,</l>
               <l n="122">He rages idly. Therefore mark thou first</l>
               <l n="123">Their age and mettle, other points anon,</l>
               <l n="124">As breed and lineage, or what pain was theirs</l>
               <l n="125">To lose the race, what pride the palm to win.</l>
               <l n="126">Seest how the chariots in mad rivalry</l>
               <l n="127">Poured from the barrier grip the course and go,</l>
               <l n="128">When youthful hope is highest, and every heart</l>
               <l n="129">Drained with each wild pulsation? How they ply</l>
               <l n="130">The circling lash, and reaching forward let</l>
               <l n="131">The reins hang free! Swift spins the glowing wheel;</l>
               <l n="132">And now they stoop, and now erect in air</l>
               <l n="133">Seem borne through space and towering to the sky:</l>
               <l n="134">No stop, no stay; the dun sand whirls aloft;</l>
               <l n="135">They reek with foam-flakes and pursuing breath;</l>
               <l n="136">So sweet is fame, so prized the victor's palm.</l>
               <l n="137">'Twas Ericthonius first took heart to yoke</l>
               <l n="138">Four horses to his car, and rode above</l>
               <l n="139">The whirling wheels to victory: but the ring</l>
               <l n="140">And bridle-reins, mounted on horses' backs,</l>
               <l n="141">The Pelethronian Lapithae bequeathed,</l>
               <l n="142">And taught the knight in arms to spurn the ground,</l>
               <l n="143">And arch the upgathered footsteps of his pride.</l>
               <l n="144">Each task alike is arduous, and for each</l>
               <l n="145">A horse young, fiery, swift of foot, they seek;</l>
               <l n="146">How oft so-e'er yon rival may have chased</l>
               <l n="147">The flying foe, or boast his native plain</l>
               <l n="148">
                  <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>, or <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>'s stubborn hold,</l>
               <l n="149">And trace his lineage back to Neptune's birth.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="123">
               <l n="150">These points regarded, as the time draws nigh,</l>
               <l n="151">With instant zeal they lavish all their care</l>
               <l n="152">To plump with solid fat the chosen chief</l>
               <l n="153">And designated husband of the herd:</l>
               <l n="154">And flowery herbs they cut, and serve him well</l>
               <l n="155">With corn and running water, that his strength</l>
               <l n="156">Not fail him for that labour of delight,</l>
               <l n="157">Nor puny colts betray the feeble sire.</l>
               <l n="158">The herd itself of purpose they reduce</l>
               <l n="159">To leanness, and when love's sweet longing first</l>
               <l n="160">Provokes them, they forbid the leafy food,</l>
               <l n="161">And pen them from the springs, and oft beside</l>
               <l n="162">With running shake, and tire them in the sun,</l>
               <l n="163">What time the threshing-floor groans heavily</l>
               <l n="164">With pounding of the corn-ears, and light chaff</l>
               <l n="165">Is whirled on high to catch the rising west.</l>
               <l n="166">This do they that the soil's prolific powers</l>
               <l n="167">May not be dulled by surfeiting, nor choke</l>
               <l n="168">The sluggish furrows, but eagerly absorb</l>
               <l n="169">Their fill of love, and deeply entertain.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="138">
               <l n="170">To care of sire the mother's care succeeds.</l>
               <l n="171">When great with young they wander nigh their time,</l>
               <l n="172">Let no man suffer them to drag the yoke</l>
               <l n="173">In heavy wains, nor leap across the way,</l>
               <l n="174">Nor scour the meads, nor swim the rushing flood.</l>
               <l n="175">In lonely lawns they feed them, by the course</l>
               <l n="176">Of brimming streams, where moss is, and the banks</l>
               <l n="177">With grass are greenest, where are sheltering caves,</l>
               <l n="178">And far outstretched the rock-flung shadow lies.</l>
               <l n="179">Round wooded Silarus and the ilex-bowers</l>
               <l n="180">Of green Alburnus swarms a winged pest—</l>
               <l n="181">Its Roman name Asilus, by the Greeks</l>
               <l n="182">Termed Oestros—fierce it is, and harshly hums,</l>
               <l n="183">Driving whole herds in terror through the groves,</l>
               <l n="184">Till heaven is madded by their bellowing din,</l>
               <l n="185">And Tanager's dry bed and forest-banks.</l>
               <l n="186">With this same scourge did Juno wreak of old</l>
               <l n="187">The terrors of her wrath, a plague devised</l>
               <l n="188">Against the heifer sprung from Inachus.</l>
               <l n="189">From this too thou, since in the noontide heats</l>
               <l n="190">'Tis most persistent, fend thy teeming herds,</l>
               <l n="191">And feed them when the sun is newly risen,</l>
               <l n="192">Or the first stars are ushering in the night.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="157">
               <l n="193">But, yeaning ended, all their tender care</l>
               <l n="194">Is to the calves transferred; at once with marks</l>
               <l n="195">They brand them, both to designate their race,</l>
               <l n="196">And which to rear for breeding, or devote</l>
               <l n="197">As altar-victims, or to cleave the ground</l>
               <l n="198">And into ridges tear and turn the sod.</l>
               <l n="199">The rest along the greensward graze at will.</l>
               <l n="200">Those that to rustic uses thou wouldst mould,</l>
               <l n="201">As calves encourage and take steps to tame,</l>
               <l n="202">While pliant wills and plastic youth allow.</l>
               <l n="203">And first of slender withies round the throat</l>
               <l n="204">Loose collars hang, then when their free-born necks</l>
               <l n="205">Are used to service, with the self-same bands</l>
               <l n="206">Yoke them in pairs, and steer by steer compel</l>
               <l n="207">Keep pace together. And time it is that oft</l>
               <l n="208">Unfreighted wheels be drawn along the ground</l>
               <l n="209">Behind them, as to dint the surface-dust;</l>
               <l n="210">Then let the beechen axle strain and creak</l>
               <l n="211">'Neath some stout burden, whilst a brazen pole</l>
               <l n="212">Drags on the wheels made fast thereto. Meanwhile</l>
               <l n="213">For their unbroken youth not grass alone,</l>
               <l n="214">Nor meagre willow-leaves and marish-sedge,</l>
               <l n="215">But corn-ears with thy hand pluck from the crops.</l>
               <l n="216">Nor shall the brood-kine, as of yore, for thee</l>
               <l n="217">Brim high the snowy milking-pail, but spend</l>
               <l n="218">Their udders' fullness on their own sweet young.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="179">
               <l n="219">But if fierce squadrons and the ranks of war</l>
               <l n="220">Delight thee rather, or on wheels to glide</l>
               <l n="221">At <placeName key="perseus,Pisa">Pisa</placeName>, with Alpheus fleeting by,</l>
               <l n="222">And in the grove of Jupiter urge on</l>
               <l n="223">The flying chariot, be your steed's first task</l>
               <l n="224">To face the warrior's armed rage, and brook</l>
               <l n="225">The trumpet, and long roar of rumbling wheels,</l>
               <l n="226">And clink of chiming bridles in the stall;</l>
               <l n="227">Then more and more to love his master's voice</l>
               <l n="228">Caressing, or loud hand that claps his neck.</l>
               <l n="229">Ay, thus far let him learn to dare, when first</l>
               <l n="230">Weaned from his mother, and his mouth at times</l>
               <l n="231">Yield to the supple halter, even while yet</l>
               <l n="232">Weak, tottering-limbed, and ignorant of life.</l>
               <l n="233">But, three years ended, when the fourth arrives,</l>
               <l n="234">Now let him tarry not to run the ring</l>
               <l n="235">With rhythmic hoof-beat echoing, and now learn</l>
               <l n="236">Alternately to curve each bending leg,</l>
               <l n="237">And be like one that struggleth; then at last</l>
               <l n="238">Challenge the winds to race him, and at speed</l>
               <l n="239">Launched through the open, like a reinless thing,</l>
               <l n="240">Scarce print his footsteps on the surface-sand.</l>
               <l n="241">As when with power from Hyperborean climes</l>
               <l n="242">The north wind stoops, and scatters from his path</l>
               <l n="243">Dry clouds and storms of <placeName key="tgn,6005315">Scythia</placeName>; the tall corn</l>
               <l n="244">And rippling plains 'gin shiver with light gusts;</l>
               <l n="245">A sound is heard among the forest-tops;</l>
               <l n="246">Long waves come racing shoreward: fast he flies,</l>
               <l n="247">With instant pinion sweeping earth and main.</l>
               <l n="248">A steed like this or on the mighty course</l>
               <l n="249">Of <placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> at the goal will sweat, and shower</l>
               <l n="250">Red foam-flakes from his mouth, or, kindlier task,</l>
               <l n="251">With patient neck support the Belgian car.</l>
               <l n="252">Then, broken at last, let swell their burly frame</l>
               <l n="253">With fattening corn-mash, for, unbroke, they will</l>
               <l n="254">With pride wax wanton, and, when caught, refuse</l>
               <l n="255">Tough lash to brook or jagged curb obey.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="209">
               <l n="256">But no device so fortifies their power</l>
               <l n="257">As love's blind stings of passion to forefend,</l>
               <l n="258">Whether on steed or steer thy choice be set.</l>
               <l n="259">Ay, therefore 'tis they banish bulls afar</l>
               <l n="260">To solitary pastures, or behind</l>
               <l n="261">Some mountain-barrier, or broad streams beyond,</l>
               <l n="262">Or else in plenteous stalls pen fast at home.</l>
               <l n="263">For, even through sight of her, the female wastes</l>
               <l n="264">His strength with smouldering fire, till he forget</l>
               <l n="265">Both grass and woodland. She indeed full oft</l>
               <l n="266">With her sweet charms can lovers proud compel</l>
               <l n="267">To battle for the conquest horn to horn.</l>
               <l n="268">In Sila's forest feeds the heifer fair,</l>
               <l n="269">While each on each the furious rivals run;</l>
               <l n="270">Wound follows wound; the black blood laves their limbs;</l>
               <l n="271">Horns push and strive against opposing horns,</l>
               <l n="272">With mighty groaning; all the forest-side</l>
               <l n="273">And far <placeName key="perseus,Olympos,Lycia">Olympus</placeName> bellow back the roar.</l>
               <l n="274">Nor wont the champions in one stall to couch;</l>
               <l n="275">But he that's worsted hies him to strange climes</l>
               <l n="276">Far off, an exile, moaning much the shame,</l>
               <l n="277">The blows of that proud conqueror, then love's loss</l>
               <l n="278">Avenged not; with one glance toward the byre,</l>
               <l n="279">His ancient royalties behind him lie.</l>
               <l n="280">So with all heed his strength he practiseth,</l>
               <l n="281">And nightlong makes the hard bare stones his bed,</l>
               <l n="282">And feeds on prickly leaf and pointed rush,</l>
               <l n="283">And proves himself, and butting at a tree</l>
               <l n="284">Learns to fling wrath into his horns, with blows</l>
               <l n="285">Provokes the air, and scattering clouds of sand</l>
               <l n="286">Makes prelude of the battle; afterward,</l>
               <l n="287">With strength repaired and gathered might breaks camp,</l>
               <l n="288">And hurls him headlong on the unthinking foe:</l>
               <l n="289">As in mid ocean when a wave far of</l>
               <l n="290">Begins to whiten, mustering from the main</l>
               <l n="291">Its rounded breast, and, onward rolled to land</l>
               <l n="292">Falls with prodigious roar among the rocks,</l>
               <l n="293">Huge as a very mountain: but the depths</l>
               <l n="294">Upseethe in swirling eddies, and disgorge</l>
               <l n="295">The murky sand-lees from their sunken bed.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="242">
               <l n="296">Nay, every race on earth of men, and beasts,</l>
               <l n="297">And ocean-folk, and flocks, and painted birds,</l>
               <l n="298">Rush to the raging fire: love sways them all.</l>
               <l n="299">Never than then more fiercely o'er the plain</l>
               <l n="300">Prowls heedless of her whelps the lioness:</l>
               <l n="301">Nor monstrous bears such wide-spread havoc-doom</l>
               <l n="302">Deal through the forests; then the boar is fierce,</l>
               <l n="303">Most deadly then the tigress: then, alack!</l>
               <l n="304">Ill roaming is it on <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>'s lonely plains.</l>
               <l n="305">Mark you what shivering thrills the horse's frame,</l>
               <l n="306">If but a waft the well-known gust conveys?</l>
               <l n="307">Nor curb can check them then, nor lash severe,</l>
               <l n="308">Nor rocks and caverned crags, nor barrier-floods,</l>
               <l n="309">That rend and whirl and wash the hills away.</l>
               <l n="310">Then speeds amain the great Sabellian boar,</l>
               <l n="311">His tushes whets, with forefoot tears the ground,</l>
               <l n="312">Rubs 'gainst a tree his flanks, and to and fro</l>
               <l n="313">Hardens each wallowing shoulder to the wound.</l>
               <l n="314">What of the youth, when love's relentless might</l>
               <l n="315">Stirs the fierce fire within his veins? Behold!</l>
               <l n="316">In blindest midnight how he swims the gulf</l>
               <l n="317">Convulsed with bursting storm-clouds! Over him</l>
               <l n="318">Heaven's huge gate thunders; the rock-shattered main</l>
               <l n="319">Utters a warning cry; nor parents' tears</l>
               <l n="320">Can backward call him, nor the maid he loves,</l>
               <l n="321">Too soon to die on his untimely pyre.</l>
               <l n="322">What of the spotted ounce to Bacchus dear,</l>
               <l n="323">Or warlike wolf-kin or the breed of dogs?</l>
               <l n="324">Why tell how timorous stags the battle join?</l>
               <l n="325">O'er all conspicuous is the rage of mares,</l>
               <l n="326">By Venus' self inspired of old, what time</l>
               <l n="327">The Potnian four with rending jaws devoured</l>
               <l n="328">The limbs of Glaucus. Love-constrained they roam</l>
               <l n="329">Past Gargarus, past the loud Ascanian flood;</l>
               <l n="330">They climb the mountains, and the torrents swim;</l>
               <l n="331">And when their eager marrow first conceives</l>
               <l n="332">The fire, in Spring-tide chiefly, for with Spring</l>
               <l n="333">Warmth doth their frames revisit, then they stand</l>
               <l n="334">All facing westward on the rocky heights,</l>
               <l n="335">And of the gentle breezes take their fill;</l>
               <l n="336">And oft unmated, marvellous to tell,</l>
               <l n="337">But of the wind impregnate, far and wide</l>
               <l n="338">O'er craggy height and lowly vale they scud,</l>
               <l n="339">Not toward thy rising, Eurus, or the sun's,</l>
               <l n="340">But westward and north-west, or whence up-springs</l>
               <l n="341">Black Auster, that glooms heaven with rainy cold.</l>
               <l n="342">Hence from their groin slow drips a poisonous juice,</l>
               <l n="343">By shepherds truly named hippomanes,</l>
               <l n="344">Hippomanes, fell stepdames oft have culled,</l>
               <l n="345">And mixed with herbs and spells of baneful bode.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="284">
               <l n="346">Fast flies meanwhile the irreparable hour,</l>
               <l n="347">As point to point our charmed round we trace.</l>
               <l n="348">Enough of herds. This second task remains,</l>
               <l n="349">The wool-clad flocks and shaggy goats to treat.</l>
               <l n="350">Here lies a labour; hence for glory look,</l>
               <l n="351">Brave husbandmen. Nor doubtfully know</l>
               <l n="352">How hard it is for words to triumph here,</l>
               <l n="353">And shed their lustre on a theme so slight:</l>
               <l n="354">But I am caught by ravishing desire</l>
               <l n="355">Above the lone Parnassian steep; I love</l>
               <l n="356">To walk the heights, from whence no earlier track</l>
               <l n="357">Slopes gently downward to Castalia's spring.</l>
               <l n="358">Now, awful Pales, strike a louder tone.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="295">
               <l n="359">First, for the sheep soft pencotes I decree</l>
               <l n="360">To browse in, till green summer's swift return;</l>
               <l n="361">And that the hard earth under them with straw</l>
               <l n="362">And handfuls of the fern be littered deep,</l>
               <l n="363">Lest chill of ice such tender cattle harm</l>
               <l n="364">With scab and loathly foot-rot. Passing thence</l>
               <l n="365">I bid the goats with arbute-leaves be stored,</l>
               <l n="366">And served with fresh spring-water, and their pens</l>
               <l n="367">Turned southward from the blast, to face the suns</l>
               <l n="368">Of winter, when Aquarius' icy beam</l>
               <l n="369">Now sinks in showers upon the parting year.</l>
               <l n="370">These too no lightlier our protection claim,</l>
               <l n="371">Nor prove of poorer service, howsoe'er</l>
               <l n="372">Milesian fleeces dipped in Tyrian reds</l>
               <l n="373">Repay the barterer; these with offspring teem</l>
               <l n="374">More numerous; these yield plenteous store of milk:</l>
               <l n="375">The more each dry-wrung udder froths the pail,</l>
               <l n="376">More copious soon the teat-pressed torrents flow.</l>
               <l n="377">Ay, and on Cinyps' bank the he-goats too</l>
               <l n="378">Their beards and grizzled chins and bristling hair</l>
               <l n="379">Let clip for camp-use, or as rugs to wrap</l>
               <l n="380">Seafaring wretches. But they browse the woods</l>
               <l n="381">And summits of Lycaeus, and rough briers,</l>
               <l n="382">And brakes that love the highland: of themselves</l>
               <l n="383">Right heedfully the she-goats homeward troop</l>
               <l n="384">Before their kids, and with plump udders clogged</l>
               <l n="385">Scarce cross the threshold. Wherefore rather ye,</l>
               <l n="386">The less they crave man's vigilance, be fain</l>
               <l n="387">From ice to fend them and from snowy winds;</l>
               <l n="388">Bring food and feast them with their branchy fare,</l>
               <l n="389">Nor lock your hay-loft all the winter long.</l>
               <l n="390">But when glad summer at the west wind's call</l>
               <l n="391">Sends either flock to pasture in the glades,</l>
               <l n="392">Soon as the day-star shineth, hie we then</l>
               <l n="393">To the cool meadows, while the dawn is young,</l>
               <l n="394">The grass yet hoary, and to browsing herds</l>
               <l n="395">The dew tastes sweetest on the tender sward.</l>
               <l n="396">When heaven's fourth hour draws on the thickening drought,</l>
               <l n="397">And shrill cicalas pierce the brake with song,</l>
               <l n="398">Then at the well-springs bid them, or deep pools,</l>
               <l n="399">From troughs of holm-oak quaff the running wave:</l>
               <l n="400">But at day's hottest seek a shadowy vale,</l>
               <l n="401">Where some vast ancient-timbered oak of Jove</l>
               <l n="402">Spreads his huge branches, or where huddling black</l>
               <l n="403">Ilex on ilex cowers in awful shade.</l>
               <l n="404">Then once more give them water sparingly,</l>
               <l n="405">And feed once more, till sunset, when cool eve</l>
               <l n="406">Allays the air, and dewy moonbeams slake</l>
               <l n="407">The forest glades, with halcyon's song the shore,</l>
               <l n="408">And every thicket with the goldfinch rings.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="239">
               <l n="409">Of <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>'s shepherds why the tale pursue?</l>
               <l n="410">Why sing their pastures and the scattered huts</l>
               <l n="411">They house in? Oft their cattle day and night</l>
               <l n="412">Graze the whole month together, and go forth</l>
               <l n="413">Into far deserts where no shelter is,</l>
               <l n="414">So flat the plain and boundless. All his goods</l>
               <l n="415">The Afric swain bears with him, house and home,</l>
               <l n="416">Arms, Cretan quiver, and Amyclaean dog;</l>
               <l n="417">As some keen Roman in his country's arms</l>
               <l n="418">Plies the swift march beneath a cruel load;</l>
               <l n="419">Soon with tents pitched and at his post he stands,</l>
               <l n="420">Ere looked for by the foe.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="349">
               <l n="421">Not thus the tribes</l>
               <l n="422">Of <placeName key="tgn,6005315">Scythia</placeName> by the far Maeotic wave,</l>
               <l n="423">Where turbid Ister whirls his yellow sands,</l>
               <l n="424">And <placeName key="tgn,7002754">Rhodope</placeName> stretched out beneath the pole</l>
               <l n="425">Comes trending backward. There the herds they keep</l>
               <l n="426">Close-pent in byres, nor any grass is seen</l>
               <l n="427">Upon the plain, nor leaves upon the tree:</l>
               <l n="428">But with snow-ridges and deep frost afar</l>
               <l n="429">Heaped seven ells high the earth lies featureless:</l>
               <l n="430">Still winter? still the north wind's icy breath!</l>
               <l n="431">Nay, never sun disparts the shadows pale,</l>
               <l n="432">Or as he rides the steep of heaven, or dips</l>
               <l n="433">In ocean's fiery bath his plunging car.</l>
               <l n="434">Quick ice-crusts curdle on the running stream,</l>
               <l n="435">And iron-hooped wheels the water's back now bears,</l>
               <l n="436">To broad wains opened, as erewhile to ships;</l>
               <l n="437">Brass vessels oft asunder burst, and clothes</l>
               <l n="438">Stiffen upon the wearers; juicy wines</l>
               <l n="439">They cleave with axes; to one frozen mass</l>
               <l n="440">Whole pools are turned; and on their untrimmed beards</l>
               <l n="441">Stiff clings the jagged icicle. Meanwhile</l>
               <l n="442">All heaven no less is filled with falling snow;</l>
               <l n="443">The cattle perish: oxen's mighty frames</l>
               <l n="444">Stand island-like amid the frost, and stags</l>
               <l n="445">In huddling herds, by that strange weight benumbed,</l>
               <l n="446">Scarce top the surface with their antler-points.</l>
               <l n="447">These with no hounds they hunt, nor net with toils,</l>
               <l n="448">Nor scare with terror of the crimson plume;</l>
               <l n="449">But, as in vain they breast the opposing block,</l>
               <l n="450">Butcher them, knife in hand, and so dispatch</l>
               <l n="451">Loud-bellowing, and with glad shouts hale them home.</l>
               <l n="452">Themselves in deep-dug caverns underground</l>
               <l n="453">Dwell free and careless; to their hearths they heave</l>
               <l n="454">Oak-logs and elm-trees whole, and fire them there,</l>
               <l n="455">There play the night out, and in festive glee</l>
               <l n="456">With barm and service sour the wine-cup mock.</l>
               <l n="457">So 'neath the seven-starred Hyperborean wain</l>
               <l n="458">The folk live tameless, buffeted with blasts</l>
               <l n="459">Of Eurus from Rhipaean hills, and wrap</l>
               <l n="460">Their bodies in the tawny fells of beasts.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="384">
               <l n="461">If wool delight thee, first, be far removed</l>
               <l n="462">All prickly boskage, burrs and caltrops; shun</l>
               <l n="463">Luxuriant pastures; at the outset choose</l>
               <l n="464">White flocks with downy fleeces. For the ram,</l>
               <l n="465">How white soe'er himself, be but the tongue</l>
               <l n="466">'Neath his moist palate black, reject him, lest</l>
               <l n="467">He sully with dark spots his offspring's fleece,</l>
               <l n="468">And seek some other o'er the teeming plain.</l>
               <l n="469">Even with such snowy bribe of wool, if ear</l>
               <l n="470">May trust the tale, Pan, God of Arcady,</l>
               <l n="471">Snared and beguiled thee, <placeName key="tgn,7010011">Luna</placeName>, calling thee</l>
               <l n="472">To the deep woods; nor thou didst spurn his call.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="394">
               <l n="473">But who for milk hath longing, must himself</l>
               <l n="474">Carry lucerne and lotus-leaves enow</l>
               <l n="475">With salt herbs to the cote, whence more they love</l>
               <l n="476">The streams, more stretch their udders, and give back</l>
               <l n="477">A subtle taste of saltness in the milk.</l>
               <l n="478">Many there be who from their mothers keep</l>
               <l n="479">The new-born kids, and straightway bind their mouths</l>
               <l n="480">With iron-tipped muzzles. What they milk at dawn,</l>
               <l n="481">Or in the daylight hours, at night they press;</l>
               <l n="482">What darkling or at sunset, this ere morn</l>
               <l n="483">They bear away in baskets—for to town</l>
               <l n="484">The shepherd hies him—or with dash of salt</l>
               <l n="485">Just sprinkle, and lay by for winter use.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="404">
               <l n="486">Nor be thy dogs last cared for; but alike</l>
               <l n="487">Swift Spartan hounds and fierce Molossian feed</l>
               <l n="488">On fattening whey. Never, with these to watch,</l>
               <l n="489">Dread nightly thief afold and ravening wolves,</l>
               <l n="490">Or Spanish desperadoes in the rear.</l>
               <l n="491">And oft the shy wild asses thou wilt chase,</l>
               <l n="492">With hounds, too, hunt the hare, with hounds the doe;</l>
               <l n="493">Oft from his woodland wallowing-den uprouse</l>
               <l n="494">The boar, and scare him with their baying, and drive,</l>
               <l n="495">And o'er the mountains urge into the toils</l>
               <l n="496">Some antlered monster to their chiming cry.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="414">
               <l n="497">Learn also scented cedar-wood to burn</l>
               <l n="498">Within the stalls, and snakes of noxious smell</l>
               <l n="499">With fumes of galbanum to drive away.</l>
               <l n="500">Oft under long-neglected cribs, or lurks</l>
               <l n="501">A viper ill to handle, that hath fled</l>
               <l n="502">The light in terror, or some snake, that wont</l>
               <l n="503">'Neath shade and sheltering roof to creep, and shower</l>
               <l n="504">Its bane among the cattle, hugs the ground,</l>
               <l n="505">Fell scourge of kine. Shepherd, seize stakes, seize stones!</l>
               <l n="506">And as he rears defiance, and puffs out</l>
               <l n="507">A hissing throat, down with him! see how low</l>
               <l n="508">That cowering crest is vailed in flight, the while,</l>
               <l n="509">His midmost coils and final sweep of tail</l>
               <l n="510">Relaxing, the last fold drags lingering spires.</l>
               <l n="511">Then that vile worm that in Calabrian glades</l>
               <l n="512">Uprears his breast, and wreathes a scaly back,</l>
               <l n="513">His length of belly pied with mighty spots—</l>
               <l n="514">While from their founts gush any streams, while yet</l>
               <l n="515">With showers of Spring and rainy south-winds earth</l>
               <l n="516">Is moistened, lo! he haunts the pools, and here</l>
               <l n="517">Housed in the banks, with fish and chattering frogs</l>
               <l n="518">Crams the black void of his insatiate maw.</l>
               <l n="519">Soon as the fens are parched, and earth with heat</l>
               <l n="520">Is gaping, forth he darts into the dry,</l>
               <l n="521">Rolls eyes of fire and rages through the fields,</l>
               <l n="522">Furious from thirst and by the drought dismayed.</l>
               <l n="523">Me list not then beneath the open heaven</l>
               <l n="524">To snatch soft slumber, nor on forest-ridge</l>
               <l n="525">Lie stretched along the grass, when, slipped his slough,</l>
               <l n="526">To glittering youth transformed he winds his spires,</l>
               <l n="527">And eggs or younglings leaving in his lair,</l>
               <l n="528">Towers sunward, lightening with three-forked tongue.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="440">
               <l n="529">Of sickness, too, the causes and the signs</l>
               <l n="530">I'll teach thee. Loathly scab assails the sheep,</l>
               <l n="531">When chilly showers have probed them to the quick,</l>
               <l n="532">And winter stark with hoar-frost, or when sweat</l>
               <l n="533">Unpurged cleaves to them after shearing done,</l>
               <l n="534">And rough thorns rend their bodies. Hence it is</l>
               <l n="535">Shepherds their whole flock steep in running streams,</l>
               <l n="536">While, plunged beneath the flood, with drenched fell,</l>
               <l n="537">The ram, launched free, goes drifting down the tide.</l>
               <l n="538">Else, having shorn, they smear their bodies o'er</l>
               <l n="539">With acrid oil-lees, and mix silver-scum</l>
               <l n="540">And native sulphur and Idaean pitch,</l>
               <l n="541">Wax mollified with ointment, and therewith</l>
               <l n="542">Sea-leek, strong hellebores, bitumen black.</l>
               <l n="543">Yet ne'er doth kindlier fortune crown his toil,</l>
               <l n="544">Than if with blade of iron a man dare lance</l>
               <l n="545">The ulcer's mouth ope: for the taint is fed</l>
               <l n="546">And quickened by confinement; while the swain</l>
               <l n="547">His hand of healing from the wound withholds,</l>
               <l n="548">Or sits for happier signs imploring heaven.</l>
               <l n="549">Aye, and when inward to the bleater's bones</l>
               <l n="550">The pain hath sunk and rages, and their limbs</l>
               <l n="551">By thirsty fever are consumed, 'tis good</l>
               <l n="552">To draw the enkindled heat therefrom, and pierce</l>
               <l n="553">Within the hoof-clefts a blood-bounding vein.</l>
               <l n="554">Of tribes Bisaltic such the wonted use,</l>
               <l n="555">And keen Gelonian, when to <placeName key="tgn,7002754">Rhodope</placeName>
               </l>
               <l n="556">He flies, or Getic desert, and quaffs milk</l>
               <l n="557">With horse-blood curdled. Seest one far afield</l>
               <l n="558">Oft to the shade's mild covert win, or pull</l>
               <l n="559">The grass tops listlessly, or hindmost lag,</l>
               <l n="560">Or, browsing, cast her down amid the plain,</l>
               <l n="561">At night retire belated and alone;</l>
               <l n="562">With quick knife check the mischief, ere it creep</l>
               <l n="563">With dire contagion through the unwary herd.</l>
               <l n="564">Less thick and fast the whirlwind scours the main</l>
               <l n="565">With tempest in its wake, than swarm the plagues</l>
               <l n="566">Of cattle; nor seize they single lives alone,</l>
               <l n="567">But sudden clear whole feeding grounds, the flock</l>
               <l n="568">With all its promise, and extirpate the breed.</l>
               <l n="569">Well would he trow it who, so long after, still</l>
               <l n="570">High Alps and Noric hill-forts should behold,</l>
               <l n="571">And Iapydian Timavus' fields,</l>
               <l n="572">Ay, still behold the shepherds' realms a waste,</l>
               <l n="573">And far and wide the lawns untenanted.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="478">
               <l n="574">Here from distempered heavens erewhile arose</l>
               <l n="575">A piteous season, with the full fierce heat</l>
               <l n="576">Of autumn glowed, and cattle-kindreds all</l>
               <l n="577">And all wild creatures to destruction gave,</l>
               <l n="578">Tainted the pools, the fodder charged with bane.</l>
               <l n="579">Nor simple was the way of death, but when</l>
               <l n="580">Hot thirst through every vein impelled had drawn</l>
               <l n="581">Their wretched limbs together, anon o'erflowed</l>
               <l n="582">A watery flux, and all their bones piecemeal</l>
               <l n="583">Sapped by corruption to itself absorbed.</l>
               <l n="584">Oft in mid sacrifice to heaven—the white</l>
               <l n="585">Wool-woven fillet half wreathed about his brow—</l>
               <l n="586">Some victim, standing by the altar, there</l>
               <l n="587">Betwixt the loitering carles a-dying fell:</l>
               <l n="588">Or, if betimes the slaughtering priest had struck,</l>
               <l n="589">Nor with its heaped entrails blazed the pile,</l>
               <l n="590">Nor seer to seeker thence could answer yield;</l>
               <l n="591">Nay, scarce the up-stabbing knife with blood was stained,</l>
               <l n="592">Scarce sullied with thin gore the surface-sand.</l>
               <l n="593">Hence die the calves in many a pasture fair,</l>
               <l n="594">Or at full cribs their lives' sweet breath resign;</l>
               <l n="595">Hence on the fawning dog comes madness, hence</l>
               <l n="596">Racks the sick swine a gasping cough that chokes</l>
               <l n="597">With swelling at the jaws: the conquering steed,</l>
               <l n="598">Uncrowned of effort and heedless of the sward,</l>
               <l n="599">Faints, turns him from the springs, and paws the earth</l>
               <l n="600">With ceaseless hoof: low droop his ears, wherefrom</l>
               <l n="601">Bursts fitful sweat, a sweat that waxes cold</l>
               <l n="602">Upon the dying beast; the skin is dry,</l>
               <l n="603">And rigidly repels the handler's touch.</l>
               <l n="604">These earlier signs they give that presage doom.</l>
               <l n="605">But, if the advancing plague 'gin fiercer grow,</l>
               <l n="606">Then are their eyes all fire, deep-drawn their breath,</l>
               <l n="607">At times groan-laboured: with long sobbing heave</l>
               <l n="608">Their lowest flanks; from either nostril streams</l>
               <l n="609">Black blood; a rough tongue clogs the obstructed jaws.</l>
               <l n="610">'Twas helpful through inverted horn to pour</l>
               <l n="611">Draughts of the wine-god down; sole way it seemed</l>
               <l n="612">To save the dying: soon this too proved their bane,</l>
               <l n="613">And, reinvigorate but with frenzy's fire,</l>
               <l n="614">Even at death's pinch—the gods some happier fate</l>
               <l n="615">Deal to the just, such madness to their foes—</l>
               <l n="616">Each with bared teeth his own limbs mangling tore.</l>
               <l n="617">See! as he smokes beneath the stubborn share,</l>
               <l n="618">The bull drops, vomiting foam-dabbled gore,</l>
               <l n="619">And heaves his latest groans. Sad goes the swain,</l>
               <l n="620">Unhooks the steer that mourns his fellow's fate,</l>
               <l n="621">And in mid labour leaves the plough-gear fast.</l>
               <l n="622">Nor tall wood's shadow, nor soft sward may stir</l>
               <l n="623">That heart's emotion, nor rock-channelled flood,</l>
               <l n="624">More pure than amber speeding to the plain:</l>
               <l n="625">But see! his flanks fail under him, his eyes</l>
               <l n="626">Are dulled with deadly torpor, and his neck</l>
               <l n="627">Sinks to the earth with drooping weight.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="525">
               <l n="628">What now</l>
               <l n="629">Besteads him toil or service? to have turned</l>
               <l n="630">The heavy sod with ploughshare? And yet these</l>
               <l n="631">Ne'er knew the Massic wine-god's baneful boon,</l>
               <l n="632">Nor twice replenished banquets: but on leaves</l>
               <l n="633">They fare, and virgin grasses, and their cups</l>
               <l n="634">Are crystal springs and streams with running tired,</l>
               <l n="635">Their healthful slumbers never broke by care.</l>
               <l n="636">Then only, say they, through that country side</l>
               <l n="637">For Juno's rites were cattle far to seek,</l>
               <l n="638">And ill-matched buffaloes the chariots drew</l>
               <l n="639">To their high fanes. So, painfully with rakes</l>
               <l n="640">They grub the soil, aye, with their very nails</l>
               <l n="641">Dig in the corn-seeds, and with strained neck</l>
               <l n="642">O'er the high uplands drag the creaking wains.</l>
               <l n="643">No wolf for ambush pries about the pen,</l>
               <l n="644">Nor round the flock prowls nightly; pain more sharp</l>
               <l n="645">Subdues him: the shy deer and fleet-foot stags</l>
               <l n="646">With hounds now wander by the haunts of men</l>
               <l n="647">Vast ocean's offspring, and all tribes that swim,</l>
               <l n="648">On the shore's confine the wave washes up,</l>
               <l n="649">Like shipwrecked bodies: seals, unwonted there,</l>
               <l n="650">Flee to the rivers. Now the viper dies,</l>
               <l n="651">For all his den's close winding, and with scales</l>
               <l n="652">Erect the astonied water-worms. The air</l>
               <l n="653">Brooks not the very birds, that headlong fall,</l>
               <l n="654">And leave their life beneath the soaring cloud.</l>
               <l n="655">Moreover now nor change of fodder serves,</l>
               <l n="656">And subtlest cures but injure; then were foiled</l>
               <l n="657">The masters, Chiron sprung from Phillyron,</l>
               <l n="658">And Amythaon's son Melampus. See!</l>
               <l n="659">From Stygian darkness launched into the light</l>
               <l n="660">Comes raging pale Tisiphone; she drives</l>
               <l n="661">Disease and fear before her, day by day</l>
               <l n="662">Still rearing higher that all-devouring head.</l>
               <l n="663">With bleat of flocks and lowings thick resound</l>
               <l n="664">Rivers and parched banks and sloping heights.</l>
               <l n="665">At last in crowds she slaughters them, she chokes</l>
               <l n="666">The very stalls with carrion-heaps that rot</l>
               <l n="667">In hideous corruption, till men learn</l>
               <l n="668">With earth to cover them, in pits to hide.</l>
               <l n="669">For e'en the fells are useless; nor the flesh</l>
               <l n="670">With water may they purge, or tame with fire,</l>
               <l n="671">Nor shear the fleeces even, gnawed through and through</l>
               <l n="672">With foul disease, nor touch the putrid webs;</l>
               <l n="673">But, had one dared the loathly weeds to try,</l>
               <l n="674">Red blisters and an unclean sweat o'erran</l>
               <l n="675">His noisome limbs, till, no long tarriance made,</l>
               <l n="676">The fiery curse his tainted frame devoured.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="1">
               <l n="1">Of air-born honey, gift of heaven, I now</l>
               <l n="2">Take up the tale. Upon this theme no less</l>
               <l n="3">Look thou, Maecenas, with indulgent eye.</l>
               <l n="4">A marvellous display of puny powers,</l>
               <l n="5">High-hearted chiefs, a nation's history,</l>
               <l n="6">Its traits, its bent, its battles and its clans,</l>
               <l n="7">All, each, shall pass before you, while I sing.</l>
               <l n="8">Slight though the poet's theme, not slight the praise,</l>
               <l n="9">So frown not heaven, and Phoebus hear his call.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="8">
               <l n="10">First find your bees a settled sure abode,</l>
               <l n="11">Where neither winds can enter (winds blow back</l>
               <l n="12">The foragers with food returning home)</l>
               <l n="13">Nor sheep and butting kids tread down the flowers,</l>
               <l n="14">Nor heifer wandering wide upon the plain</l>
               <l n="15">Dash off the dew, and bruise the springing blades.</l>
               <l n="16">Let the gay lizard too keep far aloof</l>
               <l n="17">His scale-clad body from their honied stalls,</l>
               <l n="18">And the bee-eater, and what birds beside,</l>
               <l n="19">And Procne smirched with blood upon the breast</l>
               <l n="20">From her own murderous hands. For these roam wide</l>
               <l n="21">Wasting all substance, or the bees themselves</l>
               <l n="22">Strike flying, and in their beaks bear home, to glut</l>
               <l n="23">Those savage nestlings with the dainty prey.</l>
               <l n="24">But let clear springs and moss-green pools be near,</l>
               <l n="25">And through the grass a streamlet hurrying run,</l>
               <l n="26">Some palm-tree o'er the porch extend its shade,</l>
               <l n="27">Or huge-grown oleaster, that in Spring,</l>
               <l n="28">Their own sweet Spring-tide, when the new-made chiefs</l>
               <l n="29">Lead forth the young swarms, and, escaped their comb,</l>
               <l n="30">The colony comes forth to sport and play,</l>
               <l n="31">The neighbouring bank may lure them from the heat,</l>
               <l n="32">Or bough befriend with hospitable shade.</l>
               <l n="33">O'er the mid-waters, whether swift or still,</l>
               <l n="34">Cast willow-branches and big stones enow,</l>
               <l n="35">Bridge after bridge, where they may footing find</l>
               <l n="36">And spread their wide wings to the summer sun,</l>
               <l n="37">If haply Eurus, swooping as they pause,</l>
               <l n="38">Have dashed with spray or plunged them in the deep.</l>
               <l n="39">And let green cassias and far-scented thymes,</l>
               <l n="40">And savory with its heavy-laden breath</l>
               <l n="41">Bloom round about, and violet-beds hard by</l>
               <l n="42">Sip sweetness from the fertilizing springs.</l>
               <l n="43">For the hive's self, or stitched of hollow bark,</l>
               <l n="44">Or from tough osier woven, let the doors</l>
               <l n="45">Be strait of entrance; for stiff winter's cold</l>
               <l n="46">Congeals the honey, and heat resolves and thaws,</l>
               <l n="47">To bees alike disastrous; not for naught</l>
               <l n="48">So haste they to cement the tiny pores</l>
               <l n="49">That pierce their walls, and fill the crevices</l>
               <l n="50">With pollen from the flowers, and glean and keep</l>
               <l n="51">To this same end the glue, that binds more fast</l>
               <l n="52">Than bird-lime or the pitch from Ida's pines.</l>
               <l n="53">Oft too in burrowed holes, if fame be true,</l>
               <l n="54">They make their cosy subterranean home,</l>
               <l n="55">And deeply lodged in hollow rocks are found,</l>
               <l n="56">Or in the cavern of an age-hewn tree.</l>
               <l n="57">Thou not the less smear round their crannied cribs</l>
               <l n="58">With warm smooth mud-coat, and strew leaves above;</l>
               <l n="59">But near their home let neither yew-tree grow,</l>
               <l n="60">Nor reddening crabs be roasted, and mistrust</l>
               <l n="61">Deep marish-ground and mire with noisome smell,</l>
               <l n="62">Or where the hollow rocks sonorous ring,</l>
               <l n="63">And the word spoken buffets and rebounds.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="51">
               <l n="64">What more? When now the golden sun has put</l>
               <l n="65">Winter to headlong flight beneath the world,</l>
               <l n="66">And oped the doors of heaven with summer ray,</l>
               <l n="67">Forthwith they roam the glades and forests o'er,</l>
               <l n="68">Rifle the painted flowers, or sip the streams,</l>
               <l n="69">Light-hovering on the surface. Hence it is</l>
               <l n="70">With some sweet rapture, that we know not of,</l>
               <l n="71">Their little ones they foster, hence with skill</l>
               <l n="72">Work out new wax or clinging honey mould.</l>
               <l n="73">So when the cage-escaped hosts you see</l>
               <l n="74">Float heavenward through the hot clear air, until</l>
               <l n="75">You marvel at yon dusky cloud that spreads</l>
               <l n="76">And lengthens on the wind, then mark them well;</l>
               <l n="77">For then 'tis ever the fresh springs they seek</l>
               <l n="78">And bowery shelter: hither must you bring</l>
               <l n="79">The savoury sweets I bid, and sprinkle them,</l>
               <l n="80">Bruised balsam and the wax-flower's lowly weed,</l>
               <l n="81">And wake and shake the tinkling cymbals heard</l>
               <l n="82">By the great Mother: on the anointed spots</l>
               <l n="83">Themselves will settle, and in wonted wise</l>
               <l n="84">Seek of themselves the cradle's inmost depth.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="67">
               <l n="85">But if to battle they have hied them forth—</l>
               <l n="86">For oft 'twixt king and king with uproar dire</l>
               <l n="87">Fierce feud arises, and at once from far</l>
               <l n="88">You may discern what passion sways the mob,</l>
               <l n="89">And how their hearts are throbbing for the strife;</l>
               <l n="90">Hark! the hoarse brazen note that warriors know</l>
               <l n="91">Chides on the loiterers, and the ear may catch</l>
               <l n="92">A sound that mocks the war-trump's broken blasts;</l>
               <l n="93">Then in hot haste they muster, then flash wings,</l>
               <l n="94">Sharpen their pointed beaks and knit their thews,</l>
               <l n="95">And round the king, even to his royal tent,</l>
               <l n="96">Throng rallying, and with shouts defy the foe.</l>
               <l n="97">So, when a dry Spring and clear space is given,</l>
               <l n="98">Forth from the gates they burst, they clash on high;</l>
               <l n="99">A din arises; they are heaped and rolled</l>
               <l n="100">Into one mighty mass, and headlong fall,</l>
               <l n="101">Not denselier hail through heaven, nor pelting so</l>
               <l n="102">Rains from the shaken oak its acorn-shower.</l>
               <l n="103">Conspicuous by their wings the chiefs themselves</l>
               <l n="104">Press through the heart of battle, and display</l>
               <l n="105">A giant's spirit in each pigmy frame,</l>
               <l n="106">Steadfast no inch to yield till these or those</l>
               <l n="107">The victor's ponderous arm has turned to flight.</l>
               <l n="108">Such fiery passions and such fierce assaults</l>
               <l n="109">A little sprinkled dust controls and quells.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="88">
               <l n="110">And now, both leaders from the field recalled,</l>
               <l n="111">Who hath the worser seeming, do to death,</l>
               <l n="112">Lest royal waste wax burdensome, but let</l>
               <l n="113">His better lord it on the empty throne.</l>
               <l n="114">One with gold-burnished flakes will shine like fire,</l>
               <l n="115">For twofold are their kinds, the nobler he,</l>
               <l n="116">Of peerless front and lit with flashing scales;</l>
               <l n="117">That other, from neglect and squalor foul,</l>
               <l n="118">Drags slow a cumbrous belly. As with kings,</l>
               <l n="119">So too with people, diverse is their mould,</l>
               <l n="120">Some rough and loathly, as when the wayfarer</l>
               <l n="121">Scapes from a whirl of dust, and scorched with heat</l>
               <l n="122">Spits forth the dry grit from his parched mouth:</l>
               <l n="123">The others shine forth and flash with lightning-gleam,</l>
               <l n="124">Their backs all blazoned with bright drops of gold</l>
               <l n="125">Symmetric: this the likelier breed; from these,</l>
               <l n="126">When heaven brings round the season, thou shalt strain</l>
               <l n="127">Sweet honey, nor yet so sweet as passing clear,</l>
               <l n="128">And mellowing on the tongue the wine-god's fire.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="103">
               <l n="129">But when the swarms fly aimlessly abroad,</l>
               <l n="130">Disport themselves in heaven and spurn their cells,</l>
               <l n="131">Leaving the hive unwarmed, from such vain play</l>
               <l n="132">Must you refrain their volatile desires,</l>
               <l n="133">Nor hard the task: tear off the monarchs' wings;</l>
               <l n="134">While these prove loiterers, none beside will dare</l>
               <l n="135">Mount heaven, or pluck the standards from the camp.</l>
               <l n="136">Let gardens with the breath of saffron flowers</l>
               <l n="137">Allure them, and the lord of <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>,</l>
               <l n="138">Priapus, wielder of the willow-scythe,</l>
               <l n="139">Safe in his keeping hold from birds and thieves.</l>
               <l n="140">And let the man to whom such cares are dear</l>
               <l n="141">Himself bring thyme and pine-trees from the heights,</l>
               <l n="142">And strew them in broad belts about their home;</l>
               <l n="143">No hand but his the blistering task should ply,</l>
               <l n="144">Plant the young slips, or shed the genial showers.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="116">
               <l n="145">And I myself, were I not even now</l>
               <l n="146">Furling my sails, and, nigh the journey's end,</l>
               <l n="147">Eager to turn my vessel's prow to shore,</l>
               <l n="148">Perchance would sing what careful husbandry</l>
               <l n="149">Makes the trim garden smile; of <placeName key="tgn,7004619">Paestum</placeName> too,</l>
               <l n="150">Whose roses bloom and fade and bloom again;</l>
               <l n="151">How endives glory in the streams they drink,</l>
               <l n="152">And green banks in their parsley, and how the gourd</l>
               <l n="153">Twists through the grass and rounds him to paunch;</l>
               <l n="154">Nor of Narcissus had my lips been dumb,</l>
               <l n="155">That loiterer of the flowers, nor supple-stemmed</l>
               <l n="156">Acanthus, with the praise of ivies pale,</l>
               <l n="157">And myrtles clinging to the shores they love.</l>
               <l n="158">For 'neath the shade of tall Oebalia's towers,</l>
               <l n="159">Where dark Galaesus laves the yellowing fields,</l>
               <l n="160">An old man once I mind me to have seen—</l>
               <l n="161">From Corycus he came—to whom had fallen</l>
               <l n="162">Some few poor acres of neglected land,</l>
               <l n="163">And they nor fruitful' neath the plodding steer,</l>
               <l n="164">Meet for the grazing herd, nor good for vines.</l>
               <l n="165">Yet he, the while his meagre garden-herbs</l>
               <l n="166">Among the thorns he planted, and all round</l>
               <l n="167">White lilies, vervains, and lean poppy set,</l>
               <l n="168">In pride of spirit matched the wealth of kings,</l>
               <l n="169">And home returning not till night was late,</l>
               <l n="170">With unbought plenty heaped his board on high.</l>
               <l n="171">He was the first to cull the rose in spring,</l>
               <l n="172">He the ripe fruits in autumn; and ere yet</l>
               <l n="173">Winter had ceased in sullen ire to rive</l>
               <l n="174">The rocks with frost, and with her icy bit</l>
               <l n="175">Curb in the running waters, there was he</l>
               <l n="176">Plucking the rathe faint hyacinth, while he chid</l>
               <l n="177">Summer's slow footsteps and the lagging West.</l>
               <l n="178">Therefore he too with earliest brooding bees</l>
               <l n="179">And their full swarms o'erflowed, and first was he</l>
               <l n="180">To press the bubbling honey from the comb;</l>
               <l n="181">Lime-trees were his, and many a branching pine;</l>
               <l n="182">And all the fruits wherewith in early bloom</l>
               <l n="183">The orchard-tree had clothed her, in full tale</l>
               <l n="184">Hung there, by mellowing autumn perfected.</l>
               <l n="185">He too transplanted tall-grown elms a-row,</l>
               <l n="186">Time-toughened pear, thorns bursting with the plum</l>
               <l n="187">And plane now yielding serviceable shade</l>
               <l n="188">For dry lips to drink under: but these things,</l>
               <l n="189">Shut off by rigorous limits, I pass by,</l>
               <l n="190">And leave for others to sing after me.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="149">
               <l n="191">Come, then, I will unfold the natural powers</l>
               <l n="192">Great Jove himself upon the bees bestowed,</l>
               <l n="193">The boon for which, led by the shrill sweet strains</l>
               <l n="194">Of the Curetes and their clashing brass,</l>
               <l n="195">They fed the King of heaven in Dicte's cave.</l>
               <l n="196">Alone of all things they receive and hold</l>
               <l n="197">Community of offspring, and they house</l>
               <l n="198">Together in one city, and beneath</l>
               <l n="199">The shelter of majestic laws they live;</l>
               <l n="200">And they alone fixed home and country know,</l>
               <l n="201">And in the summer, warned of coming cold,</l>
               <l n="202">Make proof of toil, and for the general store</l>
               <l n="203">Hoard up their gathered harvesting. For some</l>
               <l n="204">Watch o'er the victualling of the hive, and these</l>
               <l n="205">By settled order ply their tasks afield;</l>
               <l n="206">And some within the confines of their home</l>
               <l n="207">Plant firm the comb's first layer, Narcissus' tear,</l>
               <l n="208">And sticky gum oozed from the bark of trees,</l>
               <l n="209">Then set the clinging wax to hang therefrom.</l>
               <l n="210">Others the while lead forth the full-grown young,</l>
               <l n="211">Their country's hope, and others press and pack</l>
               <l n="212">The thrice repured honey, and stretch their cells</l>
               <l n="213">To bursting with the clear-strained nectar sweet.</l>
               <l n="214">Some, too, the wardship of the gates befalls,</l>
               <l n="215">Who watch in turn for showers and cloudy skies,</l>
               <l n="216">Or ease returning labourers of their load,</l>
               <l n="217">Or form a band and from their precincts drive</l>
               <l n="218">The drones, a lazy herd. How glows the work!</l>
               <l n="219">How sweet the honey smells of perfumed thyme</l>
               <l n="220">Like the Cyclopes, when in haste they forge</l>
               <l n="221">From the slow-yielding ore the thunderbolts,</l>
               <l n="222">Some from the bull's-hide bellows in and out</l>
               <l n="223">Let the blasts drive, some dip i' the water-trough</l>
               <l n="224">The sputtering metal: with the anvil's weight</l>
               <l n="225">Groans <placeName key="tgn,7003867">Etna</placeName>: they alternately in time</l>
               <l n="226">With giant strength uplift their sinewy arms,</l>
               <l n="227">Or twist the iron with the forceps' grip—</l>
               <l n="228">Not otherwise, to measure small with great,</l>
               <l n="229">The love of getting planted in their breasts</l>
               <l n="230">Goads on the bees, that haunt old Cecrops' heights,</l>
               <l n="231">Each in his sphere to labour. The old have charge</l>
               <l n="232">To keep the town, and build the walled combs,</l>
               <l n="233">And mould the cunning chambers; but the youth,</l>
               <l n="234">Their tired legs packed with thyme, come labouring home</l>
               <l n="235">Belated, for afar they range to feed</l>
               <l n="236">On arbutes and the grey-green willow-leaves,</l>
               <l n="237">And cassia and the crocus blushing red,</l>
               <l n="238">Glue-yielding limes, and hyacinths dusky-eyed.</l>
               <l n="239">One hour for rest have all, and one for toil:</l>
               <l n="240">With dawn they hurry from the gates—no room</l>
               <l n="241">For loiterers there: and once again, when even</l>
               <l n="242">Now bids them quit their pasturing on the plain,</l>
               <l n="243">Then homeward make they, then refresh their strength:</l>
               <l n="244">A hum arises: hark! they buzz and buzz</l>
               <l n="245">About the doors and threshold; till at length</l>
               <l n="246">Safe laid to rest they hush them for the night,</l>
               <l n="247">And welcome slumber laps their weary limbs.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="191">
               <l n="248">But from the homestead not too far they fare,</l>
               <l n="249">When showers hang like to fall, nor, east winds nigh,</l>
               <l n="250">Confide in heaven, but 'neath the city walls</l>
               <l n="251">Safe-circling fetch them water, or essay</l>
               <l n="252">Brief out-goings, and oft weigh-up tiny stones,</l>
               <l n="253">As light craft ballast in the tossing tide,</l>
               <l n="254">Wherewith they poise them through the cloudy vast.</l>
               <l n="255">This law of life, too, by the bees obeyed,</l>
               <l n="256">Will move thy wonder, that nor sex with sex</l>
               <l n="257">Yoke they in marriage, nor yield their limbs to love,</l>
               <l n="258">Nor know the pangs of labour, but alone</l>
               <l n="259">From leaves and honied herbs, the mothers, each,</l>
               <l n="260">Gather their offspring in their mouths, alone</l>
               <l n="261">Supply new kings and pigmy commonwealth,</l>
               <l n="262">And their old court and waxen realm repair.</l>
               <l n="263">Oft, too, while wandering, against jagged stones</l>
               <l n="264">Their wings they fray, and 'neath the burden yield</l>
               <l n="265">Their liberal lives: so deep their love of flowers,</l>
               <l n="266">So glorious deem they honey's proud acquist.</l>
               <l n="267">Therefore, though each a life of narrow span,</l>
               <l n="268">Ne'er stretched to summers more than seven, befalls,</l>
               <l n="269">Yet deathless doth the race endure, and still</l>
               <l n="270">Perennial stands the fortune of their line,</l>
               <l n="271">From grandsire unto grandsire backward told.</l>
               <l n="272">Moreover, not <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Aegyptus</placeName>, nor the realm</l>
               <l n="273">Of boundless <placeName key="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName>, no, nor <placeName key="tgn,7016768">Parthia</placeName>'s hordes,</l>
               <l n="274">Nor Median Hydaspes, to their king</l>
               <l n="275">Do such obeisance: lives the king unscathed,</l>
               <l n="276">One will inspires the million: is he dead,</l>
               <l n="277">Snapt is the bond of fealty; they themselves</l>
               <l n="278">Ravage their toil-wrought honey, and rend amain</l>
               <l n="279">Their own comb's waxen trellis. He is the lord</l>
               <l n="280">Of all their labour; him with awful eye</l>
               <l n="281">They reverence, and with murmuring throngs surround,</l>
               <l n="282">In crowds attend, oft shoulder him on high,</l>
               <l n="283">Or with their bodies shield him in the fight,</l>
               <l n="284">And seek through showering wounds a glorious death.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="219">
               <l n="285">Led by these tokens, and with such traits to guide,</l>
               <l n="286">Some say that unto bees a share is given</l>
               <l n="287">Of the Divine Intelligence, and to drink</l>
               <l n="288">Pure draughts of ether; for God permeates all—</l>
               <l n="289">Earth, and wide ocean, and the vault of heaven—</l>
               <l n="290">From whom flocks, herds, men, beasts of every kind,</l>
               <l n="291">Draw each at birth the fine essential flame;</l>
               <l n="292">Yea, and that all things hence to Him return,</l>
               <l n="293">Brought back by dissolution, nor can death</l>
               <l n="294">Find place: but, each into his starry rank,</l>
               <l n="295">Alive they soar, and mount the heights of heaven.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="228">
               <l n="296">If now their narrow home thou wouldst unseal,</l>
               <l n="297">And broach the treasures of the honey-house,</l>
               <l n="298">With draught of water first toment thy lips,</l>
               <l n="299">And spread before thee fumes of trailing smoke.</l>
               <l n="300">Twice is the teeming produce gathered in,</l>
               <l n="301">Twofold their time of harvest year by year,</l>
               <l n="302">Once when Taygete the Pleiad uplifts</l>
               <l n="303">Her comely forehead for the earth to see,</l>
               <l n="304">With foot of scorn spurning the ocean-streams,</l>
               <l n="305">Once when in gloom she flies the watery Fish,</l>
               <l n="306">And dips from heaven into the wintry wave.</l>
               <l n="307">Unbounded then their wrath; if hurt, they breathe</l>
               <l n="308">Venom into their bite, cleave to the veins</l>
               <l n="309">And let the sting lie buried, and leave their lives</l>
               <l n="310">Behind them in the wound. But if you dread</l>
               <l n="311">Too rigorous a winter, and would fain</l>
               <l n="312">Temper the coming time, and their bruised hearts</l>
               <l n="313">And broken estate to pity move thy soul,</l>
               <l n="314">Yet who would fear to fumigate with thyme,</l>
               <l n="315">Or cut the empty wax away? for oft</l>
               <l n="316">Into their comb the newt has gnawed unseen,</l>
               <l n="317">And the light-loathing beetles crammed their bed,</l>
               <l n="318">And he that sits at others' board to feast,</l>
               <l n="319">The do-naught drone; or 'gainst the unequal foe</l>
               <l n="320">Swoops the fierce hornet, or the moth's fell tribe;</l>
               <l n="321">Or spider, victim of Minerva's spite,</l>
               <l n="322">Athwart the doorway hangs her swaying net.</l>
               <l n="323">The more impoverished they, the keenlier all</l>
               <l n="324">To mend the fallen fortunes of their race</l>
               <l n="325">Will nerve them, fill the cells up, tier on tier,</l>
               <l n="326">And weave their granaries from the rifled flowers.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="251">
               <l n="327">Now, seeing that life doth even to bee-folk bring</l>
               <l n="328">Our human chances, if in dire disease</l>
               <l n="329">Their bodies' strength should languish—which anon</l>
               <l n="330">By no uncertain tokens may be told—</l>
               <l n="331">Forthwith the sick change hue; grim leanness mars</l>
               <l n="332">Their visage; then from out the cells they bear</l>
               <l n="333">Forms reft of light, and lead the mournful pomp;</l>
               <l n="334">Or foot to foot about the porch they hang,</l>
               <l n="335">Or within closed doors loiter, listless all</l>
               <l n="336">From famine, and benumbed with shrivelling cold.</l>
               <l n="337">Then is a deep note heard, a long-drawn hum,</l>
               <l n="338">As when the chill South through the forests sighs,</l>
               <l n="339">As when the troubled ocean hoarsely booms</l>
               <l n="340">With back-swung billow, as ravening tide of fire</l>
               <l n="341">Surges, shut fast within the furnace-walls.</l>
               <l n="342">Then do I bid burn scented galbanum,</l>
               <l n="343">And, honey-streams through reeden troughs instilled,</l>
               <l n="344">Challenge and cheer their flagging appetite</l>
               <l n="345">To taste the well-known food; and it shall boot</l>
               <l n="346">To mix therewith the savour bruised from gall,</l>
               <l n="347">And rose-leaves dried, or must to thickness boiled</l>
               <l n="348">By a fierce fire, or juice of raisin-grapes</l>
               <l n="349">From Psithian vine, and with its bitter smell</l>
               <l n="350">Centaury, and the famed Cecropian thyme.</l>
               <l n="351">There is a meadow-flower by country folk</l>
               <l n="352">Hight star-wort; 'tis a plant not far to seek;</l>
               <l n="353">For from one sod an ample growth it rears,</l>
               <l n="354">Itself all golden, but girt with plenteous leaves,</l>
               <l n="355">Where glory of purple shines through violet gloom.</l>
               <l n="356">With chaplets woven hereof full oft are decked</l>
               <l n="357">Heaven's altars: harsh its taste upon the tongue;</l>
               <l n="358">Shepherds in vales smooth-shorn of nibbling flocks</l>
               <l n="359">By <placeName key="tgn,1127058">Mella</placeName>'s winding waters gather it.</l>
               <l n="360">The roots of this, well seethed in fragrant wine,</l>
               <l n="361">Set in brimmed baskets at their doors for food.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="281">
               <l n="362">But if one's whole stock fail him at a stroke,</l>
               <l n="363">Nor hath he whence to breed the race anew,</l>
               <l n="364">'Tis time the wondrous secret to disclose</l>
               <l n="365">Taught by the swain of Arcady, even how</l>
               <l n="366">The blood of slaughtered bullocks oft has borne</l>
               <l n="367">Bees from corruption. I will trace me back</l>
               <l n="368">To its prime source the story's tangled thread,</l>
               <l n="369">And thence unravel. For where thy happy folk,</l>
               <l n="370">
                  <placeName key="tgn,1001079">Canopus</placeName>, city of Pellaean fame,</l>
               <l n="371">Dwell by the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>'s lagoon-like overflow,</l>
               <l n="372">And high o'er furrows they have called their own</l>
               <l n="373">Skim in their painted wherries; where, hard by,</l>
               <l n="374">The quivered Persian presses, and that flood</l>
               <l n="375">Which from the swart-skinned Aethiop bears him down,</l>
               <l n="376">Swift-parted into sevenfold branching mouths</l>
               <l n="377">With black mud fattens and makes Aegypt green,</l>
               <l n="378">That whole domain its welfare's hope secure</l>
               <l n="379">Rests on this art alone. And first is chosen</l>
               <l n="380">A strait recess, cramped closer to this end,</l>
               <l n="381">Which next with narrow roof of tiles atop</l>
               <l n="382">'Twixt prisoning walls they pinch, and add hereto</l>
               <l n="383">From the four winds four slanting window-slits.</l>
               <l n="384">Then seek they from the herd a steer, whose horns</l>
               <l n="385">With two years' growth are curling, and stop fast,</l>
               <l n="386">Plunge madly as he may, the panting mouth</l>
               <l n="387">And nostrils twain, and done with blows to death,</l>
               <l n="388">Batter his flesh to pulp i' the hide yet whole,</l>
               <l n="389">And shut the doors, and leave him there to lie.</l>
               <l n="390">But 'neath his ribs they scatter broken boughs,</l>
               <l n="391">With thyme and fresh-pulled cassias: this is done</l>
               <l n="392">When first the west winds bid the waters flow,</l>
               <l n="393">Ere flush the meadows with new tints, and ere</l>
               <l n="394">The twittering swallow buildeth from the beams.</l>
               <l n="395">Meanwhile the juice within his softened bones</l>
               <l n="396">Heats and ferments, and things of wondrous birth,</l>
               <l n="397">Footless at first, anon with feet and wings,</l>
               <l n="398">Swarm there and buzz, a marvel to behold;</l>
               <l n="399">And more and more the fleeting breeze they take,</l>
               <l n="400">Till, like a shower that pours from summer-clouds,</l>
               <l n="401">Forth burst they, or like shafts from quivering string</l>
               <l n="402">When <placeName key="tgn,7016768">Parthia</placeName>'s flying hosts provoke the fray.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="315">
               <l n="403">Say what was he, what God, that fashioned forth</l>
               <l n="404">This art for us, O Muses? of man's skill</l>
               <l n="405">Whence came the new adventure? From thy vale,</l>
               <l n="406">Peneian Tempe, turning, bee-bereft,</l>
               <l n="407">So runs the tale, by famine and disease,</l>
               <l n="408">Mournful the shepherd Aristaeus stood</l>
               <l n="409">Fast by the haunted river-head, and thus</l>
               <l n="410">With many a plaint to her that bare him cried:</l>
               <l n="411">“Mother, Cyrene, mother, who hast thy home</l>
               <l n="412">Beneath this whirling flood, if he thou sayest,</l>
               <l n="413">Apollo, lord of Thymbra, be my sire,</l>
               <l n="414">Sprung from the Gods' high line, why barest thou me</l>
               <l n="415">With fortune's ban for birthright? Where is now</l>
               <l n="416">Thy love to me-ward banished from thy breast?</l>
               <l n="417">O! wherefore didst thou bid me hope for heaven?</l>
               <l n="418">Lo! even the crown of this poor mortal life,</l>
               <l n="419">Which all my skilful care by field and fold,</l>
               <l n="420">No art neglected, scarce had fashioned forth,</l>
               <l n="421">Even this falls from me, yet thou call'st me son.</l>
               <l n="422">Nay, then, arise! With thine own hands pluck up</l>
               <l n="423">My fruit-plantations: on the homestead fling</l>
               <l n="424">Pitiless fire; make havoc of my crops;</l>
               <l n="425">Burn the young plants, and wield the stubborn axe</l>
               <l n="426">Against my vines, if there hath taken the</l>
               <l n="427">Such loathing of my greatness.”</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="333">
               <l n="428">But that cry,</l>
               <l n="429">Even from her chamber in the river-deeps,</l>
               <l n="430">His mother heard: around her spun the nymphs</l>
               <l n="431">Milesian wool stained through with hyaline dye,</l>
               <l n="432">Drymo, Xantho, Ligea, Phyllodoce,</l>
               <l n="433">Their glossy locks o'er snowy shoulders shed,</l>
               <l n="434">Cydippe and Lycorias yellow-haired,</l>
               <l n="435">A maiden one, one newly learned even then</l>
               <l n="436">To bear Lucina's birth-pang. Clio, too,</l>
               <l n="437">And Beroe, sisters, ocean-children both,</l>
               <l n="438">Both zoned with gold and girt with dappled fell,</l>
               <l n="439">Ephyre and Opis, and from Asian meads</l>
               <l n="440">Deiopea, and, bow at length laid by,</l>
               <l n="441">Fleet-footed Arethusa. But in their midst</l>
               <l n="442">Fair Clymene was telling o'er the tale</l>
               <l n="443">Of Vulcan's idle vigilance and the stealth</l>
               <l n="444">Of Mars' sweet rapine, and from Chaos old</l>
               <l n="445">Counted the jostling love-joys of the Gods.</l>
               <l n="446">Charmed by whose lay, the while their woolly tasks</l>
               <l n="447">With spindles down they drew, yet once again</l>
               <l n="448">Smote on his mother's ears the mournful plaint</l>
               <l n="449">Of Aristaeus; on their glassy thrones</l>
               <l n="450">Amazement held them all; but Arethuse</l>
               <l n="451">Before the rest put forth her auburn head,</l>
               <l n="452">Peering above the wave-top, and from far</l>
               <l n="453">Exclaimed, “Cyrene, sister, not for naught</l>
               <l n="454">Scared by a groan so deep, behold! 'tis he,</l>
               <l n="455">Even Aristaeus, thy heart's fondest care,</l>
               <l n="456">Here by the brink of the Peneian sire</l>
               <l n="457">Stands woebegone and weeping, and by name</l>
               <l n="458">Cries out upon thee for thy cruelty.”</l>
               <l n="459">To whom, strange terror knocking at her heart,</l>
               <l n="460">“Bring, bring him to our sight,” the mother cried;</l>
               <l n="461">“His feet may tread the threshold even of Gods.”</l>
               <l n="462">So saying, she bids the flood yawn wide and yield</l>
               <l n="463">A pathway for his footsteps; but the wave</l>
               <l n="464">Arched mountain-wise closed round him, and within</l>
               <l n="465">Its mighty bosom welcomed, and let speed</l>
               <l n="466">To the deep river-bed. And now, with eyes</l>
               <l n="467">Of wonder gazing on his mother's hall</l>
               <l n="468">And watery kingdom and cave-prisoned pools</l>
               <l n="469">And echoing groves, he went, and, stunned by that</l>
               <l n="470">Stupendous whirl of waters, separate saw</l>
               <l n="471">All streams beneath the mighty earth that glide,</l>
               <l n="472">
                  <placeName key="tgn,7012263">Phasis</placeName> and Lycus, and that fountain-head</l>
               <l n="473">Whence first the deep Enipeus leaps to light,</l>
               <l n="474">Whence father <placeName key="tgn,1130786">Tiber</placeName>, and whence Anio's flood,</l>
               <l n="475">And Hypanis that roars amid his rocks,</l>
               <l n="476">And Mysian Caicus, and, bull-browed</l>
               <l n="477">'Twixt either gilded horn, <placeName key="tgn,7010018">Eridanus</placeName>,</l>
               <l n="478">Than whom none other through the laughing plains</l>
               <l n="479">More furious pours into the purple sea.</l>
               <l n="480">Soon as the chamber's hanging roof of stone</l>
               <l n="481">Was gained, and now Cyrene from her son</l>
               <l n="482">Had heard his idle weeping, in due course</l>
               <l n="483">Clear water for his hands the sisters bring,</l>
               <l n="484">With napkins of shorn pile, while others heap</l>
               <l n="485">The board with dainties, and set on afresh</l>
               <l n="486">The brimming goblets; with Panchaian fires</l>
               <l n="487">Upleap the altars; then the mother spake,</l>
               <l n="488">“Take beakers of Maconian wine,” she said,</l>
               <l n="489">“Pour we to Ocean.” Ocean, sire of all,</l>
               <l n="490">She worships, and the sister-nymphs who guard</l>
               <l n="491">The hundred forests and the hundred streams;</l>
               <l n="492">Thrice Vesta's fire with nectar clear she dashed,</l>
               <l n="493">Thrice to the roof-top shot the flame and shone:</l>
               <l n="494">Armed with which omen she essayed to speak:</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="387">
               <l n="495">“In Neptune's gulf Carpathian dwells a seer,</l>
               <l n="496">Caerulean Proteus, he who metes the main</l>
               <l n="497">With fish-drawn chariot of two-footed steeds;</l>
               <l n="498">Now visits he his native home once more,</l>
               <l n="499">
                  <placeName key="perseus,Pallene">Pallene</placeName> and the Emathian ports; to him</l>
               <l n="500">We nymphs do reverence, ay, and Nereus old;</l>
               <l n="501">For all things knows the seer, both those which are</l>
               <l n="502">And have been, or which time hath yet to bring;</l>
               <l n="503">So willed it Neptune, whose portentous flocks,</l>
               <l n="504">And loathly sea-calves 'neath the surge he feeds.</l>
               <l n="505">Him first, my son, behoves thee seize and bind</l>
               <l n="506">That he may all the cause of sickness show,</l>
               <l n="507">And grant a prosperous end. For save by force</l>
               <l n="508">No rede will he vouchsafe, nor shalt thou bend</l>
               <l n="509">His soul by praying; whom once made captive, ply</l>
               <l n="510">With rigorous force and fetters; against these</l>
               <l n="511">His wiles will break and spend themselves in vain.</l>
               <l n="512">I, when the sun has lit his noontide fires,</l>
               <l n="513">When the blades thirst, and cattle love the shade,</l>
               <l n="514">Myself will guide thee to the old man's haunt,</l>
               <l n="515">Whither he hies him weary from the waves,</l>
               <l n="516">That thou mayst safelier steal upon his sleep.</l>
               <l n="517">But when thou hast gripped him fast with hand and gyve,</l>
               <l n="518">Then divers forms and bestial semblances</l>
               <l n="519">Shall mock thy grasp; for sudden he will change</l>
               <l n="520">To bristly boar, fell tigress, dragon scaled,</l>
               <l n="521">And tawny-tufted lioness, or send forth</l>
               <l n="522">A crackling sound of fire, and so shake of</l>
               <l n="523">The fetters, or in showery drops anon</l>
               <l n="524">Dissolve and vanish. But the more he shifts</l>
               <l n="525">His endless transformations, thou, my son,</l>
               <l n="526">More straitlier clench the clinging bands, until</l>
               <l n="527">His body's shape return to that thou sawest,</l>
               <l n="528">When with closed eyelids first he sank to sleep.”</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="415">
               <l n="529">So saying, an odour of ambrosial dew</l>
               <l n="530">She sheds around, and all his frame therewith</l>
               <l n="531">Steeps throughly; forth from his trim-combed locks</l>
               <l n="532">Breathed effluence sweet, and a lithe vigour leapt</l>
               <l n="533">Into his limbs. There is a cavern vast</l>
               <l n="534">Scooped in the mountain-side, where wave on wave</l>
               <l n="535">By the wind's stress is driven, and breaks far up</l>
               <l n="536">Its inmost creeks—safe anchorage from of old</l>
               <l n="537">For tempest-taken mariners: therewithin,</l>
               <l n="538">Behind a rock's huge barrier, Proteus hides.</l>
               <l n="539">Here in close covert out of the sun's eye</l>
               <l n="540">The youth she places, and herself the while</l>
               <l n="541">Swathed in a shadowy mist stands far aloof.</l>
               <l n="542">And now the ravening dog-star that burns up</l>
               <l n="543">The thirsty Indians blazed in heaven; his course</l>
               <l n="544">The fiery sun had half devoured: the blades</l>
               <l n="545">Were parched, and the void streams with droughty jaws</l>
               <l n="546">Baked to their mud-beds by the scorching ray,</l>
               <l n="547">When Proteus seeking his accustomed cave</l>
               <l n="548">Strode from the billows: round him frolicking</l>
               <l n="549">The watery folk that people the waste sea</l>
               <l n="550">Sprinkled the bitter brine-dew far and wide.</l>
               <l n="551">Along the shore in scattered groups to feed</l>
               <l n="552">The sea-calves stretch them: while the seer himself,</l>
               <l n="553">Like herdsman on the hills when evening bids</l>
               <l n="554">The steers from pasture to their stall repair,</l>
               <l n="555">And the lambs' bleating whets the listening wolves,</l>
               <l n="556">Sits midmost on the rock and tells his tale.</l>
               <l n="557">But Aristaeus, the foe within his clutch,</l>
               <l n="558">Scarce suffering him compose his aged limbs,</l>
               <l n="559">With a great cry leapt on him, and ere he rose</l>
               <l n="560">Forestalled him with the fetters; he nathless,</l>
               <l n="561">All unforgetful of his ancient craft,</l>
               <l n="562">Transforms himself to every wondrous thing,</l>
               <l n="563">Fire and a fearful beast, and flowing stream.</l>
               <l n="564">But when no trickery found a path for flight,</l>
               <l n="565">Baffled at length, to his own shape returned,</l>
               <l n="566">With human lips he spake, “Who bade thee, then,</l>
               <l n="567">So reckless in youth's hardihood, affront</l>
               <l n="568">Our portals? or what wouldst thou hence?”—But he,</l>
               <l n="569">“Proteus, thou knowest, of thine own heart thou knowest;</l>
               <l n="570">For thee there is no cheating, but cease thou</l>
               <l n="571">To practise upon me: at heaven's behest</l>
               <l n="572">I for my fainting fortunes hither come</l>
               <l n="573">An oracle to ask thee.” There he ceased.</l>
               <l n="574">Whereat the seer, by stubborn force constrained,</l>
               <l n="575">Shot forth the grey light of his gleaming eyes</l>
               <l n="576">Upon him, and with fiercely gnashing teeth</l>
               <l n="577">Unlocks his lips to spell the fates of heaven:</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="453">
               <l n="578">“Doubt not 'tis wrath divine that plagues thee thus,</l>
               <l n="579">Nor light the debt thou payest; 'tis Orpheus' self,</l>
               <l n="580">Orpheus unhappy by no fault of his,</l>
               <l n="581">So fates prevent not, fans thy penal fires,</l>
               <l n="582">Yet madly raging for his ravished bride.</l>
               <l n="583">She in her haste to shun thy hot pursuit</l>
               <l n="584">Along the stream, saw not the coming death,</l>
               <l n="585">Where at her feet kept ward upon the bank</l>
               <l n="586">In the tall grass a monstrous water-snake.</l>
               <l n="587">But with their cries the Dryad-band her peers</l>
               <l n="588">Filled up the mountains to their proudest peaks:</l>
               <l n="589">Wailed for her fate the heights of <placeName key="tgn,7002754">Rhodope</placeName>,</l>
               <l n="590">And tall Pangaea, and, beloved of Mars,</l>
               <l n="591">The land that bowed to Rhesus, <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> no less</l>
               <l n="592">With <placeName key="tgn,7002660">Hebrus</placeName>' stream; and Orithyia wept,</l>
               <l n="593">Daughter of Acte old. But Orpheus' self,</l>
               <l n="594">Soothing his love-pain with the hollow shell,</l>
               <l n="595">Thee his sweet wife on the lone shore alone,</l>
               <l n="596">Thee when day dawned and when it died he sang.</l>
               <l n="597">Nay to the jaws of Taenarus too he came,</l>
               <l n="598">Of Dis the infernal palace, and the grove</l>
               <l n="599">Grim with a horror of great darkness—came,</l>
               <l n="600">Entered, and faced the Manes and the King</l>
               <l n="601">Of terrors, the stone heart no prayer can tame.</l>
               <l n="602">Then from the deepest deeps of Erebus,</l>
               <l n="603">Wrung by his minstrelsy, the hollow shades</l>
               <l n="604">Came trooping, ghostly semblances of forms</l>
               <l n="605">Lost to the light, as birds by myriads hie</l>
               <l n="606">To greenwood boughs for cover, when twilight-hour</l>
               <l n="607">Or storms of winter chase them from the hills;</l>
               <l n="608">Matrons and men, and great heroic frames</l>
               <l n="609">Done with life's service, boys, unwedded girls,</l>
               <l n="610">Youths placed on pyre before their fathers' eyes.</l>
               <l n="611">Round them, with black slime choked and hideous weed,</l>
               <l n="612">Cocytus winds; there lies the unlovely swamp</l>
               <l n="613">Of dull dead water, and, to pen them fast,</l>
               <l n="614">Styx with her ninefold barrier poured between.</l>
               <l n="615">Nay, even the deep Tartarean Halls of death</l>
               <l n="616">Stood lost in wonderment, and the Eumenides,</l>
               <l n="617">Their brows with livid locks of serpents twined;</l>
               <l n="618">Even Cerberus held his triple jaws agape,</l>
               <l n="619">And, the wind hushed, Ixion's wheel stood still.</l>
               <l n="620">And now with homeward footstep he had passed</l>
               <l n="621">All perils scathless, and, at length restored,</l>
               <l n="622">Eurydice to realms of upper air</l>
               <l n="623">Had well-nigh won, behind him following—</l>
               <l n="624">So Proserpine had ruled it—when his heart</l>
               <l n="625">A sudden mad desire surprised and seized—</l>
               <l n="626">Meet fault to be forgiven, might Hell forgive.</l>
               <l n="627">For at the very threshold of the day,</l>
               <l n="628">Heedless, alas! and vanquished of resolve,</l>
               <l n="629">He stopped, turned, looked upon Eurydice</l>
               <l n="630">His own once more. But even with the look,</l>
               <l n="631">Poured out was all his labour, broken the bond</l>
               <l n="632">Of that fell tyrant, and a crash was heard</l>
               <l n="633">Three times like thunder in the meres of hell.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="494">
               <l n="634">‘Orpheus! what ruin hath thy frenzy wrought</l>
               <l n="635">On me, alas! and thee? Lo! once again</l>
               <l n="636">The unpitying fates recall me, and dark sleep</l>
               <l n="637">Closes my swimming eyes. And now farewell:</l>
               <l n="638">Girt with enormous night I am borne away,</l>
               <l n="639">Outstretching toward thee, thine, alas! no more,</l>
               <l n="640">These helpless hands.’ She spake, and suddenly,</l>
               <l n="641">Like smoke dissolving into empty air,</l>
               <l n="642">Passed and was sundered from his sight; nor him</l>
               <l n="643">Clutching vain shadows, yearning sore to speak,</l>
               <l n="644">Thenceforth beheld she, nor no second time</l>
               <l n="645">Hell's boatman brooks he pass the watery bar.</l>
               <l n="646">What should he do? fly whither, twice bereaved?</l>
               <l n="647">Move with what tears the Manes, with what voice</l>
               <l n="648">The Powers of darkness? She indeed even now</l>
               <l n="649">Death-cold was floating on the Stygian barge!</l>
               <l n="650">For seven whole months unceasingly, men say,</l>
               <l n="651">Beneath a skyey crag, by thy lone wave,</l>
               <l n="652">Strymon, he wept, and in the caverns chill</l>
               <l n="653">Unrolled his story, melting tigers' hearts,</l>
               <l n="654">And leading with his lay the oaks along.</l>
               <l n="655">As in the poplar-shade a nightingale</l>
               <l n="656">Mourns her lost young, which some relentless swain,</l>
               <l n="657">Spying, from the nest has torn unfledged, but she</l>
               <l n="658">Wails the long night, and perched upon a spray</l>
               <l n="659">With sad insistence pipes her dolorous strain,</l>
               <l n="660">Till all the region with her wrongs o'erflows.</l>
               <l n="661">No love, no new desire, constrained his soul:</l>
               <l n="662">By snow-bound <placeName key="tgn,1123466">Tanais</placeName> and the icy north,</l>
               <l n="663">Far steppes to frost Rhipaean forever wed,</l>
               <l n="664">Alone he wandered, lost Eurydice</l>
               <l n="665">Lamenting, and the gifts of Dis ungiven.</l>
               <l n="666">Scorned by which tribute the Ciconian dames,</l>
               <l n="667">Amid their awful Bacchanalian rites</l>
               <l n="668">And midnight revellings, tore him limb from limb,</l>
               <l n="669">And strewed his fragments over the wide fields.</l>
               <l n="670">Then too, even then, what time the <placeName key="tgn,7002660">Hebrus</placeName> stream,</l>
               <l n="671">Oeagrian Hebrus, down mid-current rolled,</l>
               <l n="672">Rent from the marble neck, his drifting head,</l>
               <l n="673">The death-chilled tongue found yet a voice to cry</l>
               <l n="674">‘Eurydice! ah! poor Eurydice!’</l>
               <l n="675">With parting breath he called her, and the banks</l>
               <l n="676">From the broad stream caught up ‘Eurydice!’”</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="528">
               <l n="677">So Proteus ending plunged into the deep,</l>
               <l n="678">And, where he plunged, beneath the eddying whirl</l>
               <l n="679">Churned into foam the water, and was gone;</l>
               <l n="680">But not Cyrene, who unquestioned thus</l>
               <l n="681">Bespake the trembling listener: “Nay, my son,</l>
               <l n="682">From that sad bosom thou mayst banish care:</l>
               <l n="683">Hence came that plague of sickness, hence the nymphs,</l>
               <l n="684">With whom in the tall woods the dance she wove,</l>
               <l n="685">Wrought on thy bees, alas! this deadly bane.</l>
               <l n="686">Bend thou before the Dell-nymphs, gracious powers:</l>
               <l n="687">Bring gifts, and sue for pardon: they will grant</l>
               <l n="688">Peace to thine asking, and an end of wrath.</l>
               <l n="689">But how to approach them will I first unfold—</l>
               <l n="690 707">Four chosen bulls of peerless form and bulk,</l>
               <l n="691">That browse to-day the green Lycaean heights,</l>
               <l n="692">Pick from thy herds, as many kine to match,</l>
               <l n="693">Whose necks the yoke pressed never: then for these</l>
               <l n="694">Build up four altars by the lofty fanes,</l>
               <l n="695">And from their throats let gush the victims' blood,</l>
               <l n="696">And in the greenwood leave their bodies lone.</l>
               <l n="697">Then, when the ninth dawn hath displayed its beams,</l>
               <l n="698">To Orpheus shalt thou send his funeral dues,</l>
               <l n="699">Poppies of Lethe, and let slay a sheep</l>
               <l n="700">Coal-black, then seek the grove again, and soon</l>
               <l n="701">For pardon found adore Eurydice</l>
               <l n="702">With a slain calf for victim.”</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="548">
               <l n="703">No delay:</l>
               <l n="704">The self-same hour he hies him forth to do</l>
               <l n="705">His mother's bidding: to the shrine he came,</l>
               <l n="706">The appointed altars reared, and thither led</l>
               <l n="690 707">Four chosen bulls of peerless form and bulk,</l>
               <l n="708">With kine to match, that never yoke had known;</l>
               <l n="709">Then, when the ninth dawn had led in the day,</l>
               <l n="710">To Orpheus sent his funeral dues, and sought</l>
               <l n="711">The grove once more. But sudden, strange to tell</l>
               <l n="712">A portent they espy: through the oxen's flesh,</l>
               <l n="713">Waxed soft in dissolution, hark! there hum</l>
               <l n="714">Bees from the belly; the rent ribs overboil</l>
               <l n="715">In endless clouds they spread them, till at last</l>
               <l n="716">On yon tree-top together fused they cling,</l>
               <l n="717">And drop their cluster from the bending boughs.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" resp="p" n="559">
               <l n="718">So sang I of the tilth of furrowed fields,</l>
               <l n="719">Of flocks and trees, while Caesar's majesty</l>
               <l n="720">Launched forth the levin-bolts of war by deep</l>
               <l n="721">
                  <placeName key="tgn,1123842">Euphrates</placeName>, and bare rule o'er willing folk</l>
               <l n="722">Though vanquished, and essayed the heights of heaven.</l>
               <l n="723">I Virgil then, of sweet Parthenope</l>
               <l n="724">The nursling, wooed the flowery walks of peace</l>
               <l n="725">Inglorious, who erst trilled for shepherd-wights</l>
               <l n="726">The wanton ditty, and sang in saucy youth</l>
               <l n="727">Thee, Tityrus, 'neath the spreading beech tree's shade.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
      </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>