<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epithalamium of Honorius and Maria</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor>Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date>1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian02clau#page/238/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa006.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
               <pb id="v.1.p.241" TEIform="pb"/>
       <div1 type="poem" n="praef" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PREFACE</head>
         <p>

When Pelion reared his height to form a bridal
chamber with long-drawn arches, and his hospitable
land could not contain so many gods; when Nereus,
sire of the bride, and all the throng of her sisters
strove to link day to day with feastings; when Chiron,
lying at ease with his horse-flanks curled under him,
offered the loving-cup to Jove; when Peneus turned
his cold waters to nectar and frothing wine flowed
down from Oeta's summit, Terpsichore struck her
ready lyre with festive hand and led the girlish
bands into the caves. The gods, the Thunderer
himself, disdained not these songs, for they knew
that lovers' vows ever harmonized with tender strains.
</p>
         <p>Centaurs and Fauns would have none of it: what
lyre could touch Rhoetus or move inhuman Pholus?
</p>
         <p>The seventh day had flamed in heaven, seven
times had Hesperus relumed his lamp and seen the
dances completed; then Phoebus touched his lyre
with that nobler quill, wherewith he leads captive
rocks and mountain-ashes, and sang to his sacred
strings now the promised birth of Achilles, now the
slaughter of the Trojans and the river Simois. The
happy marriage-cry re-echoed o'er leafy Olympus, and
Othrys and Ossa gave back their mistress Thetis' name.
<pb id="v.1.p."/>
         </p>
       </div1>
               <pb id="v.1.p.243" TEIform="pb"/>
       <div1 type="poem" n="1" id="poem.10" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>EPITHALAMIUM</head>
         <p>

Unfelt before was the fire the Emperor Honorius
had conceived for his promised bride, and he burned,
all unexperienced, with passion's first fever, nor knew
whence came the heat, what meant the sighs — a
tyro and as yet ignorant of love. Hunting, horses,
javelins — for none of these he now cares nor yet to
fling the spear; Love's wound occupies all his
thoughts. How often he groaned from the very
heart; how often a blush, mantling to his cheeks,
betrayed his secret; how often, unbidden of himself,
his hand would write the loved one's name. Already
he prepares gifts for his betrothed and selects to
adorn her (though their beauty is less than hers) the
jewels once worn by noble Li via of old and all the
proud women of the imperial house. The impatient
lover chafes at the delay; the long days seem as
though they stood still and the moon as though
she moved not her slow wheel. Thus Deidamia,
girl of Scyros, e'er yet she sees through his disguise,
inflamed with love the young Achilles, and taught
his warrior hands to draw the slender thread and
passed her rosy fingers through the locks of that Thessalian
of whom all Ida was soon to stand in awe.
</p>
         <p>Thus too he communed with himself: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>How long
<pb id="v.1.p.245"/>
will honoured Stilicho forbear to grant my prayers?
Why postpones he the union of those whose love he
has approved? Why should he refuse to fulfil my
chaste desires? I follow not the example of luxurious
princes in seeking the beauties of a pictured countenance,
whereby the pander canvass may pass from
house to house to make known the charms demanded;
nor yet have I sought to choose the uncertain
object of my love from this house or from
that, and thus entrusted to deceptive wax the difficult
selection of a bride. I sever not in violence the bonds
that unite a wedded woman to her lord; her I seek
who hath long been betrothed to me, who by a
father's orders was left my affianced bride and who
through her mother shares with me a common
grandsire. A suppliant I have laid aside my rank
and acted the suitor. Princes, second only to myself
in rank, have I sent from my imperial palace to
present my petition. 'Tis no small thing I ask,
Stilicho; that I admit; yet surely to me, an emperor,
son of that other emperor who, by giving thee his
brother's adopted daughter to wife, made thee his
son-in-law, — to me thou dost owe Maria. Pay
back to the son the interest due to his sire; restore
to the palace those who are its own. Mayhap
her mother 1 will be less inexorable. Daughter of
mine uncle Honorius, whence I derive my name, chief
glory of the land of swift-flowing Ebro, cousin by
birth, by mother's love a mother, to thy care was
mine infancy entrusted, in thine arms I grew to boyhood;
save for my birth thou, rather than Flacilla,
art my mother. Why dost thou separate thy two
<pb id="v.1.p.247"/>
children? Why not bestow a daughter born upon
an adopted son? Will the longed-for day ever
come; the marriage-night ever be sanctioned?</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>
With such complaint he assuages the wounds of
love. Cupid laughed and speeding across the deep
bore the news to his gentle mother, proudly spreading
his wings to their full extent.
</p>
         <p>Where Cyprus looks out over the Ionian main a
craggy mountain overshadows it; unapproachable
by human foot it faces the isle of Pharos, the home of
Proteus and the seven mouths of the Nile. The hoar
frost dares not clothe its sides, nor the rude winds
buffet it nor clouds obscure. It is consecrate to
pleasure and to Venus. The year's less clement
seasons are strangers to it, whereover ever brood the
blessings of eternal spring. The mountain's height
slopes down into a plain; that a golden hedge
encircles, guarding its meadows with yellow metal.
</p>
         <p>This demesne, men say, was the price paid by
Mulciber for the kisses of his wife, these towers were
the gift of a loving husband. Fair is the enclosed
country, ever bright with flowers though touched
with no labouring hand, for Zephyr is husbandman
enough therefor. Into its shady groves no bird may
enter save such as has first won the goddess' approval
for its song. Those which please her may flit among
the branches; they must quit who cannot pass the test.
</p>
         <p>The very leaves live for love and in his season every
happy tree experiences love's power: palm bends
down to mate with palm, poplar sighs its passion for
poplar, plane whispers to plane, alder to alder.
</p>
         <p>Here spring two fountains, the one of sweet water,
the other of bitter, honey is mingled with the first,
poison with the second, and in these streams 'tis said
<pb id="v.1.p.249"/>
that Cupid dips his arrows. A thousand brother
Loves with quivers play all around upon the banks,
a tender company like to Cupid himself in face and
of equal age. The nymphs are their mothers;
Cupid is the only child of golden Venus. He with his
bow subdues the stars and the gods and heaven, and
disdains not to wound mighty kings; of the others
the common people is the prey. Other deities, too,
are here: Licence bound by no fetters, easily moved
Anger, Wakes dripping with wine, inexperienced
Tears, Pallor that lovers ever prize, Boldness trembling
at his first thefts, happy Fears, unstable
Pleasure, and lovers' Oaths, the sport of every
lightest breeze. Amid them all wanton Youth with
haughty neck shuts out Age from the grove.
</p>
         <p>Afar shines and glitters the goddess' many-coloured
palace, green gleaming by reason of the encircling
grove. Vulcan built this too of precious stones and
gold, wedding their costliness to art. Columns cut
from rock of hyacinth support emerald beams;
the walls are of beryl, the high-builded thresholds
of polished jaspar, the floor of agate trodden as
dirt beneath the foot. In the midst is a courtyard
rich with fragrant turf that yields a harvest of
perfume; there grows sweet spikenard and ripe
cassia, Panchaean cinnamon-flowers and sprays of
oozy balm, while balsam creeps forth slowly in an
exuding stream.
</p>
         <p>Hither Love glided down, winging his way o'er
the long journey. Joyfully and with prouder gait
than e'er his wont he enters. Venus was seated on
her glittering throne, tiring her hair. On her right
hand and on her left stood the Idalian sisters. 1 Of
these one pours a rich stream of nectar over Venus'
<pb id="v.1.p.251"/>
head, another parts her hair with a fine ivory comb.
</p>
         <p>A third, standing behind the goddess, braids her
tresses and orders her ringlets in due array, yet
carefully leaving a part untended; such negligence
becomes her more. Nor did her face lack the mirror's
verdict; her image is reflected over all the palace
and she is charmed wheresoever she looks. While
she surveys each detail and approves her beauty
she notes the shadow of her son as he approaches
and catches the fierce boy to her fragrant bosom.
<q direct="unspecified">Whence comes thy joy? <q direct="unspecified">she asks;</q> cruel child,
what battles hast thou fought? What victim has
thine arrow pierced? Hast thou once more compelled
the Thunderer to low among the heifers of
Sidon? Hast thou overcome Apollo, or again
summoned Diana to a shepherd's cave? Methinks
thou hast triumphed over some fierce and potent
god.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Hanging upon his mother's kisses he answered:
<q direct="unspecified">Mother, be thou glad; a great victory is ours.
Now has Honorius felt our arrows. Thou knowest
Maria and her sire, the general whose spear protects
Gaul and Italy; the fame of noble Serena is
not hidden from thee. Haste thee, assent to their
princely prayers and seal this royal union.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Cytherea freed her from her son's embrace,
hastily bound up her hair, gathered up her flowing
dress and girt herself about with the divine girdle
whose all-compelling charm can stay the rain-swollen
torrent and appease the sea, the winds and angry
thunderbolts. Soon as she stood on the shore she
thus addressed her small foster-children. <q direct="unspecified">Come,
children, which of you will plunge beneath the glassy
wave and summon me hither fleet Triton to bear me
<pb id="v.1.p.253"/>
quickly o'er the deep? Never will he have come
to do us better service. Sacred is the marriage
that I seek. Make all speed in your search; may
be the Libyan sea rings to his conch, may be he
cleaves the Aegean main. Whoso shall find and
bring him hither shall have a golden quiver as a
reward.</q>
         </p>
         <p>She spake and, dividing into various bands, the
scouts set out. Triton was swimming beneath the
waves of the Carpathian sea, pursuing reluctant
Cymothoe. She feared her rough lover and eluded
his pursuit, her wet form gliding through the em-
braces of his strong arms. One of the Loves espied
him and cried, <q direct="unspecified">Stay! the deeps cannot hide your
amours. Make ready to carry our mistress; as a
reward for thy services (and 'tis no meagre one) thou
shalt have Cymothoe, a complaisant mistress shall she
be though she flout thee now. Come and win thy
recompense.</q>
         </p>
         <p>The dread monster uprose from the abyss; his
billowing hair swept his shoulders; hoofs of cloven
horn grown round with bristles sprang from where his
fishy tail joined his man's body. He swam three
strokes and at the fourth stranded upon the shore of
Cyprus. To shade the goddess the monster arched
back his tail; then his back, rough with living
purple, was bedded with scarlet coverlets; resting
in such a retreat does Venus voyage, her snowy
feet just dipping in the sea. A great company of
wingèd Loves fly after her, troubling the calm surface
of Ocean. Neptune's palace is all adorned with
flowers. Leucothoe, daughter of Cadmus, sports
on the water, and Palaemon drives his dolphin
with a bridle of roses. Nereus sets violets here
<pb id="v.1.p.255"/>
and there among the seaweed and Glaucus wreathes
his grey hair with deathless flowers. Hearing the
tale the Nereids, too, came mounted on various
beasts: one (maiden above but fish below) rides
the dread sea-tiger of Tartessus; another is carried
by that fierce ram, the terror of the Aegean, who
shatters ships with his forehead; a third bestrides
the neck of a sea-hon; another is borne along
by the sea-calf to which she clings. They vie with
one another in bringing gifts to the newly-wedded
pair. Cymothoe presents a girdle, Galatea a
precious necklace, Psamathe a diadem heavily encrusted
with pearls gathered by herself from the
depths of the Red Sea. Doto suddenly dives to
gather coral, a plant so long as it is beneath the
water, a jewel once it is brought forth from the waves.
</p>
         <p>The nude crowd of Nereids throng around Venus,
following her and singing praises after this manner;
<q direct="unspecified">We beg thee, Venus, our queen, to bear these
our gifts, these adornments, to queen Maria. Tell
her that never did Thetis receive their like nor
even our sister Amphitrite when she espoused
our Jupiter.1 Let the daughter of Stilicho hereby
realize the devotion of the sea and know that Ocean
is her slave. 'Tis we who bore up her father's fleet,
the hope of his victorious land, what time he set
out to avenge the ruined Greeks.</q>
         </p>
         <p>And now Triton's foam-flecked breast had touched
the Ligurian shore and his wearied coils were extended
over the surface of the water. Straightway Venus
flew high in the air to the city founded by the Gauls,
the city that shows as its device the fleece-covered
pelt of a sow.2 At the coming of the goddess the
routed clouds retire; bright shine the Alps be-
<pb id="v.1.p.257"/>
neath the clear North wind. The soldier rejoices
though he cannot tell why. The standards of
war burgeon with red flowers and the spears on a
sudden sprout with living leaves. Then Venus
thus addresses her attendant throng. <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Comrades
mine, keep away for a while the god of war that the
palace may be mine and mine alone. Banish afar
the terror of the flashing breastplate; let its scabbard
sheath the threatening sword. Advance not the
standards of war, the eagles and savage dragons.
This day the camp shall yield to my standards;
the flute shall sound instead of the bugle, the soft
strains of the happy lyre take the place of the
trumpets' blare. Let the soldiers feast even when
on guard and the beakers foam in the midst of
arms. Let regal majesty lay by its awful pride and
power, disdaining not to associate with the people,
make one the nobles with the crowd. Let joy be
unrestrained and sober Law herself be not ashamed
to laugh.
</p>
               <p>Hymen, choose thou the festal torches, and ye
Graces gather flowers for the feast. Thou, Concord,
weave two garlands. You, winged band, divide and
hasten whithersoever you can be of use: let none be
slothful or lazy. You others hang numberless lamps
in order from their brackets against the coming of
night. Let these haste to entwine the gleaming
door-posts with my sacred myrtle. Do you sprinkle
the palace with drops of nectar and kindle a whole
grove of Sabaean incense. Let others unfold yellow-dyed
silks from China and spread tapestries of Sidon
on the ground. Do you employ all your arts in
decorating the marriage-bed. Woven with jewels
and upborne on carved columns be its canopy, such
<pb id="v.1.p.259"/>
as rich Lydia ne'er built for Pelops nor yet the
Bacchae for Lyaeus, decked as his was with the
spoils of Ind and the mantling vine. Heap up there
all the gathered wealth of the family, all the spoil
that Honorius the elder, our emperor's grandsire,
won from Moor and Saxon, all that his dread father
with Stilicho at his side gained from numberless
wars, all that the Geloni and Armenians have
contributed or Meroe added— Meroe encircled by
furthermost Nile whose people decorate their hair
with arrows; whatever the Medes sent from the
banks of Persian Tigris when suppliant Parthia
bought peace of Rome. Let the lofty couch be
adorned with the barbaric splendour of kings'
treasuries; be all the wealth of all our triumphs
gathered in that marriage-chamber.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake she and all unannounced sought the
bride's home. But Maria, with no thoughts of
wedlock nor knowing that the torches were being
got ready, was listening with rapt attention to the
discourse of her saintly mother, drinking in that
mother's nature and learning to follow the example
of old-world chastity; nor does she cease under
that mother's guidance to unroll the writers of
Rome and Greece, all that old Homer sang, or
Thracian Orpheus, or that Sappho set to music
with Lesbian quill; (even so Latona taught Diana;
so gentle Mnemosyne in her cave gave instruction
to meek Thalia) — when the sky from afar grows more
bright, a sweeter air breathes through the astonished
palace and there is spread the happy fragrance
of scented locks. Soon came the proof; in all
her beauty the goddess bursts upon them. Yet
Venus stands amazed, admiring now the daughter's
<pb id="v.1.p.261"/>
loveliness, now the snowy neck and golden hair
of the mother. The one is like unto the crescent
moon, the other to the full. So grows a young
laurel beneath the shadow of its parent tree and,
small as it now is, gives promise of great branches
and thick foliage to come. Or as 'twere two roses
of Paestum on one stalk; the one day's fulness
has brought to maturity; steeped in the dews of
spring it spreads abroad its petals; the other yet
nestles in its bud nor dares receive the sun's warmth
within its tender heart.
</p>
         <p>Venus stood and addressed Maria with these gentle
words: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>All hail! revered daughter of divine Serena,
scion of great kings and destined to be the mother of
kings. For thy sake have I left my home in Paphos'
isle and Cyprus; for thy sake was I pleased to
face so many labours and cross so many seas lest
thou shouldst continue to live a private life little
befitting thy true worth and lest young Honorius
should still feed in his heart the flame of unrequited
love. Take the rank thy birth demands, resume
the crown to bequeath it to thy children and re-enter
the palace whence thy mother sprang. E'en
though no ties of blood united thee to the royal
house, though thou wert in no way related thereto,
yet would thy beauty render thee worthy of a kingdom.
</p>
               <p>What face could rather win a sceptre? What
countenance better adorn a palace? Redder than
roses thy lips, whiter than the hoar-frost thy neck,
cowslips 1 are not more yellow than thine hair, fire
not more bright than thine eyes. With how fine
an interspace do the delicate eyebrows meet upon
thy forehead! How just the blend that makes thy
blush, thy fairness not o'ermantled with too much
<pb id="v.1.p.263"/>
red! Pinker thy fingers than Aurora's, firmer thy
shoulders than Diana's; even thy mother dost thou
surpass. If Bacchus, Ariadne's lover, could transform
his mistress' garland into a constellation how
comes it that a more beauteous maid has no crown
of stars? Even now Boötes is weaving for thee a
starry crown, even now heaven brings new stars to
birth to do thee honour. Go, mate with one who
is worthy of thee and share with him an empire
co-extensive with the world. Ister now shall do
thee homage; all nations shall adore thy name.
Now Rhine and Elbe shall be thy slaves; thou shalt
be queen among the Sygambri. Why should I
number the peoples and the Atlantic's distant
shores? The whole world alike shall be thy dowry.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>She spake and fitted to Maria's neck and shining
limbs the rich gear which the happy Nereids had
just given her. She parted her hair with the spear's
point, girded up her dress, and with her own hands
set the veil over the maiden's hair.1 The procession
is halted singing at the door; brightly
gleams the holy chariot in which the new bride is to
fare. The prince burns to run and meet her and
longs for the sun's tardy setting. Even so the
noble steed when first the smell that stirs his passions
smites upon him proudly shakes his thick, disordered
mane and courses over Pharsalia's plains. His
nostrils are aflame and with a neighing he greets
the streams that saw his birth. His masters smile
at the hope of their stud's increase, and the mares
take pleasure in their handsome mate.
</p>
         <p>Meanwhile the army has laid aside its swords:
the soldiers are dressed in white and throng around
Stilicho, the bride's father. No standard-bearer nor
<pb id="v.1.p.265"/>
around Stilicho, the bride's father. No standard-bearer nor p265common soldier fails to scatter flowers like rain and to drench their leader in a mist of purple blossoms. Crowned with laurel and myrtle they sing: 
<q direct="unspecified">Blessed father, whether the vault of heaven is thy home, or thou walkest in Elysium, the mansion of the blest, behold Stilicho hath now fulfilled the promises he made thee. A happy interchange has now been made: he compensates thee for his upbringing, and renders marriage in return for marriage, giving back to a son what thou, that son's father, gave to him. Never needst thou repent of thy choice; a dying father's love misled thee not. Worthy is he to be thine heir, worthy to be entrusted with the child of so powerful a prince and to hold the reins of government. Now could I tell of the battles fought beneath the slopes of Mount Haemus, the contests wherefrom Strymon reeked red with blood; I could sing the fame of his arms and how, like a thunderbolt, he falls upon his foes, but the marriage-god says me nay. Our song must be such as now befits the singing. Who can surpass Stilicho in counsel? who in knowledge of law and equity? In thee are two opposèd qualities reconciled, wisdom and strength, prudence and fortitude. Was e'er so noble a brow? Whom would Rome's highest place more befit? What heart but thine is strong enough to bear so many troubles? Shouldst thou stand amid the crowd whoe'er shall see thee would exclaim, 'That is Stilicho.' It is thus that the aspect of supreme majesty brings its own witness — not with arrogant voice, or pompous walk, or haughty gesture. The graces which others affect and strive to seem to possess are thine by nature's gift. Modesty shines forth together with a noble sternness, 
<pb id="v.1.p.267"/>
and white hairs come hastening to increase
the reverence of thy face. Though dignity be the
crown of age and strength, by a far different lot, of
youth, yet either season decks thee with its own
peculiar honours. Thou art the ornament of fortune.
Never tookst thou up the sword for hurt nor ever
didst steep its blade in citizens' blood. No cruelties
on thy part aroused men's hatred; favouritism never
slacks the reins of justice. We love thee, yet we
fear thee. Our very fear testifies to our love, O thou
most righteous interpreter of Law, guardian most
sure of peace with honour, greatest of our generals,
most blessed among the fathers of our country.
We all confess that now we owe our emperor an even
firmer allegiance for that thou, hero invincible, art
the father of his bride. Crown thy head with a
garland, lay aside thy rank for a moment and join
our dances. An thou dost this, so may thy son
Eucherius 1 surpass the virtues of his sire; so may
the fair Thermantia,1 thy daughter, live to see a
marriage such as this; so may Maria's womb grow
big and a little Honorius, born in the purple, rest
on his grandsire's lap.</q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.269"/>
         </p>
                </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>