<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 1-3 - 3</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <biblStruct default="NO">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With an English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1920</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="NO">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb id="p.371"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="book">
                <head>Book III</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    IN the second book the subject of inquiry
was the nature and the end of rhetoric, and I proved
to the best of my ability that it was an art, that it
was useful, that it was a virtue and that its material
was all and every subject that might come up for
treatment. I shall now discuss its origin, its component parts, and the method to be adopted in handling and forming our conception of each. For most
authors of text-books have stopped short of this,
indeed Apollodorus confines himself solely to forensic
oratory.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    I know that those who asked me to write
this work were specially interested in that portion on
which I am now entering, and which, owing to the
necessity of examining a great diversity of opinions, at
once forms by far the most difficult section of this work,
and also, I fear, may be the least attractive to my
readers, since it necessitates a dry exposition of rules.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    In other portions of this work I have attempted to
introduce a certain amount of ornateness, not, I may
say, to advertise my style (if I had wished to do that, I
could have chosen a more fertile theme), but in order
that I might thus do something to lure our young
men to make themselves acquainted with those principles which I regarded as necessary to the study of
rhetoric: for I hoped that by giving them something
which was not unpleasant to read I might induce a
greater readiness to learn those rules which I feared
                    <pb id="p.373"/>
                    might, by the dryness and aridity which must necessarily characterise their exposition, revolt their minds
and offend their ears which are nowadays grown
somewhat over-sensitive.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Lucretilus has the same
object in mind when he states that he has set forth
his philosophical system in verse; for you will remember the well known simile which he uses
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">iv. 11. See also i. 936.</note>
                    :—
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">And as physicians when they seek to give</l>
                        <l part="N">A draught of bitter wormwood to a child,</l>
                        <l part="N">First smear along the edge that rims the cup</l>
                        <l part="N">The liquid sweets of honey, golden-hued,</l>
                    </quote>
                    and the rest.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    But I fear that this book will have
too little honey and too much wormwood, and that
though the student may find it a healthy draught,
it will be far from agreeable. I am also haunted by
the further fear that it will be all the less attractive
from the fact that most of the precepts which it contains are not original, but derived from others, and
because it is likely to rouse the opposition of certain
persons who do not share my views. For there are
a large number of writers, who though they are all
moving toward the same goal, have constructed
different roads to it and each drawn their followers
into their own.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The latter, however, approve of
the path on which they have been launched whatever its nature, and it is difficult to change the convictions implantted in boyhood, for the excellent reason
that everybody prefers to have learned rather than
to be in process of learning.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But, as will appear in
the course of this book, there is an infinite diversity
of opinions among writers on [his subject, since some
have added their own discoveries to those portions
of the art which were still shapeless and unformed,
                    <pb id="p.375"/>
                    and subsequently have altered even what was perfectly sound in order to establish a claim to
originality.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The first writer after those recorded by the poets
who is said to have taken any steps in the direction
of rhetoric is Empedocles. But the earliest writers
of text-books are the Sicilians, Corax and Tisias,
who were followed by another from the same island,
namely Gorgias of Leontini, whom tradition asserts
to have been the pupil of Empedocles.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    He, thanks to
his length of days, for he lived to a hundred and nine,
flourished as the contemporary of many rhetoricians,
was consequently the rival of those whom I have
just mentioned, and lived on to survive Socrates.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    In the same period flourished Thrasymachus of
Chalcedon, Prodicus of Ceos, Protagoras of Abdera,
for whose instructions, which he afterwards published
in a text-book, Euathlus is said to have paid 10,000
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">About £312.</note>
                    denarii, Hippias of Elis and Alcidamas of Elaea whom
Plato
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Phaedr.</hi>
                        261 D.
                    </note>
                    calls Palamedes.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There was Antiphon also,
who was the first to write speeches and who also wrote
a text-book and is said to have spoken most eloquently in his own defence; Polycrates, who,
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    as
have already said, wrote a speech against Socrates,
and Theodorus of Byzantium, who was one of those
called
                    <quote>word-artificers</quote>
                    by Plato.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Phaedr. 266</hi>
                        E.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Of these Protagoras and Gorgias are said to have been the
first to treat commonplaces, Prodicus, Hippias,
Protagoras and Thrasymachus the first to handle
emotional themes. Cicero in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Brutus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">vii. 27.</note>
                    states
that nothing in the ornate rhetorical style was
ever committed to writing before Pericles, and that
certain of his speeches are still extant. For my
part I have been unable to discover anything in
                    <pb id="p.377"/>
                    the least worthy of his great reputation for eloquence,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        XII, ii. 22: x. 49, where Quintilian asserts that all
the writings of Pericles have been lost.
                    </note>
                    and am consequently the less surprised that there
should be some who hold that he never committed
anything to writing, and that the writings circulating under his name are the works of others.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    These
rhetoricias had many successors, but the most
famous of (Gorgias' pupils was Isocrates, although
our authorities are not agreed as to who was his
teacher: I however accept the statement of Aristotle
on the subject.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    From this point the roads begin to
part. The pupils of Isocrates were eminent in every
branch of study, and when he was already advanced
in years (and he lived to the age of ninety-eight),
Aristotle began to teach the art of rhetoric in his
afternoon lectures,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Aristotle gave his esoteric lectures in the morning,
reserving the afternoon for those of more general interest:
see Aul. Gell. xx. v.
                    </note>
                    in which he frequently quoted
the wel-known line from the
                    <hi rend="italics">Philoctetes</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably the
                        <hi rend="italics">Philoctetes</hi>
                        of Euripides. The original line
was
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)sxro\n siwpa=n, barba/rous d' e)a=n le/gein,</foreign>
                        which Aristotle
travestied by substituting
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">*)isokra/thn</foreign>
                        for
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">barba/rous.</foreign>
                    </note>
                    in the form
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">Isocrates still speaks. 'Twere shame should I Sit silent.</l>
                    </quote>
                    Both Aristotle and Isocrates left text-books on
rhetoric, but that by Aristotle is the larger and contains more books. Theodectes, whose work I mentioned above,
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    also lived about the same period: while
Theophrastus, the pupil of Aristotle, produced some
careful work on rhetoric. After him we may note
that the philosophers, more especially the leaders of
the Stoic and Peripatetic schools, surpassed even
the rhetoricians in the zeal which they devoted to
the subject.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Hermagoras next carved out a path of
his own, which numbers have followed: of his rivals
Athenaeus seems to have approached him most
                    <pb id="p.379"/>
                    nearly. Later still much work was done by Apollonius Molon, Areus, Caecilius and Dionysius of
Halicarnassus.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    But the rhetoricians who attracted
the most enthusiastic following were Apollodorus of
Pergamus, who was the instructor of Augustus Caesar
at Apollonia, and Theodorus of Gadara, who preferred
to be called Theodorus of Rhodes: it is said that
Tiberius Caesar during his retirement in that island
was a constant attendant at his lectures.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    These
rhetoricians taught different systems, and two schools
have arisen known as the Apollodoreans and the
Theodoreans, these names being modelled on the
fashion of nomenclature in vogue with certain schools
of philosophy. The doctrines of Apollodorus are
best learned from his pupils, among whom Cains
Valgius was the best interpreter of his master's views
in Latin, Atticus in Greek. The only text-book by
Apollodorus himself seems to be that addressed to
Matius, as his letter to Domitius does not acknowledge the other works attributed to him. The
writings of Theodorus were more numerous, and
there are some still living who have seen his pupil
Herinagoras.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The first Roman to handle the subject was, to the
best of my belief, Marcus Cato, the famous censor,
while after him Marcus Antonius began a treatise on
rhetoric: I say
                    <quote>began,</quote>
                    because only this one work of
his survives, and that is incomplete. he was followed
by others of less note, whose names I will not omit to
mention, should occasion demand.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    But it was Cicero
who shed the greatest light not only on the practice
but on the theory of oratory; for he stands alone
among Romans as combining the gift of actual eloquence with that of teaching the art. With him for
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The younger Hermagoras, a rhetorician of the Augustan
age.
                    </note>
                    <pb id="p.381"/>
                    predecessor it would be more modest to be silent, but
for the fact that he himself describes his Rhetorica
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                        the
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inventione.</hi>
                    </note>
                    as a youthful indiscreition, while in his later works on
oratory he deliberately omitted the discussion of
certain minor points, on which instruction is generally
desired.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Cornificius wrote a good deal, Stertinius
something, and the elder Gallio a little on the same
subject. But Gallio's predecessors, Celsus and Laenas,
and in our own day Verginius, Pliny and Tutilius,
have treated rhetoric with greater accuracy. Even
to-day we have some distinguished writers on oratory
who, if they had dealt with the subject more comprehensively, would have saved me the trouble of
writing this book. But I will spare the names of the
living. The time will come when they will reap their
meed of praise; for their merits will endure to after
generations, while the calunmies of envy will perish
utterly.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Still, although so many writers have preceded me,
I shall not shrink from expressing my own opinion on
certain points. I am not a superstitious adherent of
any school, and as this book will contain a collection
of the opinions of many different authurs, it was desirable to leave it to my readers to selcet what they
will. I shall be content if they praise me for my
industry, wherever there is no scope for originality.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The question as to the origin of rhetoric need
not keep us long. For who can doubt that mankind
received the gift of speech from nature at its birth
(for we can hardly go further back than that), while
the usefulness of speech brought improvement and
study, and finally method and exercise gave perfection?
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    I cannot understand why some hold that
the elaboration of speech originated in the fact that
                    <pb id="p.383"/>
                    those who were in peril owing to some accusation
being made against them, set themselves to speak
with studied care for the purpose of their own defence. This, however, though a more honourable origin, cannot possibly be the earlier, for
accusation necessarily precedes defence. You might
as well assert that the sword was invented for the
purpose of self-defence and not for aggression.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It
was, then, nature that created speech, and observation that originated the art of speaking. Just as men
discovered the art of medicine by observing that some
things were healthy and some the reverse, so they
observed that some things were useful and some useless in speaking, and noted them for imitation or
avoidance, while they added certain other precepts
according as their nature suggested. These observations were confirmed by experience and each man
proceeded to teach what he knew.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inv.</hi>
                        i. 2.
                    </note>
                    it is
true, attributes the origin of oratory to the founders
of cities and the makers of laws, who must needs
have possessed the gift of eloquence. But why he
thinks this the actual origin, I cannot understand,
since there still exist certain nomad peoples without
cities or laws, and yet members of these peoples perform the duties of ambassadors, accuse and defend,
and regard one man as a better speaker than
another.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The art of oratory, as taught by most authorities, and those the best, consists of five parts:-
                    <hi rend="italics">invention, arrangement, expression, memory,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">delivery</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">action</hi>
                    (the two latter terms being used synonymously). But all speech expressive of purpose involves
also a
                    <hi rend="italics">subject</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">words.</hi>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    If such expression is brief
                    <pb id="p.385"/>
                    and contained within the limits of one sentence, it
may demand nothing more, but longer speeches
require much more. For not only what we say
and how we say it is of importance, but also
the circumstances under which we say it. It is here
that the need of arrangement comes in. But it will
be impossible to say everything demanded by the
subject, putting each thing in its proper place, without
the aid of memory.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It is for this reason that memory
forms the fourth department. But a delivery, which
is rendered unbecoming cither by voice or gesture,
spoils everything and almost entirely destroys the
effect of what is said. Delivery therefore must be
assigned the fifth place.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Those (and Albutins is among them), who maintain
that there are only three departments on the ground
that memory and delivery (for which I shall give
instructions in their proper place
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Book II. claps. ii. and iii.</note>
                    ) are given us by
nature not by art, may be disregarded, although
Thrasymachus held the same views as regards delivery.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Some have added a sixth department, subjoining
                    <hi rend="italics">judgment</hi>
                    to
                    <hi rend="italics">invention,</hi>
                    on the ground that it is
necessary first to
                    <hi rend="italics">invented</hi>
                    and then to
                    <hi rend="italics">exercise our judgment.</hi>
                    For my own part I do not believe that
                    <hi rend="italics">invention</hi>
                    can exist apart from
                    <hi rend="italics">judgement,</hi>
                    since we do not say that a
speaker has
                    <hi rend="italics">invented</hi>
                    incousistent, two-edged or foolish
arguments, but merely that he has failed to avoid
them. It is true that Cicero in his Rhetorica
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        No such statement is found in the
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inventione.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    includes
                    <hi rend="italics">judgment</hi>
                    under
                    <hi rend="italics">mention;</hi>
                    but in my opinion
                    <hi rend="italics">judgment</hi>
                    is so inextricably mingled with the first
three departments of rhetoric (for without
                    <hi rend="italics">judgment</hi>
                    neither
                    <hi rend="italics">expression</hi>
                    nor
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    are possible), that
I think that even delivery owes much to it. I say
this with all the greater confidence because Cicero in
                    <pb id="p.387"/>
                    his
                    <hi rend="italics">Partitiones oratoriae</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">i. 3.</note>
                    arrives at the same five-fold
division of which I have just spoken. For after an
initial division of oratory into
                    <hi rend="italics">invention</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">expression,</hi>
                    he assigns
                    <hi rend="italics">matter and</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    to
                    <hi rend="italics">invention, words</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">delivery</hi>
                    to
                    <hi rend="italics">expression,</hi>
                    and makes
                    <hi rend="italics">memory</hi>
                    a fifth
department common to them all and acting as their
guardian. Again in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Orator</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">14–17.</note>
                    he states that eloquence consists of five things, and in view of the fact
that this is a later work we may accept this as his
more settled opinion.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Others, who seem to me to
have been no less desirous than those mentioned
above to introduce some novelty, have added
                    <hi rend="italics">order,</hi>
                    although they had already mentioned arrangement,
as though
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    was anything else than the
marshalling of arguments in the best possible order.
Dion taught that oratory consisted only of
                    <hi rend="italics">invention</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement,</hi>
                    but added that each of these departments was twofold in nature, being concerned with
words and things, so that
                    <hi rend="italics">expression</hi>
                    comes under
                    <hi rend="italics">invention,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">delivery</hi>
                    under
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement,</hi>
                    while
                    <hi rend="italics">memory</hi>
                    must be added as a fifth department. The followers
of Theodorus divide
                    <hi rend="italics">invention</hi>
                    into two parts, the one
concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">matter</hi>
                    and the other with
                    <hi rend="italics">expression,</hi>
                    and then add the three remaining departments.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Hermagoras places
                    <hi rend="italics">judgment, division, order</hi>
                    and
everything relating to
                    <hi rend="italics">expression</hi>
                    under the heading
                    <hi rend="italics">of economy,</hi>
                    a Greek word meaning the management
of domestic affairs which is applied metaphorically to
oratory and has no Latin equivalent.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    A further question arises at this point, since
some make
                    <hi rend="italics">memory</hi>
                    follow
                    <hi rend="italics">invention</hi>
                    in the list of
departments, while others make it follow
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement.</hi>
                    Personally I prefer to place it fourth. For we ought
not merely to retain in our minds the fruits of our
                    <pb id="p.389"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">invention,</hi>
                    in order that we may be able to arrange
them, or to remember our
                    <hi rend="italics">arraangement</hi>
                    in order that
we may express it, but we must also commit to
memory the words which we propose to use, since
                    <hi rend="italics">memory</hi>
                    embraces everything that goes to the compposition of a speech.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There are also not a few who have held that these
are not
                    <hi rend="italics">parts</hi>
                    of rhetoric, but rather
                    <hi rend="italics">duties</hi>
                    to be
observed by the orator. For it is his business to
invent, arrange, express, etcetera. If, however, we
accept this view, we leave nothing to art.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    For
although the orator's task is to speak well, rhetoric
is the science of speaking well. Or if we adopt
another view, the task of the artist is to persuade,
while the power of persuasion resides in the art.
Consequently, while it is the duty of the orator to
invent and arrange,
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    may be
regarded as belonging to rhetoric.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    At this point
there has been much disagreement, as to whether
these are
                    <hi rend="italics">parts</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">duties</hi>
                    of rhetoric, or, as Athenaeus
believes,
                    <hi rend="italics">elements</hi>
                    of rhetoric, which the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">stoixei=a</foreign>
                    But they cannot correctly be called
                    <hi rend="italics">elements.</hi>
                    For in that case we should have to regard
them merely as first-principles, like the moisture, fire,
matter or atoms of which the universe is said to be
composed. Nor is it correct to call them duties, since
they are not preformed by others, but perform something themselves. We must therefore conclude that
they are
                    <hi rend="italics">parts.</hi>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For since rhetoric is composed of
them, it follows that:, since a whole consists of parts,
these must be parts of the whole which they compose. Those who have called them
                    <hi rend="italics">duties</hi>
                    seem to
me to have been further influenced by the fact that
they wished to reserve the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">parts</hi>
                    for another
                    <pb id="p.391"/>
                    division of rhetoric: for they asserted that the
                    <hi rend="italics">parts</hi>
                    of rhetoric were,
                    <hi rend="italics">panegyric, deliberative</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    oratory. But if these are parts, they are parts rather
of the material than of the art.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For each of them
contains the whole of rhetoric, since each of them
requires
                    <hi rend="italics">invention, arrangement, expression, memory</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">delivery.</hi>
                    Consequently some writers have thought
it better to say that there are three
                    <hi rend="italics">kinds</hi>
                    of oratory;
those whom Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Or.</hi>
                        I. xxxi. 141;
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxiv. 91.
                    </note>
                    has followed seem to me to
have taken the wisest course in terming them
                    <hi rend="italics">kinds of causes.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    There is, however, a dispute as to whether
there are three kinds or more. But it is quite certain that all the most eminent authorities among
ancient writers, following Aristotle who merely substituted the term
                    <hi rend="italics">public</hi>
                    for
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative,</hi>
                    have been
content with the threefold division.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Still a feeble
attempt has been made by certain Greeks and by
Cicero in his
                    <hi rend="italics">de Oratore,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Or.</hi>
                        ii. 10
                        <hi rend="italics">sq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    to prove that there are not
merely more than three, but that the number of
kinds is almost past calculation: and this view has
almost been thrust down our throats by the greatest
authority
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Unknown. Perhaps the elder Pliny.</note>
                    of our own times.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed if we place the
task of praise and denunciation in the third division,
on what kind of oratory are we to consider ourselves
to be employed, when we complain, console, pacify,
excite, terrify, encourage, instruct, explain obscurities,
narrate, plead for mercy, thank, congratulate, reproach, abuse, describe, command, retract, express
our desires and opinions, to mention no other of the
many possibilities?
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As an adherent of the older view
I must ask for indulgence and must enquire what was
the reason that led earlier writers to restrict a subject
                    <pb id="p.393"/>
                    of such variety to such narrow bounds. Those who
think such authorities in error hold that they were
influenced by the fact that these three subjects
practically exhausted the range of ancient oratory.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For it was customary to write panegyrics and denunciations and to deliver funeral orations, while the
greater part of their activities was devoted to the
law-courts and deliberative assemblies; as a result,
they say, the old writers of text-books only included
those kinds of oratory which were most in vogue.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The
defenders of antiquity point out that there are three
kinds of audience: one which comes simply for the
sake of getting pleasure, a second which meets to receive advice, a third to give judgement on causes.
In the course of a thorough enquiry into the question
it has occurred to me that the tasks of oratory must
either be concerned with the law-courts or with themes
lying outside the law-courts.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The nature of the
questions into which enquiry is made in the courts is
obvious. As regards those matters which do not
come before a judge, they must necessarily be concerned either with the past or the future. We praise
or denounce past actions, we deliberate about the
future.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Again everything on which we have to
speak must be either certain or doubtful. We praise
or blame what is certain, as our inclination leads us:
on the other hand where doubt exists, in some cases
we are free to form our own views, and it is here that
deliberation comes in, while in others, we leave the
problem to the decision of others, and it is on these
that litigation takes place.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Anaximenes regarded forensic and public oratory
as
                    <hi rend="italics">genera</hi>
                    but held that there were seven
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    :—
exhortation, dissuasion, praise, denunciation,
                    <pb id="p.395"/>
                    accusation, defence, inquiry, or as he called it
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)cetastiko/n.</foreign>
                    The first two, however, clearly belong to deliberative, the next to demonstrative, the three last to
forensic oratory.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    I say nothing of Protagoras, who
held that oratory was to be divided only into the
following heads: question and answer, command and
entreaty, or as he calls it
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">eu)xwlh/.</foreign>
                    Plato in his
                    <hi rend="italics">Sophist</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">222 o.</note>
                    in addition to public and forensic oratory
introduces a third kind which he styles
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">prosomilhtikh/,</foreign>
                    which I will permit myself to translate by
                    <quote>conversational.</quote>
                    This is distinct from forensic oratory and
is adapted for private discussions, and we may regard
it as identical with dialectic.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Isocrates
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Fr. 3
                        <hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
                    </note>
                    held that
praise and blame find a place in every kind of
oratory.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The safest and most rational course seems to be to
follow the authority of the majority. There is,
then, as I have said, one kind concerned with praise
and blame, which, however, derives its name from
the better of its two functions and is called
                    <hi rend="italics">laudatory;</hi>
                    others however call it
                    <hi rend="italics">demonstrative.</hi>
                    Both
names are believed to be derived from the Greek in
which the corresponding terms are
                    <hi rend="italics">encomiastic,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">epideictic.</hi>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The term
                    <hi rend="italics">epideictic</hi>
                    seems to me however
to imply display rather than demonstration, and to
have a very different meaning from
                    <hi rend="italics">encomiastic.</hi>
                    For
although it includes laudatory oratory, it does not
confine itself thereto.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Will any one deny the title
of
                    <hi rend="italics">epideictic</hi>
                    to
                    <hi rend="italics">panegyric?</hi>
                    But yet
                    <hi rend="italics">panegyrics</hi>
                    are advisory in form and frequently discuss the interests
of Greece. We may therefore conclude that, while
there are three kinds of oratory, all three devote
themselves in part to the matter in land, and in
part to display. But it may be that Romans are not
                    <pb id="p.397"/>
                    borrowing from Greek when they apply the title
                    <hi rend="italics">demonstrative</hi>
                    but are merely led to do so because
praise and blame demonstrate the nature of the
object with which they are concerned.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The second
kind is deliberative, the third forensic oratory. All
other
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    fall under these three
                    <hi rend="italics">genera:</hi>
                    you will
not find one in which we have not to praise or
blame, to advise or dissuade, to drive home or refute
a charge, while conciliation, narration, proof, exaggeration, extenuation and the moulding of the minds
of the audience by exciting or allaying their passions, are common to all three kind of oratory.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    I
cannot even agree with those who hold that
                    <hi rend="italics">laudalory</hi>
                    subjects are concerned with the question of
what is honourable, deliberative with the question of
what is expedient, and forensic with tie question of
what is just: the division thus made is easy and
neat rather than true: for all three kinds rely on
the mutual assistance of the other. For we deal
with justice and expediency in
                    <hi rend="italics">punegyric</hi>
                    and with
honour in
                    <hi rend="italics">(deliberations,</hi>
                    while you will rarely find a
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    case, in part of which at any rate something
of those questions just mentioned is not to be found.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Every speech however consists at once of that
which is expressed and that which expresses, that is
to say of matter and words. Skill in speaking is
perfected by nature, art and practice, to which some
add a fourth department, namely imitation, which I
however prefer to include under art.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    There are also
three aims which the orator must always have in
view; he must instruct, move and charm his hearers.
This is a clearer division than that made by those
who divide the task of oratory into that which relates
to things and that which concerns the emotions,
                    <pb id="p.399"/>
                    since both of these will not always be present in the
subjects which we shall have to treat. For some
themes are far from calling for any appeal to the
emotions, which, although room cannot always be
found for them, produce a most powerful effect
wherever they do succeed in forcing their way.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The
best authorities hold that there are some things in
oratory which require proof and others which do not,
a view with which I agree. Some on the other hand,
as for instance Celsus, think that the orator will not
speak on any subject unless there is some question
involved in it; but the majority of writers on rhetoric
are against him, as is also the threefold division of
oratory, unless indeed to praise what is allowed to be
honourable and to denounce what is admittedly disgraceful are no part of an orator's duty.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    It is, however, universally agreed that all questions
must be concerned either with something that is
written or something that is not. Those concerned with
what is written are questions of law, those which concern what is not written are questions of fact. Hermagoras calls the latter
                    <hi rend="italics">rational</hi>
                    questions, the former
                    <hi rend="italics">legal</hi>
                    questions, for so we may translate
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">logiko/n</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">nomiko/n.</foreign>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Those who hold that every question concerns either things or words, mean much the same.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It is also agreed that questions are either
                    <hi rend="italics">definite</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">indefinite. Indefinite</hi>
                    questions are those which may
be maintained or impugned without reference to
persons, time or place and the like. The Greeks call
them
                    <hi rend="italics">theses,</hi>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxi. 79.
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italics">propositions,</hi>
                    others
                    <hi rend="italics">general questions relating to civil life,</hi>
                    others again
                    <hi rend="italics">questions suited for philosophical discussion,</hi>
                    while Athenaeus calls them
                    <hi rend="italics">parts of a cause.</hi>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        81;
                        <hi rend="italics">Part. Or.</hi>
                        xviii. 62.
                    </note>
                    distinguishes two kinds,
the one concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">knowledge,</hi>
                    the other with
                    <hi rend="italics">action.</hi>
                    Thus
                    <quote>
                        Is the world governed by
                        <pb id="p.401"/>
                        providence?
                    </quote>
                    is a question of knowledge, while
                    <quote>Should we enter politics?</quote>
                    is a question of action. The
first involves three questions, whether a thing
is, what it is, and of what nature: for all these
things may be unknown: the second involves two,
how to obtain power and how to use it.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Definite</hi>
                    questions involve facts, persons, time and the like.
The Greeks call them
                    <hi rend="italics">hypotheses,</hi>
                    while we call them
                    <hi rend="italics">causes.</hi>
                    In these the whole question turns on persons and facts.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    An
                    <hi rend="italics">indefinite</hi>
                    question is always the
more comprehensive, since it is from the
                    <hi rend="italics">indefinite</hi>
                    question that the
                    <hi rend="italics">definite</hi>
                    is derived. I will illustrate
what I mean by an example. The question
                    <quote>Should a man marry?</quote>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italics">indefinite;</hi>
                    the question
                    <quote>Should Cato marry?</quote>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italics">definite,</hi>
                    and consequently may be
regarded as a subject for a
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    theme. But
even those which have no connexion with particular
persons are generally given a specific reference.
For instance the question
                    <quote>Ought we to take a share in the government of our country?</quote>
                    is abstract,
whereas
                    <quote>Ought we to take part in the government of our country under the sway of a tyrant?</quote>
                    has a
specific reference.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But in this latter case we may
say that a person is tacitly implied. For the
mention of a tyrant doubles the question, and
there is an implicit admission of time and quality;
but all the same you would scarcely be justified in
calling it a cause or definite question. Those questions which I have styled indefinite are also called
                    <hi rend="italics">general:</hi>
                    if this is correct, we shall have to call definite
questions
                    <hi rend="italics">special</hi>
                    questions. But in every special
question the general question is implicit, since the
                    <hi rend="italics">genus</hi>
                    is logically prior to the
                    <hi rend="italics">species.</hi>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And perhaps
even in actual causes wherever the notion of quality
comes into question, there is a certain intrusion of
                    <pb id="p.403"/>
                    the abstract.
                    <quote>Milo killed Clodius: he was justified in killing one who lay in wait for him.</quote>
                    Does not
this raise the general question as to whether we
have the right to kill a man who lies in wait for us?
What again of conjectures? May not they be of a
general character, as for instance,
                    <quote>What was the motive for the crime? hatred? covetousness?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Are we justified in believing confessions made under torture?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Which should carry greater weight, evidence or argument?</quote>
                    As for definitions, everything that they contain is undoubtedly of a general
nature.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There are some who hold that even those
questions which have reference to persons and particular cases may at times be called
                    <hi rend="italics">theses,</hi>
                    provided
only they are put slightly differently: for instance,
if Orestes be accused, we shall have a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause:</hi>
                    whereas
if it is put as question, namely
                    <quote>Was Orestes rightly acquitted?</quote>
                    it will be a
                    <hi rend="italics">thesis.</hi>
                    To the same class
as this last belongs the question
                    <quote>Was Cato right in transferring Marcia to Hortensius?</quote>
                    These persons distinguish a
                    <hi rend="italics">thesis</hi>
                    from a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    as follows: a
                    <hi rend="italics">thesis</hi>
                    is theoretical in character, while a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    has
relation to actual facts, since in the former case we
argue merely with a view to abstract truth, while in
the latter we have to deal with some particular act.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Some, however, think that general questions are
useless to an orator, since no profit is to be derived
from proving that we ought to marry or to take
part in politics, if we are prevented from so doing
by age or ill health. But not all general questions
are liable to this kind of objection. For instance
questions such as
                    <quote>Is virtue an end in itself?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>Is the world governed by providence?</quote>
                    cannot
be countered in this way.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Further in questions
                    <pb id="p.405"/>
                    which have reference to a particular person, although
it is not sufficient merely to handle the general
question, we cannot arrive at any conclusion on
the special point until we have first discussed the
general question. For how is Cato to deliberate
                    <quote>whether he personally is to marry,</quote>
                    unless the
general question
                    <quote>whether marriage is desirable</quote>
                    is first settled? And how is he to deliberate
                    <quote>whether he should marry Marcia,</quote>
                    unless it is
proved that it is the duty of Cato to marry?
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    There
are, however, certain books attributed to Hermagoras which support this erroneous opinion, though
whether the attribution is spurious or whether they
were written by another Hermagoras is an open
question. For they cannot possibly be by the
famous Hermagoras, who wrote so much that was
admirable on the art of rhetoric, since, as is clear
from the first book of the Rhetorica of Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inv.</hi>
                        i. 6.
                    </note>
                    he
divided the material of rhetoric into
                    <hi rend="italics">theses and causes.</hi>
                    Cicero objects to this division, contends that
                    <hi rend="italics">theses</hi>
                    have nothing to do with an orator, and refers all
this class of questions to the philosophers.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    But
Cicero has relieved me of any feeling of shame
that I might have in controverting his opinion, since
he has not only expressed his disapproval of his Rhetorica, but in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Orator,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Orator</hi>
                        xiv. 45.
                    </note>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">de Oratore</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">Topica</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Or.</hi>
                        iii. 30;
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        21.
                    </note>
                    instructs us to abstract such discussions
from particular persons and occasions,
                    <quote>
                        because
we can speak more fully on general than on special
themes, and because what is proved of the whole
must also be proved of the part.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    In all general
questions, however, the essential
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is the same as
in a cause or definite question. It is further
pointed out that there are some questions which
                    <pb id="p.407"/>
                    concern
                    <quote>things in themselves,</quote>
                    while others have
a particular reference; an example of the former
will be the question
                    <quote>Should a man marry?</quote>
                    of the
latter
                    <quote>Should an old man marry?</quote>
                    ; or again the
question whether a man is brave will illustrate the
first, while the question whether he is braver than
another will exemplify the second.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Apollodorus defines a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    in the following terms
(I quote the translation of his pupil Valgius):—
                    <quote>A cause is a matter which in all its parts bears on the question at issue,</quote>
                    or again
                    <quote>a cause is a matter of which the question in dispute is the object.</quote>
                    He then defines a
                    <hi rend="italics">matter</hi>
                    in the following terms:—
" A matter is a combination of persons, circumstances
of place and time, motives, means, incidents, acts,
instruments, speeches, the letter and the spirit of the
law.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Let us then understand a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    in the sense of
the Greek
                    <hi rend="italics">hypothesis</hi>
                    or subject, and a
                    <hi rend="italics">matter</hi>
                    in the
sense of the Greek
                    <hi rend="italics">peristasis</hi>
                    or collection of circumstances. But some, however, have defined a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    in
the same way that Apollodorus defines a
                    <hi rend="italics">matter.</hi>
                    Isocrates
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Fr. 13 Sheehan.</note>
                    on the other hand defines a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    as
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        some
definite question concerned with some point of civil affairs,
or a dispute in which definite persons are involved;
                    </hi>
                    while
Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxi. 80.
                    </note>
                    uses the following words:—
                    <quote>
                        A
                        <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                        may be
known by its being concerned with certain definite
persons, circumstances of time and place, actions, and
business, and will relate either to all or at any rate to
most of these.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    VI.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This chapter is highly technical and of little interest for
the most part to any save professed students of the technique
of the ancient schools of rhetoric. Its apparent obscurity will,
however, he found to disappear on careful analysis. The one
passage of general interest it contains is to be found in the
extremely ingenious fictitious theme discussed in sections
96
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    Since every cause, then, has a certain essential
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        There is no exact English equivalent for
                        <hi rend="italics">status. Basis</hi>
                        or
                        <hi rend="italics">ground</hi>
                        are perhaps the nearest equivalents.
                    </note>
                    on which it rests, before I proceed to set forth
how each kind of cause should be handled, I think I
                    <pb id="p.409"/>
                    should first examine a question that is common to all
of them, namely, what is meant by
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    whence it
is derived and how many and of what nature such
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    may be. Some, it is true, have thought that
they were peculiar merely to forensic themes, but
their ignorance will stand revealed when I have
treated of all three kinds of oratory.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    That which I
call the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    some style the
                    <hi rend="italics">constitution,</hi>
                    others the
                    <hi rend="italics">question,</hi>
                    and others again
                    <hi rend="italics">that which may be inferred from the question,</hi>
                    while Theodorus calls it the most
                    <hi rend="italics">general head,</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kefa/laion genikw/taton,</foreign>
                    to which everything
must be referred. These different names, however, all
mean the same thing, nor is it of the least importance
to students by what special name things are called,
as long as the thing itself is perfectly clear.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The
Greeks call this essential
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">sta/sis,</foreign>
                    a name which
they hold was not invented by Hermagoras, but
according to some was introduced by Naucrates, the
pupil of Isocrates, according to others by Zopyrus of
Clazomenae, although Aeschines in his speech against
Ctesiphon
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 206.</note>
                    seems to employ the word, when he asks
the jury not to allow Demosthenes to be irrelevant
but to keep him to the
                    <hi rend="italics">stasis</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the case.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The term seems to be derived from the fact that it
is on it that the first collision between the parties to
the dispute takes place, or that it forms the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis or standing</hi>
                    of the whole case. So much for the origin of
the name. Now for its nature. Some have defined
the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    as being the
                    <hi rend="italics">first conflict of the causes.</hi>
                    The
idea is correct, but the expression is faulty.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For the
essential
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is not the first conflict, which we may
represent by the clauses
                    <quote>You did such and such a thing</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>I did not do it.</quote>
                    It is rather the
kind of question which arises from the first conflict,
                    <pb id="p.411"/>
                    which we may represent as follows.
                    <quote>You did it,</quote>
                    <quote>I did not,</quote>
                    <quote>Did he do it?,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>You did this,</quote>
                    <quote>I did not do this,</quote>
                    <quote>What did he do?</quote>
                    It is clear
from these examples, that the first sort of question
depends on
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    the second on
                    <hi rend="italics">definition,</hi>
                    and
that the contending parties rest their respective cases
on these points: the
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    of these questions will
therefore be of a
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive</hi>
                    character
respectively.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Suppose it should be asserted that
sound is the conflict between two bodies, the statement would in my opinion be erroneous. For sound
is not the actual conflict, but a result of the conflict.
The error is, however, of small importance: for the
sense is clear, whatever the expression. But this
trivial mistake has given rise to a very serious error
in the minds of those who have not understood what
was meant: for on reading that the essential
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    was
the first conflict, they immediately concluded that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    was always to be taken from the first question,
which is a grave mistake.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For every question has
its
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    since every question is based on assertion by
one party and denial by another. But there are some
questions which form an essential part of causes, and
it is on these that we have to express an opinion;
while others are introduced from without and are,
strictly speaking, irrelevant, although they may
contribute something of a subsidiary nature to the
general contention. It is for this reason that there
are said to be several questions in one matter of
dispute.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Of these questions it is often the most
trivial which occupies the first place. For it is a
frequent artifice to drop those points in which we
place least confidence, as soon as we have dealt with
them; sometimes we make a free gift of them to our
                    <pb id="p.413"/>
                    opponents, while sometimes we are content to use
them as a step to arguments which are of greater
importance.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    A simple cause, however, although it
may be defended in various ways, cannot have more
than one point on which a decision has to be given,
and consequently the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the cause will be that
point which the orator sees to be the most important
for him to make and on which the judge sees that he
must fix all his attention. For it is on this that the
cause will stand or fall. On the other hand questions
may have more
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    than one.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 21.</note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    A brief example
will show what I mean. When the accused says
                    <quote>Admitting that I did it, I was right to do it,</quote>
                    he
makes the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    one of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality;</hi>
                    but when he adds
                    <quote>but I did not do it,</quote>
                    he introduces an element of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See § 30
                        <hi rend="italics">aqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    But denial of the facts is always the
stronger line of defence, and therefore I conceive the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    to reside in that which I should say, if I were
confined to one single line of argument.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    We are
right therefore in speaking of the first conflict of
                    <hi rend="italics">causes</hi>
                    in contradistinction to the conflict of
                    <hi rend="italics">questions.</hi>
                    For instance in the first portion of his speech on
behalf of Rabirius Postumus Cicero contends that the
action cannot lie against a Roman knight, while in
the second he asserts that no money ever came into
his client's hands. Still I should say that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    was to be found in the latter as being the stronger of
the two.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Again in the case of Milo I do not consider
that the conflict is raised by the opening questions, but
only when the orator devotes all his powers to prove that
Clodius lay in wait for Milo and was therefore rightly
killed. The point on which above all the orator must
make up his mind, even although he may be going to
                    <pb id="p.415"/>
                    take up various lines of argument in support of his
case, is this: what is it that he wishes most to impress
upon the mind of the judge? But although this
should be the first point for his consideration, it does
not follow that it should be the first that he will make
in his actual speech.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Others have thought that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    lay in the first
point raised by the other side in its defence. Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxv. 93.
                    </note>
                    expresses this view in the following words:—
                    <quote>
                        the
argument on which the defence first takes its stand
with a view to rebutting the charge.
                    </quote>
                    This involves
a further question as to whether the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    can only be
determined by the defence. Cornelius Celsus is
strongly against this view, and asserts that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is derived not from the denial of the charge, but from
him who affirms his proposition. Thus if the accused
denies that anyone has been killed, the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    will
originate with the accuser, because it is the latter
who desires to prove: if on the other hand the
accused asserts that the homicide was justifiable, the
burden of proof has been transferred and the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    will proceed from the accused and be affirmed by him.
I do not, however, agree.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For the contrary is nearer
to the truth, that there is no point of dispute if the
defendant makes no reply, and that consequently the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    originates with the defendant.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    But in my
opinion the origin of the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    varies and depends on
the circumstances of the individual case. For instance
in conjectural causes the affirmation may be regarded
as determining the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    since
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    is employed
by the plaintiff rather than the defendant, and consequently some have styled the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    originated
by the latter
                    <hi rend="italics">negative.</hi>
                    Again in any
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        where the law forms the major premise, while the
minor premiss is the act which is brought under the law.
                    </note>
                    the whole of the reasoning proceeds from him who
                    <pb id="p.417"/>
                    affirms.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But on the other hand he who in such cases
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Conjectural causes and the syllogism.</note>
                    denies appears to impose the burden of dealing with
such
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    upon his opponent. For if he says
                    <quote>I did not do it,</quote>
                    he will force his opponent to make use of con-
                    <hi rend="italics">jecture,</hi>
                    and again, if he says
                    <quote>The law is against you,</quote>
                    he will force him to employ the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism.</hi>
                    Therefore
we must admit that a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    can originate in denial.
All the same we are left with our previous conclusion
that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is determined in some cases by the
plaintiff, in some by the defendant.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Suppose the
accuser to affirm that the accused is guilty of homicide: if the accused denies the charge, it is he who
will determine the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    Or again, if he admits that
he has killed a man, but states that the victim was
an adulterer and justifiably killed (and we know that
the law permits homicide under these circumstances),
there is no matter in dispute, unless the accuser has
some answer to make. Suppose the accuser does
answer however and deny that the victim was guilty
of adultery, it will be the accuser that denies, and it
is by him that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is determined. The
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    then, will originate in the first denial of facts, but
that denial is made by the accuser and not the
accused.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Again the same question may make the
same person either accuser or accused.
                    <quote>
                        He who has
exercised the profession of an actor, is under no circumstances to be allowed a seat in the first fourteen
rows of the theatre.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Reserved for
                        <hi rend="italics">eguites.</hi>
                    </note>
                    An individual who had performed before the praetor in his private gardens, but
had never been presented on the public stage, has
taken his seat in one of the fourteen rows.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The
accuser of course affirms that he has exercised the
profession of an actor: the accused denies that he has
exercised the profession. The question then arises
                    <pb id="p.419"/>
                    as to the meaning of the
                    <quote>exercise of the profession of actor.</quote>
                    If he is accused under the law regarding
the seats in the theatre, the denial will proceed from
the accused; if on the other hand he is turned out
of the theatre and demands compensation for assault,
the denial will be made by the accuser.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    The view
of the majority of writers
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        that the defendant makes the
                        <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                        or
                        <hi rend="italics">status. See</hi>
                        § 13.
                    </note>
                    on this subject will,
however, hold good in most cases. Some have evaded
these problems by saying that a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is that which
emerges from affirmations and denials, such as
                    <quote>You did it,</quote>
                    <quote>I did not do it,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>I was justified in doing it.</quote>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    But let us see whether this is the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    itself or rather that in which the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is to be found.
Hermagoras calls a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    that which enables the
matter in question to be understood and to which the
proofs of the parties concerned will also be directed.
My own opinion has always been that, whereas there
are frequently different
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    of questions in connexion
with a cause, the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the cause itself is its most
important point on which the whole matter turns.
If anyone prefers to call that the
                    <hi rend="italics">general question</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">general head</hi>
                    of the cause, I shall not quarrel with him,
any more than I have done hitherto if he produced
a different technical term to express the same thing,
although I know that whole volumes have been
written on such disputes. I prefer however to call
it the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    There is the greatest possible disagreement among writers about this as about everything
else, but in this case as elsewhere they seem to me to
have been misled by a passion for saying something
different from their fellow-teachers. As a result
there is still no agreement as to the number and
names of
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    nor as to which are general and which
special.
                    <pb id="p.421"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    To begin with Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Categ.</hi>
                        ii. 7.
                    </note>
                    lays down that there are
ten categories on which every question seems to turn.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    First there is
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)si/a</foreign>
                    which Plautus calls
                    <hi rend="italics">essence,</hi>
                    the
only available translation: under this category we inquire
                    <hi rend="italics">whether a thing is.</hi>
                    Secondly there is
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    the meaning of which is self-evident. Third comes
                    <hi rend="italics">quantity,</hi>
                    which was subdivided by later philosophers
as dealing with two questions as to
                    <hi rend="italics">magnitude</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">number.</hi>
                    Next
                    <hi rend="italics">relation,</hi>
                    involving questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See §§ 52, 68
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.,</hi>
                        84–86, which make the meaning of
                        <hi rend="italics">translatio</hi>
                        fairly clear. No exact rendering is satisfactory.
Literally it means
                        <quote>transference of the charge</quote>
                        : the sense
is virtually the same as that of
                        <hi rend="italics">exceptio</hi>
                        (a plea made by
defendant in bar of plaintiff's action).
                        <quote>Exception</quote>
                        is
too unfamiliar and technical a term.
                        <quote>Competence,</quote>
                        despite
its vagueness, is perhaps the least unsatisfactory rendering.
                    </note>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">comparison.</hi>
                    This is followed by
                    <hi rend="italics">when</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">where.</hi>
                    Then come
                    <hi rend="italics">doing, suffering</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">possessing,</hi>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    which for example are concerned with a person's being
armed or clothed. Lastly comes
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kei=sqai</foreign>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">position,</hi>
                    which means to be in a certain position, such for instance as being warm, standing or angry. Of these
categories the first four concern
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    the remainder
concern only certain
                    <hi rend="italics">topics for argument.</hi>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Others
make the number of categories to be nine.
                    <hi rend="italics">Person,</hi>
                    involving questions concerning the mind, body or
external circumstances, which clearly has reference
to the means by which we establish
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">quality. Time,</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">xro/nos,</foreign>
                    from which we get questions
such as whether a child is born a slave, if his mother
is delivered of him while assigned
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">addicti</hi>
                        were not technically
                        <hi rend="italics">servi,</hi>
                        though in a virtual
condition of servitude, being the bondsmen of their creditors
till their debt was paid.
                    </note>
                    to her creditors.
                    <hi rend="italics">Place,</hi>
                    from which we get such disputes as to whether
it is permissible to kill a tyrant in a temple, or
whether one who has hidden himself at home can be
regarded as an exile.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Then comes
                    <hi rend="italics">time</hi>
                    in another
sense, called
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kairo/s</foreign>
                    by the Greeks, by which they
refer to a period of time, such as summer or winter;
                    <pb id="p.423"/>
                    under this heading come problems such as that about
the man who held high revel in a time of pestilence.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">There is no other reference to this theme.</note>
                    <hi rend="italics">Action</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">pra=cis,</foreign>
                    to which they refer questions as to
whether an act was committed wittingly or unwittingly, by accident or under compulsion and the like.
                    <hi rend="italics">Number,</hi>
                    which falls under the category of quantity,
under which come questions such as whether the
state owes Thrasybulus thirty talents for ridding it of
the same number of tyrants.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Cause,</hi>
                    under which
heading come a large number of disputes, whenever
a fact is not denied, but the defence pleads that the
act was just and reasonable.
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">tro/pos</foreign>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">manner,</hi>
                    which
is involved when a thing is said to have been done in
one way when it might have been done in another:
under this category come cases of such as that of the
adulterer who is scourged with thongs or starved to
death.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        An adulterer caught
                        <hi rend="italics">flagrante delicto</hi>
                        might be killed by
the husband or beaten. But to starve him to death in cold
blood would be illegal.
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italics">Opportunity</hi>
                    for action, the meaning of which
is too obvious to need explanation or illustration:
the Greeks however call it
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)/rgwn a)formai/</foreign>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    These
authorities like Aristotle hold that no question can
arise which does not come under one of these heads.
Some subtract two of them, namely
                    <hi rend="italics">number</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">opportunity,</hi>
                    and substitute for what I have called
                    <hi rend="italics">action, things,</hi>
                    or in Greek
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">pra/gmata.</foreign>
                    I have thought it sufficient to notice these doctrines, for fear someone might
complain of their omission. Still I do not consider
that
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    are sufficiently determined by these categories, nor that the latter cover every possible kind
of topic, as will be clear to any that read carefully
what I have to say on both points. For there will be
found to be many topics that are not covered by
these categories.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    I find it stated in many authors that some rhetoricians only recognise one kind of
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">con-</hi>
                    <pb id="p.425"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">jectural.</hi>
                    But they have not mentioned who these
rhetoricians are nor have I been able to discover.
They are however stated to have taken this view on
the ground that all our knowledge is a matter of
inference from indications. On this line of reasoning they might regard all
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    as
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative,</hi>
                    because
we inquire into the nature of the subject in every
case. But the adoption of either view leads to inextricable confusion.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Nor does it matter whether one
recognises only one kind of
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    or none at all, if
all causes are of the same nature.
                    <hi rend="italics">Coniectura</hi>
                    is derived from
                    <hi rend="italics">conicere</hi>
                    <quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">to</hi>
                        throw together,
                    </quote>
                    because it
implies the concentration of the reason on the truth.
For this reason interpreters of dreams and all other
phenomena are called
                    <hi rend="italics">coniectores</hi>
                    <quote>conjecturers.</quote>
                    But
the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural basis</hi>
                    has received more names than
one, as will appear in the sequel.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Some have recognised only two
                    <hi rend="italics">bases.</hi>
                    Archedemus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Fr. 11, Arnim.</note>
                    for instance admits only the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive</hi>
                    and refuses to admit the
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative,</hi>
                    since
he held that questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    take the form of
                    <quote>What is unfair? what is unjust? what is disobedience?</quote>
                    which he terms questions about
                    <hi rend="italics">identity</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">difference.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        the question may be stated
                        <quote>Does it conform to our conception of injustice or is it something different?</quote>
                        Questions of quality are regarded as questions of definition.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    A different view was held by those who
likewise only admitted two
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    but made them
the
                    <hi rend="italics">negative</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">juridical.</hi>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">negative basis is</hi>
                    identical with that which we call the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural, to</hi>
                    which some give the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">negative</hi>
                    absolutely,
others only in part, these latter holding that
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    is employed by the accuser,
                    <hi rend="italics">denial</hi>
                    only by the
accused.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">juridical is</hi>
                    that known in Greek as
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">dikaiologiko/s</foreign>
                    But just as Archedemus would not
recognise the
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative basis,</hi>
                    so these reject the
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive</hi>
                    which they include in
                    <hi rend="italics">the juridical,</hi>
                    holding
                    <pb id="p.427"/>
                    that in these questions we have to enquire whether
it is just that the act with which the accused is
charged should be called sacrilege or theft or madness.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    Pamplihlus held this opinion but subdivided
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    into several different species. The majority
of later writers have classified
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    as follows, involving however no more than a change of names:—
those dealing with ascertained facts and those
dealing with matters where there is a doubt. For
a thing must either be certain or uncertain: if
it is uncertain, the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    will be
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural;</hi>
                    if
certain, it will be some one of the other
                    <hi rend="italics">bases.</hi>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Apollodorus says the same thing when he states that
a question must either lie in
                    <hi rend="italics">things external,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>
                        circumstantial evidence.
                    </note>
                    which give
play to
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    or in our own
                    <hi rend="italics">opinions:</hi>
                    the former
he calls
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">pragmatiko/s</foreign>
                    the latter
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">peri\ e)nnoi/as</foreign>
                    The same
is said by those who employ the terms
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)prolhpto\s</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)prolhpto/s</foreign>
                        lit. = unpresumed.
                    </note>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">prolhptiko/s,</foreign>
                    that is to say
                    <hi rend="italics">doubtful</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">presumptive,</hi>
                    by this latter term meaning those facts which
are beyond a doubt.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    Theodorus agrees with them,
for he holds that the question is either as to whether
such and such a thing is really so, or is concerned
with the
                    <hi rend="italics">accidents</hi>
                    of something which is an admitted
fact: that is to say it is either
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">peri\ ou)si/as</foreign>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">peri\ sumbebhko/twn</foreign>
                    For in all these cases the first
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural,</hi>
                    while the second belongs to one
of the other classes. As for these other classes of
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    Apollodorus holds that there are two, one concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    and the other with the
                    <hi rend="italics">names of</hi>
                    things, that is to say a
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive basis.</hi>
                    Theodorus
makes them four, concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">existence, quality, quantity</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">relation.</hi>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    There are some too who make
questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">identity</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">difference</hi>
                    come under the
head of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    others who place it under the head
                    <pb id="p.429"/>
                    of
                    <hi rend="italics">definition.</hi>
                    Posidonius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Fr. p. 232, Bake.</note>
                    divides them into two
classes, those concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">words</hi>
                    and those concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">things.</hi>
                    In the first case he thinks that
the question is whether a word has any meaning; if
so, what is its meaning, how many meanings has it,
and how does it come to mean what it means? In
the latter case, we employ
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    which he calls
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kat' ai)/sqhsin,</foreign>
                    or inference from perception,
                    <hi rend="italics">quality, definition</hi>
                    which he calls
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kat' e)/nnoian,</foreign>
                    or rational inference, and
                    <hi rend="italics">relation.</hi>
                    Hence also comes the division
into things written and unwritten.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    Even Cornelius
Celsus stated that there were two general
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    one
concerned with the question
                    <hi rend="italics">whether a thing is,</hi>
                    the
other with the question
                    <hi rend="italics">of what kind it is.</hi>
                    He included
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    under the first of these, because
enquiry may equally be made as to whether sacrilege
has been committed, when a man denies that he
has stolen anything from a temple, and when he
admits that he has stolen private money from a
temple. He divides
                    <hi rend="italics">quality into fact</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law.</hi>
                    Under the head of the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law</hi>
                    he
places four classes, excluding questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence:</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        § 23;
                        <hi rend="italics">translatio</hi>
                        and
                        <hi rend="italics">exceptio</hi>
                        are virtually identical.
The four classes are Intention, Ambiguity, Contradictory
Laws, Syllogism.
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italics">quantity</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    he places under the
head of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        the
                        <hi rend="italics">conjectural basis</hi>
                        concerned with questions of fact.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    There is also another method of
dividing
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    into two classes: according to this
disputes are either about
                    <hi rend="italics">substance</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    while
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    is treated either in its most general sense or
in its special senses.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Substance</hi>
                    is dealt with by
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture:</hi>
                    for in enquiring into anything, we ask
whether it has been done, is being done, or is likely
to be done, and sometimes also consider its
                    <hi rend="italics">intention:</hi>
                    this method is preferable to that adopted by those
who style the conjectural
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis of fact,</hi>
                    as
though we only enquired into the past and what has
                    <pb id="p.431"/>
                    actually been done.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    The consideration of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    under its most general aspect rarely comes up in
the courts; I refer to questions such as
                    <quote>whether that is honourable which is generally praised.</quote>
                    With
regard to the special aspects of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    questions
sometimes occur about some common term, such as
whether sacrilege has been committed when a man
has stolen private money from a temple, or about
some act with a definite name, when there is no
doubt either as to the commission or the nature of
the act. Under this heading come all questions
about what is honourable, just or expedient.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    These
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    are said to contain others as well, because
                    <hi rend="italics">quantity</hi>
                    is sometimes concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural bases,</hi>
                    as in the question whether the sun is bigger than
the earth, and sometimes with
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative bases,</hi>
                    as in
the question what reward or punishment it would
be just to assign to some particular person, while
questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    undoubtedly are concerned
with
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    with questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See § 11 and the case cited in 38, where the accused
would argue that he was guilty not of sacrilege, but of
simple theft.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">ratiocinative basis or syllogism</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        When we argue that a certain case comes under a certain law.
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        § 15.
                    </note>
                    and the majority of questions dealing with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    are based
on equity, with the exception that this last question
sometimes admits of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    as, for instance, concerning the
                    <hi rend="italics">intentions</hi>
                    of the legislator:
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity,</hi>
                    however, must always be explained by
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    because as it is clear that the words admit of two
interpretations the only question is as to the
                    <hi rend="italics">intention.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    A large number of writers recognise
                    <hi rend="italics">general bases;</hi>
                    Cicero adopts them in his
                    <hi rend="italics">Orator,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi>
                        xiv. 45.
                    </note>
                    and holds that
everything that can form the subject of dispute or
discussion is covered by the three questions,
                    <hi rend="italics">whether</hi>
                    <pb id="p.433"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">it is, what it is,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">of what kind it is.</hi>
                    The names
of these three
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    are too obvious for mention.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Conjectural, definitive, and qualitative.</note>
                    The same view is asserted by Patrocles.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    Marcus
Antonius stated that there were three
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    in the following words:—
                    <quote>
                        The things which form
the ground of every speech are few and are as
follows:—' Was a thing done or not done? 'Was it
just or unjust?' 'Was it good or bad?'
                    </quote>
                    But since,
when we are said to have been justified in doing
anything, this does not merely mean that our action
was legal, but further implies that it was just, those
who follow Antonius attempt to differentiate these
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    with greater exactness. They therefore called
them
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural, legal</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">juridical,</hi>
                    a division which
meets with the approval of Verginius as well.
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    These
they then subdivided into species, placing
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    under the head of the
                    <hi rend="italics">legal basis,</hi>
                    together with all
others which are concerned with the letter of the law:
such as that of
                    <hi rend="italics">contradictory laws,</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ntinomi/a</foreign>
                    that
which rests on the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law</hi>
                    and on
                    <hi rend="italics">meaning</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    (which the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kata\ r(hto\n kai\ dia/noian</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">meta/lhyis</foreign>
                    to which latter we give various
names, styling it the
                    <hi rend="italics">translative, transumptive</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">transpositive basis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Concerned with questions of competence.</note>
                    ; the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism,</hi>
                    which we call the
                    <hi rend="italics">ratiocinative</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">deductive basis;</hi>
                    and those which turn
on
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)mfiboli/a.</foreign>
                    I mention these because
they are called
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    by most writers, though some
prefer to call them
                    <hi rend="italics">legal questions.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    Athenaeus laid down that there were four
                    <hi rend="italics">bases:</hi>
                    the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">protreptikh\</foreign>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">parormhtikh/,</foreign>
                    that is, the
                    <hi rend="italics">hortative,</hi>
                    which is peculiar to deliberative themes;
the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">suntelikh/</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">suntelikh/</foreign>
                        lit. = contributory.
                    </note>
                    which is shown to be the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural,</hi>
                    not
so much from the name itself, but from what
                    <pb id="p.435"/>
                    follows; the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(pallaktikh/</foreign>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive,</hi>
                    for it consists
in a change of terms.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The defendant admits the act, but gives it a different
name,
                        <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>
                        theft, not sacrilege.
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(pallaktikh/</foreign>
                        = changing.
                    </note>
                    ; and the
                    <hi rend="italics">juridical</hi>
                    to which
he gives the name employed by other Greek writers.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">dikaiologiko/s</foreign>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    For, as I have said, there is a great variety in the
names employed. There are some who, arguing from
its meaning of change, hold that
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(pallaktikh/</foreign>
                    is the
                    <hi rend="italics">translative basis,</hi>
                    which is concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">competence.</hi>
                    Others, Caecilius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Caec. fr. 49, Burkh.</note>
                    and Theon for instance, hold
that there are the same number of
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    but make
them of a different kind, namely, those covered by
the questions whether a thing is, what it is, of what
kind it is and how great it is.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ar.
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        1416
                        <hi rend="italics">b</hi>
                        : 1374
                        <hi rend="italics">a</hi>
                        .
                    </note>
                    in his
                    <hi rend="italics">Rhetoric</hi>
                    states that all enquiry turns on the questions
                    <hi rend="italics">whether a thing is, of what kind it is, how great it is,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">of how many parts it consists.</hi>
                    In one
place however he recognises the force of
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    as well, saying that certain points are defended
on the following lines:—
                    <quote>I took it, but did not steal it.</quote>
                    <quote>I struck him, but did not commit an assault.</quote>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inv.</hi>
                        I. viii. 10.
                    </note>
                    again in his Rhetorica makes the
number of
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    to be four, namely those concerned
with
                    <hi rend="italics">fact, names, kinds,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">legal action,</hi>
                    that is to say
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    is concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">fact, definition</hi>
                    with
                    <hi rend="italics">names, quality</hi>
                    with
                    <hi rend="italics">kinds,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">law</hi>
                    with
                    <hi rend="italics">action:</hi>
                    under this latter head of
                    <hi rend="italics">law</hi>
                    he included questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence.</hi>
                    But in another passage he
treats
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Part. Or.</hi>
                        31 and 38.
                    </note>
                    legal questions as a species of
                    <hi rend="italics">action.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Some writers have held that there are five
                    <hi rend="italics">bases:</hi>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural, definitive, qualitative, quantitative</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">relative.</hi>
                    Theodorus, also, as I have said,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 36.</note>
                    adopts the
same number of general heads,
                    <hi rend="italics">whether a thing is, what it is, of what kind it is, how great it is,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">to what it refers.</hi>
                    The last he considers to be chiefly concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">comparison,</hi>
                    since better and worse, greater and less
                    <pb id="p.437"/>
                    are meaningless terms unless referred to some
standard.
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    But questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">relation,</hi>
                    as I have already
pointed out, enter also into
                    <hi rend="italics">translative</hi>
                    questions, that
is, questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence,</hi>
                    since in cases such as
                    <quote>Has this man a right to bring an action?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>
                        Is
it fitting that he should do such and such a thing,
or against this man, or at this time, or in this
manner?
                    </quote>
                    For all these questions must be referred
to a certain standard.
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    Others hold that there are
six
                    <hi rend="italics">bases: conjecture</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ge/nesis,</foreign>
                    <hi rend="italics">quality, particularity</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">i)dio/ths</foreign>
                    by which word they mean
                    <hi rend="italics">definition, quantity</hi>
                    or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ci/a,</foreign>
                    <hi rend="italics">comparison</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">competence, for</hi>
                    which a new
term has been found in
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">meta/stasis</foreign>
                    I call it new
when applied to a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    for Hermagoras employs it
to describe a species of
                    <hi rend="italics">juridical question.</hi>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    Others
think there are seven, while refusing to recognise
                    <hi rend="italics">competence, quantity</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">comparison,</hi>
                    in place of which
they substitute four
                    <hi rend="italics">legal bases,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 46.</note>
                    completing the
seven by the addition of those three which they call
                    <hi rend="italics">rational.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Conjectural, definitive, qualitative.</note>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    Others again make eight by the addition
of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    to the above-mentioned seven. Some
on the other hand have introduced a fresh method
of division, reserving the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    for the
                    <hi rend="italics">rational,</hi>
                    and giving the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    to the
                    <hi rend="italics">legal,</hi>
                    as I mentioned above,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 46.</note>
                    since in the former the
problem is concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">facts,</hi>
                    in the latter with
the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law.</hi>
                    Some on the contrary reverse
this nomenclature calling the legal questions
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    and the rational grounds
                    <hi rend="italics">questions.</hi>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    But others have
thought that there are only three
                    <hi rend="italics">rational bases,</hi>
                    covered by the questions
                    <hi rend="italics">whether a thing is, what it is,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">of what kind it is?</hi>
                    Hermagoras is alone in
thinking that there are four, namely
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture, particularity, competence,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">quality:</hi>
                    to the latter he
                    <pb id="p.439"/>
                    appends the phrase
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kata\ sumbebhko/s</foreign>
                    <quote>according to its accidents,</quote>
                    illustrating his meaning by putting a
case where it is enquired whether a man
                    <hi rend="italics">happen</hi>
                    to
be good or bad. He then subdivides
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    into
four species: first that which is concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">things to he sought or avoided,</hi>
                    which belongs to
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory:
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    secondly those concerned
                    <hi rend="italics">with persons,</hi>
                    by which he indicates
                    <hi rend="italics">panegyric:</hi>
                    thirdly the
                    <hi rend="italics">practical or pragmatic,</hi>
                    which is concerned
                    <hi rend="italics">with things in general</hi>
                    without reference to persons, and may be
illustrated by questions such as whether he is free
who is claimed as a slave and waiting the trial of his
case,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">assertio</hi>
                        = a trial in which the question of a person's
liberty is involved. When waiting trial, this person is
described as
                        <hi rend="italics">in assertiolle.</hi>
                    </note>
                    whether riches beget insolence, and whether a
thing is just or good; lastly there is the
                    <hi rend="italics">juridical</hi>
                    species, under which practically the same questions
arise, but in relation to certain definite persons, as for
instance when it is asked whether that particular man
has done well or ill.
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    I am aware that another explanation is given by Cicero in the first book of his
Rhetorica
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inv.</hi>
                        i. xi. 14.
                    </note>
                    of the species known as
                    <hi rend="italics">practical,</hi>
                    where he says that it is
                    <quote>
                        the department under
which we consider what is right according to civil
usage and equity: this department is regarded by
us as the special sphere of the lawyer.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    But I have
already mentioned
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inv.</hi>
                        i. xi. 14.
                    </note>
                    what his opinion was about this
particular work. The Rhetorica are simply a collection of school-notes on rhetoric which he worked
up into this treatise while quite a young man. Such
faults as they possess are due to his instructor. In the
present instance he may have been influenced by the
fact that the first examples given by Hermagoras of
this species are drawn from legal questions, or by the
fact that the Greeks call interpreters of the law
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">pragmatikoi/.</foreign>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    But for these early efforts Cicero
                    <pb id="p.441"/>
                    substituted his splendid
                    <hi rend="italics">de Oratore</hi>
                    and therefore cannot be
blamed for giving false instruction. I will now
return to Hermagoras. He was the first rhetorician
to teach that there was a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    concerned with
                    <hi rend="italics">competence,</hi>
                    although the elements of this doctrine are
found in Aristotle,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        II. xv. 8.
                    </note>
                    without however any mention of
the name.
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    The legal questions were according to
Hermagoras of five kinds. First the letter of the
law and its intention; the names which he gives to
these are
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kata\ r(hto/n</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(pecai/resis,</foreign>
                    that is to say
                    <hi rend="italics">the letter of the law</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">exceptions</hi>
                    thereto: the
first of these classes is found in all writers, but the
term
                    <hi rend="italics">exception</hi>
                    is less in use. The number is
completed by the
                    <hi rend="italics">ratiocinative basis</hi>
                    and those
dealing with
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">contradictory laws.</hi>
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    Albutius
adopts this classification, but eliminates
                    <hi rend="italics">competence,</hi>
                    including it under the juridical
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    Further he
holds that in legal questions there is no
                    <hi rend="italics">ratiocinative basis.</hi>
                    I know that those who are prepared to
read ancient writers on rhetoric more carefully than
I have, will be able to discover yet more on this
subject, but I fear that I may have been too lengthy
even in saying what I have said.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    I must admit that I am now inclined to take a
different view from that which I once held. It would
perhaps be safer for my reputation if I were to make
no modification in views which I not only held for so
many years, but of which I expressed my open approbation.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    But I cannot bear to be thought guilty of
concealment of the truth as regards any portion of
my views, more especially in a work designed for the
profit of young men of sound disposition. For Hippocrates,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Epidem</hi>
                        V. 14.
                    </note>
                    the great physician, in my opinion took the
most honourable course in acknowledging some of
                    <pb id="p.443"/>
                    his errors to prevent those who came after from
being led astray, while Cicero had no hesitation about
condemning some of his earlier works in books which
he published later: I refer to his condemnation of
his
                    <hi rend="italics">Lucullus</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">Catulus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The two books of the first edition of the
                        <hi rend="italics">Academica.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and the books
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        the Rhetorica, better known as
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inventione.</hi>
                    </note>
                    on rhetoric
which I have already mentioned.
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed we should
have no justification for protracting our studies if we
were forbidden to improve upon our original views.
Still none of my past teaching was superfluous: for
the views which I am now going to produce will be
found to be based on the same principles, and consequently no one need be sorry to have attended my
lectures, since all that I am now attempting to do is to
collect and rearrange my original views so that they
may be somewhat more instructive. But I wish to
satisfy everybody and not to lay myself open to the
accusation that I have allowed a long time to elapse
between the formation and publication of my views.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    I used to follow the majority of authorities in adhering to three
                    <hi rend="italics">rational bases,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural, qualitative</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive,</hi>
                    and to one
                    <hi rend="italics">legal basis.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. v. 4.</note>
                    These were
my
                    <hi rend="italics">general bases.</hi>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">legal basis</hi>
                    I divided into five
                    <hi rend="italics">species,</hi>
                    dealing with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law and intention, contradictory laws,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism, ambiguity</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">competence.</hi>
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    It is now clear to me that the fourth of the
                    <hi rend="italics">general bases</hi>
                    may be removed, since the original
division which I made into
                    <hi rend="italics">rational</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">legal bases is</hi>
                    sufficient. The fourth therefore will not be a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    but a kind of
                    <hi rend="italics">question;</hi>
                    if it were not, it would form
one of the
                    <hi rend="italics">rational bases.</hi>
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    Further I have removed
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    from those which I called
                    <hi rend="italics">species.</hi>
                    For I
often asserted, as all who have attended my lectures
will remember, and even those discourses which
were published against my will
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See I. Proem. 7.</note>
                    included the
                    <pb id="p.445"/>
                    statement, that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    concerned with competence
hardly ever occurs in any dispute under such circumstances that it cannot more correctly be given some
other name, and that consequently some rhetoricians
exclude it from their list of
                    <hi rend="italics">bases.</hi>
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    I am, however,
well aware that the point of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    is raised in
many cases, since in practically every case in which
a party is said to have been ruled out of court through
some error of form, questions such as the following
arise: whether it was lawful for this person to bring
an action, or to bring it against some particular
person, or under a given law, or in such a court, or
at such a time, and so on
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    But the question of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    as regards persons, times, legal actions and
the rest originates in some pre-existent cause:
the question turns therefore not on
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    itself, but on the cause with which the point of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    originates.
                    <quote>
                        You ought to demand the
return of a deposit not before the praetor but before
the consuls, as the sum is too large to come under
the praetor's jurisdiction.
                    </quote>
                    The question then arises
whether the sum is too large, and the dispute is one
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    of fact.
                    <quote>
                        You have no right to bring an action against
me, as it is impossible for you to have been appointed
to represent the actual plaintiff.
                    </quote>
                    It then has to be
decided whether he could have been so appointed.
                    <quote>
                        You ought not to have proceeded by interdict,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                            by getting an order for restitution.
                        </note>
                        but
to have put in a plea for possession.
                    </quote>
                    The point
in doubt is whether the interdict is legal. All these
points fall under the head of
                    <hi rend="italics">legal questions.</hi>
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    not even those special pleas, in which questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    make themselves most evident, give rise to
the same species of question as those laws under
which the action is brought, so that the enquiry is
                    <pb id="p.447"/>
                    really concerned with the name of a given act,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">e. g.</hi>
                        murder or manslaughter: sacrilege or theft.
                    </note>
                    with
the letter of the law and its meaning, or with something that requires to be settled by argument? The
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    originates from the question, and in cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    it is not the question concerning which
the advocate argues that is involved, but the question
on account of which he argues.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 70.</note>
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    An example will make
this clearer.
                    <quote>You have killed a man.</quote>
                    <quote>I did not kill him.</quote>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    is whether he has killed him;
the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is the
                    <hi rend="italics">conjectural.</hi>
                    But the following case is
very different.
                    <quote>I have the right to bring this action.</quote>
                    <quote>You have not the right.</quote>
                    The question is whether he
has the right, and it is from this that we derive the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    For whether he is allowed the right or not depends
on the event, not on the cause itself, and on the decision of the judge, not on that on account of which
he gives such a decision.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    The following is a similar
example.
                    <quote>You ought to be punished.</quote>
                    <quote>I ought not.</quote>
                    The judge will decide whether he should be
punished, but it is not with this that the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    or
the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is concerned. Where then does the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    lie?
                    <quote>You ought to be punished, for you have killed a man.</quote>
                    <quote>I did not kill him.</quote>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    is
whether he killed him.
                    <quote>I ought to receive some honour.</quote>
                    <quote>You ought not.</quote>
                    Does this involve a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis?</hi>
                    I think not.
                    <quote>I ought to receive some honour for killing a tyrant.</quote>
                    <quote>You did not kill him.</quote>
                    Here
there is a
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    and a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                        the conjectural.
                    </note>
                    as well.
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    So, too,
                    <quote>You are not entitled to bring this action,</quote>
                    <quote>I have,</quote>
                    involves no
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    Where then is it to be found?
                    <quote>You have no right to bring this action, because you have been deprived of civil rights.</quote>
                    In this case the
question is whether he has been so deprived, or
whether loss of civil rights debars a person from
                    <pb id="p.449"/>
                    bringing an action. Here on the other hand we find
both
                    <hi rend="italics">questions and bases.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        sc. the conjectural or definitive basis and the qualitative.
                    </note>
                    It is therefore to
                    <hi rend="italics">kinds of causes,</hi>
                    not to
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    that the term
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    applies:
other
                    <hi rend="italics">kinds of cause</hi>
                    are the
                    <hi rend="italics">comparative</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">recriminatory.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. x. 3 and 4.</note>
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>But,</quote>
                    it is urged,
                    <quote>
                        the case 'I have a
right,' 'You have not,' is similar to 'You have killed
a man,' 'I was justified in so doing.'
                    </quote>
                    I do not deny
it, but this does not make it a
                    <hi rend="italics">basis.</hi>
                    For these statements are not propositions until the reasons for them
are added. If they were propositions as they stand,
the case could not proceed.
                    <quote>Horatius has committed a crime, for he has killed his sister.</quote>
                    <quote>
                        He has not
committed a crime, since it was his duty to kill her
for mourning the death of an enemy.
                    </quote>
                    The question
is whether this was a justifiable reason, and the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is one of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality.</hi>
                    So too as regards
                    <hi rend="italics">competence.</hi>
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        You
have no right to disinherit, since a person who has
been deprived of civil rights is not allowed to take
legal action.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>I have the right, since disinheriting is not legal action.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Disinheritance could only be effected by legal action.</note>
                    The question here is what is legal
action. And we shall arrive at the conclusion that the
son's disinheritance is unlawful, by use of the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 15.</note>
                    The case will be similar with all the
                    <hi rend="italics">rational</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">legal bases.</hi>
                    <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
                    I am aware that there have been some who
placed
                    <hi rend="italics">competence</hi>
                    among
                    <hi rend="italics">rational bases,</hi>
                    using as
illustrations cases such as,
                    <quote>I killed a man under orders from my general,</quote>
                    <quote>I gave the votive offerings in a temple to a tyrant under compulsion,</quote>
                    <quote>
                        I deserted owing to the fact that storms or floods or ill health prevented me from rejoining.
                    </quote>
                    That is to say
it was not due to me, but some external cause.
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                    From
these writers I differ even more widely: for it is not
the nature of the
                    <hi rend="italics">legal action</hi>
                    itself which is involved
in the question of
                    <hi rend="italics">competence,</hi>
                    but the cause of the act;
                    <pb id="p.451"/>
                    and this is the case in almost every defence. Finally
he who adopts this line of defence, does not thereby
abandon the
                    <hi rend="italics">qualitative basis;</hi>
                    for he states that he himself is free from blame, so that we really should
differentiate between two kinds of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        (
                        <hi rend="italics">A</hi>
                        ) Absolute, when the deed is shown to be right. (
                        <hi rend="italics">B</hi>
                        )
Relative, when the act is not defended, but the agent is
cleared of the guilt of the act.
                    </note>
                    one of
which comes into play when both the accused person
and his act are defended, and the other when the
accused person alone is defended.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
                    We must therefore accept the view of the authorities followed by Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 44.</note>
                    to the effect that there are
three things on which enquiry is made in every case:
we ask
                    <hi rend="italics">whether a thing is, that it is, and of that kind it is.</hi>
                    Nature herself imposes this upon us. For first of all
there must be some subject for the question, since we
cannot possibly determine
                    <hi rend="italics">what a thing is,</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">of what kind it is,</hi>
                    until we have first ascertained
                    <hi rend="italics">whether it is,</hi>
                    and therefore the first question raised is
                    <hi rend="italics">whether it is.</hi>
                    But even when it is clear that a thing
                    <hi rend="italics">is,</hi>
                    <milestone n="81" unit="section"/>
                    it is not
immediately obvious
                    <hi rend="italics">what it is.</hi>
                    And when we have
decided what it is, there remains the question of its
                    <hi rend="italics">quality.</hi>
                    These three points once ascertained, there
is no further question to ask. These heads cover both
                    <hi rend="italics">definite</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">indefinite questions.</hi>
                    One or more of them
is discussed in every demonstrative, deliberative or
forensic theme.
                    <milestone n="82" unit="section"/>
                    These heads again cover all cases in
the courts, whether we regard them from the point
of view of
                    <hi rend="italics">rational</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">legal questions.</hi>
                    For no legal
problem can be settled save by the aid of
                    <hi rend="italics">definition, quality</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture.</hi>
                    <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>
                    Those, however, who are
engaged in instructing the ignorant will find it useful
at first to adopt a slightly less rigid method: the road
will not be absolutely straight to begin with, but it
will be more open and will provide easier going. I
would have them therefore learn above all things
                    <pb id="p.453"/>
                    that there are four different methods which may be
employed in every case, and he who is going to plead
should study them as first essentials. For, to begin
with the defendant, far the strongest method of self-defence is, if possible, to deny the charge. The
second best is when it is possible to reply that the
particular act with which you are charged was never
committed. The third and most honourable is to
maintain that the act was justifiable. If none of
these lines of defence are feasible, there remains the
last and only hope of safety: if it is impossible either
to deny the charge or justify the act, we must evade
the charge with the aid of some point of law, making
it appear that the action has been brought against us
illegally
                    <milestone n="84" unit="section"/>
                    Hence arise those questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">legal action</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">competence.</hi>
                    For there are some things, which,
although not laudable in themselves, are yet permitted by law; witness the passage in the Twelve Tables
authorising creditors to divide up a debtor's body
amongst themselves, a law which is repudiated by
public custom. There are also certain things which
although equitable are prohibited by law; witness the
restrictions placed on testamentary disposition.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        e.g. that the legal heir must receive at least a quarter of
the property.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>
                    The
accuser likewise has four things which he must keep
in mind: he must prove that something was done,
that a particular act was done, that it was wrongly
done, and that he brings his charge according to law.
Thus every cause will turn on the same sorts of
questions, though the parts of plaintiff and defendant
will sometimes be interchanged: for instance in the
case of a claim for a reward, it will be the plaintiffs
task to show that what was done was right.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="86" unit="section"/>
                    These four schemes or forms of action which I then
called
                    <hi rend="italics">general bases</hi>
                    fall into two classes as I have
                    <pb id="p.455"/>
                    shown,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        § 67, and III.
                        <hi rend="italics">v.</hi>
                        4.
                    </note>
                    namely, the
                    <hi rend="italics">rational</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">legal.</hi>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">rational</hi>
                    is the simpler, as it involves nothing more
than the consideration of the nature of things. In
this connection, therefore, a mere mention of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjeclure, definition</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    will suffice.
                    <milestone n="87" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Legal questions</hi>
                    necessarily have a larger number of species, since
there are many laws and a variety of forms. In the
case of one law we rely on the letter, in others on the
spirit. Some laws we force to serve our turn, when
we can find no law to support our case, others we
compare with one another, and on others we put some
novel interpretation.
                    <milestone n="88" unit="section"/>
                    Thus from these three
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    we
get three resemblances of
                    <hi rend="italics">bases:</hi>
                    sometimes simple,
sometimes complex, but all having a character of their
own, as, for instance, when questions of the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law</hi>
                    and its
                    <hi rend="italics">intention</hi>
                    are involved, for these clearly
come under
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">quality;</hi>
                    or again where the
syllogism is involved, for this is specially connected
with
                    <hi rend="italics">quality;</hi>
                    or where contradictory laws are involved,
for these are on the same footing as the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law and intention;</hi>
                    or yet again in cases of
                    <hi rend="italics">ambiguity,</hi>
                    which is always resolved by
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture.</hi>
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">Definition</hi>
                    also
belongs to both classes of question, namely those
concerned with the consideration of
                    <hi rend="italics">facts</hi>
                    and those
concerned with the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law.</hi>
                    All these
questions, although they come under the three
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    yet since, as I have mentioned,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 87.</note>
                    they have certain
characteristic features of their own, require to be
pointed out to learners; and we must allow them
to be called
                    <hi rend="italics">legal bases</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">minor heads,</hi>
                    as
long as it is clearly understood that none of them
involve any other
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    than the three I have
mentioned.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 80.</note>
                    <milestone n="90" unit="section"/>
                    As regards questions of
                    <hi rend="italics">quantity, number, relation,</hi>
                    and, as some have thought,
                    <hi rend="italics">comparison,</hi>
                    the
                    <pb id="p.457"/>
                    case is different. For these have no connexion with
the complexities of the law, but are concerned with
reason only. Consequently they must always be
regarded as coming under
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    as, for
instance, when we ask with what purpose, or at what
time, or place something was done.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>
                    But I will speak of individual questions when I
come to handle the rules for
                    <hi rend="italics">division.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Book VII.</note>
                    This much is
agreed to by all writers, that one
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    possesses one
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    but that as regards secondary questions related
to the main issue of the trial, there may frequently
be a number in one single cause.
                    <milestone n="92" unit="section"/>
                    I also think there
is at times some doubt as to which
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    should be
adopted, when many different lines of defence are
brought to meet a single charge; and, just as in regard to the complexion to be given to the statement
of the facts of the case, that complexion is said to be
the best which the speaker can best maintain, so in
the present connexion I may say that the best
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    to choose is that which will permit the orator to develop a maximum of force.
                    <milestone n="93" unit="section"/>
                    It is for this reason that
we find Cicero and Brutus taking up different lines
in defence of Milo. Cicero says that Clodius was
justifiably killed because he sought to waylay Milo,
but that Milo had not designed to kill him; while
Brutus, who wrote his speech merely as a rhetorical
exercise, also exults that Milo has killed a bad citizen.
                    <milestone n="94" unit="section"/>
                    In complicated causes, however, two or three
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    may
be found, or different
                    <hi rend="italics">bases:</hi>
                    for instance a man may
plead that he did not do one thing, and that he was
justified in doing another, or to take another similar
class of case, a man may deny two of the charges.
                    <milestone n="95" unit="section"/>
                    The same thing occurs when there is a question
about some one thing which is claimed by a number
                    <pb id="p.459"/>
                    of persons, who may all of them rely on the same
kind of plea (for instance, on the right of the next of
kin), or may put in different claims, one urging that
the property was left him by will, another that he is
next of kin. Now whenever a different defence has
to be made against different claimants, there must be
different
                    <hi rend="italics">bases,</hi>
                    as for example the well-known controversial theme:
                    <milestone n="96" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        Wills that are made in accordance
with law shall be valid. When parents die intestate,
their children shall be the heirs. A disinherited son
shall receive none of his father's property. A bastard,
if born before a legitimate son, shall be treated as
legitimate, but if born after a legitimate son shall be
treated merely as a citizen. It shall be lawful to give
a son in adoption. Every son given in adoption shall
have the right to re-enter his own family if his natural
father has died childless.
                        <milestone n="97" unit="section"/>
                        A father of two legitimate
sons gave one in adoption, disinherited the other,
and acknowledged a bastard, who was born to him
later. Finally after making the disinherited son his
heir he died. All three sons lay claim to the
property.
                    </quote>
                    <hi rend="italics">Nothbus</hi>
                    is the Greek word for a bastard;
Latin, as Cato emphasized in one of his speeches, has
no word of its own and therefore borrows the foreign
term. But I am straying from the point.
                    <milestone n="98" unit="section"/>
                    The son
who was made heir by the will finds his way barred
by the law
                    <quote>A disinherited son shall receive none of his father's property.</quote>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is one resting on
the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">intention,</hi>
                    and the problem is
whether he can inherit by any means at all? can he
do so in accordance with the intention of his father?
or in virtue of the fact that he was made heir by the
will? The problem confronting the bastard is twofold, since he was born after the two legitimate sons
                    <pb id="p.461"/>
                    and was not born before a legitimate son.
                    <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>
                    The first
problem involves a syllogism: are those sons who
have been cast out from their own family to be regarded as though they had never been born? The
second is concerned with the letter of the law and
intention. For it is admitted that he was not born
before any legitimate son, but he will defend his
claim by appealing to the intention of the law, which
he will maintain to imply that the bastard, born when
there was no legitimate son in the family, should
rank as legitimate.
                    <milestone n="100" unit="section"/>
                    He will dismiss the letter of the
law, pointing out that in any case the position of a
bastard is not prejudiced by the fact that no legitimate
son was born after him, and arguing as follows:—
                    <quote>
                        Suppose that the only son is a bastard, what will
his position be? Merely that of a citizen? and yet
he was not born after any legitimate son. Or
will he rank as a son in all respects? But he
was not born before the legitimate sons. As it is
impossible to stand by the letter of the law we
must stand by its intentions.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="101" unit="section"/>
                    It need disturb no one
that one law should originate two
                    <hi rend="italics">bases.</hi>
                    The law is
twofold, and therefore has the force of two laws.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">101</note>
                    To the son who desires to re-enter the family, the
disinherited's first reply is,
                    <quote>Even though you are allowed to re-enter the family, I am still the heir.</quote>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    will be the same as in the claim put forward
by the disinherited son, since the question at issue is
whether a disinherited son can inherit.
                    <milestone n="102" unit="section"/>
                    Both the
disinherited and the bastard will object,
                    <quote>You cannot re-enter the family, for our father did not die childless.</quote>
                    But in this connexion each will rely on
his own particular question. For the disinherited son
will say that even a disinherited man does not cease
                    <pb id="p.463"/>
                    to be a son, and will derive an argument from that
very law which denies his claim to the inheritance;
namely that it was unnecessary for a disinherited son
to be excluded from possession of his father's property
if he had ceased to be one of the family; but now,
since in virtue of his rights as son he would have
been his father's heir if he had died intestate, the
law is brought to bar his claim; and yet the law does
not deprive him of his position as son, but only of his
position as heir. Here the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    is
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive,</hi>
                    as turning
on the definition of a son.
                    <milestone n="103" unit="section"/>
                    Again the bastard in his
turn will urge that his father did not die childless,
employing the same arguments that he had used in
putting forward his claim that he ranked as a son;
unless indeed he too has recourse to definition, and
raises the question whether even bastards are not sons.
Thus in one case we shall have either two special
                    <hi rend="italics">legal bases,</hi>
                    namely the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law and</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">intention,</hi>
                    with the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism</hi>
                    and also
                    <hi rend="italics">definition,</hi>
                    or those three
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 82.</note>
                    which are really the only
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    strictly so called,
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                    as regards the
                    <hi rend="italics">letter of the law and intention, quality</hi>
                    in the
                    <hi rend="italics">syllogism,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 88.</note>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">definition,</hi>
                    which needs no
explanation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="104" unit="section"/>
                    Further every kind of case will contain a
                    <hi rend="italics">cause,</hi>
                    a
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge,</hi>
                    and a
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For discussion of these technical terms see chap. xi.</note>
                    For nothing can be said which does not contain a
reason, something to which the decision of the judge
is directed, and finally something which, more than
aught else, contains the substance of the matter at
issue. But as these vary in different cases and are as
a rule explained by writers on judicial causes, I will
postpone them to the appropriate portion of my work.
For the present I shall follow the order which I
prescribed by my division
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chaps. iii. and iv.</note>
                    of
                    <hi rend="italics">causes</hi>
                    into three classes.
                    <pb id="p.465"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    VII. I will begin with the class of
                    <hi rend="italics">causes</hi>
                    which are
concerned with praise and blame. This class appears
to have been entirely divorced by Aristotle,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        1358 b. 2.
                    </note>
                    and
following him by Theophrastus, from the practical
side of oratory (which they call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">pragmatikh=|,</foreign>
                    ) and to
have been reserved solely for the delectation of
audiences, which indeed is shown to be its peculiar
function by its name, which implies display.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pideiktikh/.</foreign>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Roman
usage on the other hand has given it a place in the
practical tasks of life. For funeral orations are
often imposed as a duty on persons holding public
office, or entrusted to magistrates by decree of the
senate. Again the award of praise or blame to a
witness may carry weight in the courts, while it is
also a recognised practice to produce persons to
praise the character of the accused. Further the
published speeches of Cicero directed against his
rivals in the election to the consulship,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The speech was known as
                        <hi rend="italics">in Toga Candida.</hi>
                        Only fragments survive.
                    </note>
                    and
against Lucius Piso, Clodius and Curio,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italics">in Pisonem</hi>
                        survives, the
                        <hi rend="italics">in Clodium et Curionem,</hi>
                        to which he refers again (v. x. 92), is lost.
                    </note>
                    are full of
denunciation, and were notwithstanding delivered in
the senate as formal expressions of opinion in the
course of debate.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    I do not deny that some compositions of this kind are composed solely with a view
to display, as, for instance, panegyrics of gods and
heroes of the past, a consideration which provides
the solution of a question which I discussed a little
while back,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">III. v. 3.</note>
                    and proves that those are wrong who
hold that an orator will never speak on a subject
unless it involves some problem.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But what problem
is involved by the praise of Jupiter Capitolinus, a
stock theme of the sacred Capitoline contest,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The quinquennial contest in honour of Jupiter
Capitolinus, founded by Domitian in 86.
                    </note>
                    which
is undoubtedly treated in regular rhetorical form?
                    <pb id="p.467"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    However, just as panegyric applied to practical
matters requires proof, so too a certain semblance of
proof is at times required by speeches composed
entirely for display.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For instance, a speaker who tells
how Romulus was the son of Mars and reared by the
she-wolf, will offer as proofs of his divine origin the
facts that when thrown into a running stream he
escaped drowning, that all his achievements were such
as to make it credible that he was the offspring of the
god of battles, and that his contemporaries unquestionably believed that he was translated to heaven.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Some arguments will even wear a certain semblance
of defence: for example, if the orator is speaking
in praise of Hercules, he will find excuses for his
hero having changed raiment with the Queen of
Lydia and submitted to the tasks which legend tells
us she imposed upon him. The proper function
however of panegyric is to amplify and embellish its
themes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    This form of oratory is directed in the main to
the praise of gods and men, but may occasionally be
applied to the praise of animals or even of inanimate objects.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    In praising the gods our first step
will be to express our veneration of the majesty of
their nature in general terms. next we shall proceed
to praise the special power of the individual god and
the discoveries whereby he has benefited the human
race.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For example, in the case of Jupiter, we shall
extol his power as manifested in the governance of
all things, with Mars we shall praise his power in war,
with Neptune his power over the sea; as regards
inventions we shall celebrate Minerva's discovery of
the arts, Mercury's discovery of letters, Apollo's of
medicine, Ceres' of the fruits of the earth, Bacchus'
                    <pb id="p.469"/>
                    of wine. Next we must record their exploits as
handed down from antiquity. Even gods may derive honour from their descent, as for instance is
the case with the sons of Jupiter, or from their
antiquity, as in the case of the children of Chaos, or
from their offspring, as in the case of Latona, the
mother of Apollo and Diana.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Some again may be
praised because they were born immortal, others
because they won immortality by their valour, a theme
which the piety of our sovereign has made the glory
even of these present times.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                        by Donitian's deification of his father Vespasian and
his brother Titus.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    There is greater variety required in the praise of
men. In the first place there is a distinction to be
made as regards time between the period in which
the objects of our praise lived and the time preceding their birth; and further, in the case of the
dead, we must also distinguish the period following
their death. With regard to things preceding a
man's birth, there are his country, his parents and his
ancestors, a theme which may be handled in two
ways. For either it will be creditable to the objects of
our praise not to have fallen short of the fair fame of
their country and of their sires or to have ennobled
a humble origin by the glory of their achievements.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Other topics to be drawn from the period preceding
their birth will have reference to omens or prophecies foretelling their future greatness, such as the
oracle which is said to have foretold that the son of
Thetis would be greater than his father.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    of the individual himself will be based on his
character, his physical endowments and external
circumstances. Physical and accidental advantages
provide a comparatively unimportant theme, which
requires variety of treatment. At times for instance
                    <pb id="p.471"/>
                    we extol beauty and strength in honorific terms, as
Homer does in the case of Agamemnon
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi>
                        ii. 477.
                    </note>
                    and
Achilles
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi>
                        ii. 180.
                    </note>
                    ; at times again weakness may contribute
largely to our admiration, as when Homer says
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Iliad,</hi>
                        v. 801.
                    </note>
                    that
Tydeus was small of stature but a good fighter.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Fortune too may confer dignity as in the case of
kings and princes (for they have a fairer field for
the display of their excellences) but on the other
hand the glory of good deeds may be enhanced by
the smallness of their resources. Moreover the
praise awarded to external and accidental advantages
is given, not to their possession, but to their honourable employment.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For wealth and power and influence, since they are the sources of strength, are the
surest test of character for good or evil; they make us
better or they make us worse.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Praise awarded to
character is always just, but may be given in various
ways. It has sometimes proved the more effective
course to trace a man's life and deeds in due chronological order, praising his natural gifts as a child, then
his progress at school, and finally the whole course of
his life, including words as well as deeds. At times
on the other hand it is well to divide our praises,
dealing separately with the various virtues, fortitude, justice, self-control and the rest of them and
to assign to each virtue the deeds performed under
its influence.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    We shall have to decide which of
these two methods will be the more serviceable,
according to the nature of the subject; but we
must bear in mind the fact that what most pleases
an audience is the celebration of deeds which our
hero was the first or only man or at any rate one of
the very few to perform: and to these we must add
any other achievements which surpassed hope or
                    <pb id="p.473"/>
                    expectation, emphasising what was done for the sake
of others rather than what he performed on his
own behalf.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    It is not always possible to deal with
the time subsequent to our hero's death: this is
due not merely to the fact that we sometimes praise
him, while still alive, but also that there are but few
occasions when we have a chance to celebrate the
award of divine honours, posthumous votes of thanks,
or statues erected at the public expense.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Among
such themes of panegyric I would mention monuments of genius that have stood the test of time.
For some great men like Menander have received
ampler justice from the verdict of posterity than
from that of their own age. Children reflect glory
on their parents, cities on their founders, laws on
those who made them, arts on their inventors and
institutions on those that first introduced them; for
instance Numa first laid down rules for the worship
of the gods, and Publicola first ordered that the
lictors' rods should be lowered in salutation to the
people.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The same method will be applied to denunciations
as well, but with a view to opposite effects. For humble
origin has been a reproach to many, while in some
cases distinction has merely served to increase the
notoriety and unpopularity of vices. In regard to
some persons, as in the story of Paris, it has been
predicted that they would be the cause of destruction
to many, some like Thersites and Irus have been
despised for their poverty and mean appearance,
others have been loathed because their natural advantages were nullified by their vices: the poets for
instance tell us that Nireus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">the handsomest warrior among the Greeks of Troy.</note>
                    was a coward and
Pleisthenes
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Son of Atreus: the allusion is not known.</note>
                    a debauchee.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    The mind too has as
                    <pb id="p.475"/>
                    many vices as virtues, and vice may be denounced,
as virtue may be praised, in two different ways.
Some have been branded with infamy after death
like Maelius, whose house was levelled with the
ground, or Marcus Manlius, whose first name was
banished from his family for all generations to
come.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    The vices of the children bring hatred on
their parents; founders of cities are detested for
concentrating a race which is a curse to others, as
for example the founder of the Jewish superstition;
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Moses.</note>
                    the laws of Gracchus are hated, and we
abhor any loathsome example of vice that has been
handed down to posterity, such as the criminal form of
lust which a Persian is said to have been the first to
practise on a woman of Samos.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    And even in the
case of the living the judgment of mankind serves
as a proof of their character, and the fairness or
foulness of their fame proves the orator's praise or
blame to be true.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        i. 9.
                    </note>
                    however thinks that the place and subject of panegyrics or denunciations make a very considerable difference. For much depends on the
character of the audience and the generally received
opinion, if they are to believe that the virtues of
which they approve are pre-eminently characteristic
of the person praised and the vices which they hate
of the person denounced. For there can be
little doubt as to the attitude of the audience,
if that attitude is already determined prior to
the delivery of the speech.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    It will be wise
too for him to insert some words of praise for
his audience, since this will secure their good
will, and wherever it is possible this should be done
in such a manner as to advance his case. Literature
                    <pb id="p.477"/>
                    will win less praise at Sparta than at Athens, endurance and courage more. Among some races the life
of a freebooter is accounted honourable, while others
regard it as a duty to respect the laws. Frugality
might perhaps be unpopular with the Sybarites,
whilst luxury was regarded as a crime by the ancient Romans.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Similar differences of opinion are
found in individuals. A judge is most favourable to
the orator whose views he thinks identical with his
own. Aristotle also urges a point, which at a later
date Cornelius Celsus emphasised almost to excess,
to the effect that, since the boundary between vice
and virtue is often ill-defined, it is desirable to use
words that swerve a little from the actual truth,
calling a rash man brave, a prodigal generous, a mean
man thrifty; or the process may, if necessary, be reversed. But this the ideal orator, that is to say a
good man, will never do, unless perhaps he is led to
do so by consideration for the public interest.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Cities are praised after the same fashion as men.
The founder takes the place of the parent, and antiquity carries great authority, as for instance in the
case of those whose inhabitants are said to be sprung
from the soil. The virtues and vices revealed by
their deeds are the same as in private individuals.
The advantages arising from site or fortifications are
however peculiar to cities. Their citizens enhance
their fame just as children bring honour to their
parents.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Praise too may be awarded to public works,
in connexion with which their magnificence,
utility, beauty and the architect or artist must
be given due consideration. Temples for instance
will be praised for their magnificence, walls for
                    <pb id="p.479"/>
                    their utility, and both for their beauty or the skill of
the architect. Places may also be praised, witness
the praise of Sicily in Cicero.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">in Verr.</hi>
                        ii. 1
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.,</hi>
                        iv. 48.
                    </note>
                    In such cases
we consider their beauty and utility: beauty calls for
notice in places by the sea, in open plains and
pleasant situations, utility in healthy or fertile
localities.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    Again praise in general terms may be
awarded to noble sayings or deeds. Finally things
of every kind may be praised. Panegyrics have
been composed on sleep and death, and physicians
have written eulogies on certain kinds of food.
                </p>
                <p>
                    While therefore I do not agree that panegyric
concerns only questions regarding what is honourable, I do think that it comes as a rule under
the heading of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality,</hi>
                    although all three
                    <hi rend="italics">bases</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Quality, conjecture, definition. See chap. vi. for explanation of this term.
                    </note>
                    may
he involved in Panegyric and it was observed by
Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxv. 94.
                    </note>
                    that all were actually used by Gaius Caesar
in his denunciation of Cato. But
                    <hi rend="italics">panegyric</hi>
                    is akin
to
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory inasmuch as the same things
are usually praised in the former as are advised
in the latter.
                </p>
                <p>
                    VIII. I am surprised that
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory also
has been restricted by some authorities to questions
of expediency. If it should be necessary to assign
one single aim to deliberative I should prefer
Cicero's
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Or.</hi>
                        II. lxxxii. 334.
                    </note>
                    view that this kind of oratory is primarily
concerned with what is honourable. I do not doubt
that those who maintain the opinion first mentioned
adopt the lofty view that nothing can be expedient
which is not good.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    That opinion is perfectly sound
so long as we are fortunate enough to have wise and
good men for counsellors. But as we most often
express our views before an ignorant audience, and
more especially before popular assemblies, of which
                    <pb id="p.481"/>
                    the majority is usually uneducated, we must distinguish between what is honourable and what is expedient and conform our utterances to suit ordinary
understandings.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For there are many who do not
admit that what they really believe to be the honourable course is sufficiently advantageous, and are
misled by the prospect of advantage into approving
courses of the dishonourable nature of which there
can be no question: witness the Numantine treaty
and the surrender of the Caudine Forks.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Mancinus was surrounded on retreat from Numiantia in
137 B. C., while the surrender at the Caudine Forks took
place in 321 B. C. In both cases the Senate refused to ratify
the humiliating treaties which had been made the price of
the release of the Roman armies.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Nor does
it suffice to restrict deliberative oratory to the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    which is concerned with questions of
honour and expediency. For there is often room
for conjecture as well. Sometimes again
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    is necessary or
                    <hi rend="italics">legal</hi>
                    problems require handling; this
is especially the case when advice has to be given
on private matters, where there is some doubt of
the legality of the course under consideration. Of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture'</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        For
                        <hi rend="italics">conjecture</hi>
                        see III. vi. 30
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    I shall speak more fully a little later
on. Returning to
                    <hi rend="italics">definition</hi>
                    for the moment, we
find it in the question raised by Demosthenes,
                    <quote>whether Philip should give or restore Halonnesus,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Halonnesus had belonged to Athens, but had been seized
by pirates. Philip ejected the pirates. The Athenians asked
him to restore it; he replied that it belonged to him and
that there could be no question of restoration, but if they
asked for it as a gift he promised to give it them.
                    </note>
                    and to that discussed by Cicero in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Philippics</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        VIII. i. 2, where the question is discussed as to
whether the war with Antony is
                        <hi rend="italics">bellum</hi>
                        or
                        <hi rend="italics">tumultus,</hi>
                        the
latter being the technical name for any grave national
emergency such as civil war or a Gallic invasion within the
bounds of Italy.
                    </note>
                    as
to the nature of a
                    <hi rend="italics">tumultus.</hi>
                    Again does not the
question raised in connection with the statue of
Servius Sulpicius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Phil.</hi>
                        ix. 1.
                    </note>
                    as to
                    <quote>
                        whether statues should be
erected only in honour of those ambassadors who
perish by the sword
                    </quote>
                    bear a strong resemblance to
the questions that are raised in the law courts?
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    department of oratory (also called the
                    <pb id="p.483"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">advisory</hi>
                    department), while it deliberates about the
future, also enquires about the past, while its functions are twofold and consist in advising and
dissuading.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italics">Deliberative</hi>
                    oratory does not always require an
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium,</hi>
                    such as is necessary in forensic speeches,
since he who asks an orator for his opinion is naturally
well disposed to him. But the commencement, whatever be its nature, must have some resemblance to an
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium.</hi>
                    For we must not begin abruptly or just at
the point where the fancy takes us, since in every
subject there is something which naturally comes first.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    In addressing the senate or the people the same
methods apply as in the law courts, and we must aim
as a rule at acquiring the goodwill of our audience.
This need cause no surprise, since even in
                    <hi rend="italics">panegyric</hi>
                    we seek to win the favour of our hearers when our
aim is praise pure and simple, and not the acquisition
of any advantage. Aristotle,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        iii. 14
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    it is true, holds, not
without reason, that in
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    speeches we may
often begin with a reference either to ourselves or to
our opponent, borrowing this practice
                    <hi rend="italics">from</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    oratory, and sometimes producing the impression that
the subject is of greater or less importance than it
actually is. On the other hand he thinks that in
                    <hi rend="italics">demonstrative</hi>
                    oratory the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium</hi>
                    may be treated with
the utmost freedom,
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    since it is sometimes drawn from
irrelevant material, as for example in Isocrates' Praise
of Helen,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The speech opens with a disquisition on the absurd and
trivial nature of much that is contained in the speeches of
sophists and rhetoricians.
                    </note>
                    or from something akin to the subject,
as for instance in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Panegyricus</hi>
                    of the same author,
when he complains that more honour is given to physical than to moral excellence, or as Gorgias in his
speech delivered at the Olympic games praises the
founders of the great national games. Sallust seems
                    <pb id="p.485"/>
                    to have imitated these authors in his
                    <hi rend="italics">Jugurthine War</hi>
                    and in the introduction to his
                    <hi rend="italics">Catiline,</hi>
                    which has no
connection with his narrative.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    But it is time for me to return to
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory
in which, even when we introduce an
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium,</hi>
                    we
must content ourselves with a brief prelude, which
may amount to no more than a mere heading. As
regards the
                    <hi rend="italics">statement of facts,</hi>
                    this is never required in
speeches on private subjects, at least as regards the
subject on which an opinion has to be given, because
everyone is acquainted with the question at issue.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Statements as to external matters which are relevant
to the discussion may however frequently be introduced. In addressing public assemblies it will often
be necessary to set forth the order of the points
which have to be treated.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    As regards appeals to the
emotions, these are especially necessary in
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory. Anger has frequently to be excited or
assuaged and the minds of the audience have to be
swayed to fear, ambition, hatred, reconciliation. At
times again it is necessary to awaken pity, whether it
is required, for instance, to urge that relief should be
sent to a besieged city, or we are engaged in deploring the overthrow of an allied state. But what really
carries greatest weight in
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    speeches is the
authority of the speaker.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For he, who would have
all men trust his judgment as to what is expedient
and honourable, should both possess and be regarded as possessing genuine wisdom and excellence
of character. In
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    speeches the orator may,
according to the generally received opinion, indulge
his passion to some extent. But all will agree that
the advice given by a speaker should be in keeping
with his moral character.
                    <pb id="p.487"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The majority of Greek writers have held that this
kind of oratory is entirely concerned with addressing
public assemblies and have restricted it to politics.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Even Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Orat.</hi>
                        ii. 82.
                    </note>
                    himself deals chiefly with this department. Consequently those who propose to offer advice
upon peace, war, troops, public works or revenue must
thoroughly acquaint themselves with two things, the
resources of the state and the character of its people,
so that the method employed in tendering their advice may be based at once on political realities and
the nature of their hearers.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    This type of oratory
seems to me to offer a more varied field for eloquence,
since both those who ask for advice and the answers
given to them may easily present the greatest diversity.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Consequently there are three points which must
be specially borne in mind in advice or dissuasion:
first the nature of the subject under discussion,
secondly the nature of those who are engaged in the
discussion, and thirdly the nature of the speaker who
offers them advice.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    As to the subject under discussion
its practicability is either certain or uncertain. In
the latter case this will be the chief, if not
the only point for consideration; for it will often
happen that we shall assert first that something
ought not to be done, even if it can be done, and
secondly, that it cannot be done. Now when
the question turns on such points as to whether the
Isthmus can be cut through, the Pontine Marshes
drained, or a harbour constructed at Ostia, or whether
Alexander is likely to find land beyond the Ocean,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        the theme of a
                        <hi rend="italics">suasoria</hi>
                        of the elder Seneca (
                        <hi rend="italics">Suas.</hi>
                        i.).
                        <quote>Alexander deliberates whether to sail forth into the ocean.</quote>
                    </note>
                    we make use of
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture.</hi>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    But even in connection
with things that are undoubtedly feasible, there may
at times be room for
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    as for instance in
questions such as whether Rome is ever likely to
                    <pb id="p.489"/>
                    conquer Carthage, whether Hannibal will return to
Africa if Scipio transports his army thither, or whether
the Samnites are likely to keep faith if the Romans
lay down their arms.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi>
                        at the Caudine Forks: see above, § 3.
                    </note>
                    There are some things too
which we may believe to be both feasible and likely
to be carried into effect, but at another time or place
or in another way.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    When there is no scope for conjecture, our attention will be fixed on other points. In the first place
advice will be asked either on account of the actual
thing on which the orator is required to express his
views, or on account of other causes which affect it
from without. It is on the actual thing that the
senate for instance debates, when it discusses such
questions as whether it is to vote pay for the troops.
In this case the material is simple.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    To this however
may be added reasons for taking action or the reverse,
as for example if the senate should discuss whether
it should deliver the Fabii to the Gauls when the
latter threaten war,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See Livy, v. 36.</note>
                    or Gaius Caesar should deliberate
whether he should persist in the invasion of Germany,
when his soldiers on all sides are making their wills.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See Caesar,
                        <hi rend="italics">Gallic War,</hi>
                        i. 39, where this detail is
recorded, also 40 where the speech made to his troops is
given.
                    </note>
                    These deliberative themes are of a twofold nature.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    In the first case the reason for deliberation is the
Gallic threat of war, but there may still be a further
question as to whether even without such threat of
war they should surrender those who, contrary to the
law of nations, took part in a battle when they had
been sent out as ambassadors and killed the king
with whom they had received instructions to treat.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    In the second case Caesar would doubtless never deliberate on the question at all, but for the perturbation
shown by his soldiers; but there is still room for
enquiry whether quite apart from this occurrence it
                    <pb id="p.491"/>
                    would be wise to penetrate into Germany. But it
must be remembered that we shall always speak first
on that subject which is capable of discussion quite
apart from the consequences.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Some have held that the three main considerations
in an advisory speech are honour, expediency and
necessity. I can find no place for the last. For however great the violence which may threaten us, it may
be necessary for us to suffer something, but we are not
compelled to do anything; whereas the subject of
deliberation is primarily whether we shall do anything.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Or if by necessity they mean that into which we are
driven by fear of worse things, the question will be one
of expediency. For example, if a garrison is besieged
by overwhelmingly superior forces and, owing to the
failure of food and water supplies, discusses surrender
to the enemy, and it is urged that it is a matter of
necessity, the words
                    <quote>otherwise we shall perish</quote>
                    must
needs be added: consequently there is no necessity
arising out of the circumstances themselves, for death
is a possible alternative. And as a matter of fact the
Saguntines
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In 218 B. C., when besieged by Hannibal. See Livy,
xxi. 14.
                    </note>
                    did not surrender, nor did those who were
surrounded on the raft from Opitergium.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        C. Antonius was blockaded in an island off the Dalmatian
coast which he held for Caesar 49 B. C. Reinforcements on
rafts were sent to his rescue. Most were captured; but in
one case, of a raft carrying 1,000 men from Opitergium in
Venetia, surrender was scorned and the men slew each other
rather than yield. See Lucan, iv. 462; Florus, ii. 33.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    It follows
that in such cases also the question will be either one
of expediency alone or of a choice between expediency and honour.
                    <quote>But,</quote>
                    it will be urged,
                    <quote>if a man would beget children, he is under the necessity of taking a wife.</quote>
                    Certainly. But he who wishes to
become a father must needs be quite clear that he
must take a wife.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    It appears to me, therefore, that
where necessity exists, there is no room for deliberation, any more than where it is clear that a thing is
                    <pb id="p.493"/>
                    not feasible. For deliberation is always concerned
with questions where some doubt exists. Those
therefore are wiser who make the third consideration
for deliberative oratory to be
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">to\ dunato/n</foreign>
                    or
                    <quote>possibility</quote>
                    as we translate it; the translation may seem clumsy,
but it is the only word available.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    That all these
considerations need not necessarily obtrude themselves in every case is too obvious to need explanation.
Most writers, however, say that there are more than
three. But the further considerations which they
would add are really but
                    <hi rend="italics">species</hi>
                    of the three
                    <hi rend="italics">general</hi>
                    considerations just mentioned. For right, justice,
piety, equity and mercy (for thus they translate
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">to\</foreign>
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">h(/meron</foreign>
                    ), with any other virtues that anyone may be
pleased to add, all come under the heading of that
which is honourable.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, if the question
be whether a thing is easy, great, pleasant or free from
danger, it comes under questions of expediency. Such
topics arise from some contradiction; for example a
thing is expedient, but difficult, or trivial, or unpleasant, or dangerous.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    Some however hold that at
times deliberation is concerned solely with the question
whether a thing is pleasant, as for instance when discussion arises as to whether a theatre should be built or
games instituted. But in my opinion you will never
find any man such a slave to luxury as not to consider
anything but pleasure when he delivers an advisory
speech.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    For there must needs be something on every
occasion that takes precedence of pleasure: in proposing the institution of public games there is the honour
due to the gods; in proposing the erection of a
theatre the orator will consider the advantages to be
derived from relaxation from toil, and the unbecoming
and undesirable struggle for places which will arise if
                    <pb id="p.495"/>
                    there is no proper accommodation; religion, too, has
its place in the discussion, for we shall describe the
theatre as a kind of temple for the solemnization of a
sacred feast.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Often again we shall urge that honour
must come before expediency; as for instance when
we advise the men of Opitergium not to surrender to
the enemy, even though refusal to do so means
certain death. At times on the other hand we prefer
expediency to honour, as when we advise the arming
of slaves in the Punic War.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">After the battle of Cannae: Livy, xxii. 57.</note>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    But even in this case we
must not openly admit that such a course is dishonourable: we can point out that all men are free by
nature and composed of the same elements, while
the slaves in question may perhaps be sprung
from some ancient and noble stock; and in the
former case when the danger is so evident,
we may add other arguments, such as that they
would perish even more cruelly if they surrendered,
should the enemy fail to keep faith, or Caesar (a
more probable supposition) prove victorious.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    But
in such a conflict of principles it is usual to modify
the names which we give them. For expediency is
often ruled out by those who assert not merely that
honour comes before expediency, but that nothing
can be expedient that is not honourable, while others
say that what we call honour is vanity, ambition and
folly, as contemptible in substance as it is fair in
sound.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is expediency compared merely with
inexpediency. At times we have to choose between
two advantageous courses after comparison of their
respective advantages. The problem may be still
more complicated, as for instance when Pompey
deliberated whether to go to Parthia, Africa or
Egypt.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">After his defeat at Pharsalus.</note>
                    In such a case the enquiry is not which of
                    <pb id="p.497"/>
                    two courses is better or worse, but which of three or
more.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand in
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory there
will never be any doubt about circumstances wholly
in our favour. For there can clearly be no doubt about
points against which there is nothing to be said.
Consequently as a rule all
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    speeches are
based simply on comparison, and we must consider
what we shall gain and by what means, that it may be
possible to form an estimate whether there is more
advantage in the aims we pursue or greater disadvantage in the means we employ to that end.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    A
question of expediency may also be concerned with
time (for example,
                    <quote>it is expedient, but not now</quote>
                    )
or with place (
                    <quote>it is expedient, but not here</quote>
                    ) or
with particular persons (
                    <quote>it is expedient, but not for us</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>not as against these</quote>
                    ) or with our method of
action (
                    <quote>it is expedient, but not thus</quote>
                    ) or with
degree (
                    <quote>it is expedient, but not to this extent</quote>
                    ).
                </p>
                <p>
                    But we have still more often to consider personality with reference to what is becoming, and we
must consider our own as well as that of those
before whom the question is laid.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently,
though examples are of the greatest value in
deliberative speeches, because reference to historical parallels is the quickest method of securing assent, it matters a great deal whose authority
is adduced and to whom it is commended. For
the minds of those who deliberate on any subject differ from one another and our audience may
be of two kinds.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    For those who ask us for advice are either single individuals or a number, and
in both cases the factors may be different. For
when advice is asked by a number of persons it
makes a considerable difference whether they are
                    <pb id="p.499"/>
                    the senate or the people, the citizens of Rome or
Fidenae, Greeks or barbarians, and in the case of
single individuals, whether we are urging Cato or
Gaius Marius to stand for office, whether it is the
elder Scipio or Fabius who is deliberating on his plan
of campaign.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    Further sex, rank, and age, must be
taken into account, though it is character that will
make the chief difference. It is an easy task to
recommend an honourable course to honourable
men, but if we are attempting to keep men of bad
character to the paths of virtue, we must take care
not to seem to upbraid a way of life unlike our own.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    The minds of such an audience are not to be moved
by discoursing on the nature of virtue, which they
ignore, but by praise, by appeals to popular opinion,
and if such vanities are of no avail, by demonstration
of the advantage that will accrue from such a policy,
or more effectively perhaps by pointing out the
appalling consequences that will follow the opposite
policy.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    For quite apart from the fact that the minds
of unprincipled men are easily swayed by terror, I
am not sure that most men's minds are not more
easily influenced by fear of evil than by hope of
good, for they find it easier to understand what is
evil than what is good.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes again we urge
good men to adopt a somewhat unseemly course,
while we advise men of poor character to take a
course in which the object is the advantage of
those who seek our advice. I realise the thought
that will immediately occur to my reader:
                    <quote>Do you then teach that this should be done or think it right?</quote>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The letter is lost. the argument of the quotation is as
follows. The policy
                        <hi rend="italics">which</hi>
                        I advise is honorable, but it
would be wrong for me to urge Caesar to follow it, since it is
contrary to his interests.
                    </note>
                    might clear me from blame in the
matter; for he writes to Brutus in the following
terms, after setting forth a number of things that
                    <pb id="p.501"/>
                    might honourably be urged on Caesar:
                    <quote>
                        Should I be
a good man to advise this? No. For the end of him
who gives advice is the advantage of the man to
whom he gives it. But, you say, your advice is right.
Certainly, but there is not always room for what
is right in giving advice.
                    </quote>
                    However, this is a
somewhat abstruse question, and does not concern
deliberative oratory alone. I shall therefore reserve
it for my twelfth and concluding book.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chap. xii.</note>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    For my part
I would not have anything done dishonourably. But
for the meantime let us regard these questions as at
least belonging to the rhetorical exercises of the
schools: for knowledge of evil is necessary to enable
us the better to defend what is right.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    For the
present I will only say that if anyone is going to urge
a dishonourable course on honourable man, he
should remember not to urge it as being dishonourable, and should avoid the practice of certain declaimers who urge Sextus Pompeius to piracy just
because it is dishonourable and cruel. Even when we
address bad men, we should gloss over what is unsightly. For there is no man so evil as to wish to
seem so.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    Thus Sallust makes Catiline
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cat.</hi>
                        xx.
                    </note>
                    speak as one
who is driven to crime not by wickedness but by indignation, and Varius makes Atreus say:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">My wrongs are past all speech,</l>
                        <l part="N">And such shall be the deeds they force me to.</l>
                    </quote>
                    How much more has this pretence of honour to be
kept up by those who have a real regard for their
own good name!
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore when we advise Cicero
to beg Antonius for mercy or even to burn the
                    <hi rend="italics">Philippics</hi>
                    if Antonius promises to spare him on that
condition,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        For examples of this theme see the elder Seneca (
                        <hi rend="italics">Suas.</hi>
                        vi. and vii.).
                    </note>
                    we shall not empliasise the love of life in
our advice (for if that passion has any force with
                    <pb id="p.503"/>
                    him, it will have it none the less if we are silent),
but we shall exhort him to save himself in the interest of the state.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    For he needs some such reason
as that to preserve him from feeling shame at entreating such a one as Antony. Again if we urge
Gaius Caesar
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Julius Caesar.</note>
                    to accept the crown we shall assert
that the state is doomed to destruction unless controlled by a monarchy. For the sole aim of the man
who is deliberating about committing a criminal act
is to make his act appear as little wicked as possible.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    It also makes a great deal of difference who it is
that is offering the advice: for if his past has been
illustrious, or if his distinguished birth or age or
fortune excite high expectations, care must be taken
that his words are not unworthy of him. If on the
other hand he has none of these advantages he will
have to adopt a humbler tone. For what is regarded
as liberty in some is called licence in others. Some
receive sufficient support from their personal
authority, while others find that the force of reason
itself is scarce sufficient to enable them to maintain
their position.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently I regard
                    <hi rend="italics">impersonation</hi>
                    as the most
difficult of tasks, imposed as it is in addition to the
other work involved by a deliberative theme. For
the same speaker has on one occasion to impersonate
Caesar, on another Cicero or Cato. But it is a most
useful exercise because it demands a double effort
and is also of the greatest use to future poets and
historians, while for orators of course it is absolutely
necessary.
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    For there are many speeches composed
by Greek and Latin orators for others to deliver, the
words of which had to be adapted to suit the position and character of those for whom they were
                    <pb id="p.505"/>
                    written. Do you suppose that Cicero thought in the
same way or assumed the same character when he
wrote for Gnaeus Pompeius and when he wrote for
Titus Ampius and the rest?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Nothing is
                        <hi rend="italics">known</hi>
                        of these speeches.
                    </note>
                    Did he not rather bear
in mind the fortune, rank and achievements of each
single individual and represent the character of all
to whom he gave a voice so that though they spoke
better than they could by nature, they still might
seem to speak in their own persons?
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    For a speech
which is out of keeping with the man who delivers
it is just as faulty as the speech which fails to suit
the subject to which it should conform. It is for
this reason that Lysias is regarded as having shown
the highest art in the speeches which he wrote for
uneducated persons, on account of their extraordinary realism. In the case of declaimers indeed it is
of the first importance that they should consider
what best suits each character: for they rarely play
the role of advocates in their declamations. As a
rule they impersonate sons, parents, rich men, old
men, gentle or harsh of temper, misers, superstitious persons, cowards and mockers, so that hardly
even comic actors have to assume more numerous
roles in their performances on the stage than
these in their declamations.
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    All these rôles may
be regarded as forming part of
                    <hi rend="italics">impersonation,</hi>
                    which I have included under
                    <hi rend="italics">delibertive</hi>
                    themes,
from which it differs merely in that it involves the
assumption of a role. It is sometimes introduced
even with controversial themes, which are drawn
from history and involve the appearance of definite
historical characters as pleaders.
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    I am aware also
that historical and poetical themes are often set for
the sake of practice, such as Priam's speech to
                    <pb id="p.507"/>
                    Achilles or Sulla's address to the people on his
resignation of the dictatorship. But these will fall
under one or other of the three classes into which
I have divided causes. For entreaty, statement,
and argument, with other themes already mentioned,
are all of frequent occurrence in
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic, deliberative</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">demonstrative</hi>
                    subjects, according as circumstances
demand,
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    and we often introduce fictitious speeches
of historical persons, whom we select ourselves.
Cicero for instance in the
                    <hi rend="italics">pro Caelio</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        xiv.
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq</hi>
                    </note>
                    makes both
Appius Caecus and her brother Clodius address
Clodia, the former rebuking her for her immorality,
the latter exhorting her thereto.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    In scholastic declamations the fictitious themes for
deliberative speeches are often not unlike those of
controversial speeches and are a compromise between
the two forms, as for instance when the theme set is
a discussion in the presence of Gaius Caesar of the
punishment to be meted out to Theodotus; for it consists of accusation and defence, both of them peculiar
to forensic oratory.
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    But the topic of expediency also
enters into the case, in such questions as whether it
was to Caesar's advantage that Pompeius should be
slain; whether the execution of Theodotus would
involve the risk of a war with the king of Egypt;
whether such a war would be highly inopportune at
such a critical moment, would prove dangerous and
be certain to last a long time.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    There is also a question
of honour. Does it befit Caesar to avenge Pompeius'
death? or is it to be feared that an admission that
Pompeius did not deserve death will injure the cause
of the Caesarian party?
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    It may be noted that discussions of such a kind may well occur in actual
cases.
                    <pb id="p.509"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Declaimers have however often been guilty of an
error as regards deliberative themes which has involved a series of consequences. They have considered deliberative themes to be different and
absolutely opposed to forensic themes. For they have
always affected abrupt openings, an impetuous style
and a generous embellishment, as they call it, in their
language, and have been especially careful to make
shorter notes for
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    than for
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    themes.
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    For my part while I realise that
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    themes
do not require an
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium,</hi>
                    for reasons which I have
already stated, I do not, however, understand why
they should open in such a wild and exclamatory
manner. When a man is asked to express his opinion
on any subject, he does not, if he is sane, begin to
shriek, but endeavours as far as possible to win the
assent of the man who is considering the question by
a courteous and natural opening.
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    Why, I ask, in review of the fact that deliberations require moderation
above all else, should the speaker on such themes indulge in a torrential style of eloquence kept at one
high level of violence? I acknowledge that in controversial speeches the tone is often lowered in the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium, the</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">statement of facts</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">argument,</hi>
                    and
that if you subtract these three portions, the remainder is more or less of the
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    type of
speech, but what remains must likewise be of a more
even flow, avoiding all violence and fury.
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    With
regard to manificence of language, deliblerative declaimers should avoid straining after it more than
others, but it comes to them more naturally. For
there is a preference among those who invent such
themes for selecting great personages, such as kings,
princes, senators and peoples, while the theme itself
                    <pb id="p.511"/>
                    is generally on a grander scale. Consequently since
the words are suited to the theme, they acquire
additional splendour from the magnificence of the
matter.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    In actual deliberations the case is different,
and consequently Theophrastus laid it down that in
the
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    class of oratory the language should
as far as possible be free from all affectation: in
stating this view he followed the authority of his instructor, although as a rule he is not afraid to differ
from him. For Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        iii. 12.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    held that the
                    <hi rend="italics">demonstrative</hi>
                    type of oratory was the best suited for writing and
that the next best was
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    oratory: his reason for
this view was that the first type is entirely concerned
with display, while the second requires art, which
will even be employed to deceive the audience, if
expedience should so demand, whereas advice requires
only truth and prudence.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    I agree with this view as
regards
                    <hi rend="italics">demonstrative</hi>
                    oratory (in fact all writers are
agreed on this point), but as regards
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    themes I think that the style must be suited to
the requirements of the subject which has to be treated.
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    For I notice that the
                    <hi rend="italics">Philippics</hi>
                    of Demosthenes
are pre-eminent for the same merits as his forensic
speeches, and that the opinions expressed by Cicero
before the senate or the people are as remarkable for
the splendour of their eloquence as the speeches
which he delivered in accusing or defending persons
before the courts. And yet Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Part. or.</hi>
                        xxvii. 97.
                    </note>
                    says of
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative</hi>
                    oratory that the whole speech should be simple
and dignified, and should derive its ornament rather
from the sentiments expressed than the actual words.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the use of examples practically all authorities are with good reason agreed that there is no
subject to which they are better suited, since as a
                    <pb id="p.513"/>
                    rule history seems to repeat itself and the experience
of the past is a valuable support to reason.
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    Brevity
and copiousness are determined not so much by the
nature as by the compass of the subject. For, just as
in
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberations</hi>
                    the question is generally less complicated, so in
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    cases it is often of less
importance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Anyone who is content to read not merely speeches,
but history as well, in preference to growing grey over
the notebooks of the rhetoricians, will realise the
truth of what I say: for in the historians the speeches
delivered to the people and the opinions expressed
in the senate often provide examples of advice and
dissuasion.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    he will find an avoidance of abrupt
openings in
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberatire</hi>
                    speeches and will note that
the
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    style is often the more impetuous of the
two, while in both cases the words are suited to the
matter and
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    speeches are often shorter than
                    <hi rend="italics">deliberative.</hi>
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    Nor will he find in them those faults into
which some of our declaimers fall, namely a coarse
abuse of those who hold opposite opinions and a
general tendency to speak in such a way as to make
it seem that the speaker's views are in opposition to
those of the persons who ask his advice. Consequently
their aim seems to be invective rather than persuasion.
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    I would have my younger readers realise that these
words are penned for their special benefit that they
may not desire to adopt a different style in their
exercises from that in which they will be required to
speak, and may not be hampered by having to unlearn what they have acquired. For the rest if they
are ever summoned to take part in the counsels of
their friends, or to speak their opinions in the senate,
or advise the emperor on some point on which he
                    <pb id="p.515"/>
                    may consult them, they will learn from practice
what they cannot perhaps put to the credit of the
schools.
                </p>
                <p>
                    IX. I now come to the forensic kind of oratory,
which presents the utmost variety, but whose duties
are no more than two, the bringing and rebutting
of charges. Most authorities divide the forensic
speech into five parts: the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">statement of facts,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">proof,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">refutation,</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">peroration.</hi>
                    To these some have added the
                    <hi rend="italics">partition into heads, proposition</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">digression,</hi>
                    the two first of which
form part of the
                    <hi rend="italics">proof.</hi>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For it is obviously
necessary to
                    <hi rend="italics">propound</hi>
                    what you are going to
                    <hi rend="italics">prove</hi>
                    as well as to conclude. Why then, if
                    <hi rend="italics">proposition</hi>
                    is a
part of a speech, should not
                    <hi rend="italics">conclusion</hi>
                    be also?
                    <hi rend="italics">Partition</hi>
                    on the other hand is merely one aspect of
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement,</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">arrangement</hi>
                    is a part of rhetoric
itself, and is equally distributed through every theme
of oratory and their whole body, just as are
                    <hi rend="italics">invention</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">style.</hi>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently we must regard
                    <hi rend="italics">partition</hi>
                    not as one part of a whole speech, but as a part of
each individual question that may be involved. For
what question is there in which an orator cannot
set forth the order in which he is going to make
his points? And this of course is the function of
                    <hi rend="italics">partition.</hi>
                    But how ridiculous it is to make each question an aspect of
                    <hi rend="italics">proof,</hi>
                    but
                    <hi rend="italics">partition</hi>
                    which is an
aspect of a question a part of the whole speech.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    As
for
                    <hi rend="italics">digression (egressio,</hi>
                    now more usually styled
                    <hi rend="italics">excessus</hi>
                    ), if it lie outside the case, it cannot be part
of it, while, if it lie within it, it is merely an accessory or ornament of that portion of the case from
which
                    <hi rend="italics">digression</hi>
                    is made. For if anything that lies
within the case is to be called part of it, why not
                    <pb id="p.517"/>
                    call
                    <hi rend="italics">argument, comparison, commonplace, pathos, illustration</hi>
                    parts of the case?
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand I
disagree with those who, like Aristotle,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        ii. 26.
                    </note>
                    would remove
                    <hi rend="italics">refuation</hi>
                    from the list on the ground that it
forms part of the
                    <hi rend="italics">proof:</hi>
                    for the
                    <hi rend="italics">proof</hi>
                    is constructive, and the
                    <hi rend="italics">reputation</hi>
                    destructive. Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        iii. 13.
                    </note>
                    also
introduces another slight novelty in making
                    <hi rend="italics">proposition,</hi>
                    not
                    <hi rend="italics">statement of facts,</hi>
                    follow the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium.</hi>
                    This
however he does because he regards
                    <hi rend="italics">proposition</hi>
                    as
the
                    <hi rend="italics">genus</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">statement of facts</hi>
                    as the
                    <hi rend="italics">species,</hi>
                    with
the result that he holds that, whereas the former is
always and everywhere necessary, the latter may
sometimes be dispensed with.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It is however necessary to point out as regards
these five parts which I have established, that that
which has to be spoken first is not necessarily that
which requires our first consideration. But above
all we must consider the nature of the case,
the question at issue and the arguments for and
against. Next we must consider what points are
to be made, and what refuted, and then how the
facts are to be stated.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For the
                    <hi rend="italics">stalement of facts</hi>
                    is
designed to prepare the way for the
                    <hi rend="italics">proofs</hi>
                    and must
needs be unprofitable, unless we have first determined what
                    <hi rend="italics">proofs.</hi>
                    are to be promised in the
                    <hi rend="italics">statement.</hi>
                    Finally we must consider how best to win the
judge to take our view. For we cannot be sure until
we have subjected all the parts of the case to careful
scrutiny, what sort of impression we wish to make
upon the judge: are we to mollify him or increase
his severity, to excite or relax his interest in the
case, to render him susceptible to influence or the
reverse?
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    I cannot however approve the view of those who
                    <pb id="p.519"/>
                    think that the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium</hi>
                    should actually be written last.
For though we must collect all our material and determine the proper place for each portion of it, before
we begin to speak or write, we must commence with
what naturally comes first.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    No one begins a portrait
by painting or modelling the feet, and no art finds its
completion at the point where it should begin.
Otherwise what will happen if we have not time to
write our speech? Will not the result of such a
reversal of the proper order of things be that we
shall be caught napping? We must therefore review the subject-matter in the order laid down, but
write our speech in the order in which we shall
deliver it.
                </p>
                <p>
                    X. Every cause in which one side attacks and the
other defends consists either of one or more controversial questions. In the first case it is called
                    <hi rend="italics">simple,</hi>
                    in the second
                    <hi rend="italics">complex.</hi>
                    An example of the first is
when the subject of enquiry is a theft or an adultery
taken by itself. In
                    <hi rend="italics">complex</hi>
                    cases the several questions may all be of the same kind, as in cases of
extortion, or of different kinds, as when a man is
accused at one and the same time of homicide and
sacrilege. Such cases no longer arise in the public
courts, since the praetor allots the different charges
to different courts in accordance with a definite rule;
but they still are of frequent occurrence in the
Imperial or Senatorial courts, and were frequent in
the days when they came up for trial before the
people.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In the permanent courts (
                        <hi rend="italics">quaestiones perpetuae</hi>
                        ). There
were separate courts for, different offences. In cases brought
before the Senate or the Emperor a number of different
charges might be dealt with at once.
                    </note>
                    Private suits again are often tried by one
judge, who may have to determine many different
points of law.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    There are no other
                    <hi rend="italics">species of forensic</hi>
                    causes, not even when one person brings the same
suit on the same grounds against two different
                    <pb id="p.521"/>
                    persons, or two persons bring the same suit against
one, or several against several, as occasionally occurs
in lawsuits about inheritances. Because although a
number of parties may be involved, there is still only
one suit, unless indeed the different circumstances
of the various parties alter the questions at issue.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There is however said to be a third and different
class, the
                    <hi rend="italics">comparative.</hi>
                    Questions of comparison frequently require to be handled in portions of a cause,
as for instance in the centum viral court,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A civil court specially concerned with questions of
inheritance.
                    </note>
                    when after
other questions have been raised the question is discussed as to which of two claimants is the more deserving of an inheritance. It is rare however for a
case to be brought into court on such grounds alone,
as in
                    <hi rend="italics">divinations</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Divinatio</hi>
                        is a trial to decide between the claims of two
persons to appear as accuser, there being no public prosecutor
at Rome.
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        Cicero's
                        <hi rend="italics">Divinatio in Caecilium.</hi>
                    </note>
                    which take place to determine who
the accuser shall be, and occasionally when two informers dispute as to which has earned the reward.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Some again have added a fourth class, namely
                    <hi rend="italics">mutual accusation,</hi>
                    which they call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ntikathgori/a</foreign>
                    Others, however, regard it as belonging to the
                    <hi rend="italics">comparative</hi>
                    group, to which indeed the common case of
reciprocal suits on different grounds bears a strong
resemblance. If this latter case should also be called
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)ntikathgori/a</foreign>
                    (for it has no special name of its own), we
must divide
                    <hi rend="italics">mutual accusation</hi>
                    into two classes, in one
of which the parties bring the same charge against
each other, while in the other they bring different
charges. The same division will also apply to claims.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    As soon as we are clear as to the kind of cause on
which we are engaged, we must then consider
whether the act that forms the basis of the charge
is denied or defended, or given another name or
excepted from that class of action. Thus we determine the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of each case.
                    <pb id="p.523"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    XI. As soon as these points are ascertained, the
next step, according to Hermagoras, should be to
consider what is the
                    <hi rend="italics">question at issue,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">line of defence,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the judge's decision</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">central point,</hi>
                    or, as others call it,
                    <hi rend="italics">the foundation</hi>
                    of the case.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This highly technical chapter will be largely unintelligible
to those who have not read chapter vi. Those who have no
stomach for such points would do well to skip §§ 1–20; they
will however find consolation in § 21
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.,</hi>
                        where Quintilian
says what he really thinks of such technicalities.
                    </note>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    in its more general sense is taken to mean
everything on which two or more plausible opinions
may be advanced.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In
                    <hi rend="italics">forensic</hi>
                    subjects however it
must be taken in two senses: first in the sense in
which we say that a controversial matter involves
many questions, thereby including all minor questions; secondly in the sense of the main question on
which the case turns. It is of this, with which the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    originates, that I am now speaking. We ask
whether a thing has been done, what it is that has
been done, and whether it was rightly done.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    To these Hermagoras and Apollodorus and many other
writers have given the special name of
                    <hi rend="italics">questions;</hi>
                    Theodorus on the other hand, as I have already said,
calls them
                    <hi rend="italics">general heads,</hi>
                    while he designates minor
questions or questions dependent on these
                    <hi rend="italics">general heads</hi>
                    as
                    <hi rend="italics">special heads.</hi>
                    For it is agreed that question
may spring from question, and species be subdivided
into other species.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This main question, then, they
call the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">zh/thma.</foreign>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">line of defence</hi>
                    is the method by
which an admitted act is defended. I see no reason
why I should not use the same example to illustrate
this point that has been used by practically all my
predecessors. Orestes has killed his mother: the
fact is admitted. He pleads that he was justified in
so doing: the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    will be one of quality, the
                    <hi rend="italics">question,</hi>
                    whether he was justified in his action, the
                    <hi rend="italics">line of defence</hi>
                    that Clytemnestra killed her husband,
Orestes' father. This is called the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)/tion</foreign>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">motive.</hi>
                    <pb id="p.525"/>
                    The point for the decision of the judge is known as
the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">krino/menon</foreign>
                    and in this case is whether it was
right that even a guilty mother should be killed by
her son.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Some have drawn a distinction between
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)/tion</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)ti/an</foreign>
                    making
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)/tion</foreign>
                    mean the cause of the
trial, namely the murder of Clytemnestra,
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)ti/a</foreign>
                    the
motive urged in defence, namely the murder of
Agamemnon. But there is such lack of agreement
over these two words, that some make
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)ti/a</foreign>
                    the cause
of the trial and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)/tion</foreign>
                    the motive of the deed, while
others reverse the meanings. If we turn to Latin
writers we find that some have given these causes the
names of
                    <hi rend="italics">initinum,</hi>
                    the beginning, and
                    <hi rend="italics">ratio,</hi>
                    the reason,
while others give the same name to both.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    seems to spring from
                    <hi rend="italics">cause,</hi>
                    or as the Greeks say
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)/tion e)c ai)ti/on</foreign>
                    as will be seen from the following:—
Clytemnestra killed Agamemnon, because he had
sacrificed their daughter and brought home a captive
woman as his paramour. The same authors think
that there may be several
                    <hi rend="italics">lines of defence</hi>
                    to one
                    <hi rend="italics">question:</hi>
                    for instance Orestes may urge that he
killed his mother because driven to do so by oracles.
But the number of
                    <hi rend="italics">points for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    will be the same as the number of alleged
                    <hi rend="italics">motives</hi>
                    for
the deed: in this case it will be whether he ought to
have obeyed the oracles.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But one alleged
                    <hi rend="italics">motive</hi>
                    may
also in my opinion involve several questions and several
points for the decision of the judge, as for instance
in the case when the husband caught his wife in
adultery and slew her and later slew the adulterer,
who had escaped, in the market place. The
                    <hi rend="italics">motive</hi>
                    is
but one:
                    <quote>he was an adulterer.</quote>
                    But there arise
as
                    <hi rend="italics">questions</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">points for decision by the judge,</hi>
                    whether
                    <pb id="p.527"/>
                    it was lawful to kill him at that time and at that
place.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But just as, although there be several
                    <hi rend="italics">questions,</hi>
                    each with its special
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the case is but
one, namely that to which all else is referred, even so
the real
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    is, strictly
speaking, that on which judgment is given.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    As for
the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">su/nexon</foreign>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument,</hi>
                    as I have mentioned
it is called by some, or the
                    <hi rend="italics">foundation</hi>
                    as it is called by
others, or as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">De Inv.</hi>
                        I. xiv. 19.
                    </note>
                    styles it
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        the strongest argument of
the defender and the most relevant to the decision of the
judge,
                    </hi>
                    some regard it as being the point after which
all enquiry ceases, others as the main point for
adjudication.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">motive</hi>
                    of the deed does not arise
in all controversial cases. For how can there be a
                    <hi rend="italics">motive</hi>
                    for the deed, when the deed is denied? But
when the
                    <hi rend="italics">motive</hi>
                    for the deed does come up for
discussion, they deny that the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    rests on the same ground as
                    <hi rend="italics">the main question at issue,</hi>
                    and this view is maintained by Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">De Inv. I. c.: Part. Or.</hi>
                        xxx. 104.
                    </note>
                    in his
Rhetorica and
                    <hi rend="italics">Partitiones.</hi>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    For when it has been
asserted and denied that a deed was done, the question whether it was done is resolved by
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture,</hi>
                    and
the
                    <hi rend="italics">decision of the judge</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">main question</hi>
                    rest on
the same ground, since the first question and the
final decision are concerned with the same point.
But when it is stated and denied that Orestes was
justified in killing his mother, considerations of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality</hi>
                    are introduced: the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    is whether he was justified in killing her, but this is not yet the point for the
                    <hi rend="italics">decision of the judge.</hi>
                    When, then, does it become so?
                    <quote>She killed my father.</quote>
                    <quote>Yes, but that did not make it your duty to murder your mother.</quote>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    is whether it was his
duty to kill her.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the
                    <hi rend="italics">foundation,</hi>
                    I will put
                    <pb id="p.529"/>
                    it in the words of Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Inv. l. c.</hi>
                    </note>
                    himself:—
                    <quote>
                        The foundation
is the strongest argument for the defence, as for
instance, if Orestes were ready to say that the disposition of his mother towards his father, himself and
his sisters, the kingdom, the reputation of the race
and the family were such that it was the peculiar duty
of her children to punish her.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Others again use illustrations such as the following:—
                    <quote>He who has spent his patrimony, is not allowed to address the people.</quote>
                    <quote>But he spent it on public works.</quote>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    is whether everyone that spends his patrimony
is to be prohibited, while the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for decision is</hi>
                    whether he who spent it in such a way is to be
prohibited.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Or again take the case of the soldier
Arruntius, who killed the tribune Lusius for assaulting
his honour. The
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    is whether he was justified
in so doing,
                    <hi rend="italics">the line of defence,</hi>
                    that the murdered man
made an assault upon his honour,
                    <hi rend="italics">the point for the decision of the judge,</hi>
                    whether it was right that a man
should be killed uncondemned or a tribune by a
soldier.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Some even regard the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    as being different from the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    of the
                    <hi rend="italics">decision.</hi>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    as to whether Milo was justified in
killing Clodius, is one of
                    <hi rend="italics">quality.</hi>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge,</hi>
                    namely whether Clodius lay in
wait for Milo, is a matter for
                    <hi rend="italics">conjecture.</hi>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    They also
urge that a case is often diverted to the consideration
of some matter irrelevant to the
                    <hi rend="italics">question,</hi>
                    and that it is
on this matter that judgment is given. I strongly
disagree. Take the question whether all who have
spent their patrimony are to be prohibited from
addressing the people. This
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    must have its
                    <hi rend="italics">point for decision,</hi>
                    and therefore the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for decision</hi>
                    are not different, but there are more
                    <pb id="p.531"/>
                    than one
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    and more than one
                    <hi rend="italics">point for decision</hi>
                    in the case. Again, in the case of Milo,
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    is not the
                    <hi rend="italics">question of fact</hi>
                    ultimately referred to the
                    <hi rend="italics">question of quality</hi>
                    ? For if Clodius lay in wait for Milo, it follows
that he was justifiably killed. But when the case is
shifted to some other point far removed from the
original question, even in this case the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    will
be found to reside in the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for decision.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    As regards these questions Cicero is slightly inconsistent with himself. For in the Rhetorica, as I
have already mentioned, he followed Hermagoras,
while in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Topicai</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Top.</hi>
                        xxv. 95.
                    </note>
                    he holds that the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">krino/menon</foreign>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">disputed point</hi>
                    is originated by the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    and in
addressing the lawyer Trebatius on this subject he
calls it the
                    <hi rend="italics">point at issue,</hi>
                    and describes the elements
in which it resides as
                    <hi rend="italics">central arguments</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        foundations
of the defence which hold it together and the removal of
which causes the whole defence to fall to the ground.
                    </hi>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    But
in the
                    <hi rend="italics">Partitiones Oratoriae</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">xxix. 103.</note>
                    he gives the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">foundation</hi>
                    to that which is advanced against the defence, on the ground that the
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument,</hi>
                    as it
logically comes first, is put forward by the accuser,
while
                    <hi rend="italics">the line of defence</hi>
                    is put forward by the accused,
and the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    arises from
the question jointly raised by the
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">line of defence.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    The view therefore of those who make the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis,</hi>
                    the
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument,</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    identical, is at once more concise and nearer
to the truth. The
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument,</hi>
                    they point out,
is that the removal of which makes the whole case fall
to the ground.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    In this
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument</hi>
                    they seem to
me to have included both the alleged causes, that
                    <pb id="p.533"/>
                    Orestes killed his mother and that Clytemnestra
killed Agamemnon. the same authorities have likewise always held that the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision</hi>
                    of the judge are in agreement; any other
opinion would have been inconsistent with their
general views.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    But this affectation of subtlety in the invention of
technical terms is mere laborious ostentation: I have
undertaken the task of discussing them solely that I
might not be regarded as having failed to make sufficient inquiry into the subject which I have chosen as
my theme. But it is quite unnecessary for an instructor proceeding on less technical lines to destroy
the coherence of his teaching by attention to such
minute detail.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Many however suffer from this drawback, more especially Hermagoras who, although he
labours these points with such anxious diligence, was
a man of penetrating intellect and in most respects
deserves our admiration, so that even where we must
needs blame him, we cannot withhold a certain meed
of praise.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    But the shorter method, which for that
very reason is also by far the most lucid, will not
fatigue the learner by leading him through a maze of
detail, nor destroy the coherence of his eloquence by
breaking it up into a number of minute departments.
For he who has a clear view of the main issue of a dispute, and divines the aims which his own side and his
opponents intend to follow and the means they intend
to employ (and it is to the intentions of his own side
that he must pay special attention), will without a
doubt be in possession of a knowledge of all the points
which I have discussed above.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    And there is hardly
anyone, unless he be a born fool without the least
acquaintance with the practice of speaking, who does
                    <pb id="p.535"/>
                    not know what is the main issue of a dispute (or as
they call it the
                    <hi rend="italics">cause</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument</hi>
                    ) and what is
the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    between the parties and the
                    <hi rend="italics">point on which the judge has to decide,</hi>
                    these three being identical.
For the
                    <hi rend="italics">question</hi>
                    is concerned with the matter in dispute and the
                    <hi rend="italics">decision of the judge</hi>
                    is given on the
point involved in the
                    <hi rend="italics">question.</hi>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Still we do not keep
our attention rigidly fixed on such details, but the
desire to win praise by any available means and the
sheer delight in speaking make us wander away from
the subject, since there is always richer material for
eloquence outside the strict theme of the case, inasmuch as the points of any given dispute are always
few, and there is all the world outside, and in the one
case we speak according to our instructions, in the
other on the subjects of our own choice.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    We should
teach not so much that it is our duty to discover the
                    <hi rend="italics">question, the</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">central argument,</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">point for the decision of the judge</hi>
                    (an easy task), as that we should
continually keep our attention on our subject, or if
we digress, at least keep looking back to it, lest in
our desire to win applause we should let our weapons
drop from our grasp.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    The school of Theodorus, as I
have said, groups everything under
                    <hi rend="italics">heads,</hi>
                    by which
they mean several things. First they mean the
                    <hi rend="italics">main question,</hi>
                    which is to be identified with the
                    <hi rend="italics">basis;</hi>
                    secondly they mean the other questions dependent
on the
                    <hi rend="italics">main question,</hi>
                    thirdly the
                    <hi rend="italics">proposition</hi>
                    and the
                    <hi rend="italics">statement of the proofs.</hi>
                    The word is used as we use it
when we say
                    <quote>It is the head of the whole business,</quote>
                    or, as Menander says,
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">kefa/laio/n e)stin.</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Perhaps a gloss referring to the late rhetorician Menander. If genuine, the words must refer to the comic poet.
                    </note>
                    But generally
speaking, anything which has to be proved will be a
head of varying degrees of importance.
                    <pb id="p.537"/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    I have now set forth the principles laid down by
the writers of text-books,
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    though I have done so
at a greater length than was necessary. I have
also explained what are the various parts of forensic
causes. My next book therefore shall deal with
the
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium.</hi>
                </p>
                <pb id="p.539"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
