<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>In Defense of Aulus Cluentius Habitus</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="M. Tullius Cicero">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--   <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc> -->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-04-13" who="Lisa Cerrato">Minor revisions.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-14" who="Zach Himes">Moved some section divs that were incorrectly placed (after checking with the Latin text)</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi010.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
    <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF AULUS CLUENTIUS HABITUS.</head>
   <div type="commentary" resp="ed">
   
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>Aulus Cluentius, a Roman knight of great riches, was accused before the praetor of having
    poisoned his father-in-law, Oppianicus, who a few years previously had been tried and banished
    for an attempt to poison Cluentius. For Oppianicus had murdered Melinus, the former husband of
    Sassia, the mother of Cluentius, and married her, and finding that if Cluentius were dead his
    property would all come to his mother, endeavoured to poison him, but was detected and
    convicted. After his conviction, Lucius Quinctius, a tribune of the people, who had defended
    him on his trial, endeavoured at all times to excite odium against Cluentius, saying that he
    had procured the conviction of Oppianicus by bribery, though in point of fact Oppianicus
    himself had employed large sums in endeavours to bribe his judges, and Stalenus and others had
    been convicted of being parties to the corruption. In the fifth year of his exile Oppianicus
    died, and a prosecution was instituted against Cluentius by Sassia, his own mother; saying that
    he had poisoned Oppianicus by the agency of a man of the name of Marcus Asellius. Cluentius was
    acquitted. This happened three years before this present trial. But now Sassia, having married
    her daughter to the young Oppianicus, urged him to institute fresh proceedings against
    Cluentius. So he prosecuted him afresh. His counsel was Lucius Attius, and the cause was tried
    before Quintus Vocontius Naso in the consulship of Marcus Aemilius Lepidus and Lucius Volcatius
    Tullus, A.U.C. 688. <note anchored="true">Manutius makes a mistake in fixing this consulship of
     Lepidus and Tullus, and by consequence, the delivery of this oration, one year earlier.</note>
    Cluentius was acquitted.</p></div>
   
   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I have observed, O judges, that the whole speech of the accuser is divided into two parts, one
    of which appeared to me to rely upon, and to put its main trust in, the inveterate unpopularity
    of the trial before Junius; <note anchored="true">Junius had been the judge in the trial of
     Oppianicus. See <bibl n="Cic. Clu. 74">c. xxvii.</bibl></note> the other, just for the sake of
    usage, to touch very lightly and diffidently On the method pursued in cases of accusations of
    poisoning; concerning which matter this form of trial is appointed by law. And, therefore, I
    have determined to preserve the same division of the subject in my defence, speaking separately
    to the question of unpopularity and to that of the accusation, in order that every one may
    understand that I neither wish to evade any point by being silent with respect to it, nor to
    make anything obscure by speaking of it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p> But when I consider
    how much pains I must take with each branch of the question, one division—that, namely, which is
    the proper subject of your inquiry, the question of the fact of the poisoning—appears to me a
    very short one, and one which is not likely to give occasion to any great dispute. But with the
    other division, which, properly, is almost entirely unconnected with the case, and which is
    better adapted to assemblies in a state of seditious excitement, than to tranquil and orderly
    courts of justice, I shall, I can easily see, have a great deal of difficulty in dealing, and a
    great deal of trouble. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p> But in all this embarrassment, O
    judges, this thing still consoles me,—that you have been accustomed to hear accusations under
    the idea that you will afterwards hear their refutation from the advocate; that you are bound
    not to give the defendant more advantages towards ensuring his acquittal, than his counsel can
    procure for him by clearing him of the charges brought against him, and by proving his innocence
    in his speech. But as regards the odium into which they seek to bring him, you ought to
    deliberate together, considering not what is said by us, but what ought to be said. For while we
    are dealing with the accusations, it is only the safety of Aulus Cluentius that is at stake; but
    by the odium sought to be excited against him, the common safety of all men is imperilled.
    Accordingly, we will treat one division of the case as men who are giving you information, and
    the other division, as men who are addressing entreaties to you. In the first division we must
    beg of you to give us your diligent attention; in the second, we must implore the protection of
    your good faith. There is no one who can withstand the popular feeling when excited against him
    without the assistance of you and of men like you. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> As far as I
    myself am concerned. I hardly know which way to turn. Shall I deny that there is any ground for
    the disgraceful accusation, —that the judges were corrupted at the previous trial? Shall I deny
    that that matter has been agitated at assemblies of the people? that it has been brought before
    the courts of justice? that it has been mentioned in the senate? Can I eradicate that belief
    from men's minds? a belief so deeply implanted in them—so long established. It is out of the
    power of my abilities to do so. It is a matter requiring your aid, O judges; it becomes you to
    come to the assistance of the innocence of this man attacked by such a ruinous calumny, as you
    would in the case of a destructive fire or of a general conflagration. </p></div>
    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Indeed, as in some places truth appears to have but little foundation to rest upon, and but
    little vigour, so in this place unpopularity arising on false grounds ought to be powerless. Let
    it have sway in assemblies, but let it be overthrown in courts of justice; let it influence the
    opinions and conversation of ignorant men, but let it be rejected by the dispositions of the
    wise; let it make sudden and violent attacks, but when time for examination is given, and when
    the facts are ascertained, let it die away. Lastly, let that definition of impartial tribunals
    which has been handed down to us from our ancestors be still retained; that in them crimes are
    punished without any regard being had to the popularity or unpopularity of the accused party;
    and unpopularity is got rid of without any crime being supposed to have been ever attached to
    it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> And, therefore, O judges, I beg this of you before I begin
    to speak of the cause itself; in the first place, as is most reasonable, that you will bring no
    prejudice into court with you. In truth, we shall lose not only the authority, but even the name
    of judges, unless we judge from the facts which appear in the actual trials, and if we bring
    into court with us minds already made up on the subject at home. In the second place, I beg of
    you, if you have already adopted any opinion in your minds, that if reason shall eradicate
    it,—if my speech shall shake it,—if, in short, truth shall wrest it from you, you will not
    resist, but will dismiss it from your minds, if not willingly, at all events, impartially. I beg
    you, also, when I am speaking to each particular point, and effacing any impression my adversary
    may have made, not silently to let your thoughts dwell on the contrary statement to mine, but to
    wait to the end, and allow me to maintain the order of my arguments which I propose to myself;
    and when I have summed up, then to consider in your minds whether I have passed over anything.
     </p></div>
    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I, O judges, am thoroughly aware that I am under taking a cause which has now for eight years
    together been constantly discussed in a spirit opposed to the interests of my client, and which
    has been almost convicted and condemned by the silent opinion of men; but if any god will only
    incline your good-will to listen to me patiently, I will show you that there is nothing which a
    man has so much reason to dread as envy,—that when he has incurred envy, there is nothing so
    much to be desired by an innocent man as an impartial tribunal, because in this alone can any
    end and termination be found at last to undeserved disgrace. Wherefore, I am in very great hope,
    if I am able fully to unravel all the circumstances of this case, and to effect all that I wish
    by my speech, that this place, and this bench of judges before whom I am pleading, which the
    other side has expected to be most terrible and formidable to Aulus Cluentius, will be to him a
    harbour at last, and a refuge for the hitherto miserable and tempest-tossed bark of his
    fortunes. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> Although there are many things which seem to me
    necessary to be mentioned respecting the common dangers to which all men are exposed by
    unpopularity, before I speak about the cause itself; still, that I may not keep your
    expectations too long in suspense by my speech, I will come to the charge itself, only begging
    you, O judges, as I am aware I must frequently do in the course of this trial, to listen to me,
    as if this cause were now being this day pleaded for the first time,—as, in fact, it is; and not
    as if it had already been often discussed and proved. For on this day opportunity is given us
    for the first time of effacing that old accusation; up to this time mistake and odium have had
    the principal influence in the whole cause. Wherefore, while I reply with brevity and clearness
    to the accusation of many years standing, I entreat you, O judges, to listen to me, as I know
    that you are predetermined to do, with kindness and attention. </p></div>
    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Aulus Cluentius is said to have corrupted a tribunal with money, in order to procure the
    condemnation of his innocent enemy, Statius Albius. I will prove, O judges, in the first place,
    (since that is the principal wickedness charged against him, and the chief pretext for casting
    odium upon him, that an innocent man was condemned through the influence of in your minds
    whether I have money,) that no one was ever brought before a court on heavier charges, or with
    more unimpeachable witnesses against him to prove them. In the second place, that a previous
    examination into the matter had been made by the very same judges who afterwards condemned him,
    with such a result that he could not possibly have been acquitted, not only by them, but by any
    other imaginable tribunal. When I have demonstrated this, then I will prove that point which I
    am aware is particularly indispensable, that that tribunal was indeed tampered with, not by
    Cluentius, but by the party hostile to Cluentius; and I will enable you to see clearly in the
    whole of that cause what the facts really were—what mistake gave rise to—and what had its origin
    in the unpopularity undeservedly stirred up against Cluentius. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> The first point is this, from which it may be clearly seen that Cluentius had the greatest
    reason to confide in the justice of his cause, because he came down to accuse Albius relying on
    the most certain facts and unimpeachable witnesses. While on this topic, it is necessary for me,
    O judges, briefly to explain the accusations of which Albius was convicted. I demand of you, O
    Oppianicus, to believe that I speak unwillingly of the affair in which your father was
    implicated, because I am compelled by considerations of good faith, and of my duty as counsel
    for the defence. And, if I am unable at the present moment to satisfy you of this, yet I shall
    have many other opportunities of satisfying you at some future time; but unless I do justice to
    Cluentius now, I shall have no subsequent opportunity of doing justice to him. At the same time
    who is there who can possibly hesitate to speak against a man who has been condemned and is
    dead, on behalf of one unconvicted and living, when in the case of him who is being so spoken
    against conviction has taken away all danger of further disgrace, and death all fear of any
    further pain? and when, on the other hand, no disaster can happen to that man on behalf of whom
    one is speaking, without causing him the most acute feeling and pain of mind, and without
    branding his future life with the greatest disgrace and ignominy? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> And that you may understand that Cluentius was not induced to prosecute
    Oppianicus by a disposition fond of bringing accusations, or by any fondness for display or
    covetousness of glory, but by nefarious injuries, by daily plots against him, by hazard of his
    life, which has been every day set before his eyes, I must go back a little further to the very
    beginning of the business; and I entreat you, O judges, not to be weary or indignant at my doing
    so—for when you know the beginning, you will much more easily understand the end. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Aulus Cluentius Habitus, this man's father, O judges, was a man by far the most distinguished
    for valour, for reputation and for nobleness of birth, not only of the municipality of
     <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, of which he was a native, but also of all
    that district and neighbourhood. When he died, in the consulship of Sulla and Pompeius, <note anchored="true">a. u. c. 666. Twenty-two years before this time.</note> he left this son, a boy
    fifteen years old, and a daughter grown up and of marriageable age, who a short time after her
    father's death married Aulus Aurius Melinus, her own cousin, a youth of the fairest possible
    reputation, as was then supposed, among his countrymen, for honour and nobleness. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> This marriage subsisted with all respectability and all concord; when
    on a sudden there arose the nefarious lust of an abandoned woman, united not only with infamy
    but even with impiety. For Sassia, the mother of this Habitus, (for she shall be called his
    mother by me, just for the name's sake, although she behaves towards him with the hatred and
    cruelty of an enemy,)—she shall, I say, be called his mother; nor will I even so speak of her
    wickedness and barbarity as to forget the name to which nature entitles her; (for the more
    lovable and amiable the name of mother is, the more will you think the extraordinary wickedness
    of that mother, who for these many years has been wishing her son dead, and who wishes it now
    more than ever, worthy of all possible hatred.) She, then, the mother of Habitus, being charmed
    in a most impious matter with love for that young man, Melinus, her own son-in-law, at first
    restrained her desires as she could, but she did not do that long. Presently, she began to get
    so furious in her insane passion, she began to be so hurried away by her lust, that neither
    modesty, nor chastity, nor piety, nor the disgrace to her family, nor the opinion of men, nor
    the indignation of her son, nor the grief of her daughter, could recall her from her desires.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> She seduced the mind of the young man, not yet matured by
    wisdom and reason, with all those temptations with which that early age can be charmed and
    allured. Her daughter, who was tormented not only with the common indignation which all women
    feel at injuries of that sort from their husbands, but who also was unable to endure the
    infamous prostitution of her mother, of which she did not think that she could even complain to
    any one without committing a sin herself, wished the rest of the world to remain in ignorance of
    this her terrible misfortune, and wasted away in grief and tears in the arms and on the bosom of
    Cluentius, her most affectionate brother. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> However, there is a
    sudden divorce, which appeared likely to be a consolation for all her misfortunes. Cluentia
    departs from Melinus; not unwilling to be released from the infliction of such injuries, yet not
    willing to lose her husband. But then that admirable and illustrious mother of hers began openly
    to exult with joy, to triumph in her delight, victorious over her daughter, not over her lust.
    Therefore she did not choose her reputation to be attacked any longer by uncertain suspicions;
    she orders that genial bed, which two years before she had decked for her daughter on her
    marriage, to be decked and prepared for herself in the very same house, having driven and forced
    her daughter out of it. The mother-in-law marries the son-in-law, no one looking favourably on
    the deed, no one approving it, all foreboding a dismal end to it. </p></div>
    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Oh, the incredible wickedness of the woman, and, with the exception of this one single
    instance, unheard of since the world began! Oh, the unbridled and unrestrained lust! Oh, the
    extraordinary audacity of her conduct! To think that she did not fear (even if she disregarded
    the anger of the gods and the scorn of men) that nuptial night and those bridal torches! that
    she did not dread the threshold of that chamber! nor the bed of her daughter! nor those very
    walls, the witnesses of the former wedding! She broke down and overthrew everything in her
    passion and her madness; lust got the better of shame, audacity subdued fear, mad passion
    conquered reason. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> Her son was indignant at this common
    disgrace of his family, of his blood, and of his name. His misery was increased by the daily
    complaints and incessant weeping of his sister; still he resolved that he ought to do nothing
    more himself with reference to his grievous injuries and the terrible wickedness of his mother,
    beyond ceasing to consider her as his mother; lest, if he did continue to behave to her as if
    she were his mother, he might be thought not only to see, but in his heart to approve of, those
    things which he could not behold without the greatest anguish of mind. 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> You have heard what was the origin of the bad feeling
    between him and his mother; when you know the rest, you will perceive that I feared this with
    reference to our care; for, I am not ignorant that, whatever sort of woman a mother may be,
    still in a trial in which her son is concerned, it is scarcely fitting that any mention should
    be made of the infamy of his mother. I should not, O judges, be fit to con duct any cause, if,
    when I was employed in warding off danger from a friend, I were to fail to see this which is
    implanted and deeply rooted in the common feelings of all men, and in their very nature. I am
    quite aware, that it is right for men not only to be silent about the injuries which they suffer
    from their parents, but even to bear them with equanimity; but I think that those things which
    can be borne ought to be borne, that those things which can be buried in silence ought to be
    buried in silence. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> Aulus Cluentius has seen no calamity in
    his whole life, has encountered no peril of death, has feared no evil, which has not been
    contrived against, and brought to bear upon him, from beginning to end, by his mother. But all
    these things he would say nothing of at the present moment, and would allow them to be buried,
    if possible, in oblivion, and if not, at all events in silence as far as he is concerned, but
    she does these things in such a manner that he is totally unable to be silent about them; for
    this very trial, this danger in which he now is, this accusation which is brought against him,
    all the multitude of witnesses which is to appear, has all been provided originally by his
    mother; is marshalled by his mother at this present time; and is furthered with all her wealth
    and all her influence. She herself has lately hastened from <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> for the sake of
    destroying this her son. The woman' is at hand, bold, wealthy and cruel. She has provided
    accusers; she has trained witnesses; she rejoices in the mourning garments and miserable
    appearance of Cluentius; she longs for his destruction; she would be willing to shed her own
    blood to the last drop, if she can only see his blood shed first. Unless you have all these
    circumstances proved to you in the course of this trial, I give you leave to think that she is
    unjustly brought before the court by me now; but if all these things are made as plain as they
    are abominable, then you ought to pardon Cluentius for allowing these things to be said by me;
    and you ought not to pardon me if I were silent under such circumstances </p></div>
    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Now I will just briefly relate to you on what charges Oppianicus was convicted; that you may
    be able to see clearly both the constancy of Aulus Cluentius and the cause of this accusation.
    And first of all I will show you what was the cause of the prosecution of Oppianicus; so that
    you may see that, Aulus Cluentius only instituted it because he was compelled by force and
    absolute necessity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>When he had evidently taken poison, which Oppianicus, the husband of his mother, had prepared
    for him; and as this fact was proved, not by conjecture, but by eyesight,—by his being caught in
    the fact; and as there could be no possible doubt in the case, he prosecuted Oppianicus. With
    what constancy, with what diligence he did so, I will state hereafter; at present I wish you to
    be aware that he had no other reason for accusing him, except that this was the only method by
    which he could escape the danger manifestly intended to his life, and the daily plots laid
    against his existence. And that you may understand that Oppianicus was accused of charges from
    which a prosecutor had nothing to fear, and a defendant nothing to hope, I will relate to you a
    few of the items of accusation which were brought forward at that trial; and when you have heard them, none of you will wonder that he should have
    distrusted his case, and betaken himself to Stalenus and to bribery?</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/>There was a woman of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, named Dinea, the
    mother-in-law of Oppianicus, who had three sons, Marcus Aurius, Numerius Aurius, and Cnaeus
    Magius, and one daughter, Magia, who was married to Oppianicus. Marcus Aurius, quite a young
    man, having been taken prisoner in the social war at <placeName key="perseus,Asculum">Asculum</placeName>, fell into the hands of Quintus Sergius, a senator, who was convicted of
    assassination, and was put by him in his slaves' prison. But Numerius Aurius, his brother, died,
    and left Cnaeus Magius, his brother, his heir. Afterwards, Magia, the wife of Oppianicus, died;
    and last of all, that one who was the last of the sons of Dinea, Cnaeus Magius, also died. He
    left as his heir that young Oppianicus, the son of his sister, and enjoined that he should share
    the inheritance with his mother Dinea. In the meantime an informant comes to Dinea, (a man
    neither of obscure rank, nor uncertain as to the truth of his news,) to tell her that her son
    Marcus Aurius is alive, and is in the territory of <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, in slavery. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p> The woman having lost her
    children, when the hope of recovering one of her sons was held out to her, summoned all her
    relations, and all the intimate friends of her son, and with tears entreated them to undertake
    the business to seek out the youth, and to restore to her that son whom fortune had willed
    should be the only one remaining to her out of many. Just when she had begun to adopt these
    measures, she was taken ill. Therefore she made a will in these terms: she left to that son four
    hundred thousand sesterces; and she made that Oppianicus who has been already mentioned, her
    grandson, her heir. And a few days after, she died. However, these relations, as they had
    undertaken to do while Dinea was alive, when she was dead, went into the Gallic territory to
    search out Aurius, with the same man who had brought Dinea the information. </p></div>
    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>In the meantime, Oppianicus being, as you will have proved to you by many circumstances, a man
    of singular wickedness and audacity, by means of some <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, his intimate friend, first of all corrupted that informer with a bribe, and
    after that, at no great expense, managed to have Aurius himself got out of the way and murdered.
    But they who had gone to seek out and recover their relation, send letters to <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, to the Aurii the relations of that young man, and
    their own intimate friends, to say that the investigation was very difficult for them, because
    they understood that the man who had given the information had been since bribed by Oppianicus.
    And these letters Aulus Aurius, a brave and experienced man, and one of high rank in his own
    city, the near relation of the missing Marcus Aurius, read openly in the forum, in the hearing
    of plenty of people, in the presence of Oppianicus himself, and with a loud voice declared that
    he would prosecute Oppianicus if he found that Marcus Aurius had been murdered. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> The feelings, not only of his relations, but also of all the citizens
    of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, are moved by hatred of Oppianicus, and
    pity for that young man. Therefore, when Aulus Aurius, he who had previously made this
    declaration, began to follow the man with loud cries and with threats, he fled from <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, and betook himself to the camp of that most
    illustrious man, Quintus Metellus. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> After that flight, the
    witness of his crime, and of his consciousness of it, he never ventured to commit himself to the
    protection of a court of justice, or of the laws,—he never dared to trust himself unarmed among
    his enemies; but at the time when violence was stalking abroad, after the victory of Lucius
    Sulla, he came to <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> with a body of armed men,
    to the great alarm of all the citizens; he carried off the quatuorviri, <note anchored="true">“The highest magistrates of a <foreign xml:lang="lat">colonia</foreign> were the decemviri or
     quatuorviri, so called as the numbers might vary, whose functions may be compared with those of
     the consulate at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, before the establishment of
     the praetorship. Their principal duties were the administration of justice.”—Smith, Dict. Ant.
     p. 259, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Colonia</foreign>.</note> whom the citizens of that
    municipality had elected; he said that he and three others had been appointed by Sulla; and he
    said that he received orders from him to take care that that Aurius who had threatened him with
    prosecution and with danger to his life, and the other Aurius, and Caius Aurius his son, and
    Sextus Vibius, whom he was said to have employed as his agent in corrupting the man who had
    given the information, were proscribed and put to death. Accordingly, when they had been most
    cruelly murdered, the rest were ale thrown into no slight fear of proscription and death by that
    circumstance. When these things had been made manifest at the trial, who is there who can think
    it possible that he should have been acquitted? <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And these things are trifles. Listen to what follows, and you will wonder, not that Oppianicus
    was at last condemned, but that he remained for some time in safety. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>In the first place, remark the audacity of the man. He was anxious to marry Sassia, the mother
    of Habitus, her whose husband, Aulus Aurius, he had murdered. It is hard to say whether he who
    wished such a thing was the more impudent, or she who consented was the more heartless. However,
    remark the humanity and virtue of both of them. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> Oppianicus
    asks, and most earnestly entreats Sassia to marry him. But she does not marvel at his
    audacity,—does not scorn and reject his impudence, she is not even alarmed at the idea of the
    house of Oppianicus, red with her husband's blood; but she says that she has a repugnance to
    this marriage, because he has three sons. Oppianicus, who coveted Sassia's money, thought that
    he must seek at home for a remedy for that obstacle which was opposed to his marriage. For as he
    had an infant son by Novia, and as a second son of his, whom he had had by
      <persName><surname>Papia</surname></persName>, was being brought up under his mother's eye at
    Teanum in <placeName key="tgn,7010380">Apulia</placeName>, which is about eighteen miles from
     <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, on a sudden, without alleging any reason,
    he sends for the boy from Teanum, which he had previously never been accustomed to do, except at
    the time of the public games, or on days of festival. His miserable mother, suspecting no evil,
    sends him. He pretended to set out himself to <placeName key="tgn,7004100">Tarentum</placeName>;
    and on that very day the boy, though at the eleventh hour he had been seen in public in good
    health, died before night, and the next day was burnt before daybreak. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p> And common report brought this miserable news to his mother before any one of
    Oppianicus's household brought her news of it. She, when she had heard at one and the same time,
    that she was deprived not only of her son, but even of the sad office of celebrating his funeral
    rites, came instantly, half dead with grief, to <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, and there performs funeral obsequies over again for her already buried
    son. Ten days had not elapsed when his other infant son is also murdered; and then Sassia
    immediately marries Oppianicus, rejoicing in his mind, and feeling confident of the attainment
    of his hopes. No wonder she married him, when she saw him so eager to propitiate her, not with
    ordinary nuptial gifts, but with the deaths of his sons. So that other men are often covetous of
    money for the sake of their children, but that man thought it more agreeable to lose his
    children for the sake of money. </p></div>
    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I see, O judges, that you, as becomes your feelings of humanity, are violently moved at these
    enormous crimes now briefly related by me. What do you think must have been their feelings who
    had not only to hear of these wicked deeds, but also to sit in judgment on them? You are hearing
    of a man, in whose case you are not the judges,—of a man whom you do not see,—of a man whom you
    now can no longer hate, —of a man who has made atonement to nature and to the laws, whom the
    laws have punished with banishment, nature with death. You are hearing of these actions, not
    from any enemy, you are hearing of them without any witnesses being produced; you are hearing of
    them when those things which might be enlarged upon at the greatest length are stated by me in a
    brief and summary manner. They were hearing of the actions of a man with reference to whom they
    were bound to deliver their judgment on oath,—of a man who was present, whose infamous and
    hardened countenance they were looking upon,—of a man whom they hated on account of his
    audacity,—of him whom they thought worthy of every possible punishment. They were hearing the
    relation of these crimes from his accusers; they were hearing the statements of many witnesses;
    they were hearing a serious and long oration on each separate particular from Publius Canutius,
    a most eloquent man. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p> And is there any man who, when he has
    become acquainted with these things, can suspect that Oppianicus was taken unfair advantage of,
    and crushed at his trial, though he was innocent? I will now mention all the other things in a
    lump, O judges, in order to come to those things which are nearer to, and more immediately
    connected with, this cause. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>I entreat you to recollect that it was no part of my original intention to bring any
    accusation against Oppianicus, now that he is dead; but that as I wish to persuade you that the
    tribunal was not bribed by my client, I use this as the beginning and foundation of my
    defence,—that Oppianicus was condemned, being a most guilty and wicked man. He himself gave a
    cup to his own wife Cluentia, who was the aunt of that man Habitus, and she while drinking it
    cried out that she was dying in the greatest agony; and she lived no longer than she was
    speaking, for she died in the middle of this speech and exclamation. And besides the suddenness
    of this death, and the exclamation of the dying woman, everything which is considered a sign and
    proof of poison was discovered in her body after she was dead. </p></div>
    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And by the same poison he killed Caius Oppianicus his brother,—and even this was not enough.
    Although in the murder of his brother no wickedness seems to have been omitted, still he
    prepared beforehand the road by which he was to arrive at his abominable crime by other acts of
    wickedness. For, as Auria, his brother's wife, was in the family way, and appeared to be near
    the time of her confinement, he murdered her also with poison, so that she and his own brother's
    child, whom she bore within her, perished at the same time. After that he attacked his brother;
    who, when it was too late, after he had drank that cup of death, and when he was uttering loud
    exclamations about his own and his wife's death, and was desirous to alter his will, died during
    the actual expression of this intention. So he murdered the woman, that he might not be cut off
    from his brother's inheritance by her confinement; and he deprived his brother's children of
    life before they were able to receive from nature the light which was intended for them; so as
    to give every one to understand that nothing could be protected against him, that nothing was
    too holy for him, from whose audacity even the protection of their mother's body had been unable
    to preserve his own brother's children. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I recollect that a certain Milesian woman, when I was in <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, because she had by medicines brought on abortion, having been bribed to do
    so by the heirs in reversion, was convicted of a capital crime; and rightly, inasmuch as she had
    destroyed the hope of the father, the memory of his name, the supply of his race, the heir of
    his family, a citizen intended for the use of the republic. How much severer punishment does
    Oppianicus deserve for the same crime? For she, by doing this violence to her person, tortured
    her own body; but he effected this same crime through the torture and death of another. Other
    men do not appear to be able to commit many atrocious murders on one individual, but Oppianicus
    has been found clever enough to destroy many lives in one body. </p></div>
    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore when Cnaeus Magius, the uncle of that young Oppianicus, had become acquainted with
    the habits and audacity of this man, and, being stricken with a sore disease, had made him, his
    sister's son, his heir, summoning his friends, in the presence of his mother Dinea, he asked his
    wife whether she was in the family way; and when she said that she was, he begged of her after
    his death to live with Dinea who was her mother-in-law, till she was confined, and to take great
    care to preserve and to bring forth alive the child that she had conceived. Accordingly, he
    leaves her in his will a large sum, which she was to receive from his child if a child was born,
    but leaves her nothing from the reversionary heir. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p> You see
    what he suspected of Oppianicus; what his opinion of him was is plain enough. For though he left
    his son his heir, he did not leave him guardian to his children. Now, learn what Oppianicus did;
    and you will see that Magius, when dying, had an accurate foresight of what was to happen. The
    money which had been left to her from her child if any was born, that Oppianicus paid to her at
    once, though it was not due; if, indeed, it is to be called a payment of a legacy, and not wages
    for procuring abortion; and she, having received that sum, and many other presents besides,
    which were read out of the codicils of Oppianicus's will, being subdued by avarice, sold to the
    wickedness of Oppianicus that hope which she had in her womb, and which had been so commended to
    her care by her husband.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p> It would seem now that nothing could possibly be added to this wickedness: listen to the end.—The woman who, according to
    the solemn request of her husband, ought not for ten months to have ever entered any house but
    that of her mother-in-law; five months after her husband's death married Oppianicus himself. But
    that marriage did not last long, for it was entered into, not with any regard to the dignity of
    wedlock, but from a partnership in wickedness. </p></div>
    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What more shall I say? How notorious, while the fact was recent, was the murder of Asinius of
     <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, a wealthy young man! how much talked
    about in every one's conversation! There was a man of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> of the name of Avilius, a man of abandoned character and great poverty,
    but exceedingly skillful in rousing and gratifying the passions of young men; and as by his
    attentions and obsequiousness he had wormed himself into the acquaintance of Asinius, Oppianicus
    began forthwith to hope, that by means of this Avilius, as if he were an instrument applied for
    the purpose! he might catch the youth of Asinius, and take his father's wealth from him by
    storm. The plan was devised at <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>; the
    accomplishment of it was transferred to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. For they
    thought that they could lay the foundations of that design more easily in solitude, but that
    they could accomplish a deed of the sort more conveniently in a crowd. Asinius went to
     <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> with Avilius; Oppianicus followed on their
    footsteps. How they spent their time at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, in what
    revels, in what scenes of debauchery, in what immense and extravagant expenses, not only with
    the knowledge, but even with the company and assistance of Oppianicus, would take me a long
    while to tell, especially as I am hurrying on to other topics. Listen to the end of this
    pretended friendship. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p> When the young man was in some woman's
    house, and passing the night there, and staying there also the next day, Avilius, as had been
    arranged, pretends that he is taken ill, and wishes to make his will—Oppianicus brings witnesses
    to sign it, who knew neither Asinius nor Avilius, and calls him Asinius; and he himself departs,
    after the will has been signed and sealed in the name of Asinius. Avilius gets well immediately.
    But Asinius in a very short time is slain, being tempted out to some sand-pits outside the
     <placeName key="tgn,4012794">Esquiline</placeName> gate, by the idea that he was being taken to
    some villa. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p> And after he had been missed a day or two, and
    could not be found in those places in which he was usually to be sought for, and as Oppianicus
    was constantly saying in the forum at <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> that
    he and his friends had lately witnessed his will, the freedmen of Asinius and some of his
    friends, because it was notorious that on the last day that Asinius had been seen, Avilius had
    been with him, and had been seen with him by many people, proceed against him, and bring him
    before Quintus Manilius, who at that time was a triumvir. <note anchored="true">There were many
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri</foreign>, but the <foreign xml:lang="lat">triumviri
      capitales</foreign>, which are meant here, were regular magistrates elected by the people,
     they succeeded to many of the functions of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">quaestores
      parricidii</foreign>, and in many points they resembled the magistracy of the Eleven at
      <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Their court appears to have been near the
     Maenian Column. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. p, <date when="1009">1009</date>, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Triumvir</foreign>.</note> And Avilius at once,
    without any witness or any informer appearing against him, being agitated by the consciousness
    of his recent wickedness, relates everything as I have now stated it, and confesses that Asinius
    had been murdered by him according to the plan of Oppianicus. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p>
    Oppianicus, while lying concealed in his own house, is dragged out by Manilius; Avilius the
    informer is produced on the other side to face him. Why need you inquire what followed? Most of
    you are acquainted with Manilius; he had never from the time he was a child, had any thoughts of
    honour, or of the pursuit of virtue, or even of the advantage of a good character; but from
    having been a wanton and profligate buffoon, he had, in the dissensions of the state, arrived
    through the suffrages of the people at that office, to the seat of which he had often been
    conducted by the reproaches of the bystanders. Accordingly he arranges the business with
    Oppianicus; he receives a bribe from him; he abandons the cause after it was commended, and when
    it was fully proved. And in this trial of Oppianicus the crime committed on Asinius was proved
    by many witnesses, and also by the information of Avilius; in which, it was notorious that
    Oppianicus's name was mentioned first among the agents; and yet you say that he was an
    unfortunate and an innocent man, convicted by a corrupt tribunal. </p></div>
    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What more? Did not your father, O Oppianicus, beyond all question, murder your grandmother
    Dinea, whose heir you are? who, when he had brought to her his own physician, a well-tried man
    and often victorious, (by whose means indeed he had slain many of his enemies,) exclaimed that
    she positively would not be attended by that man, through whose attention she had lost all her
    friends. Then immediately he goes to a man of <placeName key="perseus,Ancona">Ancona</placeName>, Lucius Clodius, a travelling quack, who had come by accident at that time
    to <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, and arranges with him for four hundred
    sesterces, as was shown at the time by his account-books. Lucius Clodius, being a man in a
    hurry, as he had many more market towns to visit, did the business off-hand, as soon as he was
    introduced; he took the woman off with the first draught he gave her, and did not stay at
     <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> a moment afterwards. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p> When this Dinea was making her will, Oppianicus, who was her son-in-law,
    having taken the papers, effaced the legacies she bequeathed in it with his finger; and as he
    had done this in many places, after her death, being afraid of being detected by all those
    erasures, he had the will copied over again, and had it signed and sealed with forged seals. I
    pass over many things on purpose. And indeed I fear lest I may appear to have said too much as
    it is. But you must suppose that he has been consistent with himself in every other transaction
    of his life. All the senators <note anchored="true">The term in the original is <foreign xml:lang="lat">decuriones</foreign>. In the colonies “the name of the senate was <foreign xml:lang="lat">ordo decurionum</foreign>, in later times simply <foreign xml:lang="lat">ordo</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="lat">curia</foreign>, the members of it were <foreign xml:lang="lat">decuriones</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="lat">curiales</foreign>. Thus in the
     later ages, <foreign xml:lang="lat">curia</foreign> is opposed to <foreign xml:lang="lat">senatus</foreign>, the former being the senate of a colony, and the latter the senate of
      <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 259. v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Colonia</foreign>.</note> of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> decided that he had tampered with the public registers of the censors of
    that city. No one would have any account with him; no one would transact any business with him.
    Of all the connections and relations that he had, no one ever left him guardian to his children.
    No one thought him fit to call on, or to meet in the street, or to talk to, or to dine with. All men shunned him with contempt and hatred,—all men avoided him as some inhuman and mischievous beast or pestilence.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus"><p>Still, audacious, infamous,
    guilty as he was, Habitus, O judges, would never have accused him, if he had been able to avoid
    doing so without danger to his own life. Oppianicus was his enemy; still he was his step-father:
    his mother was cruel to him and hated him; still she was his mother. Lastly, no one was ever so
    disinclined to prosecutions as Cluentius was by nature, by disposition, and by the constant
    habits of his life. But as he had this alternative set before him, either to accuse hint, as he
    was bound to do by justice and piety, or else to be miserably and wickedly murdered himself, he
    preferred accusing him any way he could, to dying in that miserable manner. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>And that you may have this thoroughly proved to you, I will relate to you the crime of
    Oppianicus, as it was clearly detected and proved, from which you will see both things, both
    that my client could not avoid prosecuting him, and that he could not possibly escape being
    convicted. <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>There were some officers at <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> called
    Martiales, the public ministers of Mars, and consecrated to that god by the old institutions and
    religious ceremonies of the people of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>. And
    as there was a great number of them, and as, just as there were many slaves of Venus in
     <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, these also at <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName> were reckoned part of the household of Mars, on a sudden Oppianicus began
    to urge on their behalf, that they were all free men, and Roman citizens. The senators of
    Larinum and all the citizens of that municipality were very indignant at this. Accordingly they
    requested Habitus to undertake the cause and to maintain the public rights of the city. Habitus,
    although he had entirely retired from public life, still, out of regard to the place and the
    antiquity of his family, and because he thought that he was born not for his own advantage only,
    but also for that of his fellow-citizens, and of his other friends, he was unwilling to refuse
    the eager importunity of all the Larinatians. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p> Having
    undertaken the business, when the cause had been transferred to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, great contentions arose every day between Habitus and Oppianicus from the
    zeal of each for the side which he espoused. Oppianicus himself was a man of a bitter and savage
    disposition; and Habitus's own mother, being hostile to and furious against her son, inflamed
    his insane hatred. But they thought it exceedingly desirable for them to get rid of him, and to
    disconnect him from the cause of the Martiales. There was also another more influential reason
    which had great weight with Oppianicus, being a most avaricious and audacious man. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p> For, up to the time of that trial, Habitus had never made any will. For
    he could not make up his mind to bequeath anything to such a mother as his, nor, on the other
    hand, to leave his parent's name entirely out of his will. And as Oppianicus was aware of that,
    for it was no secret, he plainly saw, that, if Habitus were dead, all his property would come to
    his mother; and she might afterwards, when she had become richer, and had lost her son, be put
    out of the way by him, with more profit, and with less danger. So now see in what manner he,
    being urged on by these desires, endeavoured to take off Habitus by poison. </p></div>
    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>There were two twin brothers of the municipality of Aletrinum, by name Caius and
      <persName><surname>Lucius</surname></persName> Fabricius, men very like one another in
    appearance and disposition, but very unlike the rest of their fellow-citizens; among whom what
    uniform respectability of character, and what consistent and moderate habits of life prevail,
    there is not one of you, I imagine, who is ignorant. Oppianicus was always exceedingly intimate
    with these Fabricii. You are all pretty well aware what great power in causing friendship a
    similarity of pursuits and disposition has. As these two men lived in such a way as to think no
    gain discreditable; as every sort of fraud, and treachery, and cheating of young men was
    practiced by them; as they were notorious for every sort of vice and dishonesty, Oppianicus, as
    I have said, had cultivated their intimacy for many years. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p>
    And accordingly he now resolved to prepare destruction for Habitus by the agency of Caius
    Fabricius, for Lucius had died. Habitus was at that time in delicate health; and he was
    employing a physician of no great reputation, but a man of tried skill and honesty, by name
    Cleophantus, whose slave, Diogenes, Fabricius began to tamper with, and to induce by promises
    and bribes to give poison to Habitus. The slave, being a cunning fellow, but, as the affair
    proved, a virtuous and upright man, did not refuse to listen to Fabricius' discourse; he
    reported the matter to his master, and Cleophantus had a conference with Habitus. Habitus
    immediately communicated the business to Marcus Bebrius, a senator, his most intimate friend;
    and I imagine you all recollect what a loyal, and prudent, and worthy man he was. His advice was
    that Habitus should buy Diogenes of Cleophantus, in order that the matter might be more easily
    proved by his information, or else be discovered to be false. Not to make a long story of it,
    Diogenes is bought in a few days, (when many virtuous men had secretly been made aware of it,)
    the poison, and the money sealed up, which was given for that purpose, is seized in the hands of
    Scamander, a freedman of the Fabricii. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p> O ye immortal gods!
    will any one, when he has heard all these facts, say that Oppianicus was falsely convicted?
     <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Who was ever more audacious? who was ever more guilty? who was ever brought before a court
    more manifestly detected in his guilt? What genius, what eloquence could there be, what plea in
    defence could possibly be devised, which could stand against this single accusation? And at the
    same time, who is there that can doubt that, in such a case as this so clearly detected and
    proved, Cluentius was forced either to die himself, or to undertake the prosecution? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>I think, O judges, that it is proved plainly enough, that Oppianicus was prosecuted on such
    accusations that it was absolutely impossible for him to be honestly acquitted. Now I will show
    you that he was brought before the courts as a criminal, in such a way that he came before them
    already condemned, as there had been more than one or even two previous investigations of his
    case. For Cluentius, O judges, in the first instance, accused that man in whose hands he had
    seized the poison. That was Scamander, the freedman of the Fabricii. <placeName key="tgn,2162655">The Bench</placeName> was honest. There was no suspicion of the judges having
    been bribed. A plain case, a well-proved fact, an undeniable charge was brought before the
    court. So then this Fabricius, the man whom I have mentioned already seeing that, if his
    freedman were condemned, he himself would be in danger, because he knew that I lived in the
    neighbourhood of Aletrinum, and was very intimate with many of the citizens of that place,
    brought a number of them to me: who, although they had that opinion of the man which they could
    not help having, still, because he was of the same municipality as themselves, thought it
    concerned their dignity to defend him by what means they could; and they begged of me that I
    would do so, and that I would undertake the cause of Scamander; and on his cause all the safety
    of his master depended. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus"><p> I, as I was unable to refuse anything
    to men who were so respectable, and so much attached to me, —and as I was not aware that the
    accusation was one involving crimes of such enormity and so undeniably proved—as indeed they
    too, who were then recommending the cause to me, were not aware either,—promised to do all that
    they asked of me. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The cause began to be pleaded; Scamander the defendant was cited before the court. Publius
    Canutius was the counsel for the prosecution, a man of the greatest ability, and a very
    accomplished speaker; and he accused Scamander in plain words, saying “that the poison had been
    discovered on him.” All the force of his accusation was directed against Oppianicus. The cause
    of his designs against Cluentius was revealed; his intimacy with the Fabricii was mentioned; the
    way of life and audacity of the man was revealed; in short, the whole accusation was stated with
    great firmness and with varied eloquence, and at last was summed up by the proved discovery of
    the poison. Then I rose to reply, </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus"><p> with what anxiety, O ye
    immortal gods! with what solicitude of mind! with what fear! Indeed, I am always very nervous
    when I begin to speak. As often as I rise to speak, so often do I think that I am myself on my
    trial, not only as to my ability, but also as to my virtue and as to the discharge of my duty;
    lest I should either seem to have undertaken what I am incapable of performing, which is an
    impudent act, or not to perform it as well as I can, which is either a perfidious action or a
    careless one. But that time I was so agitated, that I was afraid of everything. I was afraid, if
    I said nothing, of being thought utterly devoid of eloquence, and, if I said much in such a
    case, of being considered the most shameless of men. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I recollected myself after a time, and adopted this resolution, that I must needs act boldly;
    that the age which I was of at that time generally had much allowance made for it, even if I
    were to stand by men in danger, though their cause had but little justice in it. And so I acted.
    I strove and contended by every possible means, I had recourse to every possible expedient, to
    every imaginable excuse in the case, which I could think of; so as, at all events, (though I am
    almost ashamed to say it,) no one could think that the cause had been left without an advocate.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p> But, whatever excuse I tried to put forth, the prosecutor
    immediately wrested out of my hands. If I asked what enmity there was between Scamander and
    Habitus, he admitted that there was none. But he said that Oppianicus, whose agent he had been,
    had always been and still was most hostile to Habitus. If again I urged that no advantage would
    accrue to Scamander by the death of Habitus; he admitted that, but he said that all the property
    of Habitus would come to the wife of Oppianicus, a man who had had plenty of practice in killing
    his wives. When I employed this argument in the defence, which has always been considered a most
    honourable one to use in the causes of freedmen, that Scamander was highly esteemed by his
    patron; he admitted that, but asked, Who had any opinion of that patron himself? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p> When I urged at some length the argument, that plot might have been
    laid against Scamander by Diogenes, and that it might have been arranged between them on some
    other account that Diogenes should bring him medicine, not poison that this might happen to any
    one; he asked why he came into such a place as that, into so secret a place, why he came by
    himself, why he came with a sum of money sealed up. And lastly, at this point, our cause was
    weighed down by witnesses, most honourable men. Marcus Bebrius said that Diogenes had been
    bought by his advice, and that he was present when Scamander was seized with the poison and the
    money in his possession. Publius Quintilius Varus a man of the most scrupulous honour, and of
    the greatest authority, said that Cleophantus had conversed with him about the plots which were
    being laid against Habitus, and about the tampering with Diogenes, while the matter was fresh.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus"><p> And all through that trial, though we appeared to be
    defending Scamander, he was the defendant only in name, but in reality, it was Oppianicus who
    was in peril, and who was the object of the whole prosecution. Nor, indeed, was there any doubt
    about it, nor could he disguise that that was the case. He was constantly present in court,
    constantly interfering in the case; he was exerting all his zeal and all his influence. And
    lastly, which was of great injury to our cause, he was sitting in that very place as if he were
    the defendant. The eyes of all the judges were directed, not towards Scamander, but towards
    Oppianicus; his fear, his agitation, his countenance betraying suspense and uncertainty, his
    constant change of colour, made all those things, which were previously very suspicious,
    palpable and evident. </p></div>
    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>When the judges were about to come to their decision, Caius Junius, the president, asked the
    defendant, according to the provisions of the <placeName key="tgn,2257061">Cornelian</placeName>
    law which then existed, whether he wished the decision to be come to in his case secretly or
    openly. He replied by the advice of Oppianicus, because he said that
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> was an intimate friend of Habitus, that he
    wished the decision to be come to secretly. The judges deliberate. Scamander on the first trial
    was convicted by every vote except one, which Stalenus said was his. Who in the whole city was
    there at that time, who when Scamander was condemned, did not think that sentence had been
    passed on Oppianicus? What point was decided by that conviction except that that poison had been
    procured for the purpose of being given to Habitus? However, what suspicion of the very
    slightest nature attached, or could attach to Scamander, so that he should be thought to have
    desired of his own accord to kill Habitus? 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And, now that this trial had taken place, now that
    Oppianicus was convicted in fact, and in the general opinion of every one, though he was not yet
    condemned by any sentence having been legally passed upon him, still Habitus did not at once
    proceed criminally against Oppianicus. He wished to know whether the judges were severe against
    those men only whom they had ascertained to have poison in their own possession, or whether they
    judged the intention and complicity of others in such crimes worthy of the same punishment.
    Therefore, he immediately proceeded against Caius Fabricius, who, on account of his intimacy
    with Oppianicus, he thought must have been privy to that crime; and, on account of the
    connection of the two causes, he obtained leave to have that cause taken first. Then this
    Fabricius not only did not bring to me my neighbours and friends the citizens of Aletrinum, but
    he was not able himself any longer to employ them as men eager in his defence, or as witnesses
    to his character. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus"><p> For they and I thought it suitable to our
    humanity to uphold the cause of a man not entirely a stranger to us, while it was undecided,
    though suspicious; but to endeavour to upset the decision which had been come to, we should have
    thought a deed of great impudence. Accordingly he, being compelled by his desolate condition and
    necessity, fled for aid to the brothers Cepasii, industrious men, and of such a disposition as
    to think it an honour and a kindness to have any opportunity of speaking afforded them.
     <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Now this is a very shameful thing, that in diseases of the body, the more serious the
    complaint is, the more carefully is a physician of great eminence and skill sought for; but in
    capital trials, the worse the case is, the more obscure and unprincipled is the practitioner to
    whom men have recourse.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus"><p>
    The defendant is brought before the court; the cause is pleaded;
    Canutius says but little in support of the accusation, it being a case, in fact, already
    decided.
    The elder Cepasius begins to reply, in a long
    exordium, tracing the facts a long way back. At first his speech is listened to with attention.
    Oppianicus began to recover his spirits, having been before downcast and dejected. Fabricius
    himself was delighted. He was not aware that the attention of the judges was awakened, not by
    the eloquence of the man, but by the impudence of the defence. After he began to discuss the
    immediate facts of the case, he himself aggravated considerably the unfavourable circumstances
    that already existed. Although he pleaded with great diligence, yet at times he seemed not to be
    defending the man, but only quibbling with the accusation. And while he was thinking that he was
    speaking with great art, and when he had made up this form of words with his utmost skill,
    “Look, O judges, at the fortunes of the men, look at the uncertainty and variety of the events
    that have befallen them, look at the old age of Fabricius;”—when he had frequently repeated this
    “Look,” for the sake of adorning his speech, he himself did look, but Caius Fabricius had slunk
    away from his seat with his head down. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus"><p> On this the judges
    began to laugh; the counsel began to get in a rage, and to be very indignant that his cause was
    taken out of his mouth, and that he could not go on saying “Look, O judges,” from that place;
    nor was anything nearer happening, than his pursuing him and seizing him by the throat, and
    bringing him back to his seat, in order that he might be able to finish his summing up. And so
    Fabricius was condemned, in the first place by his own judgment, which is the severest
    condemnation of all, and in the second place by the authority of the law, and by the sentences
    of the judges. <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Why, now, need we say any more of this cause of Oppianicus? He was brought as a defendant
    before those very judges by whom he had already been condemned in ten previous examinations. By
    the same judges, who, by the condemnation of Fabricius, had in reality passed sentence on
    Oppianicus, his trial was appointed to come on first. He was accused of the gravest crimes, both
    of those which have already been briefly mentioned by me, and of many others besides, all of
    which I now pass over. He was accused before those men who had already condemned both Scamander
    the agent of Oppianicus, and Fabricius his accomplice in crime. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus"><p> Which, O ye immortal gods! is most to be wondered at, that he was condemned, or that he dared
    to make any reply? For what could those judges do? If they had condemned the Fabricii when
    innocent, still in the case of Oppianicus they ought to have been consistent with themselves,
    and to have made their present decision harmonize with their previous ones. Could they
    themselves of their own accord rescind their own judgments, when other men, when giving
    judgment, are accustomed most especially to take care that their decisions be not at variance
    with those of other judges? And could those who had condemned the freedman of Fabricius, because
    he had been an agent in the crime, and his patron, because he had been privy to it, acquit the
    principal and original contriver of the whole wickedness? Could those who, without any previous
    examination, had condemned the other men from what appeared in the cause itself, acquit this man
    whom they knew to have been already convicted twice over? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus"><p>
    Then indeed those decisions of the senatorial body, branded with no imaginary odium, but with
    real and conspicuous infamy, covered with disgrace and ignominy, would have left no room for any
    defence of them. For what answer could these judges make if any one asked of them, “You have
    condemned Scamander; of what crime? Because, forsooth, he attempted to murder Habitus by poison,
    by the agency of the slave of the doctor. What was Scamander to gain by the death of Habitus?
    Nothing; but he was the agent of Oppianicus. You have condemned Caius Fabricius; why so?
    Because, as he himself was exceedingly intimate with Oppianicus, and as his freedman had been
    detected in the very act, it was not proved that he was entirely ignorant of his design.” If,
    then, they had acquitted Oppianicus himself, after he had been twice condemned by their own
    decisions, who could have endured such infamy on the part of the tribunals, such inconsistency
    in judicial decisions, and such caprice on the part of the judges? 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But if you now clearly see this, which has been long ago
    proved by the whole of my speech, that the defendant must inevitably be condemned by that
    decision, especially when brought before the same judges who had made two previous
    investigations into the matter, you must at the same time see this, that the accuser could have
    had no imaginable reason for wishing to bribe the bench of judges. <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For I ask you, O Titus Altius, leaving out of the question all other arguments, whether you
    think that the Fabricii who were condemned were innocent? whether you say that those decisions
    also were corruptly procured by bribes? though in one of those decisions one of the defendants
    was acquitted by Stalenus alone; in the other, the defendant, of his own accord, condemned
    himself. Come, now, if they were guilty, of what crime were they guilty? Was there any crime
    imputed to them except the seeking for poison with which to murder Habitus? Was there any other
    point mooted at those trials, except these plots which were laid against Habitus by Oppianicus,
    through the instrumentality of the Fabricii? Nothing else, you will find; I say, O judges,
    nothing else. It is fresh in people's memories There are public records of the trial. Correct me
    if I am speaking falsely. Read the statements of the witnesses. Tell me, in those trials, what
    was objected to them, I will not say as an accusation, but even as a reproach, except this
    poison of Oppianicus. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus"><p> Many reasons can be alleged why it was
    necessary that this decision should be given; but I will meet your expectation half-way, O
    judges. For although I am listened to by you in such a way, that I am persuaded no one was ever
    listened to more kindly or more attentively, still your silent expectation has been for some
    time calling me in another direction, and seeming to chide me thus:—“What then? Do you deny that
    that sentence was procured by corruption?” I do not deny that, but I say that the corruption was
    not practiced by my client. By whom, then, was it practiced? I think, in the first place, if it
    had been uncertain what was likely to be the result of that trial, that still it would have been
    more probable that he would have recourse to corruption, who was afraid of being himself
    convicted, than he who was only afraid of another man being acquitted. In the second place, as
    it was doubtful to no one what decision must inevitably be given, that he would employ such
    means, who for any reason distrusted his case, rather than he who had every possible reason to
    feel confidence in his. Lastly, that at all events, he who had twice failed before those judges
    must have been the corrupter, rather than he who had twice established his case to their
    satisfaction. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus"><p> One thing is quite certain. No one will be so
    unjust to Cluentius, as not to grant to me, if it be proved that that tribunal was bribed, that
    it was bribed either by Habitus or by Oppianicus. If I prove that it was not bribed by Habitus,
    I prove that it was by Oppianicus,—I clear Habitus. Wherefore, although I have already
    established plainly enough that the one had no reason whatever for having recourse to bribery,
    (and from this alone it follows that the bribery must have been committed by Oppianicus,) still
    you shall have separate proofs of this particular point. <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And I will adduce those facts as arguments which, however, are very weighty ones—namely, that
    he was the briber, who was in danger,—that he was the briber, who was afraid,—that he was the
    briber, who had no hope of safety by any other means; he who was always a man of extraordinary
    audacity. There are many such arguments. But when I have a case which is not doubtful, bull open
    and evident, the enumeration of every separate argument is superfluous. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus"><p> I say that Statius Albius gave Caius Attius Stalenus the judge a large sum of
    money to influence his decision. Does any one deny it? I appeal to you, O Oppianicus; to you, O
    Titus Attius; the one of whom deplores that conviction with his eloquence, the other with silent
    piety. Dare to deny it, if you can, that money was given by Oppianicus to Stalenus the judge.
    Deny it—deny it, I say, where you stand. Why are you silent? But you cannot deny it, for you
    sought to recover what had been paid. You have admitted it,—you have recovered it. With what
    face now do you dare to mention a decision given through corruption, when you confess that money
    was given by the opposite side to the judge before trial, and recovered from him after the
    trial? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus"><p> How, then, were all these things managed? I will go
    back a little way, O judges, and I will explain everything which has lain hid in long obscurity,
    so that you shall appear almost to see it with your eyes. I entreat you, as you have listened to
    me attentively up to this time, so to listen to what is to come. In truth, nothing shall be said
    by me which shall not seem to be worthy of this assembly and this silence which is maintained in
    the court,—worthy of your attention and of your ears. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>For when first Oppianicus began to suspect, from the fact of a prosecution having been
    instituted against Scamander, what danger he himself was threatened with, he immediately set
    himself to work to become intimate with a man, needy, audacious, a practiced agent in the
    corruption of tribunals but at that time himself a judge, Stalenus. And first of all, when
    Scamander was the defendant, he made such an impression on him by his gifts, and presents, and
    liberality; that he showed himself a more eager assistant than the credit of a judge could
    stand. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus"><p> But afterwards, when Scamander had been acquitted by
    the single vote of Stalenus, but when the patron of Scamander had not been acquitted even by his
    own judgment, he found that he must provide for his safety by stronger measures. Then he began
    to request of Stalenus as from a man most acute in contriving, most impudent in daring, and most
    intrepid in executing, (for all these qualities he had in a great degree, and he pretended to
    have them in a still greater degree,) assistance to save his credit and his fortunes. <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You are not ignorant, O judges, that even beasts, when warned by hunger, usually return to
    that place where they have once been fed. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus"><p> That Stalenus, two
    years before, when he had undertaken the cause of the property of Safinius at Atella, had said
    that he would bribe the tribunal with six hundred thousand sesterces. But when he had received
    this sum from the youth, he embezzled it, and when the trial was over, he did not restore it
    either to Safinius or to the purchasers of the property. But when he had spent all that money,
    and had nothing left, not only nothing to gratify his desires, but nothing even to supply his
    necessities, he made up his mind that he must return to the same system of plunder and judicial
    embezzlement. And, therefore, as he saw that Oppianicus was in a desperate way, and overwhelmed
    by two previous investigations adverse to him, he raised him up from his depression with his
    promises, and bade him not despair of safety. Oppianicus
    began to entreat the man to show him some method of corrupting the tribunal.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus"><p>
    But he, as was afterwards heard from Oppianicus himself, said that there was no one in the city except himself
    who could do this. But at first he began to make objections, because he said that he was a
    candidate for the aedileship with men of the highest rank, and that he was afraid of incurring
    unpopularity and of giving offence. Afterwards, being prevailed on, he required at first a large
    sum of money. At last, he came down to what could be managed, and desired six hundred and forty
    thousand sesterces to be sent to his house. And as soon as this money was brought to him, that
    most worthless man immediately began to form and adopt the following idea,—that nothing could be
    more advantageous for his interests than for Oppianicus to be condemned; because, if he were
    acquitted, he must either distribute the money among the judges, or else restore it to him: but
    if he were condemned, there would be no one to reclaim it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus"><p>
    Therefore, he contrives a singular plan. And you will the more easily, O judges, believe the
    things which are said by us, if you will direct your minds back a considerable space, so as to
    recollect the way of life and disposition of Caius Stalenus. For according to the opinion that
    is formed of a man's habits do people conjecture what has or has not been done by him.
     <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>As he was a man needy, expensive, audacious, cunning, perfidious, and as he saw so vast a sum
    of money laid up in his house, a most miserable and unfurnished receptacle for it, he began to
    revolve in his mind every sort of cunning and fraud. “Must I give it to the judges? In that
    case, what shall I get myself, except danger and infamy? Can I contrive no means by which
    Oppianicus must be condemned? Why not? There is nothing in the world that cannot be managed
    somehow. If any chance delivers him from danger, must I not return the money? Let us, then,
    drive him on headlong, and crush him in utter ruin.” </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus"><p> He
    adopts this plan,—he promises some of the most insignificant of the judges some money; then he
    keeps it back, hoping by this means (as he thought that the respectable men would, of their own
    accord, judge with impartiality) to make those who were less esteemed furious against Oppianicus
    on account of their disappointment. Therefore, as he had always been a blundering and a perverse
    fellow, he begins with Bulbus, and finding him sulky and yawning because he had got nothing for
    a long time, he gives him a gentle spur. “What will you do,” says he, “will you help me, O
    Bulbus, so that we need not serve the republic for nothing?” But he, as soon as he heard
    this—“For nothing,” said he, “I will follow whenever you like. But what have you got?” Then he
    promises him forty thousand sesterces if Oppianicus is acquitted. And he begs him to summon the
    rest of those with whom he is accustomed to converse, and he, the contriver of the whole
    business, adds Gutta <note anchored="true">This is quite untranslatable; it is a set of puns.
     Gutta is the name of one judge, Bulbus of another; but <foreign xml:lang="lat">gutta</foreign>
     also means a drop, and <foreign xml:lang="lat">bulbus</foreign> means an onion. He sprinkles a
     drop on this onion, or he pours water on the onion to boil it.</note> to Bulbus. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, he did not seem at all bitter after the taste he had had of
    his discourse. One or two days passed, when the matter appeared somewhat doubtful. He wanted the
    agent and some security for the money. Then Bulbus addresses the man with a cheerful
    countenance, as caressingly as he can “What will you do,” says he, “O Paetus?” (For Stalenus had
    chosen this surname for himself from the images of the Aelii, lest if he called himself Ligur,
    he should seem to be using the name of his nation rather than that of his family.) “Men are
    asking me where the money is about which you talked to me.” On this that most manifest rogue,
    fed on gains acquired by tampering with the courts of justice, as he had now all his hopes and
    all his heart set upon that sum of money which he had got in his house, begins to frown.
    (Recollect his face, and the expression that you have seen him put on.) He complains that he has
    been thrown out by Oppianicus; and he, a man wholly made up of fraud and lies, and who had even
    improved those vices which he had by nature, by careful study, and by a regular sort of system
    of wickedness, declares positively that he has been cheated by Oppianicus; and he adds this
    assertion,—that he will be condemned by the vote which in his case every one was to give openly.
     </p></div>
    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The report had reached the bench, that there was mention made of corruption being practiced
    among the judges;—the matter had not been kept as secret as it ought to have been, and yet was
    not so thoroughly detected as it was desirable that it should be for the sake of the republic.
    While the matter was so obscure, and every one in such doubt, on a sudden Canutius, a very
    clever man, and who had got some suspicion that Stalenus had been tampered with, but who thought
    that the business was not definitively settled, determined to set sentence pronounced. The
    judges said that they were willing. And at that time Oppianicus himself was in no great alarm.
    He thought that the whole business had been settled by Stalenus. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74" resp="perseus"><p> The judges who were to deliberate on the case were thirty-two in number: an
    acquittal would be obtained by the votes of sixteen of them. Forty thousand sesterces given to
    each judge ought to make up that number of votes, and then the vote of Stalenus himself, who
    would be induced by the hope of a greater reward still, would crown the whole, making the
    seventeenth. And it happened by chance, because the matter was concluded in this way on a
    sudden, that Stalenus himself was not present. He was acting as counsel for the defence in some
    cause or other before a judge. Habitus did not mind that, nor did Canutius. But Oppianicus and
    his patron Lucius Quinctius were not so well pleased; and as Lucius Quinctius was at that time a
    tribune of the people, he reproached Caius Junius the judge most bitterly, and insisted upon it
    that they should not deliberate on their decision without the presence of Stalenus, and as they
    appeared to be purposely rather careless in communicating with him on the subject by means of
    the lictors, he himself went out of the criminal court into the civil court, where Stalenus was
    engaged, and, as he had the power to do, adjourned that court, and himself brought Stalenus back
    to the bench. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75" resp="perseus"><p> The judges rise to give decisions, when
    Oppianicus said, as he had at that time a right to do, that he wished the votes to be given
    openly; his object being that Stalenus might know what was to be paid to each judge. There were
    different kinds of judges, a few were bribed, but all were unfavorable. As men who are
    accustomed to receive bribes in the <placeName key="tgn,7014001">Campus Martius</placeName> are
    usually exceedingly hostile to those candidates whose money they think is kept back, so the
    judges of the same sort were then very indignant against this defendant. The others considered
    him very guilty, but they waited for the votes of those who they thought had been bribed, that
    by seeing their votes they might judge who it was that they had been bribed by. <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Behold now—the lots were drawn with such a result that Bulbus, Stalenus, and Gutta were the
    first who were, to deliver their opinions. There was the greatest anxiety on the part of every
    one to see what vote would be given by these worthless and corrupt judges. And they all condemn
    him without the slightest hesitation. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76" resp="perseus"><p> On this, great scruples
    arose in men's minds, and some doubt as to what had really been done. Then some of the judges,
    wise men, trained in the old-fashioned principles of the ancient tribunals, as they could: not
    acquit a most guilty man, and yet, as they did not like at once to condemn a man, in whose case
    there appeared reason to suspect that bribery had been employed against him, before they were
    able to ascertain the truth of this suspicion, gave as their decision, “Not proven.” But some
    severe men, who made up their minds that regard ought to be had to the intention with which a
    thing was done by any one, although they believed that others had only given a correct decision
    through the influence of bribery, nevertheless thought that it behoved them to decide
    consistently with their previous decisions. Accordingly, they condemned him. There were five in
    all, who, whether they did so out of ignorance, or out of pity, or from being influenced by some
    secret suspicion, or by some latent ambition, acquitted that innocent Oppianicus of yours
    altogether. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>After Oppianicus had been condemned, immediately Lucius Quinctius, an excessive seeker after
    popularity, who was accustomed to catch at every wind of report, and at every word uttered in
    the assemblies, thought that he had an opportunity of rising himself, by exciting odium against
    the senators; because he thought that the decisions of that body were already falling into
    disfavour in the eyes of the people. One or two assemblies are held, very violent and stormy: a
    tribune of the people kept loudly asserting that the judges had taken money to condemn an
    innocent prisoner: he kept saying, that the fortunes of all men were at stake; that there were
    no courts of justice; that no one could be safe who had a wealthy enemy. Men ignorant of the
    whole business, who had never even seen Oppianicus, and who thought that a most virtuous
    citizen, that a most modest man had been crushed by money, being exasperated by this suspicion,
    began to demand that the whole matter should be brought forward and inquired into, and in fact,
    to require an investigation of the whole business; and at that very time Stalenus, having been
    sent for by Oppianicus, came by night to the house of Titus Annius, a most honourable man, and a
    most intimate friend of my own. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78" resp="perseus"><p> By this time the whole
    business is known to every one;—what Oppianicus said to him about the money; how he said that he
    would restore the money; how respectable men heard the whole of their conversation, having been
    placed in a secret place with that view; how the whole matter was laid open, and mentioned
    publicly in the forum, and how all the money was extorted from and compelled to be restored by
    Stalenus. <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The character of this Stalenus, already known to and thoroughly ascertained by the people, was
    such as to make no suspicion unnatural; still, those who were present in the assembly did not
    understand that the money which he had promised to pay on behalf of the defendant, had been kept
    back by him.—For this they were not told. They were aware that reports of bribery had been at
    work in the court of justice; they heard that a defendant had been condemned who was innocent;
    they saw that he had been condemned by Stalenus's vote. They judged, because they knew the man
    that it had not been done for nothing. A similar suspicion existed with respect to Bulbus, and
    Gutta, and some others. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, I confess, (for I may now
    make the confession with impunity, especially in this place,) that not only the habits of life
    of Oppianicus, but that even his name was unknown to the people before that trial. Moreover
    that, as it did seem a most scandalous thing for an innocent man to have been crushed by the
    influence of money; and as the general profligacy of Stalenus, and the baseness of some others
    of the judges who resembled him, increased this suspicion; and as Lucius Quinctius pleaded his
    cause, a man not only of the greatest influence, but also of exceeding skill in arousing the
    feelings of the multitude; by these circumstances a very great degree of suspicion was excited
    against, and a very great degree of odium attached to that tribunal. And I recollect, that Caius
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> who had presided over that trial, was thrown,
    as it were, into the fresh fire; and that he, a man of aedilitian rank, who was already praetor
    in the universal opinion of all men, was driven out of the forum and even out of the city, not
    by any regular discussion, but by the outcry raised against him by all men. 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And I am not sorry that I am defending the cause of Aulus
    Cluentius at this time rather than at that time. For the cause remains the same, and cannot by
    any means be altered; the violence of the times, and the unpopularity then stirred up, has
    passed away; so that the evil that existed in the time is now no injury to us, the good which
    there was in the cause is still advantageous to us. And, therefore, I perceive now how
    attentively I am listened to, not only by those to whom the judgment and the power of deciding
    belongs, but even by those whose influence is confined to their mere opinion. But if at that
    time I had been speaking, I should not have been listened to: not that the circumstances were
    different; they are exactly the same; but because the time was different—and of that you may
    feel quite sure. <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Who at that time could have dared to say? Oppianicus had been condemned because he was guilty?
    who now ventures to deny it? Who at that time could have ventured to assert that Oppianicus had
    endeavoured to corrupt the bench of judges with money? at the present time who is there who can
    deny it? Who, at that time, would have been suffered to mention that Oppianicus was prosecuted,
    after having been already condemned by two previous investigations? who is there at the present
    time who can attempt to invalidate this statement? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81" resp="perseus"><p> Wherefore,
    all party feeling being now out of the question, for time has removed that, my oration has
    begged you to dismiss it from your minds, and your good faith and justice has discarded it from
    an inquiry into truth; it is there besides in the cause that remains in doubt? 
   <milestone unit="para"/>It is perfectly notorious that bribery was practiced or attempted at that trial. The question
    is, By whom was it practiced; by the prosecutor, or by the defendant? The prosecutor says, “In
    the first place, I was prosecuting him on the most serious charges, so that I had no need of
    bribery; in the second place, I was prosecuting a man who was already condemned, so that he
    could not have been saved even by bribery; and lastly, even if he had been acquitted, my
    position and my fortune would have been uninjured by his acquittal.” What does the defendant
    say, on the other hand? “In the first place, I was alarmed at the very number and atrocity of
    the charges; in the second place, I felt that, after the Fabricii had been condemned on account
    of their being privy to my wickedness, I was condemned myself; lastly, I was in such a condition
    that my whole position and all my fortunes depended entirely on that one trial, from which I was
    in danger.” </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Come now, since the one had many and grave reasons for bribing the judges, and the other had
    none, let us try to trace the course of the money itself. Cluentius has kept his accounts with
    the greatest accuracy; and this system has this in it, that by that means nothing can possibly
    be added to or taken from the income without its being known. It is eight years after that cause
    occupied men's attention that you are now handling, stirring up, and inquiring into everything
    which relates to it, both in his accounts and in the papers of others; and in the meantime you
    find no trace of any money of Cluentius's in the whole business. What then? Can we trace the
    money of Albius by the scent, or can you guide us, so that we may be able to enter into his very
    chamber, and find it there? There are in one place six hundred and forty thousand sesterces;
    they are in the possession of one most audacious man; they are in the possession of a judge.
    What would you have more? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83" resp="perseus"><p> Oh, but Stalenus was not
    commissioned to corrupt the judges by Oppianicus, but by Cluentius. Why, when the judges were
    retiring to deliberate, did Cluentius and Canutius allow him to go away? Why, when they were
    going to give their votes, did they not require the presence of Stalenus the judge, to whom they
    had given the money Oppianicus did not for him; Quinctius did demand his presence. The
    tribunitian power was interposed to prevent a decision being come to without Stalenus. But he
    condemned him. To be sure, for he had given this condemnatory vote as a sort of pledge to Bulbus
    and the rest to prove that he had been cheated by Oppianicus. If, therefore, on one side, there
    is a reason for corrupting the tribunal; on one side, money; on one side, Stalenus; on one side,
    every description of fraud and audacity: and on the other side, modesty, an honourable life, and
    no suspicion of corruption, and no object in corrupting the tribunal; allow, now that the truth
    is made clear and all error dispelled, the discredit of that baseness to adhere to that side to
    which all the other wickednesses are attached; and allow the odium of it to depart at last from
    that man, whom you do not perceive to have ever been connected with any fault. </p></div>
    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Oh, but Oppianicus gave Stalenus money, not to corrupt the judges, but to conciliate their
    favour. Can you, O Attius, can a man endued with your prudence, to say nothing of your knowledge
    of the world, and practice in pleading, say such a thing as this? For they say that he is the
    wisest man; to whom everything which is necessary is sure to occur of his own accord; and that
    he is next best to him, who is guided by the clever experience of another. <note anchored="true">There is an epigram in the Greek anthology from which these sentiments of Cicero seem to be
      taken:—<quote xml:lang="grc">
      <l>ou(=tos me\n pana/ristos, o(\s au)to\s pa/nta noh/sh|, </l>
      <l>e)sqlo\s d' au)= ka)/keinos, o(\s eu)= ei)po/nti pi/qhtai, </l>
      <l>o(/s de/ ke mh/t' au)/to\s noe/h|, mh/t' a)/llou a)kou/wn </l>
      <l>e)n qumw=| ba/llhtai, o(/d' au)=t' a)xrh/ios a)nh/r.</l>
     </quote>
    </note> But in folly it is just the contrary; for he is less foolish to whom no folly occurs
    spontaneously, than he who approves of the folly which occurs to another. That idea of
    conciliating favour Stalenus thought of, while the case was fresh, when he was held by the
    throat as it were; or rather, as people said at the time, he took the hint from Publius
    Cethegus, when he published that fable about conciliation and favour. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="85" resp="perseus"><p> For you can recollect that this was what men said at the time; that Cethegus,
    because he hated the man and because he wished to get rid of such rascality out of the republic,
    and because he saw that he who had confessed that, while a judge, he had secretly and
    irregularly taken money from a defendant, could not possibly get off, had given him treacherous
    advice. If Cethegus behaved dishonestly in this matter, he appears to me to have wished to get
    rid of an adversary; but if the case was such that Stalenus could not possibly deny that he had
    received the money, (and nothing could be more dangerous or more disgraceful than to confess for
    what purpose he had received it,) the advice of Cethegus is not to be blamed. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="86" resp="perseus"><p> But the case of Stalenus then was very different from what your case is now, O
    Attius. He, being pressed by the facts, could not possibly say anything which was not more
    creditable than confessing what had really happened. But I do marvel that you should have now
    brought up again the very same plea which was then hooted out of court and rejected; for how could Cluentius possibly become friends with Oppianicus, when
    he was at enmity with his mother? The names of the defendant and prosecutor were recorded in the
    public documents; the Fabricii had been condemned; Albius could not possibly escape if there
    were any other prosecutor, nor could Cluentius abandon the prosecution without rendering himself
    liable to the imputation of having trumped up a false accusation. </p></div>
    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="87" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Was the money given to procure any collusion? That, too, has a direct reference to corrupting
    the judges. But what was the necessity for employing a judge as an agent in such a business? And
    above all things, what need was there for transacting the whole business through the agency of
    Stalenus, a man perfectly unconnected with either party, —a most sordid and infamous man—rather
    than through the intervention of some respectable person, some common friend or connection of
    both parties? But why need I discuss this matter at length, as if there were any obscurity in
    the business, when the very money which was given to Stalenus, proves by its amount and by its
    sum total, not only how much it was, but for what purpose it was given? I say that it was
    necessary to bribe sixteen judges, in order to procure the acquittal of Oppianicus; I say that
    six hundred and forty thousand sesterces were taken to Stalenus's house. If, as you say, this
    was for the purpose of conciliating good-will, what is the meaning of that addition of forty
    thousand sesterces? but if, as we say, it was in order that forty thousand sesterces might be
    given to each judge, then Archimedes himself could not calculate more accurately. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="88" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But a great many decisions have been come to, tending to prove that the tribunal was corrupted
    by Cluentius. I say, on the other hand, that before this time, that matter has never been
    brought before the court at all on its own merits. The matter has been so very much canvassed,
    and has been so long the subject of discussion, that this is the very first day that a word has
    been said in defence of Cluentius; this is the very first day that truth, relying on these
    judges, he ventured to lift up her voice against the popular feeling. However, what are all
    those numerous decisions? for I have prepared myself to encounter everything, and I am ready to
    show that the decisions which were said to have been come to afterwards, bearing on that
    decision, were, as to some of them, more like an earthquake or a tempest, than an orderly
    judgment or a regular decision; that, as to some of them they had no weight against Habitus at
    all; that some of them even told in his favour; and that some were such that they were never
    called judicial decisions at all, and never even thought so. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="89" resp="perseus"><p>
    Here I, rather for the sake of adhering to the usual custom, than from any fear that you would
    not do so of your own accord, will beg of you to listen to me with attention, while I discuss
    each of these decisions. <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Caius <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>, who presided over that trial, has been
    condemned; add that also, if you please,—he was condemned at the time that he was a criminal
    judge. No relaxation of the prosecution or mitigation of the law was procured by the means of
    any one of the tribunes of the people. At a time that it was contrary to law for him to be taken
    away from the investigation of the case before him to discharge any duty to the republic
    whatever;—at that very time, I say, he was hurried off to the investigation. But to what
    investigation? For the expression of your countenances, O judges, invites me to say freely what
    I had thought I must have suppressed. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="90" resp="perseus"><p> What shall I say? Was
    that then an investigation, or a discussion, or a decision? I will suppose it was. Let him, who
    wishes today to speak on the subject of the people having been excited, say whose wishes were at
    that time complied with; let him say on what account
     <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> gave his decision. Whomsoever you ask, you will
    get this answer;—Because he received money, because he unfairly crushed an innocent man. This is
    the common opinion. But if that were the truth, he ought to have been prosecuted under the same
    law as Habitus is impeached under. But he himself was carrying on an investigation according to
    that law. Quinctius would have waited a few days. But he was unwilling to accuse him as a
    private man, and when the odium of the business had been allayed. You see then that all the hope
    of the accuser was not in the cause itself, but in the time and in the influence of individuals.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="91" resp="perseus"><p> He sought a fine. According to what law? Because he had not
    taken the oath to observe the law: a thing which never yet was brought against any man as a
    crime: and because Caius Verres, the city praetor, a very conscientious and careful man, had not
    the list out of which judges were to be chosen in the place of those who had been rejected, in
    that book which was then produced full of erasures. On all these accounts Caius Junius was
    condemned, O judges, for these trivial and unproved reasons, which had no business to have been
    ever brought before the court at all. And therefore he was defeated, not on the merits of his
    case, but by the time. </p></div>
    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="92" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Do you think that this decision ought to be any hindrance to Cluentius? On what account? If
    Junius had not appointed the judges in the place of those who had been objected to according to
    law—if he had omitted to take the oath to obey the law—does it follow that any decision bearing
    on Cluentius's case was pronounced or implied in his condemnation? “No,” says he; “but he was
    condemned by these laws, because he had committed an offence against another law.” Can those who
    admit this urge also in defence that that was a regular decision? “Therefore,” says he, “the
    praetor was hostile to Junius on this account, because the tribunal was thought to have been
    bribed by his means.” Was then the whole cause changed at this time? Is the case different, is
    the principle of that decision different, is the nature of the whole business different now from
    what it was then? I do not think that of all the things that were done then anything can be
    altered. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="93" resp="perseus"><p> What, then, is the reason why our defence is
    listened to with such silence now, but that all opportunity of defending himself was refused to
    Junius then? Because at that time there was nothing in the cause but envy, mistake, suspicion,
    daily assemblies, seditiously stirred up by appeals to popular feeling. The same tribune of the
    people was the accuser before the assemblies, and the prosecutor in the courts of law. Be came
    into the court of justice not from the, assembly, but bringing the whole assembly with him.
    Those steps of <persName><surname>Aurelius</surname></persName>, <note anchored="true">These
     were steps built in the forum by Marcus Aurelius Cotta, and called by his name.</note> which
    were new at that time, appeared as if they had been built on purpose for a theatre for the
    display of that tribunal. And when the prosecutor had filled them with men in a state of great
    excitement, there was not only no opportunity of speaking in favour of the defendant, but none
    of even rising up to speak. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="94" resp="perseus"><p> It happened lately, before Caius
    Orchinius, my colleague, that the judges refused to sanction a prosecution against Faustus
    Sulla, in a cause concerning some money which remained unpaid. Not because they considered that
    Sulla was an outlaw, or because they thought the cause of the public money insignificant or
    contemptible; but because, when a tribune of the people was the accuser, they did not think that
    there could be a fair trial. What? Shall I compare Sulla with
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>? or this tribune of the people with Quinctius?
    or one time with the other time? Sulla, with his great wealth, his numerous relations,
    connections, friends, and clients; but in the case of
     <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> all these things were small, and insignificant,
    and collected and acquired by his own exertions. The one a tribune of the people, moderate,
    modest, not only not seditious himself, but an enemy to seditious men; the other bitter, fond of
    raking up accusations, a hunter after popularity, and a turbulent man. The present a tranquil
    and a peaceable time; the former time one ruffled with every imaginable storm of ill-will. And
    as all this was the case, still in the case of Faustus those judges decided that a defendant was
    brought before the court on very unfair terms, when his adversary was in possession of the
    greatest power known to the state, which he could avail himself of to add force to his
    accusations. </p></div>
    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="95" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And this principle you, O judges, ought, as your wisdom and humanity prompts and enables you
    to do, to consider over in your mind carefully; and to be thoroughly aware what disaster and
    what danger the tribunitian power can bring upon every one individual among us, especially when
    it is egged on by party spirit, and by assemblies of the people, stirred up in a seditious
    manner. In the very best times, forsooth, when men defended themselves, not by boastings
    addressed to the populace, but by their own worth and innocence, still neither Publius
    Popillius, nor Quintus Metellus, most illustrious and most honourable men, could withstand the
    power of the tribunes; much less at the present time, with such manners as we now have, and such
    magistrates, can we possibly be saved without the aid of your wisdom, and without the relief
    which is afforded by the courts of justice. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="96" resp="perseus"><p> That court of
    justice then, O judges, was not like a court of justice; for in it there was no moderation
    preserved, no regard was had to custom and usage, nor was the cause of the defendant properly
    advocated. It was all violence, and, as I have said before, a sort of earthquake or tempest,—it
    was anything rather than a court of justice, or a legal discussion, or a judicial investigation.
    But if there be any one who thinks that that was a regular proceeding, and who thinks it right
    to adhere to the decision that was then delivered; still he ought to separate this cause from
    that one. For it is said that a great many things were demanded of him either because he had not
    taken the oath to observe the law, or because he had not cast lots for electing judges in the
    room of those to whom objection had been made in a legal manner. But the case of Cluentius can
    in no particular be connected with these, laws, in accordance with which a penalty was sought to
    be recovered from <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="97" resp="perseus"><p> Oh, but Bulbus also was condemned. Add that he was condemned of treason, in
    order that you may understand that this trial has no connection with that one. But this charge
    was brought against him. I confess it; but it was also made evident by the letters of Caius
    Cosconius and by the evidence of many witnesses, that a legion in <placeName key="tgn,7016683">Illyricum</placeName> had been tampered with by him; and that charge was one peculiarly
    belonging to that sort of investigation, and was one which was comprehended under the law of
    treason. But this was an exceedingly great disadvantage to him. That is mere guess work; and if
    we may have recourse to that, take care, I beg you, that my conjecture be not far the more
    accurate of the two. For my opinion is, that Bulbus, because he was a worthless, base, dishonest
    man, and because he came before the court contaminated with many crimes of the deepest dye, was
    on that account the more easily condemned. But you, out of Bulbus's whole case, select that
    which seems to suit your own purpose, in order that you may say that it was that which
    influenced the judges. </p></div>
    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="98" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, this decision in the case of Bulbus ought not to be any greater injury to this
    cause, than those two which were mentioned by the prosecutor in the case of Publius Popillius
    and Titus Gutta, who were prosecuted for corruption,—who were accused by men who had themselves
    been convicted of bribery, and whom I do not imagine to have been restored to their original
    position merely because they had proved that these other men also had taken money for the
    purpose of influencing their decision, or because they proved to the judges that they had
    detected others in the same sort of offence of which they had themselves been guilty; and that,
    therefore, they were entitled to the rewards offered by the law. Therefore, I think that no one
    can doubt that that conviction for bribery can in no possible way be connected with the cause of
    Cluentius and with your decision. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="99" resp="perseus"><p> What! not if Stalenus was
    condemned? I do not say at this present moment, O judges, that which I am not sure ought to be
    said at all, that he was convicted of treason,—I do not read over to you the testimonies of most
    honourable men, which were given against Stalenus by men who were lieutenants, and prefects, and
    military tribunes, under Mamercus Aemilius, that most illustrious man, by whose evidence it was
    made quite plain that it was chiefly through his instrumentality, when he was quaestor, that a
    seditious spirit was stirred up in the army. I do not even read to you that evidence which was
    given concerning these six hundred thousand sesterces, which when he had received on presences
    connected with the trial of Safinius, he retained and embezzled as he did afterwards in the case
    of the trial of Oppianicus.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="100" resp="perseus"><p> I say nothing of all these
    things, and of many others which were stated against Stalenus at that trial. This I do say,—that
    Publius and Lucius Cominius, Roman knights, most honourable and eloquent men, had the same
    dispute with Stalenus then, whom they were accusing, that I now have with Attius. The Cominii
    said the same thing that I say now,—that Stalenus received money from Oppianicus to induce him
    to corrupt the tribunal, and Stalenus said that he had received it to conciliate good-will
    towards him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="101" resp="perseus"><p> This conciliation of good-will was laughed at,
    and so was this assumption of the character of a good man, as in the gilded statues which he
    erected in front of the temple of Juturna, at the bottom of which he had the following
    inscription engraved,—“that the kings had been restored by him to the favour of the people.” All
    his frauds and dishonest tricks were brought under discussion; his whole life, which has been
    spent in such a way as that, was laid open; his domestic poverty, the profits which he made in
    the courts of law, were all brought to light: an interpreter of peace and concord who regulated
    everything by the bribes which he received was not approved of. Therefore, Stalenus was
    condemned at that time, while he urged the same defence as Attius did. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="102" resp="perseus"><p> When the Cominii did the same thing that I have done throughout the whole of
    this cause, people approved of them. Wherefore, if by the condemnation of Stalenus it was
    decided that Oppianicus had desired to corrupt the judges,—that Oppianicus had given one of the
    judges money to purchase the votes of the other judges, (since it has been already settled that
    either Cluentius is guilty of that offence, or else Oppianicus, but that no trace whatever is
    found of any money belonging to Cluentius having been ever given to any judge, while money
    belonging to Oppianicus was taken away, after the trial was over, from a judge,)—can it be
    doubtful that that conviction of Stalenus does not only not make against Cluentius, but is the
    greatest possible confirmation of our cause and of our defence? </p></div>
    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="103" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, I see now that the case respecting the decision of
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> is of this nature, that I think it ought to be
    called an inroad of sedition, an instance of the violence of the multitude, an outrage on the
    part of a tribune, any thing rather than a judicial proceeding. But if any one calls that a
    regular trial, still he must inevitably admit this,—that that penalty which was sought to be
    recovered from <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> cannot by any means be connected
    with the cause of Cluentius. That decision of the tribunal over which
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> presided, was brought about by evidence. The
    cases of Bulbus, of Popillius, and of Gutta, do not make against Cluentius. That of Stalenus is
    actually in favour of Cluentius. Let us now see if there is any other decision which we can
    produce which is favourable to Cluentius. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Was not Caius Fidiculanius Falcula, who had condemned Oppianicus, prosecuted especially
    because—and that was the point which in that trial was the hardest to excuse—he had sat as judge
    a few days after the appointment of a substitute? He was, indeed, prosecuted, and that twice.
    For Lucius Quinctius had brought him into extreme unpopularity by means of daily seditious and
    turbulent assemblies. On one trial a penalty was sought to be recovered from him, as from
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>, because he had sat as judge, not in his own
    decury, nor according to the law. He was prosecuted at a rather more peaceable time than
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>, but under almost the same law, and on very
    nearly the same indictment. But because at the trial shore was no sedition, no violence, and no
    crowd, he was easily acquitted at the first hearing. I do not count this acquittal.<note anchored="true">The passage which follows in the text is given up by Orellius altogether
     corrupt, and is wholly unintelligible as it stands at present. Weiske thinks that several words
     have dropped out.</note><gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="104" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> What was Fidiculanius said to have done? To have received
    from Cluentius four hundred sesterces. Of what rank was he? A senator. He was accused according
    to that law by which an account is properly demanded of a senator in a prosecution for
    peculation, and he was most honourably acquitted. For the cause was pleaded according to the
    custom of our ancestors, without violence, without fear, without danger. Everything was fairly
    stated, and explained, and proved. The judges were taught that not only could a defendant be
    honestly condemned by a man who had not sat as a judge uninterruptedly, but that if that judge
    had known nothing else except what previous investigations it was clear had taken place in the
    case, he ought to have heard nothing else. </p></div>
    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="105" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Then, also, those five judges, who, hunting for the vague rumours of ignorant men, acquitted
    him at the time, were unwilling that their clemency should be extravagantly praised; and if any
    one asked them whether they had sat as judges on Caius Fabricius, they said that they had, if
    they were asked whether he had been accused of any crime except of that poison which was said to
    have been endeavoured to be administered to Habitus, they said no; if, after that, they were
    asked what their decision had been, they said that they had condemned him. For no one acquitted
    him. In the same manner, if any question had been asked about Scamander, they would certainly
    have given the same answer, although he was acquitted by one vote; but at that time no one of
    those men would have liked that one vote to be called his. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="106" resp="perseus"><p>
    Which, then, could more easily give an account of his vote,—he who said that he had been
    consistent with himself and with the previous decision, or he who said that he had been lenient
    to the principal offender, and very severe against his assistants and accomplices? But
    concerning their decision I have no occasion to say anything; for I have no doubt, that such men
    as they, being influenced by some sudden suspicion, avoided the point at issue. On which account
    I find no fault with the mercy of those who acquitted him. I approve of the firmness of those
    men who, in giving their judgment, followed the precedent of the previous decisions of their own
    accord, and not in consequence of the fraudulent trick of Stalenus; but I praise the wisdom of
    those men who said that to their minds it was not proved, who could by no means acquit a man
    whom they knew to be very guilty, and whom they themselves had already condemned twice before,
    but who, as such a disgraceful plan, and as a suspicion of such an atrocious act had been
    suggested to them, preferred condemning him a little later, when the facts were clearly
    ascertained. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="107" resp="perseus"><p> And, that you may not judge them to have been
    exceedingly wise men merely by their actions, but that you may also feel sure, from their very
    names, that what they did was most honestly and wisely done; who can be mentioned superior to
    Publius Octavius Balbus, as to ability more prudent,—in knowledge of law more skillful,—in good
    faith, in religion, in the performance of his duty, more scrupulous or more careful? He did not
    acquit him. Who is a better man than Quintus Considius? who is better acquainted with the
    practice of courts of justice, and with that sense of right which ought always to exist in the
    public courts? who is his superior in virtue, in wisdom, or in authority? Even he did not acquit
    him. It would take me too long to cite the virtue of each separate individual in the same
    manner; and in truth, their good qualities are so will known to every one, that they do not need
    the ornaments of language to set them off. What a man was Marcus Juventius Pedo, a man formed on
    the principles and system of the judges of old! What a man was Lucius Caulius Mergus! and Marcus
    Basilus! and Caius Caudinus! all of whom flourished in the public courts of justice at that time
    when the republic also was flourishing. Of the same body were Lucius Cassius and Cnaeus Heius,
    men of equal integrity and wisdom. And by the vote of none of those men was Oppianicus
    acquitted. And the youngest of all but one, who in ability, and in diligence, and in
    conscientiousness was equal to those men whom I have already mentioned, Publius Saturius,
    delivered the same opinion. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="108" resp="perseus"><p> O, the singular innocence of
    Oppianicus! when in the case in which he was defendant, those who acquitted him are supposed to
    have had some ulterior end,—those who postponed their decision, to have been cautious; but every
    one who condemned him is esteemed virtuous and firm. <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>These things, though Quinctius agitated them, were not proved at that time either in the
    assembly or in a court of justice. For he himself would not allow them to be stated, nor indeed,
    by reason of the excited state of the multitude, could any one stand up to speak. Therefore he
    himself, after he had overthrown <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>, abandoned the
    whole cause. For in a very few days' time he became a private individual, and he perceived too
    that the violence of men's feelings had cooled down. But if at the time that he accused
      <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> he had also chosen to accuse Fidiculanius,
    Fidiculanius would have had no opportunity of making any reply. And at first, indeed, he
    threatened all those judges who had voted against Oppianicus. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="109" resp="perseus"><p> By this time you know the insolence of the man. You know what a tribune-like pride and
    arrogance he has. How great was the animosity which he displayed! O ye immortal gods! how great
    was his pride! how great his ignorance of himself! how preposterous and intolerable was his
    arrogance! when he was indignant even at this, (from which all those proceedings of his took
    their rise,) that Oppianicus was not pardoned at his entreaty and owing to his defence; just as
    if it ought not to have been proof enough that he was deserted by every one, that he had
    recourse to such an advocate as him. For there was at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> a great abundance of advocates, most eloquent and most honourable men, of
    whom certainly any one would have defended a Roman knight, of noble birth in his municipality,
    if he had thought that such a cause could be defended with honour. </p></div>
    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="110" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For, as for Quinctius, indeed, what cause had he ever pleaded before, though he was now nearly
    fifty years old? Who had ever seen him not only in the position of a counsel for the defence,
    but even as a witness to character, or as employed in any <note anchored="true">“The Latin is,
      ‘<foreign xml:lang="lat">non modo in <emph>patroni</emph>, sed in laudatoris, aut
       <emph>advocati</emph>, loco viderat.</foreign>’ In the time of Cicero the <foreign xml:lang="lat">advocatus</foreign> was different from the person who conducted the suit
      (<foreign xml:lang="lat">patronus</foreign>) and made the speech, though in later times this
     person likewise is called <foreign xml:lang="lat">advocatus</foreign>.”—Riddle, Lat. Dict. in
     voc.</note> way in any cause? who, because he had seized on the rostrum which had been for some
    time empty, and the place which had been deserted by the voice of the tribunes ever since the
    arrival of Lucius Sulla, and had recalled the multitude, which had now been for some time unused
    to assemblies, to the likeness of the old custom, was on that account for a short time rather
    popular with a certain set of men. But yet afterwards how hated he became by those very men by
    whose means he had mounted into a higher position!—and very deservedly. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="111" resp="perseus"><p> For just take the trouble to recollect not only his manners and his arrogance,
    but also his countenance, and his dress, and his purple robe reaching down as far as his ankles.
    He, as if it were a thing quite impossible to be borne that he should have been defeated in this
    trial, transferred the case from the court of justice to the public assembly. And do we still
    reiterate our complaints, that new men have not sufficient encouragement in this city? I say,
    that there never was a time or place where they had more; for here, if a man, though born in a
    low rank of life, lives so as to seem able to uphold by his virtue the dignity of nobility, he
    meets with no obstacle to his arriving at that eminence to which his industry and innocence
    conduct him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="112" resp="perseus"><p> But if any one depends on the fact of his being
    meanly born as his chief claim, he often goes greater lengths than if he was a man of the
    highest birth devoted to the same vices. As, in the case of Quinctius, (for I will say nothing
    of the others,) if he had been a man of noble birth, who could have endured him with his pride
    and intolerance? But because he was of the rank of which he was, people put up with it, as if
    they thought that if he had any good quality by nature, it ought to be allowed to save him and
    as if, owing to the meanness of his birth, they thought his pride and arrogance matters to be
    laughed at rather than feared. <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>However, to return to my original subject: What decision did you—you, I say, who mention those
    trials— think ought to have bean come to at the time that Fidiculanius was acquitted? At least you think that the decision was not a corrupt one.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="113" resp="perseus"><p>But he had
    condemned him; but he had not heard the entire case; but he had been greatly and repeatedly
    annoyed at every assembly of the people, by Lucius Quinctius. Then the whole of Quinctius's
    judicial conduct was unjust, deceitful, fraudulent, turbulent, dictated by a wish for
    popularity, seditious. Be it so; Falcula may have been innocent. Well then, some one condemned
    Oppianicus without being paid for it; <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName> did not
    appoint men as judges in the place of the others, to condemn him for a bribe. It is possible
    that there may have been some one who did not sit as judge from the beginning, and who,
    nevertheless, condemned Oppianicus without having been bribed to do so. But if Falcula was
    innocent, I wish to know who was guilty? If he condemned him without being bribed to do so, who
    was bribed? I say that there has been nothing imputed to any one of these men which was not
    imputed to Fidiculanius; I say that there was nothing in the case of Fidiculanius which did not
    also exist in the case of the rest. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="114" resp="perseus"><p> You must either find
    fault with this trial, the prosecution in which appeared to rely on previous decisions, or else,
    if you admit that this was an honest one, you must allow that Oppianicus was condemned without
    money having been paid to procure his condemnation. Although it ought to be proof enough for any
    one, that no one out of so many judges was proceeded against after Falcula had been
    acquitted.—For why do you bring up men convicted of bribery under a different law, the charges
    being well proved, the witnesses being numerous? when, in the first place, these very men ought
    to be accused of peculation rather than of bribery. For if, in trials for bribery, this was an
    hindrance to them, that they were being prosecuted under a different law, at all events it would
    have been a much greater injury to them to be brought before the court according to the law
    properly belonging to this offence. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="115" resp="perseus"><p> In the second place, if
    the weight attached to this accusation was so great, that, under whatever law any one of those
    judges was prosecuted, he must be utterly ruined; then why, when there: are such crowds of
    accusers, and when the reward is so great, were not the others prosecuted too? On this, that
    case is mentioned, (which, however, has no right to be called a trial,) that an action for
    damages was brought against Publius Septimius Scaevola on that account; and what the practice is
    in cases of that sort, as I am speaking before men of the greatest learning, I have no need to
    occupy much time in explaining. For the diligence which is usually displayed in other trials, is
    never exercised after the defendant has been convicted. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="116" resp="perseus"><p> In
    actions for damages, the judges usually, either because they think that a man whom they have
    once convicted is hostile to them, if any mention of a capital charge against him is made, do
    not allow it; or else, because they think that their duties are over when they have given their
    decision respecting the defendant, they attend more carelessly to the other points. Therefore,
    very many men are acquitted of treason, when, if they were condemned, actions would be brought
    to recover damages on charges of peculation. And we see this happen every day,—that when a
    defendant has been convicted of peculation, the judges acquit those men to whom, in fixing the
    damages, it has been settled that the money has come; and when this is the case, the decisions
    are not rescinded, but this principle is laid down, that the assessment of damages is not a
    judicial trial. Scaevola was convicted of other charges, by a great number of witnesses from
     <placeName key="tgn,7010380">Apulia</placeName>. The greatest possible eagerness was shown in
    endeavoring to have that action considered as a capital prosecution. And if it had had the
    weight of a case already decided, he afterwards, according to this identical law, would have
    been prosecuted either by the same enemies, or by others. </p></div>
    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="117" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>That follows, which they call a trial, but which our ancestors never called a trial, and never
    paid any attention to as if it had been a formal judicial decision, the animadversion and
    authority of the censors. But before I begin to speak on that subject, I must say a few words
    about my own duty, in order that it may be clearly seen that I have paid proper attention to
    this danger, and also to all other considerations of duty and friendship. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>For I have a friendship with both those brave men who were the last censors; and with one of
    them, (as most of you are aware,) I have the greatest intimacy, and the closest connection
    cemented by mutual good offices. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="118" resp="perseus"><p> So that, if I am forced to
    say anything of the reasons which they have given for their sentences, I shall say it with these
    feelings, that I shall wish everything that I say considered as having reference not to their
    individual conduct in particular, but to the whole principle of the censorial animadversion. But
    from Lentulus, my intimate friend, who out of regard for his eminent virtue and for the high
    honours which he has received from the Roman people, is named by me to do him honour, I shall
    easily obtain this indulgence, that, as he himself is always accustomed to employ the greatest
    good faith and diligence in matters affecting the safety of his friends, and also the greatest
    vigour of mind and freedom of speech, so, in this instance, he will not be offended with me for
    taking as much freedom my self, as I cannot forbear to take without danger to my client. But,
    everything shall be said by me carefully and deliberately, as indeed it ought to be, so that I
    shall not appear to have betrayed the cause entrusted to my good faith for its defence, nor to
    have injured the dignity of any one, nor to have disregarded any of the claims of friendship.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="119" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/>I see then, O judges, that the censors passed animadversion
    on some of the judges who sat on that trial which <persName><surname>Junius</surname></persName>
    presided over, and added to their sentence that that very trial was the cause of it. Now, first
    I will lay down this general principle, that this city has never been so content with censorial
    animadversions as with judicial decisions. Nor in so notorious a case need I waste time by
    citing instances. I will just adduce this one fact,—that Caius Geta, after he had been expelled
    the senate by Lucius Metellus and Cnaeus Domitius when they were censors, was himself appointed
    censor afterwards; and that he whose morals had met with this reproof from the censors, was
    afterwards appointed to judge of the morals of the whole Roman people, and of those very men who
    had thus punished him. But if that had been thought a final judicial decision, (as other men
    when they have been condemned by a sentence involving infamy are deprived for ever of all honour
    and all dignity, so) a man branded with this ignominy would never have had any subsequent access
    to honour, or any possibility of return to the senate. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="120" resp="perseus"><p> Now,
    if the freedman of Cnaeus Lentulus or of Lucius Gellius should convict any man of theft, he,
    being deprived of all his credit, will never recover any portion of his honourable position in
    the city; but those men, whom Lucius Gellius himself and Cnaeus Lentulus, the two censors, most
    illustrious citizens and most wise men, have animadverted on, and, in their reasons for their
    sentences, have imputed to them theft and peculation, have not only returned to the senate, but
    have been acquitted of those very charges by judicial sentence. <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Our ancestors did not think it fit for any one to be a judge, not only of any one's character,
    but not even of the most insignificant money matter, if he had not been agreed to by both the
    contending parties. Wherefore, in every law in which exception has been made of causes for which
    a magistrate may not be taken, or a judge elected, or another man accused, this cause of
    ignominy is passed over. For their intention was that the power of the censors should strike the
    profligate with terror, but not that it should have power over their lives. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="121" resp="perseus"><p> Therefore, O judges, I will not only prove what you are already aware of, that
    the censorial animadversions, and the reasons given for them too, have often been overturned by
    the votes of the Roman people, but that they have also been upset by the judicial sentences of
    those men who, being on their oaths, were bound to give their decisions with more scrupulousness
    and care. In the first place, O judges, in the case of many defendants, whom the censors in
    their notes accused of having taken money contrary to the laws, they were guided by their own
    conscientious judgment, rather than by the opinion expressed by the censors. In the second
    place, the city praetors, who are bound by their oaths to select only the most virtuous men to
    be judges, have never thought that the fact of a man's having been branded with ignominy by the
    censors was any impediment to their making him a judge. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="122" resp="perseus"><p> And
    lastly, the censors themselves have very often not adhered to the decisions, if you insist on
    their being called decisions, of former censors. And even the censors themselves consider their
    own decisions to be of only so much weight, that one is not afraid to find fault with, or even
    to rescind the sentence of the other; so that one decides on removing a man from the senate, the
    other wishes to have him retained in it, and thinks him worthy of the highest rank. The one
    orders him to be degraded to the rank of an aerarian <note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="lat">Aerarii</foreign> were those citizens of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> who did not enjoy the perfect franchise. They had to pay the <foreign xml:lang="lat">aes militare</foreign>, and to remove a citizen in the enjoyment of the full
     franchise into the list of those who enjoyed a less complete one, was of course a degradation
     and a punishment.</note> or to be entirely disfranchised; the other forbids it. So that how can
    it occur to you to call those judicial decisions which you see constantly rescinded by the Roman
    people, repudiated by judges on their oaths, disregarded by the magistrates, altered by those
    who have the same power subsequently conferred on them, and in which you see that the colleagues
    themselves repeatedly disagree? </p></div>
    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="123" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And as all this is the case, let us see what the censors are said to have decided respecting
    that corrupt tribunal. And first of all let us lay down this principle; whether a thing is so
    because the censors have stated it in their notes, or whether they made such a statement in
    their notes because it was the fact. If it is the case because they have so stated it, take care
    what you are doing; beware lest you are establishing for the future a king by power in the
    person of every one of our censors,—beware lest the note <note anchored="true">In the <bibl n="Liv. 29.37.1">twenty-ninth book of Livy, c. 37</bibl>, an extraordinary instance is related
     of disagreement between the censors; for one of them, Caius Claudius Nero, degraded his
     colleague, Marcus Livius, and Livius in his turn degraded Caius Claudius.</note> of a censor
    may hereafter be able to cause as much distress to the citizens as that terrible proscription
    did,—beware lest we have reason to dread for the future that pen of the censor, whose point our
    ancestors blunted by many remedies, as much as that sword of the dictator. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="124" resp="perseus"><p> But if the statement which has been made in their notes ought to carry weight
    with it because it is true, then let us inquire whether it be true or false; let the authority
    of the censor be put out of the question —let that consideration be taken out of the cause which
    has no connection with it. Tell me what money Cluentius gave, where he got it, how he gave it;
    show me, in short, one trace of any money having proceeded from Cluentius. After that, prove
    that Oppianicus was a virtuous citizen, or an honest man; that no one had ever had a bad opinion
    of him; that no unfavourable decision had ever been come to respecting him. Then take in the
    authority of the censors; then argue that their decision has any connection whatever with this
    case. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="125" resp="perseus"><p> But as long as it is plain that Oppianicus was a man
    who was convicted of having tampered with the public registers of his own municipality, of
    having made erasures in a will, of having substituted another person in order to accomplish the
    forgery of a will, of having murdered the man whose name he had put to the will, of having
    thrown into slavery and into prison the uncle of his own son and then murdered him, of having
    contrived to get his own fellow-citizens proscribed and murdered, of having married the wife of
    the man whom he had murdered, of having given money for poisoning, of having murdered his
    mother-in-law and his wife, of having murdered at one time his brother's wife, the children who
    were expected, and his own brother himself,—lastly, of having murdered his own children; as he
    was a man who was manifestly detected in procuring poison for his son-in-law,—who, when his
    assistants and accomplices had been condemned, and when he himself was prosecuted, gave money to
    one of the judges to influence by bribes the votes of the other judges;—while, I say, all this
    is notorious about Oppianicus, and while the accusation of bribery against Cluentius is not
    sustained by any one single proof, what reason is there that that sentence of the censors,
    whether it is to be called their wish or their opinion, should either seem to be any assistance
    to you, or to be able to overwhelm my innocent client? </p></div>
    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="126" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What was it, then, that influenced the censors? Even they themselves, if they were to allege
    the most serious reason that they could, would not say it was anything else beyond common
    conversation and report. They will say that they found out nothing by witnesses, nothing by
    documents, nothing by any important evidence, nothing, in short, from any investigation of the
    cause. If they had investigated it, still their sentence ought not to have been so fixed as to
    be impossible to be altered. I will not quote precedents, of which, however, there is an
    infinite number; I will not mention any old instance, or any powerful or influential man. Very
    lately, when I had defended an insignificant man, clerk to the aediles, Decius Matrinius, before
    Marcus Junius and Quintus Publicius, the praetors, and before Marcus Platorius and Caius
    Flaminius, the curule aediles, I persuaded them,—men sworn to do their duty,—to choose him for
    their secretary whom those same censors had made an aerarian; for as there was no fault found in
    the man, they thought that they ought to inquire what he deserved, and not what resolution had
    been come to respecting him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="127" resp="perseus"><p> For as for these things which
    they have stated in their notes, about corrupting the judges, who is there who believes that
    they were sufficiently ascertained or carefully inquired into by them? I see that a note was
    made by the censors respecting Marcus Aquillius and Titus Gutta;—what does this mean? Were those
    two the only men corrupted with bribes? What became of the rest? Did they, forsooth, condemn him
    for nothing? He, then, was not unfairly dealt with; he was not overwhelmed by means of bribes;
    it is not the case, as all these assemblies stirred up by Quinctius would have it, that all the
    men who voted against Oppianicus are to be imagined criminal, or at all events suspected. I see
    that two men alone are judged by the authority of the censors to have been implicated in that
    infamy; or else they must allege that there is something which they have found out concerning
    those two men which they have not found out respecting the others. </p></div>
    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="128" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For that indeed can never be allowed, that they should transfer the usage of military
    discipline to the animadversions and authority of the censors; for our ancestors established a
    rule, that if in military affairs a crime had been committed by a number of soldiers, a few
    should be punished by lot, that so fear might have its influence on all, while the punishment
    reached only a few. But how can it be fitting for the censors to act on this principle in the
    distribution of dignities, in their judgment on the character of citizens, and in their
    punishment of their vices? For a soldier who has not maintained his post, who has been afraid of
    the vigorous attack of the enemy, may still hereafter become a better soldier, and a virtuous
    man, and a useful citizen. Wherefore, to prevent his committing offences in time of war through
    fear of the enemy, the great fear of death and execution was established by our ancestors; but
    yet, that the number of those who underwent capital punishment might not be too great, that plan
    of drawing lots was invented. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="129" resp="perseus"><p> But will you, O censor, act in
    this way when choosing the senate? Supposing there are many who have taken bribes to condemn an
    innocent man, will you not punish all of them, but will you pick as you choose, and select a few
    out of the many to brand with ignominy? Shall the senate then, while you see and know it to be
    the case, have a senator—shall the Roman people have a judge—shall the republic have a citizen,
    unmarked by any ignominy, who, to cause the ruin of an innocent man, has sold his good faith and
    religion for a bribe? And shall a man, who, being induced by a bribe, has deprived an innocent
    citizen of his country, his fortune, and his children, not be branded by the stigma of the
    censor's severity? Are you the prefect appointed to supervise our manners—are you a teacher of
    the ancient discipline and severity, if you either knowingly retain any one in the senate who is
    tainted with such wickedness, or if you decide that it is not right to inflict the same
    punishment on every one who is guilty of the same fault, or wild you establish the same
    principle of punishment with respect to the dishonesty of a senator in his peaceful capacity,
    which our ancestors chose to establish with respect to the cowardice of a soldier in time of
    war? Moreover, if this precedent ought to have been transferred from military affairs to the
    animadversion of the censors, at all events the system of drawing lots should have been
    retained. But if it is not consistent with the dignity of a censor to draw lots for punish meet,
    and to commit the guilt of men to the decision of fortune, it certainly cannot be right in the
    case of an offence committed by many, that a few should be selected for ignominy and disgrace.
     </p></div>
    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="130" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But we all understand that in these notes of the censors the real object was to catch at some
    breeze of popular favour. The matter had been brought forward in the assembly by a factious
    tribune; without any investigation into the business, his conduct was approved by the multitude;
    no one was allowed to say a word on the other side; indeed, no one showed the least anxiety to
    espouse the other side of the question. Moreover, those judges had already become exceedingly
    unpopular. A few months afterwards there was a fresh and very great odium excited with respect
    to the courts of justice, arising out of the affair of marking the balloting balls. The disgrace
    into which the courts were fallen appeared quite impossible to be overlooked or treated with
    indifference by the censors. So they chose to brand those men whom they saw were infamous for
    other vices, and for generally disgraceful lives, with their animadversion and special note
    also; and so much the more, because at that very time, during their censorship, the right of
    sitting as judges was divided with the equestrian body, in order that they might seem to have
    reproved those tribunals by their authority, through the ignominy inflicted on deserving men.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="131" resp="perseus"><p> But if I or any one else had been allowed to plead this
    cause before those censors, I would certainly have proved to the satisfaction of men endowed
    with such prudence, (for the facts of the case prove it,) that they themselves had ascertained
    nothing, had discovered nothing; but that in all those notes appended to their animadversions
    nothing had guided them but rumour, and nothing had been sought but popular applause. For to the
    name of Publius Popillius, who had condemned Oppianicus. Lucius Gellius had appended a note,
    “because he had taken money to condemn an innocent man.” Now what a real conjurer that man must
    be, O judges, to know that a man was innocent, whom, very likely, he had never seen, when the
    very wisest men, to say nothing of those who actually condemned him, after investigation of the
    case, said that they, were not without doubt in the matter? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="132" resp="perseus"><p>
   
   <milestone unit="para"/>However, be it so. Gellius condemns Popillius. He decides that he had accepted money from
    Cluentius. Lentulus says that he had not. For he did not elect Popillius into the senate,
    because he was the son of a freedman; but he left him his place as a senator at the games, and
    the other ornaments of that rank, and released him from all ignominy. And by doing so, he
    declares his opinion, that he had voted against Oppianicus without having been bribed to do so.
    And afterwards Lentulus, on a trial for bribery, gave his evidence most zealously in favour of
    this same Popillius. Wherefore, if Lentulus did not agree with the decision of Lucius Gellius,
    and if Gellius was not contented with the opinion delivered by Lentulus, and if each censor
    thought himself not bound at all by the opinion of the other censor, what reason is there why
    any one of us should think that the notes of the censors ought to be all fixed and ratified so
    as to be unalterable for ever? </p></div>
    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="133" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Oh, but they visited Habitus himself with their censure. Not for any baseness, nor for any, I
    will not say vice, but not even for any fault of his own in his whole life. For no one can
    possibly be a more religious man, or a more honourable one, or more scrupulous in fulfilling all
    his duties. Nor indeed does the opposite party say anything to the contrary, but they adopt the
    same report of the judges having been bribed. Nor indeed have they any contrary opinion to that
    which we wish to be entertained about his modesty, integrity, and virtue; but they thought it
    quite impossible for the accuser to be passed over after the judges had been punished. And with
    respect to this whole business, if I produce one precedent from the whole of our ancient
    history, I will say no more. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="134" resp="perseus"><p> For I think that I ought not to
    pass over the instance of that most eminent and most illustrious man, Publius Africanus; who,
    when he was censor, and when Caius Licinius Sacerdos had appeared on the register of the
    knights, said with a loud voice, so that the whole assembly could hear him, that he knew that he
    had committed deliberate perjury and that if any one denied it, he would give him his own
    evidence in support of this assertion. But when no one ventured to deny it, he ordered him to
    give up his horse. <note anchored="true">“If the censors considered a knight unworthy of his
     rank, they struck him off of the list of knights, and deprived him of his horse, or ordered him
     to sell it, with the intention, no doubt, that the person thus degraded should refund to the
     state the money which had been advanced to him for its purchase. (Niebuhr, <title>Hist. of
      Rome</title>, vol. i. p. 433.)”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 895, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Equites</foreign>.</note> So that he, with whose decision the Roman people and foreign
    nations had been accustomed to content themselves, was not content with his own private
    knowledge as justifying him in branding another with ignominy. But if Habitus had been allowed
    to do this, he would have found it an easy matter to have resisted those very judges themselves,
    and the false suspicion, and the odium excited in the breasts of the people against him.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="135" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/>There is still one thing which especially perplexes me, and
    a topic to which I appear to have scarcely made any sufficient reply,—namely, the eulogy which
    you read, extracted from the will of Caius Egnatius, the father, a most honourable man, and a
    most wise one; saying that he had disinherited his son, because he had taken a bribe to vote for
    the condemnation of Oppianicus. Of that man's inconstancy and feebleness I will not say another
    word. This very will which you are reading is such, that he, when he was disinheriting that son
    whom he hated, was joining with his other son whom he loved, the most perfect strangers as his
    coheirs. But I think that you, O Attius, should consider carefully, whether you wish the
    decision of the censors, or that of Egnatius, to carry most weight with it. If that of Egnatius,
    that is a trifling thing which the censors have expressed in their notes about the others; for
    they expelled Egnatius himself from the senate, whom you wish to be considered an authority. If
    that of the censors is to preponderate, then the censors when they expelled his father, retained
    this Egnatius in the senate, whom his father disinherited on account of the note which the
    censors had written respecting him. </p></div>
    <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="136" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Oh, but the whole senate judged that that tribunal had been bribed. How so? It undertook the
    cause. Could it pass over with indifference a matter of that sort when reported to it? When a
    tribune of the people, having stirred up the multitude, had almost brought the matter to a trial
    of strength; when a most virtuous citizen and most innocent man was said to have been unjustly
    condemned through the influence of money; when the whole body of senators was exceedingly
    unpopular, was it possible for no edict to be issued? Was it possible for all that excitement of
    the multitude to be disregarded without extreme danger to the republic? But what was decreed?
    How justly, how wisely, how diligently was it decreed? “If there are any men by whose agency the
    public court of justice was corrupted.” Does the senate appear here to decide that any such
    thing was really done? or rather to be exceedingly angry and indignant if such a thing was done?
    If Aulus Cluentius himself were asked his opinion about the courts of justice he would express
    no other sentiments than those which they expressed, by whose sentences you say that Aulus
    Cluentius was condemned. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="137" resp="perseus"><p> But I ask of you whether Lucius
    Lucullus, the consul, a very wise man, passed that law according to that resolution of the
    senate? I ask whether Marcus Lucullus and Caius Cassius passed that law, against whom, when they
    were the consuls elect, the senate passed the very same resolution? They did not pass it. And
    that which you assert to have been brought about by Habitus's money, though you do not confirm
    your assertion by even the very slightest circumstances of suspicion, was done in the first
    instance by the justice and wisdom of those consuls, in order that men might not think that what
    the senate had decreed for the purpose of extinguishing the flames of present unpopularity,
    might afterwards be referred to the people. The Roman people itself afterwards, which formerly
    when excited by the fictitious complaints of Lucius Quinctius, a tribune of the people, had
    demanded that thing and the proposal of that law, now being influenced by the tears of the son
    of Caius Junius, a little boy, rejected the whole law and the whole proposition with the
    greatest outcry and with the greatest eagerness. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="138" resp="perseus"><p> From which
    that was easy to be understood which has been often said,—that as the sea, which by its own
    nature is tranquil, is often agitated and disturbed by the violence of the winds, so, too, the
    Roman people is, when left to itself, placable, but is easily roused by the language of
    seditious men, as by the most violent storm. <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>There is also one other very great authority besides, which I had almost passed over in a
    shameful manner; for it is said to be my own. Attius read out of some oration or other, which he
    said was mine, a certain exhortation to the judges to judge honestly, and a certain mention of
    judicial decisions in other cases, which had not been approved of, and also of that very trial
    before Junius; just as if I had not said at the beginning of this defence, that had been a trial
    which had incurred great unpopularity; or as if, when I was discussing the discredit into which
    the courts of justice had fallen in some instances, I could possibly at that time pass over that
    one which was so notorious. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="139" resp="perseus"><p> But I, if I said anything of
    that sort, did not mention it as a thing within my own knowledge, nor did I state it in
    evidence; and that speech was prompted rather by the occasion, than by my judgment and
    deliberate intention. For when I was acting as accuser, and had proposed to myself at the
    beginning to rouse the feelings of the Roman people and of the judges; and as I was mentioning
    all the errors of the courts of justice, relying not on my own opinion, but on the common report
    of men; I could not pass over that matter which had been so universally discussed. But whoever
    thinks that he has my positive opinions recorded indelibly in those orations which we have
    delivered in the courts of justice, is greatly mistaken. For all those speeches are speeches of
    the cause, and of the occasion, and are not the speeches of the men or of the advocates
    themselves. For if the causes themselves could speak for themselves, no one would employ an
    orator. But, as it is, we are employed, in order to say, not things which are to be considered
    as asserted on our own authority, but things which are derived from the circumstances of the
    cause itself. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="140" resp="perseus"><p> They say that that able man, Marcus Antonius,
    was accustomed to say, “that he had never written a speech, in order that, if at any time he had
    said anything which was not desirable, he might be able to deny that he had said it.” Just as if
    whatever were said or pleaded by us was not retained in men's memories, if we did not ourselves
    commit it to writing. <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But I, with respect to speeches of that sort, am guided by the authority of many men, and
    especially of that most eloquent and most wise man, Lucius Crassus; who—when he was defending
    Lucius Plancius, whom Marcus Brutus, a man both vehement and able as a speaker, was prosecuting;
    when Brutus, having set two men to read, made them read alternate chapters out of two speeches
    of his, entirely contrary to one another, because when he was arguing against that motion which
    was introduced against the colony of <placeName key="tgn,7008368">Narbo</placeName>, he
    disparaged the authority of the senate as much as he could, but when he was urging the adoption
    of the Servilian law, he extolled the senate with the most excessive praises; and when he had
    read out of that oration many things which had been spoken with some harshness against the Roman
    knights, in order to inflame the minds of those judges against Crassus—is said to have been a
    good deal agitated. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="141" resp="perseus"><p> And so, in making his reply, he first of
    all explained the difference between the two times, so that the speech might appear to have
    arisen from the case and from its circumstances; after that, in order that Brutus might learn
    what a man, not only eloquent but endued with the greatest wit and facetiousness, he had
    provoked, he himself in his turn brought up three readers with a book a piece, all which books
    Marcus Brutus, the father of the prosecutor, had left, on the civil law. When the first lines of
    them were read, those which I take to be known to all of you, “It happened by chance that I and
    Brutus my son were in the country near <placeName key="perseus,Privernum">Privernum</placeName>,” he asked what had become of his farm at <placeName key="perseus,Privernum">Privernum</placeName>. “I and Brutus my son were in the district of
    Alba.” He begged to know where his <placeName key="tgn,1031727">Alban</placeName> farm was.
    “Once, when I and Brutus my son had sat down in the fields near <placeName key="perseus,Tibur">Tibur</placeName>.” Where was his farm near <placeName key="perseus,Tibur">Tibur</placeName>?
    And he said that “Brutus, a wise man, seeing the profligacy of his son, evidently wished to
    leave a record behind him of what farms he left him. And if he could with any decency have
    written that he had been in the bath with a son of that age, he would not have passed it over;
    and still that he preferred inquiring about those baths, not from the books of his father, but
    from the registers and the census.” Crassus then chastised Brutus in this manner, and made him
    repent of his readings. For perhaps he had been annoyed at being reproved for those speeches
    which he had delivered in the affairs of the republic; in which perhaps deliberate wisdom is
    more required than in those in court. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="142" resp="perseus"><p> But I am not at all
    vexed at those things having been read. For they were not unsuited to the state of the times
    which then existed, nor to the cause in which they were spoken. Nor did I take any obligation on
    myself when I spoke them, to prevent my defending this cause with honour and freedom. But
    suppose I were now to confess, that I had now become acquainted with the real merits of
    Cluentius's case, but that I was previously influenced by popular opinion concerning it, who
    could blame me especially when, O judges, it is most reasonable that this also should be granted
    me by you, which I begged at the beginning, and which I request now, that if you have brought
    with you into court a somewhat unfavourable opinion of this cause, you will lay it aside now
    that you have thoroughly investigated the case and learnt the whole truth. </p></div>
    <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="143" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Now since, O Titus Attius, I replied to everything which was said by you concerning the
    condemnation of Oppianicus, you must inevitably confess that you were very much deceived when
    you thought that I would defend the cause of Aulus Cluentius, not by arguing on his own actions,
    but on the law. For you very often said that you had been informed that I intended to defend
    this action, relying on the protection of the law. Is it so? Are we, then, without knowing it,
    betrayed by our friends? and is there some one among those whom we think our friends, who
    carries intelligence of our plans to our adversaries? Who reported this to you? Who was so
    dishonest? But to whom did I tell it? No one I imagine, is in fault; but in truth it was the law
    itself which suggested this to you. But do I appear to have defended it in such a way as to have
    made throughout the whole case the least mention of the law? Do I appear to have defended this
    cause differently from the way in which I should have defended it if Habitus had been guilty by
    law, supposing the facts to be proved? Certainly, as far as a man may assert a thing positively,
    I have omitted no opportunity of clearing him from the odious imputation sought to be cast on
    him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="144" resp="perseus"><p> What do I mean, then? Some one will ask, perhaps,
    whether I have any objection to ward off danger from a client's life by the protection with
    which the law supplies me? I have no objection at all, O judges; but I adhere to my own plan of
    action. In a trial in which all honourable and a wise man is concerned, I have been accustomed,
    not only to consult my own judgment, but very much also to be guided by the judgment and
    inclination of him whom I am defending. For when this cause was brought to me, as to a person
    who ought to know the laws on which we are employed, and to which we devote ourselves, I said at
    once to Habitus that he was perfectly safe from the law about “those who conspired together to
    procure a man's condemnation;” but that our order was liable to be impeached under that law. And
    he began to beg and entreat me not to defend him by urging points of law. And when I said what I
    thought, he brought me over to his opinion; for he affirmed with tears that he was not more
    desirous of retaining his freedom as a citizen, than of preserving his character. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="145" resp="perseus"><p> I complied with his wishes, and yet I did it (for it is not a thing
    which we ought to do at all times) because I saw that the cause itself could be amply defended
    on its own merits, without any reference to law at all. I saw that in this defence, which I now
    have employed, there was more dignity, but that in that one which he begged me not to use, there
    would be less trouble. But if I had no other object in view beyond merely gaining this cause, I
    should have read the laws to you, and then have summed up. <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Nor am I moved by that argument which Attius uses when he says that it is a scandalous thing
    that, if a senator should procure a wrongful conviction of any one, he should be made liable to
    the laws, but that if a Roman knight does the same, he should not. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="146" resp="perseus"><p> Although I should grant to you that it would be a scandalous thing, (and the
    fact I will examine into presently,) still you must inevitably grant to me that it is a much
    more scandalous thing that the laws should be departed from in that state which is entirely held
    together by the laws; for this is the bond of this dignity which we enjoy in the republic, this
    is the foundation of our liberty, this is the source of justice. The mind, and spirit, and
    wisdom, and intentions of the city are all situated in the laws. As our bodies cannot, if
    deprived of the mind, so the state, if deprived of law, cannot use its separate parts, which are
    to it as its sinews, its blood, and its limbs. The ministers of the law are the magistrates; the
    interpreters of the law are the judges; lastly, we are all servants of the laws, for the very
    purpose of being able to be freemen.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="147" resp="perseus"><p>What is the reason, O <persName><surname>Naso</surname></persName>, why you sit in that place? What is the power by which those judges, invested with such dignity, are
    separated from you? And you too, O judges, how is it that out of such a multitude of citizens,
    you with your small numbers decide on the fortunes of man? By what right is it that Attius said
    whatever he chose? Why have I had an opportunity of speaking at such length? What is the meaning
    of all these secretaries and lictors, and all the rest of those whom I see assisting at this
    investigation? I think that all these things take place according to law, and that the whole of
    this trial is conducted and governed (as I said before) by the mind, as it were, of the law.
    What, then, shall we say? Is this the only investigation that is so conducted? What became of
    the question of classing Marcus Plaetorius and Caius Flaminius as assassins? What became of the
    charge of peculation brought against Caius Orchinius? or of my oration, when prosecuting a
    charge of embezzlement? or of the speech of Caius Aquillius, before whom a case of bribery is at
    this moment being tried? or of all the other investigations that are habitually taking place?
    Survey all the different parts of the republic; you will see that everything takes place under
    the general dominion, and according to the special enactment of the laws. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="148" resp="perseus"><p> If anyone, O Titus Attius, were to wish to prosecute you before me as judge,
    you would cry out that you were not liable under the law about extortion. Nor would this
    demurrer of yours be any confession that you had appropriated the money illegally; but it would
    be merely a refusal to encounter a labour and a danger which you were not obliged to encounter
    by the law. <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Now see what is being done, and what law is laid down by you. The law, according to the
    provisions of which this investigation has been instituted, orders the judge who presides over
    the investigation, that is to say, Quintus Voconius, with the other judges, who are his
    colleagues, (it means you, O judges,) to make inquiry concerning the fact of poisoning. To make
    inquiry with respect to whom? The subject is interminable. “Whoever has made it, or sold it, or
    bought it, or had it in his possession, or administered it.” What does the same law subjoin
    immediately afterwards? Read—“And bring him to a capital trial.” Whom? He who has conspired? he
    who has agreed? Not so. What, then, is meant? Tell me. “Whoever is a military tribune of the
    four first legions, or a quaestor, or a tribune of the people.” Then all the magistrates are
    named. “Or who has delivered or shall deliver his opinion in the senate?” What then? “If any one
    of them has agreed, or shall agree, has conspired, or shall conspire, to get any one condemned
    in a criminal trial.” “Any one of them:” Of whom? Of those, forsooth, who have been enumerated
    above. What does it signify in which way the law was framed? Although it is plain enough, yet
    the law itself shows its own meaning; for when it binds all the world, it uses this expression:
    “Whoever has committed or shall commit an act of poisoning.” All men and women, freemen and
    slaves, are brought under the power of the court. If, again, it had wished to include
    conspiracy, it would have added, “or who has conspired.” Now it runs, “And let any one who has
    conspired, or shall conspire, be brought to a capital trial, before one who has filled any
    magistracy, or who has delivered his opinion in the senate.” </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="149" resp="perseus"><p>
    Does that apply to Cluentius? Certainly not. Who, then, is Cluentius? He is a man who still does
    not wish to get off on a trial by any quibble of law. Well, then, I discard the law. I comply
    with Cluentius's wishes; still I will say a few things which are not connected with my client's
    case, by way of reply to you, O Attius. For there is something in this cause which Cluentius
    thinks concerns him; there is also something which I think concerns me. He thinks it is for his
    interest that his defence should rest on the facts and merits of the case, not on the letter of
    the law; but I think that it concerns me not to appear defeated by Attius in any discussion. For
    this is not the only cause that I have to plead; my labour is at the service of every one who
    can be content with my ability as their advocate. I do not wish any one of those who are present
    to think, if I remain silent, that I approve of what has been said by Attius respecting the law.
    Wherefore, O Cluentius, I am complying with your wishes in this your cause; and I do not read
    any law in this court, nor do I allege any law in your favour. But I will not omit those things
    which I think are expected from me. </p></div>
    <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="150" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>It seems to you, O Attius, to be a scandalous thing that every one should not be bound by the
    same laws. In the first place, (suppose I do grant to you that it is a most scandalous thing,)
    it is an evil of this sort, that it is a proof that we have need to have the laws altered, not
    that we are not to obey the laws while they are in existence. In the next place, what senator
    has ever made this complaint, that when, by the kindness of the Roman people, he had attained a
    higher rank, he did not think he ought by that promotion to be put under more severe conditions
    of law? How many advantages are there, which we are without; how many troubles and annoyances
    are there which we undergo.—And all these things are compensated by the advantages of honour and
    dignity. Now apply these same conditions of life to the equestrian order, and to the other ranks
    of the state. They will not endure them; for they think that fewer inconveniences of the laws,
    and of the courts of justice, ought to be allotted to them, who have either never been able to
    mount to the higher ranks of the state, or have never tried. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="151" resp="perseus"><p>
    And, to say nothing of all other laws, by which we are bound, and from which all the other ranks
    are released, Caius Gracchus passed this law, “That no one should be circumvented.” And he
    passed, it for the sake of the common people, not against the common people. Afterwards Lucius
    Sulla, a man who had not the slightest connection with the common people, still, when he was
    appointing a trial concerning a case of this sort to take place according to the provisions of
    this very law, by which you are sitting as judges at the present moment, did not dare to bind
    the Roman people with this new sort of proceeding, whom he had received free from any such
    obligation. But if he had thought it practicable to do so, from the hatred which he bore the
    equestrian order, he would not have been more glad to do anything than to turn the whole fury of
    that proscription of his which he let loose upon the old judges, on this single tribunal.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="152" resp="perseus"><p> Nor is there any other object aimed at now, (believe me, O
    judges, and provide for what you must provide for,) except the bringing the whole equestrian
    body within the danger of this law. Not that this is the object of every one, but of a few. For
    those senators who easily keep themselves in integrity and innocence, such as (I will speak the
    truth,) you yourselves are, and those others who have lived free from covetousness are anxious
    that the knights, as they are next to the senatorial body in rank, should also be most closely
    united to them by community of feeling. But those who wish to engross all power to themselves,
    and to prevent any from existing in any other man, or in any other rank, think that by holding
    this single fear over them, they will be able to bring the Roman knights under their power, if
    it is once established that investigations of this sort can be held upon those men who have
    acted as judges. For they see that the authority of this order is strengthened, they see that
    its judicial decisions are approved; but if this fear be suspended over you they feel confident
    that they shall be able to pluck the sting out of your severity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="153" resp="perseus"><p> For, who would dare to decide with truth and firmness in the case of a man
    possessed of at all greater power or riches than the generality, when he sees that he himself
    may be afterwards prosecuted with reference to that case, for having been guilty of some
    agreement or conspiracy? <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>O the gallant men, the Roman knights! who resisted that most eminent and most powerful man,
    Marcus Drusus, when tribune of the people, when he was aiming at nothing with respect to the
    whole body of nobility which existed at that time, except contriving that they, who had sat as
    judges, might be themselves brought before the court by proceedings of this sort. Then Caius
    Flavius Pusio, Cnaeus Titinnius, Caius Maecenas, those props of the Roman people, and the other
    men of this order, did not do the same thing that Cluentius does now, in refusing, because they
    thought that they should by that means incur some blame; but they most openly resisted, when
    they demurred to these proceedings, and said openly, with the greatest courage and honesty, that
    they might have arrived by the decision of the Roman people at the highest rank, if they had
    chosen to set their hearts on seeking honours; that they were aware how much splendour, how much
    honour, and how much dignity there was in that sort of life; and that they had not despised
    these things, but had been content with their own order, which had been the rank of their
    fathers before them; and that they had preferred following that tranquil course of life, removed
    from the storms of unpopularity, and from the intricacies of these judicial proceedings.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="154" resp="perseus"><p> They said, that either the proper age for offering
    themselves as candidates for honours ought to be restored to them, or, since that was
    impossible, that that condition of life had better remain which they had followed when they
    abstained from being candidates; that it was unjust that they, who had avoided all the
    decorations of those honours, on account of the multitude of their dangers, should be deprived
    of the kindness of the people, and yet not be free from the dangers of these new tribunals; that
    a senator could not make this complaint, because he had originally offered himself as a
    candidate for them, knowing all the conditions, and because he had a great many honourable
    circumstances which in his case might lessen the inconvenience,—the place, the authority, the
    dignity it gave him at home, the name and influence it conferred on him among foreign nations,
    the <foreign xml:lang="lat">toga praetexta</foreign>, the curule chair, the ensigns of the rank,
    the forces, the armies, the military command, the provinces, all which things our ancestors
    wished to be the greatest rewards for virtuous actions, and by them they wished, also, that
    there should be the greatest dangers held out, as a terror to offences. They did not refuse to
    be prosecuted under this law, under which Habitus is now prosecuted, which was then called the
    Sempronian law, and now is called the Cornelian law. For they were aware that the equestrian
    order is not bound by that law; but they were anxious not to be bound by any new law. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="155" resp="perseus"><p> Habitus has never demurred even to this, not to giving an account of
    his course of life according to the provisions of a law by which he was not at all bound. And if
    this condition pleases you, let us all strive to have this investigation extended to all ranks
    and orders in the city. <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But in the mean time, in the name of the immortal gods! since we have all our advantages, our
    laws, our liberty, and our safety by means of the laws, let us not depart from the laws. And at
    the same time let us consider what a scandalous thing it is for the Roman people to be now
    pursuing another object; for them to have entrusted to you the republic and their own fortunes;
    to be themselves without any care; to have no fear of being bound by the decision of a few
    judges, by a law which they have never sanctioned, and by a form of judicial investigation of
    which they think themselves independent. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="156" resp="perseus"><p> For Titus Attius, a
    virtuous and eloquent young man, conducts this case in such a manner; saying that all the
    citizens are bound by all the laws; and you attend and listen in silence, as you ought to do. 
   <milestone unit="para"/>Aulus Cluentius, a Roman knight, is prosecuted according to that law by which the senators,
    and those who have served magistracies, alone are bound. I, by his desire, am prevented from
    demurring to this and from establishing the main bulwark of my defence on the citadel of the
    law. If Cluentius gains his cause, as we, relying on your equity, feel sure that he will, all
    will believe, what indeed will be the truth, that he has gained it because of his innocence,
    since he has been defended in such a manner as this; but in the law, all appeal to which he
    discarded, he found no protection at all. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="157" resp="perseus"><p> Here now is
    something which concerns me, as I said before, and which I ought to make good to the
    satisfaction of the Roman people, since my condition of life is such that the whole of my care
    and labour is devoted to defending every one from danger. I see how great, and how dangerous,
    and how bound less a field of investigation is attempted to be opened by the prosecutors, when
    they endeavour to transfer that law, which was framed with reference to our order alone, to the
    whole Roman people. And in that law are the words—“Who has conspired.” You see how wide an
    application that may have. “Or agreed.” That is just as vague and indefinite. “Or consented.”
    But this is not only vague and indefinite, but is also obscure and unintelligible. “Or given any
    false evidence.” Who is there of the common people at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, who has ever given any evidence at all, who is not, as you see, exposed to
    this danger, if Titus Attius is to have his own way? At all events I assert this positively,
    that no one will ever give evidence for the future, if this tribunal is held over the common
    people of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="158" resp="perseus"><p> But
    I make this promise to every one, if by chance any one is brought into trouble by this law, who
    is not properly liable to this law, that if he will employ me to defend him, I will defend his
    cause by the protection that the law affords, and that I will prove my ease easily to these
    judges, or to any others who resemble them, and that I will use every means of defence with
    which the law provides me, which I am now not permitted to use, by the man with whose wishes I
    am bound to comply. <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For I ought not to doubt, O judges, that, if a cause of this sort be brought before you, of a
    man who does not come under the provisions of that law, even if he be unpopular, or if he seem
    to be disliked by many, or even if you hate him yourselves, and are unwilling to acquit him,
    still you will acquit him; and you will be guided rather by your sense of duty than by your
    personal hatred. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="159" resp="perseus"><p> For it is the part of a wise judge, to
    think that he has just that power permitted to him by the Roman people, which is committed and
    entrusted to him; and to remember that not only is power given to him, but also that confidence
    is placed in him: that he is a man capable of acquitting a man whom he hates, of condemning one
    whom he does not hate; and of always thinking not what he himself wishes, but what the law and
    the obligation of his oath requires of him—of considering according to what law the defendant is
    brought before him, who the defendant is into whose conduct he is inquiring, and what are the
    facts which are being investigated. All these things require to be looked at, and also it is the
    part of a great and wise man, O judges, when he has taken in his hand his judicial tablet, to
    think that he is not alone, and that it is not lawful for him to do whatever he wishes; but that
    he must employ in his deliberations law, equity, religion, and good faith; that he must discard
    lust, hatred, envy, fear, and all evil passions, and must think that consciousness implanted in
    one's mind, which we have received from the immortal gods, and which cannot be taken from us, to
    be the most powerful motive of all. And if that is a witness of virtuous counsels and virtuous
    actions throughout our whole lives, we shall live without any fear, and in the greatest honour. 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="160" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> If Titus Attius had known these things, or thought of
    them, certainly he would not have ventured to say what he did assert at great length, that a
    judge decides whatever he chooses, and ought not to be bound by the laws. But now concerning all
    these topics I think I have said too much, if judged by the inclination of Cluentius; little
    enough, if we love to the dignity of the republic; but quite enough with reference to your
    wisdom. There are a few topics remaining, which because they belonged to your investigation they
    thought ought to be considered and urged by them, that they might not be considered the most
    worthless of all men, as they would deserve to be if they brought nothing into the court but
    their own personal ill-feeling. <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And that you may see that it is of necessity that I have urged the topics which I have now
    been mentioning, at considerable length, listen to what remains. You will then understand that
    all those points of the defence which could be stated in a few words, have been stated with the
    greatest brevity possible. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="161" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You have said that an injury was done by the family of my client to Cnaeus Decius, a Samnite;
    him I mean who was proscribed, in his calamity. He was never treated by any one more liberally
    than by Cluentius. It was the riches of Cluentius that relieved him in his distresses; and he
    himself, and all his friends and relations, know it well. You have said “that his stewards
    offered violence to and assaulted the shepherds of Ancarius and Pacenus.” When some dispute (as
    is often the case) had arisen in the hills between the shepherds, the stewards of Habitus
    defended the property and private possessions of their master. The parties expostulated with one
    another, the cause was proved to the satisfaction of the others, and the matter was settled
    without any trial or any recourse to law. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="162" resp="perseus"><p> You have said,
    “when a relation of Publius Aelius had been disinherited by his will, this man, who was no
    relation of his, was declared his heir.” Publius Aelius acted so from his knowledge of Habitus's
    merit. He was not present at the making of the will, and that will was signed by Oppianicus as a
    witness. You have said, “that he refused to pay Florius a legacy bequeathed to him in the will.”
    That is not the case; but as thirty sesterces had been written instead of three hundred, and as
    it did not appear to him to have been very carefully worded, he only wished him to consider what
    he received as due to his liberality. He first denied that the money was legally due, but,
    having done so, he then paid it without any dispute. You have said, “that the wife of a certain
    Samnite named Caelius was, after the war, recovered from Cluentius.” He had bought the woman as
    a slave from the brokers; but the moment that he heard that she was a free woman he restored her
    to Caelius without any action. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="163" resp="perseus"><p> You have said, “that there is
    a man named Ennius, whose property Habitus is in possession of.” This Ennius is a needy man, a
    bumper-up of false accusations, a hired tool of Oppianicus; who for many years remained quiet;
    then at last he accused a slave of Habitus of theft; lately, he began to claim things from
    Habitus himself. By that private proceeding, he will not (believe me), though we may perhaps be
    his advocates, escape calumny. And also, as it is reported to us, you suborn an entertainer of
    many guests, a certain Aulus Binnius, an innkeeper on the Latin road, to say that violence was
    offered to him in his own tavern by Aulus Cluentius and his slaves. But about that man I have no
    need at present to say anything. If he invited them, as is commonly the case, we will treat the
    man so as to make him sorry for having gone out of his way. 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="164" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/>You have now, O judges, everything which the prosecutors,
    after eight years' meditation, have been able to collect against the morals of Aulus Cluentius
    during his whole life, the man whom they state to be so hated and unpopular. Charges how
    insignificant in their kind! how false in their facts! how briefly replied to! <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Learn now this, which has a reference to your oath, which belongs to your tribunal, which is a
    burden the law has imposed on you, in accordance with which you have assembled here,—the law, I
    mean, about accusations of poison; so that all may understand in how few words this cause may be
    summed up, and how many things have been said by me which had a great deal to do with the
    inclination of my client, but very little with your decision. 
   <milestone unit="para"/></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="165" resp="perseus"><p> It has been urged in the case for the prosecution, that
    Caius Vibius Capax was taken off by poison by this Aulus Cluentius. It happens very seasonably
    that a man is present, endowed with the greatest good faith, and with every virtue, Lucius
    Plaetorius, a senator, who was connected by ties of hospitality with, and was an intimate friend
    of that man Capax. He used to live with him at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>; it
    was in his house that he was taken in, in his house that he died. “But Cluentius is his heir.” I
    say that he died without a will, and that the possession of his property was given by the
    praetor's edict to this man, his sister's son, a most virtuous young man, and one held in the
    highest esteem for honourable conduct, Numerius Cluentius, who is present in court. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="166" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is another poisoning charge. They say that poison was, by the contrivance of Habitus,
    prepared for this young Oppianicus, when, according to the custom of the citizens of Larinum, a
    large party was dining at his wedding feast; that, as it was being administered in mead, a man
    of the name of Balbutius, his intimate friend, intercepted it on its way, drank it, and died
    immediately. If I were to deal with this charge as one that required to be refuted, I should
    treat those matters at great length, which, as it is, my speech will pass over in a few words.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="167" resp="perseus"><p> What has Habitus ever done that he is not to be thought a
    man incapable of such an atrocity as this? And what reason had he for being so exceedingly
    afraid of Oppianicus, when he could not possibly say a word in this case, and while accusers
    could not possibly be wanting, as long as his mother was alive? which you will soon have proved
    to you. Was it his object to have no sort of danger wanting to his cause, that this new crime
    was added to it? But what opportunity had he of giving him poison on that day, and in so large a
    company? Moreover, by whom was it given? Whence was it got? How, too, was the cup allowed to be
    intercepted? Why was not another given to him over again? There are many arguments which may be
    urged; but I still not appear to wish to urge them, and still not to do so. For the facts of the
    case shall speak for themselves. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="168" resp="perseus"><p> I say that that young man,
    whom you say died the moment that he had drank that cup, did not die at all on that day. O great
    and impudent lie! Now see the rest of the truth. I say that he, having come to the dinner while
    labouring under an indigestion, and still, as people of that age often do, had not spared
    himself, was taken ill, continued ill some days, and so died. Who is my witness for this fact?
    The man who is a witness also of his own grief—his own father. The father, I say, of the young
    man himself: he, who, from his grief of mind, would have been easily inclined by even the
    slightest suspicion to appear as a witness against Aulus Cluentius, gives evidence in his
    favour. Read his evidence. But do you, unless it is too grievous for you, rise for a moment, and
    endure the pain which this necessary recollection of your trouble causes you; on which I will
    not dwell too long, since, as became a virtuous citizen, you have not allowed your own grief to
    be the cause of distress or of a false accusation to an innocent man. [The testimony of
    Balbutius the father is read.] </p></div>
    <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="169" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>There is one charge remaining, O judges; a charge of such a nature, that you may see from it
    the truth of what I said at the beginning of my speech,—that whatever misfortune has happened to
    Aulus Cluentius of late years, whatever anxiety or trouble he has at the present time, has all
    been contrived by his mother. You say that Oppianicus was killed by poison, which was
    administered to him in bread by some one of the name of Marcus Asellius, an intimate friend of
    his own; and that that was done by the contrivance of Habitus. Now, in this matter, I ask first
    of all what reason Habitus had for wishing to kill Oppianicus. For I admit that ill-will did
    exist between them; but men only wish their enemies to be slain, either because they fear them,
    or because they hate them. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="170" resp="perseus"><p> Now, by fear of what could
    Habitus have been influenced, that he should have endeavoured to commit so great a crime? What
    reason could any one have had for fearing Oppianicus, already condemned to punishment for his
    crimes, and banished from the city? What did Cluentius fear? Did he fear being attacked by a
    ruined man? or being accused by a convict? or being injured by the evidence of an exile? But if,
    because Habitus hated him, he, on that account, did not wish him to live, was he such a fool, as
    to think that a life which he was then living, the existence of a convict, of an exile, of a man
    abandoned by every one? whom, on account of his odious disposition, no one was willing to admit
    into his house, or to visit, or to speak to, or even to look at? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="171" resp="perseus"><p> Did Habitus, then, envy the life of this men? If he had hated him bitterly and
    utterly, ought he not to have wished him to live as long as possible? Would an enemy have
    hastened his death, when death was the only refuge which he had left from his calamity? If the
    man had had any virtue or any courage, he would have killed himself, (as many brave men have
    done in many instances, when in similar misfortunes.) How is it possible for an enemy to have
    wished to offer to him what he must himself have wished for eagerly For now indeed, what evil
    has death brought him? Unless, perchance, we are influenced by fables and nonsense, to think
    that he is enduring in the shades below the punishments of' the wicked, and that he has met with
    more enemies there than he left behind here; and that he has been driven headlong into the
    district and habitation of wicked spirits by the avenging furies of his mother-in-law, of his
    wife, of his brother, and of his children. But if these stories are false, as all men are well
    aware that they are, what else has death taken from him except the sense of his misery? Come
    now, by whose instrumentality was the poison administered? By that of Marcus Asellius.
     </p></div>
    <milestone n="62" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="172" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>What connection had he with Habitus? None—nay rather, as he was a very intimate friend of
    Oppianicus, he was rather an enemy to Habitus. Did he then pick out that man whom he knew to be
    rather unfriendly to himself, and to be exceedingly intimate with Oppianicus, to be above all
    others the instrument of his own wickedness, and of the other's danger, In the next place, why
    do you, who have been prompted by pity to undertake this prosecution, leave this Asellius so
    long unpunished? Why did not you follow the precedent of Habitus, and have a previous
    examination, which should affect him, by means of an investigation into his conduct who had
    administered the poison? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="173" resp="perseus"><p> But now, as for that circumstance
    of poison being administered in bread, how improbable, how unusual, how strange a thing it is.
    Was it easier than administering it in a cup? Could it be hid more secretly in some part of the
    bread than if it had been all liquefied and amalgamated with a potion? Could it pass more
    rapidly into the veins and into every separate part of the body if it were eaten than if it were
    drunk? Could it escape notice (if that was thought of) more easily in bread, than in a cup, when
    it might then have been so mixed up as to be wholly impossible to be separated? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="174" resp="perseus"><p> “But he died by a sudden death.” But if that was the case, still that
    circumstance, from the number of men who die in that way, would not give rise to any
    well-grounded suspicion of poison. If it were a suspicious circumstance, still the suspicion
    would apply to others rather than to Habitus. But as to that fact itself, men tell most impudent
    lies. And that you may see this, listen to this statement of the truth respecting his death, and
    how after his death an accusation was sought for out of it against Habitus, by his mother.
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="175" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>When Oppianicus was wandering about as a vagabond and an exile, excluded from every quarter,
    he went into the Falernian district of Caius Quintilius; there he first fell sick, and had a
    very violent illness. As Sassia was with him, and as she was more intimate with a man of the
    name of Statius Albius, a citizen of that colony, a man in good health, who was constantly with
    her, than that most dissolute husband could endure, while his fortune was unimpaired, and as she
    thought that that chaste and legitimate bond of wedlock was dissolved by the condemnation of her
    husband, a man of the name of Nicostratus, a faithful slave of Oppianicus's, a man who was very
    curious and very truth-telling, is said to have been accustomed to carry a good many tales to
    his master. In the meantime, when Oppianicus was becoming convalescent, and could not endure any
    longer the profligacy of this Falernian, and after he had come nearer the city,—for he had some
    sort of hired house outside the gates,—he is said to have fallen from his horse, and, being a
    man in delicate health before, to have hurt his side very badly, and having come to the city in
    a state of fever, to have died in a few days. This is the manner of his death, O judges, such as
    to have no suspicious circumstance at ale attached to it, or if it has any, they must apply to
    some domestic wickedness carried on within his own walls. </p></div>
    <milestone n="63" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="176" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>After his death Sassia, that abandoned woman, immediately began to devise plots against her
    son. She determined to have an investigation made into the death of her husband. She bought of
    Aulus Rupilius, whom Habitus had employed as his physician, a slave of the name of
      <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, as if she were following the example of
    Habitus in purchasing Diogenes. She said that she was going to investigate the conduct of this
      <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, and of some servant of her own. Besides that,
    she begged of that young Oppianicus that slave Nicostratus, whom she thought to be too
    talkative, and too faithful to his master, for judicial examination. As Oppianicus was at that
    time quite a boy, and as that investigation was being instituted about the death of his own
    father, although he thought that that slave was a well-wisher both to himself and to his father,
    still he did not venture to refuse anything. The friends and connections of Oppianicus, and many
    also of the friends of Sassia herself, honourable men, and accomplished in every sense of the
    word, are invited to attend. The investigation is carried on by means of the severest tortures.
    When the minds of the slaves had been tried both with hope and fear, to induce them to say
    something in the examination, still, compelled (as I imagine) by the authority of those who were
    present, and by the power of the tortures, they adhered to the truth, and said that they knew
    nothing of the matter. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="177" resp="perseus"><p> The examination was adjourned on that
    day, by the advice of the friends who were present. After a sufficient interval of time, they
    are summoned a second time. The examination is repeated all over again. No degree of the most
    terrible torture is emitted. The witnesses who had been summoned turned away, and could scarcely
    bear to witness it. The cruel and barbarous woman began to storm, and to be furious that her
    plans were not proceeding as she had hoped that they would. When the torturer and the very
    tortures themselves were worn out, and still she would not desist, one of the men who had been
    summoned as witnesses, a man distinguished by honours conferred on him by the people, and endued
    with the highest virtue, said that he plainly saw that the object was not to find out the truth,
    but to compel them to give some false evidence. After the rest had shown their approbation of
    these words, it was resolved by the unanimous opinion of them all, that the examination had been
    carried far enough. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="178" resp="perseus"><p> Nicostratus is restored to Oppianicus;
    Sassia goes to Larinum with her friends, grieving, because she thought that her son would
    certainly be safe; since not only no true accusation could be proved against him, but there
    could not be even any false suspicion made to attach to him, and since not only the open attacks
    of his enemies were unable to injure him, but even the secret plots of his mother against him
    proved harmless to him. After she came to Larinum, she, who had pretended to be persuaded that
    poison had been previously given to her husband by that man
     <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, immediately gave him a shop at Larinum,
    properly furnished and provided for carrying on the business of an apothecary. <milestone n="64" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>One, two, three years did Sassia remain quiet, so that she seemed rather to be wishing and
    hoping for some misfortune to her son, than to be planning and contriving any such thing against
    him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="179" resp="perseus"><p> Then in the meantime, in the consulship of Hortensius
    and Metellus, in order that she might persuade Oppianicus, who was occupied about other matters,
    and thinking of nothing of the sort, to this accusation, she betroths to him against his will
    her own daughter, her whom she had borne to his father-in-law, in order that she might have him
    in her power, now that he was bound to her by this marriage, and also by the hope of her will.
    Nearly about the same time, <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, that great
    physician, committed a theft and murder in his own house in the following manner: —As there was
    in his house a chest, in which he knew there was a good deal of money and gold, he murdered by
    night two slaves, while they were asleep, and threw their bodies into a fishpond. Then he cut
    out the bottom of the chest, and took out . . . . sesterces, and five pounds' weight of gold,
    with the knowledge of one of his slaves, a boy not grown up. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="180" resp="perseus"><p>
    The theft being discovered the next day, all the suspicion attached to those slaves who did not
    appear. When the cutting out of the bottom of the chest was noticed, men asked how that could
    have been done? One of the friends of Sassia recollected that he had lately seen at an auction,
    among a lot of very small things, a crooked and twisted saw sold, with teeth in every direction;
    and by such an instrument as this it seemed that the bottom of the chest might have been cut
    round in the manner in which it was. To make my story short, inquiry is made of the auctioneer.
    That saw is found to have become the property of <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>.
    When suspicion was excited in this manner, and<persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> was
    openly accused, the boy who had been privy to the deed got alarmed; he gave information of the
    whole business to his mistress; the men were found in the fishpond;
      <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> was thrown into prison; and the money, though
    not all of it, was found in his shop.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="181" resp="perseus"><p> A prosecution for theft
    is commenced against him. For what else can any one suspect? Do you say this, that when a chest
    had been pillaged, money taken away, only some of it recovered, and when men had been murdered,
    that then an investigation into the death of Oppianicus was instituted? Who will you get to
    believe that? What is that you could possibly allege, that would be less possible? In the next
    place, to pass over the other points, was an investigator made into the death of Oppianicus
    three years after that death?—Yes, and being exasperated against him on account of her former
    grudge, she then, without the slightest reason, demanded that same Nicostratus, in order to
    submit him to the question. Oppianicus at first refused. After she threatened that she would
    take her daughter away from him, and alter her will, he, I will not say brought his most
    faithful servant to that most cruel woman, for her to subject him to the question, but he
    clearly gave him up to her for punishment. </p></div>
    <milestone n="65" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="182" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>After three years had elapsed, then, the long projected investigation into the death of her
    husband was made; and what slaves were especially pointed at in the investigation ? I suppose
    some new circumstances were alleged in the accusation; some new men were involved in the
    suspicion. <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> and Nicostratus were those mentioned.
    What? had not an ample investigation into their conduct taken place at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>? Was it not so? The woman, now mad, not by disease, but with
    wickedness, though she had conducted an investigation at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, though it had been resolved, in accordance with the opinion of Titus Annius,
    Lucius Rutilius, Publius Saturius, and other most honourable men, that the investigation had
    been carried far enough, still, three years afterwards she attempted to institute an
    investigation into the conduct of the same men, allowing, I will not say no man, (lest you
    should say by chance that some one of the inhabitants of the colony was present,) but no
    respectable man to be present; and this investigation was in reality directed against the life
    of her son. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="183" resp="perseus"><p> Can you say, (for it occurs to me to think what
    possibly can be said, even if it has not been said as yet,) that when the investigation about
    the robbery was proceeding, <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> made some confession
    respecting the poisoning? By this single means, O judges, truth, though kept under by the
    wickedness of many, often raises its head, and the defence which has been cut away from
    innocence gets breathing time; either because they who are cunning in devising fraud, do not
    dare to execute all that they devise, or because they whose audacity is conspicuous and
    prominent, are destitute of the craftiness of malice. But if cunning were bold, or audacity
    crafty, it would scarcely be possible to resist them. Was there no robbery committed? Nothing
    was more notorious at Larinum. Did no suspicion attach to
     <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>? On the contrary, he was accused on account of
    the circumstance of the saw, and he was also informed against by the boy who was his accomplice.
    Was that not stated in the investigation? Why, what other reason was there for making the
    investigation at all? Did <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> then, (this is what you
    are bound to say, and what Sassia was constantly saying at that time,) while the investigation
    was going on about the robbery, while under the torture, make any confession about the
    poisoning! </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="184" resp="perseus"><p> Behold now, here is the case which I have just
    mentioned. The woman abounds in audacity, she is deficient in contrivance and in ability. For
    many documents of what came out in the investigation are preserved, which have been read to you,
    and made public, those very documents which he said were then sealed up; and in all these
    documents there is not one letter about theft. It never once occurred to her to write out the
    first speech of <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> about the robbery, and after
    that, to add to it some expression about poisoning, which might seem not to have been extracted
    by any interrogatory, but to have been wrung from him by pain. The investigation into the
    robbery was superseded by the suspicion of the poisoning, which was a previous subject for
    investigation, which this very woman herself had pointed out; who, after she had come to the
    resolution (being compelled thereto by the opinion of her friends,) that the examination had
    been pushed far enough, for three years afterwards loved that man
      <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> above all the other slaves, and held him in the
    greatest honour, and loaded him with all sorts of kindnesses.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="185" resp="perseus"><p>When, therefore, the investigation into a robbery was going on, and that robbery too which he, beyond dispute, had committed, did
    he then abstain from saying a word about that which was the subject of the investigation, but at
    once say something about the poisoning?
 And did he never say
    one word at all about the robbery, (even if not at the time when he ought to have said it,
    still) either at the end, or middle, at any part whatever of his examination? <milestone n="66" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You see now, O judges, that that wicked woman, with the same hand with which she would murder
    her son, if it were in her power, has made up this false report of the examination. And who, I
    should like to know, has signed this report of the examination? Name any one person. You will
    find no one except perhaps a man of that sort, whom I would rather mention than have no one
    named. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="186" resp="perseus"><p> What do you say, O Titus Attius? will you bring
    before the court matter involving danger to a man's life, will you bring forward the information
    laid with respect to this wickedness, and the fortunes of another, all written down in this
    document, and yet refuse to name the author of this document, or the witness, or any one who
    will in any respect confirm it? And will such men as these judges, before whom we stand, approve
    of this destruction which you have drawn forth out of the mother's bosom against her most
    innocent son? Be it so then; these documents have no author. What next? Why is not the
    investigation itself reserved for the judges; for the friends and connections of Oppianicus,
    whom she had invited to be present before, and for this identical time? What was done to these
    men, Strato and Nicostratus? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="187" resp="perseus"><p> I ask of you, O Oppianicus,
    what you say was done to your slave Nicostratus? whom you, as you were shortly about to accuse
    this man, ought to have taken to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, to have given
    him an opportunity of giving information; lastly, to have preserved him unhurt for examination,
    to have preserved him for these judges, and to have preserved him for this time. For, O judges,
    know that <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> was crucified, having had his tongue
    cut out; for there is no one of all the citizens of Larinum who does not know this. That frantic
    woman was afraid, not of her own conscience, not of the hatred of her fellow-citizens, not of
    the reports flying about among everybody; but, as if every one was not likely to be hereafter
    the witness of her wickedness, she was afraid of being convicted by the last words of a dying
    slave. 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="188" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> What a prodigy is this, O ye immortal gods! What shall we
    say of this enormity? What shall we call this enormous and inhuman wickedness, or where shall we
    say it has its birth? For now, in truth, you see, O judges, that I did not, at the beginning of
    my oration, say what I did about his mother without the strongest and most unavoidable
    necessity; for there is no evil, no wickedness, which she has not from the very beginning
    wished, and prayed for, and planned and wrought against her son. I say nothing of that first
    jury which she did him through her lust—I say nothing of her nefarious marriage with her
    son-in-law—I say nothing of her daughter driven from her husband by the profligate desires of
    her mother,—because they have relation, not to the existing danger of his life to my client, but
    to the common disgrace of the family. I say nothing of the second marriage with Oppianicus, to
    ensure which she first received from him his dead sons as hostages, and then married, to the
    grief of the family, and the destruction of her stepsons. I pass over how, when she knew that
    Aurius Melinus, whose mother-in-law she had formerly been, and whose wife she had been a little
    before that, had been proscribed and murdered by the contrivance of Oppianicus, she chose for
    herself that place as the abode and home of her married state, in which she might every day
    behold the proofs of the death of her former husband, and the spoils of his fortune. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="189" resp="perseus"><p> This is what I complain of first of all,—that wickedness which is now
    at length thoroughly revealed, of the poisoning of Fabricius; which, being then recent, was
    suspicious to others, incredible to him, but which now appears plain and evident to everybody.
    In fact, his mother is hardly concealed in that act of poisoning; nothing was devised by
    Oppianicus without the counsel of that woman; and unless that had been the case, certainly she
    would not afterwards, when the affair was detected, have departed from him as from a wicked
    husband, but she would have fled from him as from a most pitiless enemy, and she would have for
    ever left that house overflowing with every imaginable wickedness. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="190" resp="perseus"><p> She not only did not do that, but from that time forth she omitted no
    opportunity of planning some treachery or other, but day and night, she, a mother, directed all
    her thoughts to compassing the destruction of her son. But first, in order to confirm Oppianicus
    in his resolution of becoming the accuser of her son, she bound him to her by gifts and
    presents, by giving him her daughter in marriage, and by the hope of her inheritance. <milestone n="67" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, among other people too, when sudden enmities have arisen between relations, we
    often see divorces and ruptures of connections take place; but this woman thought that no one
    could be sufficiently reined upon as the prosecutor of her son, unless he first married his
    sister. Other men, induced by new connections, often lay aside their ancient enmities; she
    thought that a connection with the family would be a pledge to ensure the strengthening of
    enmity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="191" resp="perseus"><p> And she was not only diligent in providing an
    accuser for her son, but she also planned how to furnish him with the requisite weapons. Hence
    were all those tamperings with the slaves, both by means of threats and of promises; hence those
    repeated and cruel investigations into the death of Oppianicus; to which at last it was not the
    moderation of the woman, but the authority of her friends that put a limit. From the same
    wickedness proceeded that investigation conducted at Larinum three years afterwards. The false
    reports of the investigation were fabricated by the same frantic criminality. From that same
    frenzy proceeded also that abominable cutting out of her victim's tongue; and lastly, the whole
    contrivance of this accusation has been managed and carried out by her. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="192" resp="perseus"><p> And when she had herself sent the accuser armed with all these weapons against
    her son to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, she remained herself a little while at
    Larinum, for the sake of seeking out and hiring witnesses. But afterwards, when news was brought
    to her that this man's trial was coming on, she immediately flew hither, to prevent any
    diligence being wanting on the part of the accusers, or any money to the witnesses; or perhaps
    lest she, as his mother, should lose this sight which she had so eagerly desired, of this man's
    mourning habit, and grief, and melancholy condition. <milestone n="68" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But now, what sort of journey do you think that woman had to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>? which I, by means of the neighbourhood of the people of Aquinum and
    Venafrum, heard and ascertained from many people. What throngings of the people were there in
    these cities! what groanings of men and women! that a woman should go from Larinum, should go
    all the way from the Adriatic to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, with a large
    retinue, and great sums of money, in order to be the more easily able to convict and oppress by
    a capital charge, falsely trumped up, her own son! 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="193" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> There was not one of all those people (I may almost say)
    who did not think that every place required purifying, by which she had passed on her journey;
    no one who did not think the very earth itself, the common mother of us all, polluted by the
    footsteps of that wicked mother. Accordingly, she could not stay long in any city; of all that
    number of people, who might have been her entertainers, not one was found who did not flee from
    the contagion of her sight. She trusted herself to night and solitude, rather than to any city
    or to any host. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="194" resp="perseus"><p> But now, which of us does she think is
    ignorant of what she is doing, of what she is contriving, of what she is thinking? We know whom
    she has addressed herself to, whom she has promised money to, whose good faith she has
    endeavoured to undermine by means of bribes. Moreover, we are acquainted with her nocturnal
    sacrifices, which she thinks are secret, and her wicked prayers, and her abominable vows; in
    which she makes even the immortal gods to be witnesses of her wickedness, and does not perceive
    that the minds of the gods are propitiated by piety, by religion, and holy prayers, not by a
    polluted superstition, nor by victims slain to conciliate their sanction for acts of wickedness.
    This insanity and barbarity of hers I may well feel sure that the immortal gods have rejected
    with disgust from their altars and temples. </p></div>
    <milestone n="69" unit="chapter"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="195" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Do you now, O judges, whom fortune has appointed to be a sort of other gods, as it were, to
    Aulus Cluentius, my client, throughout his whole life, ward off this savage attack of his mother
    from her son's head. Many men, while sitting as judges, have pardoned the sins of the children
    out of pity for the parents;—we now entreat you, hot to give up the most virtuously spent life
    of this man to the inhumanity of his mother, especially when you may see all his fellow-citizens
    in his municipality on the other side of the question. Know all of you, O judges, (it is a most
    incredible statement, but still a perfectly true one,) that all the men of Larinum, who have
    been able to do so, have come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, in order by
    their zeal, and by the display of their numbers, to comfort this man as far as they could, in
    this his great danger; know that that town is at the present moment delivered to the keeping of
    children and women, and that it is now, at this time of common peace over <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, defended by its domestic forces only. But even those who
    are left behind are equally eager with those whom you see present here, and are harassed day and
    night by anxiety about the result of this trial. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="196" resp="perseus"><p> They think
    that you are going to deliver a decision, not about the fortunes of one of their citizens, but
    about the condition, and the dignity, and all the advantages of the whole municipality. For the
    industry of that man in the common service of the municipality is extreme, O judges; his
    kindness to each individual citizen, and his justice and good faith towards all men, are of the
    highest order. Besides, he so preserves his high rank among his countrymen, and the position
    which he has inherited from his ancestors, that he equals the gravity, and wisdom, and
    popularity, and character for liberality of his ancestors. Therefore they give their public
    testimony in his favour, in words which signify not only their opinion of, and their esteem for
    him, but also their own anxiety of mind and grief. And while their panegyric is being read, I
    beg of you, who have brought it hither, to rise up. [ The panegyric on Cluentius, in pursuance
    of the resolution of the senators of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, is
    read.] </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="197" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> From the tears of these men, you, O judges, may
    easily imagine that the senators did not pass these resolutions without tears. Come now, how
    great is the zeal of his neighbours in his behalf, how incredible their good-will towards him,
    how great their anxiety for him. They have not, indeed, sent resolutions drawn up in papers of
    panegyric, but they have chosen their most honourable men, whom we are all acquainted with, to
    come hither in numbers, and to give their personal evidence in his favour. The Frentani are
    present, most noble men. The Marrucini a tribe of equal dignity, are present too. You see Roman
    knights, most honourable men, come to praise him from Teanum in <placeName key="tgn,7010380">Apulia</placeName>, and from Luceria. Most honourable panegyrics have been sent from
     <placeName key="perseus,Bovianum">Bovianum</placeName>, and from the whole of Samnium, and also
    the most honourable and noble men of these states have come too. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="198" resp="perseus"><p> As for those men who have farms in the district of <placeName key="perseus,Larinum">Larinum</placeName>, or business as merchants, or flocks and herds,
    honourable men and of the highest character, it is impossible to say how eager and anxious they
    are. It seems to me that there are not many men so beloved by a single individual as he is by
    all these nations. <milestone n="70" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>How I wish that Lucius Volusienus were not absent from my client's trial, a man of the
    greatest virtue and most exalted character! How I wish that I could say that Publius Helvidius
    Rufus was present, the most accomplished of all the Roman knights! who, while, in this man's
    cause, he was kept awake night and day, and while he was instructing me in many of the facts of
    this case, has been stricken with a severe and dangerous illness; but even while in this state
    of suffering, he is not less anxious for the acquittal of Cluentius than for his own recovery.
    You shall witness the equal zeal of Cnaeus Tudicius, a senator, a most virtuous and honour able
    man, shown both in giving evidence and in uttering an encomium on him. We speak with the same
    hope, but with more diffidence, of you, O Publius Volumnius, since you are one of the judges of
    Aulus Cluentius. In short, we assert to you that the
    good-will of all his neighbours towards this man is unequalled.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="199" resp="perseus"><p>His mother alone opposes the
    zeal of all these men, and their anxiety and diligence in his behalf, and my labour, who,
    according to the rules of old times, have pleaded the whole of this cause by myself, and also
    your equity, O judges, and your merciful dispositions. But what a mother! One whom you see
    hurried on, blinded by cruelty and wickedness,—whose desires no amount of infamy has ever
    restrained,—who, by the vices of her mind, has perverted all the laws of men to the foulest
    purposes,—whose folly is such, that no one can call her a human being,—whose violence is such,
    that no one can call her a woman,—whose barbarity is such, that no one can call her a mother.
    And she has changed even the names of relationships, and not only the name and laws of nature:
    the wife of her son-in-law, the mother-in-law of her son, the invader of her daughter's bed! she
    has come to such a pitch, that she has no resemblance, except in form, to a human creature. 
   </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="200" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Wherefore, O judges, if you hate wickedness, prevent the
    approach of a mother to a son's blood; inflict on the parent this incredible misery, of the
    victory and safety of her children; allow the mother (that she may not rejoice at being deprived
    of her son) to depart defeated rather by your equity. But if, as your nature requires, you love
    modesty, and beneficence, and virtue, then at last raise up this your suppliant, O judges, who
    has been exposed for so many years to undeserved odium and danger,—who now for the first time,
    since the beginning of that fire kindled by the actions and fanned by the desires of others, has
    begun to raise his spirits from the hope of your equity, and to breathe awhile after the alarms
    he has suffered,—all whose hopes depend on you,—whom many, indeed, wish to be saved, but whom
    you alone have the power to save. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="201" resp="perseus"><p> Habitus prays to you, O
    judges, and with tears implores you, not to abandon him to odium, which ought to have no power
    in courts of justice; nor to his mother, whose vows and prayers you are bound to reject from
    your minds; nor to Oppianicus, that infamous man, already condemned and dead. <milestone n="71" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>But if any misfortune in this trial should overthrow this innocent man, verily, that miserable
    man, O judges, if indeed (which will be hard for him) he remains alive at all, will complain
    frequently and bitterly that that poison of Fabricius was ever detected. But if at that time
    that information had not been given, it would have been to that most unhappy man not poison, but
    a medicine to relieve him from many distresses; and, lastly, perhaps even his mother would have
    attended his funeral, and would have feigned to mourn for the death of her son. But now, what
    will have been gained by his escape then, beyond making his life appear to have been preserved
    from the snares of death which then surrounded him for greater grief, and beyond depriving him
    when dead of a place in his father's tomb? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="202" resp="perseus"><p> He has been long
    enough, O judges, in misery. He has been years enough struggling with odium. No one has been so
    hostile to him, except his parent, that we may not think his ill-will satisfied by this time.
    You who are just to all men, who, the more cruelly any one is attacked, do the more kindly
    protect him, preserve Aulus Cluentius, restore him uninjured to his municipality. Restore him to
    his friends, and neighbours, and connections, whose eagerness in his behalf you see. Bind all
    those men for ever to you and to your children. This business, O judges, is yours; it is worthy
    of your dignity, it is worthy of your clemency. This is rightly expected of you, to release a
    most virtuous and innocent man, one dear and beloved by many men, at last from these his
    misfortunes; so that all men may see that odium and faction may be excited in popular
    assemblies, but that in courts of justice there is room only for truth.
    </p></div>
  </div>
 </body></text>

</TEI>
