<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>In Defense of Cnaeus Plancius </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN DEFENCE OF CNAEUS PLANCIUS.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>Cnaeus Plancius had been quaestor in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                        >Macedonia</placeName> when Cicero fled there from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, and had been at that time of the
                    greatest assistance to him. He had now been chosen aedile, but was accused by a
                    disappointed candidate, Marcus Laterensis, of bribery and corruption; and Cicero
                    (though there had been a good deal of coldness between them of late, as Plancius
                    when tribune of the people had very much altered towards him and shown an
                    inclination to take the part of his adversaries) defended him in the following
                    speech. </p>
                <p>The speech appears to have been spoken in the year A. U. C. 609. Plancius was
                    acquitted.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>When, O judges, I saw that on account of the eminent and singular good faith of
                Cnaeus Plancius, shown in taking care of my safety, so many excellent men were
                favourers of his cause, I felt no ordinary pleasure, because I saw that the
                recollection of what happened at the time of my necessities was pleading for him
                whose kindness had been my preservation. But when I heard that men, some of whom
                were my enemies, and some of whom were envious of me, favoured this accusation and
                that the very same thing was now adverse to the interests of Cnaeus Plancius in this
                trial which had been advantageous to him in his canvass, I was grieved, O judges,
                and was very indignant at the idea of his safety being endangered for the sole
                reason that he, by his benevolence, and energy, and vigilance had protected my
                safety and my life. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But now, O judges, the sight
                of you, and the fact of such men as you being the judges, strengthens and refreshes
                my mind, when I look upon and behold each individual of you; for in all this number
                I see no one to whom my safety has not been dear, no one who has not acted with the
                greatest <pb n="102"/> kindness towards me, no one to whom I am not under eternal
                obligations from the recollection of their services. Therefore I do not fear that
                the care shown by Cnaeus Plancius for my safety will be any injury to him with those
                men who themselves have wished above all things to see me in safety; and, O judges,
                it has more frequently come into my mind that it is a strange thing that Marcus
                Laterensis, a man who has shown the greatest regard for my dignity and safety,
                should have picked out this man of all the world to institute a prosecution against,
                than that I have any ground to fear lest he should appear to you to have had good
                reason for doing so. </p>
            <p><milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Although I do not assume so much, or claim so much
                importance for myself, O judges, as to think that Cnaeus Plancius is entitled to
                impunity on account of his kindness towards me. If I do not display to you that his
                life is most upright, his habits most virtuous, his good faith unimpeachable,—if I
                do not prove him to be a man of perfect temperance, piety, and innocence, I will not
                object to your punishing him; but if I establish that he has every quality which may
                be expected in the character of a virtuous man, then I will beg of you, O judges, to
                grant, at my entreaty, your pity to that man, through whose pity it is that I myself
                have been preserved in safety. In truth, in addition to the labour which I am
                devoting to this cause, in a greater degree than I think necessary in other trials.
                I have this anxiety also, that I have not only to speak on behalf of Cnaeus
                Plancius, whose safety I am bound to defend equally with my own, but on behalf of
                myself also, since the prosecutors have said almost more about me than they have
                about the merits of the case, and about the real defendant. <milestone n="2"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="4" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Although, O judges, if they have found any fault in me which is not connected with
                the case of my present client, I am not much disturbed about that; for I am not
                afraid that, because it is a very rare thing to meet with grateful men, on that
                account it can really be considered as a charge against me when those men say that I
                am too grateful. But as for the points that have been urged by them, when they have
                said either that the services done me by Cnaeus Plancius were of less importance
                than I make them out to be; or that if they were ever so great, still they ought not
                to have that weight with you which I considered them entitled to; these <pb n="103"
                /> points, O judges, must be touched on by me with moderation, indeed, lest I should
                give any offence myself; and not until I have fully replied to the accusations
                brought against him, lest my client should seem to have been defended not so much by
                his own innocence, as by the recollection of his conduct at the time of my
                necessity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But, considering how plain and simple my case is, O judges, the line to be taken by
                me in defending it is exceedingly difficult and slippery. For if it were merely
                necessary for me to argue against Laterensis, yet even this would be a very
                vexatious thing, considering our great friendship and intimacy; for it is an old
                principle of genuine and real friendship, such as subsists between him and me, that
                friends should always have the same wishes; nor is there any surer bond of
                friendship than an agreement in and community of designs and wishes. But the most
                annoying circumstance to me in the case is, not that I have merely to argue against
                him, but much more, that I have to argue against him in a cause in which it seems
                impossible to avoid drawing some comparison between the parties themselves.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For Laterensis asks, and presses this point
                above all others, in what virtue, in what sort of renown or worth Plancius is
                superior to himself. And so, if I admit his high qualifications,—and he has plenty
                of them, and important ones too—I must not only run the risk of Plancius losing this
                dignity which he has obtained, but he must submit also to the suspicion of bribery.
                If I speak of my client as superior to him, then my speech will be considered
                insulting, and I shall be supposed to say, (as he puts the question himself,) that
                Laterensis was surpassed by Plancius in real worth. And so I must either hurt the
                feelings of a man who is a great friend of mine, if I follow the line taken by the
                prosecutor, or else I must abandon the safety of one who has behaved to me with the
                greatest kindness. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But I, O Laterensis, will confess that I should be conducting this cause in the most
                blind and headlong manner, if I were to say that you could be surpassed in worth by
                either Plancius, or any one else. Therefore I will discard that comparison to which
                you invite me and will proceed to those arguments to which the cause itself
                naturally conducts me. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What? Do you think that the
                people is judge of a man's worth? Perhaps it is sometimes. I wish indeed it were so
                    <pb n="104"/> always. But it is very seldom the case, and if it ever is, it is
                so when the question is concerning the election of those magistrates to whom it
                considers that its own safety is entrusted. At the less important <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, honours are gained by the diligence and
                influence of the candidates, and not by those high qualities which we see exist in
                you. For, as to what concerns the people, that man must always be an incompetent
                judge of worth who either envies any one or favours any one, although you cannot, O
                Laterensis, point to any good quality in yourself, as peculiarly entitled to praise,
                which Plancius has not in common with you. </p>
            <p><milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But all this shall be discussed presently. At
                present I am only arguing about the right of the people, which both can and
                sometimes does pass over worthy men; and it does not follow because a man has been
                passed over by the people who ought not to have been, that he who has not been
                passed over is to be condemned by the judges. For if that were the case, the judges
                would have that power which the senate itself could not maintain in the times of our
                ancestors,—namely, that of being correctors of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia</foreign>: or a power which is even more intolerable than that; for at
                that time a man who had been elected did not enter upon the duties of his office if
                the senators had not approved of his election; but now it is required of you to
                correct the judgment of the Roman people by the banishment of the man who has been
                elected by them. Therefore, although I have entered upon the cause by a door which I
                did not wish to open, still I seem to hope, O Laterensis, that my speech will be so
                far removed from all suspicion of being intended to give you offence, that I may
                rather reprove you for bringing your own dignity into an unreasonable contest, than
                attempt myself to disparage it by any injurious expressions on my part. <milestone
                    n="4" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="9" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Do you think your temperance, your industry, your attachment to the republic, your
                virtue, your innocence, your integrity, and your exertions disregarded and despised
                and trampled on, just because you have not been made aedile? See, O Laterensis, how
                greatly I differ from you in opinion. If, I declare to God, there were only ten
                virtuous, and wise, and just, and worthy men in this state who had pronounced you
                unworthy of the aedileship, I should think that decision a much more unfavourable
                one to you than this has been, on account <pb n="105"/> of which you fear that this
                may seem to be the opinion of the people. For in the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia</foreign> the people does not invariably act in obedience to its
                judgment; but it is usually influenced by interest, or it yields to entreaties and
                it elects those by whom it has been canvassed with the greatest assiduity. And
                lastly if it does proceed according to its judgment, still it is not led to form
                that judgment by any careful selection, or by wisdom, but more frequently by impulse
                and what I may even call a sort of precipitation. For there is no wisdom in the
                common people, no method, no discrimination, no diligence, and wise men have at all
                times considered the things which the people may have done necessary to be endured,
                but not at all invariably necessary to be praised. So that when you say that you
                ought to have been elected aedile, it is the people you are finding fault with, and
                not your competitor. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Allow that you were more
                worthy than Plancius (though that point I will contest with you presently, though
                without at all disparaging your pretensions or character,) still allow that you were
                more worthy, yet it is not your competitor by whom you have been defeated, but the
                people by whom you have been passed over, that is in fault. </p>
            <p>And in this affair you ought to recollect that at all <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia</foreign>, and especially at those held for the election of aediles, it
                is the party spirit of the people, and not their deliberate judgment which bears
                sway, that their votes are coaxed out of them not extorted by merit, that the voters
                are more apt to consider what obligations they themselves are under to each
                individual, than what benefits the republic has received at his hands. But if you
                insist on it that it is their deliberate judgment, then you must not annul it but
                bear it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The people has decided wrongly. Still it
                has decided. It ought not to have decided so. Still it had the power. I will not
                bear it. But many most illustrious and wise citizens have borne it. For this is the
                inalienable privilege of a free people, and especially of this the chief people of
                the world, the lord and conqueror of all nations, to be able by their votes to give
                or to take away what they please to or from any one. And it is our duty,—ours, I
                say, who are driven about by the winds and waves of this people, to hear the whims
                of the people with moderation, to strive to win over their affections when alienated
                from us, to retain them when we have won them, <pb n="106"/> to tranquilize them
                when in a state of agitation. If we do not think honours of any great consequence,
                we are not bound to be subservient to the people; if we do strive for them, then we
                must be unwearied in soliciting them. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="12" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I proceed now to take on myself the part of the people, so as to argue with you in
                their language rather than in my own. If the people then could meet you, and speak
                with one voice, it would say this-—“I, O Laterensis, have not preferred Plancius to
                you; but, as you were both equally virtuous men, I have conferred my favours on him
                who entreated me for them, rather than on him who had not solicited me with any
                great humility.” You will reply, I suppose, that you relied on your high character,
                and the antiquity of your family, and did not think it necessary to canvass very
                laboriously. But the people will remind you of its own established principles, and
                of the precedents of its ancestors. It will say that it has always chosen to be
                asked for these honours, and to be solicited eagerly. It will tell you that it
                preferred Marcus Seius, a man who was unable to keep even his dignity as a knight
                undamaged by an adverse decision in a court of justice, to a man of the highest
                rank, most unimpeachable, and most eloquent Marcus Piso. It will tell you that it
                preferred to Quintus Catulus, a man of the most illustrious family, a most wise and
                admirable man, I will not say Caius Seranus a most foolish man, for nevertheless he
                was a noble; nor Caius Fimbria, a new man, for he was a magnanimous man and a wise
                counselor; but Cnaeus Mallius, a man not only of no rank or family at all, but
                utterly destitute of virtue and ability, and of contemptible and sordid habits of
                life. —<milestone n="13" unit="section"/>“My eyes,” says the people, “looked in vain
                for you when you were at <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>; for I
                should have preferred reaping the benefit of your virtue myself to letting your
                companions have it all to themselves; and the more it was an object to me to do so,
                the more did you keep aloof from me. At all events, I did not see you. Then you
                deserted and abandoned me, though thirsting for your virtue; for you had begun to
                offer yourself as a candidate for the tribuneship of the people at a time which was
                especially in need of your eloquence and virtue; and when you abandoned your canvass
                for that office, if you intimated by so doing that in such a stormy time you could
                not take the helm, I had reason to doubt your courage; <pb n="107"/> but if you did
                so because you did not then choose to assume so much responsibility, then I had
                grounds for questioning your attachment to me. But if the truth was, as I rather
                believe, that you reserved yourself for other times, I too,” the Roman people will
                say, “have now recalled you to the time for which you had of your own accord
                reserved yourself. Offer yourself, then, now for that magistracy in which you can be
                of great use to me. Whoever the aediles are, I shall have the same games prepared
                for me; but it is of the greatest consequence who are the tribunes of the people.
                Either, then, give me those exertions of yours which you encouraged me to hope for,
                or, if your heart is most set on what is of the least consequence to me, how can you
                expect that I will give you the aedileship, especially when you ask for it with such
                indifference? But if you wish to gain the most distinguished honours, as most suited
                to your worth, then learn, I pray you, to solicit them of me with a little more
                earnestness.” <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="14" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>This is what the people says to you. But what I say to you, O Laterensis, is this:
                that the judge has nothing to do with inquiring why you were defeated, as long as
                you were not defeated through bribery. For it as often as any man is passed over who
                ought not to have been passed over, the man who has been elected is to be condemned,
                there will no longer be any reason for canvassing the people at all. There will be
                no reason in waiting for the polling or for addressing entreaties to the magistrates
                or for the final declaration of the state of the poll; the moment that I see who are
                standing I shall say—“This man is of a consular family that man is of a praetorian
                one; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I see that all the rest are of equestrian
                rank; they are all without stain all equally virtuous and upright men but it is
                necessary that the distinctions of rank should be observed that the praetorian
                family should yield to the consular, and that the equestrian body should not contend
                with a praetorian house.” There is an end to all eagerness for any candidate, an end
                to all voting; there are no longer any contests; the people has no longer any
                liberty of choice in electing magistrates; there is no anxiety to see how the votes
                will be given; nothing will ever happen, (as is so often the case,) contrary to the
                general expectation; there will be for the future no variety in the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>. But if it is constantly happening that we
                marvel why some men have been <pb n="108"/> elected, and why some men have not; if
                the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName> and those waves of the
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, like a deep and wide sea, swell in
                such a manner, as if through some tide or other, that they approach one party and
                recede from another; why, when the impulse of party spirit is so great and when so
                much is done with precipitation, are we to seek for any rational explanation, any
                deliberate intention or any system in such a case? </p>
            <p><milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Do not then, O Laterensis, insist on my drawing
                any comparison between you. In truth, if the voting tablet is dear to the people,
                which shows the countenances of men, while it conceals their intentions, and which
                gives them the liberty of doing whatever they please, while they can promise
                whatever they are asked, why do you require that to be done in a court of justice
                which is not done in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus
                Martius</placeName>?—This man is more worthy than that man. It is a very grave
                assertion to make. What then is it more reasonable to say? Say this, (and this is
                the question, this is sufficient for the judge)—This is the man who has been
                elected. Why should he have been elected rather than I? Either I do not know, or I
                do not choose to say, or lastly, (which, however, would be a very vexatious thing to
                me to say, and yet I ought to be able to say with impunity), he ought not to have
                been. For what would you gain if I were to have recourse to this last defence, that
                the people had done what it chose, and not what it ought to have done? <milestone
                    n="7" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="17" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>What will you say, if, besides, I defend the act of the people, O Laterensis, and
                prove that Cnaeus Plancius did not creep by underhand means to that honour, but that
                he arrived at it by the regular course which has at all times been open to men born
                in this equestrian rank of ours; can I, by this argument expunge from your speech
                the comparison between you two, which cannot be handled without an appearance of
                insult, and can I thus bring you at last to the merits of the case itself and of
                your accusation? If, because he is the son of a Roman knight he ought to have been
                inferior to you, all the rest who were candidates at the same time with you were the
                sons of Roman knights. I say no more: but this I do wonder at, why you should be
                angry with this man above all the rest who was the furthest removed from you. In
                truth, if, at any time, as is sometimes the case, I am pushed about in the crowd, I
                do not find fault with <pb n="109"/> that man who is on the very crown of the Via
                Sacra, when I am pushed up against the arch of Fabius; but with him who was against
                me and pushes me. But you are not angry with Quintus Pedius, a very gallant man; nor
                with Aulus Plotius,<note anchored="true">Aulus Plotius was, however, the other
                    aedile elect, as Plancius's colleague.</note> whom I see here, a most
                accomplished citizen, and my own intimate friend; but you think yourself defeated by
                him who has also defeated them, rather than by those who were nearest yourself in
                the number of votes, and who therefore pressed more immediately on you. <milestone
                    n="18" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But, nevertheless, you compare yourself with Plancius, in the first place as to your
                race and family, in which he is beaten by you. For why should not I confess what
                cannot he denied? But he is not more inferior to you in this respect than I was to
                my competitors, both on other occasions, and when I was a candidate for the
                consulship. But beware lest these very particulars for which you look down upon him
                may have told in his favour. For let us make the comparison in this way—You are
                descended from a consular family on both sides. Have you any doubt then that all
                those who favour the nobility of birth, who think that the finest of all things, who
                are influenced by the images and great names of your ancestors, all voted for you as
                aedile. I myself have not a doubt of it. But if the number of those who are thus
                devoted to high birth is not very large, is that our fault? In truth, let us go back
                to the head and origin of each of your families. <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="19" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You are of that most ancient municipal town of <placeName key="perseus,Tusculum"
                    >Tusculum</placeName>, from which many of our consular families are derived,
                among which is also the Juventian family; there have not so many families of that
                rank proceeded from all the other municipal towns put together. Plancius comes from
                the prefecture of <placeName key="tgn,7006695">Atina</placeName>; certainly a less
                ancient and distinguished abode, and not so near to the city. How much difference do
                you think this ought to make in standing for an office? In the first place, which
                people do you suppose are most eager to support their own fellow-citizens; the
                people of <placeName key="tgn,7006695">Atina</placeName>, or those of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>? The one, (for this is a matter with
                which I may easily be well acquainted, on account of my neighbourhood to them,) when
                they saw the <pb n="110"/> father of this most accomplished and excellent man,
                Cnaeus Saturninus, elected aedile, and afterwards, when they saw him elected
                praetor, were delighted in a most extraordinary manner, because he was the first man
                who had ever brought a curule honour, not only into that family, but even into that
                prefecture. But I never understood that the others (I suppose because that
                municipality is crammed full of consuls, for I know to a certainty that they are not
                an ill-natured people) were particularly delighted at any honour obtained by their
                fellow-citizens. This is our feeling, and it is the feeling of our municipal towns.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Why should I speak of myself; or of my
                brother? The very fields—I might almost say, the very hills themselves,—supported us
                in the pursuit of our honours. Do you ever see any man of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName> boast of that great man, Marcus
                Cato, the first man in every sort of virtue, or of Tiberius Coruncanius, though a
                citizen of their own municipal town, or of all the Fulvii? No one ever mentions
                them. But if ever you fall in with a citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Arpinum"
                    >Arpinum</placeName>, you are forced, whether you will or no, perhaps, to hear
                something about us, but at all events something about Caius Marius. In the first
                place, then, Plancius had the ardent zeal of his fellow-citizens in his favour; you
                had no more than was likely to exist among men who are by this time surfeited with
                honours. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> In the next place, your fellow-citizens
                are indeed most admirable men, but still they are very few in number if they are
                compared with the people of <placeName key="tgn,7006695">Atina</placeName>. The
                prefecture to which Plancius belongs is so full of the bravest men, that no city in
                all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> can be pronounced more populous.
                And that multitude you now behold, O judges, in mourning attire and in distress
                addressing its supplications to you. All these Roman knights whom you see here, all
                these aerarian tribunes, (for we have sent the common people away from this court,
                though they were all present at the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>,)—how
                much strength, how much dignity did they not add to my client's demand of the
                aedileship? They did not give him only the aid of the Terentian tribe, of which I
                will speak hereafter, but they added dignity to him, they kept their eyes fixed upon
                him, they attended him with a solid, and vigorous, and unceasing escort; and even
                now my own municipal town is greatly interested in his cause, from the sort of
                connection which the fact of their being neighbours to him engenders. <pb n="111"/>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="22" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Everything which I am saying about Plancius, I say having experienced the truth of it
                in my own case. For we of <placeName key="perseus,Arpinum">Arpinum</placeName> are
                near neighbours of the people of <placeName key="tgn,7006695">Atina</placeName>. It
                is a neighbourhood to be praised, and even to be loved, retaining the old-fashioned
                habits of kindness for one another: one not tainted with ill-nature, nor accustomed
                to falsehood, not insincere, nor treacherous, nor learned in the suburban, or shall
                I say, the city artifices of dissimulation. There was not one citizen of Arpinum who
                was not anxious for Plancius, not one citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Sora"
                    >Sora</placeName>, or of <placeName key="perseus,Casinum">Casinum</placeName>,
                or of <placeName key="perseus,Aquinum">Aquinum</placeName>. The whole of that most
                celebrated district, the territory of <placeName key="perseus,Venafrum"
                    >Venafrum</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Allifae">Allifae</placeName>,
                in short, the whole of that rugged mountainous faithful simple district, a district
                cherishing its own native citizens, thought that it was honoured itself in his
                honour, that its own consequence was increased by his dignity. And from those same
                municipalities Roman knights are now present here, having been sent by the public
                authority, commissioned to bear evidence in his favour; nor is their anxiety in his
                behalf now inferior to the zeal which they displayed then. For, in truth, it is a
                more terrible thing to be stripped of one's goods than not to attain a dignity. </p>
            <p><milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Therefore, although the other qualifications, O
                Laterensis, those which your ancestors bequeathed to you, were more conspicuous in
                you than in him; yet, on the other hand, Plancius had an advantage over you not only
                in the zeal of his municipality, but in that of his whole neighbourhood. Unless,
                indeed, the neighbourhood of <placeName key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>
                to Lavicum, or <placeName key="perseus,Gabii">Gabii</placeName>, or Bovillae was any
                use to you; municipal towns in which you can now hardly find a single citizen to
                bear a part in the Latin holidays. I will add, if you like, that which you consider
                is even an objection to him, that his father is a farmer of the revenues. And who is
                there who does not know what a great assistance that body of men is to any one in
                seeking for any honour? For the flower of the Roman knights, the ornament of the
                state, the great bulwark of the republic is all comprehended in that body.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> Who is there, then, who can deny that that
                body showed extraordinary zeal in aiding Plancius in his contest for honour? And it
                was very natural that they should, because his father is a man who has for a long
                time been the head of the company of farmers; and because he was exceedingly beloved
                by his fellows of that <pb n="112"/> company; and because he canvassed them with the
                greatest diligence; and because he was entreating them in favour of his son; and
                because it was notorious that Plancius himself had both in his quaestorship and
                tribuneship done many kindnesses to that body; and because in promoting him they
                thought that they were promoting themselves, and consulting the welfare and dignity
                of their children. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Something, moreover, (I say it timidly, but still I must say it)—something we
                ourselves contributed to his success; not, indeed, by our riches, not by any
                invidious exertion of influence, not by any scarcely endurable stretch of power, but
                by the mention of his kindness to ourselves, by our pity for him, and by our prayers
                in his behalf. I appealed to the people; I went round the tribes, and besought them;
                I entreated even those who, of their own accord, offered themselves to me, who
                volunteered their promises. He prevailed, owing to the motive which I had for
                soliciting them, not owing to my interest. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> Nor,
                if a most honourable man, to whom there is nothing which may not deservedly be
                granted at his entreaty, failed, as you say, in obtaining something which he
                desired, am I arrogant if I say that I did prevail? For, to say nothing of the fact
                that I was exerting myself in behalf of a man who had great influence himself, that
                solicitation is always the most agreeable which is the most closely connected with
                previous obligations and friendship. Nor, indeed, did I ask for him in such a manner
                as to seem to request it because he was my intimate friend, because he was my
                neighbour, because I had always been on terms of the greatest intimacy with his
                father; but I asked as if I were soliciting on behalf of one who was as it were my
                parent, and the guardian of my safety. It was not my interest but the cause which
                prompted my requests, which was so influential. No one rejoiced at my restoration,
                no one grieved at my injury, to whom the pity shown me by this man was not
                acceptable. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> In truth, if before my return, good
                men in numbers, of their own accord, offered their services to Cnaeus Plancius when
                he was a candidate for the tribuneship, do not you suppose that, if my name, while I
                was absent was a credit to him, my entreaties, when I was present, must have been
                serviceable to him? Are the colonists of <placeName key="perseus,Minturnae"
                    >Minturnae</placeName> held in everlasting honour because they saved Caius
                Marius from the sword of civil war and from the hands of wicked men, because <pb
                    n="113"/> they received him in their houses, because they enabled him to recruit
                his strength when exhausted with fighting and with tossing on the waves, because
                they furnished him with means for his journey, and gave him a vessel and when he was
                leaving that land which he had saved, followed him with tears and prayers, and every
                good wish? And do you wonder that his good faith and merciful and courageous
                disposition was a credit to Cnaeus Plancius, who, whether I was expelled by
                violence, or yielded from a deliberate plan or conduct, received me, assisted me,
                protected me, and preserved me for these citizens, and for the senate and people of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, that they might be able at a
                subsequent time to restore me? <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="27"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>These circumstances which I have been mentioning might in truth have been sufficient
                to throw a veil over the vices of Cnaeus Plancius. Do not then wonder that in such a
                life as I am proceeding to describe, they should have been such numerous and great
                helps to him in the attainment of honour; for this is he, who, when quite a young
                man, having gone with Aulus Torquatus into <placeName key="tgn,7001242"
                    >Africa</placeName> was beloved by that most dignified and holy man, so worthy
                of every description of praise and honour, to as great a degree as the intimacy
                engendered by being messmates, and the modesty of a most pure minded youth allowed.
                And if he were present he would affirm it no less zealously than his cousin who is
                here present and his father-in-law, Titus Torquatus, his equal in every sort of
                glory and virtue, who is indeed connected with him in the closest bonds of
                relationship and connection, but these obligations of affection are so strong that
                those other reasons for intimacy drawn from relationship appear insignificant. He
                was in <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> afterwards as the comrade of
                Saturninus, his relation as a soldier of Quintus Metellus, who is here present, and
                as he was most highly approved of by them and is so to this day, he has a right to
                hope that he will be approved of by every one. In that province Caius Sacerdos was
                the lieutenant,—how virtuous, how consistent a man and Lucius Flaccus,—what a man,
                what a citizen was he! and they by their zeal in his behalf, and by their evidence,
                declare what sort of man they think Plancius. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> In
                    <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> he was a military tribune. In
                that same province he was afterwards quaestor. In the first place, <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> is so attached to him as these men, the
                chief men of their respective cities, state <pb n="114"/> it to be; who, though they
                were sent with another object, still, being moved by his unexpected danger, give him
                their countenance, sitting here by his side, and put forth all their exertions in
                his behalf; if they stand by him, they think that they shall be doing what is more
                acceptable to their fellow-citizens, than if they attend strictly and solely to
                their embassy, and to the commission that was entrusted to them. But Lucius
                Appuleius considers him so excellent a man, that by his attentions and kindness to
                him, he has gone beyond that principle of our ancestors which enjoins that praetors
                ought to consider themselves as standing in the light of parents to their quaestors.
                He was a tribune of the people, not perhaps as violent as those men whom you
                naturally extol, but certainly such a one, that if all had at all times been like
                him, a violent tribune would never have been wished for or regretted. <milestone
                    n="12" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="29" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I say nothing of those things which if they are less brought on the stage than
                others, still at all events are always praised when they do come to light; for
                instance, how he lives among his own relations; in the first place with his father,
                (for in my opinion filial affection is the foundation of all the virtues,) whom he
                venerates as a god, (and indeed a parent does not stand in a very different relation
                to his children,) but loves as a companion, as a brother, as a friend of his own
                age. Why should I speak of his conduct to his uncle? to his connections? to his
                relations? to this Cnaeus Saturninus whom you see in court, a most gallant man? And
                you may judge how desirous this man was of his attaining honour, when you see how he
                partakes of his grief. Why should I speak of myself? for I seem to myself, now that
                he is in danger, to be put on my own defence too. Why should I speak of all these
                virtuous men whom you see in court, with their garments changed for mourning robes?
                But these are all solid and well marked proofs, O judges; these are evidences of
                integrity, not coloured by forensic artifice, but deeply dyed with the indelible
                marks of truth. All that running about and caressing of the people is very easy
                work; it is looked at at a distance, not taken into the hand and examined; it makes
                a fine show if you do not get too near and shake it. </p>
            <p><milestone n="30" unit="section"/> I say, then, that this man is adorned with every
                high quality, both such as are eminent abroad and amiable at <pb n="115"/> home. I
                admit that he was inferior to you in some points, such as those of name and family;
                but in others I assert that he was superior to every one within the recollection of
                the present generation, in the zeal of his fellow-citizens, and neighbours, and of
                the companies of farmers in his behalf; equal to any one in virtue, integrity, and
                modesty; and yet do you wonder at his being elected aedile? </p>
            <p>Do you try to defile the brilliancy of such a life as this with those imputations?
                You impute adulteries to him which no one can recognise, not only by having ever
                heard any one's name mentioned, but even by having heard a suspicion breathed
                against him. You call him twice-married, in order to invent new words, and not only
                new accusations. You say that some one was taken by him into his province to gratify
                his lust; but that is not an accusation, but a random lie, ventured on from the
                expectation of impunity. You say that an actress was ravished by him. And this is
                said to have happened at <placeName key="tgn,7006695">Atina</placeName>, while he
                was quite young, by a sort of established licence of proceeding towards theatrical
                people, well known in all towns. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/> O how elegantly
                must his youth have been passed, when the only thing which is imputed to him is one
                that there was not much harm in, and when even that is found to be false. He
                released some one from prison illegally. The man you allude to was discharged out of
                ignorance—discharged, as you know, at the request of an intimate friend and a most
                virtuous young man; and the same man was arrested subsequently again. And these, and
                no others, are all the faults which you can discover to attribute to him throughout
                the whole of his life, while at the same time you affect to doubt his virtue, and
                religion, and integrity. <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>“But his father,” says the prosecutor, “ought to be considered an objection to the
                son.” O what a harsh expression, how unworthy of your honesty, O Laterensis! To say
                that in a capital trial, that in a contest where all his fortunes are at stake, a
                father ought to be an objection to his son in the eyes of such men as these judges!
                when even if he were ever so mean, or ever so sordid, still, by the mere name of
                father, he would have weight with mild and merciful judges; would have weight I say,
                because of the common feelings of all men, and through the sweet recommendation of
                nature. <milestone n="32" unit="section"/> But as that Cnaeus Plancius is a Roman
                knight, whose rank <pb n="116"/> as such is of that antiquity that his father, his
                grandfather, and all his ancestors were Roman knights before him, and in a most
                flourishing prefecture<note anchored="true">“In some Italian towns there was a
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">praefectus juri dicundo</foreign>. He was in the
                    place of, and not coexistent with, <foreign xml:lang="la">duumviri</foreign>.
                    The <foreign xml:lang="la">duumviri</foreign> were originally chosen by the
                    people, but the <foreign xml:lang="la">praefectus</foreign> was appointed
                    annually in <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, and sent to the town
                    called a <foreign xml:lang="la">praefectura</foreign>, which might be either a
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">municipium</foreign> or a <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >colonia</foreign>; for it was only in the matter of the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">praefectus</foreign> that a town called a <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">praefectura</foreign> differed from other Italian towns.
                        <placeName key="perseus,Arpinum">Arpinum</placeName> is called both a
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">municipium</foreign> and a <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >praefectura</foreign>.”—Smith Dict. Ant. p. 259, v. <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >Colonia</foreign>, q. v.</note> occupied the highest position both for rank
                and influence; secondly, as he himself while serving in the legions under Publius
                Crassus as general, enjoyed a character of the highest respectability among a number
                of most accomplished men, Roman knights; as he was after that the chief man among
                his fellow-citizens, a most incorruptible and upright judge in many causes, a
                promoter of many companies, and president of some;—if not only no fault has ever
                been found with him, but if the whole of his conduct has been universally praised;
                shall we still be told that such a father shall be an objection to a most honourable
                son, when he would be able by his authority, or, if not, by his interest, to protect
                a less honourable man, or one entirely unconnected with him? <milestone n="33"
                    unit="section"/> “He has at times,” says he, “said some very harsh things.”
                Perhaps he may have spoken rather freely. “But that speaking freely, as you term
                it,” says he, “is not to be borne.” Are then those men to be borne who complain that
                they cannot bear the freedom of a Roman knight? Where are our old customs? Where is
                our equality of privileges? Where is that ancient liberty, which, having been
                overwhelmed by civil disasters, ought by this time to be raising its head and to be
                at last recovered and assuming a more erect attitude again? Need I recount the abuse
                directed by the Roman knights against even the noblest men, or that of the harsh,
                ferocious, unbridled expressions of the farmers against Quintus Scaevola, a man
                superior to all others in genius, justice, and integrity? <milestone n="14"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Granius, the crier, replied to the consul Publius Nasica in the middle of the forum,
                when he, after a suspension of all judicial proceedings had been proclaimed, as he
                was returning home, had asked Granius “why he was sad; was it because all the
                auctions were postponed?” “Rather,” said he, <pb n="117"/> “because they have sent
                back the ambassadors.” The same man made this answer to a tribune of the people,
                Marcus Drusus, a most influential man, but one who was causing great disturbances in
                the republic. When Drusus had saluted him, as is the fashion, and had said, “How do
                you do, O Granius?” he replied, “I should rather ask, O Drusus, what are you doing?”
                And he often reproved with impunity the designs of Lucius Crassus and Marcus
                Antonius, with still harsher witticisms. At present the state is to such a degree
                oppressed by your arrogance, that the freedom of laughing in which a crier used to
                be indulged, is more than is now allowed to a Roman knight in making lamentations.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/> For what expression was ever used by Plancius
                which was not dictated by grief rather than by insult? And what did he ever complain
                of, except at times when he was protecting his companions or himself from injury?
                When the senate was hindered from making a reply to a representation of the Roman
                knights,—a thing which was invariably given even to enemies,—that injury was a great
                grief to all the farmers of the revenue and that indignation this man did not care
                to conceal. Their common feelings may perhaps have been disguised by others, but the
                sentiments which my client shared with the rest he revealed more plainly than the
                rest both by his countenance and by his language. </p>
            <p><milestone n="35" unit="section"/> Although, O judges, (for thus much I know of my
                own knowledge,) many things are attributed to Plancius which were never said by him.
                In my own case, because I sometimes say something, not from any deliberate
                intention, but either in the heat of speaking, or because I have been provoked; and
                because as is natural, among the many things which I say in this manner something
                comes out at times if not excessively witty, still perhaps not altogether stupid,
                the consequence is that, whatever anyone else says people say that I have said. But
                I, if it is anything clever and worthy of a well-educated and learned man have no
                great objection but I am very angry when the sayings of other men are attributed to
                me, which are utterly unworthy of me. For, because he was the first person to give
                his vote for the law concerning the farmers, at the time when that most illustrious
                man the consul gave that privilege to that order of men by a vote of the people,
                which if he had have done it, he would have given them by a vote of the senate, if
                it be a crime in him <pb n="118"/> to have given his vote for it, I ask what farmer
                was there who did not vote for it? If the charge be that he was the first to vote,
                is that the fault of chance, or of the man who proposed the law? If it was the
                effect of chance, then there can be no crime in what happened by chance. If it was
                by the choice of the consul, then it adds to the renown of Plancius that he was
                considered the chief man of his order by so illustrious a man. <milestone n="15"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="36" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But let us at last come to the merits of the case; in which, under cover of the
                Licinian law, which relates to treating,<note anchored="true">The Latin word is
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">sodalitium</foreign>. “Especially a feasting club; at
                    these parties conspiracies were frequently hatched, and so they obtained a bad
                    name. <bibl n="Cic. Planc. 15">Cic. <title>Planc.</title> 15</bibl>.”—Riddle,
                    Lat. Dict. in voc. “<foreign xml:lang="la">Lex Licinia</foreign> was specially
                    directed against the offence of <foreign xml:lang="la">sodalitium</foreign> or
                    the wholesale bribery of a tribe by gifts and treating.”—Smith, Dict. Ant. p.
                    36, v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Ambitus</foreign>.</note> you have embraced all
                the laws relating to bribery. Nor have you had any other object in view in dwelling
                on this law, except the power which it gave you of selecting your judges. And if
                this sort of tribunal is an equitable one in any other case except that of bribing
                the tribes, I do not understand why, in this one description of prosecution alone,
                the senate has allowed the tribes from which the judges are taken to be selected by
                the prosecutor, and has not given the same power of selection in other cases also.
                In actual prosecutions for bribery, it has directed the tribunal to be formed by
                each party striking off judges alternately; and though it omitted no other species
                of severity to the defendant, still it thought it ought to omit this. <milestone
                    n="37" unit="section"/> What? Is the reason of this conduct still obscure? was
                it not mooted when that matter was discussed in the senate, and argued most
                abundantly by Hortensius yesterday, who carried all the senate with him? This, then,
                was our opinion, that if he had bribed any tribe by means of this hospitality—which
                the treating would be called by people more solicitous to give it a respectable name
                than a true one;—if he had, I say, corrupted any tribe by disgraceful bribery, he
                must be known to have done so by the men who belonged to that tribe above all
                others. Accordingly, the senate thought that when those tribes were selected is the
                judges of the accused person, which he was said to have corrupted by bribery, they
                would serve both as witnesses of the truth and as judges. It is altogether a very
                severe sort <pb n="119"/> of tribunal; but still, if either his own tribe, or one
                with which he was especially connected, was proposed to a man as that which was to
                judge him, it could hardly be refused. <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="38" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But in this case, O Laterensis, what tribes did you select? The Terentian tribe, I
                suppose. That certainly was an equitable proceeding, and certainly one that was
                expected, and it was quite worthy of your wisdom and firmness. The tribe of which
                you keep crying out that Plancius had been the seller, and corrupter, and briber;
                that tribe, especially since it consists, as it does, of most virtuous and highly
                respectable men, you ought to have chosen. Did you choose the Voltinian tribe? for
                you have taken it into your head to connect some charge or other with that tribe.
                Why, then, did you not select that tribe? What had Plancius to do with the Lemonian
                tribe? What had he to do with the Ufentian? or with the Crustumine? for as for the
                Maecian tribe, you selected that to be one, not to judge, but to be rejected.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/> Have you any doubt, then, O judges, that
                Marcus Laterensis selected you on his own judgment having regard not to the spirit
                of the law, but to some hope which he had himself formed with reference to the
                state? Have you any doubt that when he avoided selecting those tribes among which
                Plancius had extensive connections, the reason was that he judged that they had been
                won over by legitimate attention and kindness, not corrupted by bribery? For what
                reason can he allege why that power of selection given to the prosecutor is not a
                measure of great severity towards the defendant, if it is adopted without the
                consideration which determined us to pass such a law? <milestone n="40"
                    unit="section"/> Are you to choose out of all the people either those who are
                personal friends of your own, or personal enemies to me, or men whom you consider
                inexorable, inhuman and cruel? Are you, without my knowing, or suspecting, or
                dreaming of such a step, to choose your own connections and those of your friends,
                personal enemies to me and to my counsel? And are you to add to them those whom you
                think by nature harsh and unfriendly to all the world? And are you then to produce
                them all of a sudden, so that I see the bench of judges who are to try me before I
                can form the least idea who they are going to be? And are you to compel me to plead
                my cause, one in which all my fortunes are at stake, before those men, without
                having the power of rejecting even five, which was <pb n="120"/> a privilege allowed
                to the last man who was put on his trial by the decision of the judges themselves?
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/> For it does not follow because Plancius has
                lived in such a manner as never willfully to offend any one, or because you have
                made such a mistake as unintentionally to select such men that we find we are come
                before judges, and not before executioners, that on that account that selection, if
                looked at by itself, is not a severe measure. <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Was it not lately the case that some most illustrious citizens would not endure the
                idea of a judge selected by the prosecutor, (when, out of a hundred and twenty-five
                judges, the chief men of the equestrian order, the defendant rejected seventy-five,
                and retained fifty,) and preferred throwing the whole business into confusion, to
                obeying that law and complying with those terms? And shall we put up with judges
                chosen not out of the select body of judges, but out of the whole people, and not
                proposed to us with a power of striking off the obnoxious ones, but appointed by the
                prosecutor in such a way that we have no power to object to a single one? </p>
            <p><milestone n="42" unit="section"/> I am not now complaining of the injustice of the
                law, but I am showing that your conduct is at variance with the spirit of the law;
                and I not only should not complain of the severity of that proceeding, if you had
                acted as the senate intended and as the people decreed, and had proposed to him as
                judges his own tribe, and those which he had paid attentions to; but, if you had
                given him those men as judges who ought also to have served as witnesses, I should
                think him acquitted at once. And even now my opinion is not very different. For when
                you proposed these tribes, you showed plainly that you preferred having judges who
                were unknown rather than such as were known; you evaded the intention of the law;
                you discarded every principle of justice; you preferred enveloping the case in
                obscurity to throwing light upon it. “The Voltinian tribe was corrupted by him.” “He
                had bought the Terentian tribe.” <milestone n="43" unit="section"/> What could he
                say then before men of the Voltinian tribe, or before his own tribesmen, if they
                were his judges? Yes, what rather could you say yourself? What judge of all the
                number could you find who might be a silent witness of those matters, or which of
                them could you summon as such? In truth, if the defendant himself were to propose
                the tribes which were to furnish his judges, Plancius perhaps <pb n="121"/> would
                have proposed the Voltinian tribe on account of his neighbourhood to and connection
                with it; but most unquestionably he would have proposed his own. And if he had had
                to propose the president of the court whom would he have been more likely to propose
                than this very Caius Alfius, who is the president to whom he ought to be thoroughly
                well-known, his own neighbour, a man of his own tribe, a most respectable and
                upright man? Whose impartiality and desire for the safety of Cnaeus Plancius which,
                without the least suspicion of being influenced by any covetous motives he makes no
                concealment of, declares plainly enough that my client had no reason to avoid having
                men of his own tribe for judges, when you see that a man of his own tribe for
                president was a most desirable thing for him. <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="44" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Nor am I now finding fault with your prudence in not giving him those tribes to which
                he was best known, but I am proving that the intention of the senate was disregarded
                by you. In truth which of all these men would listen to you? Or what could you say?
                Could you say that Plancius was guilty of the depository of the money to be used in
                bribery? Men's ears would reject the assertion. No one would endure it. All would
                turn away from it. That he was a very acceptable man to the tribes? They would hear
                that willingly. We ourselves should not be afraid to allow that. For do not think, O
                Laterensis, that the effect of those laws which the senate has thought fit to
                establish concerning bribery has been to put an end to the recommendation of
                candidates to attentions being paid to electors, or to personal influence. There
                have always been virtuous men who have been anxious to have influence among the men
                of their own tribe. <milestone n="45" unit="section"/> Nor, indeed, has our order
                ever been so harsh towards the common people, as to be unwilling to have it courted
                by moderate liberality on our part. Nor are our children to be forbidden to pay
                attention to the men of their own tribe or to show regard for them or to canvass
                them on behalf of their friends, or to expect a similar service from them when they
                are themselves candidates for any office. For all these things are only acts of
                mutual kindness and politeness, and are sanctioned by ancient customs and precedent.
                That was on our conduct when the occasions of our ambition required it; and such we
                have seen to be the course of most illustrious men; and even <pb n="122"/> at the
                present day we see many men alive to the necessity of keeping up their interests. It
                was the dividing the men of a tribe into decuries, the classification of the whole
                people, and the attempt to bind men's votes by bribes, that provoked the severity of
                the senate, and the energetic indignation of all good men. Allege this, prove this,
                direct your attention to this point, O Laterensis, that Plancius divided the tribes
                into decuries, that he classified the people, that he was an agent with whom money
                was deposited, that he promised money, that he distributed it; and then I shall
                wonder at your not having chosen to use the weapons which the law has armed you
                with. For with judges taken from the men of our own tribe, I need not say we could
                not if those things were true, bear their severity, but we could not even look them
                in the face. <milestone n="46" unit="section"/> But, after having avoided this line
                of conduct, and declined having those men for judges, who, as they must have had the
                most certain knowledge of such conduct, were bound to feel the greatest indignation
                at it what will you say before those men who silently ask of you why you have
                imposed this burden upon them; why you have chosen them above all men; why you
                prefer having them to proceed by guesswork, rather than those men to decide who had
                means of knowing the truth? <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I, O Laterensis, say that Plancius himself is a popular man, and that he had to
                assist him in his canvass many men eager in his cause, who were also popular men.
                And if you call them agents to treat people, you are polluting a kind and zealous
                friendship, by a very insidious name. But if, because they are popular, you think
                them on that account objects for prosecution, then do not wonder that you yourself,
                after repudiating the friendship of popular men, failed in attaining what your real
                worth demanded for you. </p>
            <p><milestone n="47" unit="section"/> But now, as I prove that Plancius was a popular
                man in his tribe, because he has been kind to many of them, because he has been
                security for many of them, because he has procured employment for many of them by
                means of the authority and interest of his father, and because he has bound the
                whole prefecture of <placeName key="tgn,7006695">Atina</placeName> to himself by all
                the kindness displayed by himself, by his father, and by his ancestors; I call on
                you to prove in an equally convincing manner, that he was an agent for receiving
                money to be spent in bribery; that he <pb n="123"/> was himself a briber; that he
                classified the people; that he divided the tribes into decuries. And if you cannot,
                do not deny our order the exercise of a legitimate liberality; do not think that
                popularity is a crime; do not enact a punishment to be inflicted for courteous
                attentions. </p>
            <p>And accordingly, as you were forced to hesitate about this charge of corrupting a
                tribe by means of treating, you had recourse to a general accusation of bribery. And
                in examining this, let us, if you please, cease awhile to contend in vulgar and
                random declamation. <milestone n="48" unit="section"/> For I will argue with you in
                this way. Do you choose any one tribe you please, and prove, as you are bound to do,
                what agent received the money for corrupting it, and who distributed the money among
                the men of the tribe. And if you cannot do that, which in my opinion you will not
                even begin to attempt, I will show you the means to which he owes his success. Is
                not this a fair challenge? Do not you like to proceed in this manner? Can I come to
                closer quarters, as they say, or can I meet you on a fairer field? Why are you
                silent? Why do you conceal your intentions? Why do you seek to shirk off? Again and
                again I press upon you, and keep close to you; I pursue you, I ask for, I even
                demand some definite accusation. Whatever tribe, I say, you select, whose votes
                Plancius received, you show, if you can, any flaw in that one instance. I will then
                show you by what means he really did gain its vote, and the principle shall be
                exactly the same in his case, and, O Laterensis, in yours. For as you, if I were to
                ask you, may be able to explain to me through whose influence it was that you gained
                the affection of these tribes who voted for you, so do I assert that I will explain
                to you, our adversary, the means by which we gained the vote of any tribe you choose
                to inquire about. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="49" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>But why do I argue in this manner? Just as if Plancius had not already been elected
                aedile in the former <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>. Which <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> were begun to be held by the consul, a man in
                every respect of the very highest authority, and the author of those very laws
                concerning bribery. And besides, he began to hold them very suddenly, contrary to
                any one's expectation; so that, even if any one had formed the design of committing
                bribery, he would never have had time to manage it. The tribes were summoned; the
                votes were <pb n="124"/> given; counted up, declared. Plancius was by far the
                highest of all on the poll.<note anchored="true">Cicero, in his oration against
                    Rullus, shows that the votes were given twice over at elections for magistrates,
                    the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia tributa</foreign> being twice held for that
                    object.</note> There neither was nor could there be any suspicion of bribery. Is
                it not the case that the one prerogative century carries such weight with it that no
                one has ever gained the vote of that, but what he has been declared consul either at
                that very <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>, or at all events consul for the
                year? And yet do you wonder that Plancius was elected aedile when it was not a small
                portion of the people, but the whole people that had declared their good-will
                towards him? when it was not a portion of one tribe, but the whole <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> which were prerogative <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia</foreign> in his behalf? <milestone n="50" unit="section"/> And at that
                time if you, O Laterensis, had been inclined, or if you had thought it consistent
                with your gravity to do what many men of high birth have often done, who, having
                gained a great many fewer votes than they had expected, afterwards, when the
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> had been adjourned, have prostrated
                themselves, and, with broken spirits and in a humble tone, had addressed
                supplications to the Roman people, I do not question but that the whole multitude
                would have turned towards you. For nobility, especially when upright and innocent
                has never, when appearing as a suppliant, been rejected by the Roman people. But if
                your personal dignity and character for magnanimity was, as it ought to have been,
                of more importance to you than the aedileship, then, since you have that which you
                preferred, do not regret that which you thought of less consequence. I myself, in
                truth, have always striven most zealously, in the first place, to be worthy of
                honour; in the second place, to be considered so. The third consideration with me,
                though with most men it is the first, has been the honour itself; but that is a
                thing which ought to be acceptable to those men in whose case the Roman people has
                conferred it on them as a testimony to their worth, and not as a favour granted to
                their assiduity in canvassing for it. <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="51" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You ask also, O Laterensis, what answer you can make to the images of your ancestors;
                how you are to excuse yourself to that most accomplished and excellent man your <pb
                    n="125"/> deceased father? Never think about those things. Take care rather lest
                that querulousness and excessive grief of yours be reproved by those men of
                consummate wisdom. For your father saw that Appius Claudius a most noble man, even
                in the lifetime of his own father a most influential and most illustrious citizen,
                Caius Claudius, failed in his endeavour to obtain the aedileship, and yet that he
                was afterwards elected consul without a repulse. He saw that a man most closely
                connected with himself a most illustrious citizen, Lucius Volcatius, and he saw that
                Marcus Piso too, having both sustained a slight defeat in the matter of the
                aedileship, received afterwards the very highest honours from the Roman people. But
                your grandfather could tell you also of the rejection of Publius Nasica, when he
                stood for the aedileship, though I am sure that a greater citizen has never existed
                in this republic, and of Caius Marius too, who was twice rejected when a candidate
                for the aedileship, and yet was seven times made consul, and of Lucius Caesar and of
                Cnaeus Octavius and of Marcus Tullius, every one of whom we know were beaten for the
                aedileship, and were elected consul afterwards. <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But why am I hunting up instances of men having failed as candidates for the
                aedileship, when it is an office which has often been discharged in such a way that
                the people appeared to have been doing a kindness to the men who had been passed
                over. Lucius Philippus, a man of the highest truth and most distinguished eloquence
                failed in his election to military tribune. Caius Caelius, a most illustrious and
                admirable young man, was beaten for the quaestorship. Publius Rutilius Rufus, Caius
                Fimbria, Caius Cassius, Cnaeus Orestes all stood in vain for the tribuneship of the
                people. And yet we know that every one of these men were afterwards made consuls.
                And your father and your ancestors will of their own accord tell you this not with
                the object of comforting you, nor to excuse you from any fault which you fear that
                you must seem to have been guilty of, but with a view of encouraging you to
                persevere in that course which you have followed from your earliest youth. No credit
                believe me, O Laterensis, has been lost by you. Lost, do I say? I declare solemnly,
                if you were to come to a right appreciation of what has happened, an especial
                testimony has been borne to your virtue. <pb n="126"/>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>For think not that there was not a great impression made by the circumstances of your
                offering yourself as a candidate for that office from all competition for which you
                subsequently withdrew, rather than swear to a particular thing. You then, being
                quite a young man, declared plainly what were your sentiments about public affairs:
                speaking more boldly, indeed, than some men who had already attained the honours of
                the state, and more undisguisedly than regard to your ambition, or to your age,
                required. <milestone n="53" unit="section"/> And, therefore, among the people so
                disparaged your pretensions, you must not think that there were none who had taken
                offence at the intrepid spirit which you then displayed; who were able, perhaps, to
                keep you, incautious as you were, from arriving at that rank, but will never be able
                to move you when you are on your guard and watchful against them. </p>
            <p>Have these arguments had any influence with you? “Have you any doubt,” says he, “that
                a coalition was entered into against me, when you see that Plancius and Plotius
                gained the votes of the majority of the tribes?” But could they have acted in
                concert if the tribes did not give their votes in concert? But some of the tribes
                gave almost the very same number of votes for each of them. Yes, when at the
                preceding <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> those two had been already almost
                elected and declared. Although even that fact would not necessarily involve any
                suspicion of a coalition. For our ancestors would never have established a rule of
                casting lots for the aedileship, if they had not seen that it was possible that the
                competitors should have had an equal number of votes. <milestone n="54"
                    unit="section"/> And you say that at the preceding <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia</foreign> the tribe of the Anio was given up by Plotius to Pedius, and
                the Terentian tribe by Plancius to you; but now, that they are taken away from both
                Pedius and you, lest they should run the contest too fine. What a probable story it
                is, that before the inclination of the people was ascertained, those men, who you
                say had already joined their forces, should have thrown away their own tribes in
                order to assist you, and that the same men should afterwards have been close and
                stingy, when they had tried and found out how strong they were. They were afraid, I
                suppose, of a close contest. As if the matter could come to a close point, or as if
                there could be any danger. But nevertheless, do you bring the same charge against
                Aulus Plotius, a most <pb n="127"/> accomplished man? or do you admit that you have
                only attacked the man who never requested you to spare him?<note anchored="true"
                    >Orellius and all editors consider this passage corrupt, and correct it in
                    different ways.</note> For as for your having complained that you had more
                witnesses concerning the case of the Voltinian tribe, than you had received votes in
                that tribe, you show by that, either that you are bringing forward those men as
                witnesses who passed you over because they had taken a bribe, or else that you could
                not get their votes though they were paid nothing for them. <milestone n="23"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="55" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But as for that charge about the money which you say was seized in the Flaminian
                Circus, it made a great noise while the matter was recent, but now it has got quite
                cold. For you have never explained what money that was, nor what were the tribes
                which were to receive it, nor who was to distribute it to them. And he, indeed, who
                was then impeached on this account, being brought before the consuls complained that
                he had been shamefully treated by your partisans. For if he acted as the distributor
                of the money particularly for that man whom you were prosecuting, why was he also
                not prosecuted by you? Why did you get some appearance of a decision having been
                already come to in this cause by his conviction? But the fact is that you have no
                proofs to advance, nor do you place the slightest reliance on any. It is quite
                another motive and another consideration which has induced you to cherish the hope
                of crushing this man. You have great resources; very extensive influence many
                friends; many eager partisans; many favourers of your credit: many are envious of my
                client, to many too his father a most excellent man, appears to be too great a
                stickler for the freedom and privileges of the equestrian order. Many too are the
                common enemies of every defendant, men who always give their evidence on trials for
                bribery and corruption in such a way as if they could influence the minds of the
                judges by their evidence, or as if it were pleasing to the Roman people, and as if,
                on that account, they would the more easily attain that dignity which they are
                desirous of. <milestone n="56" unit="section"/> But you shall not see me, O judges,
                contending with those men in my former fashion; not because it is right for me to
                shirk anything which the safety of Plancius requires, but because it is neither
                necessary, that I should follow up that argument with my voice, <pb n="128"/> which
                you already see with your mind; and because those very men whom I see already as
                witnesses, have deserved so well of me, that you ought to take upon your own
                prudence the task of reproving them, and to excuse my modesty from that task. </p>
            <p>This one thing I beg and entreat of you, O judges, both for the sake of this man whom
                I am defending, and out of regard to the common danger; not to think that the
                fortunes of innocent men are to be placed at the mercy of reports which people
                falsely pretend that they have heard, or of vague and uncertain conversation.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/> Many friends of the prosecutor, some men,
                too, who are personal enemies of ours, many general and universal calumniators, and
                men who envy everybody, have invented heaps of things. But there is nothing which
                travels so fast as slander; nothing is more easily sent abroad, nothing is received
                more rapidly, nothing is spread more extensively. Nor will I, if you can ever trace
                the origin of a calumny, ever require you to disregard it or conceal it. But if
                anything gets abroad without a head, or if there be any report of such a nature that
                no author of it can be found; if he who has heard it appears to you either so
                careless as to have forgotten where he heard it; or if he knows his authority to be
                so insignificant that he is ashamed to confess that he recollects who he is,—then I
                do beg of you not to let that common expression, “I heard that<gap reason="* * * *"
                />,” injure an innocent man upon his trial. <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="58" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But I come now to Lucius Cassius, my own intimate friend, and I have not as yet made
                any complaint about that Juventius whom that young man, accomplished in every virtue
                and in every branch of polite learning, mentions in his speech, and says that he was
                the first man of the common people who was ever made a curule aedile. And with
                reference to that case, if, O Cassius, I were to reply to you that the Roman people
                knew nothing of that fact and that there is no one who can tell us anything about
                him, especially now that Longinus is dead, you would not wonder, I imagine, when I
                myself, who am not at all inclined to neglect the study of antiquity, confess that I
                first heard of this fact in this place, from your mouth. And since your oration was
                very elegant and very ingenious; worthy both of the learning and modesty of a Roman
                knight, and since you were listened to by these <pb n="129"/> men with such
                attention as did great honour both to your abilities and to your character as a
                gentleman and a scholar, I will reply now to what you said, of which the greater
                part concerned me myself, and in which the very stings, if you did put out any in
                your reproof of me, were still not disagreeable to me. <milestone n="59"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>You asked me whether I thought that the road to the attainment of honours had been
                easier to me the son of a Roman knight, than it would be to my son, who was now of a
                consular family. But although I would rather that all good fortune fell to his lot
                than to my own, still I have never wished for him that the road to honour might be
                more easy to him than I have found it myself. Moreover, lest he should by chance
                think that I have procured him honours myself rather than pointed out to him the
                path by which he might arrive at them, I am accustomed to read him this lesson
                (although his age is not exactly the age to attend to instruction,) which the great
                son of <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName> is represented teaching his children,—<quote>
                    <l>“Men must always be vigilant; there are many snares in the path of virtuous
                        men.”</l>
                </quote> You know the rest do you not? <quote>
                    <l>“That which many men envy <gap reason="* * * *"/>”</l>
                </quote><note anchored="true">This is a fragment of Attius from his play of
                    Philoctetes, see also the <bibl n="Cic. Sest. 48">oration for Sestius, chap.
                        xlviii</bibl>.</note> Which that wise and ingenious poet wrote not in order
                to excite those boys who were no longer in existence to toil and the desire of glory
                but to encourage us and our children in such pursuits. <milestone n="60"
                    unit="section"/> You ask what more Plancius could have got if he had been the
                son of Cnaeus Scipio. He could not have been made an aedile more than he is; but he
                would have gained this, that he would not be so much envied. In truth the degrees of
                honour are equal in the case of the highest and the lowest citizens, but the glory
                of arriving at them is unequal. <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Who of us would call himself equal to Manius Curius, or to Caius Fabricius or to
                Caius Duilius? Who reckons himself a match for Atilius Calatinius or for Cnaeus and
                Publius Scipio or for Africanus, Marcellus or Maximus? And yet we have arrived at
                the same degree of rank that they <pb n="130"/> did. In truth, in virtue there are
                many steps; so that he is the most eminent in renown, who is the superior in virtue.
                The summit of the honours conferred by the people is the consulship. And by this
                time nearly eight hundred men have obtained that. And of this eight hundred, if you
                examine carefully, you will find hardly one tenth of the number worthy of such a
                preeminence. But yet no one ever went on as you do. “Why is that man made consul?
                What could he have got more if he had been Lucius Brutus, who delivered the city
                from the tyranny of the kings?” He could have got no higher rank certainly, but he
                would have much more glory. And in the same manner, therefore, Plancius has been
                made quaestor, and tribune of the people, and aedile, just as much as if he had been
                a man of the highest rank by birth; but a countless number of other men, born in the
                same rank as he, have also attained these honours. <milestone n="61" unit="section"
                /> You speak of the triumphs of Titus Didius, and Caius Marius; and ask what there
                is like these exploits in Plancius. As if those men whom you are speaking of
                obtained their magistracies because they had triumphed, and did not on the contrary
                triumph after having performed great achievements, because those magistracies were
                entrusted to them. You ask what campaigns he has served; when he was a soldier in
                    <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, while Metellus, who is here in
                court, was commander-in-chief, and military tribune in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                    >Macedonia</placeName>; and when he was quaestor he only abstracted just so much
                time from his attention to his military duties as he thought it better to devote to
                protecting me. </p>
            <p><milestone n="62" unit="section"/> You ask whether he is an eloquent man. At all
                events, what is the next best thing to being so, he does not think himself one. “Is
                he a lawyer?” As if there were any one who complains that he has given him a false
                answer in a point of law. For all such acts as that are open to criticism in the
                case of men who, after they have professed an acquaintance with them, are unable to
                satisfy people's expectations; not in the case of men who confess that they have
                never paid any attention to those pursuits. What is usually required in a candidate
                is virtue, and honesty, and integrity, not volubility of tongue, or an acquaintance
                with any particular art or science. As we, when we are procuring slaves, are annoyed
                if we have bought a man as a smith or a plasterer, and find, <pb n="131"/> however
                good a man he may be, that he knows nothing of those trades which we had in view in
                buying him; but if we have bought a man to give him charge of our property as
                steward, or to employ him to look after our stock, then we do not care for any other
                qualities in him except frugality, industry, and vigilance; so the Roman people
                elects magistrates to be as it were stewards of the republic, and if they are
                masters of some accomplishment besides, the people have no objection, but if not,
                they are content with their virtue and innocence. For how few men are eloquent; how
                few are skillful lawyers, even if you include all those in your calculation who wish
                to be so! But if no one else is worthy of honour, what on earth is to become of so
                many most virtuous and most accomplished citizens? <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="63" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You request Plancius to mention any faults of Laterensis. He cannot mention any,
                unless he thinks him too ill-tempered towards himself. At the same time you extol
                Laterensis highly yourself. I have no particular objection to your spending a number
                of words on what has nothing to do with the trial, and to your occupying so much
                time, while conducting the prosecution, in saying what I, who am the counsel for the
                defence can admit without any danger. And I do not only admit that every sort of
                high quality is to be found in Laterensis, but I even find fault with you, for not
                enumerating his chief excellences, but descending to look for trifling and
                insignificant subjects for panegyric. You say “That he celebrated games at
                    <placeName key="perseus,Praeneste">Praeneste</placeName>.” Well; have not other
                quaestors done the same? “That at <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName> he
                was liberal towards the farmers of the revenue, and just towards the allies.” Who
                denies it? but so many important transactions take place at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, that it is difficult for those things which
                are done in the provinces to get heard of. <milestone n="64" unit="section"/> I have
                no fear, O judges, of appearing to assume too much credit to myself, if I speak of
                my own quaestorship. For although I got great credit in it, still I consider that I
                have been employed since that in the highest offices of the state, so that I have no
                need to seek for much glory from the credit I gained in my quaestorship; but still I
                do not fear that any one will venture to say that anybody's quaestorship in
                    <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> has been either more acceptable
                to the people, or has gained a higher reputation for the quaestor. Indeed, I can say
                this with truth, <pb n="132"/> I, too, at that time thought that men at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> were talking of nothing else except my
                quaestorship. At a time of great dearness, I had sent an immense quantity of corn to
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. I had been affable to the
                traders, just to the merchants, liberal to the citizens of the municipal towns,
                moderate as regards the allies, and in every respect I appeared to have been most
                diligent in the discharge of every part of my duty. Some perfectly unheard-of
                honours were contrived for me by the Sicilians. <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                Therefore I left my province with the hope that the Roman people would come forward
                of its own accord to pay me every sort of honour. But when one day by chance at that
                time, I, on my road from the province, had arrived in the course of my journey at
                    <placeName key="perseus,Puteoli">Puteoli</placeName>, at a time which great
                numbers of the wealthiest men are accustomed to spend in that district, I almost
                dropped with vexation when some one asked me what day I had left <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, and whether there was any news there. And
                when I had replied that I was on my road from my province, “Oh yes,” said he, “from
                    <placeName key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>, I suppose.” <milestone n="27"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>On this, I, angry and disgusted, said, “No; from <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                    >Sicily</placeName>.” And then, some one else, with the air of a man who knew
                everything, said, “What! do not you know that Cicero has been quaestor at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>?” I need not make a long story of
                it; I gave over being angry, and was content to be considered one of those who had
                come to <placeName key="perseus,Puteoli">Puteoli</placeName> for the waters.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/> But I do not know, O judges, whether what
                happened then did not do me more good than if every one had congratulated me. For
                after I learnt from this that the people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName> had deaf ears, but very sharp and active eyes, I gave up
                thinking what men would have said of me; but took care that they should every day
                see me in their presence: I lived in their sight; I stuck to the forum; neither my
                porter nor even sleep was allowed to prevent any one from having access to me. Need
                I say anything about my time which was devoted to business, when even my leisure
                time was never my own? For the very orations which you say, O Cassius, that you are
                in the habit of reading when you are at leisure, I wrote on days of festival and on
                holidays, so that I never was at leisure at all. In truth, I have always thought
                that saying of Marcus Cato, which he put at the head of his <title>Origines</title>,
                a splendid and admirable one: “That eminent and great men ought to lay down a
                regular plan for their leisure <pb n="133"/> as well as for their business.” And,
                therefore, if I have any credit, I hardly know how much I have; it has all been
                acquired at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> and earned in the forum.
                And public events have sanctioned my private counsels in such a way that even at
                home I have had to attend to the general interests of the republic, and to preserve
                the city while in the city. The same road, O Cassius, is open to Laterensis, the
                same path by virtue to glory. <milestone n="67" unit="section"/> And it will be the
                easier to him perhaps on this account that I have mounted up hither without having
                any family interest to push me on and relying solely on my self; but his admirable
                virtues will be assisted by the recommendation which the virtues of his ancestors
                supply him with. </p>
            <p>However, to return to Plancius, he has never been absent from the city unless any lot
                which he may have drawn or some law, or some necessity compelled him to be so. He
                did not excel in those things in which some men perhaps do but he did excel in
                diligence, he did excel in paying attention to his friends, he did excel in
                liberality. He kept himself before men's eyes; he stood for offices; he has followed
                at all times that course of life by which, while there is less danger that way of
                incurring unpopularity, the greatest number of new men have attained the same
                honours which he has. <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="68"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For as to what you say, O Cassius—that I am not under greater obligations to Plancius
                than I am to all good men, because my safety was equally dear to all of them,—I
                confess that I am under obligations to all good men. But even those men to whom I am
                under obligations, good men and virtuous citizens, said at the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> for the election of the aediles, that they
                themselves were under some obligations to Plancius on my account. However grant that
                I am under obligations to many people and among others to Plancius, ought it
                therefore to make me bankrupt; ought I not rather, when each man's turn comes, to
                pay them all this debt which I acknowledge, whenever it is demanded? Although, being
                in debt for money and for kindness are two different things. For the man who pays
                money, the moment he does so, no longer has that which he has paid, and he who owes
                is in debt. But the man who shows his gratitude by requiting a kindness, still
                preserves the feeling; and he who feels it, requites the kindness by the mere fact
                of his feeling it. Nor shall I cease to be under obligations to Plancius even if I
                requite his service <pb n="134"/> to me now;<milestone n="69" unit="section"/> nor
                should I have been less grateful to him as far as my inclination went, if this
                trouble had not befallen him. You ask of me, O Cassius, what I could do more for my
                own brother, who is most dear to me,—what I could do more for my own children, than
                whom nothing can be more delightful to me, than I am doing for Plancius? And you do
                not see that the very affection which I feel for them, stimulates and excites me to
                defend the safety of Plancius, too. For they have nothing more at heart than the
                safety of the man by whom they know that my safety was ensured; and I myself never
                look on them without recollecting that it is by his means that I was preserved to
                them, and remembering his great services done to me. </p>
            <p>You relate that Opimius was condemned, though he himself had been the saviour of the
                republic. You add to him Calidius, by whose law Quintus Metellus was restored to the
                state; and you find fault with my prayers on behalf of Cnaeus Plancius, because
                Opimius was not released on account of his services, nor Calidius on account of
                those of Quintus Metellus. <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>As for Calidius, I will only state this in answer to you, which I saw myself. That
                Quintus Metellus Pius, when consul, at the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>
                for the election of praetors, for which office Quintus Calidius was standing,
                addressed supplications to the Roman people, and did not hesitate—though he was
                consul at the time, and a man of the very highest rank—to call him his patron and
                the patron of his most noble family. <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And now I ask of you whether you think that, if Calidius had been on his trial,
                Metellus Pius, if he had been able to be at <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName>, or his father, if he had been alive, would have done for him
                what I am doing on the trial of Cnaeus Plancius? I wish, indeed, that the misfortune
                of Opimius could be eradicated from men's memories. But it is to be considered as a
                wound inflicted on the republic, as a disgrace to this empire, as the infamy of the
                Roman people, and not as a judicial verdict. For what more terrible blow could those
                judges—if indeed they deserve to be called judges, and not parricides of their
                country—inflict on the republic, than they did when they drove that man out of the
                state, who as praetor had delivered the republic from a war waged against it by its
                neighbours, and as consul, from one carried on against it by its own citizens? <pb
                    n="134"/>
            </p>
            <p><milestone n="71" unit="section"/> But you say that I make out the kindness done me
                by Plancius to have been greater than it really was, and as you say, I exaggerate it
                in speaking of it as if I were bound to regulate my gratitude by your estimate and
                not by my own. “What great service was it after all that he did you? Was it that he
                did not put you to death?” Say rather that he prevented me from being put to death.
                And, while speaking on this point, O Cassius, you even acquitted my enemies and said
                that no plots had been laid by them against my life. And Laterensis advanced the
                same assertion. Wherefore I will presently say a little more on that head. At
                present I only ask of you whether you think it was but a slight hatred which my
                enemies had conceived against me? Did any barbarians ever entertain such savage and
                cruel feelings against an open enemy? Or do you suppose that there was in those men
                any regard for fame or any fear of punishment when you saw them during the whole of
                that year brandishing their swords in the forum, menacing the temples with
                conflagration, and disturbing the whole city with their violence? Unless, perhaps,
                you think that they spared my life because they had no apprehension of my return. Do
                you think that there was any one so wholly destitute of sense as not to think that
                if these men were permitted to live, and if the city and the senate-house were
                allowed to remain standing, I also ought certainly to be restored if I too remained
                alive? Wherefore you, being such a man and such a citizen as you are, ought not to
                say that my enemies were too moderate to attack my life, when the fact is that it
                was preserved by the fidelity of my friends. <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="72" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I will now reply to you, O Laterensis, perhaps less vigorously than I have been
                attacked by you and certainly in a manner not more destitute of consideration for,
                or of friendly feeling towards you than your manner was towards me. For in the first
                place that was rather a harsh thing for you to say, that in what I was saying about
                Plancius I was speaking falsely, and inventing statements to suit the emergency. I
                suppose, forsooth, I, like a wise man, planned how I might appear bound to another
                by the greatest bonds of kindness and gratitude when I was in reality a free man and
                under no obligation at all. Why need I have done so? Had I not plenty of reasons
                besides for defending Plancius? were <pb n="136"/> not my own intimacy with him, my
                neighbourhood to him, and my friendship for his father, sufficiently cogent motives?
                And even if they had not existed, I had reason to fear, I suppose, lest I should be
                doing a discreditable thing in defending a man of his high respectability and worth.
                It must have been a very clever idea of mine to pretend that I owed everything to
                that man who was about to owe everything to me! But this is a thing which even
                common soldiers do against their will, and they are reluctant to give a civic crown
                to a citizen, and to confess that they have been saved by any one; not because it is
                discreditable to have been protected in battle, or to be saved out of the hands of
                the enemy, (for in truth that is a thing which can only happen to a brave man, and
                to one fighting hand to hand with the enemy,) but they dread the burden of the
                obligation, because it is an enormous thing to be under the same obligation to a
                stranger that one is to a parent. <milestone n="73" unit="section"/> But because
                others deny kindnesses which they have received, even when they are of less
                importance, in order not to appear under any obligation, am I on that account
                speaking falsely, when I say that I am bound to a man by his previous services done
                to me, for which it is quite impossible for me to make any adequate return? Are you
                ignorant of this, O Laterensis?—you who being, as you were, a great friend of mine,
                and willing to share with me even the danger with which my life was at that time
                threatened,—when you had escorted me in that hope of my sad and bitter agony and
                departure from the city not only with your tears, but also with your courage and
                your person, and with all your resources,—when you had in my absence defended with
                all your means, and all your power of protection, my children and my wife, were
                always pressing this statement upon me, that you willingly allowed and granted that
                I should employ all my zeal in contributing to the honour of Cnaeus Plancius because
                you said that the services which he had done me were acceptable to you yourself
                also. <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And is not even that oration, which is the first which I made in the senate after my
                return, a proof that I am saying nothing new now,—nothing just to meet the
                emergency? For as in that I returned thanks to very few by name, because it was
                quite impossible to enumerate all those who had served me, (and it would have been a
                crime to press over any <pb n="137"/> one,) and because I had therefore laid down a
                rule for myself to name those men only who had been the leaders and standard-bearers
                as it were in our cause; still among them I returned thanks to Plancius by name. Let
                the oration be read—which, on account of the importance of the business was
                pronounced from a written paper, in which I, cunning fellow that I must have been,
                gave myself up to a man to whom I was under no very great obligation and bound
                myself to the slavery of this duty which I am now discharging by this undying
                testimony against myself. I do not wish to recite the other things which I committed
                to writing. I pass them over, that I may not seem to bring them up now on this
                emergency, or to avail myself of that description of learning which appears to be
                more suitable to my private studies than to the usages of courts of justice.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="75" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And you keep crying out, O Laterensis, “How long are you going to keep on saying
                this? You did no good in the case of Cispius; people have got tired of your
                entreaties.” Will you object to me what I did in the case of Cispius, who had indeed
                deserved well of me, but whom I defended, having you for a witness in his favour,
                and at your especial request? And will you say “How long” to a man who you say was
                unable to obtain what he begged on behalf of Cispius? For to say “How long” to a man
                who exerted himself for one friend alone and who did not succeed in his object is
                rather like laughing at a person than reproving him, unless perhaps, I, above all
                other men, have behaved in such a manner in the courts of justice, have lived in
                such a manner with those men who are the judges and among them—unless I am such an
                advocate of defendants on their trial and unless I am, and always have been, such a
                citizen in the republic, as to deserve to he held up by you as the only person who
                never ought to obtain anything from the judges by my entreaties.<milestone n="76"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And then you object to me a tear which I shed at the trial of Cispius. For this is
                what you said “I saw your tear.” See now how I repent of having given you cause to
                say so. You might have seen not only a tear but many tears, and weeping and sobbing.
                Was I to abstain from showing my grief at the danger of a man who was so far moved
                by the tears of my family in my absence that he laid aside the enmity which he had
                conceived against me, and was not only <pb n="138"/>no opposer of my safety, (as my
                enemies had expected that he would have been,) but was even a great defender of it?
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/> And you, O Laterensis, who then said that my
                tears were a grateful sight, now wish to found an accusation against me on them.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>You say that the tribuneship of Plancius did not bring any assistance to my dignity.
                And in this place, (as you can do with the greatest truth,) you enumerate the
                godlike services done to me by Lucius Racilius, a most gallant and sensible man. And
                I never have concealed, and I shall at all times openly assert, that I am under the
                very greatest obligations to him, as I am to Cnaeus Plancius; for he never thought
                any contest, or any enmity, or any danger even of his life too great for him to
                encounter for the sake of my welfare, or of that of the republic. And I wish that
                the Roman people were not prevented by the violence and injustice of wicked men from
                proving to him their gratitude by their acts, and measuring it by the extent of my
                own. But if Plancius did not make the same exertions in my favour when he was
                tribune, you ought to think, not that his inclination was wanting, but that I, being
                already under such vast obligations to Plancius, was now content with the services
                of Racilius. <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Do you think that the judges will be the less inclined to do anything for my sake,
                because you accuse me of gratitude? Or, when the senators themselves, in that
                resolution of the senate which was passed in the monument of Marius,<note
                    anchored="true">The decree for Cicero's return was passed in a temple built by
                    Marius, and called on that account Marius' monument, and this was a circumstance
                    that had specially delighted Cicero, as being in accordance with a dream of his
                    when he first left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, in which he
                    fancied that Marius had appeared to him, and had ordered his lictor to conduct
                    him to his monument, telling him that he should find safety there. <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Vide</foreign>
                    <bibl n="Cic. Div. 1.28">Cic. <title>de Divin.</title> i. 28</bibl>.</note> in
                which my safety was recommended to all nations, returned thanks to Plancius alone,
                (for he was the only defender of my safety, of all the magistrates or
                vice-magistrates, to whom the senate thought it proper to return thanks on my
                behalf,) shall I think that I myself am not bound to show my gratitude to him? And
                when you see all these things, what do you suppose must be my feelings towards you,
                O Laterensis? Do you think that there is any danger, or any labour, or any <pb
                    n="139"/> contest of so arduous a nature that I would shun it if it could
                advance not only your safety, but even your dignity? And I am so much the more, I
                will not say miserable, (for that is an expression which is inconsistent with the
                character of a virtuous man) but severely tried not because I am under obligations
                to many people, (for gratitude for kindness received is a very light burden) but
                because circumstances often happen, on account of the quarrels of some men who have
                deserved well of me with one another which make me fear that it is impossible for me
                to appear grateful to them all at the same time. <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                But I must weigh in my own scales not only what I owe to each individual, but also
                of what importance the case is to each person, and what the necessities of each
                require of me at the particular moment. <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>What is at stake now on your part is this,—your eager wishes, or even, if you like,
                your reputation and the glory of the aedileship. But on the side of Cnaeus Plancius,
                it is his safety, his rights as a Roman and a citizen which are in peril. You wished
                me to be safe; he even ensured every safety by his actions. Yet I am torn asunder
                and rent in pieces by grief—I do grieve that in a contest where the stakes are so
                unequal, you should be offended by my conduct, but, I declare most solemnly, I would
                much rather endanger my own safety on your behalf than abandon the safety of Cnaeus
                Plancius to your hostility in this contest. <milestone n="80" unit="section"/> In
                truth, O judges, while I wish to be adorned with every virtue, yet there is nothing
                which I can esteem more highly than the being and appearing grateful. For this one
                virtue is not only the greatest, but is also the parent of all the other virtues.
                What is filial affection, but a grateful inclination towards one's parents?—who are
                good citizens, who are they who deserve well of their country both in war and at
                home but they who recollect the kindness which they have received from their
                country?—who are pious men who are men attentive to religious obligations, but they
                who with proper honours and with a grateful memory acquit themselves to the immortal
                gods of the gratitude which they owe to them?—what pleasure can there be in life, if
                friendships be taken away?—and, moreover, what friendship can exist between
                ungrateful people?—<milestone n="81" unit="section"/>Who of us has been liberally
                educated, by whom his bringers up, and his teachers, and his governors, and even <pb
                    n="140"/> the very mute place itself in which he has been brought up and taught,
                are not preserved in his mind with a grateful recollection?—who ever can have, or
                who ever had such resources in himself as to be able to stand without many acts of
                kindness on the part of many friends?—and yet no such acts can possibly exist, if
                you take away memory and gratitude. I, in truth, think nothing so much the peculiar
                property of man, as the quality of being bound, not only by a kindness received, but
                by even the intimation of good-will towards one; and I think nothing so inconsistent
                with one's idea of a man—nothing so barbarous or so brutal—as to appear, I will not
                say unworthy of, but surpassed by kindness. </p>
            <p><milestone n="82" unit="section"/> And as this is the case, I will succumb, O
                Laterensis, to your accusation; and in that very particular in which there cannot by
                any possibility be any excess,—namely, in gratitude, I will confess that I have gone
                to excess, since you insist upon it that it is so. And I will entreat you, O judges,
                to bind that man to you by a kindness, in whom the only fault that those who blame
                him find with him is that they accuse him of being immoderately grateful. And that
                ought not to prevail with you so as to make you think lightly of my gratitude, when
                he said that you were neither guilty men nor litigious men, so that there was the
                less reason for your allowing me any great influence over you: as if in my
                intercourse with my friends I did not always prefer that these abilities of mine (if
                indeed I have any abilities) should be at the service of my friends, rather than
                they should become necessary to them. In truth, I do venture to say this of myself,
                that my friendship has been a pleasure to more men than those to whom it has been a
                protection; and I should greatly repent of my past life; if there was no room in my
                friendship for any one who was not either a litigious person or a guilty one.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="83" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But somehow or other you have repeated over and over again, and have dwelt upon the
                assertion, that you did not choose to connect this case with the games, lest I,
                according to my usual custom, should say something about the sacred cars, for the
                sake of exciting pity; as I had done before in the case of other aediles. No doubt
                you got something by this; for you deprived me of an embellishment of my speech. I
                shall be laughed at now if I make any mention <pb n="141"/> of the sacred cars,
                after you have predicted that I should do so. And without the sacred cars what can I
                find to say? And here you added, too, that this was the reason why I by my law had
                established the penalty of banishment in cases of bribery, that I might be able to
                sum up my orations in ways more calculated to excite pity. Does he not, when he says
                all this, seem to you to be arguing against some teacher of declamation, and not
                with one who is a pupil, as I may say, of the real toils of the forum? <milestone
                    n="84" unit="section"/> “Yes, for I was not at <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                    >Rhodes</placeName>,” says he (He means that I was) “But I was,” says he, (I
                thought he was going to say, at <placeName key="tgn,7000989">Vacca</placeName>,<note
                    anchored="true"><placeName key="tgn,7000989">Vacca</placeName> was a town in
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName> which had a reputation for a
                    very bad style of oratory, as also had <placeName key="tgn,7006288"
                        >Cordoba</placeName>.</note>) “twice at <placeName key="perseus,Nicaea"
                    >Nicaea</placeName>, in Bithynia” If the place gives a person any handle for
                finding fault with one, I know not why you should think <placeName
                    key="perseus,Nicaea">Nicaea</placeName> stricter than <placeName
                    key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> if we are to examine into the cause, then
                you were in <placeName key="tgn,7016608">Bithynia</placeName> with the greatest
                credit, and I was at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> with no less.
                For as to the point on which you found fault with me, namely, that I had defended
                too many people, I wish that you who are able to do it and others too, who shirk it,
                were willing to relieve me of this labour. But the effect of your diligence, who
                weigh causes so carefully that you reject almost all of them, is that nearly all
                causes come to me who am not able to deny anything to men who are in misery and
                distress. <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>You reminded me also, since you had been in <placeName key="tgn,7012056"
                    >Crete</placeName> that something might have been said against your offering
                yourself as a candidate, and that I let that opportunity slip. Which of us, then, is
                more covetous of a smart saying? I, who did not say what might have been said, or
                you, who said it even against yourself? You were fond of saying that you had sent
                home no letters with accounts of your exploits, because mine, which I had sent to
                some one or other, had injured me. But I am not aware that they did injure me I am
                quite sure that they might have been of service to the republic. <milestone n="35"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="86" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>These things are, however, of but little importance; but those points are serious and
                weighty, that you wish now to find fault with, and in an underhand manner, to accuse
                my departure from the city, which you had often wept over. For you have said that
                assistance was not wanting to me, but that I was wanting to those who were willing
                to assist me. But I confess that, because I saw that aid was not wanting to me, I
                did on that account spare that aid; for who is there who does not know what was the
                state of things at that time.—what danger and what a storm there was in the
                republic? Was it fear of the tribunes, or was it the frenzy of the consuls which
                influenced me? Was it a very formidable thing for me to fight with the sword with
                the relics of those men, whom, when they were flourishing with their strength
                unimpaired, I had defeated without the sword? The basest and most infamous consuls
                in the memory of man,—as both the beginning of their conduct and as their recent
                termination of those affairs, show them to have been, (one of whom lost his army,
                and the other sold it,)—having bought their provinces, had deserted the senate, and
                the republic, and all good men. When no one knew what were the feelings of those men
                who by means of their armies, and their arms, and their riches, were the most
                powerful men in the state, then that voice, rendered insane by its infamous
                debaucheries, made effeminate by its attendance on holy altars, kept crying out in a
                most ferocious manner that both these men and the consuls were acting in concert
                with him. </p>
            <p>Needy men were armed against the rich, abandoned men against the good, slaves against
                their masters. <milestone n="87" unit="section"/> The senate was with me, even
                changing its garments in token of the danger; a measure which was adopted by public
                resolution for no one else except myself in the memory of man. But recollect who
                were then our enemies with the name of consuls. The only men since the city was
                built who ever prevented the senate from complying with a resolution of the senate,
                and who by their edict took away, not indeed grief, from the conscript fathers, but
                the power of deciding on the reasons for their grief. The whole equestrian order was
                with me; whom, indeed, that dancing consul of Catiline's used to frighten in the
                assemblies of the people with menaces of proscription. All <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> was assembled, and terrified with fear of
                civil war and devastation. <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I admit, O Laterensis, that I might have availed myself of these assistants, zealous
                in my behalf, and in a state of great excitement as they were. But the contest must
                have been decided not by right, nor by the laws, nor by argument; <pb n="143"/> for,
                in truth, that assistance of my own, which has often been placed so readily at the
                disposal of others, would not especially in so good a cause have been wanting to me
                myself. We must have fought with arms—yes, with arms I say; and it would have been
                destruction to the republic for arms to have been employed by slaves and leaders of
                slaves for the slaughter of the senate and of the virtuous citizens. <milestone
                    n="88" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>I confess that it would have been a fine thing for the wicked to have been conquered
                by the good, if I could have seen the end of the victory (which, in truth I could
                not). For where should I have found to stand by me so brave a consul as Lucius
                Opimius or as Caius Marius or as Lucius Flaccus? under whom, as her leaders, the
                republic did put down wicked men with armed citizens, or if I could not get men as
                fearless as those, yet where could I find men as just as Publius Mucius, who, after
                Tiberius Gracchus had been slain, defended Publius Scipio and asserted that the aims
                which he as a private individual had taken up, had been taken up in strict
                accordance with the law? We, then, should have had to fight with the consuls. I say
                no more, except this one thing; I saw that there were formidable adversaries ready
                to dispute the victory with us, and no one who would avenge us if we fell.
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/> If, then, I was wanting to these aids to the
                cause of my safety, because I was unwilling to do battle for it, I will then
                confess, as you say, that assistance was not wanting to me, but that I myself was
                wanting to the assistance which I had. But if, the greater I saw the zeal of good
                men in my behalf, the more I thought it my duty to consult their interests and to
                spare them, do you find fault with me for the same conduct which was considered a
                credit to Quintus Metellus and which is to this day, and always will be, his
                greatest glory? for it is well known—as you may hear from many who were present at
                the time—that he departed greatly against the will of all good men; and there is not
                the slightest doubt that he would have had the best of it if they had come to a
                struggle and a trial of arms. Therefore, though he was defending his own actions,
                and not those of the senate, though it was his own opinion that he was resolutely
                upholding and not the welfare of the republic,—still when he endured that voluntary
                wound he surpassed in glory and credit the justest and most illustrious triumphs of
                all the Metelli; because he would not be the <pb n="144"/> cause of even those
                wickedest of citizens being slain, and because he provided against the danger of any
                good man being involved in their slaughter. And should I,—seeing such great danger
                before us, as, if I were defeated, the total destruction of the republic must ensue,
                and if I got the better, an endless contest would follow, should I, I say, give any
                one reason to style me the destroyer of the republic, after having been its saviour?
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="90" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You say that I was afraid of death. But I should think it wrong to accept even
                immortality at the expense of the welfare of the republic; much less should I be
                willing to die, if by that means I was to damage the commonwealth. For as for those
                men who have given up their lives for the sake of the state, (although you may say
                that I am talking foolishly,) I have never considered that they had met with death
                so much as with immortality. But if I had at that time fallen by the weapons and
                hands of wicked men, the republic would for ever have lost the civil guardian of its
                safety. Moreover, if any violence of disease, or if nature itself had carried me
                off, still the resources of posterity would have been diminished, because by my
                death the opportunity would have been lost of showing what great zeal of the senate
                and people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> was to be exerted in
                retaining me. Should I, if I had ever had any extravagant fondness for life, have
                challenged the weapons of all those parricides in the month of December of the year
                of my consulship, when, if I had remained quiet for twenty days longer, they would
                all have fallen on the vigilance of other consuls? Wherefore, if fondness for life
                when contrary to the interests of the republic is shameful, at all events a desire
                for death in my case, which must have been accompanied with injury to the state,
                would have been more shameful still. </p>
            <p><milestone n="91" unit="section"/> For as for your boasting that you were a free man
                in the republic, I confess that you are, and I rejoice at it, and I also
                congratulate you on that account; but as for your denying that I am free also, as to
                that particular I will neither allow you nor any one else to continue in your
                mistake any longer. <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>For if any one thinks that my independence has suffered any diminution, because I do
                not now differ in opinion with all those same men with whom I was formerly
                accustomed to differ; in the first place, if I show myself grateful <pb n="145"/> to
                those who have deserved well of me, I do not cease to be attacked with the
                accusation of being a man of too good a memory, and too grateful. But if, without
                any injury to the republic, I sometimes show a regard to my own safety and that of
                my family, at all events I not only do not deserve to be blamed for this, but, even
                if I were to wish myself to run on ruin, there are good men who would entreat me not
                to do so. </p>
            <p><milestone n="92" unit="section"/> But the republic itself, if it were able to speak,
                would plead with me, that as I had always served her interests, and never my own,
                and as I had received a reward from her not such as I ought, rich and abundant, but
                mingled with exceeding bitterness, now at length to serve myself, and to consult the
                interests of my family; and would urge not only that she herself had received enough
                from me, but that she even feared that she had made me but an inadequate return for
                all the services which I had rendered her. </p>
            <p><milestone n="93" unit="section"/> But what will you say if I think nothing of all
                these things, and if I persevere in the same course in the republic which I have
                always pursued? will you still ask what is become of my independence? which you make
                to consist in the fact of our struggling for ever with any one with whom we have at
                any time had a contest. But this is all nonsense; for we ought at all times to act
                as if we were standing in some revolving orb of the republic, and as that turns
                round we ought to choose that part to which the advantage and safety of the republic
                direct us. <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But I do not call Cnaeus Pompeius the author, and prime cause, and defender of my
                safety, (for these things demand perhaps a recollection of the kindness and
                gratitude for it from a man in his private capacity,) but I say this, which has
                reference to the common welfare of the republic; should not I defend that man whom
                every one admits to be the first man in the republic? should I be wanting to the
                praises of Caius Caesar, when I see them celebrated first of all by numerous and
                most honourable decisions of the Roman people, and now too by those of the senate,
                to which body I have always devoted myself? In that case, in truth, I should confess
                that I had never formed any opinion with reference to the welfare of the republic,
                but that I was guided solely by my friendship for or enmity towards particular
                persons. <milestone n="94" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="146"/>
            </p>
            <p>When I see a ship holding on its course with favourable winds, if it does not proceed
                towards that port which I at one time thought best, but to some other no less safe
                and tranquil than that, shall I rather strive with the tempest even at the risk of
                danger, instead of yielding to it and being guided by it, especially when there is a
                hope of safety in such a line of conduct? But I have learnt these principles, I have
                seen and read them in books, written records have handed down to us these memorials
                of wise and most illustrious men, both in this republic and in other cities, and
                show that the same opinions have not at all times been upheld by the same men, but
                that they have adopted whatever sentiments the constitution of the republic, the
                state of affairs at the time, and the considerations of peace and concord pointed
                out as desirable. And this is what I am doing, O Laterensis, and what I always shall
                do; and the independence which you profess to look for in me, and which I have never
                lost, I never will lose, and yet on the other hand I will not believe it to consist
                in obstinacy, but in moderation. <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="95"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Now I come to your last assertion, when you said that, while I was extolling so
                highly the services which Plancius had done me, I was making a castle out of a
                sewer, and worshipping a stone taken from a sepulchre as a god; and that I had never
                been in the least danger of any one forming plots against me, or of death. And
                therefore I will in a few words, and not reluctantly, explain the circumstances of
                that time. For there is nothing that has happened during my lifetime which has got
                abroad less, or which has been seldomer talked about by me, or which has been less
                heard of and which is less commonly known by men in general. For I, O Laterensis,—on
                departing from that general conflagration of laws and justice, and the senate, and
                all good men, at a time when my house threatened while burning itself to set fire to
                the city and to all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, if I did not
                remain perfectly quiescent,—I, I say, intended to proceed to <placeName
                    key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, which was all united like one family in my
                favour, and which was at that time governed by Caius Virgilius, with whom I was most
                intimately connected both by the long duration of our acquaintance, and by
                friendship, and by his belonging to some of the same guilds as my brother, and by
                our common attachment to the republic. <milestone n="96" unit="section"/> See, now,
                the blackness of those times. When the <pb n="147"/> very island itself—I may almost
                say—wished to come forward to meet me, that praetor, repeatedly harassed as he was
                by the harangues and attacks of that same tribune of the people, on account of his
                attachment to the republic, would not consent (I will not use a stronger term) to my
                coming to <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. What shall I say? Shall I
                say that Caius Virgilius, that that excellent citizen and man had forgotten his
                regard for me, the recollection of the days of our companionship, and all regard for
                piety, humanity, and good faith? Nothing of the sort, O judges, was the case; he was
                only afraid that he might not be able by his own unassisted strength to make a stand
                against that tempest which we even, when supported by you, had been unable to
                encounter. Then, my plans being thus suddenly changed, I determined to proceed by
                land from Vibo to <placeName key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName>, for
                the severity of the weather prevented any attempt at proceeding by sea. <milestone
                    n="41" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="97" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>As all those municipal towns which are between Vibo and <placeName
                    key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName> were in my interest, O judges,
                they, though many people threatened me, and though they were in great alarm
                themselves, rendered my journey safe to me. I arrived at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Brundusium">Brundusium</placeName>, or, I should rather say, I
                arrived outside the walls. I avoided entering the city which was of all others the
                most friendly to me and which would have allowed itself to be destroyed before it
                would have permitted me to be torn from its embrace. I went to the villa of Marcus
                Laenius Flaccus; and though he had every sort of fear before his eyes,—though he was
                threatened with confiscation of his property, and exile and death, yet he chose to
                encounter all these things, if they were to happen rather than abandon the design of
                protecting my life. I, placed by his hands and by those of his father, a most
                sensible and virtuous man, and by those of his brother and both his sons in a safe
                and trustworthy ship, and being escorted by their prayers and vows for my return,
                departed thence to go to <placeName key="tgn,7010750">Dyrrachium</placeName>, which
                was devoted to my interests. <milestone n="98" unit="section"/> And when I had come
                thither, I ascertained—as indeed I had heard before—that <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> was full of wicked and abandoned men, whose
                impious weapons and destructive firebrands my consulship had wrested from their
                hands. And before they could hear that I had arrived in those districts, and
                although they were many days' journey from them, I proceeded into <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> to Plancius. But as <pb n="148"/> soon
                as ever Plancius heard that I had crossed the sea.—(listen, listen, I say, and take
                notice, O Laterensis, that you may know how much I owe to Plancius, and that you may
                confess at last that what I am doing I am doing out of proper gratitude and piously;
                and that the trouble which he took for my safety, if it is not to do him any good,
                ought at all events not to be any injury to him,)—as soon, I say, as he heard that I
                had arrived at <placeName key="tgn,7010750">Dyrrachium</placeName>, he immediately
                came to me himself, without his lictors, without any of the insignia of his office,
                and with his robe changed for one of morning. <milestone n="99" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, how bitter to me, O judges, is the recollection of that time and place, when he
                fell on my neck, when he embraced me, and bedewed me with his tears, and was unable
                to speak for grief! O circumstance cruel to be heard of, and impious to be beheld! O
                all the remainder of those days and nights during which he never left me, until he
                had conducted me to <placeName key="tgn,7011182">Thessalonica</placeName>, and to
                his official house as quaestor! Here I will say nothing at present about the praetor
                of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, beyond this, that he was
                always a most excellent citizen, and a friend to me; but that he felt the same fear
                that the rest did; and that Cnaeus Plancius was the only man—I will not say, who had
                no such fear—but who, even if those things were to happen which were dreaded, was
                willing to encounter and endure them in my company and for my sake. <milestone
                    n="100" unit="section"/> For even when Lucius Tubero, my intimate friend, who
                had been lieutenant to my brother, had come to me on his return from <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, and had revealed to me in the most friendly
                spirit the treacherous designs which he heard were formed against me by the banished
                conspirators, and when I was preparing therefore to go into <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> on account of the connection subsisting
                between that province and my brother and myself, he would not allow me to depart.
                He, Plancius, I say, detained me by force and by a close embrace, and for many
                months never departed from me, discarding his character as a quaestor and assuming
                that of my companion. <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="101"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>O what miserable nights of watching did you pass, O Cnaeus Plancius! O what tearful
                vigils! O what bitter nights! O what a miserable task was that which you undertook
                of protecting my life! if I, now that I am alive, am unable to be of any service to
                you, though perhaps I might have been of some if I had been dead. For I recollect, I
                    <pb n="149"/> well recollect, and I never shall forget, that night when I,
                miserable man that I was, and led on by ungrounded hopes, made you who were watching
                over me, and sitting by me, and lamenting, some vain and empty promises. I promised
                that, if I were restored to my country, then I would in person show my gratitude;
                but, if chance deprived me of life, or if any greater violence prevented my return,
                then I undertook that these men, these whom we see here, (for what others could I
                then be thinking of?) would make you a fitting return on my behalf, for all your
                exertions. Why do you fix your eyes upon me now? Why do you claim the performance of
                my promise? Why do you implore my observance of good faith? I was not promising you
                at that time anything from my own resources, but from the good-will of these men
                towards me. I saw that these men were mourning for me; that they were groaning for
                me; that they were willing to do battle in defence of my rights and safety, even at
                the hazard of their own lives—I, as well as you, was hearing every day of the
                regret, and grief, and complaints of these men; and now I fear that I may be able to
                make you no other return beyond tears, of which you yourself shed plenty for my
                distresses. <milestone n="102" unit="section"/> For what can I do more than grieve?
                more than weep? more than consider your safety bound up with my own? The same men
                who gave me safety are the only men who have the power to give it to you. But I
                (rise up and stand forward, I beg you,) will cling to you and embrace you; and I
                will profess myself, not only one who prays to the judges to protect your fortunes,
                but one who will be your companion and partner in them. And, as I hope, no one will
                be of so cruel and inhuman a disposition, nor so unmindful—I will not say of the
                services which I have done the good, but of the services which the good have done
                me—as to tear away and separate the saviour of my very existence as a citizen from
                me. I beg of you, O judges, to save a man who has been, not loaded with kindnesses
                by me, but the guardian of my safety. I am not striving in his behalf with wealth,
                and authority, and influence; but with prayers, and tears, and appeals to your
                mercy. And his unhappy and most virtuous father, whom you see before you, joins his
                entreaties to mine; we, being as it were two parents of his, pray your mercy for our
                one son. <milestone n="103" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Do not, O judges, I entreat you in the name of yourselves, <pb n="150"/> of your
                fortunes, and of your children, give joy to my enemies, especially to those whom I
                have made my enemies by labouring for your safety, by allowing them to boast that
                you have by this time forgotten me, and that you have shown yourselves enemies to
                the safety of the man by whom my safety was ensured. Do not crush my spirit not only
                with grief, but also with fear that your kind regard for myself is altered; allow me
                to pay the man from you, that which I repeatedly promised him because I relied on
                you. <milestone n="104" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And you, O Caius Flavius,<note anchored="true">Caius Flavius was one of the praetors
                    of the year, and, as such, president of this court.</note> you I beg and
                entreat—you who were the partner of my counsels during my consulship, and the sharer
                of my dangers, and my assistant in the exploits which I performed; and who have at
                all times wished me to be not only safe, but prosperous also and flourishing,—I
                entreat you, I say, to preserve for me, by the instrumentality of these men, that
                man to whom it is owing that you see me preserved to them and to you. It is not only
                my own tears, but yours also, O Flavius, and yours too, O judges, that hinder me
                from saying more: and by them I—though I am in a state of great apprehension—am
                induced to hope that you will show yourselves the same men with reference to the
                saving of Plancius that you did in my case; since by those tears which I now behold,
                I am reminded of those which you so repeatedly and abundantly shed for my sake.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
