<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 24</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="896" xml:id="p.896"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXIV.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Hieronymus, king of Syracuse, whose grandfather Hiero had been a faithful
                        ally of Rome, revolts to the Carthaginians, and for his tyranny is put to
                        death by his subjects. Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, the pro-consul, defeats
                        the Carthaginians under Hanno at Beneventum chiefly by the services of the
                        slaves in his army, whom he subsequently liberated. Claudius Marcellus, the
                        consul, besieges Syracuse. War is declared against Philip, king of Macedon;
                        he is routed by night at Apollonia and retreats into Macedonia. This war is
                        intrusted to Valerius the praetor. Operations of the Scipios against the
                        Carthaginians in Spain. Syphax, king of the Numidians, is received into
                        alliance by the Romans, and is defeated by Masinissa, king of the
                        Massillians, who fought on the side of the Carthaginians. The Celtiberians
                        joined the Romans, and their troops having been taken into pay, mercenary
                        soldiers for the first time served in a Roman camp. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ON his return from Campania into Bruttium,
                    Hanno, with the assistance and under the guidance of the Bruttians, made an
                    attempt upon the Greek cities; which were the more disposed to continue in
                    alliance with the Romans, because they perceived that the Bruttians, whom they
                    feared and hated, had taken part with the Carthaginians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The first place attempted was Rhegium, where several days
                    were spent without effect. Meanwhile the Locrians hastily conveyed from the
                    country into the city, corn, wood, and other things necessary for their use, as
                    also that no booty might be left for the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> The number of persons which poured out of every gate increased daily, till at
                    length those only were left in the city whose duty it was to repair the walls
                    and gates, and to collect weapons in the fortresses. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Against this mixed multitude, composed of persons of all
                    ages and ranks, while rambling through the country, and for the most part
                    unarmed, Hamilcar, the Carthaginian, sent out his cavalry, who, having been
                    forbidden to hurt any one, only interposed their squadrons, so as to cut them
                    off from the city when dispersed in flight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The general himself, having posted himself upon an eminence which commanded a
                    view of the country and the city, ordered a cohort of Bruttians to approach the
                    walls, call out <pb n="897" xml:id="p.897"/> the leaders of the Locrians to a
                    conference, and promising them the friendship of Hannibal, exhort them to
                    deliver up the city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At first the Bruttians
                    were not believed in any thing they stated in the conference, but afterwards,
                    when the Carthaginian appeared on the hills, and a few who had fled back to the
                    city brought intelligence that all the rest of the multitude were in the power
                    of the enemy, overcome with fear, they said they would consult the people.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> An assembly of the people was immediately
                    called, when, as all the most fickle of the inhabitants were desirous of a
                    change of measures and a new alliance, and those whose friends were cut off by
                    the enemy without the city, had their minds bound as if they had <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> given hostages, while a few rather silently
                    approved of a constant fidelity than ventured to support the opinion they
                    approved, the city was surrendered to the Carthaginians, with an appearance of
                    perfect unanimity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lucius Atilius, the captain
                    of the garrison, together with the Roman soldiers who were with him, having been
                    privately led down to the port, and put on board a ship, that they might be
                    conveyed to Rhegium, Hamilcar and the Carthaginians were received into the city
                    on condition that an alliance should be formed on equal terms; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> which condition, when they had surrendered, the
                    Carthaginian had very nearly not performed, as he accused them of having sent
                    away the Roman fraudulently, while the Locrians alleged that he had
                    spontaneously fled. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A body of cavalry went in
                    pursuit of the fugitives, in case the tide might happen to detain them in the
                    strait, or might carry the ships to land. The persons whom they were in pursuit
                    of they did not overtake, but they descried some ships passing over the strait
                    from Messana to Rhegium. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These contained
                    Roman troops sent by the praetor, Claudius, to occupy the city with a garrison.
                    The enemy therefore immediately retired from Rhegium. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> At the command of Hannibal, peace was concluded with the
                    Locrians on these terms: that <quote> they should live free under their own
                        laws; that the city should be open to the Carthaginians, the harbour in the
                        power of the Locrians. That their alliance should rest on the principle,
                        that the Carthaginian should help the Locrian and the Locrian the
                        Carthaginian in peace and war. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus the Carthaginian troops were led back
                    from the strait, while the Bruttians loudly complained that Locri and <pb
                        n="898" xml:id="p.898"/> Rhegium, cities which they had fixed in their minds
                    that they should have the plundering of, they had left untouched. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Having therefore levied and armed fifteen thousand of
                    their own youth, they set out by themselves to lay siege to Croto, which was
                    also a Greek city, and on the coast; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> believing
                    that they would obtain a great accession to their power, if they could get
                    possession of a city upon the sea-coast, which had a port and was strongly
                    defended by walls. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This consideration annoyed
                    them, that they neither could venture on the business without calling in the
                    Carthaginians to their assistance, lest they should appear to have done any
                    thing in a manner unbecoming allies; and on the other hand, lest, if the
                    Carthaginian general should again show himself to have been rather an umpire of
                    peace than an auxiliary in war, they should fight in vain against the liberty of
                    Croto, as before in the affair of the Locrians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The most advisable course, therefore, appeared to be, that ambassadors should
                    be sent to Hannibal, and that a stipulation should be obtained from him that
                    Croto, when reduced, should be in possession of the Bruttians. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal replied, that it was a question which should be
                    determined by persons on the spot, and referred them to Hanno, from whom they
                    could obtain no decisive answer. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For they were
                    unwilling that so celebrated and opulent a city should be plundered, and were in
                    hopes that if the Bruttians should attack it, while the Carthaginians did not
                    ostensibly approve or assist in the attack, the inhabitants would the more
                    readily come over to them. The Crotonians were not united either in their
                    measures or wishes. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All the states of Italy
                    were infected with one disease, as it were; the commons dissented from the
                    nobles; the senate favouring the Romans, while the commons endeavoured to draw
                    the states over to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A
                    deserter announced to the Bruttii that such a dissension prevailed in the city;
                    that Aristomachus was the leader of the commons, and the adviser of the
                    surrender of the city; that the city was of wide extent and thinly inhabited,
                    that the walls in every part were in ruins, that it was only here and there that
                    the guards and watches were kept by senators, and that wherever the commons kept
                    guard, there an entrance lay open. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Under the
                    direction and guidance of the deserter, the Bruttians completely invested the
                    city; and being received into it by the commons, got possession of every <pb
                        n="899" xml:id="p.899"/> part, except the citadel, on the first assault.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The nobles held the citadel, which they
                    had taken care beforehand to have ready as a refuge against such an event. In
                    the same place Aristomachus took refuge, as though he had advised the surrender
                    of the city to the Carthaginians, and not to the Bruttians. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The wall of the city of Croto in circuit
                    extended through a space of twelve miles, before the arrival of Pyrrhus in
                    Italy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the devastation occasioned by
                    that war, scarcely half the city was inhabited. The river which had flowed
                    through the middle of the town, now ran on the outside of the parts which were
                    occupied by buildings, and the citadel was at a distance from the inhabited
                    parts. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Six miles from this celebrated city
                    stood the temple of Juno Lacinia, more celebrated even than the city itself, and
                    venerated by all the surrounding states. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here
                    was a grove fenced with a dense wood and tall fir trees, with rich pastures in
                    its centre, in which cattle of every kind, sacred to the goddess, fed without
                    any keeper; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the flocks of every kind going out
                    separately and returning to their folds, never being injured, either from the
                    lying in wait of wild beasts, or the dishonesty of men. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> These flocks were, therefore, a source of great revenue,
                    from which a column of solid gold was formed and consecrated; and the temple
                    became distinguished for its wealth also, and not only for its sanctity.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some miracles are attributed to it, as is
                    generally the case with regard to such remarkable places. Rumour says that there
                    is an altar in the vestibule of the temple, the ashes of which are never moved
                    by any wind. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the citadel of Croto,
                    overhanging the sea on one side, on the other, which looks towards the land, was
                    protected formerly by its natural situation only, but was afterwards surrounded
                    by a wall. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was in this part that Dionysius,
                    the tyrant of Sicily, took it by stratagem, approaching by way of some rocks
                    which faced from it. This citadel, which was considered sufficiently secure, was
                    now occupied by the nobles of Croto, the <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                    Bruttians, in conjunction even with their own commons, besieging them.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Bruttians, however, perceiving at
                    length that it was impossible to take the citadel by their own efforts,
                    compelled by necessity, implored the aid of Hanno. He endeavoured to bring the
                    Crotonians to surrender, under an agreement that they should allow a colony of
                    Bruttians to <pb n="900" xml:id="p.900"/> settle there; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> so that their city, desolate and depopulated by wars, might
                    recover its former populousness: but not a man besides Aristomachus did he move;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> they affirmed, that <quote> they would
                        die sooner than, mixing with Bruttians, be turned to the rites, manners, and
                        laws, and soon the language also of others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Aristomachus alone, since he was neither able
                    to persuade them to surrender, nor could obtain an opportunity for betraying the
                    citadel as he had betrayed the city, deserted to Hanno. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> A short time afterwards ambassadors of Locri, entering the
                    citadel with the permission of Hanno, persuaded them to allow themselves to be
                    removed to Locri, and not resolve to hazard extremities. They had already
                    obtained leave from Hannibal to do this, by ambassadors sent for this purpose.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Accordingly, Croto was evacuated, and the
                    inhabitants were conducted to the sea, where they embarked; and the whole
                    multitude removed to Locri. In Apulia, Hannibal and the Romans did not rest even
                    during the winter. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The consul Sempronius
                    wintered at Luceria, Hannibal not far from Arpi. Slight engagements took place
                    between them, accordingly as either side had an opportunity or advantage; by
                    which the Roman soldiery were improved, and became daily more guarded and more
                    secure against stratagems. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Sicily, the death of Hiero, and the
                    transfer of the government to his grandson, Hieronymus, had completely altered
                    all things with regard to the Romans. Hieronymus was but a boy, as yet scarcely
                    able to bear liberty, still less sovereign power. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> His guardians and friends gladly observed in him a
                    disposition which might be easily plunged into every kind of vice; which Hiero
                    foreseeing, is said to have formed an intention, in the latter part of his long
                    life, of leaving Syracuse free, lest the sovereignty which had been acquired and
                    established by honourable means, should be made a sport of and fall into ruin,
                    under the administration of a boy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This plan
                    of his his daughters strenuously opposed, who anticipated that the boy would
                    enjoy the name of royalty, but that the administration of all affairs would be
                    conducted by themselves and their husbands, Andranodorus and Zoippus, for these
                    were left the principal of his guardians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It
                    was not an easy task for a man in his ninetieth year, beset night and day by the
                    winning artifices of women, to disenthral his judgment, and to consult only the
                    good of the state in his domestic affairs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="901" xml:id="p.901"/> Accordingly, all he did was to leave fifteen
                    guardians over his son, whom he entreated, on his death-bed, to preserve
                    inviolate that alliance with the Romans, which he had himself cultivated for
                    fifty years, and to take care that the young king should, above all things,
                    tread in the steps of his father, and in that course of conduct in which he had
                    been educated. Such were his injunctions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On
                    the death of the king, the will was brought forward by the guardians, and the
                    young king, who was now about fifteen, introduced into the public assembly,
                    where a few persons, who had been placed in different parts on purpose to raise
                    acclamations, expressed their approbation of the will; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> while all the rest were overwhelmed with apprehensions, in
                    the destitute condition of the state, which had lost as it were its parent.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The funeral of the king was then
                    performed, which was honoured more by the love and affection of his citizens
                    than the attentions of his kindred. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Andranodorus next effected the removal of the other guardians, giving out that
                    Hieronymus had now attained the years of manhood, and was competent to assume
                    the government; and thus, by voluntarily resigning the guardianship which he
                    shared with several others, united the powers of all in himself. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It would scarcely have been easy even for any
                    good and moderate king, succeeding one so deeply rooted in their affections as
                    Hiero was, to obtain the favour of the Syracusans. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But Hieronymus, forsooth, as if he was desirous of exciting
                    regret for the loss of his grandfather by his own vices, showed, immediately on
                    his first appearance, how completely every thing was changed. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For those who for so many years had seen Hiero and his son
                    Gelon differing from the rest of the citizens neither in the fashion of their
                    dress nor any other mark of distinction, now beheld the purple, the diadem, and
                    armed guards, and their <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> king sometimes
                    proceeding from his palace in a chariot drawn by four white horses, according to
                    the custom of the tyrant Dionysius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                    costliness in equipage and appearance was accompanied by corresponding contempt
                    of everybody, capricious airs, insulting expressions, difficulty of access, not
                    to strangers only, but even to his guardians also, unheard of lusts, inhuman
                    cruelty. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Terror so great took possession of
                    every body therefore, that some of his guardians, either by a voluntary death,
                    or by exile, anti- <pb n="902" xml:id="p.902"/> cipated the terror of his
                    inflictions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Three of those persons to whom
                    alone belonged a more familiar access to the palace, Andranodorus and Zoippus,
                    sons-in-law of Hiero, and one Thraso, were not much attended to upon other
                    subjects; but the two former exerting themselves in favour of the Carthaginians,
                    while Thraso argued for the Roman alliance, they sometimes engaged the attention
                    of the young king by their zeal and earnestness. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> It was at this time that a conspiracy formed against the life of the tyrant
                    was discovered by a certain <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> servant, of the
                    same age as Hieronymus, who from his very childhood had associated with him on
                    entirely familiar terms. The informer was able to name one of the conspirators,
                    Theodotus, by whom he himself had been solicited. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He was immediately seized, and delivered to Andranodorus to
                    be subjected to torture, when, without hesitation, he confessed as to himself,
                    but concealed his accomplices. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At last, when
                    racked with every species of torture, beyond the power of humanity to bear,
                    pretending to be overcome by his sufferings, he turned his accusation from the
                    guilty to the innocent, and feigned that Thraso was the originator of the plot,
                    without whose able guidance, he said, they <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                    never would have been bold enough to attempt so daring a deed, he threw the
                    guilt upon such innocent men, near the king's person, as appeared to him to be
                    the most worthless, while fabricating his story amid groans and agonies.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The naming of Thraso gave the highest
                    degree of credibility to the story in the mind of the tyrant. Accordingly he was
                    immediately given up to punishment, and others were added who were equally
                    innocent. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Not one of the conspirators, though
                    their associate in the plot was for a long time subjected to torture, either
                    concealed himself or fled; so great was their confidence in the fortitude and
                    fidelity of Theodotus, and so great was his firmness in concealing their secret. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus on the removal of Thraso, who formed the
                    only bond which held together the alliance with the Romans, immediately affairs
                    clearly indicated defection. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ambassadors were
                    sent to Hannibal, who sent back in company with a young man of noble birth named
                    Hannibal, Hippocrates and Epicydes, natives of Carthage, and of Carthaginian
                    extraction on their mother's side, but whose grandfather was an exile from
                    Syracuse. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Through their means an alliance was
                    formed <pb n="903" xml:id="p.903"/> between Hannibal and the tyrant of Syracuse;
                    and, with the consent of Hannibal, they remained with the tyrant. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> As soon as Appius Claudius, the praetor, whose
                    province Sicily was, had received information of these events, he sent
                    ambassadors to Hieronymus; who, upon stating that the object of their mission
                    was to renew the alliance which had subsisted between the Romans and his
                    grandfather, were heard and dismissed in an insulting manner, Hieronymus asking
                    them sneeringly, <quote> how they had fared at the battle of Cannae? for that
                        the ambassadors of Hannibal stated what could hardly be credited. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He said, <quote> he wished to know the truth,
                        in order that before he made up his mind, he might determine which he should
                        espouse as offering the better prospect. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Romans replied, that they would return to
                    him when he had learned to receive embassies with seriousness; and, after having
                    cautioned, rather than requested him, not rashly to change his alliance, they
                    withdrew. Hieronymus sent ambassadors to Carthage, to conclude a league in
                    conformity with the alliance with Hannibal. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It
                    was settled in the compact, that after they had expelled the Romans from Sicily,
                    (which would speedily be effected if the Carthaginians sent ships and troops,)
                    the river Himera, which divides the island in nearly equal portions, should be
                    the limit of the Carthaginian and Syracusan dominions. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Afterwards, puffed up by the flattery of those persons who
                    bid him be mindful, not of Hiero only, but of king Pyrrhus, his maternal
                    grandfather, he sent another embassy, in which he expressed his opinion that
                    equity required that the whole of Sicily should be conceded to him, and that the
                    dominion of Italy should be acquired as the peculiar possession of the
                    Carthaginians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This levity and inconstancy of
                    purpose in a hot-headed youth, did not excite their surprise, nor did they
                    reprove it, anxious only to detach him from the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But every thing conspired to hurry him into
                    perdition. For having sent before him Hippocrates and Epicydes with two thousand
                    armed men, to make an attempt upon those cities which were occupied by Roman
                    garrisons, he himself also proceeded to <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    Leontium with all the remaining troops, which amounted to fifteen thousand foot
                    and horse, when the conspirators (who all happened to be in the army) took
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> posses- sion of an uninhabited house,
                    which commanded a narrow <pb n="904" xml:id="p.904"/> way, by which the king was
                    accustomed to go to the forum. The rest stood here prepared and armed, waiting
                    for the king to pass by. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> One of them, by name
                    Dinomenes, as he was one of the body-guards, had the task assigned him of
                    keeping back the crowd behind in the narrow way, upon some pretext, when the
                    king approached the door. All was done according to the arrangement. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Dinomenes having delayed the crowd, by pretending to
                    lift up his foot and loosen a knot which was too tight, occasioned such an
                    interval, that an attack being made upon the king, as he passed by unattended by
                    his guards, he was pierced with several wounds before any assistance could be
                    brought. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the shout and tumult was heard,
                    some weapons were discharged on Dinomenes, who now openly opposed them; he
                    escaped from them, however, with only two wounds. The body-guard, as soon as
                    they saw the king prostrate, betook themselves to flight. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Of the assassins, some proceeded to the forum to the
                    populace, who were rejoiced at the recovery of their liberty; others to Syracuse
                    to anticipate the measures of Andranodorus and the rest of the royal party.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Affairs being in this uncertain state,
                    Appius Claudius perceiving a war commencing in his neighbourhood, informed the
                    senate by letter, that Sicily had become reconciled to the Carthaginians and
                    Hannibal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For his own part, in order to
                    frustrate the designs of the Syracusans, he collected all his forces on the
                    boundary of the province and the kingdom. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At
                    the close of this year, Quintus Fabius, by the authority of the senate,
                    fortified and garrisoned Puteoli, which, during the war, had begun to be
                    frequented as an emporium. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Coming thence to
                    Rome to hold the election, he appointed the first day for it which could be
                    employed for that purpose, and, while on his march, passed by the city and
                    descended into the Campus Martius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On that
                    day, the right of voting first having fallen by lot on the junior century of the
                    Anien tribe, they appointed Titus Otacilius and Marcus Aemilius Regillus
                    consuls, when Quintus Fabius, having obtained silence, delivered the following
                    speech: </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> If we had either peace in Italy, or had war with such an enemy that the
                        necessity to be careful was less urgent than it is, I should consider that
                        man as wanting in respect for your liberty, who would at all impede that
                        zealous desire which you bring with you into the Campus Martius, of con- <pb
                            n="905" xml:id="p.905"/> ferring honours on whom you please. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> But since during the present war, and with the
                        enemy we have now to encounter, none of our generals have ever committed an
                        error which has not been attended with most disastrous consequences to us,
                        it behoves you to use the same circumspection in giving your suffrages for
                        the creation of consuls, which you would exert were you going armed into the
                        field of battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Every man ought thus to
                        say to himself: I am nominating a consul who is to cope with the general
                        Hannibal. In the present year, at Capua, when Jubellius Taurea, the most
                        expert horseman of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the Campanians, gave
                        a challenge, Claudius Asellus, the most expert among the Roman horsemen, was
                        pitted against him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Against the Gaul who
                        at a former period gave a challenge on the bridge of the Anio, our ancestors
                        sent Titus Manlius, a man of resolute courage and great strength. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> It was for the same reason, I cannot deny it,
                        that confidence was placed in Marcus Valerius, not many years ago, when he
                        took arms against a Gaul who challenged him to combat in a similar manner.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the same manner as we wish to have
                        our foot and horse more powerful, but if that is impracticable, equal in
                        strength to the enemy, so let us find out a commander who is a match for the
                        general of the enemy. Though we should select the man as general whose
                        abilities are greater than those of any other in the nation, yet still he is
                        chosen at a moment's warning, his office is only annual; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> whereas he will have to cope with a veteran general who
                        has continued in command without interruption, unfettered <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> by any restrictions either of duration or of authority,
                        which might prevent him from executing or planning every thing according as
                        the exigencies of the war shall require. But with us the year is gone merely
                        in making preparations, and when we are only commencing our operations.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having said enough as to what sort of
                        persons you ought to elect as consuls, it remains that I should briefly
                        express my opinion of those on whom the choice of the prerogative century
                        has fallen. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius Regillus is
                        flamen of Quirinus, whom we can neither send abroad nor retain at home
                        without neglecting the gods or the war. Otacilius is married to my sister's
                        daughter, and has children by her, but the favours you have conferred upon
                        me and my ancestors, are not such' as that I should prefer private
                        relationship to the public weal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Any
                        sailor or pas- <pb n="906" xml:id="p.906"/> senger can steer the vessel in a
                        calm sea, but when a furious storm has arisen, and the vessel is hurried by
                        the tempest along the troubled deep, then there is need of a man and a
                        pilot. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> We are not sailing on a tranquil
                        sea, but have already well nigh sunk with repeated storms; you must
                        therefore employ the utmost caution and foresight in determining who shall
                        sit at the helm. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Of you, Titus Otacilius,
                        we have had experience in a business of less magnitude; and, certainly, you
                        have not given us any proof that we ought to confide to you affairs of
                        greater moment. The fleet which you commanded this year we fitted out for
                        three objects: to lay waste the coast of Africa, to protect the shores of
                        Italy, but, above all, to prevent the conveyance of reinforcements with pay
                        and provisions from Carthage to Hannibal. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        Now if Titus Otacilius has performed for the state, I say not all, but any
                        one of these services, make him consul. But if, while you had the command of
                        the fleet, supplies of whatever sort were conveyed safe and untouched to
                        Hannibal, even as though he had no enemy on the sea; <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> if the coast of Italy has been more infested this year
                        than that of Africa, what can you have to urge why you should be preferred
                        before all others as the antagonist of Hannibal? <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> Were you consul, we should give it as our opinion that
                        a dictator should be appointed in obedience to the example of our ancestors.
                        Nor could you feel offended that some one in the Roman nation was deemed
                        superior to you in war. It concerns yourself more than any one else, Titus
                        Otacilius, that there be not laid upon your shoulders a burthen under which
                        you would fall. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> I earnestly exhort you,
                        that with the same feelings which would influence you if standing armed for
                        battle, you were called upon suddenly to elect two generals, under whose
                        conduct and auspices you were to fight, you would this day elect your
                        consuls; <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> to whom your children are to
                        swear allegiance, at whose command they are to assemble, and under whose
                        protection and care they are to serve. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                        The Trasimene Lake and Cannae are melancholy precedents to look back upon,
                        but form useful warnings to guard against similar disasters. Crier, call
                        back the younger century of the Anien tribe to give their votes again.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Titus Otacilius, vociferating in the most
                    furious manner, that his object was to continue in the consulship, the consul
                    ordered the lictors to go to him; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and as he
                    had not entered <pb n="907" xml:id="p.907"/> the city, but had proceeded
                    directly without halting from his march to the Campus Martius, admonished him
                    that the axes were in the fasces which were carried before him. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The prerogative century proceeded to vote a second time,
                    when Quintus Fabius Maximus for the fourth time, and Marcus Marcellus for the
                    third time, were created consuls. The other centuries voted for the same persons
                    without any variation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> One praetor, likewise,
                    Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, was reelected; the other new ones who were chosen, were
                    Titus Otacilius Crassus a second time, Quintus Fabius, son of the consul, who
                    was at that time curule aedile, and Publius Cornelius Lentulus. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The election of the praetors completed, a decree of the
                    senate was passed, that Quintus Fulvius should have the city department out of
                    the ordinary course, and that he in preference to any other should command in
                    the city while the consuls were absent in the war. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Great floods happened twice during this year, and the Tiber
                    overflowed the fields, with great demolition of houses and destruction of men
                    and cattle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the fifth year of the second
                    Punic war Quintus Fabius Maximus for the fourth time, and Marcus Claudius
                    Marcellus for the third time, entering upon their office, drew the attention of
                    the state upon them in a more than ordinary degree, for there had not been two
                    such consuls now for many years. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The old men
                    observed, that thus Maximus Rullus and Publius Decius were declared consuls for
                    conducting the Gallic war; that thus afterwards Papirius and Carvilius were
                    appointed to that office against the Samnites, the Bruttians, and the Lucanian
                    with the Tarentine people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcellus, who was
                    with the army, was created consul in his absence; to Fabius, who was present and
                    held the election himself, the office was continued. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The critical state of affairs, the exigencies of the war,
                    and the danger which threatened the state, prevented any one from looking
                    narrowly into the precedent, or suspecting that the consul was actuated by an
                    excessive love of command; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> on the contrary,
                    they applauded his magnanimity in that when he knew the state was in want of a
                    general of the greatest ability, and that he was himself confessedly such an
                    one, he thought less of the personal odium which might arise out of the
                    transaction, than of the good of the state. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the day on which the consuls entered on
                    their office, the senate was assembled in the Capitol, and in the first place
                        <pb n="908" xml:id="p.908"/> a decree <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    was passed to the effect that the consuls should draw lots, and settle between
                    themselves which should hold the election for the creation of censors, before
                    they proceeded to join the army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Next, all
                    those who had the command of armies were continued in their offices, and ordered
                    to remain in their provinces; Tiberius Gracchus at Luceria, where he was with an
                    army of volunteer slaves; Caius Terentius Varro in the Picenian, and Manius
                    Pomponius in the Gallic territory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of the
                    praetors of the former year, it was settled that Quintus Mucius should have the
                    government of Sardinia as proprietor, Marcus Valerius the command of the
                    sea-coast near Brundusium, watchful against all the movements of Philip, king of
                    the Macedonians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To Publius Cornelius
                    Lentulus, the praetor, the province of Sicily was assigned. Titus Otacilius
                    received the same fleet which he had employed the year before against the
                    Carthaginians. Many prodigies were reported to have happened this year, which
                    increased in proportion as they were believed by the credulous and
                    superstitious. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That crows had built a nest
                    within the temple of Juno Sospita at Lanuvium; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    that a green palm-tree had taken fire in Apulia; that a pool at Mantua, formed
                    by the overflowing of the river Mincius, had assumed the appearance of blood;
                    that it had rained chalk at Cales, and blood at Rome in the cattle market;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that a fountain under ground in the
                    Istrian street had discharged so violent a stream of water, that rolling along
                    with the impetuosity of a torrent, it carried away the butts and casks which
                    were near it; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that the public court in the
                    Capitol had been struck by lightning; also the temple of Vulcan in the Campus
                    Martius, a nut-tree in the Sabine territory, a wall and gate at Gabii.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Now other miracles were published: that
                    the spear of Mars at Praeneste moved forward of its own accord; that in Sicily
                    an ox had spoken; that a child in the womb of its mother cried out Io Triumphe!
                    in the country of the Marrucinians; at Spoletum, that a woman was transformed
                    into a man; at Hadria, that an altar, with appearances as of men surrounding it
                    in white clothing, was seen in the heavens. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Nay, even in the city of Rome itself, after a swarm of bees had been seen in the
                    forum, some persons roused the citizens to arms, affirming that they saw armed
                    legions on the Janiculum; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> but those who were
                    on the Janiculum at the time, declared that they had seen no person there
                    besides the usual cultivators <pb n="909" xml:id="p.909"/> of the hill.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These prodigies were expiated by victims
                    of the larger kind, according to the response of the aruspices; and a
                    supplication was ordered to all the deities who had shrines at Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ceremonies which were intended to
                    propitiate the gods being completed, the consuls took the sense of the senate on
                    the state of the nation, the conduct of the war, what troops should be employed,
                    and where they were severally to act. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was
                    resolved that eighteen legions should be engaged in the war; that the consuls
                    should take two each; that two should be employed in each of the provinces of
                    Gaul, Sicily, and Sardinia; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that Quintus
                    Fabius, the praetor, should have the command of two in Apulia, and Tiberius
                    Gracchus of two legions of volunteer slaves in the neighbourhood of Luceria;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that one each should be left for Caius
                    Terentius, the proconsul, for Picenum, and to Marcus Valerius for the fleet off
                    Brundusium, and two for the protection of the city. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> To complete this number of legions six fresh ones were to
                    be enlisted, which the consuls were ordered to raise as soon as possible;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and also to prepare the fleet, so that,
                    together with the ships which were stationed off the coasts of Calabria, it
                    might amount that year to one hundred and fifty men of war. The levy completed,
                    and the hundred new ships launched, Quintus Fabius held the election for the
                    creation of censors, when Marcus Atilius Regulus and Publius Furius Philus were
                    chosen. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A rumour prevailing that war had
                    broken out in Sicily, Titus Otacilius was ordered to proceed thither with his
                    fleet; but as there was a deficiency of sailors, the consuls, in conformity with
                    a decree of the senate, published an order that those persons who themselves or
                    whose fathers had been rated in the censorship of Lucius Aemilius and Caius
                    Flaminius, at from fifty to one hundred thousand <hi rend="italics">asses,</hi>
                    or whose property had since reached that amount, should furnish one sailor and
                    six months' pay; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> from one to three hundred
                    thousand, three sailors with a year's pay; from three hundred thousand to a
                    million, five sailors; above one million, seven sailors; that senators should
                    furnish eight sailors with a year's pay. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    sailors furnished according to this proclamation being armed and equipped by
                    their masters, embarked with cooked provisions for thirty days. Then first it
                        <pb n="910" xml:id="p.910"/> happened that the Roman fleet was manned at the
                    expense of individuals. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These unusually great preparations alarmed the
                    Campanians particularly, lest the Romans should commence the year's campaign
                    with the siege of Capua. They therefore sent ambassadors to Hannibal, to implore
                    him to bring his army to Capua, and tell him that new armies were levying at
                    Rome for the purpose of besieging it; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and that
                    there was not any city the defection of which had excited more hostile feelings.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As they announced this with so much fear,
                    Hannibal concluded he must make haste lest the Romans should get there before
                    him; and setting out from Arpi, took up his position in his old camp at Tifata,
                    above Capua. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Leaving his Numidians and
                    Spaniards for the protection both of the camp and Capua, he went down thence
                    with the rest of his troops to the lake Avernus on the pretence of performing
                    sacrifice, but in reality to make an attempt upon Puteoli and the garrison in
                    it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Maximus, on receiving intelligence that
                    Hannibal had set out from Arpi, and was returning to Campania, went back to his
                    army, pursuing his journey without intermission by night or by day. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> He also ordered Tiberius Gracchus to bring up his
                    troops from Luceria to Beneventum, and Quintus Fabius the praetor, the son of
                    the consul, to go to Luceria in the room of Gracchus. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time the two praetors set out for Sicily,
                    Publius Cornelius to join his army, Otacilius to take the command of the
                    sea-coast and the fleet; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the rest also
                    proceeded to their respective provinces, and those who were continued in command
                    remained in the same countries as in the former year. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Hannibal was at the lake Avernus, five
                    noble youths came to him from Tarentum. They had been made prisoners partly at
                    the lake Trasimenus, and partly at Cannae, and had been sent home by the
                    Carthaginian with the same civility which he had shown towards all the Roman
                    allies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They stated to him that, impressed
                    with gratitude for his favours, they had succeeded in inducing a large portion
                    of the Tarentine youth to prefer his alliance and friendship to that of the
                    Romans; and that they were sent by their countrymen as ambassadors to request
                    Hannibal to bring his forces nearer to Tarentum; <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> that if his standards and camp were <pb n="911" xml:id="p.911"/> within sight
                    of Tarentum, that city would be delivered into his hands without delay; that the
                    commons were under the influence of the youth, and the state of Tarentum in the
                    hands of the commons. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal after bestowing
                    the highest commendations upon them, and loading them with immense promises, bid
                    them return home to mature their plans, saying that he would be there in due
                    time. With these hopes, the Tarentines were dismissed. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal had himself conceived the strongest desire of
                    getting possession of Tarentum. He saw that it was a city opulent and
                    celebrated, on the coast, and lying conveniently over against Macedonia. And
                    that as the Romans were in possession of Brundusium, king Philip would make for
                    this port if he crossed over into Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Having completed the sacrifice for which he came, and during his stay there laid
                    waste the territory of Cumae as far as the promontory of Misenum, he suddenly
                    marched his troops thence to Puteoli to surprise the Roman garrison there.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It consisted of six thousand men, and the
                    place was secured not only by its natural situation, but by works also. The
                    Carthaginian having waited there three days, and attempted the garrison in every
                    quarter, without any success, proceeded thence to devastate the territory of
                    Naples, influenced by resentment more than the hope of getting possession of the
                    place. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The commons of Nola, who had been long
                    disaffected to the Romans and at enmity with their own senate, moved into the
                    neighbouring fields on his approach; and in conformity with this movement
                    ambassadors came to invite Hannibal to join them, bringing with them a positive
                    assurance that the city would be surrendered to him. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The consul, Marcellus, who had been called in by the
                    nobles, anticipated their attempt. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In one day
                    he had reached Suessula from Cales, though the river Vulturnus had delayed him
                    crossing; and from thence the ensuing night introduced into Nola for the
                    protection of the senate, six thousand foot and three hundred horse. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The dilatoriness of Hannibal was in proportion to
                    the expedition which the consul used in every thing he did in order to preoccupy
                    Nola. Having twice already made the attempt unsuccessfully, he was slower to
                    place confidence in the Nolans. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same time, the consul, Fabius, came
                    to attempt Casilinum, which was occupied by a Carthaginian garrison; and, as if
                    by concert, Hanno approached Beneventum on <pb n="912" xml:id="p.912"/> one side
                    from the Bruttians, with a large body of foot and horse, while on the other side
                    Gracchus approached it from Luceria. The latter entered the town first.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then, hearing that Hanno had pitched his
                    camp three miles from the city, at the river Calor, and from thence was laying
                    waste the country, he himself marched without the walls, and pitching his camp
                    about a mile from the enemy, harangued his soldiers. The legions he had
                    consisted for the most part of volunteer slaves, who chose rather to earn their
                    liberty silently by another year's service, than demand it openly. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The general, however, on quitting his winter
                    quarters, had perceived that the troops murmured, asking when the time would
                    arrive that they should serve as free citizens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> He had written to the senate, stating not so much what they wanted as what
                    they had deserved; he said they had served him with fidelity and courage up to
                    that day, and that they wanted nothing but liberty, to bring them up to the
                    model of complete soldiers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Permission was
                    given him to act in the business as he thought for the interest of the state,
                    and, accordingly, before he engaged with the enemy, he declared that the time
                    was now arrived for obtaining that liberty which they had so long hoped for;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that on the following day he should fight
                    a pitched battle on a level and open plain, in which the contest would be
                    decided by valour only, without any fear of ambuscade. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The man who should bring back the head of an enemy, he
                    would instantly order to be set free; but that he would punish, in a manner
                    suited to a slave, the man who should quit his post; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> that every man's fortune was in his own hands; that not he
                    himself alone would authorize their enfranchisement, but the consul, Marcus
                    Marcellus, and the whole body of the fathers, who, on being consulted by him on
                    the subject, had left the matter to his disposal. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He then read the letter of the consul and the decree of the
                    senate, on which they raised a general shout of approbation, demanded to be led
                    to battle, and vehemently urged him to give the signal forthwith. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Gracchus broke up the assembly, after proclaiming
                    the battle for the following day. The soldiers, highly delighted, particularly
                    those whose enfranchisement was to be the reward of one day's prowess, employed
                    the remaining time in getting ready their arms. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day, as soon as the trumpets began to
                    sound, they were the first to assemble at the general's tent, armed <pb n="913"
                        xml:id="p.913"/> and ready for action. When the sun had risen, Gracchus led
                    out his troops to the field of battle; nor did the enemy delay to engage him.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His troops consisted of seventeen thousand
                    infantry, principally Bruttians and Lucanians, with twelve hundred horse, among
                    which were very few Italians, almost all the rest being Numidians and Moors. The
                    contest was fierce and protracted. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For four
                    hours neither side had the advantage, nor did any other circumstance more impede
                    the Romans, than that the heads of their enemies were made the price of their
                    liberty. For when each man had gallantly slain his enemy, first, he lost time in
                    cutting <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> off his head, which was done with
                    difficulty amid the crowd and confusion, and secondly, all the bravest troops
                    ceased to be engaged in fight, as their right hands were employed in holding the
                    heads; and thus the battle was left to be sustained by the inactive and
                    cowardly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But when the military tribunes
                    reported to Gracchus that the soldiers were employed not in wounding any of the
                    enemy who were standing, but in mangling those who were prostrate, their right
                    hands being occupied in holding the heads of men instead of their swords, he
                    promptly ordered a signal to be given that they should throw down the heads and
                    charge the enemy; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that they had given evident
                    and signal proofs of valour, and that the liberty of such brave men was certain.
                    Then the fight was revived, and the cavalry also were sent out against the
                    enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Numidians engaging them with great
                    bravery, and the contest between the cavalry being carried on with no less
                    spirit than that between the infantry, the victory again became doubtful; when,
                    the generals on both sides vilifying their opponents, the Roman saying, that
                    their enemies were Bruttians and Lucanians, who had been so often vanquished and
                    subjugated by their ancestors; the Carthaginian, that the troops opposed to them
                    were Roman slaves, soldiers taken out of a workhouse; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> at last Gracchus exclaimed, that his men had no ground to
                    hope for liberty unless the enemy were routed and put to flight that day. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These words at length kindled their courage so
                    effectually, and renewing the shout, as if suddenly changed into other men, they
                    bore down upon the enemy with such impetuosity that they could not longer be
                    withstood. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> First, those of the Carthaginians
                    who stood before the standards; <pb n="914" xml:id="p.914"/> then the standards
                    were thrown into disorder; and lastly, the whole line was compelled to give way.
                    They then turned their backs downright, and fled precipitately to their camp
                    with such terror and consternation, that not a man made a stand in the gates or
                    on the rampart; while the Romans, who pursued them so close as to form almost a
                    part of their body, commenced the battle anew, enclosed within the rampart of
                    the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here the battle was more bloody as
                    the combatants had less room to move, from the narrowness of the place in which
                    they fought. The prisoners too assisted; for snatching up swords in the
                    confusion, and forming themselves into a body, they slew the Carthaginians in
                    the rear and prevented their flight. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thus less
                    than two thousand men out of so large an army, and those principally cavalry,
                    effected their escape with their commander, all the rest were slain or taken
                    prisoners. Thirty-eight standards were taken. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Of the victors about two thousand fell. All the booty except that of the
                    prisoners was given up to the soldiery. Such cattle also as the owners should
                    identify within thirty days was excepted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When
                    they returned to their camp loaded with spoil, about four thousand of the
                    volunteer slaves who had fought with less spirit, and had not joined in breaking
                    into the enemy's camp, through fear of punishment, took possession of a hill not
                    far from the camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Being brought down thence
                    the next day by a military tribune, it happened that they arrived during an
                    assembly of the soldiers which Gracchus had called. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> At this assembly the proconsul, having first rewarded the
                    veteran soldiers with military presents, according to the valour displayed, and
                    the service rendered by each man in the engagement, then observed, with respect
                    to the volunteer slaves, that he would rather that all should be praised by him
                    whether deserving it or not, than that any one should be chastised on that day.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I bid you, said he, all be free, and may
                    the event be attended with advantage, happiness, and prosperity to the state and
                    to yourselves. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These words were followed by
                    the most cordial acclamations, the soldiers sometimes embracing and
                    congratulating one another, at other times lifting up their hands to heaven, and
                    praying that every blessing might attend the Roman people, and Gracchus in
                    particular; when Gracchus addressed them thus: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Before I had placed you all on an equal footing with respect to the
                        enjoyment of <pb n="915" xml:id="p.915"/> liberty, I was unwilling to affix
                        any marks by which the brave and dastardly soldier might be distinguished.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But now the pledge given by the state
                        being redeemed, lest all distinction between courage and cowardice should
                        disappear, I shall order that the names of those persons be laid before me,
                        who, conscious of their dastardly conduct in the battle, have lately
                        seceded. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I shall have them cited before
                        me, when I shall bind them by an oath, that none of them, except such as
                        shall have the plea of sickness, will, so long as they serve, take either
                        meat or drink in any other posture than standing. This penalty you will bear
                        with patience when you reflect that it is impossible your cowardice could be
                        marked with a slighter stigma. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He then gave the signal for packing up the
                    baggage; and the soldiers, sporting and jesting as they drove and carried their
                    booty, returned to Beneventum in so playful a mood, that they appeared to
                        <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> be returning, not from the field of
                    battle, but from a feast celebrated on some remarkable holiday. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> All the Beneventans pouring out in crowds to meet
                    them at the gate, embraced, congratulated, and invited the troops to
                    entertainments. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> They had all prepared
                    banquets in the courts of their houses, to which they invited the soldiers, and
                    of which they entreated Gracchus to allow them to partake. Gracchus gave
                    permission, with the proviso that they should feast in the public street. Each
                    person brought every thing out before his door. <milestone n="18" unit="section"
                    /> The volunteers feasted with caps of liberty on their heads, or filletted with
                    white wool; some reclining at the tables, others standing, who at once partook
                    of the repast, and waited upon the rest. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> It
                    even seemed a fitting occasion that Gracchus, on his return to Rome, should
                    order a picture representing the festivities of that day to be executed in the
                    temple of Liberty, which his father caused to be built on the Aventine out of
                    money arising from fines, and which his father also dedicated. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events occurred at Beneventum,
                    Hannibal having laid waste the territory of Naples, moved his camp to Nola.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul, as soon as he was aware of his
                    approach, sent for Pomponius the proprietor, with the troops he had in the camp
                    above Suessula; and then prepared to meet the enemy and to make no delay in
                    fighting. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He sent out Caius Claudius Nero in
                    the dead of night with the main strength of the cavalry, through the gate which
                    was farthest removed <pb n="916" xml:id="p.916"/> from the enemy, with orders to
                    make a circuit so as not to be observed, and then slowly to follow the enemy as
                    they moved along, and as soon as he perceived the battle begun, to charge them
                    on the rear. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whether Nero was prevented from
                    executing these orders by mistaking the route, or from the shortness of the
                    time, is doubtful. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Though he was absent when
                    the battle was fought, the Romans had unquestionably the advantage; but as the
                    cavalry did not come up in time, the plan of the battle which had been agreed
                    upon was disconcerted, and Marcellus, not daring to follow the retiring enemy,
                    gave the signal for retreat when his soldiers were conquering. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> More than two thousand of the enemy are said, however, to
                    have fallen on that day; of the Romans, less than four hundred. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Nero, after having fruitlessly wearied both men and horses,
                    through the day and night, without even having seen the enemy, returned about
                    sunset; when the consul went so far in reprimanding him as to assert, that he
                    had been the only obstacle to their retorting on the enemy the disaster
                    sustained at Cannae. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The following day the
                    Roman came into the field, but the Carthaginian, beaten even by his own tacit
                    confession, kept within his camp. Giving up all hope of getting possession of
                    Nola, a thing never attempted without loss, during the silence of the night of
                    the third day he set out for Tarentum, which he had better hopes of having
                    betrayed to him. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nor were the Roman affairs administered with
                    less spirit at home than in the field. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    censors being freed from the care of letting out the erection of public works,
                    from the low state of the treasury, turned their attention to the re- gulation
                    of men's morals, and the chastisement of vices which sprung up during the war,
                    in the same manner as constitutions broken down by protracted disease, generate
                    other maladies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the first place, they cited
                    those persons who, after the battle of Cannae, were said to have formed a design
                    of abandoning the commonwealth, and leaving Italy. The chief of these was Lucius
                    Caecilius Metellus, who happened to be then quaestor. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In the next place, as neither he nor the other persons
                    concerned were able to exculpate themselves on being ordered to make their
                    defence, they pronounced them guilty of having used words and discourse
                    prejudicial to the state, that a conspiracy might be formed for the abandonment
                    of Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="917" xml:id="p.917"/> After them were cited those persons who showed too
                    much ingenuity in inventing a method of discharging the obligation of their
                    oath, namely, such of the prisoners as concluded that the oath which they had
                    sworn to return, would be <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> fulfilled by their
                    going back privately to Hannibal's camp, after setting out on their journey.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such of these and of the abovementioned as
                    had horses at the public expense were deprived of them, and all were degraded
                    from their tribes and disfranchised. Nor was the attention of the censors
                    confined to the regulation of the senate and the equestrian order. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They erased from the lists of the junior centuries
                    the names of all who had not served during the last four years, unless they were
                    regularly exempted, or were prevented by sickness. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Those too, amounting to more than two thousand names, were
                    numbered among the disfranchised, and were all degraded. To this more gentle
                    stigma affixed by the censors, a severe decree of the senate was added, to the
                    effect that all those whom the censor had stigmatized, should serve on foot, and
                    be sent into Sicily to join the remains of the army of Cannae, a class of
                    soldiers whose time of service was not to terminate till the enemy was driven
                    out of Italy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The censors, in consequence of
                    the poverty of the treasury, having abstained from receiving contracts for the
                    repairs of the sacred edifices, the furnishing of curule horses, and similar
                    matters, the persons who had been accustomed to attend auctions of this
                    description, came to the censors in great numbers, and exhorted them to <quote>
                        transact all their business and let out the contracts in the same manner as
                        if there were money in the treasury. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That
                        none of them would ask for money out of the treasury before the war was
                        concluded. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Afterwards the owners of those slaves whom
                    Tiberius Sempronius had manumitted at Beneventum, came to them, stating that
                    they were sent for by the public bankers, to receive the price of their slaves,
                    but that they would not accept of it till the war was concluded. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> This disposition on the part of the commons to
                    sustain the impoverished treasury having manifested itself, the property of
                    minors first, and then the portions of widows, began to be brought in; the
                    persons who brought them being persuaded, that their deposit would no where be
                    more secure and inviolable than under the public faith. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> If any thing was bought or laid in for the widows and
                    minors, an order upon the quaes- <pb n="918" xml:id="p.918"/> tor was given for
                    it. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This liberality in individuals flowed
                    from the city into the camp also, insomuch that no horseman or centurion would
                    accept of his pay, and those who would accept it were reproached with the
                    appellation of mercenary men. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius, the consul, was encamped
                    before Casilinum, which was occupied by a garrison of two thousand Campanians
                    and seven hundred of the soldiers of Hannibal The commander was <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> Statius Metius, who was sent there by Cneius Magius
                    Atellanus, who was that year Medixtuticus, and was arming the slaves and people
                    without distinction, in order to assault the Roman camp, while the consul was
                    intently occupied in the siege of Casilinum. None of these things escaped
                    Fabius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He therefore sent to his colleague at
                    Nola, <quote> That another army was requisite, which might be opposed to the
                        Campanians, while the siege of Casilinum was going on; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> that either he should come himself, leaving a force
                        sufficient for the protection of Nola, or if the state of Nola required him
                        to stay there, in consequence of its not being yet secure against the
                        attempts of Hannibal, that he should summon Tiberius Gracchus, the
                        proconsul, from Beneventum </quote> On this message, Marcellus, leaving two
                    thousand troops in garrison at Nola, came to Casilinum with the rest of his
                    forces; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and at his arrival the Campanians, who
                    were already in motion, desisted from their operations. Thus the siege of
                    Casilinum was commenced by the two consuls. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But as the Roman soldiers received many wounds as they rashly approached the
                    walls, and as they did not succeed satisfactorily in their attempts, Fabius gave
                    it as his opinion that this, which was a small matter, though as difficult as
                    more important ones, should be abandoned, and that they should retire from the
                    place, as affairs of greater moment were pressing. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus, however, succeeded in persuading him that they
                    should not go away with their object unaccomplished, observing that as there
                    were many objects which great generals should not attempt, so when once
                    attempted they should not be abandoned, because the mere report in either case
                    would have important consequences. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Upon this
                    the vineae and all kinds of military works and engines were applied; in
                    consequence of which, the Campanians entreated Fabius to allow them to retire to
                    Capua in safety; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> when a few of them having
                    come out of the town, Marcellus took pos- <pb n="919" xml:id="p.919"/> session
                    of the gate through which they passed, and first slew all indiscriminately who
                    were near the gate, and then rushing in, the slaughter commenced in the town
                    also. About fifty of the Campanians, who at first came out of the city, having
                    fled for refuge to Fabius, arrived safe at Capua under his protection.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus Casilinum was captured on an
                    accidental opportunity which occurred during the conferences and delay of those
                    who were soliciting protection. The prisoners, both those who were Campanians
                    and those who were Hannibal's soldiers, were sent to Rome, where they were shut
                    up in a prison. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The crowd of townsmen was
                    distributed among the neighbouring people to be kept in custody. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time that the consuls retired from
                    Casilinum, their object having been accomplished, Gracchus, who was in Lucania,
                    sent, under a praefect of the allies, some cohorts which he had levied in that
                    country to ravage the lands of the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    These, as they were straggling in a careless manner, Hanno surprising, retorted
                    upon his enemy a defeat not much less disastrous than he had himself received at
                    Beneventum, and then hastily retired to the territory of the Bruttians, lest
                    Gracchus should overtake him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of the consuls,
                    Marcellus returned to Nola, whence he had come, Fabius proceeded to Samnium to
                    waste the lands, and recover by force the cities which had revolted. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Samnites of Caudium suffered the severest
                    devastation; their fields were laid waste by fire for a wide extent, and both
                    men and cattle were conveyed away as booty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The towns of Compulteria, Telesia, Compsa, Melae, Fulfulae, and Orbitanium, were
                    taken by storm. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Blandae, belonging to the
                    Lucanians, and $Aecae to the Apulians, were taken after a siege. Twenty-five
                    thousand of the enemy were captured or slain in these towns, and three hundred
                    and seventy deserters recovered; who, being sent to Rome by the consul, were all
                    of them beaten with rods in the comitium, and thrown down from the rock.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such were the achievements of Fabius
                    within the space of a few days. Ill health detained Marcellus from active
                    operations at Nola. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The town of Accua also was
                    taken by storm, during the same period, by the praetor Quintus Fabius, whose
                    province was the neighbourhood of Luceria; he also fortified a stationary camp
                    at Ardonea. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> While the Romans were thus
                    employed in different quarters, Hannibal had reached Tarentum, utterly <pb
                        n="920" xml:id="p.920"/> destroying every thing whichsoever way he went. In
                    the territory of Tarentum, the troops at length began to march in a peaceable
                    manner. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There nothing was violated, nor did
                    they ever go out of the road; it was evident that this was done not from the
                    moderation of the soldiery, or their general, but to conciliate the affections
                    of the Tarentines. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> However, on advancing
                    almost close to the walls without perceiving any movement, which he expected
                    would occur on the sight of his vanguard, he pitched his camp about a mile off
                    the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Three days before the arrival of
                    Hannibal, Marcus Livius, who had been sent by Marcus Valerius, the propraetor,
                    commanding the fleet at Brundusium, had enlisted the young nobility of Tarentum,
                    and stationing guards at every gate, and <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    round the walls, wherever circumstances made it necessary, had kept such a
                    strict watch both by day and night, as to give no opportunity for making any
                    attempt either to the enemy or doubtful allies. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> On this account several days were consumed there to no purpose, when
                    Hannibal, as none of those who had come to him at the lake Avernus, either came
                    themselves or sent any letter or message, perceiving that he had carelessly
                    followed delusive promises, moved his camp thence. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Even after this he did not offer any violence to the
                    Tarentine territory, not quitting the hope of shaking their allegiance to the
                    Romans, though his simulated lenity had hitherto been of no advantage to him;
                    but as soon as he came to Salapia he collected stores of corn there from the
                    Metapontine and Heraclean lands; for midsummer was now past, and the situation
                    pleased him as a place for winter quarters. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    From hence the Moors and Numidians were detached to plunder the territory of
                    Sallentum, and the neighbouring woods of Apulia, from which not much booty of
                    any other sort was obtained, but principally droves of horses, four thousand of
                    which were distributed among his horsemen to be broken. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans, since a war by no means to be
                    despised was springing up in Sicily, and the death of the tyrant had furnished
                    the Syracusans with more enterprising leaders, rather than changed their
                    attachment to the Carthaginian cause, or the state of their minds, decreed that
                    province to Marcus Marcellus, one of their consuls. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> After the assassination of Hieronymus, at first a tumult
                    had taken place among the sol- <pb n="921" xml:id="p.921"/> diery in the
                    territory of the Leontines. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They exclaimed
                    furiously that the manes of the king should be appeased with the blood of the
                    conspirators. Afterwards the frequent repetition of the word liberty, which was
                    restored to them, a word so delightful to the ear, the hopes they had conceived
                    of largesses from the royal treasury, and of serving in future under better
                    generals, the relation of the horrid crimes and more horrid lusts of the tyrant,
                    effected such an alteration in their sentiments, that they suffered to lie
                    unburied the corpse of the king, whom a little before they regretted. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> As the rest of the conspirators remained behind, in
                    order to keep the army on their side, Theodotus and Sosis, mounted on the king's
                    horses, rode off to Syracuse with all possible speed, that they might surprise
                    the king's party, while unacquainted with all that had occurred. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> But they were anticipated not only by report, than
                    which nothing is swifter in such affairs, but also by a messenger who was one of
                    the royal servants. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In consequence,
                    Andranodorus had occupied with strong garrisons the Insula and the citadel, and
                    every other convenient part which he could. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    After sunset, when it was now growing dark, Theodotus and Sosis rode in by the
                    Hexapylum, and displayed the royal vest stained with blood, and the ornament of
                    the king's head; then passing through the Tycha, and calling the people at once
                    to liberty and arms, bid them assemble in the Achradina. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Some of the multitude ran out into the streets, some stood
                    in the porches of their houses, while others looked out from the roofs and
                    windows, and inquired what was the matter. Every part of the city was filled
                    with lights and noises of various kinds. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Assemblies of armed men were formed in the open spaces. Those who had no arms
                    tore down from the temple 'of the Olympian Jupiter the spoils of the Gauls and
                    Illyrians, which had been presented to Hiero by the Roman people, and hung up
                    there by him; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> at the same time offering up
                    prayers to Jupiter, that he would willingly, and without feeling offence, lend
                    those consecrated weapons to those who were arming themselves in defence of
                    their country, of the temples of their gods, and their liberty. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> This multitude was also joined by the watches which
                    were stationed through the principal quarters of the city. In the island,
                    Andranodorus, among other places, secured the public granaries by a garrison.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This place, which was enclosed by a wall
                    of <pb n="922" xml:id="p.922"/> stones hewn square, and built up on high, after
                    the manner of a citadel, was occupied by a body of youth, who had been appointed
                    to garrison it, and these sent messengers to the Achradina, to give information
                    that the granaries and the corn were in the power of the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At break of day the whole populace, armed and
                    unarmed, assembled at the senate-house in the Achradina; where from the altar of
                    Concord, which stood there, one of the nobles, named Polyaenus, delivered a
                    liberal and temperate address. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He said, that
                        <quote> men who had experienced servitude and contumely, were enraged
                        against an evil which was well known, but that the Syracusans had rather
                        heard from their fathers than seen with their own eyes the disasters which
                        civil discord introduces. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He said, <quote> he commended them for the
                        alacrity with which they had taken arms; but that he should commend them
                        more if they should abstain from using them unless compelled by extreme
                        necessity. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At present he advised that
                        ambassadors should be sent to Andranodorus, to charge him to submit to the
                        direction of the senate and the people, to throw open the gates of the
                        island, and withdraw the garrison. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If he
                        resolved to usurp the sovereignty of which he had been appointed guardian,
                        that he would recommend that their liberty be recovered more energetically
                        from Andranodorus than it had been from Hieronymus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From this assembly ambassadors were
                    despatched. The senate began now to meet, which though during the reign of Hiero
                    it had continued to be the public council of the state, from the time of his
                    death up to the present had never been assembled or consulted upon any subject.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the ambassadors came to Andranodorus,
                    he was himself moved by the unanimous opinion of his countrymen, by their having
                    possession of other parts of the city, and by the fact that the strongest part
                    of the island was betrayed and placed in the hands of others; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> but his wife, Demarata, the daughter of Hiero, still
                    swelling with the pride of royalty and female presumption, called him out from
                    the presence of the ambassadors, and reminded him of the expression so often
                    repeated by the tyrant Dionysius, that a man ought only to relinquish sovereign
                    power when dragged by the feet, and not while sitting on horseback. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> That it was an easy thing, at any moment one pleased,
                    to give up possession of grandeur, but that to create and obtain them was <pb
                        n="923" xml:id="p.923"/> difficult and arduous. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> That he should obtain from the ambassadors a little time to
                    deliberate, and to employ it in fetching the soldiers from the Leontines; to
                    whom, if he promised the royal treasure, every thing would be at his disposal."
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This advice, suggested by a woman,
                    Andranodorus neither entirely rejected nor immediately adopted, considering it
                    the safer way to the attainment of power to temporize for the present.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Accordingly he told the ambassadors to
                    carry word back, that he should act subserviently to the senate and the people.
                    The next day, as soon as it was light, he threw open the gates of the island,
                    and came into the forum of the Achradina; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    then mounting the altar of Concord, from which Poly- aenus had delivered his
                    harangue the day before, he commenced a speech by soliciting pardon for his
                    delay. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>He had kept the gates closed,</quote> he said, <quote> not as separating
                        his own from the public interest, but from fear as to where the carnage
                        would stop when once the sword was drawn; whether they would be satisfied
                        with the blood of the tyrant, which was sufficient for their liberty, or
                        whether all who were connected with the court, by consanguinity, affinity,
                        or any offices, would, as implicated in another's guilt, be butchered.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After he perceived that those who had
                        liberated their country were desirous of preserving it when liberated, and
                        that the counsels of all were directed towards the public good, he had not
                        hesitated to restore to his country his own person and every thing else
                        which had been committed to his honour and guardianship, since the person
                        who had intrusted him with them had fallen a victim to his own madness. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Then turning to the persons who had killed
                    the tyrant, and calling on Theodotus and Sosis by name, he said, <quote> You
                        have performed a memorable deed, but believe me, your glory is only
                        beginning, not yet perfected; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> and there
                        still remains great danger lest the enfranchised state should be destroyed,
                        if you do not provide for its tranquillity and harmony. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the conclusion of this speech, he laid the
                    keys of the gates and of the royal treasure at their feet; and on that day,
                    retiring from the assembly in the highest spirits, they made supplication with
                    their wives and children at all the temples of the gods. On the following day an
                    assembly was held for the election of praetors. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Andranodorus was created among the first; the rest consisted for the most
                    part of the <pb n="924" xml:id="p.924"/> destroyers of the tyrant; two of these,
                    Sopater and Dinomenes, they appointed in their absence. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> These, on hearing of what had passed at Syracuse, conveyed
                    thither the royal treasure which was at Leontini, and put it into the hands of
                    quaestors appointed for that purpose. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    treasure also in the island and the Achradina was delivered to them, and that
                    part of the wall which formed too strong a separation between the island and the
                    other parts of the city, was demolished by general consent. Every thing else
                    which was done was in conformity with this inclination of their minds to
                    liberty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hippocrates and Epicydes, on hearing
                    of the death of the tyrant, which Hippocrates had wished to conceal even by
                    putting the messenger to death, being deserted by the soldiery, returned to
                    Syracuse, as that appeared the safest course under present circumstances;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but lest if they appeared there in common
                    they should become objects of suspicion, and looked upon as persons who were
                    seeking an opportunity of effecting some change, they in the first place
                    addressed themselves to the praetors and then through them to the senate.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They declared, that <quote> they were sent
                        by Hannibal to Hieronymus, as to a friend and ally; that they had obeyed the
                        orders of that man whom their general wished them to obey; that they desired
                        to return to Hannibal; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but as the journey
                        would not be safe, as armed Romans were ranging at large through the whole
                        of Sicily, that they requested to be furnished with some escort which might
                        convey them in safety to Locri in Italy; and that thus they would confer a
                        great obligation upon Hannibal, with little trouble. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The request was easily obtained, for they were
                    desirous of getting rid of these generals of the king, who were skilled in war,
                    and at once necessitous and enterprising. But they did not exert themselves so
                    as to effect what they desired with the requisite speed. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Meanwhile these young men, who were of a military turn and
                    accustomed to the soldiers, employed themselves in circulating charges against
                    the senate and nobles, sometimes in the minds of the soldiers themselves,
                    sometimes of the deserters, of which the greater part were Roman sailors, at
                    other times of men belonging to the lowest order of the <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> populace, insinuating, that <quote> what they were secretly
                        labouring and contriving to effect, was to place Syracuse under the dominion
                        of the Romans with the pretence of a renewed alliance, and then that a <pb
                            n="925" xml:id="p.925"/> faction and the few promoters of the alliance
                        would be supreme. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The crowds of persons disposed to hear and
                    credit these insinuations which flowed into Syracuse from every quarter
                    increased daily, and afforded hopes, not only to Epicydes but to Andranodorus
                    also, of effecting a revolution. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The latter,
                    wearied at length by the importunities of his wife, who warned him, <quote> that
                        now was the favourable time for seizing the government, while every thing
                        was in confusion in consequence of liberty being recent and not yet
                        regularly established; while a soldiery supported by the royal pay was to be
                        met with, and while generals sent by Hannibal and accustomed to the soldiery
                        might forward the attempt; </quote> he communicated his design with
                    Themistus, who had married the daughter of Gelon, and a few days afterwards
                    incautiously disclosed it to a certain tragic actor, named Ariston, to whom he
                    was in the habit of committing other secrets. He was a man of reputable birth
                    and fortune, nor did his profession disgrace them, for among the Greeks no
                    pursuit of that kind was considered dishonourable. He therefore discovered the
                    plot to the praetors, from a conviction that his country had a superior claim
                    upon his fidelity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These having satisfied
                    themselves that his statement was not false by indubitable proofs, took
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the advice of the elder senators, and
                    with their sanction, having placed a guard at the doors, slew Themistus and
                    Andranodorus as soon as they had entered the senate-house. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> A disturbance arising in consequence of this act, which, as
                    none but the praetors knew the cause of it, wore an appearance of atrocity, the
                    praetors, having at length procured silence, introduced the informer into the
                    senate-house; and after he had in a regular manner detailed to the senate every
                    particular, showing that the conspiracy owed its origin to the marriage of
                    Harmonia, the daughter of Gelon, with Themistus; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> that the African and Spanish auxiliaries had been prepared to murder the
                    praetors and others of the nobility; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that it
                    had been given out that their goods were to be the booty of the assassins; that
                    already a band of mercenaries accustomed to obey the command of Andranodorus had
                    been procured for the reoccupation of the island; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and having then distinctly represented to them the several
                    parts which the persons implicated in the transaction were performing, and
                    having <pb n="926" xml:id="p.926"/> brought under their view the entire plot
                    prepared for execution with men and arms; it seemed to the senate that they had
                    fallen as justly as Hieronymus had. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A shout
                    was raised before the senate-house by a crowd of people variously disposed and
                    uncertain of the facts; but as they were conducting themselves in a furious and
                    menacing manner, the bodies of the conspirators in the vestibule of the
                    senate-house restrained them with such alarm, that they silently followed the
                    more discreet part of the commons to an assembly. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Sopater was the person commissioned by the senate and his
                    colleague to explain the affair. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Treating them as if they stood upon their
                    trial, he began with their past lives; and insisted that Andranodorus and
                    Themistus were the authors of every act of iniquity and impiety which had been
                    perpetrated since the death of Hiero. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>For what,</quote> said he, <quote> did the boy Hieronymus ever do of his
                        own accord? What could he do who had scarce as yet arrived at puberty? His
                        tutors and guardians had ruled, while the odium rested on another. Therefore
                        they ought to have been put to death either before Hieronymus or with him.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nevertheless those men, deservedly
                        marked out for death, had attempted fresh crimes after the decease of the
                        tyrant; first openly, when, closing the gates of the island, Andranodorus
                        declared himself heir to the throne, and kept that as proprietor which he
                        had held only in the capacity of guardian; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        afterwards, when betrayed by those who were in the island and blockaded by
                        the whole body of the citizens who held the Achradina, he endeavoured to
                        obtain, by secret and artful means, that sovereignty which he had in vain
                        attempted openly; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> whom not even benefits
                        and honorary distinction could move, for even this conspirator against the
                        liberty of his country was created praetor among her liberators. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> But that wives of royal blood had infected them
                        with this thirst for royalty, one having married the daughter of Hiero, the
                        other the daughter of Gelon. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On hearing these words, a shout arose from
                    every part of the assembly, that <quote> none of these women ought to live, and
                        that not one of the royal family should be left alive. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Such is the nature of the populace; they are
                    either cringing slaves or haughty tyrants. They know not how with moderation to
                    spurn or to enjoy that liberty which holds the middle place; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> nor are there generally wanting ministers, the panders <pb
                        n="927" xml:id="p.927"/> to their resentment, who incite their eager and
                    intemperate minds to blood and carnage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus,
                    on the present occasion, the praetors instantly proposed the passing of a
                    decree, which was consented to almost before it was proposed, that all the royal
                    family should be put to death; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and persons
                    despatched for the purpose by the praetors, put to death Demarata, the daughter
                    of Hiero, and Harmonia, the daughter of Gelon, the wives of Andranodorus and
                    Themistus. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was a daughter of Hiero, named Heraclea,
                    the wife of Zoippus, who, having been sent by Hieronymus as ambassador to king
                    Ptolemy, had become a voluntary exile. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As soon
                    as she was apprized that they were coming to her also, she fled for refuge into
                    the chapel to the household gods, accompanied by her two virgin daughters, with
                    dishevelled hair, and other marks of wretchedness. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In addition to this, she had recourse to prayers also; she
                    implored them <quote> by the memory of her father, Hiero, and her brother,
                        Gelon, that they would not suffer her, a guiltless person, to be consumed by
                        their hatred of Hieronymus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That all that
                        she had derived from his reign was the exile of her husband. That neither
                        did she enjoy the same advantages as her sister while Hieronymus was alive,
                        nor was her cause the same as hers now he was dead. What? <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Though her sister would have shared the throne with
                        Andranodorus, had he succeeded in his designs, she must have been in
                        servitude with the rest. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Can any one
                        doubt, that if information should be conveyed to Zoippus that Hieronymus had
                        been put to death, and that Syracuse was free, he would instantly embark and
                        return to his native land. But how are all human hopes deceived! <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> His wife and children are struggling for their
                        lives in his native land, now blessed with liberty! In what manner standing
                        in the way of liberty or the laws? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> What
                        danger could arise to any one from them, from a solitary, and in a manner,
                        widowed woman and girls living in a state of orphanage? But perhaps it will
                        be granted that no danger is to be apprehended from them, but alleged that
                        the whole royal family is detested. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If
                        this were the case, she entreated that they would banish them far from
                        Syracuse and Sicily, and order them to be conveyed to Alexandria, the wife
                        to her husband, the daughters to their father. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Seeing that their ears and minds were
                    unimpressed, and that certain of them were drawing their swords to prevent a
                    fruitless <pb n="928" xml:id="p.928"/> consumption of time, she gave over
                    entreating for herself, and began to implore them to <quote>spare, at least, her
                        daughters, at an age which even exasperated enemies spared.</quote> She
                    entreated them <quote> that they would not, in their revenge on tyrants,
                        themselves imitate the crimes which were odious to them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While thus employed, they dragged her from
                    the sanctuary and murdered her; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and after
                    that they fell upon the virgins, who were sprinkled with the blood of their
                    mother; who, distracted alike by fear and grief, and as if seized with madness,
                    rushed out of the chapel with such rapidity, that had there been an opening by
                    which they might have escaped into the street, they would have filled the city
                    with confusion. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As it was, they several times
                    made their escape through the midst of so many armed men with their persons
                    uninjured in the contracted space which the house afforded, and extricated
                    themselves from their grasp, though they had to disengage themselves from so
                    many and such strong hands; but at length enfeebled by wounds, and after
                    covering every place with blood, they fell down lifeless. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> This murder, piteous as it was in itself, was rendered
                    still more so by its happening that a short time after it a message arrived that
                    they should not be killed, as the minds of the people were now turned to
                    compassion. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This compassion then gave rise to
                    a feeling of anger, because so much haste had been shown in carrying the
                    punishment into effect, and because no opportunity was left for relenting or
                    retracing the steps of their passion. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The
                    multitude therefore gave vent to their indignation, and demanded an election to
                    supply the places of Andranodorus and Themistus, for both of them had been
                    praetors; an election by no means likely to be agreeable to the praetors. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The day was fixed for the election, when, to
                    the surprise of all, one person from the extremity of the crowd nominated
                    Epicydes, and then another from the same quarter nominated Hippocrates.
                    Afterwards the voices in favour of these persons increased with the manifest
                    approbation of the multitude. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The assembly was
                    one of a heterogeneous character, consisting not only of the commons, but a
                    crowd of soldiers, with a large admixture even of deserters, who were desirous
                    of innovation in every thing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The praetors, at
                    first, concealed their feelings, and were for protracting the business; but at
                    length, overcome by the general opinion, <pb n="929" xml:id="p.929"/> and
                    apprehensive of a sedition, they declared them the prae- tors. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> These did not, however, immediately openly avow their
                    sentiments, though they were chagrined that ambassadors had been sent to Appius
                    Claudius to negotiate a ten days' truce, and that on obtaining this, others were
                    sent to treat for the renewal of the old alliance. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans, with a fleet of a hundred ships, were then
                    stationed at Murgantia, waiting the issue of the commotion raised at Syracuse by
                    the death of the tyrants, and to what their recent acquisition of liberty would
                    impel the people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, the Syracusan
                    ambassadors were sent by Appius Claudius to Marcellus on his coming into Sicily,
                    and Marcellus having heard the conditions of peace, and being of opinion that
                    matters might be brought to a settlement, himself also sent ambassadors to
                    Syracuse to treat with the praetors in person on the renewal of the alliance.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But now by no means the same state of
                    quiet and tranquillity existed there. Hippocrates and Epicydes, their fears
                    being removed, after that intelligence had arrived that a Carthaginian fleet had
                    put in at Pachynum, complained sometimes to the mercenary soldiers, at other
                    times to the deserters, that Syracuse was being betrayed to the Romans.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And when Appius began to station his ships
                    at the mouth of the port, in order to inspire the other party with courage,
                    their false insinuations appeared to receive great corroboration; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> and on the first impulse, the populace had even run
                    down in a disorderly manner to prevent them from disembarking. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While affairs were in this unsettled state, it
                    was resolved to call an assembly; in which, when some leaned to one side and
                    some to the other, and an insurrection being on the point of breaking out,
                    Apollonides, one of the nobles, delivered a speech fraught with salutary advice,
                    considering the critical state of affairs: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Never,</quote> he said, <quote> had a state a nearer prospect of safety
                        and annihilation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For if they would all
                        unanimously espouse the cause either of the Romans or the Carthaginians,
                        there could be no state whose condition would be more prosperous and happy;
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but if they pulled different ways, the
                        war between the Romans and Carthaginians would not be more bloody than that
                        which would take place between the Syracusans themselves, in which both the
                        contending parties would have their forces, their troops, and their
                        generals, within the same walls. Every exertion ought there- <pb n="930"
                            xml:id="p.930"/> fore to be made that all might think alike. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Which alliance would be productive of the greater
                        advantages, was a question of quite a secondary nature, and of less moment;
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> though the authority of Hiero ought to
                        be followed in preference to that of Hieronymus in the selection of allies,
                        and a friendship of which they had had a happy experience through a space of
                        fifty years, ought to be chosen rather than one now untried and formerly
                        unfaithful. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That it ought also to have
                        some weight in their deliberations, that peace with the Carthaginians might
                        be refused in such a manner as not immediately, at least, to have a war with
                        them, while with the Romans they must forthwith have either peace or war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The less of party spirit and warmth appeared
                    in this speech the greater weight it had. A military council also was united
                    with the praetors and a chosen body of senators; the commanders of companies
                    also, and the prefects of the allies, were ordered to consult conjointly.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After the question had been agitated with
                    great warmth, at length, as there appeared to be no means of carrying on a war
                    with the Romans, it was resolved that a treaty of peace should be formed, and
                    that ambassadors should be sent with those from Rome to ratify the same. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not many days intervened before ambassadors
                    came from the Leontines, requesting troops to protect their frontiers; an
                    embassy which appeared to afford a very favourable opportunity for
                    disencumbering the city of a turbulent and disorderly rabble, and for removing
                    their leaders to a distance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The praetor,
                    Hippocrates, was ordered to lead the deserters thither. Many of the mercenary
                    auxiliaries accompanying them made them number four thousand armed men.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This expedition gave great delight both to
                    those who were sent and those who sent them, for to the former an opportunity
                    was afforded of change which they had long desired, while the latter were
                    rejoiced because they considered that a kind of sink of the city had been
                    drained off. But they had, as it were, only relieved a sick body for a time,
                    that it might afterwards fall into a more aggravated disease. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> For Hippocrates began to ravage the adjoining parts of the
                    Roman province, at first by stealthy excursions, but afterwards, when Appius had
                    sent a body of troops to protect the lands of the allies, he made an attack with
                    all his forces upon the guard posted over against him, and slew many. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Marcellus, when informed of <pb n="931"
                        xml:id="p.931"/> this, immediately sent ambassadors to Syracuse, who said
                    that the faith of the treaty had been broken, and that there would never be
                    wanting a cause for hostilities, unless Hippocrates and Epicydes were removed
                    not only from Syracuse, but far from all Sicily. Epicydes, lest by being present
                    he should be arraigned for the offence committed by his absent brother, or
                    should be wanting on his own part in stirring up a war, proceeded himself also
                    to the Leontines; and seeing that they were already sufficiently exasperated
                    against the Romans, he endeavoured to detach them from the Syracusans also.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His argument was, that the terms on which
                    they had formed a treaty of peace with the Romans were, that whatever people had
                    been subject to their kings should be placed under their dominion; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and that now they were not satisfied with liberty
                    unless they could also exercise kingly power and dominion over others.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The answer, therefore, he said, which they
                    ought to send back was, that the Leontines also considered themselves entitled
                    to liberty, either on the ground that the tyrant fell in the streets of their
                    city, or that there the shout was first raised for liberty; and that they were
                    the persons who, abandoning the king's generals, flocked to Syracuse. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> That, therefore, either that article must be expunged
                    from the treaty, or that that term of it would not be admitted. They easily
                    persuaded the multitude; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and when the
                    ambassadors of Syracuse complained of the slaughter of the Roman guard, and
                    ordered that Hippocrates and Epicydes should depart either to Locri or any other
                    place they pleased, provided they quitted Sicily, a reply was made to them in a
                    haughty manner, <quote> that they had neither placed themselves at the disposal
                        of the Syracusans to make a <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> peace for
                        them with the Romans, nor were they bound by the treaties of other people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This answer the Syracusans laid before the
                    Romans, declaring at the same time that <quote> the Leontines were not under
                        their control, and that, therefore, the Romans might make war on them
                        without violating the treaty subsisting between them; that they would also
                        not be wanting in the war, provided that when brought again under
                        subjection, they should form a part of their dominion, agreeably to the
                        conditions of the peace. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus marched with his entire forces
                    against Leontini, having sent for Appius also, in order that he might <pb
                        n="932" xml:id="p.932"/> attack it in another quarter; when, such was the
                    ardour of the troops in consequence of the indignation they felt at the Roman
                    guard's being put to the sword during the negotiations for a peace, that they
                    took the town by storm on the first assault. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Hippocrates and Epicydes, perceiving that the enemy were getting possession of
                    the walls and breaking open the gates, retired with a few others into the
                    citadel, from which they fled unobserved during the night to Herbessus.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Syracusans, who had marched from home
                    with eight thousand troops, were met at the river Myla by a messenger, who
                    informed them that the city was taken. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    rest which he stated was a mixture of truth and falsehood; he said that there
                    had been an indiscriminate massacre of the soldiers and the townsmen, and that
                    he did not think that one person who had arrived at puberty had survived;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that the town had been pillaged, and the
                    property of the rich men given to the troops. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    On receiving such direful news the army halted; and while all were under violent
                    excitement, the generals, Sosis and Dinomenes, consulted together as to the
                    course to be taken. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The scourging and
                    beheading of two thousand deserters had given to this false statement a
                    plausibility which excited alarm; but no violence was offered to any of the
                    Leontine or other soldiers after the city was taken; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and every man's property was restored to him, with the
                    exception only of such as was destroyed in the first confusion which attended
                    the capture of the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The troops, who
                    complained of their fellow-soldiers having been betrayed and butchered, could
                    neither be induced to proceed to Leontini, nor wait where they were for more
                    certain intelligence. The praetors, perceiving their minds disposed to mutiny,
                    but concluding that their violence would not be of long continuance, if
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> those who had led them on to such folly
                    were removed, led the troops to Megara, whence they themselves with a few
                    horsemen proceeded to Herbessus, under the expectation of having the city
                    betrayed to them in the general consternation; <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> but being disappointed in this attempt, they resolved to resort to force, and
                    moved their camp from Megara on the following day, in order to attack Herbessus
                    with all their forces. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hippocrates and
                    Epicydes having formed the design of putting themselves into the hands of the
                    soldiers, who were for the most part accustomed to them, and were now incensed
                    at the report of the <pb n="933" xml:id="p.933"/> massacre of their comrades,
                    not so much as a safe measure on the first view of it as that it was their only
                    course, now that all hope was cut off, went out to meet the army. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> It happened that the troops which marched in the van
                    were six hundred Cretans, who had been engaged in the service of Hieronymus
                    under their command, and were under obligation to Hannibal, having been captured
                    at the Trasimenus among the Roman auxiliaries, and dismissed by him. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Hippocrates and Epicydes, recognising them by their
                    standards and the fashion of their armour, held out olive branches, and the
                    fillets usually worn by suppliants, and implored them to receive them into their
                    ranks, protect them when received, and not betray them to the Syracusans, by
                    whom they themselves would soon be delivered up to the Romans to be butchered. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the Cretans with one accord called out to
                    them to be of good courage; that they would share every fortune with them.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During this conversation, the vanguard had
                    halted, and the march was delayed; nor had the cause of the delay as yet reached
                    the generals. After the report had spread that Hippocrates and Epicydes were
                    there, and a voice was heard through the whole army, which showed evidently that
                    the troops were pleased at their arrival, the praetors immediately gallopped to
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the front, and earnestly asked <quote>
                        what was the meaning of that violation of discipline, which the Cretans had
                        committed in holding conference with the enemy, and allowing them to mingle
                        with their ranks without the authority of the praetors </quote> They ordered
                    Hippocrates to be seized and thrown into chains. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> On hearing which such a clamour was raised, first by the Cretans and then by
                    the rest, that it was quite evident if they proceeded farther that they would
                    have cause to fear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In this state of anxiety
                    and perplexity, they gave orders to march back to Megara, whence they had set
                    out, and sent messengers to Syracuse, to give information of their present
                    condition. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hippocrates added a deception,
                    seeing that the minds of the troops were disposed to entertain every suspicion.
                    Having sent some Cretans to lie in wait in the roads, he read a letter he
                    pretended had been intercepted, but which he had written himself. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The address was: <quote>The praetors of Syracuse to
                        the consul Marcellus.</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After the customary wishing of health, it
                    stated <quote> that he had acted duly and properly in sparing none of the
                        Leontines, but that the cause of all the <pb n="934" xml:id="p.934"/>
                        mercenary troops was the same, and that Syracuse would never be tranquil
                        while there were any foreign auxiliaries in the city or in the army.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That it was therefore necessary that
                        he should endeavour to get into his power those who were encamped at Megara,
                        with their praetors, and by punishing them, at length restore Syracuse to
                        liberty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After this letter had been read, they ran to
                    seize their arms in every direction, with so great a clamour, that the praetors,
                    in the utmost consternation, rode away to Syracuse during the confusion.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The mutiny, however, was not quelled even
                    by their flight, but an attack was made upon the Syracusan soldiers; nor would
                    any one have escaped their violence, had not Hippocrates and Epicydes opposed
                    the resentment of the multitude, not from pity or any humane motive, but lest
                    they should cut off all hope of effecting their return; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and that they might have the soldiers, both as faithful
                    supporters of their cause, and as hostages, and conciliate to themselves their
                    relatives and <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> friends, in the first place
                    by so great an obligation, and in the next by reason of the pledge. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Having also experienced that the populace could be
                    excited by any cause, however groundless or trifling, they procured a soldier of
                    the number of those who were besieged at Leontini, whom they suborned to carry a
                    report to Syracuse, corresponding with that which had been falsely told at the
                    Myla; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and by vouching for what he stated, and
                    relating as matters which he had seen, those things of which doubts were
                    entertained, to kindle the resentment of the people. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This man not only obtained credit with the
                    commons, but being introduced into the senate-house, produced an impression upon
                    the senate also. Some men of no small authority openly declared, that it was
                    very fortunate that the rapacity and cruelty of the Romans had been made
                    apparent in the case of the Leontines; that if they had entered Syracuse, they
                    would have committed the same or even more horrible acts, as there the
                    temptations to rapacity would have been greater. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> All, therefore, advised that the gates should be closed and the city guarded,
                    but not the same persons were objects of fear or hatred to all alike. Among the
                    soldiers of every kind, and a great part of the people, the Roman name was
                    hated. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The praetors, and a few of the nobles,
                    though enraged by the fictitious intelligence, rather directed their cautions
                    against a <pb n="935" xml:id="p.935"/> nearer and more immediate evil.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hippocrates and Epicydes were now at the
                    Hexapylum; and conversations were taking place, fomented by the relatives of the
                    native soldiers who were in the army, touching the opening of the gates, and the
                    allowing their common country to be defended from the violence of the Romans.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> One of the doors of the Hexapylum was now
                    thrown open, and the troops began to be taken in at it, when the praetors
                    interposed; and first by commands and menaces, then by advice, they endeavoured
                    to deter them from their purpose, and last of all, every other means proving
                    ineffectual, forgetful of their dignity, they tried to move them by prayers,
                    imploring them not to betray their country to men heretofore the satellites of
                    the tyrant, and now the corrupters of the army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> But the ears of the excited multitude were deaf to all these arguments, and
                    the exertions made from within to break open the gates, were not less than those
                    without; the gates were all broken open, and the whole army received into the
                    Hexapylum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The praetors, with the youth of the
                    city, fled into the Achradina; the mercenary soldiers and deserters, with all
                    the soldiers of the late king who were at Syracuse, joined the forces of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Achradina also was therefore taken
                    on the first assault, and all the praetors, except such as escaped in the
                    confusion, were put to the sword. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Night put an
                    end to the carnage. On the following day the slaves were invited to liberty, and
                    those bound in prison were released; after which this mixed rabble created
                    Hippocrates and Epicydes their praetors, and thus Syracuse, when for a brief
                    period the light of liberty had shone on it, relapsed into her former state of
                    servitude. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans, on receiving information of these
                    events, immediately moved their camp from Leontini to Syracuse. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It happened at this time that ambassadors were sent by
                    Appius in a quinquereme, to make their way through the harbour. A quadrireme was
                    sent in advance, which was captured as soon as it entered the mouth of the
                    harbour, and the ambassadors with difficulty made their escape. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> And now not only the laws of peace but of war also were not
                    regarded, when the Roman army pitched their camp at Olympium, a temple of
                    Jupiter, a mile and a half from the city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From
                    which place also it was thought proper that ambassadors should be sent forward;
                    these were met by Hippocrates and <pb n="936" xml:id="p.936"/> Epicydes with
                    their friends without the gate, to prevent their entering the city. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman, who was appointed to speak, said that
                        <quote> he did not bring war, but aid and assistance to the Syracusans, not
                        only to such as, escaping from the midst of the carnage, fled to the Romans
                        for protection, but to those also, who, overpowered by fear, were submitting
                        to a servitude more shocking, not only than exile, but than death. Nor would
                        the Romans suffer the horrid murder of their friends to go unavenged.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If, therefore, those who had taken
                        refuge with them were allowed to return to their country with safety, the
                        authors of the massacre delivered up, and the Syracusans reinstated in the
                        enjoyment of their liberty and laws, there would be no necessity for arms;
                        but if these things were not done, they would direct their arms unceasingly
                        against those who delayed them, whoever they might be. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Epicydes replied, that <quote> if they had
                        been commissioned with any message for them, they would have given them an
                        answer; and when the government of Syracuse was in the hands of those
                        persons to whom they were come, they might visit Syracuse again. If they
                        should commence hostilities, they would learn by actual experience that it
                        was by no means the same thing to besiege Syracuse and Leontini. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With this he left the ambassadors and closed
                    the gate. The siege of Syracuse then commenced by sea and land at the same time;
                    by land on the side of the Hexapylum; by sea on the side of the Achradina, the
                    wall of which is washed by its waves; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and as
                    the Romans felt a confidence that as they had taken Leontini by the terror they
                    occasioned on the first assault, they should be able in some quarter to effect
                    an entrance into a city so desert, and diffused over so large an extent of
                    ground, they brought up to the walls every kind of engine for besieging cities. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And an attempt made with so much energy would
                    have succeeded, had it not been for one person then at Syracuse. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> That person was Archimedes, a man of unrivalled skill
                    in observing the heavens and the stars, but more deserving of admiration as the
                    inventor and constructor of warlike engines and works, by means of which, with a
                    very slight effort, he turned to ridicule what the enemy effected with great
                    difficulty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The wall which ran along unequal
                    eminences, most of which were high and difficult of access, some low and open to
                    approach along level vales, he furnished with every kind of <pb n="937"
                        xml:id="p.937"/> warlike engine, as seemed suitable to each particular
                    place. Marcellus attacked from the quinqueremes the wall of the Achradina,
                    which, as before stated, was washed by the sea. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> From the other ships the archers and slingers and light infantry, whose
                    weapon is difficult to be thrown back by the unskilful, allowed scarce any
                    person to remain upon the wall unwounded. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    These, as they required room for the discharge of their missiles, kept their
                    ships at a distance from the wall. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Eight more
                    quinqueremes joined together in pairs, the oars on their inner sides being
                    removed, so that side might be placed to side, and which forming as it were
                    ships, were worked by means of the oars on the outer sides, carried <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> turrets built up in stories, and other engines
                    employed in battering walls. Against this naval armament, Archimedes placed on
                    different parts of the walls engines of various dimensions. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Against the ships which were at a distance he discharged
                    stones of immense weight. Those which were nearer he assailed with lighter, and
                    therefore more numerous missiles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lastly, in
                    order that his own men might heap their weapons upon the enemy, without
                    receiving any wounds themselves, he perforated the wall from the top to the
                    bottom with a great number of loop-holes, about a cubit in diameter, through
                    which some with arrows, others with scorpions of moderate size, assailed the
                    enemy without being seen. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Certain ships which
                    came nearer to the walls in order to get within the range of the engines, he
                    placed upon their sterns, raising up their prows by throwing upon them an iron
                    grapple, attached to a strong chain, by means of a tolleno which projected from
                    the wall, and overhung them, having a heavy counterpoise of lead which forced
                    back the lever to the ground; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> then the
                    grapple being suddenly disengaged, the ship falling as it were from the wall,
                    was, by these means, to the utter consternation of the mariners, dashed in such
                    a manner against the water, that even if it fell back in an erect position it
                    took in a great quantity of water. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thus the
                    attack by sea was foiled, and their whole efforts were directed to an attack by
                    land with all their forces. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But on this side
                    also the place was furnished with a similar array of engines of every kind,
                    procured at the expense of Hiero, who had given his attention to this object
                    through a course of many years, and constructed by the unrivalled abilities of
                    Archimedes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The nature of the place also
                    assisted <pb n="938" xml:id="p.938"/> them; for the rock which formed the
                    foundation of the wall was for the most part so steep, that not only materials
                    discharged from engines, but such as were rolled down by their own gravity, fell
                    upon the enemy with great force; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> the same
                    cause rendered the approach to the city difficult, and the footing unsteady.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Wherefore, a council being held, it was
                    resolved, since every attempt was frustrated, to abstain from assaulting the
                    place, and keeping up a blockade, only to cut off the provisions of the enemy by
                    sea and land. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, Marcellus, who had set out with
                    about a third part of the army, to recover the towns which, during the
                    commotion, had gone over to the Carthaginians, regained Helorus and Herbessus by
                    voluntary surrender. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Megara, which he took by
                    storm, he demolished and plundered, in order to terrify the rest, but
                    particularly the Syracusans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Much about the
                    same time, Himilco, who had kept his fleet for a long time at the promontory of
                    Pachynus, landed twenty-five thousand infantry, three thousand horse, and twelve
                    elephants, at Heraclea, which they call Minoa. This force was much greater than
                    that which he had before on board his fleet at Pachynus. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But after Syracuse was seized by Hippocrates, he proceeded
                    to Carthage, where, being aided by ambassadors from Hippocrates, and a letter
                    from Hannibal, who said that now was the time to recover Sicily with the highest
                    honour, while his own advice given in person had no small influence, he had
                    prevailed upon the Carthaginians to transport into Sicily as large a force as
                    possible, both of foot and horse. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Immediately
                    on his arrival he retook Heraclea, and within a few days after Agrigentum;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and in the other states which sided with
                    the Carthaginians, such confident hopes were kindled of driving the Romans out
                    of Sicily, that at last even those who were besieged at Syracuse took courage;
                    and thinking that half their forces would be sufficient for the defence of the
                    city, they divided the business <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of the war
                    between them in such a manner, that Epicydes superintended the defence of the
                    city, while Hippocrates, in conjunction with Himilco, prosecuted the war against
                    the Roman consul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The latter, having passed by
                    night through the intervals between the posts, with ten thousand foot and five
                    hundred horse, was pitching a camp near the city Acrillae, when Marcellus came
                    upon them, while engaged in raising <pb n="939" xml:id="p.939"/> the
                    fortifications, on his return <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> from
                    Agrigentum, which was already occupied by the enemy, having failed in his
                    attempt to get there before the enemy by expeditious marching. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Marcellus calculated upon any thing rather than meeting
                    with a Syracusan army at that time and place; but still through fear of Himilco
                    and the Carthaginians, for whom he was by no means a match with the forces he
                    had with him, he was marching with all possible circumspection, and with his
                    troops so arranged, as to be prepared for any thing which might occur. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that the caution he had observed
                    with intent to guard him against the Carthaginians, proved useful against the
                    Sicilians. Having caught them in disorder and dispersed, employed in forming
                    their camp, and for the most part unarmed, he cut off all their infantry. Their
                    cavalry, having commenced a slight engagement, fled to Acrae with Hippocrates.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This battle having checked the Sicilians
                    in their purpose of revolting from the Romans, Marcellus returned to Syracuse,
                    and a few days after Himilco, being joined by Hippocrates, encamped on the river
                    Anapus, about eight miles distant from that place. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Nearly about the same time, fifty-five ships of war of the
                    Carthaginians, with Bomilcar as commander of the fleet, put into the great
                    harbour of Syracuse from the sea, and a Roman fleet of thirty quinqueremes
                    landed the first legion at Panormus; and so intent were both the contending
                    powers upon Sicily, that the seat of war might seem to have been removed from
                    Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Himilco, who thought that the Roman
                    legion which had been landed at Panormus, would doubtless fall a prey to him on
                    its way to Syracuse, was mistaken in his road; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    for the Carthaginian marched through the inland parts of the country, while the
                    legion, keeping along the coast, and attended by the <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> fleet, came up with Appius Claudius, who had advanced to
                    Pachynum with a part of his forces to meet it. Nor did the Carthaginians delay
                    longer at Syracuse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Bomilcar, who at the same
                    time that he did not feel sufficient confidence in his naval strength, as the
                    Romans had a fleet more than double his number, was aware that delay which could
                    be attended with no good effect, would only increase the scarcity of provisions
                    among the allies by the presence of his troops, sailed out into the deep, and
                    crossed over into Africa. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Himilco, who had in
                    vain followed <pb n="940" xml:id="p.940"/> Marcellus to Syracuse, to see if he
                    could get any opportunity of engaging him before he was joined by larger forces,
                    failing in this object, and seeing that the enemy were secured at Syracuse, both
                    by their fortifications and the strength of their forces, to avoid wasting time
                    in sitting by as an idle spectator of the siege of <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> his allies, without being able to do any good, marched his
                    troops away, in order to bring them up wherever the prospect of revolt from the
                    Romans might invite him, and wherever by his presence he might inspire
                    additional courage in those who espoused his interest. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He first got possession of Murgantia, the Roman garrison
                    having been betrayed by the inhabitants themselves. Here a great quantity of
                    corn and provisions of every kind had been laid up by the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this revolt the minds of other states also
                    were stimulated; and the Roman garrisons were now either driven out of the
                    citadels, or treacherously given up and overpowered. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Enna, which stood on an eminence lofty and of difficult
                    ascent on all sides, was impregnable on account of its situation, and had
                    besides in its citadel a strong garrison commanded by one who was very unlikely
                    to be overreached by treachery, Lucius Pinarius, a man of vigorous mind, who
                    relied more on the measures he took to prevent treachery, than on the fidelity
                    of the Sicilians; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and at that time
                    particularly the intelligence he had received of so many cities being betrayed,
                    and revolting, and of the massacre of the garrisons, had made him solicitous to
                    use every precaution. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly, by day and
                    night equally, every thing was kept in readiness, and every place furnished with
                    guards and watches, the soldiery being continually under arms and at their
                    posts. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But when the principal men in Enna, who
                    had already entered into a covenant with Himilco to betray the garrison, found
                    that they could get no opportunity of circumventing the Roman, they resolved to
                    act openly. They urged, that <quote> the city and the citadel ought to be under
                        their control, as they had formed an alliance <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> with the Romans on the understanding that they were to
                        be free, and had not been delivered into their custody as slaves. That they
                        therefore thought it just that the keys of the gates should be restored to
                        them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That their honour formed the
                        strongest tie upon good allies, and that the people and senate of Rome would
                        entertain feelings of gratitude towards them if they continued in friendship
                        with them of their own free will, and <pb n="941" xml:id="p.941"/> not by
                        compulsion. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Roman replied, that <quote> he was placed
                        there by his general to protect the place; that from him he had received the
                        keys of the gates and the custody of the citadel, trusts which he held not
                        subject to his own will, nor that of the inhabitants of Enna, but to his who
                        committed them to him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That among the
                        Romans, for a man to quit his post was a capital offence, and that parents
                        had sanctioned that law by the death even of their own children. That the
                        consul Marcellus was not far off; that they might send ambassadors to him,
                        who possessed the right and liberty of deciding. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But they said, they would certainly not send
                    to him, and solemnly declared, that as they could not obtain their object by
                    argument, they would seek some means of asserting their liberty. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Pinarius upon this observed, <quote> that if they
                        thought it too much to send to the consul, still they would, at least, grant
                        him an assembly of the people, that it might be ascertained whether these
                        denunciations came from a few, or from the whole state. </quote> An assembly
                    of the people was proclaimed for the next day, with the general consent. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this conference, he returned into the
                    citadel, and assembling his soldiers, thus addressed them: <quote> Soldiers, I
                        suppose you have heard in what manner the Roman garrisons have been betrayed
                        and cut off by the Sicilians of late. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> You
                        have escaped the same treachery, first by the kindness of the gods, and
                        secondly by your own good conduct, in unremittingly standing and watching
                        under arms. I wish the rest of our time may be passed without suffering or
                        committing dreadful things. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This caution,
                        which we have hitherto employed, has been directed against covert treachery,
                        but not succeeding in this as they wished, they now publicly and openly
                        demand back the keys of the gates; but as soon as we shall have delivered
                        them up, Enna will be instantly in the hands of the Carthaginians, and we
                        shall be butchered under circumstances more horrid than those with which the
                        garrison of Murgantia were massacred. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I
                        have with difficulty procured a delay of one night for deliberation, that I
                        might employ it in acquainting you with the danger which threatens you.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At daybreak they intend holding a
                        general assembly for the purpose of criminating me, and stirring up the
                        people against you; to-morrow, therefore, Enna will be inundated either with
                        your blood, or that of its own inhabit- <pb n="942" xml:id="p.942"/> ants.
                        If they are beforehand with you, you will have no hope left; but if you
                        anticipate their proceedings, you will have no danger. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Victory will belong to that side which shall have drawn
                        the sword first. You shall all, therefore, full armed, attentively wait the
                        signal. I shall be in the assembly, and by talking and disputing will spin
                        out the time till every thing shall be ready. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> When I shall have given the signal with my gown, then,
                        mind me! raising a shout on all sides, rush upon the multitude, and fell all
                        before you with the sword, taking care that no one survive from whom either
                        force or fraud can be apprehended. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> You,
                        mother Ceres and Proserpine, I entreat, and all ye other gods, celestial and
                        infernal, who frequent this city and these consecrated lakes and groves,
                        that you would lend us your friendly and propitious aid, as we adopt this
                        measure not for the purpose of inflicting, but averting injury. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> I should exhort you at greater length, my
                        soldiers, if you were about to fight with armed men; men unarmed and off
                        their guard, you will slay to satiety. The consul's camp too is near, so
                        that nothing can be apprehended from Himilco and the Carthaginians. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Being allowed to retire immediately after this
                    exhortation, they employed themselves in taking refreshment. The next day they
                    stationed themselves some in one place and others in another, to block up the
                    streets, and shut up the ways by which the townsmen might escape, the greater
                    part of them stationing themselves upon and round the theatre, as they had been
                    accustomed before also to be spectators of the assemblies. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When the Roman prefect, having been brought into the
                    presence of the people by the magistrates, said, that the power and authority of
                    deciding the question appertained to the consul, and not to him, repeating for
                    the most part what he had urged the day before; <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> first of all a small number, and then more, desired him to give up the keys,
                    but afterwards all with one consent demanded it; and when he hesitated and
                    delayed, threatened him furiously, and seemed as though they would not further
                    delay violent extremities; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> then the prefect
                    gave the signal agreed upon with his gown, and the soldiers, who had been long
                    anxiously waiting the signal, and in readiness, raising a shout, ran down, some
                    of them from the higher ground, upon the rear of the assembly, while others
                    blocked up the passages leading out of the <pb n="943" xml:id="p.943"/> crowded
                    theatre. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The people of Enna thus shut up in
                    the pit were put to the sword, being heaped one upon another not only in
                    consequence of the slaughter, but also from their own efforts to escape; for
                    some scrambling over the heads of others, and those that were unhurt falling
                    upon the wounded, and the living upon the dead, they were accumulated together.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thence they ran in every direction
                    throughout the city, when nothing was any where to be seen but flight and
                    bloodshed, as though the city had been captured; for the rage of the soldiery
                    was not less excited in putting to the sword an unarmed rabble, than it would
                    have been had the heat of battle and an equality of danger stimulated it.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thus possession of Enna was retained, by
                    an act which was either atrocious or unavoidable. Marcellus did not disapprove
                    of the deed, and gave up the plunder of the place to the soldiery; concluding
                    that the Sicilians, deterred by this example, would refrain from betraying their
                    garrisons. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As this city was situated in the
                    heart of Sicily, and was distinguished both on account of the remarkable
                    strength of its natural situation, and because every part of it was rendered
                    sacred by the traces it contained of the rape of Proserpine of old, the news of
                    its disaster spread through the whole of Sicily in nearly one day; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> and as people considered that by this horrid massacre
                    violence had been done not only to the habitations of men, but even of the gods,
                    then indeed those who even before this event were in doubt which side they
                    should take, revolted to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Hippocrates and Himilco, who had in vain brought up their troops to Enna at the
                    invitation of the traitors, retired thence, the former to Murgantia, the latter
                    to Agrigentum. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Marcellus retrograded into the
                    territory of Leontium, and after collecting a quantity of corn and other
                    provisions in his camp there, left a small body of troops to protect it, and
                    then went to carry on the siege of Syracuse. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Appius Claudius having been allowed to go from thence to Rome to put up for the
                    consulship, he appointed Titus Quintus Crispinus to command the fleet and the
                    old camp in his room. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He himself fortified
                    his camp, and built huts for his troops at a distance of five miles from
                    Hexapylum, at a place called Leon. These were the transactions in Sicily up to
                    the beginning of the winter. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same summer the war with king Philip, as
                    had been before suspected, broke out. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Ambassadors from Oricum <pb n="944" xml:id="p.944"/> came to Marcus Valerius,
                    the praetor, who was directing his fleet around Brundusium and the neighbouring
                    coasts of Calabria, with intelligence, that Philip had first made an attempt
                    upon Apollonia, having approached it by sailing up the river with a hundred and
                    twenty barks with two banks of oars; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> after
                    that, not succeeding so speedily as he had hoped, that he had brought up his
                    army secretly to Oricum by night; which city, as it was situated on a plain, and
                    was not secured either by fortifications or by men and arms, was overpowered at
                    the first assault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the same time that they
                    delivered this intelligence, they entreated him to bring them succour, and repel
                    that decided enemy of the Romans by land or by a naval force, since they were
                    attacked for no other cause than that they lay over against Italy. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius, leaving Publius Valerius
                    lieutenant-general charged with the protection of that quarter, set sail with
                    his fleet equipped and prepared, having put on board of ships of burthen such
                    soldiers as there was not room for in the men of war, and reached Oricum on the
                    second day; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and as that city was occupied by a
                    slight garrison, which Philip had left on his departure thence, he retook it
                    without much opposition. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here ambassadors came
                    to him from Apollonia, stating that they were subjected to a siege because they
                    were unwilling to revolt from the Romans, and that they would not be able any
                    longer to resist the power of the Macedonians, unless a Roman force were sent
                    for their protection. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Having undertaken to
                    perform what they wished, he sent two thousand chosen armed men in ships of war
                    to the mouth of the river, under the command of Quintus Naevius Crista, prefect
                    of the allies, a man of enterprise, and experienced in military affairs.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having landed his troops, and sent back
                    the ships to join the rest of the fleet at Oricum, whence he had come, he
                    marched his troops at a distance from the river, by a way not guarded at all by
                    the king's party, and entered the city by night, so that none of the enemy
                    perceived him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> During the following day they
                    remained quiet, to afford time for the praefect to inspect the youth of
                    Apollonia, together with the arms and resources of the city. Having derived
                    considerable confidence from a review and inspection of these, and at the same
                    time discovering from scouts the supineness and negligence which prevailed among
                    the enemy, he marched out of the city during the dead <pb n="945" xml:id="p.945"
                    /> of night without <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> any noise, and entered
                    the camp of the enemy, which was in such a neglected and exposed state, that it
                    was quite clear that a thousand men had passed the rampart before any one
                    perceived them, and that had they abstained from putting them to the sword, they
                    might have penetrated to the royal pavilion. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The killing of those who were nearest the gate aroused the enemy; and in
                    consequence, they were all seized with such alarm and dismay, that not only none
                    of the rest attempted to take arms or endeavour to expel the enemy from the
                    camp, but even the <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> king himself, betaking
                    himself to flight, in a manner half naked and just as he was when roused from
                    his sleep, hurried away to the river and his ships in a garb scarcely decent for
                    a private soldier, much less for a king. Thither also the rest of the multitude
                    fled with the utmost precipitation. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Little
                    less than three thousand men were slain or made prisoners in the camp;
                    considerably more, however, were captured than slain. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> The camp having been plundered, the Apollonians removed
                    into their city the catapults, ballistas, and other engines which had been got
                    together for the purpose of assaulting their city, for the protection of their
                    walls, in case at any time a similar conjuncture should arise; all the rest of
                    the plunder which the camp afforded was given up to the Romans. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> Intelligence of these events having been carried to
                    Oricum, Marcus Valerius immediately brought his fleet to the mouth of the river,
                    that the king might not attempt to make his escape by ship. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> Thus Philip, having lost all hope of being able to cope
                    with his enemies by land or sea, and having either hauled on shore or burnt his
                    ships, made for Macedonia by land, his troops being for the most part unarmed
                    and despoiled of their baggage. The Roman fleet, with Marcus Valerius, wintered
                    at Oricum. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same year the war was prosecuted in Spain
                    with various success; for before the Romans crossed the Iberus, Mago and
                    Hasdrubal had routed an immense army of Spaniards; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and the farther Spain would have revolted from the Romans,
                    had not Publius Cornelius, hastily crossing the Iberus with his army, given a
                    seasonable stimulus to the wavering resolutions of his allies by his arrival
                    among them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans first encamped at a
                    place called the High Camp, which is remarkable for the death of the great
                    Hamilcar. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It <pb n="946" xml:id="p.946"/> was
                    a fortress strongly defended by works, and thither they had previously conveyed
                    corn; but as the whole circumjacent country was full of enemy's troops, and the
                    Roman army on its march had been charged by the cavalry of the enemy without
                    being able to take revenge upon them, two thousand men, who either loitered
                    behind or had strayed through the fields, having been slain, the Romans quitted
                    this place to get nearer to a friendly country, and fortified a camp at the
                    mount of Victory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To this place came Cneius
                    Scipio with all his forces, and Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo, and a third
                    Carthaginian general, with a complete army, all of whom took up a position
                    opposite the Roman camp and on the other side the river. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Scipio, going out with some light troops to take a
                    view of the surrounding country, was observed by the enemy; and he would have
                    been overpowered in the open plain, had he not seized an eminence near him.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here too he was closely invested, but was
                    rescued from the troops which environed him by the arrival of his brother.
                    Castulo, a city of Spain, so strong and celebrated, and so closely connected
                    with the Carthaginians, that Hannibal had taken a wife from it, revolted to the
                    Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians commenced the siege
                    of Illiturgi, because there was a Roman garrison in it; and it seemed that they
                    would carry the place, chiefly in consequence of a lack of provisions.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Cneius Scipio, setting out with a legion
                    lightly equipped, in order to bring succour to his allies and the garrison,
                    entered the city, passing between the two camps of the enemy, and slaying a
                    great number of them. The next day also he sallied out and fought with equal
                    success. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Above twelve thousand were slain in
                    the two battles, more than a thousand made prisoners, and thirty-six military
                    standards captured. In consequence of this they retired from Illiturgi.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After this the siege of Bigerra, a city
                    which was also in alliance with the Romans, was commenced by the Carthaginians;
                    but Scipio coming up, raised the siege without experiencing any opposition. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians then removed their camp to
                    Munda, whither the Romans speedily followed them. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Here a pitched battle was fought, which lasted almost four
                    hours; and while the Romans were carrying all before them in the most glorious
                    manner, the signal for retreat was sounded, because the thigh of Cneius Scipio
                    had been transfixed with a javelin. <pb n="947" xml:id="p.947"/> The soldiers
                    round about him were thrown into a state of great alarm, lest the wound should
                    be mortal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, there was no doubt but
                    that if they had not been prevented by the intervention of this accident, they
                    might have taken the Carthaginian camp that day. By this time, not only the men,
                    but the elephants, were driven quite up to the rampart; and even upon the top of
                    it nine and thirty elephants were pierced with spears. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In this battle, too, as many as twelve thousand are said to
                    have been slain, nearly three thousand captured, with fifty-seven military
                    standards. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians retired thence to
                    the city Auringis, whither the Romans followed them, in order to take advantage
                    of their terror. Here Scipio again fought them, having been carried into the
                    field in a small litter; the victory was decisive; but not half so many of the
                    enemy were slain as before, because fewer survived to fight. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But this family, which possessed a natural talent at
                    renewing war and restoring its effects, in a short time recruited their army,
                    Mago having been sent by his brother to press soldiers, and assumed courage to
                    try the issue of a fresh struggle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though the
                    soldiers were for the most part different, yet as they fought in a cause which
                    had so often been unsuccessful within the space of a few days, they carried into
                    the field the same state of mind as those which had been engaged before, and the
                    issue of the battle was similar. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> More than
                    eight thousand were slain, not much less than a thousand captured, with
                    fifty-eight military standards. The greater part of the spoils had belonged to
                    the Gauls, consisting of golden chains and bracelets in great numbers. Also two
                    distinguished Gallic petty princes, whose names were Mnicaptus and Civismarus,
                    fell in this battle. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Eight elephants were
                    captured and three slain. When affairs went on so prosperously in Spain, the
                    Romans began to feel ashamed that Saguntum, on account of which the war had
                    originated, should continue for now the eighth year in the power of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly, having expelled by force the
                    Carthaginian garrison, they retook that town, and restored it to such of the
                    ancient inhabitants as had survived the fury of the war. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The Turditanians also, who had been the cause of the war
                    between that people and the Carthaginians, they reduced under their power, sold
                    them as slaves, and razed their city. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the achievements in Spain during the
                    con- <pb n="948" xml:id="p.948"/> sulate of Quintus Fabius and Marcus Claudius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At Rome, as soon as the new plebeian
                    tribunes entered upon their office, Lucius Metellus, a plebeian tribune,
                    immediately appointed a day for impleading the censors, Publius Furius and
                    Marcus Atilius, before the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the
                    preceding year, when he was quaestor, they had deprived him of his horse,
                    removed him from his tribe, and disfranchised him, on account of the conspiracy
                    entered into at Cannae to abandon Italy. But being aided by the other nine
                    tribunes, they were forbidden to answer while in office, and were discharged.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The death of Publius Furius prevented
                    their completing the lustrum. Marcus Atilius abdicated his office. An assembly
                    for the election of consuls was held by Quintus Fabius Maximus. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls elected were Quintus Fabius Maximus, son of the
                    consul, and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus a second time, both being absent.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The praetors appointed were Marcus
                    Atilius, and the two curule aediles, Publius Sempronius Tuditanus and Cneius
                    Fulvius Centumalus, together with Marcus Aemilius Lepidus. It is recorded, that
                    the scenic games were this year, for the first time, celebrated for four days by
                    the curule aediles. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The aedile Tuditanus was
                    the man who made his way through the midst of the enemy at Cannae when all the
                    rest were paralysed with fear, in consequence of that dreadful calamity.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as the elections were completed,
                    the consuls elect having been summoned to Rome, at the instance of Quintus
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> Fabius, the consul, entered upon their
                    office, and took the sense of the senate respecting the war, their own provinces
                    as well as those of the praetors, and also respecting the armies to be employed,
                    and which each of them was to command. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The provinces and armies were thus
                    distributed: the prosecution of the war with Hannibal was given to the consuls,
                    and of the armies, one which Sempronius himself had commanded, and another which
                    the consul Fabius had commanded, each consisting of two legions. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius, the praetor, who had the foreign
                    jurisdiction, was to have Luceria as his province, with the two legions which
                    Quintus Fabius, then consul, had commanded as praetor, his colleague, Marcus
                    Atilius, the city praetor, undertaking the duties of his office. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The province of Ariminum fell to the lot of Publius
                    Sempronius, that of Suessula to Cneius Fulvius, with two legions each likewise;
                    Fulvius taking with him the city legions; <pb n="949" xml:id="p.949"/> Tuditanus
                    receiving his from Manius Pomponius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    following generals were continued in command, and their provinces assigned to
                    them thus: to Marcus Claudius, so much of Sicily as lay within the limits of the
                    kingdom of Hiero; to Lentulus, the proprietor, the old province in that island;
                    to Titus Otacilius, the fleet; no additional troops were assigned to them.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius had Greece and Macedonia,
                    with the legion and the fleet which he had there; Quintus Mucius had Sardinia,
                    with his old army, consisting of two legions; Caius Terentius, Picenum, with one
                    legion which he then commanded. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Besides,
                    orders were given to enlist two legions for the city, and twenty thousand men
                    from the allies. With these leaders and these forces did they fortify the Roman
                    empire against the many wars which had either actually broken out, or were
                    suspected at one and the same time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After
                    enlisting the city legions and raising troops to make up the numbers of the
                    others, the consuls, before they quitted the city, expiated the prodigies which
                    were reported. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A wall and a gate had been
                    struck by lightning; and at Aricia even the temple of Jupiter had been struck by
                    lightning. Other illusions of the eyes and ears were credited as realities. An
                    appearance as of ships had been seen in the river at Tarracina, when there were
                    none there. A clashing of arms was heard in the temple of Jupiter Vicilinus, in
                    the territory of Compsa; and a river at Amiternum had flowed bloody. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> These prodigies having been expiated according to a
                    decree of the pontiffs, the consuls set out, Sempronius for Lucania, Fabius for
                    Apulia. The father of the latter came into the camp at Suessula, as his
                    lieutenant-general; and when the son advanced to meet him, the lictors, out of
                    respect for his dignity, went on in silence. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The old man rode past eleven of the fasces, when the consul ordered the lictor
                    nearest to him to take care, and he called to him to dismount; then at length
                    dismounting, he exclaimed, <quote>I wished to try, my son, whether you were duly
                        sensible that you are a consul.</quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this camp came Dasius Altinius of Arpi
                    privately and by night, attended by three slaves, with a promise that if he
                    should receive a reward for it, he would engage to betray Arpi to them.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fabius having laid the matter before a
                    council, some were of opinion that <quote> he ought to be scourged and put to
                        death as a deserter, as a man of unstable mind, and a <pb n="950"
                            xml:id="p.950"/> common enemy to both sides; who, after the defeat at
                        Cannae, had gone over to Hannibal and drawn Arpi into revolt, as if it were
                        right that a man's fidelity should vary according to the fluctuations of
                        fortune; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and who now, when the Roman
                        cause, contrary to his hopes and wishes, was as it were rising up again,
                        would seem to aggravate his baseness by recompensing those whom he had
                        formerly betrayed, by fresh betrayal. That a man whose custom it was to
                        espouse one side, while his heart was on another, was unworthy of confidence
                        as an ally, and contemptible as an enemy; that he ought to be made a third
                        example to deserters, in addition to the betrayers of Falerii and Pyrrhus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the other hand, Fabius, the father of the
                    consul, observed, that, <quote> forgetful of circumstances, men were apt to
                        exercise a free judgment on every question in the heat of war, as in time of
                        peace; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for though in the present instance
                        that which ought rather to form the object of their endeavours and to occupy
                        their thoughts, is by what means it may be brought about that none of the
                        allies may revolt from the Roman people, yet that they never think of; but,
                        on the contrary, they urge that an example ought to be made of any who might
                        repent and look back upon their former alliance. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> But if it is allowable to forsake the Romans, and not
                        allowable to return to them, who can doubt but that in a short time the
                        Romans, deserted by their allies, will see every state in Italy united in
                        leagues with the Carthaginians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Not,
                        however, that he was of opinion that any confidence was to be reposed in
                        Altinius, but he would invent some middle course of proceeding. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Treating him neither as an enemy nor as a friend
                        for the present, his wish was, that he should be kept during the war in some
                        city whose fidelity could be relied on, at a short distance from the camp,
                        in a state of easy restraint; and that when the war was concluded, they
                        should then deliberate whether he more deserved to be punished for his
                        former defection, or pardoned for his present return. </quote> The opinion
                    of Fabius was approved of. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Altinius was bound
                    in chains and given into custody, together with his companions, and a large
                    quantity of gold which he brought with him was ordered to be kept for him.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was kept at Cales, where, during the
                    day, he was unconfined, but attended by guards who locked him up at night. He
                    was first missed and inquired for at his house at Arpi, but afterwards, when the
                        <pb n="951" xml:id="p.951"/> report of his <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> absence had spread through the city, a violent sensation
                    was excited, as if they had lost their leader, and, from the apprehension of
                    some attempt to alter the present state of things, messengers were immediately
                    despatched to Hannibal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> With this the
                    Carthaginian was far from being displeased, both because he had long regarded
                    the man himself with suspicion, as one of doubtful fidelity, and because he had
                    now been lucky enough to get a pretext for possessing himself of the property of
                    so wealthy a person. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But that the world might
                    suppose that he had yielded to resentment more than to avarice, he added cruelty
                    to rapacity; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> for he summoned his wife and
                    children to the camp, and after having made inquiry, first, respecting the
                    flight of Altinius, and then, touching the quantity of gold and silver which was
                    left at his house, and informed himself on all these points, he burned them
                    alive. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius, setting out from Suessula, first set
                    about the siege of Arpi; and having pitched his camp about half a mile from it,
                    he took a near view of the site and walls of the city, and resolved to attack
                    it, in preference, in that quarter where it was most secured by works, and where
                    the least care was taken in guarding it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After
                    getting all things together which could be of use in besieging a city, he
                    selected the most efficient of the centurions out of the whole army, placing
                    them under the command of tribunes of approved valour, and giving them six
                    hundred soldiers, a number which was thought sufficient for the purpose. These
                    he ordered to bring the scaling ladders to the place which he had marked out, as
                    soon as the signal of the fourth watch had sounded. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In this part there was a low and narrow gate, opening into
                    a street which was little frequented, and which led through a deserted part of
                    the city. He ordered them, after scaling the wall, to proceed to this gate, and
                    break down the bars on the inside by force; and when they were in possession of
                    that part of the city, to give a signal with a cornet, that the rest of the
                    troops might be brought up, observing, that he would have every thing prepared
                    and ready. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These orders were executed
                    promptly; and that which seemed likely to impede their operations, served more
                    than any thing to conceal them. A shower of rain, which came on suddenly at
                    midnight, compelled the guards and watches to slip away from their posts, <pb
                        n="952" xml:id="p.952"/> and take shelter in the houses; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and the noise of the shower, which was somewhat copious, at
                    first prevented their hearing that which was made by the men in breaking open
                    the gate. Afterwards, when it fell upon the ear more gently and uniformly, it
                    lulled a great number of the men to sleep. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    After they had secured possession of the gate, they placed cornet-players in the
                    street at equal distances, and desired them to sound, in order to call the
                    consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This being done according to the plan
                    previously agreed upon, the consul ordered the troops to march, and a little
                    before daylight entered the city through the broken gate. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then at length the enemy were roused, the
                    shower was now subsiding, and daylight coming on. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal had a garrison of about five thousand armed men in
                    the city, and the inhabitants themselves had three thousand men in arms; these
                    the Carthaginians placed in front against the enemy, to guard against any
                    treachery on their rear. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The fight was carried
                    on at first in the dark, and in the narrow streets, the Romans having seized not
                    only the streets, but the houses also nearest the gate, that they might not be
                    struck or wounded by any thing discharged at them from above. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Some of the Arpinians and Romans recognised each other,
                    which led to conversations, in which the Romans asked them, what it was they
                    meant? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for what offence on the part of the
                    Romans, or what service on that of the Carthaginians, they, who were Italians,
                    made war in favour of foreigners and barbarians, against their ancient allies
                    the Romans, and endeavoured to render Italy tributary and stipendiary to Africa?
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Arpinians urged in excuse of
                    themselves, that in ignorance of all the circumstances, they had been sold to
                    the Carthaginians by their nobility, and that they were kept in a state of
                    thraldom and oppression by the few. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A
                    beginning having been made, greater numbers on both sides entered into
                    conversation; and at length the praetor of Arpi was brought by his countrymen
                    before the consul, and after exchanging assurances in the midst of the standards
                    and the troops, the Arpinians suddenly turned their arms against the
                    Carthaginians, in favour of the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Some
                    Spaniards also, little less than a thousand in number, after only stipulating
                    with the consul that the Carthaginian garrison might be <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> allowed to march out unhurt, passed over to the consul.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The gates were therefore <pb n="953"
                        xml:id="p.953"/> thrown open for the Carthaginians; and being allowed to go
                    out unmolested, in conformity with the stipulation, they joined Hannibal in
                    Salapia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thus was Arpi restored to the
                    Romans, without the loss of a life, except that of one man, who was formerly a
                    traitor, and recently a deserter. The Spaniards were ordered to receive a double
                    allowance of provisions, and on very many occasions the republic availed itself
                    of their brave and faithful services. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> While
                    one of the consuls was in Apulia, and the other in Lucania, a hundred and twelve
                    Campanian noblemen, having gone out of Capua, with the permission of the
                    magistrates, under pretence of collecting booty from the enemy's lands, came
                    into the Roman camp, which lay above Suessula. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> They told the soldiers, forming the vanguard, that they wished to speak with
                    the praetor. Cneius Fulvius commanded the camp; who, on being informed of the
                    circumstance, ordered ten of them to be brought into his presence unarmed; and
                    after hearing their request, (and all they asked was, that when the Romans
                    should recover Capua, their property might be restored to them,) they were all
                    received under his protection. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The other
                    praetor, Sempronius Tuditanus, took by force the town of Aternum; more than
                    seven thousand were captured, with a considerable quantity of coined brass and
                    silver. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A dreadful fire happened at Rome,
                    which continued for two nights and a day; every thing was burnt to the ground
                    between the Salinae and the Carmental gate, with the Aequimaelium and the
                    Jugarian street. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> In the temples of Fortune,
                    Mater Matuta, and Hope, which latter stood without the gate, the fire, spreading
                    to a wide extent, consumed much both sacred and profane. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same year, the two Cornelii, Publius and
                    Cneius, as affairs were now in a prosperous state in Spain, and they had
                    recovered many ancient allies, and attached fresh ones to them, extended their
                    views even to Africa. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Syphax was a king of the
                    Numidians, who had suddenly become hostile to the Carthaginians; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> to him they sent three centurions as ambassadors, to
                    form a treaty of friendship and alliance with him; and to promise, that, if he
                    persevered in pressing the war against the Carthaginians, he would render an
                    acceptable service to the senate and people of Rome, and they would endeavour to
                    requite the favour with large additions, and at a seasonable time. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This embassy was gratifying to the barbarian; and
                    when conversing with the ambassadors on the <pb n="954" xml:id="p.954"/> art of
                    war, he heard the observations of those experienced soldiers, by comparing his
                    own practice with so regular a system of discipline, he became sensible of how
                    many things he himself was ignorant. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then he
                    entreated them to give the first proof of their being good and faithful allies,
                        <quote> by letting two of them carry back the result of their embassy to
                        their generals, while one remained with him as his instructor in military
                        science, observing that the Numidian nation were unacquainted with the
                        method of carrying on war with foot forces, being useful only as mounted
                        soldiers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That it was in this manner that
                        their ancestors had carried on war even from the first origin of their
                        nation, and to this they were habituated from their childhood. But that they
                        had to contend with an enemy who relied upon the prowess of their infantry;
                        with whom, if they wished to be placed upon an equality in respect of
                        efficient strength, they must also furnish themselves with infantry.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That his dominions abounded with a
                        large quantity of men fit for the purpose, but that he was unacquainted with
                        the art of arming, equipping, and marshalling them; that all his infantry
                        were unwieldy and unmanageable, like a rabble collected together by chance. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The ambassadors answered, that they would
                    comply with his request for the present, on his engaging to send him back
                    immediately, if their generals did not approve of what they had done. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The name of the person who staid behind with the king
                    was Quintus Statorius. With the two other Romans, the Numidian sent ambassadors
                    into Spain, to receive the ratification of the alliance from the Roman generals.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He gave it in charge to the same persons,
                    forthwith to induce the Numidians, who were serving as auxiliaries among the
                    Carthaginian troops, to go over to the other side. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Statorius raised a body of infantry for the king out of the
                    large number of young men which he found; and having formed them into companies,
                    in close imitation of the Roman method, taught them to follow their standards
                    and keep their ranks when being marshalled, and when performing their
                    evolutions; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and he so habituated them to
                    military works and other military duties, that in a short time the king relied
                    not more on his cavalry than on his infantry; and in a regular and pitched
                    battle, fought on a level plain, he overcame his enemies, the Carthaginians.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In Spain also the arrival of the king's
                    ambassadors was of the greatest advantage to the Romans, for at the news thereof
                    the Numidians began <pb n="955" xml:id="p.955"/> rapidly to pass over. Thus the
                    Romans and Syphax were united in friendship, which the Carthaginians hearing of,
                    immediately sent ambassadors to Gala, who reigned in another part of Numidia,
                    over a nation called Massylians. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Gala had a son named Masinissa, seventeen
                    years of age, but a youth of such talents, that even at that time it was evident
                    that he would render the kingdom more extensive and powerful than when he
                    received it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The ambassadors represented that,
                        <quote> since Syphax had united himself with the Romans, that by their
                        alliance he might strengthen his hands against the kings and nations of
                        Africa, it would be better for Gala also to unite with the Carthaginians as
                        soon as possible, before Syphax crossed over into Spain, or the Romans into
                        Africa; that Syphax might be overpowered, while as yet he derived nothing
                        from his league with the Romans but the name of it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Gala, his son claiming to be intrusted with
                    the conduct of the war, was easily prevailed upon to send an army, <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> which, joined by the legions of the Carthaginians,
                    totally defeated Syphax in a great battle. In this thirty thousand men are said
                    to have been slain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Syphax, with a few
                    horsemen, fled from the field, and took refuge among the Maurusian Numidians, a
                    nation dwelling at the extremity of Africa, near the ocean, and over against
                    Gades. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the barbarians flocking to his
                    standard from all sides, in consequence of his great renown, he speedily armed a
                    very large force. Before he passed over with these forces into Spain, which was
                    separated only by a narrow strait, Masinissa came up with his victorious army;
                    and here he acquired great glory in the prosecution of the war with Syphax, in
                    which he acted alone and unsupported by any aid from the Carthaginians.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In Spain nothing worth mentioning was
                    performed, except that the Romans drew over to their side the Celtiberian youth,
                    by giving them the same pay which they had stipulated with the Carthaginians to
                    pay them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They also sent above three hundred
                    Spaniards of the greatest distinction into Italy, to bring over their
                    countrymen, who served among the auxiliary troops of Hannibal. The only
                    memorable circumstance of this year in Spain was, that the Romans then, for the
                    first time, employed mercenary troops in their camp, namely, the Celtibe- rians.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
