<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 23-25 - 24</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Moore" role="editor"> Frank Gardener Moore, Professor Emeritus in
                    Columbia University </editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XXIII-XXV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1940: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.175"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="book">
                <head>Book XXIV</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> HAVING returned from Campania to the land of
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> the
                    Bruttii, Hanno, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He had been with
                        Hannibal around Nola, and was sent back to the country of the Bruttii;
                        XXIII. xlvi. 8. </note> with the Bruttii as supporters and guides, attacked
                    the Greek cities, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Operations against
                        Regium, Locri and Croton, barely mentioned in XXIII. xxx. 6 ff., are given
                        here in greater detail. It is late autumn, <date when="-0215">215
                            B.C.</date>
                    </note> which were all the more ready to remain in alliance with Rome because
                    they saw that the Bruttii, whom they both hated and feared, had gone over to the
                    side of the Carthaginians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Regium was the
                    first city to be attacked, and some days were spent there to no purpose.
                    Meantime the Locrians hastily brought grain and wood and the other things needed
                    to supply their wants from the farms into the city, also that no booty might be
                    left for the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And every day a larger
                    crowd poured out of all the gates. Finally there were left in the city only six
                    hundred men, who were made to repair walls and gates and to carry arms to the
                    battlements. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Against the multitude made up of
                    all ages and classes, wandering about the country, many of the unarmed, Hamilcar
                    the Carthaginian sent out his cavalry. Forbidden to injure anyone, they
                    interposed their squadrons merely to shut off from the city those who had
                    scattered in flight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The commander himself,
                    after capturing higher ground from which he could see the country and the city,
                    ordered a cohort of Bruttii <pb n="p.177"/> to go up to the walls and call out
                    the chief men of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        215</note> the Locrians to a conference, and with a promise of Hannibal's
                    friendship to encourage them to surrender the city. In the conference the
                    Bruttians at first were not believed at all. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Then, when the Carthaginians were seen on the hills, and a few returning
                    fugitives repeatedly asserted that all the rest of the multitude were in the
                    power of the enemy, overcome by fear, they answered that they would consult the
                    people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> An assembly being at once called, all
                    the fickle preferred political change and a new alliance; also those whose
                    relations had been shut off outside the city by the enemy had mortgaged their
                    affections, having virtually given hostages. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    And the few silently approved of steadfast loyalty, rather than dared to declare
                    and defend it. Hence surrender to the Carthaginians was voted with apparently
                    unquestioned unanimity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After Lucius Atilius,
                    commander of the garrison, and the Roman soldiers who were with him had been
                    secretly led down to the harbour and put on ships to be carried to Regium, they
                    admitted Hamilcar and the Carthaginians into the city on condition that a treaty
                    be made at once on fair terms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The promise of
                    such a treaty was almost broken after they surrendered, when the Carthaginian
                    charged that the Roman had been allowed by trickery to go away, while the
                    Locrians pleaded that he had escaped unaided. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Also the cavalry pursued him in the hope that possibly the current in the strait
                    might delay the ships or bring them to shore. They did not indeed overtake the
                    men they were pursuing, but they sighted other ships crossing the strait from
                    Messana to Regium. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not directly
                        opposite Messana, but about seven miles to the southeast. </note> It was the
                    Roman soldiers sent by Claudius, the <pb n="p.179"/> praetor, to garrison and
                    hold the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And so the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> siege of
                    Regium was at once raised. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Peace was granted
                    the Locrians by Hannibal's order: they were, namely, to live in freedom under
                    their own laws, the city to be open to the Carthaginians, the harbour in the
                    power of the Locrians, the alliance to rest upon this basis: that the
                    Carthaginian should help the Locrian, the Locrian the Carthaginian, in peace and
                    in war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus the Carthaginians were withdrawn from the
                    strait, though the Bruttians were indignant because they had left Regium and
                    Locri untouched, the cities which they had counted upon plundering. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And so without aid they enlisted and armed 15,000 of
                    their young men and set out to besiege Croton, another Greek city and on the
                    sea, believing <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> that it would be a great
                    addition to their resources if they should hold a fortified city and harbour on
                    the seacoast. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It troubled them that they did
                    not quite dare not to call the Carthaginians to their aid, for fear they might
                    seem to have failed to act as became allies. At the same time they feared that,
                    if the Carthaginian should again be rather an arbiter of peace than a helper in
                    war, fighting to secure freedom for Croton might be profitless, as previously
                    for Locri. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And thus it seemed best to send
                    legates to Hannibal and gain assurance from him that Croton when captured should
                    belong to the Bruttians. Hannibal having replied that decision in the matter lay
                    with those on the ground, thus referring them to Hanno, they obtained no
                    definite answer from Hanno. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He did not wish a
                    city well-known and rich to be plundered, and he was hoping that, while the
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Bruttian was besieging them and the
                    Carthaginians <pb n="p.181"/> obviously neither approving nor helping the siege,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> they
                    would all the more promptly come over to his side. At Croton there was among the
                    citizens no one policy or common preference. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    One malady, so to speak, had attacked all the city-states of Italy, that the
                    common people were at odds with the upper class, the senate inclining to the
                    Romans, the common people drawing the state to the side of the Carthaginians.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This disagreement in the city was reported
                    to the Bruttians by a deserter: that Aristomachus was the leader of the
                    plebeians and advised surrender of the city; also that in the sparsely inhabited
                    city, with its walls at a great distance, there were only scattered posts and
                    guards of the senators; that wherever plebeians were on guard there was free
                    access to the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> With the deserter as
                    adviser and leader the Bruttians completely encircled the city, and being
                    admitted by the plebeians, they took the whole city by assault, with the
                    exception of the citadel. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The optimates held
                    the citadel, having previously prepared a place of refuge for such an emergency.
                    To it Aristomachus also fled, as though he had advised surrendering the city to
                    the Carthaginians, not to the Bruttians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The city of Croton had a wall with a circuit
                    of twelve miles before the coming of Pyrrhus to Italy. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Since the desolation caused by that war scarcely half of
                    the city was inhabited. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to
                        XXIII. xxx. 6 the city now had less than 2000 inhabitants. </note> The river
                    which had flowed through the middle of the city now flowed past, outside the
                    quarters which had numerous houses, and the citadel was far from the inhabited
                    portions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Six miles from the famous city was a
                    temple more <pb n="p.183"/> famous than the city itself, that of Lacinian Juno,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cp. XXIII. xxxiii. 4. At that
                        temple, the most celebrated shrine in Magna Graecia, Polybius found and used
                        Hannibal's own inscription in Punic and Greek, recording his successes
                        (Polyb. III. xxxiii. 18; lvi. 4), a document which Livy barely mentions
                        (XXVIII. xlvi. 16). A single column of the temple still stands on the
                        promontory. Livy is correct in regard to the distance from the city of
                        Croton ( <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 9 km.). </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> revered
                    by all the surrounding <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> peoples. There a sacred
                    grove, which was enclosed by dense woods and tall fir-trees, had in its centre
                    luxuriant pastures, where cattle of all kinds, being sacred to the goddess, used
                    to pasture without any <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> shepherd. And at night
                    the flocks of each kind would return separately to their stalls, being never
                    harmed by wild beasts lying in wait, nor by the dishonesty of <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> men. Therefore great profits were made from the cattle, and
                    out of the profits a massive golden column <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Coelius the historian said that Hannibal, finding it
                        was not merely plated, decided to carry it away, but was deterred by a
                        dream; Cicero <hi rend="italics">de Div.</hi> I. 48. </note> was wrought and
                    consecrated. And the temple was famous for its wealth also, not merely for its
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> sanctity. They give it some pretended
                    marvels also, as generally in places so noted. It is reported that in the space
                    in front of the temple there is an altar whose ashes are never stirred by any
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> wind. But the citadel of Croton, on one
                    side overhanging the sea, while the other slopes down toward the country, was
                    once protected merely by its natural situation, but later encircled with a wall
                    also, where, along the cliffs on the farther side, it had been taken by ruse of
                    Dionysius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Who captured Croton about
                            <date when="-0389">389 B.C.</date> and is said to have held it twelve
                        years. </note> tyrant of <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Sicily. In that
                    citadel, sufficiently safe, as it seemed, the optimates of Croton were at the
                    time maintaining themselves, besieged even by their own plebs as well as by the
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Bruttians. Finally the Bruttians, seeing
                    that the citadel was for their resources impregnable, were of necessity
                    constrained to beg aid of <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hanno. He attempted
                    to compel the Crotonians to surrender on condition that they <pb n="p.185"/>
                    permit a colony of Bruttians to be established there, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> and allow the city,
                    desolate and depopulated by wars, to recover its old-time <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> numbers. But among them all he prevailed upon no one except
                    Aristomachus. They claimed that they would sooner die than mingle with the
                    Bruttians and change to the rites, customs and laws, and presently even the
                    language, of another <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> people. Aristomachus,
                    since he was unable by persuasion to bring them to surrender and could find no
                    opportunity to betray the citadel, as he had betrayed the city, alone went over
                    to <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Hanno. Soon after that the Locrian legates
                    entered the citadel with Hanno's consent and persuaded them to allow themselves
                    to be transferred to Locri, and not to risk desperate <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> measures. Permission to that effect they had already
                    obtained from Hannibal, having sent legates for that very purpose. So Croton was
                    evacuated, and the Crotonians were led down to the sea and went on <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> shipboard. They went, the whole number of them,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The entire population, while
                            <quote>Crotonians</quote> refers primarily to the optimates. </note> to
                    Locri. </p>
                <p> In Apulia even the winter was not without conflict between the Romans and
                    Hannibal. Sempronius, the consul, was wintering at Luceria, Hannibal not far
                    from <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Arpi. Skirmishes between them kept
                    occurring as opportunity offered, or the favourable moment for one side or the
                    other. And in consequence the Romans were better soldiers, daily more cautious
                    and safer from surprise attacks. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Sicily everything had been changed for the
                    Romans by the death of Hiero <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For
                        Hiero's family see the table on p. 338.</note> and the transfer of the
                    kingdom to his grandson Hieronymus, a boy hardly able to keep his independence
                    under control, much less absolute power. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Such
                    was the age, such <pb n="p.187"/> the disposition which guardians and friends
                    took in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note>
                    hand, to throw him into all the vices. Hiero, seeing that this would happen, is
                    said in his extreme old age to have wished to leave Syracuse free, that kingly
                    power gained and confirmed by good qualities might not come to an end in
                    disgrace under the tyranny of a boy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This his
                    plan was opposed might and main by his daughters, who thought the boy would have
                    the kingly title, but that complete control would be in their hands and those of
                    their husbands, Adranodorus and Zoippus, who were being left as the principal
                    guardians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was not easy for a man now in
                    his ninetieth year, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He lived more
                        than ninety years according to Polybius VII. viii. 7. </note> surrounded day
                    and night by the blandishments of women, to be independent and turn his
                    attention from the personal to the public interest. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly he merely left fifteen guardians for the boy,
                    and dying entreated them to keep inviolate that loyalty to the Roman people
                    which he had maintained for fifty years <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In fact 48 years (263- <date when="-0215">215
                            B.C.</date> ). </note> and to choose above all to have the young man
                    tread in his footsteps and continue the training in which he had been brought
                    up. Such were his instructions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After he had
                    breathed his last the guardians produced the will and brought the boy, at that
                    time about fifteen years old, before an assembly of the people. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> While a few men, who had been posted in all parts of the
                    assembly to start applause, showed approval of the will, while the rest, as if
                    deprived of a father and in an orphaned city, had only fears, the guardians
                    &lt;took charge&gt;. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then came the king's
                    funeral, honoured rather by the love and regard of the citizens than by the
                    grief of his <pb n="p.189"/> family. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Soon
                    afterwards Adranodorus removed the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 215</note> rest of the guardians, saying that Hieronymus
                    was now a young man and capable of ruling. And laying down his own guardianship,
                    which was shared with a number of others, he took to himself alone the powers of
                    them all. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It would have been difficult for any king,
                    even a good one and self-controlled, to find favour with the Syracusans as
                    successor to Hiero, so beloved. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But certainly
                    Hieronymus at his very first appearance showed how different everything was,
                    just as if he wished by his vices to make them regret his grandfather.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For, though through so many years they had
                    seen Hiero and his son Gelo <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See note
                        on XXIII. xxx. 11.</note> not differing from the rest of the citizens in
                    garb or in any other distinction, they beheld purple and a diadem and armed
                    attendants and a man who came forth from the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    palace sometimes even in a chariot with four white horses after the manner of
                    Dionysius the tyrant. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This haughty state and
                    costume were suitably attended by contempt shown towards everyone, by haughty
                    ears, insulting words, infrequent access, not only for outsiders but even for
                    his guardians, by unheard of lusts, by inhuman cruelty. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See note on XXIII. xxx. 11.</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Consequently such alarm had laid hold of all
                    that some of the guardians anticipated the dreaded punishments either by suicide
                    or by flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Three of them, who alone had
                    more intimate access to the palace, Adranodorus and Zoippus, the sons-in-law of
                    Hiero, and a certain Thraso, were not indeed much listened to on other matters;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but as two of them were inclining to the
                    Carthaginians, Thraso to alliance with Rome, by their partisan rivalry they were
                    occasionally attracting the young man's attention, when a conspiracy <pb
                        n="p.191"/> formed against the life of the tyrant was revealed <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> by one
                    Callo, of the same age as Hieronymus and from boyhood accustomed to all the
                    rights of intimacy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The informer was able to
                    name but one of the conspirators, Theodotus, by whom he had himself been
                    approached. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And Theodotus, at once seized and
                    handed over for torture to Adranodorus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Zoippus had been sent about this time to Egypt; xxvi.
                        1.</note> confessed without hesitation in regard to himself, but did not
                    reveal his accomplices. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Finally, racked by
                    all the tortures which pass human endurance, pretending to be mastered by his
                    sufferings, he turned informer against the innocent instead of against his
                    accomplices, and falsely stated that Thraso was responsible for the plan: that
                    they would not have ventured upon such an undertaking if they had not relied
                    upon so powerful a leader. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He also named
                    attendants of the tyrant as associates, men whose lives, it occurred to him, as
                    he was fabricating between pains and groans, were of the least account.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> His mentioning Thraso made the
                    information particularly credible to the mind of the tyrant. Accordingly Thraso
                    was forthwith handed over for execution, and the rest, equally innocent, shared
                    his punishment. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Not one of the accomplices
                    either hid himself or fled, though their partner in the plot was long under
                    torture. Such confidence was theirs in the courage and loyalty of Theodotus, and
                    such will-power to keep secrets did Theodotus himself possess. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus as soon as Thraso, <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> who was the sole link to <milestone n="3??" unit="section"
                    /> an alliance <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> with the Romans, had been
                    removed from their midst, matters <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> at once
                    tended unquestionably <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> toward defection. And
                    ambassadors <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy mentions only
                        Hannibal's envoys. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Polybius gives the
                        names of <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> two sent from Hieronymus'
                        court, viz. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Polyclitus and Philodemus (
                            <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ii. 2). </note> were sent to Hannibal, and
                    he sent back with a young noble named Hannibal <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This Hannibal was only a trierarch; <hi rend="italics"
                            >ibid.</hi> § 3. </note> also Hippocrates and Epicydes, <pb n="p.193"/>
                    who were born at Carthage but Syracusans by origin <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> (their grandfather being
                    an exile), Carthaginians themselves on the mother's side. Through these men an
                    alliance was made between Hannibal and the tyrant of Syracuse, and with
                    Hannibal's consent they remained with the tyrant. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Appius Claudius, the praetor, whose province was Sicily, on
                    learning of this, forthwith sent legates to Hieronymus. While they were saying
                    that they had come to renew the alliance which they had had with his
                    grandfather, they were heard with derision and dismissed by Hieronymus, who in
                    jest asked what success they had had in the battle at Cannae; for Hannibal's
                    envoys reported what was scarcely to be believed. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He wished to know, he said, what the truth was, that he
                    might accordingly determine from which side he had the more to hope. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans departed, saying that they would return to
                    him when he began to give a sober hearing to embassies, and warning rather than
                    asking him not to be rash in changing his loyalty. Hieronymus sent ambassadors
                    to Carthage to make a treaty in accordance with the alliance arranged with
                    Hannibal. The agreement was that, after they had driven the Romans out of Sicily
                    (and this would be shortly done if <hi rend="italics">they</hi> would send ships
                    and an army), the river Himera, which nearly divides the island in halves,
                    should be the boundary of the kingdom of Syracuse and the Carthaginian empire.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thereupon, puffed up by the flatteries of
                    those who bade him remember not Hiero only but also King Pyrrhus, his maternal
                    grandfather, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Pyrrhus seems to have
                        been his mother's grandfather; see table on p. 338. </note> Hieronymus sent
                    another embassy, through which he declared it was fair for them to yield all
                    Sicily to him, and for the Carthaginian people to seek their own dominion over
                    Italy. <pb n="p.195"/> At this trifling and boastful spirit in a madcap youth
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> they
                    did not wonder, nor find fault either, provided they made him break with the
                    Romans. </p>
                <p> VII. But in everything he was on the verge of ruin. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> For after sending Hippocrates and Epicydes in advance, each
                    with two thousand armed men, to attack the cities which were held by Roman
                    garrisons, he too setting out with all the rest of the army —and they were about
                    fifteen thousand infantry and cavalry —had gone to Leontini. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Northwest of Syracuse and looking down
                        on a lake and the plain of Catana; captured by Marcellus, xxx. 1. </note>
                    The conspirators all of whom, as it happened, were in the army, took possession
                    of an empty house looking down upon the narrow street by which the king used to
                    go down to the market-place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There, while the
                    rest, drawn up under arms, were to stand waiting for him to pass, one of them
                    —his name was Dinomenes —, as being a body-guard, was assigned the rôle of
                    halting, on some pretext, the column following the king in the narrow street,
                    when he approached the door of the house. This was carried out as had been
                    arranged. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Dinomenes, raising one foot and
                    pretending to loosen a knot drawn too tight, delayed the crowd and caused such a
                    gap that, when the attack on the king was made as he passed without guards, he
                    was stabbed with several thrusts before help could reach him. On hearing the
                    shouting and uproar they hurled their weapons at Dinomenes, who was now
                    obviously blocking the way. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the midst of
                    these, however, he escaped with only two wounds. The guards fled as soon as they
                    saw the king lying there. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Of the assassins
                    some proceeded to the market-place and into a crowd which rejoiced in its
                    freedom, some to Syracuse to forestall the designs of Adranodorus and the other
                    supporters of the king. In the unsettled <pb n="p.197"/> state of affairs Appius
                    Claudius, seeing a war <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 215</note> beginning near at hand, informed the senate by letter that
                    Sicily was being won over to the Carthaginian people and Hannibal. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> For his own part, to meet the schemes of the
                    Syracusans, he concentrated all his garrisons on the frontier between the
                    province and the kingdom. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In <date
                            when="-0241">241 B.C.</date> Hiero as a faithful ally for 22 years was
                        allowed to keep the eastern end of the island (about one-fourth, and not
                        including Messana). </note>
                </p>
                <p> At the end of that year Quintus Fabius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > The Delayer, consul this year and the next (five times in all), dictator
                        in <date when="-0217">217 B.C.</date>
                    </note> by the authority of the senate fortified and garrisoned Puteoli, which
                    as a commercial centre had grown in population during the war. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Then, while on his way to Rome to hold the elections, he
                    proclaimed them for the first date available for an election, and without
                    stopping passed the city and came down to the Campus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Thus he retains full military authority, which would
                        not be the case if he had entered the city; cp. ix. 2. </note> On the day
                    set the right to vote first fell to the century of the younger men of the
                    Aniensis tribe, and it named Titus Otacilius and Marcus Aemilius Regillus as
                    consuls. Thereupon Quintus Fabius, after silence had been made, spoke somewhat
                    as follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> If we had either peace in Italy or such a war and such an enemy that
                        there was ample room for carelessness, should someone interpose any delay to
                        the enthusiasm which you bring to the Campus in order to entrust
                        magistracies to the men of your choice, such a man would seem to me
                        forgetful of your freedom. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But since in
                        this war, in dealing with this enemy, never has a mistake been made by any
                        commander without huge losses to us, you ought in electing consuls to enter
                        the polls with the same seriousness with which you go into battle-line under
                        arms, and each man should say to himself: 'I name as consul a man who is a
                        match for Hannibal the general.' <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This year
                        at Capua, when Vibellius <pb n="p.199"/> Taurea, a distinguished Campanian
                        knight, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            215</note> challenged, Asellus Claudius, a distinguished Roman knight,
                        was matched against him. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf.
                            XXIII. xlvii.</note>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Against the Gaul who once challenged at
                        the bridge over the Anio our ancestors sent Titus Manlius, <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. VII. x. 2 ff.</note> who relied
                        upon his courage and his strength. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There
                        was the same reason, I am inclined to admit, why not many years later Marcus
                        Valerius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Also in Book VII (xxvi. 2
                            ff.).</note> found no lack of confidence in him when he took up arms for
                        the fray against a Gaul who made a like challenge. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Just as we desire to have foot and horse stronger than
                        those of the enemy, if not, then a match for him, so let us seek a general
                        who is a match for the commander of the enemy. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> When we shall have chosen the man who is the greatest
                        commander in the state, nevertheless, although suddenly chosen, elected for
                        a single year, he will be pitted against an experienced permanent general,
                        hampered by no restrictions of time or authority to prevent him from doing
                        and directing everything as the phases of the war shall require. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> But with us the year rolls round in mere
                        preparation and while we are just beginning. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> Having sufficiently stated what kind of men you ought to elect as
                        consuls, it remains for me to say a few words in regard to those to whom the
                        favour of the first century to vote has inclined. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius Regillus is the flamen of Quirinus, and
                        we can neither send him away from the sacred rites nor keep him at home
                        without abandoning our responsibility for the gods or else for the war.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Titus Otacilius has my sister's
                        daughter as his wife and children by her. But not so slight are your favours
                        to my ancestors and myself that I can fail to hold the state of more account
                        than personal ties. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Any one of the <pb
                            n="p.201"/> sailors and passengers can steer when the sea is <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note> calm.
                        When a savage storm comes and the ship is swept over a rough sea by the
                        wind, then there is need of a man and a pilot. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> We are not sailing a calm sea, but have been almost
                        sunk already by a number of squalls. And so who is to sit at the helm is for
                        you to decide with the greatest seriousness and foresight. In a lesser
                        affair we have tested you, Titus Otacilius. Certainly you have not shown any
                        reason why we should trust you for greater things. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> This year we equipped the fleet which you commanded for
                        three purposes: to ravage the coast of Africa, to make our Italian shores
                        safe, but above all to prevent reinforcements with pay and supplies from
                        being brought over from Carthage for Hannibal. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Citizens, elect Titus Otacilius consul, if he has
                        performed, I do not say all of these things, but some part of them, for the
                        state. But if, while you, Titus Otacilius, commanded the fleet, even the
                        things he did not need came to Hannibal from home safe and intact, as though
                        he had conquered the sea, if the coast of Italy has been more unsafe this
                            <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> year than that of Africa, what
                        reason can you give why we are to match you by preference as commander
                        against such an enemy as Hannibal? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> If you
                        were consul we should propose the appointment of a dictator, following the
                        precedent of our ancestors, and you could not be incensed that some one in
                        the Roman state was considered a better man in war than you. It is to no
                        one's interest more than yours, Titus Otacilius, that no such burden be
                        placed on your shoulders that you may fall beneath it. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> I earnestly entreat and urge you, citizens, that the
                        same spirit which you <pb n="p.203"/> would show if, while standing armed in
                        battle-line, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            215</note> you had suddenly to choose two generals under whose command
                        and auspices you should fight, be yours today also in electing <milestone
                            n="19??" unit="section"/> consuls to whom your sons shall repeat the
                        oath, in response to whose edict they shall assemble, under whose guardian
                        care they shall serve. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> The Lake of
                        Trasumennus and Cannae are sad examples to recall, but to guard against like
                        disasters they are a warning. Herald, summon the Aniensis century of the
                        younger men to vote again! </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Titus Otacilius was fiercely and noisily
                    shouting that Fabius wanted to have his consulship prolonged, the consul ordered
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the lictors to go up to him, and, as he
                    had not entered the city, having gone without <milestone n="3??" unit="section"
                    /> a halt directly to the Campus, he warned Otacilius that the fasces carried
                    before the consul had their axes. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Removed when a magistrate entered the city, as an indication that there his
                        sentence was subject to appeal. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the leading century proceeded to
                    vote, and in it were elected consuls Quintus Fabius Maximus for the fourth time
                    and Marcus Marcellus for the third time. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    rest of the centuries without exception named the same men as consuls. And of
                    the praetors one, Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, was reflected, the others newly
                    created, Titus <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> Otacilius Crassus for the
                    second time, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> His first praetorship
                        was in <date when="-0217">217 B.C.</date> ; XXII. X. 10. </note> Quintus
                    Fabius, son of the consul and at the time curule aedile, and Publius Cornelius
                    Lentulus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The election of praetors being now
                    completed, the senate decreed <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ordinarily praetors received their particular assignment of duty by casting
                        lots or by agreement. </note> that Quintus Fulvius by special designation
                    should have the duties of city praetor, and that he, and <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> no one else, should be in charge of the city when the
                    consuls took the field. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There were great
                    floods twice <pb n="p.205"/> that year and the Tiber overflowed the farms with
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 215</note>
                    great destruction of buildings and cattle and much loss of life. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the fifth year of the Second Punic War,
                    Quintus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    Fabius Maximus entering his fourth consulship and Marcus Claudius Marcellus his
                    third attracted the attention of the citizens more than was usual. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> For many years there had been no such pair of
                    consuls. Old men recalled that thus Maximus Rullus had been declared consul
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For <date when="-0295">295
                            B.C.</date> ; <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> xxiv. 1. </note> with Publius Decius for
                    the Gallic war, thus, later on, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For
                            <date when="-0272">272 B.C.</date>
                    </note> Papirius and Carvilius against the Samnites and Bruttians and the people
                    of Lucania and of Tarentum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Marcellus was made
                    consul in his absence, being with the army; for Fabius, who was present and
                    himself conducted the election, his consulship was continued. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The times and the straits of war and danger to the
                    existence of the state deterred any one from searching for a precedent for that,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> immediate reëlection, which a plebiscite of
                            <date when="-0217">217 B.C.</date> had made legal for the duration of
                        the war in Italy; cf. XXVII. vi. 7 f. </note> and from suspecting the consul
                    of greed for power. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the contrary they
                    praised his high-mindedness, in that, knowing the state had need of a great
                    commander, and that he was himself undoubtedly that man, he counted his own
                    unpopularity, should any be the consequence, as of less moment than the
                    advantage of the state. </p>
                <p> X. On the day on which the consuls entered upon office the senate met on the
                    Capitol, and it was decreed first of all that the consuls should decide by lot
                    or by mutual arrangement which of them should hold the election for naming the
                    censors before leaving for the army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then for
                    all who were with <pb n="p.207"/> the army their commands were continued, and
                    they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    were ordered to remain in their assignments, Tiberius Gracchus at Luceria, where
                    he was with the army of slave-volunteers, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIII. xxxii. 1.</note> Gaius Terentius Varro in the
                    Picene district, Marcus Pomponius in the Gallic; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> and that of the praetors of the previous year, now as propraetors, Quintus
                    Mucius should govern Sardinia and Marcus Valerius should be in command of the
                    sea-coast at Brundisium, watchful against all movements of Philip, King of the
                    Macedonians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Sicily was assigned as his
                    province to Publius Cornelius Lentulus, the praetor, and to Titus Otacilius the
                    same fleet which he had had against the Carthaginians the previous year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Prodigies <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIII. xxxi. 15; XXIV. xliv. 8.</note> in large
                    numbers —and the more they were believed by men simple and devout, the more of
                    them used to be reported —were reported that year: that at Lanuvium ravens had
                    made a nest inside the temple of Juno Sospita; that in Apulia a green palm took
                    fire; that at Mantua a lake, the overflow of the river Mincius, appeared bloody;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and at Cales it rained chalk, and at Rome
                    in the Cattle Market blood; and that on the Vicus Insteius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A street leading up to the Collis Latiaris (part of the
                        Quirinal), not far from the Curia. </note> an underground spring flowed with
                    such a volume of water that the force of a torrent, as it were, overturned the
                    jars, great and small, that were there and carried them along; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> that the Atrium Publicum on the Capitol, the temple of
                    Vulcan in the Campus, that of Vacuna <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Honoured especially by the Sabines, and known to modern readers chiefly in
                        Horace's <hi rend="italics">post fanum putre Vacunae; Epist.</hi> I. x. 49.
                    </note> and a public street in the Sabine country, the wall and a gate at Gabii
                    were struck by lightning. Moreover other marvels were widely <pb n="p.209"/>
                    circulated: that the spear of Mars at Praeneste moved <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> of itself; that an ox in
                    Sicily spoke; that among the Marrucini an infant in its mother's womb shouted
                        <quote>Hail, triumph!</quote> ; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that at
                    Spoletium a woman was changed into a man; that at Hadria an altar was seen in
                    the sky, and about it the forms of men in white garments. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> In fact at Rome also, actually in the city, directly after
                    the appearance of a swarm of bees in the Forum —a wonder because it is rare
                    —certain men, asserting that they saw armed legions on the Janiculum, aroused
                    the city to arms, whereas those who were on the Janiculum denied that anyone had
                    been seen there except the usual dwellers on that hill. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Atonement was made for these prodigies with full-grown
                    victims on the advice of the soothsayers, and a season of prayer to all the gods
                    who had festal couches <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> draped <hi rend="italics">lecti</hi> with
                        their cushions, kept in the temples of such gods as received the special
                        honour of a <hi rend="italics">lectisternium,</hi> a feast at which images
                        of gods reclined in pairs; XXII. x. 9. </note> at Rome was proclaimed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The rites which concerned peace with the gods
                    being now completed, the consuls laid before the senate the condition of the
                    state and the conduct of the war, and what forces there were and where severally
                    stationed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was voted to carry on the war
                    with eighteen legions; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not including
                        those in Spain. Similarly in § 5 no mention is made of a fleet for Spain.
                    </note> that each consul should take two; that with two legions in each case
                    Gaul and Sicily and Sardinia should be held; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    that with two legions Quintus Fabius, a praetor, should be in charge of Apulia,
                    and that with two legions of slave-volunteers Tiberius Gracchus should be in
                    command in the region of Luceria; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that one
                    legion each should be left for Gaius Terentius, the proconsul, in the Picene
                    district and for Marcus Valerius for service with the fleet near Brundisium;
                    that two should form the garrison of the city. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    To make up this number of legions six new legions had to be enrolled. <pb
                        n="p.211"/> The consuls were ordered to enroll them as soon as <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> possible,
                    and to furnish a fleet, so that, including the ships at anchor defending the
                    coast of Calabria, the fleet should amount that year to a hundred and fifty
                    warships. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After conducting the levy and
                    launching a hundred new ships, Quintus Fabius held an election for the choosing
                    of censors. Marcus Atilius Regulus and Publius Furius Philus were elected. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As the rumour that there was a war in Sicily
                    spread more widely, Titus Otacilius was ordered to set sail thither with his
                    fleet. Owing to the lack of sailors <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi>
                        <date when="-0220">220 B.C.</date> ; XXIII. xxiii. 5. </note> the consuls in
                    accordance with a decree of the senate issued an edict that a man who in the
                    censorship of Lucius Aemilius and Gaius Flaminius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Meaning chiefly <hi rend="italics">remiges</hi> , who
                        pulled the long oars and were in general slaves; cf. XXVI. xxxv. </note> had
                    been rated —either he or his father —at from 50,000 to 100,000 asses, or if his
                    property had since increased to that amount, should furnish one sailor provided
                    with six months' pay; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that one who had more
                    than 100,000 and up to 300,000 should furnish three sailors and a year's pay; he
                    who had over 300,000 and up to a million asses, five sailors; he who had over a
                    million, seven; that senators should furnish eight sailors and a year's pay.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The sailors furnished in accordance with
                    this edict went on board armed and equipped by their masters, and with cooked
                    rations for thirty days. It was the first time that a Roman fleet was manned
                    with crews secured at private expense. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This extraordinary preparation particularly
                    alarmed the Campanians, for fear the Romans might begin that year's war with a
                    siege of Capua. Accordingly they sent legates to Hannibal to beg him to bring
                    his army to Capua. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> New armies, they said, <pb
                        n="p.213"/> were being enrolled at Rome for besieging it, and the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> defection
                    of no city had more embittered the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Since they reported this with such excitement, Hannibal, thinking he must make
                    haste, lest he be anticipated by the Romans, set out from Arpi and established
                    himself by Tifata in his old camp above Capua. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Then leaving Numidians and Spaniards to defend the camp and Capua at the same
                    time, he came down with the rest of his army to the Lake of Avernus, with the
                    pretext of sacrificing, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably in
                        connection with the necromancy practised at Avernus. </note> in reality to
                    attack Puteoli and the garrison which was there. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Maximus, on being informed that Hannibal had left Arpi and was returning to
                    Campania, without interrupting his journey by day or night returned to the army.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And he ordered Tiberius Gracchus to bring
                    his troops from Luceria to Beneventum, and Quintus Fabius, the praetor —he was
                    the consul's son —, to relieve Gracchus at Luceria. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two praetors set out at the same time for
                    Sicily, Publius Cornelius to the army, and Titus Otacilius to take command of
                    the sea-coast and of naval operations. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And the
                    others set out for their several assignments, and those whose commands had been
                    prolonged held the same regions as in the previous year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Hannibal was at the Lake of Avernus
                    five-noble young men came to him from Tarentum, some of whom had been captured
                    at the Lake of Trasumennus, others at Cannae, and sent to their homes with that
                    same courtesy which the Carthaginian had shown toward all allies of the Romans.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Mindful of his favours, they reported that
                    they had induced a large part of the young men of Tarentum to prefer the
                    friendship and alliance of Hannibal to <pb n="p.215"/> those of the Roman
                    people; and that, as legates <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 214</note> sent by their people, they asked Hannibal to
                    bring his army nearer to Tarentum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If his
                    standards, if his camp should be seen from Tarentum there would be no delay in
                    the surrender of the city; that the common people were in the power of the
                    younger men, the Tarentine state in the hands of the common people. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal praised them and overwhelmed them with great
                    promises, and bade them return home to carry out their undertaking promptly;
                    that he would be there at the right moment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    With this hope the Tarentines were sent away. He himself had conceived a great
                    desire to gain possession of Tarentum. He saw that the city was not only rich
                    and famous but also a seaport, and favourably placed in the direction of
                    Macedonia, and that accordingly King Philip, if he should cross into Italy,
                    would make for this port, since the Romans held Brundisium. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then, after accomplishing the rite for which he had come,
                    and devastating the territory of Cumae as far as the promontory of Misenum,
                    while he lingered there, he suddenly headed his column toward Puteoli, to
                    surprise the Roman garrison. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were six
                    thousand men and the place was defended by a wall also, not merely by nature.
                    There the Carthaginian tarried three days, attacking the garrison from every
                    side; and then, when he met with no success, he set out to ravage the territory
                    of Neapolis, rather in anger than with the hope of taking the city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His coming into a neighbouring region aroused
                    the common people of Nola, who had long been estranged from the Romans and
                    hostile to their own senate. Consequently legates came to invite Hannibal,
                    bringing a definitive promise to surrender the city. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.217"/> Marcellus, the consul, was called in by the leading <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> men and
                    forestalled their undertaking. From Cales he had hastened in one day to
                    Suessula, though the river Volturnus had delayed his crossing. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Thence he sent six thousand infantry and three hundred
                    horsemen that night into Nola, to defend the senate. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> And whereas the consul did everything with energy, in order
                    to anticipate him in occupying Nola, Hannibal was wasting time, having twice
                    already made the vain attempt, and being now less inclined to believe the men of
                    Nola. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time not only did Quintus Fabius,
                    the consul, come to Casilinum, to attack the city, held by a Carthaginian
                    garrison, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since Hannibal had captured
                        the city; XXIII. xix; 15 f.; xx. 1. </note> but also, as if by
                    prearrangement, Hanno, with a large force of infantry and cavalry, from the land
                    of the Bruttii, came to Beneventum from one side, while on the other side
                    Tiberius Gracchus came to it from Luceria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    latter at first entered the town, and then, on hearing that Hanno had pitched
                    his camp about three miles from the city by the river Calor, and from that point
                    was ravaging the country, he likewise left the city and pitched camp about a
                    mile from the enemy. There he held an assembly of the soldiers. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The legions he had were largely made up of
                    slave-volunteers, who now for two years had preferred silently to earn their
                    freedom rather than openly to demand it. Yet as he came out of winter quarters
                    he had been aware that there was murmuring in the column, as they asked whether
                    they were ever at all to serve as free men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And he had written to the senate, not so much what they wanted as what they had
                    deserved; that he had had good and brave service from them up to that time, and
                    that they lacked <pb n="p.219"/> nothing toward the standard of the real soldier
                    except <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    their freedom. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In this matter he had been
                    given permission to do whatever he thought to be for the good of the state.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And so, before engaging the enemy, he
                    announced that the time had come for them to gain the freedom for which they so
                    long had hoped; that the next day he would fight, standards against standards,
                    in a clear and open field, where without any fear of ambush the battle could be
                    fought with pure courage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whoever should bring
                    back the head of an enemy would by his order be a free man at once. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Whoever retreated from his post would meet the
                    punishment of a slave. Each man's fortune was in his own hand. The giver of
                    their freedom would be not merely himself, but the consul Marcus Marcellus, but
                    the whole senate, for they had been consulted by him and had given him
                    permission in the matter of their freedom. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                    then read the letter of the consul and the decree of the senate. Upon that a
                    shout was raised with great applause. They clamoured for battle and with high
                    spirit insisted that he give the signal at once. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Gracchus announced a battle for the morrow and dismissed
                    the assembly. The soldiers were happy, especially those for whom freedom was to
                    be the reward of a single day's service, and spent the rest of the day in
                    putting their arms in order. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the next day, when the signals began to
                    sound, these soldiers were the first of all to assemble at headquarters, ready
                    and in formation. After sunrise Gracchus led his troops out into line, and the
                    enemy did not delay the battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They had
                    seventeen thousand infantry, mostly Bruttians and Lucanians, twelve hundred
                    cavalry, among them very few <pb n="p.221"/> Italians, nearly all the rest
                    Numidians and Mauri. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 214</note> The battle was fierce and long; for four hours it did not
                    incline either way. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And nothing hampered the
                    Romans more than that enemies' heads were made the price of freedom. For when a
                    man had boldly slain an enemy, in the first place he was wasting time in cutting
                    off the head with difficulty in the confusion and turmoil; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and then, as his right hand was occupied in holding the
                    head, the bravest had ceased to be fighters, while the battle was turned over to
                    the spiritless and the fearful. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the
                    tribunes of the soldiers reported' this to Gracchus: that they were not wounding
                    a single enemy standing, but butchering the fallen; and that in the soldier's
                    right hands there were human heads instead of swords, he ordered the command at
                    once given that they should throw away the heads and attack the enemy.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their courage, he said, was sufficiently
                    clear and conspicuous, and for active men freedom would be beyond a doubt.
                    Thereupon the battle Was renewed, and the cavalry also charged the enemy.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Since the Numidians met this charge
                    gallantly and the cavalry battle was no less spirited than that of the infantry,
                    the issue was for the second time made doubtful. While the commanders on both
                    sides heaped abuse, the Roman on the Bruttians and Lucanians, so many times
                    defeated and subdued by their ancestors, the Carthaginian on the Roman slaves
                    and prison-house <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> .soldiers, Gracchus finally
                    declared that they had no reason to hope for freedom, unless on that day the
                    enemy should-be routed and put to flight. <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Those words at last so fired their courage
                    that, as though they were suddenly different men, they raised a shout again and
                    charged the enemy <pb n="p.223"/> with such force that they could no longer be
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    withstood. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At first the front line <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy often applies Roman military terms
                        to the enemy's army. Here <hi rend="italics">signa</hi> suggests a second
                        line somewhat like the Roman <hi rend="italics">principes.</hi> Cf. XXII. v.
                        7 for <hi rend="italics">antesignani.</hi>
                    </note> of the Carthaginians, then the second was in confusion; finally the
                    whole line was forced back. Then it was unmistakeable flight, and fleeing they
                    dashed into their camp in such fright and excitement that no one halted even at
                    the gates or on the wall. And the Romans, pursuing in almost unbroken column,
                    fought an entirely new battle while hemmed in by the enemies' wall. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> There the battle was indeed more hampered in a
                    confined space, but the slaughter was more savage. And they were aided by the
                    captives, who, seizing weapons during the confusion and advancing in a mass,
                    slashed the Carthaginians from the rear and also hindered their flight.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And so out of that great army less than
                    two thousand men, mainly cavalry at that, escaped along with the general
                    himself. All the rest were slain or captured. Captured were also thirty-eight
                    standards. Of the victors about two thousand fell. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> All the booty except the captives was given to the
                    soldiers. Cattle also were excepted, if the owners should identify them within
                    thirty days. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they had returned to camp laden with
                    booty, about four thousand of the slave-volunteers, who had fought with less
                    spirit and had not dashed into the camp with the others, for fear of punishment
                    occupied a hill not far from the camp. The next day they were brought down by
                    military tribunes and arrived after an assembly of the soldiers had been called
                    by Gracchus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There the proconsul first
                    presented military decorations to the old soldiers, to each according to his
                    valour and his part in that battle; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and then
                    he said that, so far as the slave-volunteers <pb n="p.225"/> were concerned, he
                    preferred to have all of them, the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 214</note> . worthy and the unworthy, praised by himself,
                    rather than to have any one of them punished that day; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> that, with the prayer that it might be good and happy and
                    fortunate for the state and for the men themselves, he ordered them all to be
                    free. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At these words they raised a shout with
                    great enthusiasm, and now embracing and congratulating each other, now raising
                    their hands to heaven, they prayed for every blessing for the Roman people and
                    for Gracchus himself. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thereupon Gracchus
                    said: <quote> Before making you all equals by the right of freedom, I wished to
                        stamp not one man of you with the mark of a brave or of a cowardly soldier.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But now, the promise made in the name
                        of the state being already fulfilled, to prevent the loss of every
                        distinction between valour and cowardice, I shall order the names of those
                        who, remembering their refusal to fight, left us a while ago to be reported
                        to me; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and summoning them one by one I
                        shall make them swear that, excepting men who shall have illness as an
                        excuse, they will take food and drink standing only, so long as they shall
                        be in the service. This penalty you will bear with patience, if you will
                        reflect that you could not have been marked with any slighter sign of
                        cowardice. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He then gave the signal to pack baggage, and
                    the soldiers carrying and driving their booty returned with sport and mirth so
                    gaily to Beneventum that they <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> seemed to be
                    returning from a feast on a day of general festivity, not from a battle.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> All the people of Beneventum, having come
                    out <hi rend="italics">en masse</hi> to the gates to meet them, embraced the
                    soldiers, congratulated them, invited them into their houses. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> Feasts had been made ready by all in the atria <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Thus the good things could be seen
                        through the open door, as in XXV. <hi rend="italics"/> xii. 15: <hi
                            rend="italics">apertis ianuis in propatulo epulati sunt.</hi>
                    </note> of <pb n="p.227"/> their houses. To these they invited the soldiers and
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    implored Gracchus to allow the soldiers to feast. And Gracchus did permit them,
                    provided they all feasted in the open, each before the door of his house.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Everything was brought out. Wearing caps
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics"
                            >pilleus</hi> was evidence of freedom, as was the <hi rend="italics"
                            >lana alba.</hi>
                    </note> or white woollen headbands the volunteers feasted, some reclining, and
                    some standing served and ate at the same time. <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                    /> This seemed to deserve the order Gracchus gave on his return to Rome for a
                    representation of that day of festivity to be painted in the Temple of Liberty
                    which his father, with money yielded by fines, caused to be built on the
                    Aventine and dedicated. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The closing
                        words are possibly copied from an inscription on the temple. The father was
                        consul in <date when="-0238">238 B.C.</date>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were going on about
                    Beneventum, Hannibal, after ravaging the territory of Neapolis, removed his camp
                    to Nola. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the consul learned of his
                    approach, summoning Pomponius, the propraetor, with the army which was in camp
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Castra Claudiana;</hi> XXIII. xxxi. 3 and elsewhere.
                        Pomponius must have been relieved of his duties in the North (x. 3). </note>
                    above Suessula, he prepared to advance to meet the enemy and to engage without
                    delay. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He sent Gaius Claudius Nero with the
                    best of the cavalry out by the gate farthest from the enemy in the silence of
                    the night, and commanded him to ride around unseen and follow the enemy's column
                    slowly, and when he saw that the battle had begun, to throw himself upon their
                    rear. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whether it was by losing the way that
                    Nero was unable to carry this out, or from the shortness of the time, is
                    uncertain. After the battle had begun in his absence, the Roman indeed
                    unquestionably had the upper hand; but since the cavalry were not there at the
                    right moment, the <pb n="p.229"/> prearranged plan for the battle was ruined.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcellus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> not venturing to pursue
                    the retreating, gave his men, victorious though they were, the signal to retire.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> More than two thousand of the enemy,
                    however, are said to have been slain that day, of the Romans less than four
                    hundred. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> About sunset Nero, returning with his
                    horses and men exhausted to no purpose by their efforts for a day and a night,
                    without even seeing the enemy, was sternly rebuked by the consul, who went so
                    far as to say that it was his fault that the disaster suffered at Cannae was not
                    paid back to the enemy. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cannae was
                        avenged by this Nero and his colleague Livius at the Metaurus, <date
                            when="-0207">207 B.C.</date> ; XXVII. xlviii f.; xlix. 5. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the next day the Roman went into line of
                    battle, while the Carthaginian, beaten, as he tacitly admitted also, remained in
                    camp. The third day, giving up hope of capturing Nola, an undertaking which had
                    never prospered, he set out in the dead of night for Tarentum, led by a surer
                    hope of its betrayal. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And it was with no less spirit that the Roman
                    state was administered at home than in the field. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The censors, freed from the charge of contracting for
                    public works on account of the emptiness of the treasury, turned their attention
                    to the control of morals and the punishment of vices which had sprung from that
                    war, just as bodies suffering from long illnesses of themselves produce defects.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> First they summoned those who after the
                    battle of Cannae were said to have abandoned the state. The foremost among them,
                    Marcus Caecilius Metellus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For his
                        plan to leave Italy cf. XXII. liii. 5, where his praenomen is Lucius.
                    </note> happened at this time to be quaestor. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Inasmuch as he and the rest of those guilty of the same offence, on being
                    ordered to plead their cases, proved unable <pb n="p.231"/> to clear themselves,
                    the censors gave their verdict <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 214</note> that in conversation and formal speeches they
                    had attacked the state, in order to form a conspiracy to desert Italy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next after them were summoned those who
                    had been too crafty in interpreting the discharge of an oath, —those of the
                    captives who, after setting out and then returning secretly to Hannibal's camp,
                    thought the oath they had sworn, that they would return, had been discharged.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So ten of them pretended to
                        think, XXII. lxi. 8. Another version ( <hi rend="italics">ib.</hi> 4 and
                        lviii. 8) had only a single perjurer. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From these men and those mentioned above their
                    horses, if they had such from the state, were taken away, and all were ejected
                    from their tribes and made <hi rend="italics">aerarii.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Transfer to one of the four city
                        tribes was a degradation, but, since the reform of <date when="-0312">312
                            B.C.</date> , <hi rend="italics">aerarii</hi> ( <quote>taxpayers
                            only</quote> ) were allowed to vote and serve in the army. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And the diligence of the censors did not
                    confine itself to regulating the senate and the order of the knights. From the
                    lists of the younger men they culled the names of all who during four years had
                    not served, without having had a legitimate exemption from the service or ill
                    health as an excuse. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And of these above two
                    thousand names were placed on the list of the <hi rend="italics">aerarii,</hi>
                    and they all were ejected from their tribes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    And to this relentless stigma of the censors was added a severe decree of the
                    senate that all of those whom the censors had stigmatised should serve on foot
                    and be sent to Sicily, to the remnant of the army of Cannae. For this class of
                    soldiers the term of service was not at an end until the enemy should be driven
                    out of Italy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Since the censors on account of the emptiness
                    of the treasury now refrained from letting contracts for the maintenance of
                    temples and the furnishing of horses <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The two-wheeled vehicles ( <hi rend="italics">tensae</hi> ) which carried
                        attributes of the Capitoline deities in procession to the Circus were
                        usually drawn by four horses. </note> used in religious processions and for
                    similar <pb n="p.233"/> matters, those who had been in the habit of such <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> ; bidding
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At sales and the letting of
                        contracts a spear ( <hi rend="italics">hasta</hi> ) symbolised the authority
                        of the state, and gave its name to the proceedings. </note> came in large
                    numbers to the censors, and urged them to take action and let contracts at once
                    for everything, just as if there were money in the treasury; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> that no one would claim his money from the treasury until
                    the war was over. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then came the owners of the
                    slaves Tiberius Sempronius had manumitted at Beneventum, and said they had been
                    summoned by the bank commissioners <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cf. XXIII. xxi. 6. These emergency officials ( <hi rend="italics">triumviri
                            mensarii</hi> ) evidently served for some years; cf. XXVI. xxxvi. 8.
                    </note> to receive the price of their slaves; but that they would not receive it
                    until the war was over. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Such being now the
                    tendency of the people to relieve the poverty of the treasury, funds, first of
                    wards, and then of widows and single women, began also to be turned in; for
                    those who brought in the sums believed that nowhere could they deposit them with
                    a sense of greater safety and honesty than under the guarantee of the state.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Thereafter when anything was purchased or
                    provided for wards and widows and single women, it was paid for by an order of a
                    quaestor. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> This generosity of private citizens
                    spread from the city also even to the camps, so that no knight, no centurion
                    accepted pay, and the man who did accept was reproachfully called a hireling. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius, the consul, had his camp near
                    Casilinum, which was held by a garrison of two thousand Campanians and seven
                    hundred of Hannibal's soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In command was
                    Statius Metius, who had been sent by Gnaeus Magius, of Atella (who was the <hi
                        rend="italics">medix tuticus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXIII. xxxv. 13; XXVI. vi.
                        13.</note> that year), and Metius had armed slaves and plebeians without
                    distinction, in order to <pb n="p.235"/> make an attack upon the Roman camp
                    while the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        214</note> consul was occupied with the siege of Casilinum. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Of all this nothing escaped Fabius. So he sends word to his
                    colleague at Nola that he needs the other army, to face the Campanians while
                    Casilinum was being besieged: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> either Marcellus
                    should leave a suitable garrison at Nola and come in person, or if Nola held him
                    back and there was still danger from Hannibal, he would himself summon Tiberius
                    Gracchus, the proconsul, from Beneventum. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On
                    receiving this message Marcellus left two thousand soldiers as a garrison at
                    Nola, and with the rest of his army came to Casilinum; and upon his arrival the
                    Campanians, who were already bestirring themselves, became inactive. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> So began the siege of Casilinum by the two consuls.
                    Since in this operation the Roman soldiers rashly approaching the walls were
                    receiving many wounds and the undertaking was not successful, Fabius thought
                    that they should give up a small affair which was as difficult as great
                    ventures, and that they must leave the place, since greater matters were
                    impending. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus, saying that, while there
                    were many places which great generals ought not to attack, yet, once the attack
                    has begun, they should not give them up, since reputation has great influence in
                    both directions, carried his point, not to depart while their attempt was
                    unsuccessful. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then while sheds and all other
                    kinds of siege-works and apparatus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Catapults, towers, rams, etc. Movable sheds protected the besiegers. </note>
                    were being brought up, and the Campanians were begging Fabius for permission to
                    go to Capua in safety, after a few had left the city, Marcellus occupied the
                    gate by which they were leaving. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And a general
                    slaughter began, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy touches lightly
                        upon Marcellus' apparent ruthlessness; cf. xxxix. 7. </note> first around
                    the gate, and then, as the troops burst in, <pb n="p.237"/> even inside the
                    city. About fifty Campanians who <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 214</note> had left the city first sought refuge with
                    Fabius and, escorted by his men, reached Capua. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Casilinum was captured, as opportunity offered during the conversations and
                    the delay due to those who begged a promise of protection. And the captives,
                    whether Campanians or of Hannibal's soldiers, were sent to Rome and there
                    imprisoned. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The mass of the townspeople were
                    distributed among the neighbouring communities to be guarded. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time that they left Casilinum
                    after their success, Gracchus in Lucania sent a number of cohorts which had been
                    enlisted in that region, under the command of a prefect of the allies, into the
                    enemy's farm lands to plunder. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hanno attacked
                    as they were widely scattered, inflicting upon the enemy in return a defeat not
                    much less serious than that which he had received near Beneventum, and withdrew
                    hastily into the land of the Bruttians, that Gracchus might not overtake him.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of the consuls, Marcellus returned to
                    Nola, whence he had come, Fabius advanced into Samnium, to lay waste their farms
                    and to recover by force the cities which had revolted. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Samnium around the Caudine Pass was more thoroughly laid
                    waste. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Farms were burned over far and wide,
                    cattle and men carried off as booty. Conpulteria, Telesia and Compsa, towns of
                    that region, were taken by storm, also Fugifulae and Orbitanium in Lucania.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Blanda and, in Apulia, Aecae were taken
                    after a siege. In these cities twenty-five thousand of the enemy were captured
                    or slain, and three hundred and seventy deserters recovered. These were all sent
                    to Rome by the consul, scourged in the Comitium and hurled from <pb n="p.239"/>
                    the Rock. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The Tarpeian Rock of the
                        Capitol (site still disputed).</note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Such were the acts of Fabius within a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> few days,
                    while Marcellus was kept out of employment by illness at Nola. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> And the praetor Quintus Fabius, whose field of duty was
                    around Luceria, stormed the town of Acuca about that time and fortified a
                    permanent camp at Ardaneae. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The same
                        as Herdonea, XXV. xxi. 1; XXVII. i. 3.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> While the Romans were thus employed elsewhere,
                    Hannibal had now reached Tarentum, leaving the most complete devastation
                    wherever he had passed. Not until it had entered the territory of Tarentum did
                    his column begin to advance peaceably. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There
                    they did no damage, and nowhere did they leave the road. And it was plain that
                    this was not due to the self-restraint of the soldiers, but to the commander's
                    orders, for the purpose of winning over the Tarentines. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> But when he had come quite close to the walls, and there
                    was no movement at the first sight of his column, as he supposed there would be,
                    he pitched camp about a mile from the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In Tarentum three days before Hannibal approached the walls, Marcus Livius, who
                    had been sent by Marcus Valerius, the propraetor in command of the fleet at
                    Brundisium, actively enlisted young <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> men,
                    posted guards at all the gates and along the walls, wherever required, and alert
                    by night as well as by day, he left neither the enemy nor wavering allies any
                    opening for an attack. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> After spending some
                    days there to no purpose, Hannibal, since none of the men who had come before
                    him at the Lake of Avernus either came in person or sent a messenger or letter,
                    saw that he had rashly followed empty promises and moved his camp away.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Even then he left the <pb n="p.241"/>
                    territory of Tarentum unharmed, as he did not give <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> up his hope of weakening
                    their loyalty, although his pretended clemency had had no effect as yet. Arrived
                    at Salapia, he brought in grain from the districts of Metapontum and Heraclea;
                    for the summer was now over, and he thought well of the place for winter
                    quarters. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> From it Numidians and Mauri were
                    sent out to plunder in the Sallentine territory <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XXIII. xlviii. 3.</note> and the nearest forests of
                    Apulia. From these places not many other cattle were driven off as booty, but
                    chiefly herds of horses, about four thousand of which were distributed among the
                    cavalry to be broken. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans, inasmuch as a war that was by no
                    means to be despised was breaking out in Sicily, and the death of the tyrant had
                    given energetic commanders to the Syracusans, and had not changed the situation
                    or their feelings, assigned that country to Marcus Marcellus, one of the
                    consuls, as his province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Directly after the
                    assassination of Hieronymus there was at first an uproar among the soldiers at
                    Leontini, and a fierce outcry that they must offer sacrificial vengeance to the
                    dead king in the blood of the conspirators. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Later the frequent mention of restored freedom —a word sweet to the ears —and
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the hope of a largess out of the king's
                    money, and of serving under better generals, also the enumeration of the
                    shameful crimes and still more shameful lusts of the tyrant, so changed their
                    feelings that they allowed the body of the king, whose loss they had just been
                    regretting, to lie unburied. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although the rest
                    of the conspirators had remained, in order to keep their hold on the army,
                    Theodotus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. V. 10 ff</note> and
                    Sosis hastened to <pb n="p.243"/> Syracuse on the king's horses at the greatest
                    possible <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    speed, to surprise his supporters while they were in complete ignorance.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However, not only rumour, than which
                    nothing is swifter in such cases, but also a messenger, one of the royal slaves,
                    had anticipated them. And so Adranodorus had garrisoned the Island <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The oldest quarter of Syracuse,
                        Ortygia. Cf. Cicero's description of the city, <hi rend="italics">Verr.</hi>
                        IV. 117 ff. </note> and the citadel and such other places as were possible
                    and of advantage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By the Hexapylon <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The great northern gate of the Wall of
                        Dionysius; xxxii. 4 ff.; XXV. xxiv. 2f., etc.; v. Appendix. </note> after
                    sunset Theodotus and Sosis rode into the city in the twilight, showing the
                    bloody garment of the king and his diadem. Then riding across the quarter of
                    Tycha, and calling people to freedom and at the same time to arms, they bid them
                    assemble in Achradina. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A quarter that
                        included a level tract, in which lay the market-place (xxii. 12), but not
                        the rocky heights to the northward facing the sea; frequently mentioned
                        below; v. Appendix. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the populace some dash into the streets,
                    some stand before the entrance to their houses, some look out from roofs and
                    windows and keep asking what it means. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Everywhere there are bright lights, every place filled with mingled noises. The
                    armed gather in open spaces; those without arms take down from the Temple of
                    Olympian Jupiter <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On the market-place;
                        built by Hiero; not to be confused with the much older and larger temple
                        west of the Great Harbour; xxxiii. 3; cf. Cicero <hi rend="italics">op.
                            cit.</hi> 119. </note> the spoils of Gauls and Illyrians, presented by
                    the Roman people to Hiero and hung up there by him. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> And this they did with a prayer to Jupiter that he
                    graciously consent to furnish consecrated arms to men arming themselves for
                    their native city, for the temples of the gods, for liberty. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> This crowd also was added to the guard stationed by the
                    leading citizens of the quarters. On the Island Adranodorus had garrisoned,
                    among other positions, the public granaries. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    This place, which was walled about with squared stone and made strong like a
                    citadel, was captured by the young <pb n="p.245"/> men who had been assigned to
                    its defence; and they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 214</note> sent messengers into Achradina to say that the granaries
                    and the grain were under the authority of the senate. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">A council, rather than a senate in the Roman
                        sense.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At daybreak all the people, armed and unarmed,
                    gathered at the Senate House in Achradina. There, standing on the altar of
                    Concord, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This altar and the Senate
                        House were in the market-place; 12f. </note> which had been erected on that
                    spot, one of the leading men, Polyaenus by name, delivered a speech at once
                    outspoken and restrained. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He said that men who
                    had experienced the terrors of slavery and its humiliations had been inflamed
                    against an evil which they knew. As for civil strife, the Syracusans had heard
                    from their fathers, rather than seen for themselves, what disasters it brings.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He praised them for having taken up arms
                    readily, and would praise them the more willingly if they did not use them
                    except when compelled by absolute necessity. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For the present he approved of sending representatives to Adranodorus, to
                    instruct him to put himself under the authority of the senate and people, open
                    the gates of the Island and surrender the citadel. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time, if Adranodorus should try to turn a
                    regency into a kingship of his own, he favoured reclaiming their freedom from
                    Adranodorus much more fiercely than from Hieronymus. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> After this speech representatives were sent directly. Then
                    began a session of the senate, which in the reign of Hiero had indeed continued
                    to be the council of state, yet since his death had not been called together nor
                    consulted about anything until that day. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When
                    the legates reached Adranodorus, he for his part was <pb n="p.247"/> moved by
                    the agreement of the citizens, also by the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> occupation of other
                    quarters of the city, and especially by the betrayal and loss of the most
                    strongly fortified part of the Island. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But his
                    wife Damarata, daughter of Hiero and still puffed up with princely pride and a
                    woman's boldness, called him aside from the legates and reminded him of the
                    oft-repeated utterance of Dionysius the tyrant, that one should leave a tyranny,
                    not on horseback, but dragged by the feet. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It
                    was easy, she said, to give up the possession of an exalted station at any
                    moment one wished; to create and achieve it was difficult and all but
                    impossible. He should gain time for deliberation from the legates. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> He should use it to summon the soldiers from
                    Leontini, and if he should promise them money from the royal treasury everything
                    would be in his power. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These feminine
                    counsels Adranodorus neither wholly rejected nor at once adopted, thinking it a
                    safer way to gain power if for the moment he should yield to the crisis. And so
                    he bade the legates report that he would be under the authority of the senate
                    and people. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On the following day at dawn he opened the
                    gates of the Island and came to the market-place of Achradina. There he mounted
                    the altar of Concord, from which Polyaenus had addressed the people the day
                    before, and began a speech in which he first begged pardon for his hesitation.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For he had kept the gates closed, he
                    said, not that he wished to separate his cause from that of the people, but
                    because he feared what limit there would be to slaughter, when swords should
                    once be drawn; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> whether they would be content
                    with the death of the tyrant, which would be sufficient to secure freedom, <pb
                        n="p.249"/> or on the other hand every one who either by blood <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> or
                    marriage or certain duties was connected with the palace would be slain, as
                    being chargeable with another's guilt. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After
                    he observed that those who had freed their native city wished also to keep her
                    free, and that the common good was the aim of all, he had not hesitated to
                    surrender to the city his own person and in addition all that had been confided
                    to his honour and protection, since the man who had given that charge had been
                    destroyed by his own madness. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Turning then to
                    the assassins of the tyrant and addressing Theodotus and Sosis by name, he said:
                        <quote> It is a memorable deed that you have done. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> But believe me, your glory is but begun, not yet
                        finished, and unless you provide for peace and harmony there remains a very
                        great danger that this may be the funeral of the liberated state. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech he laid the keys of the
                    gates and those of the royal treasure at their feet. And they, dismissed from
                    the assembly and happy that day at least, with their wives and children gave
                    thanks at all the temples of the gods. On the next day elections for the naming
                    of magistrates were held. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Among the first so
                    named was Adranodorus, the rest largely assassins of the tyrant. Two who were
                    not even present, Sopater and Dinomenes, were elected. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> These, hearing what had been done at Syracuse, brought the
                    royal treasure that was at Leontini to Syracuse and turned it over to treasurers
                    elected for that very purpose. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The money that
                    was on the Island was also transferred to Achradina. And that part of the wall
                    which shut off the Island from the rest of the city by a needlessly strong
                    fortification was thrown down by common consent. The other <pb n="p.251"/>
                    measures also were in keeping with this trend toward <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> freedom. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hippocrates and Epicydes, on hearing of the
                    tyrant's death, which Hippocrates had wished to keep secret even by slaying the
                    messenger, were deserted by the soldiers and returned to Syracuse, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">For their service under Hieronymus, cf.
                        vii. 1.</note> since that course seemed safest in the circumstances.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There, to avoid going about under
                    suspicion as seeking some opportunity for a revolution, they first came before
                    the magistrates, and then through them before the senate. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They stated that, having been sent by Hannibal to
                    Hieronymus as his friend and ally, they had obeyed the orders of the man to whom
                    their own commander wished them to be obedient. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> They wished to return to Hannibal; but since the way was unsafe while the
                    Romans were at large everywhere in Sicily, they asked the senators to give them
                    some escort to conduct them to Locri <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Cf. i. 2 ff.</note> in Italy. The senate, they said, would gain great
                    favour with Hannibal by a small service. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This
                    request was readily granted; for the senate greatly desired the departure of the
                    king's generals, as men skilled in military art, and, what was more, needy also
                    and daring. But they took no active steps to carry out their wish with the
                    required promptness. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the generals,
                    as young men of military training and familiar with soldiers, at one time in the
                    presence of these, at another among the deserters, the majority of whom were
                    from the crews of the Romans, at another even among the lowest of the people,
                    made charges against the senate and the aristocrats: <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> that they were secretly working and contriving that
                    Syracuse under the guise of a reestablished alliance should be subject to the
                        <pb n="p.253"/> Romans, and that then a faction, that is, a few who <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> supported
                    the renewal of the treaty, should rule. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Ready to hear and believe these charges, a
                    daily larger multitude was flocking to Syracuse and giving not Epicydes only,
                    but also Adranodorus, the hope of a revolution. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The latter was at length wearied by admonitions of his wife: that it was now
                    the time to seize the power, while everything was confused by the new freedom
                    not yet organized; while the soldiers one met were fattened on the king's pay;
                    while generals sent by Hannibal and familiar with the soldiers could aid the
                    undertaking. Accordingly he formed a plot with Themistus, whose wife was Gelo's
                    daughter, and after a few days rashly revealed it to one Aristo, a tragic actor,
                    to whom he had been in the habit of confiding other secrets. This man's family
                    and station were respectable and not tarnished by his artistic profession, since
                    among the Greeks nothing of the sort brings discredit. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> And so thinking that the loyalty he owed to his native city
                    took precedence, he reports the matter to the magistrates. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They, finding from trustworthy information that this was
                    not unfounded, conferred with the older men, placed a guard at the doors on
                    their advice, and when Themistus and Adranodorus had entered the senate, slew
                    them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And after the confusion resulting from
                    an act even more terrible in appearance than in reality, since others were
                    unaware of the reason, they at length secured silence and brought the informer
                    into the Senate House. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He first told
                    everything in order: that the conspiracy had taken its start from the marriage
                    of Gelo's daughter Harmonia, uniting her with Themistus; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> that African and Spanish auxiliaries had been made ready
                    for the <pb n="p.255"/> slaughter of the magistrates and other leading <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> citizens,
                    and the announcement made that their property would be spoil for the assassins;
                    moreover that a force of mercenaries accustomed to the orders of Adranodorus had
                    been provided, to occupy the Island again. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                    then set forth in detail what was to be done, and by whom, and pictured the
                    whole conspiracy manned and armed. And to the senators indeed they appeared to
                    have been slain with as much justice as Hieronymus. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But in front of the Senate House there was shouting by the
                    mixed crowd unacquainted with the situation. Uttering wild threats, they were
                    checked by the corpses of the conspirators before the entrance to the Senate
                    House, in such fear that they silently followed the orderly populace to the
                    assembly. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Sopater was instructed by the
                    senate and his colleagues to speak. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Beginning with their previous life, just as if
                    he were prosecuting them, he charged that every act of violence or impiety
                    committed since the death of Hiero had been done by Adranodorus and Themistus.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For what could Hieronymus, a boy who had
                    hardly reached puberty, have done of his own motion? His guardians and teachers,
                    shielded by the embitterment directed against another, had been the real kings.
                    Accordingly they ought to have perished either before Hieronymus or at least
                    with Hieronymus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But though doomed already and
                    marked for death, they had contrived fresh crimes since the death of the tyrant,
                    at first openly, when Adranodorus, closing the gates of the Island, took over
                    the kingdom as his own inheritance and as owner entered into possession of what
                    he had held as agent: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> again when, betrayed by
                    those who were on the Island, beset by the whole <pb n="p.257"/> body of
                    citizens holding Achradina, he attempted <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> secretly and craftily to
                    win the kingdom which he had sought in vain openly and above board, and could
                    not be won over even by the bestowal of public office. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> For among those who gained liberty for the state, he, a
                    plotter against liberty himself, had been elected a magistrate. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But their autocratic temper was due to their royal
                    consorts, Hiero's daughter married to the one, Gelo's daughter to the other.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Following this statement there arose in
                    all parts of the assembly a shout that none of those women ought to live, nor
                    any one of the family of the tyrants to survive. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> This is the nature of the mass: either it is a humble slave or a haughty
                    master. As for freedom, which is the mean, they know no moderation either in
                    assuming or in keeping it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And angry passions
                    usually do not lack complaisant helpers, to provoke to bloodshed those who are
                    immoderately eager for punishment; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> as in this
                    case the magistrates forthwith proposed a bill-and it was adopted almost before
                    it was proposed-that all members of the royal family should be put to death.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And by order of the magistrates men were
                    sent who put to death Damarata the daughter of Hiero and Harmonia the daughter
                    of Gelo, being the wives of Adranodorus and Themistus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Heraclia was the daughter of Hiero and wife of
                    Zoippus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. v. 7.</note> who was sent
                    as ambassador to King Ptolemy <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Ptolemy
                        IV Philopator, XXIII. x. 11.</note> by Hieronymus and had accepted voluntary
                    exile. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> She, having learned in advance that
                    they were coming to her house also, fled into the chapel of the household gods
                    with her two maiden daughters, her hair dishevelled and her general appearance
                    moving to pity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And in addition were <pb
                        n="p.259"/> her prayers, now by the gods, now by the memory of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> her father
                    Hiero and her brother Gelo, that they should not allow her innocent self to
                    perish by the fire of resentment against Hieronymus. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Nothing had she gained by his reign except the exile of her
                    husband; and while Hieronymus lived, her station had not been so high as her
                    sister's, nor was their situation the same after his death. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> What of it that, if Adranodorus' plans had succeeded, the
                    sister would have reigned with her husband, while she herself and all the rest
                    must be slaves? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If someone should inform
                    Zoippus that Hieronymus had been slain and Syracuse set free, who would have any
                    doubt that he would forthwith board ship and return to his native city?
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> How the hopes of men were disappointed! In
                    his native city, now set free, his wife and children were fighting for their
                    lives, offering what obstacle to freedom and laws? <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> What danger to anyone was there from herself, a lone woman,
                    virtually a widow, and from maidens living as orphans? But they might say that
                    no danger was indeed feared from her, that nevertheless the royal family was
                    hated. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Therefore they should send them far
                    from Syracuse and Sicily and bid them to be carried away to Alexandria, the wife
                    to her husband, the daughters to their father. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> When they paid no attention whatever and shouted not to waste time, she could
                    see some men drawing swords. Then ceasing entreaties for herself, she urgently
                    begged them at least to spare the girls —an age on which even enraged enemies do
                    not lay hands; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that in taking vengeance on
                    the tyrants they should not themselves imitate the crimes which they hated.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> While still speaking, they dragged her
                    away from the altar and cut her throat, <pb n="p.261"/> then turned their attack
                    upon the girls spattered with B.C. 214 their mother's blood. Beside themselves
                    for grief and fear, as though insane, they dashed out of the chapel with such
                    speed that, if there had been any escape to the street, they would have caused a
                    riot throughout the city. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Even as it was, in
                    the limited space of the house, amidst so many armed men, they several times
                    escaped unharmed and tore themselves away from those who tried to hold them,
                    although they had to fight off hands so many and so strong. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> At last exhausted by wounds, after staining everything with
                    their blood, they fell lifeless. The slaughter, in itself pitiful, was made
                    still more pitiful by the coincidence that shortly after came the word that they
                    were not to be put to death, for animosity had suddenly changed to pity.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> From pity then came anger, that such
                    haste to punish had been made, and no chance left for a change of mind or a
                    cooling of anger. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> And so the multitude
                    complained, and to replace Adranodorus and Themistus —for both had been
                    magistrates —they clamoured for an election, which would not prove at all to the
                    liking of the magistrates. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A day was set for the election, and on that
                    day, to the surprise of everybody, one man on the outskirts of the crowd
                    nominated Epicydes, then after him another named Hippocrates, whereupon these
                    shouts were repeated and with evident approval of the multitude. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And the assembly was disturbed by the crowd not only
                    of citizens but also of soldiers, even deserters in large part mingling with
                    them and eager for any change. The magistrates at first ignored them and by
                    postponing delayed matters. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Finally, compelled
                    by the general <pb n="p.263"/> agreement and fearing an uprising, they declared
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    Epicydes and Hippocrates magistrates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And at
                    first the newly elected did not reveal their intentions, although they were
                    indignant that legates had gone to Appius Claudius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Now a legatus of Marcellus; praetor in Sicily the
                        previous year; vi. 4; vii. 8. </note> to sue for a ten days' truce, and
                    that, this being secured, others had been sent to negotiate the renewal of the
                    old treaty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At that time the Roman commander
                    had a fleet of a hundred ships off Murgantia, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A seaport of unknown situation. Another town of the
                        same name was in the interior, to the east of Henna. </note> waiting to see
                    what would be the outcome of the disturbances at Syracuse due to the massacre of
                    the tyrant's family, and to what the new and unwonted freedom would prompt them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About the same time Marcellus was just
                    arriving in Sicily, and the Syracusan ambassadors were sent to him by Appius.
                    After hearing the peace terms, Marcellus thought agreement could be reached, and
                    himself sent ambassadors to Syracuse to treat in person with the magistrates for
                    a renewal of the treaty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And by this time the
                    situation there was by no means so orderly and peaceful. When word was received
                    that a Carthaginian fleet had reached the promontory of Pachynum, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Little more than thirty miles south of
                        Syracuse.</note> Hippocrates and Epicydes, relieved of their fear, kept
                    making the charge, now before the mercenaries, now among the deserters, that
                    Syracuse was being betrayed to the Roman. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                    from the time Appius began to keep ships at anchor at the harbour mouth in order
                    to encourage the men of the other party, the false charges apparently had
                    received strong confirmation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And at first the
                    crowd had even rushed down in disorder to keep them off in case they should be
                    landing. </p>
                <pb n="p.265"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this confused state of affairs it 'was
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    decided to summon the people to an assembly. There while some inclined in one
                    direction, some in another, and an uprising was not far away, Apollonides, one
                    of the leading citizens, made a speech which was well-advised, considering the
                    crisis. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He said that neither the prospect of
                    safety nor that of destruction had ever been nearer to any state. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> For if with one mind they should all incline, whether
                    to the Romans or to the Carthaginians, no state would be in a more highly
                    favoured and happier condition. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If they pulled
                    in different directions, war between Carthaginians and Romans would not be more
                    cruel than that among the Syracusans themselves, since within the same walls
                    each side would have its own armies, its own weapons, its own generals.
                    Accordingly they must make the greatest effort to reach agreement. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Which alliance was the more advantageous was a
                    question decidedly subordinate and of far less weight. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Yet Hiero's authority ought to be followed in choosing
                    allies rather than that of Hieronymus; in other words, a friendship which had
                    proved happy for fifty years should be preferred to one unknown at present and
                    formerly faithless. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For their decision it was
                    also of considerable importance that they could decline the Carthaginians' offer
                    of peace without necessarily waging war with them at once. With the Romans they
                    must straightway have either peace or-war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    less of party passion the speech seemed to have, the greater was its influence.
                    To the magistrates and picked senators they added a military council also.
                    Commanders of units and prefects of auxiliaries as well were ordered to take
                    part in the deliberations. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After the question
                    had been repeatedly debated with <pb n="p.267"/> great contention, finally, as
                    they evidently had no <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 214</note> means of carrying on a war with the Romans, it was decided
                    to make an alliance with them, and to send ambassadors for the ratification. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not many days had elapsed, when ambassadors
                    from Leontini arrived, pleading for a force to defend their territory. The
                    request of this embassy seemed very timely for the purpose of relieving the city
                    of a disorderly and turbulent multitude and of sending away its leaders.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hippocrates as magistrate was ordered to
                    lead the deserters thither. Many of the mercenary auxiliaries followed, making
                    four thousand armed men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That enterprise gave
                    joy both to the senders and the sent; for the one party were given a
                    long-desired opportunity for revolution, and the other rejoiced also to think
                    that the dregs of the city had been drained off. But they relieved the diseased
                    body, so to speak, merely for the moment, only to have it relapse presently into
                    a more serious ailment. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For Hippocrates began,
                    at first with stealthy raids, to ravage lands on the border of the Roman
                    province. Later, when Appius had sent troops to protect the farms of the allies,
                    he made an attack with all his forces upon the unit on, guard duty facing him,
                    and many were slain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcellus, being informed
                    of this, at once sent legates to Syracuse, to say that the promised peace had
                    been broken, and that a reason for war would never be wanting unless Hippocrates
                    and Epicydes should be sent far away, not merely from Syracuse, but from all
                    Sicily. Epicydes, to avoid being present under an accusation brought against his
                    absent brother, or else failing to do his part in provoking war, went likewise
                    to Leontini; and seeing that its citizens were sufficiently <pb n="p.269"/>
                    aroused against the Roman people, began also to <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> estrange them from the
                    Syracusans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For, he explained, the Syracusans
                    had made an alliance with the Romans with the provision that all the states
                    which had been subject to the kings should be under their rule; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> that now they were not satisfied with freedom, without also
                    being lords and masters. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They must therefore
                    report to them that the Lenities likewise thought it right that they should be
                    free, either because it was on the soil of their city that the tyrant fell, or
                    because there for the first time men shouted the summons to liberty, and
                    deserting the king's generals flocked to Syracuse. Accordingly either that
                    clause, he said, must be removed from the treaty, or else an alliance on such
                    terms was not to be accepted. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The multitude
                    was easily persuaded, and when the legates of the Syracusans complained of the
                    slaughter of the <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> Roman guard-post and also
                    bade Hippocrates and Epicydes go away to Locri or wherever they preferred,
                    provided they withdrew from Sicily, the people replied with spirit that they had
                    not instructed the Syracusans to make a treaty for them with the Romans, and
                    that they were not bound by treaties not of their own making. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> This was reported to the Romans by the Syracusans, who
                    stated that the men of Leontini were not subject to their authority; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> and that consequently the Romans would make war upon
                    them without violating the treaty made with Syracuse; also that they would
                    themselves not refuse to give help in the war, on condition that, when reduced
                    to subjection, the Leontini should again be under their authority, as had been
                    settled in the treaty. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcellus, proceeding with his whole army <pb
                        n="p.271"/> to Leontini and summoning Appius also to make an <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> attack
                    from the other side, found such enthusiasm in his soldiers, due to anger aroused
                    by the slaughter of men of the guard while negotiations were pending, that they
                    took the city at the first assault. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Hippocrates and Epicydes, on seeing that the walls were being taken and gates
                    forced, sought refuge with a few men in the citadel. Thence they fled secretly
                    by night to Herbesus. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably
                        between Syracuse and Leontini, perhaps on the Mylas. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Syracusans, who had set out from home in a
                    column of eight thousand men, were met at the river Mylas by a messenger,
                    reporting that the city <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Leontini.</note> had been captured, but for the rest mingling the false
                    with the true: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that a general massacre of
                    soldiers and townspeople had occurred, and no adults, he thought, had survived;
                    that the city had been plundered, the property of the wealthy given away.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On hearing news so terrible the column
                    halted, and in the general excitement the commanders —and they were Sosis and
                    Dinomenes — considered what they should do. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The appearance of well-founded alarm had been lent to the falsehood by the
                    scourging and beheading of deserters, about two thousand men. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> But not one of the Leontinians or of the other soldiers had
                    been injured after the capture of the city; and, except what had been lost in
                    the first confusion of the capture of the city, all their property was being
                    restored to them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And the soldiers,
                    complaining that their comrades had been betrayed to their death, could neither
                    be induced to go to Leontini nor to wait at the same spot for more trustworthy
                    news. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The generals, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">praetores,</hi> having taken the
                        field, are now generals, as repeatedly below. </note> seeing them inclined
                    to mutiny, but that the outbreak would not last long if the leaders in folly
                    should be removed, led the army to Megara: <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On the coast north of Syracuse; destroyed by Marcellus,
                        xxxv. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and then with a few <pb n="p.273"/> horsemen
                    they went themselves to Herbesus, in the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> hope of getting possession
                    of the city by treachery, owing to the general alarm. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When this undertaking disappointed them, they thought they
                    must use force, and moved their camp from Megara the next day, to attack
                    Herbesus with all their troops. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hippocrates
                    and Epicydes, thinking that their plan to put themselves at the mercy of the
                    soldiers, who were in large part used to them and also at that time inflamed by
                    the report of the slaughter of their comrades, was not so much one which at
                    first sight promised safety, as it was the only possible plan in a desperate
                    situation, went out to meet the column. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    first unit happened to be that of six hundred Cretans, who had served under them
                    in the army of Hieronymus and were under obligations to Hannibal, as they had
                    been captured among the Roman auxiliaries at Lake Trasumennus and allowed to go
                    free. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Recognizing them from their standards
                    and the character of their weapons, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >They were archers.</note> Hippocrates and Epicydes, holding out olive
                    branches and in addition the woollen bands of suppliants, implored them to admit
                    them and, having done so, to protect and not betray them to the Syracusans, to
                    be themselves presently surrendered by the same to the Roman people for brutal
                    execution. <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And in fact the Cretans shouted to them to
                    take courage, saying they would share every lot with them. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> During this conversation the standards had halted and the
                    column was being held up. And word had not yet reached the generals as to what
                    was the cause of the delay. When the report that Hippocrates and Epicydes were
                    there did reach them, and down the whole length of the column there was a shout
                    of evident joy over their coming, at once the <pb n="p.275"/> generals made
                    their way at a gallop to the head <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 214</note> of the column. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Asking what a practice, what a breach of discipline, it was on the part of
                    the Cretans to <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> join in conversation with an
                    enemy and to admit the men to their own column without orders from the generals,
                    they ordered them to be arrested and Hippocrates <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Mention of one brother is meant to include the other,
                        Epicydes; xxiv. 1; xxxv. 4. </note> to be put in chains. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Upon that command such an outcry was first raised by the
                    Cretans, and then caught up by others, that it was easy to see that if they took
                    any further steps they would have to fear for themselves. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Troubled and uncertain as to their own situation, they
                    ordered a retreat to Megara, from which they had set out, and sent messengers to
                    Syracuse to report how matters stood. </p>
                <p> While men were inclined to suspect everything, Hippocrates also resorted to a
                    ruse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After sending some of the Cretans to lie
                    in wait by the roads, with the pretence that it had been intercepted, he
                    publicly read a letter written by himself: <quote>The magistrates of Syracuse to
                        the Consul Marcellus.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Only the heading is quoted verbatim,
                        with suppression of the conventional greeting. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Following the customary greeting it was stated
                    that he had been entirely right in sparing no one at Leontini; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> but that the situation of all the mercenary soldiers was
                    the same, and Syracuse would never have peace so long as there were any foreign
                    auxiliaries in either the city or its army. Therefore he should take measures to
                    reduce to submission the men who were encamped at Megara under the command of
                    their own generals, and by their punishment to set Syracuse free at last.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After this had been read, they rushed to
                    arms with such shouting that during the confusion the generals rode away in
                    alarm to Syracuse. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And the mutiny was not
                    quelled even by their flight; but attacks were repeatedly made on the Syracusan
                    soldiers. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.277"/> Nor would they have spared any of them, had not <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> Epicydes
                    and Hippocrates opposed the enraged multitude, not out of pity and a humane
                    intent, but in order not to cut off the hope of their own return, and that they
                    might not only keep the men themselves as <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    loyal soldiers and at the same time hostages, but also win over their relatives
                    and friends, first by so great a service, and then by the personal security.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Since the soldiers would
                        virtually be hostages, to ensure the support of many friends and relatives
                        in the city. </note>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And having learned how empty or faint a
                    breath moves the crowd, they took a soldier from among those who had been
                    besieged at Leontini and bribed him to carry to Syracuse a message in agreement
                    with what had been falsely reported at the Mylas, and by showing <milestone
                        n="15??" unit="section"/> himself to vouch for it and by relating the
                    doubtful as things that he had seen, to inflame men's anger. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This man was not only believed by the common
                    people, but on being admitted to the Senate House, he stirred the senate as
                    well. Some men of consequence openly declared it was very well that the avarice
                    and cruelty of the Romans had been revealed at Leontini; that if they had
                    entered Syracuse they would have done the same things or even more terrible, in
                    proportion to the greater prize for avarice there. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, they all voted that the gates should be closed
                    and the city guarded. But not all were afraid of the same persons or hated the
                    same men. Among the whole military class and a large part of the common people
                    the Roman name was hated. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As for the generals
                    and a few of the best citizens, although they had been misled by the false news,
                    they were nevertheless more circumspect in the face of a danger more immediately
                    impending. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And already Hippocrates <pb
                        n="p.279"/> and Epicydes were at the Hexapylon, and there were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note>
                    communications through intermediaries who were relatives of citizens in the
                    army: that they should open the gates and allow the defence of the city, their
                    common home, against attack by the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By
                    this time one of the gates of the Hexapylon had been opened, and by it they had
                    begun to be admitted, when the generals intervened. And at first by their
                    military authority and by threats, then by using their personal influence to
                    restrain them, finally, when all was without affect, disregarding dignity they
                    prayed them not to betray their native city to former minions of the tyrant and
                    present seducers of the army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the ears of
                    the excited crowd were deaf to all that; and the gates were being forced with no
                    less violence from within than from without, and when all had been forced, the
                    column was admitted through the whole breadth of the Hexapylon. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The generals with the younger citizens flee for refuge to
                    Achradina. The mercenary soldiers and deserters and such royal troops as were at
                    Syracuse swell the column of the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thus
                    Achradina also is taken by assault, and all the magistrates, except those who
                    escaped in the midst of the uproar, are slain. Night put an end to the
                    slaughter. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On the next day slaves were called
                    to wear the cap of freedom <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. xvi.
                        18.</note> and criminals in chains released from prison; and all this
                    assorted multitude elected Hippocrates and Epicydes generals. And Syracuse,
                    after the light of liberty had shone upon it for a short time, had fallen back
                    into its old-time servitude. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these facts were reported to the Romans,
                    the camp was at once removed from Leontini <pb n="p.281"/> to Syracuse.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And, as it happened, legates had <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> been sent
                    by Appius by way of the harbour on a five-banker. The four-banker sent in
                    advance was captured on entering the narrows. The legates barely escaped.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And now there remained no longer any
                    rights even of war, not to say of peace, when the Roman army pitched camp at the
                    Olympium, that is, the Temple of Jupiter, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Westward of the Great Harbour, plainly visible from the
                        Island and from part of Achradina. Near this great temple the Athenians had
                        encamped, as also the Carthaginians, in other sieges. Two columns still
                        stand. </note> a mile and a half from the city. From this place also it was
                    decided to send legates in advance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To prevent
                    their entering the city, Hippocrates and Epicydes and their retinue advanced
                    beyond the gate to meet them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The speaker for
                    the Romans said he was not bringing war, but aid and comfort to the Syracusans,
                    both to those who, escaping from the midst of the slaughter, had sought refuge
                    with the Romans, and to those who, subdued by their fear, were enduring a
                    slavery more shameful, not only than exile, but even than death; and that the
                    Romans would not leave the atrocious slaughter of their allies unavenged.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly, if a safe return to their
                    native city should be open to those who had sought refuge with the Romans, if
                    those responsible for the slaughter should be surrendered and their freedom and
                    laws restored to the Syracusans, there was no need of arms. If those conditions
                    should not be met, the Romans would wage war against every man who caused delay.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In reply Epicydes said that, if their
                    message had been addressed to his colleague and himself, they would have given
                    them an answer. When the Syracusan state should be under the control of the men
                    to whom they came, then let them return. Should they make war, they would find
                    from actual experience that to attack Syracuse was by no means the same as <pb
                        n="p.283"/> to attack Leontini. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So he left
                    the ambassadors and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        214</note> closed the gates. </p>
                <p> Thereupon began the siege of Syracuse at the same time by land and by sea, by
                    land from the side of the Hexapylon, by sea from that of Achradina, the wall of
                    which is washed by the waves. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And because,
                    having taken Leontini by a panic and the first assault, the Romans did not doubt
                    that at some point they would make their way into a city immense and widely
                    scattered, they brought all their equipment for besieging cities up to the
                    walls. <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And an undertaking begun with so vigorous an
                    assault would have met with success if one man had not been at Syracuse at that
                    time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was Archimedes, an unrivalled
                    observer of the heavens and the stars, more remarkable, however, as inventor and
                    contriver of artillery and engines of war, by which with the least pains he
                    frustrated whatever the enemy undertook with vast efforts. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy does not mention Archimedes' celebrity as a
                        mathematician. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The walls, carried along uneven hills, mainly
                    high positions and difficult to approach, but some of them low and accessible
                    from level ground, we reequipped by him with every kind of artillery, as seemed
                    suited to each place. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The wall of Achradina,
                    which, as has been said already, is washed by the sea, was attacked by Marcellus
                    with sixty five-bankers. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The number
                        sixty agrees with Polybius VIII. 4(6). 1.</note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From most <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Most,</quote> since <hi rend="italics">coterie</hi> is contrasted
                        with <hi rend="italics">alias</hi> in § 6 (eight in Polybius). </note> of
                    the ships archers and slingers, also light-armed troops, whose weapon is
                    difficult for the inexpert to return, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Owing to the skill required in using the thong ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >agendum</hi> ). </note> allowed hardly anyone to stand on the wall
                    without being wounded; and these men kept their ships at a distance from the
                    wall, since range is needed for missile weapons. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.285"/> Other five-bankers, paired together, with the inner <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> oars
                    removed, so that side was brought close to side, were propelled by the outer
                    banks of oars like a single ship, <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> and
                    carried towers of several stories and in addition engines for battering walls.
                    To meet this naval equipment Archimedes disposed artillery of different sizes on
                    the walls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Against ships at a distance he kept
                    discharging stones of great weight; nearer vessels he would attack with lighter
                    and all the more numerous missile weapons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Finally, that his own men might discharge their bolts at the enemy without
                    exposure to wounds, he opened the wall from bottom to top with numerous
                    loopholes about a cubit wide, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy
                        seems to mean the width on the inside, while Polybius gives a palm (three
                        inches) as the width of a loophole on the outside (VIII. 7. 6). </note> and
                    through these some, without being seen, shot at the enemy with arrows, others
                    from small scorpions. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As for the ships which
                    came closer, in order to be inside the range of his artillery, against these an
                    iron grapnel, fastened to a stout chain, would be thrown on to the bow by means
                    of a swing-beam projecting over the wall. When this <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Literally the grappling hook; but here, as if the <hi
                            rend="italics">ferret</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">manus</hi> might serve as a name for the entire crane,
                        the reference is in fact to another part, viz. the beam, the after end of
                        which sank to the ground inside the wall when the leaden weight was shifted.
                        Polybius, VIII. 6(8). 1-4, gives a more detailed account. </note> sprung
                    backward to the ground owing to the shifting of a heavy leaden weight, it would
                    set the ship on its stern, bow in air. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then,
                    suddenly released, it would dash the ship, falling, as it were, from the wall,
                    into the sea, to the great alarm of the sailors, and with the result that, even
                    if she fell upright, she would take considerable water. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Thus the assault from the sea was baffled, and all hope
                    shifted to a plan to attack from the land with all their forces. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> But that <pb n="p.287"/> side also had been provided
                    with the same complete <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 214</note> equipment of artillery, at the expense and the pains of
                    Hiero during many years, by the unrivalled art of Archimedes. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The nature of the place <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Evidently meaning the northern face of Etiolate, the
                        great triangle at whose western apex stood the fortress of Burials; cf. XXV.
                        xxiv. 4; ax. 2; v. Appendix. </note> also helped, in that the rock on which
                    the foundations of the wall were laid is generally so steep that not only
                    missiles from a machine, but also whatever rolled down of its own weight fell
                    heavily upon the enemy. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The same circumstance
                    made approach to the wall difficult and footing unsteady. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> So, after a war council, since every attempt was being
                    balked, it was decided to give up the assault and merely by a blockade to cut
                    off the enemy by land and sea from their supplies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile Marcellus set out with about a third
                    of his army to recover the cities which in the unsettled state of affairs had
                    gone over to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Helorus and
                    Herbesus he did recover by their own surrender; Megara he took by assault,
                    destroyed and plundered, to terrify the others and especially the Syracusans.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About the same time also Himilco, who had
                    long kept his fleet off the promontory of Pachynum, landed at Heraclea, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">West of Agrigentum, on the south
                        coast.</note> called Minoa, 25,000 infantry, 3,000 cavalry and twelve
                    elephants, a very much larger force than that with which he had previously kept
                    his fleet off Pachynum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But after Syracuse had
                    been seized by Hippocrates, Himilco went to Carthage and was aided there both by
                    the legates of Hippocrates and by a letter from Hannibal, who said the time had
                    come to recover Sicily in the most honourable manner. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Himilco <pb n="p.289"/> himself, being an influential
                    adviser, present in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        214</note> person, had easily prevailed upon them to send across to Sicily
                    the largest possible forces of infantry and cavalry. Arrived at Heraclea, he
                    recovered Agrigentum within a few days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And
                    the hopes of the other city-states which were on the side of the Carthaginians
                    were so fired to drive the Romans out of Sicily that finally even those who were
                    besieged at Syracuse took courage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And
                    thinking the city could be sufficiently defended by a part of the forces, they
                    so divided the military duties that Epicydes should be in charge of the defence
                    of the city, and Hippocrates, together with Himilco, should carry on the war
                    against the Roman consul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With 10,000 infantry
                    and five hundred horse he set out by night through places unguarded and pitched
                    camp near the city of Acrillae. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">To the
                        west of Syracuse, as was Acrae, xxxvi. 1.</note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As they were fortifying, Marcellus arrived,
                    returning from Agrigentum, which was already occupied, since it was in vain that
                    he had endeavoured to anticipate the enemy by hastening thither. Nothing was
                    farther from his thoughts than that a Syracusan army should meet him there at
                    that time. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, from fear of Himilco
                    and the Carthaginians, being no match for them with the forces he had, he was
                    advancing with all possible alertness and with a column so formed as to meet any
                    emergency. <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The precaution which had been taken against
                    Carthaginians served him, as it happened, against Sicilians. Coming upon them
                    after they had broken ranks and were scattered in the act of pitching camp and
                    mostly unarmed, he overwhelmed all the infantry. The cavalry, after a slight
                    engagement, fled with Hippocrates to Acrae. </p>
                <pb n="p.291"/>
                <p> Marcellus, by that battle having restrained the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> Sicilians inclined to
                    revolt from the Romans, returned to Syracuse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    And a few days later Himilco was joined by Hippocrates and pitched camp by the
                    river Anapus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The small river of
                        Syracuse, emptying into the Great Harbour. Near its mouth was a Roman camp;
                        xxxiii. 3. </note> about eight miles away. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    About the same time it so happened that fifty-five warships of the Carthaginians
                    under Bomilcar sailed from the open sea into the Great Harbour of Syracuse, and
                    also a Roman fleet of thirty quinqueremes debarked the first legion at Panormus.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Now Palermo; the chief city of
                        Carthaginian Sicily, until taken by the Romans in <date when="-0254">254
                            B.C.</date> ; Polybius I. xxxviii. fin. </note> And the war could be
                    considered as now diverted from Italy, so intent were both nations upon Sicily.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Himilco, thinking that the legion which
                    had been landed at Panormus would certainly fall a prey to him on its way to
                    Syracuse, was baffled by its route. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For the
                    Carthaginian led his troops along an inland road, while the legion, escorted by
                    the fleet, made its way along the coast to Appius <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> Claudius, who with a part of his forces had advanced as far
                    as Pachynum <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Probably an error for
                        Pelorum, the north-eastern promontory of Sicily, since, with Agrigentum in
                        the hands of the Carthaginians, the route via the western and southern
                        coasts (much longer in any case) would have been impracticable. </note> to
                    meet it. And so the Carthaginians did not tarry longer near Syracuse. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> On the one hand Bomilcar, lacking confidence in his
                    own ships, since the Romans had a fleet of fully double the number, and at the
                    same time seeing that by useless delay the lack of supplies for the allies was
                    only intensified by his forces, put out to sea and crossed over to Africa.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the other hand Himilco first followed
                    Marcellus to Syracuse to no purpose, in the hope that there might be some
                    opportunity for an engagement before should unite with larger forces. Then, when
                    no such opportunity fell to him, and he <pb n="p.293"/> saw the enemy safe near
                    Syracuse thanks to his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 214</note> fortifications and military strength, fearing to waste time
                    in besieging him in vain and watching the blockade of the allies, he moved his
                    camp away. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> His purpose was to bring up his
                    army to any point to which the hope of revolting from the Romans might call him,
                    and by his presence to give encouragement to those who inclined to support his
                    cause. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Murgantia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. xxvii. 5.</note> was first recovered, after the
                    inhabitants had betrayed the Roman garrison. There a great quantity of grain and
                    supplies of every kind had been accumulated for the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Upon this revolt, feeling was aroused in other
                    city-states, and Roman garrisons were being either driven out of citadels or
                    betrayed by treachery and slain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Henna, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The most commanding city-site in
                        Sicily, with its citadel 3200 ft. above the sea. Described by Cicero <hi
                            rend="italics">in Verr.</hi> IV. 107. Henna was the centre of the
                        worship of Demeter and Persephone; cf. xxxix. 8. </note> perched on a lofty
                    site with cliffs on every side, was not only impregnable from its position, but
                    also had a strong garrison in its citadel and a garrison commander who was
                    certainly no easy prey to plotters. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This was
                    Lucius Pinarius, a man of high spirit and one who gave more weight to
                    precautions against possible deception than to the honour of Sicilians. And at
                    this time the news of so many cities betrayed and in revolt and of so many
                    garrisons destroyed had made him more intent upon guarding against every danger.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly every position had been
                    prepared and provided with guards and sentinels night and day; and the soldier
                    did not leave his arms and his post. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When this
                    was noticed by the leading men of Henna, who had already made an agreement with
                    Himilco to betray the garrison, namely, that the Roman left no opportunity for
                    treachery, they were forced to act openly. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They said that city and citadel ought to be under their own control, if as free
                    men <pb n="p.295"/> they had entered into alliance with the Romans, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> and had
                    not been consigned to custody as slaves. Consequently they said they thought it
                    right that the keys of the gates should be restored to them. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For good allies their loyalty was the strongest bond, and
                    the Roman people and senate would be grateful to them only in case they remained
                    in their friendship willingly and not under compulsion. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> In reply to this the Roman commandant said that he had been
                    placed at his post by his general and had received from him both the keys to the
                    gates and the guarding of the citadel, to keep them, not at his own discretion
                    nor that of the people of Henna, but of the man who had confided them to him.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To leave one's post was among the Romans a
                    capital offence, and fathers had punished that crime with the death even of
                    their own sons. The consul Marcellus was not far away; they should send legates
                    to him who had the right to decide the matter. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> But they said that they would not send them, and asserted that if they
                    accomplished nothing by words, they would seek some means of recovering their
                    freedom. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Upon that Pinarius said that, if
                    they objected to sending to the consul, very well, let them at least give him an
                    assembly of the people, that it might be known whether their demand was that of
                    a few men or of the whole city. They agreed to an assembly on the next day. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Returning from that conference to the citadel,
                    he called his men together and said: <quote> I believe you have heard, soldiers,
                        how in these days Roman garrisons have been beset and overwhelmed by
                        Sicilians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Such treachery you have
                        escaped, thanks first to the favour of the gods, and then to your own
                        courage, by standing guard day and night <pb n="p.297"/> under arms. Would
                        that the remaining time <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 214</note> could be passed without either suffering
                        or committing atrocities! In covert trickery the method of defence is that
                        which we have so far employed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Since the
                        trick does not succeed, they demand back the keys of the gates openly and
                        above board. And the moment we surrender them, Henna will be in the hands of
                        the Carthaginians, and we shall be more cruelly slaughtered here than was
                        the garrison slain at Murgantia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With
                        difficulty I have gained for deliberation one night in which to inform you
                        of the impending danger. At daybreak they are to hold an assembly for the
                        purpose of accusing me and arousing the people against you. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> And so tomorrow Henna will be deluged either with your
                        blood or with that of the Hennensians. If forestalled, you will have no
                        hope, nor any danger if you forestall them. Who first draws the sword will
                        have the victory. Therefore, alert and armed, you will all await the signal.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I shall be in the assembly, and I will
                        kill time in speaking and disputing, until everything is ready. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> When I give the signal with my toga, then do you
                        from all sides raise a shout, attack the crowd, and strike down everyone
                        with the sword; and see to it that no one survives whose violence or
                        treachery can be feared. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Mother Ceres and
                        Proserpina, and all the other gods, above and below, who inhabit this city,
                        these hallowed lakes and groves, I pray that ye attend us with your favour
                        and support, if so be that we are taking this step for the purpose of
                        guarding against treachery, not of practising it. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I should exhort you, soldiers, at greater length if
                        your battle were to be with armed men. Unarmed and off their guard, you will
                        massacre them to your hearts' content. <pb n="p.299"/> And the consul's camp
                        is near; I tell you this that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 214</note> you may have no possible fear from Himilco
                        and the Carthaginians. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Dismissed immediately after this exhortation,
                    they took food and rest. On the following day they were posted in different
                    places, to occupy the roads and close the ways of escape. The majority took
                    their positions above and around the theatre, being already familiar with the
                    sight of an assembly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Roman commandant,
                    being brought before the people by the magistrates, said that right and
                    authority in the matter belonged to the consul, not to himself, and in general
                    the same things he had said the day before. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    And at first insensibly and only a few, presently a larger number, then all, now
                    with one voice kept bidding him to deliver the keys; and when he delayed and
                    postponed, they repeated savage threats and apparently would not further
                    postpone violence, their last resort. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Thereupon the prefect gave the signal with his toga, as had been agreed, and the
                    soldiers, alert and ready long before, dashed down, some of them from above,
                    upon the rear of the assembly with a shout, while others, massed at the exits of
                    the theatre, blocked the way. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The men of
                    Henna, shut up in the cavea, were slain and piled together not only owing to the
                    slaughter, but also by the panic, since they rushed down over each others'
                    heads, and as the unharmed fell upon the wounded, the living upon the dead, they
                    were lying in heaps. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thence the soldiers
                    scattered in every direction, and, just as in a captured city, flight and
                    slaughter were in complete possession, while the wrath of the soldiers was not a
                    whit less intense because they were slaying an unarmed <pb n="p.301"/> crowd,
                    than if equal danger and ardour for the fray <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> were spurring them on.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So by an act, it may have been criminal,
                    it may have been unavoidable, Henna was held. </p>
                <p> Marcellus, without reproving the act, allowed the soldiers to plunder the
                    Hennensians, thinking the frightened Sicilians had been deterred from betraying
                    their garrisons. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And as was natural in the
                    case of a city in the heart of Sicily and famous, whether for the remarkable
                    natural defences of its site, or as hallowed everywhere by the footprints of
                    Proserpina, long ago carried away, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As
                        in Cicero <hi rend="italics">in Verr.</hi> IV. 107 the very place reminds
                        one how Pluto carried off Proserpina from the meadows below Henna. </note>
                    news of the massacre made its way over the whole of Sicily almost in a single
                    day. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And then in truth, since they thought
                    that the abode, not of men only but also of gods, had been desecrated by an
                    atrocious massacre, even those who till then had wavered went over to the
                    Carthaginians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hippocrates thereupon went
                    back to Murgantia, Himilco to Agrigentum, after bringing up their army to Henna
                    to no purpose at the summons of the traitors. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Marcellus returned to Leontini, had grain and other supplies brought into the
                    camp, left a suitable garrison there and came to Syracuse to carry on the siege.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He then relieved Appius Claudius, to sue
                    for the consulship at Rome, and in his place put Titus Quinctius Crispinus in
                    command of the fleet and the old camp. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > Cf. xxxiii. 3; XXV. xxvi. 4. The new winter camp was northwest of
                        Syracuse. </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As for himself, he fortified and built winter
                    quarters five miles from the Hexapylon — Leon they call the place. Such were the
                    events in Sicily up to the beginning of the winter. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same summer the war with King Philip also
                    that for some time had been foreshadowed broke <pb n="p.303"/> out. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Legates came from Oricum <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> In southern Illyria (Albania), at the south end of the
                        bay behind the Acroceraunian Mountains, almost directly opposite Brundisium.
                    </note> to Marcus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        214</note> Valerius, the praetor, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Strictly propraetor; x. 4; xx. 12.</note> who with his fleet was guarding
                    Brundisium and the neighbouring coast of Calabria. They reported that Philip had
                    first sailed up the river with a hundred and twenty small vessels having two
                    banks of oars and attacked Apollonia; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The city, in southern Illyria, and allied with Rome since <date when="-0229"
                            >229 B.C.</date> , lay near the river Aoüs and about seven miles inland,
                        about thirty miles north of Oricum. Later it attracted young Romans pursuing
                        their studies, <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Octavian. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that then, when the undertaking proved
                    slower than he anticipated, had secretly moved his army to Oricum by night; also
                    that that city, situated in a plain and not strong either in walls or armed men,
                    had been taken by assault. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Making this report,
                    they begged him to lend aid and by land and sea to keep an undoubted enemy of
                    the Romans away from the coast cities, which were being attacked for no other
                    reason than that they faced Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Valerius, after leaving a garrison of two thousand soldiers and placing Publius
                    Valerius, his lieutenant, in command of them, with his fleet drawn up and in
                    readiness, while such soldiers as the warships could not accommodate had been
                    placed on transports, came on the second day to Oricum; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and as only a small garrison which the king had left when
                    he withdrew held the city, he recaptured it after slight resistance. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> To it came legates from Apollonia, reporting that
                    they were being besieged because they refused to revolt from the Romans and
                    could no longer withstand the attack of the Macedonians, unless a Roman force
                    should be sent. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Valerius promised to do as
                    they desired, and sent two thousand picked soldiers in <pb n="p.305"/> warships
                    to the mouth of the river <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> the Aoüs. </note> under the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> command of
                    a prefect of the allies, Quintus Naevius Crista, a man of action and an
                    experienced soldier. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He landed his men, sent
                    the ships back to the rest of the fleet at Oricum, his starting-point, led his
                    soldiers at a distance from the river along the road least beset by the king's
                    troops and entered the city by night, so that no one of the enemy was aware of
                    it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The following day they rested, that the
                    prefect might inspect the young men of Apollonia and the arms and resources of
                    the city. The result of that inspection gave him sufficient encouragement, and
                    he learned also from scouts what carelessness and indifference there was among
                    the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thereupon in the silence of the
                    night and without making any noise he went out of the city and entered the
                    enemy's camp, so neglected and open that a thousand men had entered the wall
                    before anyone was aware of it, so it was generally asserted; also, that if they
                    had refrained from slaughter, they could have reached the king's tent.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The slaughter of the men nearest to the
                    gate aroused the enemy. Then such alarm and panic took possession of them all
                    that not only did no one else seize his arms and attempt to drive the <milestone
                        n="13??" unit="section"/> enemy out of the camp, but even the king himself,
                    fleeing almost half-naked, just as he was when awakened, fled to the river and
                    his ships in a garb scarcely seemly even for a common soldier, much less a king.
                    Thither the rest of the disorderly crowd also poured out. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Little fewer than three thousand soldiers were either
                    captured or slain in the camp; a considerably larger number of men were captured
                    than slain. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After plundering the camp the
                    Apollonians carried away the catapults, ballistae and other <pb n="p.307"/>
                    engines which had been provided for a siege of the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> city to Apollonia, in
                    order to defend their walls, if ever a similar situation should arise. All the
                    remaining booty of the camp was left to the Romans. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> When this news reached Oricum, Marcus Valerius at once led
                    his fleet to the mouth of the river, to prevent the king from escaping by ship.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> And so Philip, believing he would not be
                    quite equal to a battle either on land or sea, stranded his ships, set fire to
                    them, and started for Macedonia with an army in large part disarmed and
                    despoiled. The Roman fleet wintered at Oricum under the command of Marcus
                    Valerius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year operations in Spain were
                    chequered. For Mago and Hasdrubal, before the Romans should cross the Ebro,
                    routed immense forces of Spaniards. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And
                    Farther Spain would have revolted from the Romans if Publius Cornelius had not
                    hastily led his army across the Hiberus and arrived in the nick of time, while
                    the allies were still wavering. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first the
                    Romans had their camp at Castrum Album, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Probably modern Alicante, on the coast and northeast of
                        Carthago Nova; built by Hamilcar Barca, who fell in battle there 229- <date
                            when="-0008">8 B.C.</date>
                    </note> noted as the place where the great Hamilcar fell. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The citadel had been fortified and they had previously
                    brought in grain. Yet the country all around was filled with the enemy, and the
                    Roman column had been attacked with impunity by the enemy's cavalry and about
                    two thousand men, either straggling or scattered over the farms, had been slain.
                    The Romans therefore retired from the place to a position nearer peaceful
                    regions and fortified a camp at Victory Mountain. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Situation unknown.</note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thither came Gnaeus Scipio with all his
                    troops, and Hasdrubal the son of Gisgo, making three Carthaginian generals and a
                    complete army; and all three established themselves across <pb n="p.309"/> the
                    river, opposite the Roman camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Publius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> Scipio,
                    who set out secretly to reconnoitre with unencumbered troops, did not escape the
                    notice of the enemy, and they would have overwhelmed him in the open meadows if
                    he had not captured a hill near by. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Even there
                    he was beset, but by the arrival of his brother he escaped a siege. Castulo
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the upper valley of the Baetis
                        (Guadalquivir), on the main road from the Pyrenees to Gades. </note>
                    revolted to the Romans, a strong and famous city of Spain, so closely joined to
                    the Carthaginians by alliance that Hannibal's wife <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Imilce, if Silius Italicus (III. 97 and 106) is
                        correct.</note> was from that place. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginians attempted to capture Iliturgis, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On the left bank of the Baetis, southwest of Castulo;
                        cf. XXIII. xlix. 5, where the form was Iliturgi. </note> because there was a
                    Roman garrison there, and it seemed that they would take the town mainly by
                    starvation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Gnaeus Scipio, to lend aid to the
                    allies and the garrison, set out with an unencumbered legion, passing between
                    their two camps, and after slaying many of the enemy entered the city, and on
                    the following day engaged them in an equally successful sally. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Over twelve thousand men were slain in the two battles,
                    more than a thousand men captured, with thirty-six military standards. So they
                    withdrew from Iliturgis. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then began the siege
                    of Bigerra <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Site unknown.</note> —these
                    also were allies of the Romans —by the Carthaginians. Gnaeus Scipio on his
                    arrival raised the siege without an engagement. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereupon the Carthaginian camp was removed to
                    Munda, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Near Corduba. This is the
                        first mention of Caesar's Munda; probably Montilla. </note> and the Romans
                    promptly followed them thither. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There they
                    fought in pitched battle for about four hours, and though the Romans were
                    winning a brilliant victory, the signal for recall was given, because Gnaeus
                    Scipio's thigh had been <pb n="p.311"/> pierced by a light javelin, and fear
                    that the wound <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        214</note> might prove fatal had seized the soldiers around him. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> But there was no doubt that, if this delay had not
                    occurred, the Carthaginian camp could have been captured that day. Already not
                    only soldiers but the elephants also had been driven even up to the wall, and
                    just as they crossed the trenches thirty-nine elephants were struck down by
                    heavy javelins. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In this battle also about
                    twelve thousand men are said to have been slain, about three thousand captured,
                    with fifty-seven military standards. The Carthaginians then retired to the city
                    of Aurinx, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Perhaps the same as
                        Orongis, XXVIII. iii. 2.</note> and the Roman followed, to threaten men
                    already terrified. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There Scipio again engaged,
                    being carried into battle-line in a litter, and the victory was not to be
                    questioned. Less than half as many of the enemy as before, however, were slain,
                    because fewer men had survived to fight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But,
                    as Mago was sent by his brother to recruit soldiers, a race adapted by nature to
                    renew wars and to make fresh preparations for them soon refilled the army and
                    gave them the spirit to essay another conflict. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The soldiers were mostly Gauls, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        From Celtic tribes already established in Spain, even in the southwest.
                    </note> and they fought with the same spirit as their predecessors for the side
                    which had been beaten so many times within a few days, and with the same result.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> More than eight thousand men were slain,
                    and not much less than a thousand captured, also fifty-eight military standards.
                    And the spoils were largely Gallic, golden collars and armbands —a great number
                    of them. Also two conspicuous princes of the Gauls —Moeniacoeptus and Vismarus
                    were their names <pb n="p.313"/> —fell in that battle. Eight elephants were
                    captured, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        214</note> three slain. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The situation in Spain being so favourable,
                    the Romans came at last to be ashamed that the town of Saguntum, which was the
                    cause of the war, had been by that time seven years <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy's own chronology would make it four complete
                        years; XXI. vii. ff.; xv. 5; XXIV. ix. 7. </note> in the power of the
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> enemy. Accordingly the Carthaginian
                    garrison was driven out by force, and recovering the town the Romans restored it
                    to its former inhabitants —such of them as the violence of war had <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> spared. And as for the Turdetani, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXI. vi. 1. Better known is the
                        tribe of the same name in southern Baetica. </note> who had brought on the
                    war between Saguntum and the Carthaginians, they reduced them to subjection,
                    sold them under the garland and destroyed their city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the events in Spain in the
                    consulship of Quintus Fabius and Marcus Claudius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> At Rome, immediately after the newly elected tribunes of
                    the plebs had entered upon office, a day was set by Marcus Metellus, a tribune
                    of the plebs, for the censors Publius Furius and Marcus Atilius to appear at the
                    bar of the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In his quaestorship the
                    year before they had taken away his horse, removed him from his tribe and made
                    him an aerarian on account of the conspiracy formed at Cannae to desert Italy.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. xviii. 3 and 6; XXVII. xi.
                        12. The scene was Canusium, after Cannae. </note> But by the aid of nine
                    tribunes they were forbidden to plead their cause while in office and were
                    released. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From completing the ceremony of
                    purification they were prevented by the death of Publius Furius. Marcus Atilius
                    abdicated his office. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For the consulship the election was conducted
                    by Quintus Fabius Maximus, the consul. Elected consuls, both in absence, were
                    Quintus Fabius Maximus, the consul's son, and Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus, the
                    latter for the second time. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two men <pb
                        n="p.315"/> who were at the time curule aediles, Publius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 214</note> Sempronius
                    Tuditanus and Gnaeus Fulvius Centumalus, were made praetors, and with them
                    Marcus Atilius and Marcus Aemilius Lepidus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Tradition has it that at the festival given that year by the curule aediles four
                    days had dramatic performances for the first time. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The aedile Tuditanus was the man who at Cannae, when others
                    were paralyzed by fear in such a disaster, led his men through the midst of the
                    enemy. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XXII. 1. 6 ff.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These elections being completed, the consuls
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note>
                    designate were summoned to Rome, as proposed by Quintus Fabius, the consul,
                    entered upon office and consulted the senate in regard to the war and the
                    provinces, their own and those of the praetors, and as to the armies which they
                    should respectively command; <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/> and the
                    provinces and armies were divided as follows: the war with Hannibal was assigned
                    to the consuls, and two armies, one which Sempronius himself, and the other
                    which Fabius had commanded as consul. These were of two legions each. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Marcus Aemilius, the praetor to whom fell
                    jurisdiction in cases involving foreigners, was to assign his judicial function
                    to his colleague Marcus Atilius, the city praetor, and have Luceria as his
                    province, and two legions which Quintus Fabius, who was now consul, had
                    commanded as praetor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To Publius Sempronius
                    Ariminum fell as his assignment, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Gallia was the more recent name of this <quote>province,</quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">ager Gallicus</hi> in x. 3. </note> to Gnaeus Fulvius,
                    Suessula, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> With the important Roman
                        camp near it, the <hi rend="italics">castra</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">Claudiana;</hi> xvii. 2; xlvii. 12; XXIII. xxxi. 3.
                    </note> likewise with two legions in each case, so assigned that Fulvius should
                    take with him the legions at the city, and Tuditanus take over from Marcus
                    Pomponius his legions. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Commands and
                    assignments were continued as follows: for Marcus Claudius Sicily, with the <pb
                        n="p.317"/> boundaries which Hiero's kingdom had had; for <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> Publius
                    Lentulus, as propraetor, the old province; for Titus Otacilius the fleet; and
                    for them new armies were not added. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So also
                    for Marcus Valerius Greece and Macedonia, with the legion and the fleet which he
                    had; for Quintus Mucius Sardinia, with its old army —there were two legions; for
                    Gaius Terentius one legion which he already commanded, and Picenum. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> It was further ordered that two city legions should
                    be enrolled, also twenty thousand allies. With these generals, these forces,
                    they defended the Roman empire at the same time against many wars, either
                    already begun or foreshadowed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls, after enrolling two legions for
                    the city and enlisting recruits to reinforce the others, before setting out from
                    the city made expiation for the prodigies which had been reported. The wall and
                    gates at... <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and at Aricia even the temple of
                    Jupiter had been struck by lightning. And for eyes and ears there were other
                    illusions, accepted as real: that in the river at Tarracina forms of warships
                    which had no existence had been seen; and that in the temple of Jupiter
                    Vicilinus, in the territory of Compsa, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > Cf. XXIII. i. 1. In that southern part of Samnium Jupiter had the rare
                        epithet Vicilinus. </note> there was a sound of clashing arms; and that the
                    river at Amiternum ran with blood. These portents being expiated according to a
                    decree of the pontiffs, the consuls set out, Sempronius for Lucania, Fabius for
                    Apulia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The father came as his son's
                    lieutenant to the camp at Suessula. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While the
                    son was advancing to meet him and the lictors out of respect for the father's
                    dignity were silent as they preceded the consul, the old man rode past eleven
                    fasces. And not until the consul had ordered the last lictor to take notice and
                    the latter had called <pb n="p.319"/> out the order to dismount, did the father
                    leap to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        213</note> ground and say: <quote>I wished to find out, son, whether you
                        were quite aware that you are consul.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A famous story. Gellius (II. ii. 13)
                        gives the brief version of Claudius Quadrigarius. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To that camp came Dasius Altinius of Arpi
                    secretly by night with three slaves, promising that if rewarded he would betray
                    Arpi. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In northern Apulia, east of
                        Luceria and not far from the Adriatic; cf. iii. 16; xii. 3, 5; XXIII. xlvi.
                        8. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When Fabius brought the matter before the
                    council, the others thought that as a deserter he should be scourged and put to
                    death, a waverer and an enemy to both sides, who after the disaster at Cannae,
                    as if loyalty should side with success, had gone over to Hannibal and dragged
                    Arpi into revolt. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But now, because, contrary
                    to his expectation and his wishes, the Roman state seemed to be springing up
                    again, as it were from the roots, he was promising to present the betrayed with
                    a new betrayal, and always taking part with one side, but with the other in
                    heart, faithless as an ally, inconstant as an enemy. To the betrayers of Falerii
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. V. xxvii. 2 ff.</note> and of
                    Pyrrhus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This story was told in the
                        lost XIIIth book (cf. <hi rend="italics">Epit.</hi> ). </note> he should be
                    added as a third example to deserters. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the
                    contrary the consul's father Fabius said that men were forgetting the situation,
                    when they exercised free judgment in each individual case in the midst of the
                    heat of war, as though in peace, the result was that, although <milestone
                        n="5??" unit="section"/> the thing to be done and to be borne in mind was
                    rather to prevent any allies-if this was somehow possible from abandoning the
                    Roman people, they were not bearing that in mind. On the contrary, they were
                    saying that, if a man came to his senses and turned his eyes to the previous
                    alliance, he ought to be made a <pb n="p.321"/> warning example. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> If then it was permissible to leave <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> the
                    Romans, but not to return to them, who could doubt that soon the Roman state,
                    despaired of by the allies, would see the whole of Italy joined together by
                    Carthaginian treaties? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For himself, however,
                    he was not the man to think that any trust should be placed in Altinius, but
                    would follow a middle course. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He thought it
                    best, namely, that Altinius should not be treated as either enemy or ally for
                    the present, that under qualified arrest he should be guarded for the duration
                    of the war in some loyal city-state not far from the camp. When the war was over
                    they should then deliberate whether his previous defection deserved punishment
                    more than his present return merited pardon. They agreed with Fabius, and the
                    man was turned over to representatives of Cales, himself and his companions.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And it was ordered that the gold —and the
                    weight of it was considerable —which he had then brought with him should be kept
                    for him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At Cales he was free to go about by
                    day followed by guards, at night confined and watched by them. At Arpi it was in
                    his house that he was first missed and search for him began. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Then the report spreading through the city caused the usual
                    commotion when a leading man is missing, and for fear of a rebellion they at
                    once sent messengers. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I,e.</hi> to Hannibal. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian was by no means displeased
                    at this news, since he had long regarded the man himself with suspicion, as
                    unsettled in his loyalty, and also he now had an excuse for taking possession of
                    the property of a man of such wealth and selling it. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> But that men might believe he was yielding to anger rather
                    than greed, he added cruelty also to avarice, that is, he summoned <milestone
                        n="14??" unit="section"/> the wife and children to the camp, and, <pb
                        n="p.323"/> after investigating first the flight of Altinius, then <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> how much
                    gold and silver had been left in his house, now fully informed, he burned them
                    alive. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius setting out from Suessula first pressed
                    the siege of Arpi. There he pitched his camp at a distance of about five hundred
                    paces, and after observing the situation of the city and the walls at close
                    range, he decided to attack just at that part of the city which was best
                    defended by walls, because he saw that that was the most carelessly guarded.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He assembled everything useful for siege
                    operations, selected from the entire army the pick of the centurions, and placed
                    tribunes who were brave men in command of them. And he assigned them six hundred
                    soldiers —all that seemed necessary —and ordered them to carry ladders to that
                    place, when the trumpet should sound for the fourth watch. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There was a low, narrow gate there, as the street, leading
                    through a deserted part of the city, was not much frequented. He ordered them
                    first to climb over the wall by means of their ladders, and then to open that
                    gate from the inside, or else break down the bars, and then, holding a part of
                    the city, to give the signal on a trumpet for the rest of the troops to move up.
                    He would have everything ready and in order. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    These commands were carried out with spirit, and a circumstance which seemed
                    likely to hamper action proved of the greatest help to secrecy. Heavy rain
                    beginning at midnight forced the guards and sentries to slip away from their
                    posts and run to cover. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And the sound, at
                    first of a heavier shower, prevented the noise they made in forcing the gate
                    from being heard clearly, and then, gentler and more monotonous as they
                    listened, it lulled a great many <pb n="p.325"/> of the men to sleep. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Once in possession of the gate, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> they ordered the
                    trumpeters, posted at equal intervals along the road, to sound, in order to
                    summon the consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This done according to
                    agreement, the consul orders the standards to be carried out of the camp, and a
                    little before daylight enters the city through the gate they had forced. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not until then were the enemy aroused, as the
                    noise of the rain was now lessening and daylight approaching. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In the city there was a garrison of Hannibal's, about five
                    thousand armed men, and the citizens of Arpi also had armed three thousand men.
                    These were the first troops with which the Carthaginians, to prevent any
                    treachery in the rear, confronted the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    They fought at first in darkness and in narrow streets. The Romans gained
                    possession not only of the streets but also of the houses nearest to the gate,
                    that they might not be attacked and wounded from above. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Thereupon some Arpini and Romans recognized each other and
                    then began conversations. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans asked
                    what the Arpini meant, for what offence on the part of the Romans, or for what
                    service on the part of the Carthaginians they, although Italians, were waging
                    war for foreigners and barbarians against their old allies the Romans, and
                    making Italy a tributary and a taxpayer to Africa. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Arpini pleaded as excuse that in complete ignorance
                    they had been sold by their leading citizens to the Carthaginian and captured
                    and overpowered by a few men. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With that
                    beginning larger groups conversed with larger. Finally the magistrate of Arpi
                    was escorted by fellowcitizens to the consul, and after promises had been given
                    in the midst of standards and battle-lines, the <pb n="p.327"/> Arpini suddenly
                    fought for the Romans, turning their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 213</note> weapons against the Carthaginians. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The Spanish troops also, hardly fewer than a thousand
                    men, after making no other terms with the consul than that the Punic garrison be
                    allowed <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> to go without injury, brought their
                    standards over to the consul. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The gates were
                    opened for the Carthaginians, they were allowed to leave, as promised, and came
                    unharmed to Hannibal at Salapia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Arpi, with
                    the loss of no man but a single veteran traitor and recent deserter, was
                    restored to the Romans. To the Spaniards double rations were ordered to be
                    issued, and the state repeatedly availed itself of their brave and faithful
                    service. </p>
                <p> While one consul was in Apulia, the other <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> Gracchus; xliv. 9. </note> in Lucania, a
                    hundred and twelve noble Campanian horsemen, setting out from Capua, with
                    permission of the magistrates, under pretext of plundering the enemy's country,
                    came to the Roman camp above Suessula. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They
                    told the guards outside who they were; that they wished to speak with the
                    praetor. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Gnaeus Fulvius was in command of the
                    camp, and on being informed, he ordered that ten of their number be disarmed and
                    brought to him. After he had heard their demands —and they made no other request
                    than that upon the recovery of Capua their property should be restored to them,
                    they were all taken under his protection. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And
                    the other praetor, Sempronius Tuditanus, took the town of Atrinum <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Situation unknown.</note> by storm. More
                    than seven thousand men were captured and a considerable amount of coined copper
                    and silver. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> At Rome a terrible fire lasted
                    two nights and a day. Everything between the Salinae and Porta Carmentalis was
                    levelled to the ground, <pb n="p.329"/> including the Aequimaelium and Vicus
                    Iugarius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The devastated area was
                        that along the river from the Aventine to the Capitoline, including part of
                        the southeast slope (Aequimaelium) of the latter, and the street (Vicus
                        Iugarius) leading to the Forum. The temples mentioned were near the Tiber
                        and close together; cf. XXXIII. xxvii. 4. </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> also the
                    Temples of Fortune and Mater <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Matuta. Outside
                    the gate also the fire spread to a distance and destroyed many buildings sacred
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Among these was the Temple of
                        Spes, one of three in the Forum Holitorium, outside the wall; XXI. lxii. 4;
                        XXV. vii. 6. </note> and profane. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same year Publius and Gnaeus Cornelius, in
                    consequence of their success in Spain and their recovery of many old allies and
                    the addition of new allies, enlarged their hopes in the direction of Africa as
                    well. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was Syphax, king of the Numidians,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi> of the western Numidians, the Masaesulians, in
                        Algeria and Oran; XXVIII. xvii. 5. </note> who had suddenly become an enemy
                    of the Carthaginians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To him they sent three
                    centurions as legates, to establish friendship and alliance with him, and to
                    promise that if he should continue to embarrass the Carthaginians by war, it
                    would be acceptable to the senate and the Roman people, and they would endeavour
                    to return the favour at the right moment and with generous interest. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This embassy pleased the barbarian, and he conferred
                    with the ambassadors on the conduct of the war; and hearing what was said by
                    experienced soldiers, he noted, from comparison with so well-ordered a system,
                    how many things he did not know himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then,
                    as the first act befitting good and faithful allies, be begged that two of the
                    legates might report to their generals, and one remain with him as instructor in
                    tactics. He said the Numidian nation was inexpert in infantry warfare, of
                    service only as horsemen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This was the way
                    their ancestors from their earliest history had waged war, thus they had <pb
                        n="p.331"/> themselves been trained from boyhood. But he <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> had an
                    enemy who relied upon infantry battles, and if he wished to be a match for him
                    in military strength he too must acquire infantry. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And for that purpose his kingdom was supplied with men in
                    great numbers, but they did not understand the art of arming and equipping them
                    and placing them in battle-line. Everything was formless and unmethodical, as if
                    a mob had been gathered by chance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The legates
                    replied that for the present they would do as he desired, after receiving his
                    pledge to send back the man at once, if their generals should not approve of
                    their action. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Quintus Statorius was the name
                    of the one who remained with the king. With the two Romans the king sent three
                    legates from the Numidians to Spain, to receive confirmation from the Roman
                    generals. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He further instructed them at once
                    to persuade Numidians who were auxiliaries in the forces of the Carthaginians to
                    desert them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And Statorius out of the mass of
                    young men enrolled infantry for the king, organized them almost in the Roman
                    manner, taught them in formation and evolution to follow standards and keep
                    their ranks, and to such an extent accustomed them to fortifying and other
                    regular <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> duties of the soldier that in a
                    short time the king had as much confidence in his infantry as in his cavalry,
                    and in a regular engagement in formal array on level ground he defeated the
                    Carthaginian enemy. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans also in Spain
                    profited greatly by the coming of the king's representatives. For upon the news
                    of their arrival desertions by the Numidians began to be frequent. </p>
                <p> Thus began the friendship of the Romans with Syphax. When the Carthaginians
                    learned of the <pb n="p.333"/> matter they at once sent legates to Gala, who
                    reigned <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note>
                    in the other part of Numidia, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        eastern part, adjoining Carthaginian territory. Cirta (Constantine) was
                        Syphax's capital, until it fell to Masinissa in <date when="-0203">203
                            B.C.</date> ; XXX. xii. </note> his people being called the Maesulians.
                        <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Gala had a son Masinissa, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Who fought against the Romans in Spain
                        down to the time of Gala's death in <date when="-0206">206 B.C.</date> , and
                        then became an ally of Rome, and a friend of Scipio. At present he must have
                        been nearer twenty-seven, since he died in <date when="-0149">149
                            B.C.</date> at 92 ( <hi rend="italics">Epit.</hi> 48 fin.; cf. 50).
                    </note> seventeen years old, but a young man of such promise that even then it
                    was evident that he would make the kingdom larger and richer than what he had
                    received. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The legates stated that, inasmuch as
                    Syphax had attached himself to the Romans, in order, through alliance with them,
                    to be more powerful against the kings and peoples of Africa, it would be well
                    for Gala too to attach himself as soon as possible to the Carthaginians, before
                    Syphax should cross into Spain or the Romans into Africa. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Syphax could be surprised, they said, while he had as yet
                    no advantage from his treaty with the Romans except the name. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They easily persuaded Gala to send an army, as his son was
                    begging for the command; and reinforced by the Carthaginian legions, Masinissa
                    defeated Syphax in a great battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thirty
                    thousand men are said to have been slain in that battle. Syphax with a few
                    horsemen fled from the field to the Maurusian Numidians, who live far away, near
                    the Ocean opposite Gades. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And as the
                    barbarians on hearing of him flocked together from all sides, he soon armed
                    immense forces with which to cross into Spain, separated only by a narrow
                    strait. But Masinissa came with his victorious army, and there by himself,
                    without any help from the Carthaginians, he carried on war against Syphax with
                    great distinction. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.335"/>
                <p> In Spain nothing notable occurred except that the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 213</note> Roman commanders attracted
                    to their side the young men of the Celtiberians at the same pay at which these
                    had made an agreement with the Carthaginians, and more than three hundred
                    Spaniards of the highest rank were sent to Italy to win over their
                    fellow-countrymen who were among Hannibal's auxiliaries. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> This is the only occurrence of that year in Spain that is
                    worthy of record, since the Romans had no mercenary soldiers in their camps
                    previous to the Celtiberians whom they had at that time. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
