<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On Behalf of King Deiotarus </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO IN BEHALF OF KING DEIOTARUS. ADDRESSED TO CAIUS
                CAESAR.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>This speech, like those for Marcellus and Ligarius, was addressed to Caesar.
                    Deiotarus was king of Galatia, and during Cicero's pro-consulship in Cilicia he
                    had formed a friendship with him, and had been of great assistance to him in his
                    campaign against Pacorus and the Parthians. Having been an adherent of Pompey,
                    he had already been deprived of a considerable part or his dominions by Caesar,
                    and he was now accused by his grandson, who was aware of Caesar's inveterate
                    dislike to him, of having formed a design against Caesar's life four years
                    before, when he entertained him in his palace on his return from Egypt. It is
                    probable that Caesar was aware of the groundlessness of the charge, but
                    countenanced it, and allowed it to be brought before him, in the hopes of
                    finding a pretext for stripping the king of all the rest of his dominions. </p>
                <p>Brutus espoused Deiotarus's cause very warmly, and went towards Spain <pb n="484"
                    /> to meet Caesar, and made him a most earnest address in favour of Deiotarus. </p>
                <p>The present trial was held in Caesar's house, and Cicero proved the king's
                    innocence so completely that he was unable to condemn him; but, as he would not
                    acquit him, he adjourned the further consideration of the matter till he himself
                    could go into the East and investigate the affair on the spot. </p>
                <p>This speech was delivered in the year of Caesar's fourth consulship the year
                    before he was killed.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>In all causes of more than ordinary importance, O Caius Caesar, I am accustomed, at
                the beginning of my speech, to be more vehemently affected than either common custom
                or my own age appears to require. And in this particular cause I am agitated by so
                many considerations, that in proportion as my fidelity to my friend inspires me with
                zeal to defend the safety of king Deiotarus, in the same proportion do my fears take
                away from my ability to do so. In the first place, I am speaking in defence of the
                life and fortunes of a king; and although there is no particular injustice in such a
                fact, especially when it is oneself who is in danger yet it is so unusual for a king
                to be tried for his life, that up to this time no such thing has ever been heard of.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the second place, I am compelled now to
                defend against a most atrocious accusation that very king whom I, in common with all
                the senate, used formerly to extol on account of his uninterrupted services towards
                our republic. There is this further consideration, that I am disturbed by the
                cruelty of one of the prosecutors, and by the unworthy conduct of the other. </p>
            <p>O cruel, not to say wicked and impious, Castor! a grandson, who has brought his
                grandfather into danger of his life, and has caused that man to dread his youth,
                whose old age he was bound to defend and protect; who has sought to recommend his
                entrance into life to our favour by impiety and wickedness; who has instigated his
                grandfather's slave, whom he corrupted by bribes, to accuse his master, and has
                carried him away from the feet of the king's ambassadors. </p>
            <p><milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But when I saw the countenance and heard the words
                of this runaway slave, accusing his master,—his absent master,—his master, who was a
                most devoted friend to our republic,—I did not feel so much grief at the depressed
                condition of the monarch himself, as fear for the general fortunes of every one. For
                though, according to the usage of our ancestors, it is not lawful to examine a slave
                as a witness against his master, not <pb n="485"/> even by torture,—in which mode of
                examination pain might, perhaps, elicit the truth from a man even against his
                will,—a slave has arisen, who, without any compulsion, accuses him against whom he
                might not legally say a word even on the rack. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="4" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>This thing also, O Caius Caesar, at times disturbs me; which, however, I cease to
                fear when I come to a complete recollection of your disposition. For in principle it
                is an unjust thing, but by your wisdom it becomes a most just one. For it is a
                serious business (if you consider the matter by itself) to speak concerning a crime
                before that man against whose life you are accused of having meditated that crime;
                for there is hardly anybody who, when he is a judge in any matter in which his own
                safety is at stake, does not act with more partiality towards himself than towards
                the accused person; but, O Caius Caesar, your admirable and extraordinary natural
                virtue to a great extent releases me from this fear. For I am not so much afraid
                what you may wish to decide with respect to king Deiotarus, as I am sure what you
                wish to decide in all other cases. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>I am affected, also, by the unusual circumstance of the trial in this place; because
                I am pleading so important a cause—one, the fellow of which has never been brought
                under discussion—within the walls of a private house; I am pleading it out of the
                hearing of any court or body of auditors, which are a great support and
                encouragement to an orator. I rest on nothing but your eyes, your person and
                countenance; I behold you alone; the whole of my speech is necessarily confined to
                you alone. And if those considerations are very important as regards my hope of
                establishing the truth, they for all that are impediments of the energy of my mind,
                and to the proper enthusiasm and ardour of speaking. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                />
            </p>
            <p>For if, O Caius Caesar, I were pleading this cause in the forum, still having you for
                my auditor and my judge, with what great cheerfulness would the concourse of the
                Roman people inspire me! For what citizen would do otherwise than favour that king,
                the whole of whose life he would recollect had been spent in the wars of the Roman
                people? I should be beholding the senate-house, I should be surveying the forum, I
                should call the heaven above me itself to witness;—and so, while calling to mind the
                kindnesses of the immortal gods, and of the Roman people, and of the senate to king
                Deiotarus, it <pb n="486"/> would be impossible for me to be at a loss for topics or
                armaments for my speech. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But since the walls of a
                house narrow, all these topics, and since the pleading of the cause is greatly
                crippled by the place, it behoves you, O Caesar, who have yourself often pleaded for
                many defendants, to consider within yourself what my feelings at present must be; so
                that your justice, and also your careful attention in listening to me, may the more
                easily lessen my natural agitation and anxiety. </p>
            <p>But before I say anything about the accusation itself, I will say a few words about
                the hopes entertained by the accusers. For though they appear to be possessed of no
                great skill or experience in affairs, nevertheless they have never, surely,
                undertaken this cause without some hope or other and some definite design.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="8" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>They were not ignorant that you were offended with king Deiotarus. They recollected
                that he had been already exposed to some inconvenience and loss on account of the
                displeasure with which you regarded him; and while they knew that you were angry
                with him, they had had proofs also that you were friendly to them. And as they would
                be speaking before you of a matter involving personal danger to yourself, they
                reckoned that a fictitious charge would easily lodge in your mind, which was already
                sore. Wherefore, O Caius Caesar, first of all by your good faith, and wisdom and
                firmness, and clemency deliver us from this fear, and prevent our suspecting that
                there is any ill-temper lurking in you. I entreat you by that right hand of yours
                which you pledged in token of everlasting friendship to king Deiotarus; by that
                right hand, I say, which is not more trustworthy in wars or in battles than in
                promises and pledges of good faith. You have chosen to enter his house, you have
                chosen to renew with him the ancient ties of friendship and hospitality. His
                household gods have received you under their protection; the altars and hearths of
                king Deiotarus have beheld you at peace with and friendly towards him. <milestone
                    n="9" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>You are accustomed, O Caius Caesar, not only to he prevailed upon by entreaties
                easily, but to he prevailed on once for all. No enemy has ever been reconciled to
                you who has found any remnant of hostility remaining in your breast afterwards.
                Although, who is there who has not heard of your complaints against king Deiotarus?
                You have never accused him as being an enemy to you, but as being a friend very
                slack in his duty, <pb n="487"/> because his inclination led him more to friendships
                with Cnaeus Pompeius than with you. And yet that very fact you said that you would
                have pardoned, if when he sent reinforcements and even his son to Pompeius, he had
                himself availed himself of the excuse furnished him by his age. <milestone n="10"
                    unit="section"/> And in this way, which you were acquitting him of the most
                important charges, you left behind only the little blame of his friendship for
                another. </p>
            <p>Therefore, you not only abstained from punishing him, but you released him from all
                apprehension; you acknowledged him as your friend, you left him king. And, indeed,
                his proceedings were not dictated by any hatred of you; he fell by the general error
                of us all. That king, whom the senate had repeatedly addressed by this name, using
                it in decrees most complimentary to him, and who from his youth up had always
                considered that order most important and most sacred, being a man living at a great
                distance, and a foreigner by birth, was perplexed by the same affairs which
                embarrassed us who were born and who at all times had lived in the middle of the
                republic. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="11" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>When he heard that men had taken arms by the authority of the senate, acting with
                great unanimity; that the defence of the republic had been entrusted to the consuls,
                the praetors, the tribunes of the people, and to all of us who had received the
                title of <foreign xml:lang="la">Imperator</foreign>, he was agitated in his mind,
                and being a man most deeply attached to this empire, he became alarmed for the
                safety of the Roman people, in which also he considered that his own was bound up.
                And being in a state of the greatest alarm, he thought it best to remain quiet
                himself. But he was beyond measure agitated when he heard that the consuls had fled
                from Italy, and all the men of consular rank (for so it was reported) with them, and
                all the senate, and that the whole of Italy was emptied. For the road was wide open
                for all such messengers and reports to travel to the East, and no true accounts
                followed. He never heard a word of the conditions which you offered, nor of your
                eagerness for concord and peace, nor of the way in which certain men conspired
                against your dignity. And though this was the state of things, still he continued
                quiet until ambassadors and letters came to him from Cnaeus Pompeius. <milestone
                    n="12" unit="section"/> Pardon Deiotarus, pardon him, I entreat you, O Caesar,
                if he, though a king, yielded to the authority of that man whom we all followed, and
                on whom both gods and men had heaped every sort of distinction, and on whom you
                yourself had conferred the <pb n="488"/> most numerous and most important
                    honours<note anchored="true">For Caesar had given Pompey his daughter in
                    marriage.</note> of all. Nor indeed, does it follow that, because your exploits
                have thrown a cloud over the praises of others, we have, therefore, entirely lost
                all recollection of Cnaeus Pompeius. Who is there who is ignorant how great the name
                of that man was, how great his influence, how great his renown in every description
                of war, how great were the honours paid him by the Roman people, and by the senate,
                and by you yourself? He had surpassed all his predecessors in glory as much as you
                have surpassed all the world. Therefore, we used to count up with admiration the
                wars, and the victories, and the triumphs, and the consulship; of Cnaeus Pompeius.
                But yours we are wholly unable to reckon. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="13" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>To him then came king Deiotarus in this miserable and fatal war, to him whom he had
                previously assisted in his regular wars against the enemies of Rome, and with whom
                he was bound, not only by ties of hospitality, but also by personal intimacy. And he
                came, either because he had been asked, as a friend; or because he had been sent for
                as an ally; or because he had been summoned, like one who had learnt to obey the
                senate; and last of all, he came as to a man flying, not to one pursuing others—that
                is to say, as a sharer of danger, not a partner in victory. Therefore, after the
                result of the battle of Pharsalia, he departed from Pompeius; he did not choose to
                persist in hopes of which he saw no end. He thought he had done quite enough to
                satisfy the claims of duty, if indeed he was under any such obligations, and that he
                had made quite mistake enough if he had ignorantly erred. He returned home; and all
                the time that you were engaged in the Alexandrian war, he consulted your interests.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He supported in his palaces and from his own
                resources the army of Cnaeus Domitius, that most distinguished man. He sent money to
                Ephesus to him whom you selected as the most faithful and most highly esteemed of
                all your friends. He gave him money a second time; he gave him money a third time
                for you to employ in the war, though be was forced to sell property by auction in
                order to raise it. He exposed his own person to danger and he was with you, serving
                in your army against Pharnaces, and he considered him as his own enemy because he
                was yours. And all those actions of his were accepted by you, O Caius Caesar, in
                such a spirit that you paid him the <pb n="489"/> highest possible honours, and
                confirmed hint in the dignity and title of king. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>He, therefore, having been not only released from danger by you, but having been also
                distinguished by you with the highest honours, is now accused of having intended to
                assassinate you in his own house—a thing which you cannot in truth possibly suspect,
                unless you consider him to have been utterly mad. For, to say nothing of what a deed
                of enormous wickedness it would have been to assassinate his guest in the sight of
                his own household gods; what a deed of enormous unreasonableness it would have been
                to have extinguished the brightest light of all nations, and of all human
                recollection; what a deed of enormous ferocity it would have been to have had no
                dread of the conqueror of the whole earth; what a sign of an inhuman and ungrateful
                disposition it would have been to be found to behave like a despot to the very man
                by whom be had been addressed as a king;—to say nothing of all this, what a deed of
                utter frenzy would it have been to rouse all kings, of whom there were numbers on
                the borders of his own kingdom, all free nations, all the allies, all the provinces,
                all the arms, in short, of every people on earth against himself alone! To what
                misery would he not have exposed his kingdom, his house, his wife, and his beloved
                son, not merely by the accomplishment of such a crime, but even by the bare idea of
                it! <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="16" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But I suppose that improvident and rash man did not see all this! On the contrary,
                who is a more considerate than he? Who is more secret in his plans? Who is more
                prudent? Although in this place it is not so much on the ground of cleverness and
                prudence that it seems to me that I should defend Deiotarus, as on that of good
                faith and religious feeling and conduct. You are well acquainted, O Caius Caesar,
                with the honesty of the man, with his virtuous habits, with his wisdom and firmness.
                Indeed, who is there who has ever heard of the name of the Roman people, who has not
                heard also of the integrity, and wisdom, and virtue, and good faith of Deiotarus? A
                crime, then, that cannot be imputed to an imprudent man, on account of his fear of
                instant destruction, nor to an unscrupulous man, unless he be at the same time
                utterly insane; will you pretend that such a crime was thought of by a most virtuous
                man, and one too who was never accounted a fool? <pb n="490"/>
            </p>
            <p><milestone n="17" unit="section"/> And in what a way do you try and support this
                invention! in a way not only not calculated to win belief, but not even such as to,
                give rise to the least suspicion. When, says the prosecutor, you had come to the
                Luceian fort, and had turned aside to the palace of the king your entertainer, there
                certain place where all those things were arranged which the king had settled to
                offer you as presents. To this place he intended to conduct you on coming out of the
                bath, before you lay down; for there were armed men stationed in that very place on
                purpose to kill you. This is the charge; this is the reason why a runaway should
                accuse a monarch, a slave accuse his master! I, in truth, O Caius Caesar, at the
                very beginning, when the cause was originally laid before me, was struck with a
                suspicion that Philippus, the physician, one of the king's slaves, who had been sent
                with the ambassadors, had been corrupted by that young man. He has suborned the
                physician to act as informer, thought I; he will be sure to invent some accusation
                of poisoning. Although my conjecture was some way from the exact truth, it was not
                much out as to the general principle of the accusation. What says the physician?
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Not a word about poison. But in the first
                place, that might have been administered much more a in a potion or in food; in the
                second place, a crime is committed in that way with greater impunity, because when
                it has been done, it can be denied. If he had assassinated you openly, he would have
                brought upon himself not only the hatred of all nations, but their arms also. If he
                had slain you by poison, to be sure he never would have been able to conceal the
                action from the divine wrath of the Jupiter who presides over hospitality, but he
                might perhaps have concealed it from men. Are we, then, to suppose that that which
                he might have attempted in secret and have executed with great caution, he never
                entrusted to you who were a skillful physician, and, as he believed, a faithful
                servant and yet that he could conceal nothing from you with respect to arms and
                blood, and ambuscade? And how cleverly is the whole nation worked up! <milestone
                    n="19" unit="section"/> It was your own good fortune, says he that fortune which
                always preserves you, which saved you then. You said that you did not wish at that
                moment to see the presents. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>What happened afterwards? Did Deiotarus, after he had failed in accomplishing the
                business at that time, at once <pb n="491"/> dismiss his army? was there no other
                place where he could set an ambush? But you said that when you had supped you would
                come back again the same way; and you did so. Was it a very difficult job to detain
                the armed men one or two hours in the place where they had been stationed? After you
                had spent your time at the banquet courteously and merrily, then you went back that
                way, as you had said; and then and there you found that the behaviour of Deiotarus
                to you resembled that of king Attalus to Publius Africanus to whom, as we have read,
                he sent the most magnificent gifts from Asia to Numantia; which Africanus accepted
                in the sight of all his army. And when Deiotarus, being present with you, had done
                all this in a kingly spirit and with royal courtesy, you departed to your chamber.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> I entreat you, O Caesar, trace back your
                recollection of that time, bring that day back before your eyes, remember the
                countenances of the men who were then gazing on you and admiring you; was there any
                trepidation among them? any disorder? Was anything done except in an orderly and
                quiet manner,—except as became the establishment of a dignified and honourable man?
                What reason then can be imagined why he should have intended to murder you after you
                had bathed, and why he should not have chosen to do so after you had supped?
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> “Oh, he put it off,” says the prosecutor,
                “till the next day, in order that when he arrived at the Luceian fort, he might
                there put his designs in execution.”I do not understand the effect of his changing
                the place; but still the whole case was conducted in an incriminatory manner.
                “When,” says the prosecutor, “you said after supper that you wished to vomit, they
                began to lead you to the bath-room; for that was the place where the ambuscade was;
                but still that same fortune of yours saved you; you said that you had rather go to
                your bedroom.” May the gods forgive you, you run-away slave! Are you so utterly, not
                only worthless and infamous, but also stupid and senseless? What? were they brazen
                statues that he had planted in ambush, so that they could not be moved from the
                bath-room to the bed-chamber? </p>
            <p>Here you have the whole charge as to the ambuscade: for he said nothing further. “In
                all this,” says he, “I was his accomplice.” What do you mean? Was he so demented as
                to allow a man to leave him who was privy to so enormous a wickedness? As even to
                send him to Rome, where he knew his grandson was, who was most bitterly hostile to
                him, and <pb n="492"/> where Caius Caesar was, against whom he had laid this plot?
                especially when he was the only man who could give any information against him in
                his absence. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> “My brothers too,” says he, “because
                they also were privy to it he threw into prison.” When, then, he was putting those
                men in prison whom he had with him, did he leave you at large and send you to
                Rome,—you who knew the very same facts which you say that they knew? <milestone
                    n="8" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The remainder of the accusation was of a twofold character; one part of which was,
                that the king was always in his watch-tower because he was so disaffected to your
                interests; the other, that he had levied a large army against you. As to the army, I
                will reply to that charge in a very few words, as I will to the rest of the charges.
                King Deiotarus never had any forces with which he could have made war upon the Roman
                people; but only just sufficient to protect his own territories from the incursions
                of enemies, and to send reinforcements to our generals. And before this time he was
                able to maintain a larger force than he can now; at present he can with difficulty
                keep up a very small one. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> “Oh, but he sent to
                Caecilius; I don't know who it was he sent, but he threw those whom he sent or
                rather ordered to go, into prison, because they would not go.” I do not stop to ask
                how far it is probable that a king should have had no one to send; or that those
                whom he ordered to go should not have obeyed him; or how it was that those men who
                refused obedience in so important an affair, were put in prison, and not executed;
                but still, when he was sending to Caecilius,<note anchored="true">This was Quintius
                    Caecilius Brassus, a zealous partisan of Pompey's, who after the battle of
                    Pharsalia collected some of the remnants of his army in Syria, with which he
                    afterwards joined Cassius after the death of Caesar.</note> was he ignorant that
                that party had been defeated, or did he think that Caecilius a person of great
                importance? a man whom he, who was well acquainted with our leading men, would have
                despised because he knew him, and just as much because he did not know him.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> He added, also, that he did not send his best
                cavalry;—I dare say, they were old troops, O Caesar: nothing to your cavalry; but
                still they were the best men he had, his picked men. He says, that one of the body
                was recognised as being a slave;—I do not believe it; I never heard of it. But
                still, even if such a thing had happened, I should not conceive that that was any
                fault of the king's. <pb n="493"/>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>“He was very ill-disposed towards you.” How so? He hoped, I suppose, that you would
                find it difficult to get out of Alexandria, on account of the nature of the country
                and of the river. But, at that very time, he supplied you with money, and with
                provisions for your army; he cooperated to the utmost of his power with the officer
                to whom you had given command in Asia; he assisted you when victorious, not only in
                the way of affording you hospitality, but with you he encountered danger, and stood
                by your side in the array of battle. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>The African war followed: there were unfavourable reports spread about you, which
                also roused that frantic Caecilius. What on that occasion was the disposition
                evinced towards you by the king? He sold property by auction, and preferred
                stripping himself to not supplying you with money. “But,” says the prosecutor, “at
                that very time he was sending men to Nicaea, and to Ephesus, to catch every report
                that came from Africa, and to bring it to him with all speed.” Therefore, when news
                came that Domitius had perished by shipwreck, and that you were blockaded in some
                fortress, he quoted a Greek verse with reference to Domitius, having the same
                meaning as that of our poet: <quote>
                    <l>So can we well afford to lose our friends, </l>
                    <l>If our foes perish in the same destruction:</l>
                </quote>
                <note anchored="true">The Greek proverb is given by Plutarch as <quote
                        xml:lang="grc">e)rre/tw fi/los so\n e)/xqrw|</quote>. If the Latin iambic
                    quoted by Cicero comes from any Latin poet, it is not known who he was.</note>
                an expression which he would never have uttered had he been ever so much an enemy to
                you. For he himself is a man of a humane disposition; and that verse is a savage
                one. Besides, how could a man be a friend to Domitius, who was an enemy to you?
                Moreover, why should he be an enemy to you, by whom he might even have been put to
                death according to the laws of war, and by whom he recollected that he and his son
                had been appointed kings? <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>What is the next statement? What is the next step taken by this scoundrel? He says
                that Deiotarus was so elated at this, that he drowned his joy in wine, and danced
                naked at a banquet. What cross is there that could be a sufficient punishment for
                this slave? Did any one ever see Deiotarus dancing,—did any one ever see him drunk?
                All kingly virtues are united in that man, and that I think yourself <pb n="4945"/>
                are well aware of, O Caesar; but most especially is that singular and admirable
                economy of his conspicuous. Although this is an attribute for which I know that it
                is not usual to praise kings. To say that a man is economical is not much praise for
                a king. To be brave, just, severe, dignified, magnanimous, open-handed, beneficent
                liberal—these are the praises suited to a king. Economy is a virtue for a private
                individual. Let every one take it as he pleases: but I consider economy—that is to
                say, moderation and temperance—the very greatest of virtues. And this existed in
                this man from his earliest youth, and was experienced by, and known to, all Asia,
                and by all our magistrates and ambassadors, and by all the Roman knights who
                trafficked in Asia. </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> It was by many successive steps of dutiful
                service towards our republic that he arrived at this title of king; but still,
                whatever leisure he had from the wars of the Roman people, he devoted entirely to
                cultivating friendship and intimacy with our citizens, and to uniting his affairs
                and interests to theirs. So that he was not only considered a noble tetrarch, but
                also an excellent father of a family, and a most industrious farmer and grazier. Did
                he, then, who, while a young man, before he had arrived at his subsequent high rank,
                never did anything that was inconsistent with the most rigid virtue and the greatest
                dignity, after he had raised to himself the esteem in which he is now held, and when
                he had become of so advanced an age, did he dance? <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="28" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You ought, O Castor, rather to imitate the manner and principles of your grandfather,
                than calumniate a most virtuous and most illustrious man with the language of a
                runaway slave. Even if you had had a grandfather who was a dancer, and not a man
                from whom examples of modesty and chastity might be derived, still this reproach is
                one which is very little suited to your age. Those pursuits to which he had been
                habituated from his earliest age—not dancing, but such as would train him to wield
                his arms and manage his horses in the best manner,—those all had now failed him at
                his advanced time of life; so that we used to wonder, when several men had lifted
                Deiotarus on his horse, how so old a man as he could contrive to stick on. But this
                young man, who was a soldier of mine in Cilicia, and a comrade of mine in Greece,
                how was he used to ride about in <pb n="495"/> that army of ours, with his own
                picked body of cavalry, whom his father had sent with him to join Pompeius! what
                gallops he used to take; how he used to display his skill! What a parade he used to
                make! How did he refuse to yield to any one in his zeal and eagerness for the
                success of that cause! <milestone n="29" unit="section"/> But even after the army
                was lost, I, who had at all times been an adviser of peace, but who, after the
                battle of Pharsalia, urged every one not to lay aside, but to throw away their arms,
                could never bring this young man to adopt my advice, both because of his own
                eagerness for that war, and because he thought himself bound to satisfy the
                expectations of his father. </p>
            <p>Happy is that house which has obtained, not only impunity, but licence to accuse
                others! Unfortunate Deiotarus, who is not only accused by one who was in the same
                camp with him, before you, but who is impeached even by his own relations. Cannot
                you, O Castor, be content with your own good fortune without bringing misery on your
                relations? <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="30" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Grant that there may be enmity between you; which, however, there ought not to be;
                for it was king Deiotarus who raised your family, when abject and obscure, from
                darkness into light. Who ever heard of your father, or who he was, before they heard
                whose son-in-law he was? But even supposing you repudiated the name of the
                connection with ever so much ingratitude and impiety, still you might have conducted
                your quarrel like a man, and not pursue him with a false accusation, not seek his
                life, not prosecute him on a capital charge. Be it so:—let even this excess of
                bitterness and hatred be permitted. Was it to go to such an extent that all the laws
                of ordinary life and of common safety, and even of humanity, are to be violated? to
                tamper with slaves by words, to corrupt them by hopes and promises; to lead them
                away to your own house, to arm them against their master, to wage an impious war not
                against one relation, but against every family in the world? For that corruption of
                slaves, if it be not only unpunished, but even approved by such a great authority as
                that of this tribunal, no walls, no laws, no rights will be sufficient for the
                protection of our safety. For when that which is in our houses and is our own can
                sally out with impunity and fight against us, slavery then gets the mastery, and the
                master's position is slavery. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Shame on the times, and on our present habits! That <pb n="496"/> Cnaeus Domitius,
                whom we as boys saw consul, and censor and chief pontiff, when, as tribune of the
                people, he had impeached Marcus Scaurus, the chief man of the state, before the
                people, and when a slave of Scaurus had come secretly to him at his own house, and
                had offered to give information with respect to charges which might he brought
                against his master ordered the slave to be apprehended, and taken to Scaurus. See
                what a difference there is now,—although it is a shame of me to compare Castor to
                Domitius; still, he sent his slave back to his enemy, you have seduced one from your
                grandfather; he refused to listen to one though he had not been bribed, you have
                bribed one; he rejected a slave as his assistant against his master, you have
                employed one even as an accuser. But was it only once that that fellow was corrupted
                by you? <milestone n="32" unit="section"/> Did he not escape back again to the
                ambassadors after he had been brought forward by you, and after he had been with
                you? Did he not even come to Caius Cnaeus Domitius? Did not he, in the hearing of
                this Servius Sulpicius that most illustrious man, who is present here, and of this
                Titus Torquatus, a most virtuous young man, who is also present, confess that he had
                been bribed by you, and that it was by your promises that he had been instigated to
                this dishonesty? <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>What then is the object of this shameless, and barbarous, and unrestrained
                inhumanity? Was it for this that you came into this city, that you might corrupt the
                principles predominant in, and the examples furnished by this city, and that you
                might pollute the humanity of our state by your own private ferocity? </p>
            <p><milestone n="33" unit="section"/> And how ingeniously have all your charges been
                collected! Blesamius, says he, (for it was in his name, a very excellent man, and
                one who was a stranger to you, that he was calumniating you, O Deiotarus,) used to
                write to the king, that you, O Caesar, were very unpopular; that you were considered
                a tyrant; that men were exceedingly offended at your statue having been placed among
                those of the kings; that you were never well received on your appearance in public.
                Do not you perceive, O Caesar, that these statements were collected by these
                fellows, from the city conversation of spiteful men? Could Blesamius have written to
                say that Caesar was a tyrant? Yes, for he had seen the heads of many citizens
                exposed; he had seen many men by the orders of Caesar ill-treated, scourged <pb
                    n="497"/> and executed; he had seen many houses pillaged and destroyed; he had
                seen the forum filled with armed troops!—No; those things which previously we always
                have felt after victories in civil war, we have not seen now, when you have been our
                conqueror. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/> You are the only man—you I say, O
                Caius Caesar, are the only man, by whose victory no one has perished except with
                arms in his hand. And can the man whom we, free men, born in the enjoyment of the
                perfect liberty of the Roman people, consider not only no tyrant but as even the
                most merciful man possible in the use of victory, can he appear a tyrant to
                Blesamius, who is living under a king? For who complains about a statue, especially
                about one single statue, when he sees such a number? Great reason have we, indeed,
                to envy a man his statues, when we do not grudge him trophies; for if it be the
                place which provokes envy, surely there is no place more open and fit for a statue
                than the <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign>. And as to the way in which he is
                received in public, why need I make any reply at all? for public applause has never
                been desired by you, and sometimes, owing to the amazement with which men have
                viewed your achievements, it has even been stifled by the excess of their
                admiration; and perhaps, too, it has been omitted because nothing vulgar could
                possibly appear worthy of you. <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="35"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I do not think that anything has been omitted by me; but some topics have been
                reserved for the end of my speech, and they are of such a nature that they ought to
                reconcile you cordially to Deiotarus—for I am not now afraid of your being angry
                with him; I am apprehensive rather of your suspecting that he harbours some
                resentment against you. And that suspicion, believe me, O Caesar, is as remote as
                possible from the truth. For he recollects only what he still has left owing to you,
                and not what he has lost by your means; nor does he consider that he has been
                deprived of anything by you, but being aware that it was necessary for you to give
                many rewards to many people, he did not think it hard that you should take something
                from him who had been on the other side. <milestone n="36" unit="section"/> In
                truth, if that great prince, Antiochus the Great the king of Asia, who, after he had
                been conquered by Scipio, was ordered to consider Mount Taurus as the boundary of
                his dominions, and was deprived of all this Asia which is now a province of our
                own,—if he was accustomed to say that he had been kindly treated by the Roman <pb
                    n="498"/> people, because be had been released by them from the care of an
                overgrown empire, and was now at liberty to enjoy a kingdom of moderate extent,
                Deiotarus can comfort himself much more easily. For Antiochus had suffered a
                chastisement for his insanity, my client only for an error. You, O Caesar, gave
                everything to Deiotarus when you gave him and his son the title of King; and as long
                as he is allowed to retain and preserve this title, he does not think that the
                kindness of the Roman people is at all diminished, or that the senate has come to
                any unfavourable decision respecting him. He preserves a great and lofty spirit, and
                will never succumb to his enemies, nor even to fortune. <milestone n="37"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>He thinks that by his previous conduct he has given birth to much, and that by his
                own courage and virtue he still has much which he cannot possibly he deprived of.
                For what fortune, or what accident, or what injury can happen to Deiotarus of such
                severity as to efface the decrees of all our generals respecting him? For he has
                been complimented and distinguished ever since he was of an age to serve in their
                camps, by all those men who have had the conduct of our wars in Asia, and in
                Cappadocia, and in Pontus, and in Cilicia, and in Syria. And what length of time
                will ever efface, what forgetfulness will ever obliterate those numerous and
                honourable resolutions of the senate respecting him, which have been recorded in the
                public writings and memorials of the Roman people? </p>
            <p>Why need I speak of his valour? why of his greatness of mind? of his wisdom? of his
                firmness and consistency? qualities which not only have all wise and learned men
                pronounced to be the greatest blessings, but which some have even considered the
                only real ones, and have said that virtue wanted nothing more than these for the
                purpose of living not only well, but even happily. <milestone n="38" unit="section"
                /> He, considering these things, and reflecting on them day and night, is so far
                from feeling resentment against you, (for he would not only be ungrateful, but even
                mad to do so,) that he attributes the whole of the tranquillity and quiet of his old
                age which he enjoys to your clemency. <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And as these were his sentiments previously, I do not doubt also that after the
                receipt of your letters, of which I have read a copy, which you gave to this
                Blesamius at Tarraco for Deiotarus, his spirit became loftier still, and that <pb
                    n="499"/> he ceased to feel any anxiety whatever. For in them you bid him
                entertain good hopes, and to be of good courage—expressions which I know you are not
                in the habit of using without a meaning: for I recollect that you wrote to me in
                almost the same language, and that when you bade me entertain good hopes of the
                future you were not deceiving me. </p>
            <p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="section"/> I am anxious, indeed, in this cause of King
                Deiotarus, with whom the affairs of this republic have united me in friendship,
                while our mutual regard for one another has connected us by ties of hospitality,
                with whom long acquaintance has engendered intimacy, and his great services to me
                and to my army have wrought in me the greatest affection for him. But while I am
                anxious about him, I am anxious also about many most distinguished men, who have
                been pardoned by you, and who ought to be able to consider their pardon, whenever
                pronounced, as binding for ever; and who ought not to feel that a doubt is thrown on
                the permanency of your kindness to them, nor to have a perpetual anxiety implanted
                in their minds; nor, in short, ought it to be allowed to happen that any one of
                those men should begin again to feel apprehension, who has once been released by you
                from fear. <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>I ought not, O Caesar, to endeavour, as is often done by men in such danger as this,
                to move your pity by my language. There is no need of my doing so. Your feelings are
                of their own accord accustomed to come to the aid of the suppliant and unfortunate,
                without being elicited by the eloquence of anybody. Place before your eyes two
                kings, and contemplate with your mind what you cannot behold with your eyes. You
                will surely yield to your feelings of compassion what you refused to your
                resentment. There are many monuments of your clemency, but the chief, sure, are the
                secure happiness of those men to whom it is you have been the author of safety. And
                if such an action is glorious in the case of a private individual, much more will it
                be celebrated when it is a king who is the object of it. The title of King has
                always been accounted a holy name in this city; but the names of ally and king, when
                united together, are then the holiest of all titles. <milestone n="15"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="41" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And these kings were afraid that if you were victorious they might lose that name.
                But now that they have been allowed to retain it, and have been confirmed in it by
                you, I confidently trust that they will even transmit it to <pb n="500"/> their
                posterity. Moreover, these ambassadors whom you see before you, Hieras, and
                Blesamius, and Antigonus, men with whom you and all of us have long been acquainted,
                and also Dorylaus, a man of the same loyalty and virtue as they, who was lately sent
                as ambassador to you in company with Hieras, devoted friends of the king, and men
                too who, as I hope, are highly esteemed by you, offer you their persons as hostages
                and pledges to secure the safety of their prince. <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                Ask Blesamius whether he ever wrote anything to the king to the disparagement of
                your dignity. Hieras, indeed, undertakes the whole cause of Deiotarus, and offers
                himself as the defendant against all these charges in behalf of, and instead of, the
                king. He implores the aid of your recollection in his favour; a quality in which you
                greatly excel: he declares that all the time that you were in the tetrarchy of
                Deiotarus he never left your side. He says that he met you on the frontier, and that
                he attended you to the borders on the opposite side of the country; that when you
                left the bath he was with you, and when you surveyed all those presents after
                supper, and when you retired to rest in your bed-chamber. And he says, too, that he
                attended you in the same unremitting manner all the next day. <milestone n="43"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Wherefore, if any one of those things which Deiotarus has been accused of, really was
                thought of, he does not object to your thinking the crime his. I entreat you, O
                Caius Caesar, to consider that on this day your sentence will bring on those kings
                either most miserable calamity, accompanied with infinite disgrace, or an unsullied
                reputation attended with safety; and to desire the one of those results would be an
                act of cruelty, to secure the other is an action suitable to your clemency. </p>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
