<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Quintus Roscius</title>
        <title>For Quintius, Sextus Roscius, Quintus Roscius, against Quintus Caecilius, and against
          Verres</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
        <editor role="translator" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor> 
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder> 
      </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>  <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
            <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
              Yonge</title><idno type="OCLC">4709897</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons</publisher>
              <date>1903</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      
      <!--<refsDecl>
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="text=Ver.">
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState delim=" " unit="actio"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="book"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl> -->
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="fre">French</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>  
      <change when="2016-02-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Moved front matter for more uniform treatment within series.</change>
<change when="2016-01-29" who="Lisa Cerrato">CTS conversion and minor cleanup.</change>
<change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
<change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
<change when="2014-07" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
<change who="rsingh04" when="2010-09-03">cleaned up log keyword</change>
<change who="student" when="2010-07-08">fixing place tags - AD</change>
<change who="rsingh04" when="2009-10-09">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
<change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
<change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed chunking for cic. ver. to text:actio:book:section in order for bibls to work</change>
<change who="lcerrato" when="2009-06-03">fixed bad bibls</change>
<change who="packel" when="2006-05-05">fixed date tags</change>
<change who="packel" when="2006-02-10">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
<change who="packel" when="2005-08-01">removed stray item tags</change>
<change who="packel" when="2005-07-25">Converted to XML</change>
<change who="lcerrato" when="2003-10-10">fixed four random typos</change>
<change who="yorkc" when="2003-07-01">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
<change who="lcerrato" when="2002-10-02">fixed typo you have not this to you have not heard this</change>
<change who="dasmith" when="2000-03-04">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
<change who="lcerrato" when="1996-11-30">revised and proofread again</change>
<change who="dasmith" when="1999-10-14">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
<change who="lcerrato" when="1999-10-01">fixed valour for velour</change>
<change who="dasmith" when="1999-08-12">Fixed refsDecl</change>
<change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Minor tagging changes.</change>
<change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Lisa's edits.</change>
<change who="textgod" when="1997-09-01">Added sections.</change>
<change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Changed Quint. abbreviation to Quinct.</change>
<change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Added to repository. Passes TEI parsing.</change>
<change when="1997-03-19" who="DAS">ed.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text xml:lang="eng">
          <body>
          <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi003.perseus-eng2">
          <head>THE SPEECH FOR Q. ROSCIUS THE ACTOR</head>
            <div type="commentary" resp="ed">
              <head>THE ARGUMENT</head>
              <p>After the last speech which was delivered A. U. C. 674, Cicero went to <placeName
                key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, where he remained eighteen months, and after
                his return he did not employ himself at first as an advocate but devoted himself
                rather to philosophical studies. But in the third year, A. U. C. 677, when his friend
                Roscius, the comic actor, was interested in a cause, he returned to the bar. The
                subject of the action in which this speech was this: A man of the name of Fannius
                Chaerea had articled a young slave to Roscius on condition that Roscius was to teach
                him the art of acting, and that he and Fannius were afterwards to share his earnings.
                The slave was afterwards killed and Roscius brought an action against the man who had
                killed him, Quintus Flavius by name and received as damages a farm worth 100,000
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>—for his half share in the slave,
                according to his own account, but as the full value of the slave according to Fannius
                but the fact was that Fannius also had brought an action against Flavius and had
                recovered similar damages. Fannius sued Roscius for 50,000 <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                  >sesterces</foreign>, as his share of the damages which he (Roscius) had received
                from Flavius, suppressing the fact of his having obtained a similar sum himself. The
                beginning of this speech is lost, and also a considerable portion at the end. </p>
            </div>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus">
          <p>... He, forsooth, excellent man, and of singular integrity, endeavours in his own cause
            to bring forward his account-books as witnesses. Men are accustomed to say.... <note
              anchored="true">There is a hiatus here so that though there are some words more in the
              Latin text, which I have omitted, it is impossible to make an sense of them.</note>
            Did I endeavour to corrupt such a man as that, so as to induce him to make a false
            entrance for my sake? I am waiting till Chaerea uses this argument. Was I able to induce
            this hand to be full of falsehood, and these fingers to make a false entry? But if he
            produces his accounts, Roscius will also produce his.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>
            These words will appear in the books of the one, but not in those of the other. Why
            should you trust one rather than the other? Oh, would he ever have written it if he had
            not borne this expense by his authority? No, says the other, would he not have written
            it if he had given the authority? For just as it is discreditable to put down what is
            not owed, so it is dishonest not to put down what you do owe. For his accounts are just
            as much condemned who omits to make an entry of the truth, as his who puts down what is
            false. But see now to what, relying on the abundance and cogency of my arguments, I am
            now coming. If Caius Fannius produces in his own behalf his accounts of money received
            and paid, written at his own pleasure, I do not object to your giving your decision in
            his favour. </p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>What brother would show so much indulgence
            to a brother, what father to a son, as to consider whatever he entered in this manner
            proof of a fact? Oh, Roscius will ratify it. Produce your books; what you were convinced
            of, he will be convinced of; what was approved of by you, will be approved of by him. A
            little while ago we demanded the accounts of Marcus Perperna, and of Publius Saturius.
            Now, O Caius Fannius Chaerea, we demand your accounts alone, and we do not object to the
            action being decided by them—Why then do you not produce them? </p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
              Does he not keep accounts? Indeed he does most carefully. Does
            he not enter small matters in his books? Indeed be does everything. Is this a small and
            trifling sum? It is 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>. How is it that such
            an extraordinary sum us omitted?—how is it that a hundred thousand <foreign
              xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>, received and expended, are not down in the books? Oh,
            ye immortal gods that there should be any one endued with such audacity, as to dare to
            demand a sum which he is afraid to enter in his account-books; not to hesitate to swear
            before the court to what, when not on his oath, he scrupled to put on paper; to
            endeavour to persuade another of what he is unable to make out to his own satisfaction.</p></div> 
              
            <milestone n="2" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus">
          <p>He says that I am indignant, and sent the accounts too soon; he confesses that he has
            not this sum entered in his book of money received and expended; but he asserts that it
            does occur in his memoranda. Are you then so fond of yourself, have you such a
            magnificent opinion of yourself, as to ask for money from us on the strength, not of
            your account-books, but of your memoranda? To read one's account-books instead of
            producing witnesses, is a piece of arrogance; but is it not insanity to produce mere
            notes of writings and scraps of paper?</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>If memoranda
            have the same force and authority, and are arranged with the same care as accounts,
            where is the need of making an account-book? of making out careful lists? of keeping a
            regular order? of making a permanent record of old writings? But if we have adopted the
            custom of making account-books, because we put no trust in flying memoranda, shall that
            which, by all individuals, is considered unimportant and not to be relied on, be
            considered important and holy before a judge?</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>Why is
            it that we write down memoranda carelessly, that we make up account-books carefully? For
            what reason? Because the one is to last a month, the other for ever; these are
            immediately expunged those are religiously preserved; these embrace the recollection of
            a short time, those pledge the good faith and honesty of a man for ever; these are
            thrown away, those are arranged in order. Therefore, no one ever produced memoranda at a
            trial; men do produce accounts, and read entries in books. 
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          You, O Caius Piso, a man of the greatest good faith, and virtue, and dignity, and
          authority, would not venture to demand money on the strength of memoranda.</p></div>
            
             <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>I need not say any more about matters in which the custom is so
            notorious; but I ask you this, which is very material to the question, How long ago is
            it, O Fannius, that you made this entry in your memoranda? He blushes; he does not know
            what to answer; he is at a loss for anything to invent off-hand. “It is two
            months ago,” you will say; yet it ought to have been copied into the
            account-book of money received and paid. “It is more than six
            months.” Why then is it left so long in the memorandum-book? What if it is
            more than three years ago? How is it that, when every one else who makes up
            account-books transfers his accounts every month almost into his books you allow this
            sum to remain among your memoranda more than three years?</p></div> 
               
               <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>Have you all other sums of money received and expended regularly
            entered, or not? If not, how is it that you make up your books? If you have, how is it
            that, when you were entering all other items in regular order, you leave this sum, which
            was one of the greatest of all in amount, for more than three years in your memoranda?
            “You did not like it to be known that Roscius was in your debt.” Why
            did you put it down at all? “You were asked not to enter it.” Why
            did you put it down in your memoranda? But, although I think this is strong enough, yet
            I cannot satisfy myself unless I get evidence from Caius Fannius himself that this money
            is not owed to him. It is a great thing which I am attempting; it is a difficult thing
            which I am undertaking; yet I will agree that Roscius shall not gain the verdict unless
            he has the same man both for his adversary and for his witness.</p></div> 
                 
            <milestone n="4" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus">
          <p>A definite sum of money was owed to you, which is now sought to be recovered at law;
            and security for a legitimate portion of it has been given. In this case, if you have
            demanded one sesterce more than is owed to you, you have lost your cause; because trial
            before a judge is one thing, arbitration is another. <note anchored="true">Professor
              Long's explanation of the difference here laid down is little more than a translation
              of and comment on this passage. He says, “The following is the distinction
              between <foreign xml:lang="lat">arbitrium</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >judicium</foreign> according to Cicero (<bibl n="Cic. Q. Rosc. 4">Pro Rosc. Com.
                4</bibl>). In a <foreign xml:lang="lat">judicium</foreign> the demand was of a certain or
              definite amount, <foreign xml:lang="lat">pecuniae certae</foreign>).; in an <foreign
                xml:lang="lat">arbitrium</foreign> the amount was not determined (<foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >incertae</foreign>.) In a <foreign xml:lang="lat">judicium</foreign> the plaintiff
              obtained all that he claimed or nothing, as the words of the formula show,
                “<foreign xml:lang="lat">si paret H. S. 1000 dari
              oportere.</foreign>” (Compare <bibl n="Gaius Inst. 4.50">Gaius, iv.
                50.</bibl>) The corresponding words in the formula arbitraria were
                “<foreign xml:lang="lat">Quantum aequius melius, id dari</foreign>”;
              and their equivalents were “<foreign xml:lang="lat">ex fide bona; ut inter bonos
                bene agier.</foreign>” (Top. 17)... If the matter was brought before a
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">judex</foreign>, properly so called, the <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >judicium</foreign> was constituted with a <foreign xml:lang="lat">poena</foreign>, that
              is <foreign xml:lang="lat">per sponsionem</foreign>; there was no <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >poena</foreign> when an arbiter was demanded, and the proceeding was by the formula
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">arbitraria</foreign>. The proceeding by the <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >sponsio</foreign> then was the strict one, “<foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >Angustissima formula sponsionis</foreign>,” (<bibl n="Cic. Q. Rosc. 14"
                >Cic. pro Rosc. Com. 14</bibl>); that of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">arbitrium</foreign>
              was <foreign xml:lang="lat">ex fide bona</foreign>, and the arbiter, though he was bound by
              the instructions of the formula, was allowed a greater latitude by its terms. The
              engagement between the parties who accepted an arbiter, by which they bound themselves
              to abide by his <foreign xml:lang="lat">arbitrium</foreign>, was <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >compromissum</foreign>. (<bibl n="Cic. Q. Rosc. 40">Pro Rosc. Com. 40</bibl>) But
              this term was also employed, as it appears, to express the engagement by which parties
              agreed to settle their differences by arbitration, without the intervention of the
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">praetor</foreign>. Smith, Dict. Ant. v. 530 v. <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >Judex</foreign>. </note> Trial before a judge is about a definite sum of money;
            arbitration about one which is not determined. We come before a judge so as either to
            gain the whole suit or to lose it; we go before an arbiter on the understanding that we
            may not get all we asked, and on the other hand may not get nothing.</p></div>  
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>Of that the very words of the formula are a proof. What is the
            formula in a trial before a judge? Direct severe, and simple; “if it be plain
            that fifty thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> ought to be paid.”
            Unless he makes it plain that fifty thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> to a
            single farthing are due to him, he loses his cause. What is the formula in a cause
            brought before an arbiter? “That whatever is just and right shall be
            given.” But that man confesses that he is asking more than is owed to him, but
            that he will be satisfied and more than satisfied with what is given him by the arbiter.
            Therefore the one has confidence in his case, the other distrusts his.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>And as this is the case, I ask you why you made an agreement to abide
            by arbitration in a matter involving this sum, this very fifty thousand <foreign
              xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>, and the credit of your own account-books? why you
            admitted an arbitrator in such a case to decide what it was right and proper should be
            paid to you; or secured to you by bond, if it so seemed good to him? Who was the
            arbitrator in this matter? I wish he were at <placeName key="tgn,7013962"
              >Rome</placeName>. He is at <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>. I wish he
            were in court. He is. I wish he were sitting as assessor to Caius 
                <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName>. He is Caius Piso himself. Did you take the same
            man for both arbitrator, and judge? Did you permit to the same man unlimited liberty of
            varying his decision, and also limit him to the strictest formula of the bond? Who ever
            went before an arbitrator and got all that he demanded? No one; for he only got all that
            it was just should be given him. You have come before a judge for the very same sum for
            which you had recourse to an arbiter.</p></div> 
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>Other men, when
            they see that their cause is failing before a judge, fly to an arbitrator. This man has
            dared to come from an arbiter to a judge, who when he admitted an arbitrator about this
            money, and about the credit due to his account-books, gave a plain indication that no
            money was owing to him. Already two-thirds of the cause are over. He admits that he has
            not set down the sum as due, and he does not venture to say that he has entered it as
            paid, since he does not produce his books. The only alternative remaining, is for him to
            assert that he had received a promise of it; for otherwise I do not see how he can
            possibly demand a definite sum of money. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          Did you receive a promise of it? When? On what day? At what time? In whose presence?</p></div>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>Who says that I made such a promise? No one. If I
            were to make an end of speaking here, I appear to have said enough to acquit myself as
            far as my good faith and diligence are at stake—to have said enough for the
            cause and dispute, enough for the formula and bond; I seem to have said enough to
            satisfy the judge why judgment ought to pass for Roscius. A definite sum of money has
            been demanded; security is given for a third part of it; this money must either have
            been given, or set down as paid, or promised. Fannius admits it was not given; the books
            of Fannius prove that it has not been set down as paid; the silence of witnesses proves
            that it was never promised.</p></div> 
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>What do we want more?
            Because the defendant is a man to whom money has always seemed of no value, but
            character of the very highest, and the judge is a man whom we are no less anxious to
            have think well of us than to decide favourably for us, and the bar present is such,
            that on account of its extraordinary brilliancy we ought to feel almost as much respect
            for it as for another judge, we will speak as if every regular trial, every honorary
            arbitration, every domestic duty were included and comprehended in the present formula.
            That former oration was necessary, this shall be a voluntary one; the other was
            addressed to the judge, this is addressed to Caius Piso; that was on behalf of a
            defendant, this is on behalf of Roscius; the one was prepared to gain a victory, this
            one to preserve a good character.</p></div> 
            <milestone n="6" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus">
          <p>You demand, O Fannius, a sum of money from Roscius. What sum? Is it money which is owed
            to you from the partnership? or money which has been promised and assured to you by his
            liberality? One demand is important and odious, the other is more trifling and easy to
            be got rid of. Is it a sum which is owing from the partnership? What are you saying?
            This is neither to be borne lightly nor to be defended carelessly. For if there are any
            private actions of the greatest, I may almost say, of capital importance, they are these
            three—the actions about trust, about guardianship, and about partnership. For
            it is equally perfidious and wicked to break faith, which is the bond of life, and to
            defraud one's ward who has come under one's guardianship, and to deceive a partner who
            has connected himself with on. in business.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>And as
            this is the case, let us consider who. it is who in this instance has deceived and
            cheated his partner. For his past life shall silently give us a trustworthy and
            important testimony one way or other. Is it Quintus Roscius? What do you say? Does not,
            as fire dropped upon water is immediately extinguished and cooled, so, does not, I say,
            a false accusation, when brought in contact with a most pure and holy life, instantly
            fall and become extinguished? Has Roscius cheated his partner? Can this guilt belong to
            this man? who, in truth, (I say it boldly,) has more honesty than skill, more truth than
            learning; whom the Roman people think even a better man than he is an actor; who is as
            worthy of the stage because of his skill, as he is wholly of the senate on account of
            his moderation.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p>But why am I so foolish as to say
            anything about Roscius to Piso? I suppose I am recommending an unknown man in many
            words. Is there any man in the whole world of whom you have a better opinion? Is there
            any man who appears to you more pure, more modest, more humane, more regardful of his
            duty, more liberal? Have even you, O Saturius, who appear against him, have you a
            different opinion? Is it not true that as often as you have mentioned his name in the
            cause, you have said that he was a good man, and have spoken of him with expressions of
            respect? which no one is in the habit of doing except in the case of either a most
            honorable man, or of a most dear friend.</p></div> 
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>While doing
            so, in truth, you appeared to me ridiculously inconstant in both injuring and praising
            the same man; in calling him at the same time a most excellent man and a most dishonest
            man. You were speaking of the man with respect, and calling him a most exemplary man,
            and at the same time you were accusing him of having cheated his partner. But I imagine
            the truth is, your praise was prompted by truth; the accusation by your duty to your
            client. You were speaking of Roscius as you really thought; you were conducting the
            cause according to the will of Chaerea. Roscius cheated him. 
             <milestone n="7" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
             This, in truth, seems absurd to the ears and minds of men. What? If he had got hold of
            some man, rich, timid, foolish and indolent, who was unable to go to law with him, still
            it would Be incredible.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>But let us see whom he has
            cheated. Roscius has cheated Caius Fannius Chaerea. I beg and entreat you, who know them
            both, compare the lives of the two men together; you who do not know them, compare the
            countenance of both. Does not his very head, and those eye-brows entirely shaved off,
            seem to smell of wickedness, and to proclaim cunning? Does he not from his toe-nails to
            his head, if the voiceless figure of a man's person can enable men to conjecture his
            character, seem wholly made up of fraud, and cheating, and lies? He who has his head and
            eyebrows always shaved that he may not be said to have one hair of an honest man about
            him. And Roscius has been accustomed to represent his figure admirably on the stage, and
            yet he does no meet with the gratitude due to such kindness. For when he acts Ballio,
            that most worthless and perjured pimp, he represents Chaerea. That foul, and impure, and
            detestable character is represented in this man's manners, and nature, and life. And why
            he should have thought Roscius like himself in dishonesty and wickedness, I do not know;
            unless, perhaps, because he observed that he imitated himself admirably in the character
            of the pimp.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>Wherefore consider over and over again,
            O Caius Piso, who is said to have cheated, and who to have been cheated. Roscius is said
            to have cheated Fannius? What is that? The honest man is said to have cheated the rogue;
            the modest man, the shameless one; the chaste man, the perjurer; the unpractised man,
            the cunning one; the liberal man is said to have cheated the covetous one. It is
            incredible how, if Fannius were said to have cheated Roscius, each fact would appear
            probable from the character of each man; both that Fannius had acted wickedly, and that
            Roscius had been cheated by his imprudence. So when Roscius is accused of having cheated
            Fannius, both parts of the story are incredible, both that Roscius should have sought
            anything covetously, and that Fannius should have lost anything by his good-nature.</p></div>
            <milestone n="8" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/><div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus">
          <p>Such is the beginning. Let us see what follows. Quintus Roscius has cheated Fannius of
            50,000 <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>. On what account? Saturius smiles; a
            cunning fellow, as he seems to himself. He says, for the sake of the fifty thousand
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>. I see; but yet I ask why he was so exceedingly
            desirous of this particular fifty thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>? For
            certainly, O Marcus Perperna and Caius Piso, they would not have been of such
            consequence to either of you, as to make you cheat your partner. I ask, then, why they
            were of such consequence to Roscius! Was he in want of money? No, he was even a rich
            man. Was he in debt? On the contrary, he was living within his income. Was he
            avaricious? far from it; even before he was a rich man he was always most liberal and
            munificent.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>Oh, in the name of good faith, of gods,
            and men! he who once refused to make a gain of three hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign>—for he certainly both could and would have earned three
            hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> if Dionysia <note anchored="true"
              >Dionysia was a celebrated dancer.</note> can earn two hundred thousand,—did
            he seek to acquire fifty thousand by the greatest dishonesty, and wickedness and
            treachery? And that sum was immense, this trifling; that was honourable, this sordid;
            that was pleasant, this bitter; that would have been his own, this must have been stated
            on an action and a trial. In these last ten years he might have earned six millions of
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> most honourably. He would not; he undertook the
            labour entitled to gain, but refused the gain of his labour. He did not yet desist from
            serving the Roman people; he has long since ceased to benefit himself.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>Would you even do this, O Fannius? And if you were able to receive
            such profits, would you not act with all your gestures, and even at the risk of your
            life? Say now that you have been cheated of fifty thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign> by Roscius, who has refused such enormous sums, not because he
            was too indolent to labour for them, but out of a magnificence of liberality. What now
            shall I say of these things which I know to a certainty occur to your minds, O judges?
            Roscius cheated you in a partnership. There are laws, there are formularies <note
              anchored="true">“As the <foreign xml:lang="lat">formulae</foreign> comprehended,
              or were supposed to comprehend, every possible form of action that could be required
              by a plaintiff; it was presumed that he could find among all the <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >formulae</foreign> some one which was adapted to his case; and he was accordingly
              supposed to be without excuse if he did not take pains to select the proper
                formula.”—<bibl>Cic. pro Rosc. Com. 8</bibl>. <bibl>Smith, Dict.
                Ant. p. 9, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Actio</foreign></bibl>.</note> established for
            every case, that no one may make a blunder, either as to the legal description of injury
            which he has suffered, or as to the sort of action he should bring; for public formulae
            have been given by the praetor to suit every evil, or vexation, or inconvenience, or
            calamity, or injury which any one can suffer and to them each private action is adapted.</p></div>
            <milestone n="9" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus">
          <p>And as this is the case, I ask why you have not Roscius as your partner before an
            arbitrator? Did you not know the formula? It was most notorious. Were you unwilling to
            adopt severe proceedings? Why so? On account of your ancient intimacy? Why then do you
            injure him now? On account of the integrity of the man? Why then do you accuse him now?
            On account of the magnitude of the crime? Is it so? The man whom you could not
            circumvent before an arbitrator, to whose decision such a matter properly belonged, will
            you seek to convict before a judge, who has no power of arbitrating in it? Either, then,
            bring this charge where it may be discussed, or do not bring it where it may not:
            although the charge is already done away with by your own evidence; for when you
            declined to adopt that formula, you showed that he had committed no fraud against the
            partnership. Oh, he made a covenant. Has he account-books, or not? If he has not, how is
            the covenant shown? If he has, why do you not tell us?</p></div>  
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>Say now, if you dare, that Roscius begged of you to appoint his own intimate friend
            arbitrator. He did not beg you to. Say that he made a covenant in order to procure his
            acquittal. He made no covenant. Ask why then he was acquitted? Because he was a man of
            the most perfect innocence and integrity. For what happened? You came of your own accord
            to the house of Roscius; you apologised to him; you begged him to announce to the judge
            that you had acted hastily, and to pardon you; you said that you would not appear
            against him; you said loudly that he owed you nothing on account of the partnership. He
            gave notice to the judge; he was acquitted. And still do you dare to mention dishonesty
            and theft? He persists in his impudence. I did all this, says he, for he had made a
            covenant with me. Yes, I suppose to procure his acquittal. What reason had he to fear
            that he would be condemned? </p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>Oh, the matter was
            evident, the theft was undeniable. A theft of what? He begins, in a manner to create
            great expectations, to relate his partnership with the old actor. 
              <milestone n="10" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
          Panurgus, says he, was a slave of Fannius. He had an equal share in him with Roscius.
            Here in the first place Saturius began to complain bitterly that Roscius had had a in
            him given to him for nothing, when he had become the property of Fannius by purchase.
            That liberal man, forsooth, that extravagant man, that man overflowing with kindness,
            made a present of his share to Roscius? No doubt of it.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>Since he rested on this point for a while, it is necessary for me also to dwell a
            little on it. You say, O Saturius, that Panurgus was the private property of Fannius.
            But I say that the whole of him belonged to Roscius, for how much of him belonged to
            Fannius? His body. How much to Roscius? His education. His person was of no value; his
            skill was valuable. As far as he belonged to Fannius, he was not worth fifty thousand
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>; as far as he belonged to Roscius, he was worth
            more than a hundred thousand. For no one looked at him because of his person; but people
            estimated him by his skill as a comic actor. For those limbs could not earn by
            themselves more than twelve <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>; owing to the
            education which was given him by Roscius, he let himself out for not less than a hundred
            thousand.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>Oh, tricky and scandalous partnership, when
            the one brings what is worth fifty thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> into
            the partnership, the other what is worth a hundred thousand; unless you are indignant at
            this, that you took the fifty thousand out of your strong box, and Roscius got his
            hundred thousand out of his learning and skill. For what was it that Panurgus brought
            with him on the stage? What was the expectation formed of him why was there such zeal
            for him, such partiality to him? Because he was the pupil of Roscius. They who loved the
            one, favoured the other; they who admired the one, approved of the other; lastly, all
            who had heard the name of the one, thought the other well-trained and accomplished. And
            this is the way with the common people; they estimate few things by the real truth, many
            things by prejudice.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>Very few observed what he knew,
            but every one asked where he had been taught; they thought that nothing poor or had
            could be produced by him. If he had come from Statilius, even if he had surpassed
            Roscius in skill, no one would have been able to see it. For just as no one supposes
            that a good son can be born to a worthless father, so no one would suppose that a good
            Comedian could be formed by a very bad actor; but because he came from Roscius, he
            appeared to know more than he really did know. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
                And this lately did actually happen in the case of Eros the comedian, for he, after he
            was driven off the stage, not merely by hisses, but even by reproaches, took refuge, as
            at an altar, in the house, and instruction, and patronage, and name of Roscius.
            Therefore, in a very short time he who had not been even one of the lowest class of
            actors, came to be reckoned among the very first comedians.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>What was it that raised him? This man's commendation alone who not
            only took this Panurgus home that he might have the name of a pupil of Roscius, but who
            also instructed him with the greatest pains and energy and patience. For the more
            skillful and ingenious any one is, the more vehement and laborious is he in teaching his
            art; for that which he himself caught quickly, he is tortured by seeing slowly
            comprehended by another. My speech has extended itself to some length, in order that you
            may thoroughly understand the conditions of this partnership.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>What then followed? A man of <placeName key="tgn,7006776"
              >Tarquinii</placeName>, Quintus Flavius by name, knew this Panurgus, the common slave
            of Roscius and Fannius, and you appointed me as the advocate to conduct the action about
            that business. The cause having been commenced, and an action being appointed according
            to the formula, “for injury and loss inflicted,” you brought it to a
            conclusion with Flavius, without my knowledge. Was it for the half share, or for the
            entire partnership? I will speak plainly. Was it for myself, or for myself and for
            yourself? Was it for myself alone? I could do so according to the precedent set by many
            people; it is lawful to do so; many men have legally done so; I have done you no injury
            in that matter. Do you demand what is due to you? Exact it, and carry it off. Let every
            one have and follow up his portion of his right. “But you managed your affair
            very well.” “Do you too manage yours well” “You
            get your half share valued at a high price.” “Do you too get yours
            valued at a high price.” “You get a hundred thousand <foreign
              xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>,”—if indeed that be true.
            “Then do you also get a hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign>.”</p></div> 
            <milestone n="12" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
             <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus">
          <p>But you may easily, both in belief and in speaking of it, have exaggerated the terms on
            which Roscius concluded his business; in fact and reality you will find them moderate
            and unimportant. For he got a farm at a time when the prices of farms were very
            low,—a farm which had not a house on it, and was not well cultivated in any
            respect, which is worth much more now than it was. And no wonder, for at that time, on
            account of the calamities of the republic, every one's possessions were uncertain; now,
            by the kindness of the immortal gods, the fortunes of every one are well assured: then
            it was an uncultivated farm, without a house; now it is beautifully cultivated, with an
            excellent villa on it.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus"><p>But since by nature you are so
            malevolent, I will never relieve you from that vexation and that anxiety. Roscius
            managed his business well; he got a most fertile farm. What is that to you? Do you
            settle your half of the matter anyhow you please. He then changes his plan of attack,
            and endeavours to invent a story which he cannot prove. “You,” says
            he, “arranged the whole matter, and not your share of it only.” The
            whole cause then is brought to this point,—whether Roscius came to a
            settlement with Flavius for his own share, or for the whole partnership.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus"><p>For I confess that, if Roscius touched anything on their joint
            account, he ought to pay it to the partnership. Did he settle the quarrel of the
            partnership, and not merely his own, when he received this farm from Flavius? If so, why
            did he not give security to Flavius, that no one else should make any demand on him? He
            who settles his own demand only, leaves to the rest their right of action unimpaired; he
            who acts for his partners, gives security that none of them shall afterwards make any
            demand. Why did it not occur to Flavius to take this precaution for himself? Was he,
            forsooth, not aware that Panurgus belonged to a partnership. He knew that. Was he not
            aware that Fannius was Roscius' partner? Thoroughly; for he himself had a law-suit
            commenced with him.</p></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus"><p>Why then does he settle this
            action, and not exact an agreement that no one shall make any further demand on him? Why
            does he lose the farm, and yet get no release from this action? Why does he act in so
            inexperienced a manner, as neither to bind Roscius by any stipulation, nor on the other
            hand to get a release from Fannius' action?</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus"><p>This
            first argument, drawn both from the rules of civil rights, and from the customs
            prevailing with respect to such security, is a most important and powerful one, which I
            would press at greater length, if I had not other more undeniable and manifest proofs in
            the cause. <milestone n="13" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
                And that you may not say I have promised this on insufficient grounds, I will call
            you—you, I say, Fannius—from your seat as a witness against
            yourself.—What is your charge? That Roscius settled with Flavius on behalf of
            the partnership.—When? Four years ago.—What is my defence? That
            Roscius settled with Flavius for his share in the property. You yourself, three years
            ago, made a new engagement with Roscius.—What? Recite that stipulation
            plainly.—Attend, I beg you, O <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName>—I am compelling Fannius against his will, and though he is
            shuffling off in every direction, to give evidence against himself. For what are the
            words of this new agreement? “Whatever I receive from Flavius, I undertake to
            pay one half of to Roscius.” These are your words, O Fannius.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus"><p>What can you get from Flavius, if Flavius owes you nothing?
            Moreover, why does he now enter into a mutual engagement about a sum which he has
            already exacted some time ago? But what can Flavius be going to give you, if he has
            already paid Roscius everything that he owed? Why is this new mutual arrangement
            interposed in so old an affair, in a matter so entirely settled, in a partnership which
            has been dissolved? Who is the drawer up of this agreement? who is the witness? who is
            the arbitrator? who? You, O <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName>: for you
            begged Quintus Roscius to give Fannius fifteen thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign>, for his care, for his labour, for having been his agent, and for
            having given security, on this condition, that, if he get anything from Flavius, he
            should give half of that sum to Roscius. Does not that agreement seem to show you with
            sufficient clearness that Roscius settled the affair on his own behalf alone?</p></div> 
             <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus"><p>But perhaps this also may occur to you, that Fannius did in
            requital promise Roscius half of whatever he might get from Flavius, but that be got
            nothing at all. What has that to do with it? You ought to regard not the result of the
            demand, but the beginning of the mutual agreement. And it does not follow, if he did not
            choose to prosecute his demand, that he did not for all that, as far as it depended on
            him, show his opinion that Roscius had only settled his own claim, and not the claim of
            the partnership. What more? Suppose I make it evident, that after the whole settlement
            come to by Roscius, after this fresh mutual agreement entered into by Fannius, Fannius
            also recovered a hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> from Flavius,
            for the loss of Panurgus? Will he after that still dare to sport with the character of
            that most excellent man, Quintus Roscius?</p></div> 
            <milestone n="14" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
               <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus">   
          <p>I asked a little before—what was very material to the business, on what
            account Flavius, when (as they say) he was settling the whole claim, did neither take
            security from Roscius, nor obtain a release from all demands from Fannius? But now I ask
            how it was that, when he had settled the whole affair with Roscius, he paid also a
            hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> to Fannius on his separate
            account? (a thing still more strange and incredible.) I should like to know, O Saturius,
            what answer are you preparing to give to this? Whether you are going to say that Fannius
            never got a hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> from Flavius at all,
            or that he got them for some other claim, and on some other account?</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus"><p>If you say it was on some other account, what dealings had you ever
            had with him? None. Had you obtained any verdict against him? No. I am wasting time to
            no purpose. He never, he says, got a hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign> from Flavius at all, neither on account of Panurgus, nor of any
            one else. If I prove that, after this recent agreement with Roscius, you did get a
            hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> from Flavius, what have you to
            allege why you should not leave the court defeated with disgrace? By what witness then
            shall I make this plain?</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus"><p>This affair, as I imagine,
            came to trial. Certainly. Who was the plaintiff? Fannius. Who the defendant? Flavius.
            Who was the judge? Cluvius. Of all these men I must produce one as witness who can say
            that the money was paid. Who of these is the most authoritative witness? Beyond all
            controversy, he who was approved of as judge by the sentence of every one. Which of the
            three then will you look to me for as a witness? The plaintiff? That is Fannius; he will
            never give evidence against himself. The defendant? That is Flavius. He has been dead
            some time. The judge? That is Cluvius. What does he say? That Flavius did pay a hundred
            thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> to Fannius on account of Panurgus. And
            if you look at the rank of Cluvius, he is a Roman knight; if at his life, he is a most
            illustrious man; if at your own opinion of him, you chose him as judge; if to his truth,
            he has said what he both could know, and ought to know.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus"><p>Deny now, deny, if you can, that credit ought to be given to a Roman knight, to an
            honest man, to your own judge. He looks round; he fumes; he denies that we are going to
            recite the testimony of Cluvius. We will recite it; you are mistaken, you are consoling
            yourself with a slight and empty hope. Recite the testimony of Titus Manilius and Caius
            Luscius Ocrea, two senators, most accomplished men, who heard it from Cluvius. 
            (<emph>The secretary reads the evidence of Manilius and Luscius.</emph>) What do you
            say now—that we are not to believe Luscius and Manilius, or that we are not to
            believe Cluvius? I will speak more plainly and openly. <milestone n="15" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            Did Luscius and Manilius hear nothing from Cluvius about the hundred thousand <foreign
              xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>? or did Cluvius say what was false to Luscius and
            Manilius? On this point I am of a calm and easy mind, and I am not particularly anxious
            as to which way you answer. For the cause of Roscius is fortified by the strongest and
            most solemn evidence of most excellent men. If you have taken time enough to consider to
            which you will refuse belief on their oath, answer me.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus"><p>Do you say that one must not believe Manilius and Luscius? Say it. Dare to say it.
            Such a saying suits your obstinacy, your arrogance, your whole life. What! Are you
            waiting till I say presently of Luscius and Manilius that they are as to rank senators;
            as to age, old; as to their nature, pious and religious; as to their property, rich and
            wealthy I will not do so; I will not, on pretence of giving these men the credit due to
            a life passed with the greatest strictness, put myself in so bad a light as to venture
            to panegyrize men so much older and nobler than myself, whose characters stand in no
            need of my praise. My youth is in more need of their favourable opinion than their
            strict old age is of my commendation. But you, O Piso, must deliberate and consider for
            a long time whether you will rather believe Chaerea, though not on his oath, and in his
            own cause, or Manilius and Luscius on their oaths, in a cause in which they have no
            interest.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus"><p>The remaining alternative is for him to
            contend that Cluvius told a falsehood to Luscius and Manilius. And, if he does that, how
            great is his impudence! Will he throw discredit on that man as a witness whom he
            approved of as a judge? Will he say that you ought not to trust that man whom he has
            trusted himself? Will he disparage the credit of that man as a witness to the judge,
            when on account of his opinion of his good faith and scrupulousness as a judge, he
            brought witnesses before him? When I produce that man as a witness, will he dare to find
            fault with him, when if I were to bring him as a judge even, he would be bound not to
            decline him? Oh, but says he, he was not on his oath when he said that to Luscius and
            Manilius. Would you believe him, if he said it on his oath?</p></div> 
            <milestone n="16" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus">
          <p>But what is the difference between a perjurer and a liar? He who is in the habit of
            lying, is in the habit of perjuring himself. The man whom I can induce to tell a lie, I
            shall easily be able to prevail on to take a false oath. For he who has once departed
            from truth, is easily led on, with no greater scruples to perjury than to a lie. For who
            is influenced by just a mention of the gods in the way of deprecating their anger, and
            not by the influence of conscience? Because the same punishment which is appointed by
            the immortal gods for a perjurer is appointed also for a liar. For the immortal gods are
            accustomed to be indignant and angry, not on account of the form of words in which an
            oath is contained, but on account of the treachery and malice by which a plot is laid to
            deceive any one.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus"><p>But I, on the contrary, argue in
            this way. The authority of Cluvius would be less if be were speaking on his oath, than
            it is now when he is not speaking on his oath. For then, perhaps, he might seem to bad
            men over eager in being a witness in a cause in which he had been judge. But now he must
            appear to all his enemies most upright and most wise, inasmuch as he only tells his
            intimate friends what he knows.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus"><p>Say now, if you can,
            if the business, if the cause permits you to, that Cluvius has spoken falsely. Has
            Cluvius spoken falsely? Truth itself lays its hand upon me, and compels me to stop, and
            dwell on this point for a short time. Whence was all this lie drawn, and where was it
            forged? Roscius, forsooth, is a deep and crafty man. He began to think of this from the
            first. Since, said he to himself, Fannius claims fifty thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign> from me, I will ask Caius Cluvius, a Roman knight, a most
            accomplished man, to tell a lie for my sake; to say that a settlement was made which was
            not made; that a hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> were given by
            Flavius to Fannius, which were not given. This is the first idea of a wicked mind, of a
            miserable disposition, of a man of no sense. What came next? </p></div>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus"><p>After he had thoroughly made up his mind, he came to Cluvius. What
            sort of a man was he? an insignificant man? No, a most influential one. A fickle man? A
            most consistent one. An intimate friend of his? A perfect stranger. After he had saluted
            him, he began to ask him, in gentle and elegant language to be
            sure,—“Tell a lie for my sake, tell some excellent men, your own
            intimate friends who are here with you, that Flavius settled with Fannius about
            Panurgus, though in truth he did not; tell them that he paid a hundred thousand <foreign
              xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign>, though in reality he did not pay a penny.”
            What answer did he give? “Oh, indeed, I will willingly and eagerly tell lies
            for your sake; and if at any time you wish me to perjure myself in order to make a
            little profit, know that I am quite ready; you need not have taken so much trouble as to
            come to me yourself; you could have arranged such a trifle as this by a
            messenger.”</p></div> 
            <milestone n="17" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus">
          <p>Oh, the faith of gods and men! Would Roscius ever have asked this of Cluvius, even if
            he had had a hundred millions of <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> at stake on the
            issue of the trial? Or would Cluvius have granted it to Roscius at his request, even if
            he had been to be a sharer in the whole booty? I scarcely, by the gods, think that you,
            O Fannius, would dare to make this request to Ballio, or to any one like him; and that
            you would be able to succeed in a matter not only false, but in its nature incredible.
            For I say nothing about Roscius and Cluvius being excellent men. I imagine them for this
            occasion to be worthless.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus"><p>Roscius, then, suborned
            Cluvius as a false witness. Why did he do it so late? Why did he do so when the second
            payment was to be made, not when the first was? for already he had paid fifty thousand
            sesterce. Secondly; if Cluvius was, by this time, persuaded to tell lies, why did he say
            that a hundred thousand <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> had been given to Fannius
            by Flavius, rather than three hundred thousand; when, according to the mutual agreement,
            a half-share of it belonged to Roscius. By this time you see, O Caius Piso, that Roscius
            had made his demand for himself alone, and had made no demand for the partnership. When
            Saturius perceives that this is proved, he does not dare to resist and struggle against
            the truth. He finds another subterfuge of dishonesty and treachery in the same track.</p></div>
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus"><p>“I admit,” says he,
            “that Roscius demanded his own share from Flavius; I admit that he left
            Fannius's right to make a similar demand entire and unimpaired; but I contend that what
            he got for himself became the common property of the partnership” than which
            nothing more tricky or more scandalous can be said. For I ask whether Roscius had the
            power to demand his share from the partnership, or not? If he could not, how did he get
            it? If he could, how was it that he did not demand it for himself? For that which is
            demanded for one's self, is certainly not exacted for another.</p></div> 
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus"><p>Is it so? If he had made a demand of what belonged to the entire
            partnership, all would equally have shared what then came in. Now, when he demanded what
            was a part of his own share, did he not demand for himself alone what he got? <milestone
              n="18" unit="chapter" resp="yonge"/><milestone unit="Para"/>What is the difference between him who goes to law for himself, and him who is assigned
            as agent for another? He who commences an action for himself, makes his demand for
            himself alone. No one can prefer a claim for another except him who is constituted his
            agent. Is it not so? If her had been your agent, you would get your own, because he had
            gained the action. But he preferred this claim in his own name; so what he got he got
            for himself, and not for you.</p></div> 
                  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus"><p>But if any one can make
            a claim on behalf of another, who is not appointed his agent, I ask why then, when
            Panurgus was slain, and an action was commenced against Fannius on the plea of injury
            sustained by the loss, you were made the agent of Roscius for that action? especially
            when, according to what you now say, whatever claim you made for yourself you made for
            him; whatever recompense you exacted for yourself, would belong to the partnership. But
            if nothing would have come to Roscius which you had got from Flavius, unless he had
            appointed you agent for his action, so nothing ought to come to you which Roscius has
            exacted for his share, since he was not appointed your agent.</p></div> 
              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus"><p>For what answer can you make to this case, O Fannius? When Roscius
            settled with Flavius for his own share, did he leave you your right of action, or not?
            If he did not leave it you, how was it that you afterwards exacted a hundred thousand
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> from him? If he did leave it, why do you claim
            from him what you ought to demand and follow up yourself? For partnership is very like
            inheritance, and, as it were, its twin sister. As a partner has a share in a
            partnership, so an heir has a share in an inheritance. As an heir prefers a claim for
            himself alone, and not for his co-heirs, so a partner prefers a claim for himself alone,
            and not for his partners. And as each prefers a claim for his own share, so he makes
            payments for his share alone; the heir, out of the share which he has received of the
            inheritance the partner, out of that property with which he entered into the
            partnership.</p></div> 
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus"><p>As Roscius could have executed a release
            to Flavius in his own name, so as to prevent you from preferring any claim; so, as he
            only exacted his own share, and left you your right to prefer a claim unimpaired, he
            ought not to share what he got with you—unless, indeed, you, by a perversion
            of all justice, are able to rob him of what is his, though you are not able to extort
            your own rights from another. Saturius persists in his opinion, that whatever a partner
            claims for himself becomes the property of the partnership. But if that be true, how
            great (plague take it!) was the folly of Roscius, who, by the advice and influence of
            lawyers, made a mutual agreement with Fannius, very carefully, that he should pay him
            half of whatever he got from Flavius; if indeed, without any security or mutual
            agreement, nevertheless, Fannius owed it to the partnership; that is to say, to Roscius 
            [The rest of this speech is lost.] <gap reason="lost"/></p></div>
          </div>
        </body>
   
      </text>
      </TEI>