<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight books - 2</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight Books</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1857</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/4/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="79" xml:id="p.79"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="book">
                <head>BOOK II.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Brutus binds the people by oath, never to suffer any king to reign at Rome,
                        obliges Tarquinius Collatinus, his colleague, to resign the consulship, and
                        leave the state; beheads some young noblemen, and among the rest his own and
                        his sister's sons, for a conspiracy to receive the kings into the city. In a
                        war against the Veientians and Tarquiniensians, he engages in single combat
                        with Aruns the son of Tarquin the Proud, and expires at the same time with
                        his adversary. The ladies mourn for him a whole year. The Capitol dedicated.
                        Porsena, king of Clusium, undertakes a war in favour of the Tarquins.
                        Bravery of Horatius Cocles, and of Mucius. Porsena concludes a peace on the
                        receipt of hostages. Conduct of Claelia. Ap. Claudius removes from the
                        country of the Sabines to Rome: for this reason the Claudian tribe is added
                        to the former number, which by this means are increased to twenty-one. A.
                        Posthumius the dictator defeats at the lake Regillus Tarquin the Proud,
                        making war upon the Romans with an army of Latins. Secession of the commons
                        to the Sacred Mount; brought back by Menenius Agrippa. Five tribunes of the
                        people created. Corioli taken by C. Martius; from that he is surnamed
                        Coriolanus. Banishment and subsequent conduct of C. M. Coriolanus. The
                        Agrarian law first made. Sp. Cassius condemned and put to death. Oppia, a
                        vestal virgin, buried alive for incontinence. The Fabian family undertake to
                        carry on that war at their own cost and hazard, against the Veientians, and
                        for that purpose send out three hundred and six men in arms, who were all
                        cut off. Ap. Claudius the consul decimates his army because he had been
                        unsuccessful in the war with the Veientians, by their refusing to obey
                        orders. An account of the wars with the Volscians, Aequians, and Veientians,
                        and the contests of the fathers with the commons. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE affairs, civil and military, of the Roman
                    people, henceforward free, their annual magistrates, and the sovereignty of the
                    laws, more powerful than that of men, I shall now detail. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> —The haughty insolence of the late king had caused this
                    liberty to be the more welcome: for the former kings reigned in such a manner
                    that they all in succession might be not undeservedly set down as founders of
                    the parts, at least of the city, which they added as new residences for the
                    population augmented by themselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor is
                    there a <pb n="80" xml:id="p.80"/> doubt but that the very same Brutus who
                    earned so much glory for expelling this haughty monarch, would have done so to
                    the greatest injury of the public weal, if, through an over-hasty desire of
                    liberty, he had wrested the kingdom from any of the preceding kings. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> For what would have been the consequence if that
                    rabble of shepherds and strangers, fugitives from their own countries, having,
                    under the protection of an inviolable asylum, found liberty, or at least
                    impunity, uncontrolled by the dread of regal authority, had begun to be
                    distracted by tribunician storms, and to engage <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> in contests with the fathers in a strange city, before the
                    pledges of wives and children, and love of the very soil, to which it requires a
                    length of time to become habituated, had united their affections. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Their affairs not yet matured would have been
                    destroyed by discord, which the tranquil moderation of the government so
                    cherished, and by proper nourishment brought to such perfection, that, their
                    strength being now developed, they were able to produce the wholesome fruits of
                    liberty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the origin of liberty you may
                    date from this period, rather because the consular authority was made annual,
                    than that any diminution was made from the kingly prerogative. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The first consuls had all their privileges and ensigns of
                    authority, only care was taken that the terror might not appear doubled, by both
                    having the fasces at the same time. Brutus was, with the consent of his
                    colleague, first attended by the fasces, who had not been a more zealous
                    assertor of liberty than he was afterwards its guardian. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> First of all he bound over the people, whilst still
                    enraptured with their newly-acquired liberty, by an oath that they would suffer
                    no one to be king in Rome, lest afterwards they might be perverted by the
                    importunities or bribes of the royal family. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Next in order, that the fulness of the house might produce more of strength in
                    the senate, he filled up the number of the senators, diminished by the king's
                    murders, to the amount of three hundred, having elected the principal men of the
                    equestrian rank; and from thence it is said the custom was derived of summoning
                    into the senate both those who were patres and those who were conscripti. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> All were called <hi rend="italics"
                            >Patres conscripti.</hi> Scil. Patres et Conscripti, the conjunction
                        being omitted. Nieb. i. p. 517. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Forsooth they styled those who were elected
                    into the new senate Conscripti. It is wonderful how <pb n="81" xml:id="p.81"/>
                    much that contributed to the concord of the state, and to attach the affection
                    of the commons to the patricians. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then attention was paid to religious matters,
                    and as some part of the public worship had been performed by the kings in
                    person, that they might not be missed in any respect, they elect a king of the
                    sacrifices. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This office they made subject to
                    the pontiff, that honour being added to the name might be no infringement on
                    their liberty, which was now their principal care. And I know not whether by
                    fencing it on every side to excess, even in the most trivial matters, they may
                    not have exceeded bounds. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For when there was
                    nothing else to offend, the name of one of the consuls became an object of
                    dislike to the state. <quote> That the Tarquinii had been too much habituated to
                        sovereignty; Priscus first commenced; that Servius Tullus reigned next; that
                        though an interval thus intervened, that Tarquinius Superbus, not losing
                        sight of the kingdom as the property of another, had reclaimed it by crime
                        and violence, as the hereditary right of his family. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> That Superbus being expelled, the government was in the
                        hands of Collatinus: that the Tarquinii knew not how to live in a private
                        station; the name pleased them not; that it was dangerous to liberty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> —Such discourses were at first gradually
                    circulated through the entire state by persons sounding their dispositions; and
                    the people, now excited by jealousy, Brutus convenes to a meeting. There first
                    of all he recites the people's oath: <quote> that they would suffer no one to be
                        king, nor any thing to be in Rome whence danger might result to liberty.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That it ought to be maintained with
                        all their might, and nothing that could tend that way ought to be
                        overlooked; he said it with reluctance, for the sake of the individual; and
                        would not say it, did not his affection for the commonwealth predominate;
                        that the people of Rome do not believe that entire liberty has been
                        recovered; that the regal family, the regal name, was not only in the state
                        but even in the government; that was unfavourable, that was injurious to
                        liberty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Do you, L. Tarquinius, </quote>
                    says he, <quote> do you, of your own accord, remove this apprehension. We
                        remember, we own it, you expelled the royal family; complete your kindness;
                        take hence the royal name —your property your fellow citizens shall not only
                        restore you, by my advice, but if any thing is wanting they will generously
                        supply. Depart in <pb n="82" xml:id="p.82"/> amity. Relieve the state from a
                        dread which is perhaps groundless. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So
                        firmly are they persuaded in mind that only with the Tarquinian race will
                        kingly power depart hence. </quote> Amazement at so extraordinary and sudden
                    an occurrence at first impeded the consul's utterance; then, when he was
                    commencing to speak, the chief men of the state stand around him, and by many
                    importunities urge the same request. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Others
                    indeed had less weight with him. After Sp. Lucretius, superior in age and rank,
                    his father-in-law besides, began to try various methods, by entreating and
                    advising alternately, that he would suffer himself to be prevailed on by the
                    general feeling of <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the state, the consul,
                    apprehending lest hereafter these same things might befall him, when again in a
                    private station, together with loss of property and other additional disgrace,
                    he resigned his consulship; and removing all his effects to Lavinium, he
                    withdrew from the state. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Collatinus
                        is supposed to have earned the odium of the people, and his consequent
                        expulsion from Rome, by his endeavours to save his nephews, the Aquillii,
                        from punishment. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Brutus, according to a decree of the senate,
                    proposed to the people, that all the family of the Tarquins should be banished
                    from Rome; and in an assembly by centuries he elected P. Valerius, with whose
                    assistance he had expelled the kings for his colleague. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though nobody doubted that a war was impending
                    from the Tarquins, yet it broke out later than was universally expected; but
                    liberty was well nigh lost by treachery and fraud, a thing they had never
                    apprehended. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There were, among the Roman
                    youth, several young men of no mean families, who, during the regal government,
                    had pursued their pleasures without any restraint; being of the same age with,
                    and companions of, the young Tarquins, and accustomed to live in princely style.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Longing for that licentiousness, now that
                    the privileges of all were equalized, they complained that the liberty of others
                    has been converted to their slavery: <quote> that a king was a human being, from
                        whom you can obtain, where right, or where wrong may be necessary; that
                        there was room for favour and for kindness; that he could be angry, and
                        could forgive; that he knew the difference between a friend and an enemy;
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that laws were a deaf, inexorable
                        thing, more beneficial and advantageous for the poor than the rich; that
                        they allowed of no relaxation or indulgence, if <pb n="83" xml:id="p.83"/>
                        you transgress bounds; that it was a perilous state, amid so so many human
                        errors, to live solely by one's integrity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst their minds were already thus
                    discontented of their own accord, ambassadors from the royal family come
                    unexpectedly, demanding restitution of their effects merely, without any mention
                    of return. After their application was heard in the senate, the deliberation on
                    it lasted for several days, (fearing) lest the non-restitution might be a
                    pretext for war, and the restitution a fund and assistance for war. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> In the mean time the ambassadors were planning
                    different schemes; openly demanding the property, they secretly concerted
                    measures for recovering the throne, and soliciting them as if for the object
                    which appeared to be under consideration, they sound their feelings; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> to those by whom their proposals were favourably
                    received they give letters from the Tarquins, and confer with them about
                    admitting the royal family into the city secretly by night. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The matter was first intrusted to brothers of
                    the name of Vitellii and those of the name of Aquilii. A sister of the Vitellii
                    had been married to Brutus the consul, and the issue of that marriage were young
                    men, Titus and Tiberius; these also their uncles admit into a participation of
                    the plot: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> several young noblemen also were
                    taken in as associates, the memory of whose names has been lost from distance of
                    time. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the mean time, when that opinion had
                    prevailed in the senate, which recommended the giving back of the property, and
                    the ambassadors made use of this as a pretext for delay in the city, because
                    they had obtained from the consuls time to procure modes of conveyance, by which
                    they might convey away the effects of the royal family; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> all this time they spend in consulting with the
                    conspirators, and by pressing they succeed in having letters given to them for
                    the Tarquins. For otherwise how were they to believe that the accounts brought
                    by the ambassadors on matters of such importance were not idle? <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The letters, given to be a pledge of their sincerity,
                    discovered the plot; for when, the day before the ambassadors set out to the
                    Tarquins, they had supped by chance at the house of the Vitellii, and the
                    conspirators there in private discoursed much together concerning their new
                    design, as is natural, one of the slaves, who had already perceived what was
                    going on, overheard their conversation; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but
                    waited for <pb n="84" xml:id="p.84"/> the occasion when the letters should be
                    given to the ambassadors, the detection of which would prove the transaction;
                    when he perceived that they were given, he laid the whole affair before the
                    consuls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls, having left their home
                    to seize the ambassadors and conspirators, crushed the whole affair without any
                    tumult; particular care being taken of the letters, lest they should escape
                    them. The traitors being immediately thrown into chains, a little doubt was
                    entertained respecting the ambassadors, and though they deserved to be
                    considered as enemies, the law of nations however prevailed. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The question concerning the restitution of the
                    tyrants' effects, which the senate had formerly voted, came again under
                    consideration. The fathers, fired with indignation, expressly forbad them either
                    to be restored or confiscated. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were given
                    to be rifled by the people, that after being made participators in the royal
                    plunder, they might lose for ever all hopes of a reconciliation with the
                    Tarquins. A field belonging to them, which lay between the city and the Tiber,
                    having been consecrated to Mars, has been called the Campus Martius. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> It happened that there was a crop of corn upon it
                    ready to be cut down, which produce of the field, as they thought it unlawful to
                    use, after it was reaped, a great number of men carried the corn and straw in
                    baskets, and threw them into the Tiber, which then flowed with shallow water, as
                    is usual in the heat of summer; that thus the heaps of corn as it stuck in the
                    shallows became settled when covered over with mud: by these and the afflux of
                    other things, which the river happened to bring thither, an island was formed by
                    degrees. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Afterwards I believe that mounds were
                    added, and that aid was afforded by art, that a surface so well raised might be
                    firm enough for sustaining temples and porticoes. After plundering the tyrants'
                    effects, the traitors were condemned and capital punishment inflicted.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their punishment was the more remarkable,
                    because the consulship imposed on the father the office of punishing his own
                    children, and him who should have been removed as a spectator, fortune assigned
                    as the person to exact the punishment. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Young
                    men of the highest quality stood tied to a stake; but the consul's sons
                    attracted the eyes of all the spectators from the rest of the criminals, as from
                    persons unknown; nor did the people pity them more on account of the severity of
                    the punishment, than the <pb n="85" xml:id="p.85"/> horrid crime by which they
                    had deserved it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That they, in that year particularly, should have brought themselves to
                        betray into the hands of Tarquin, formerly a proud tyrant, and now an
                        exasperated exile, their country just delivered, their father its deliverer,
                        the consulate which took its rise from the family of the Junii, the fathers,
                        the people, and whatever belonged either to the gods or the citizens of
                        Rome. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Niebuhr will have it that Brutus
                        punished his children by his authority as a father, and that there was no
                        appeal to the people from the father. See Nieb. i. p. 488. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls seated themselves in their
                    tribunal, and the lictors, being despatched to inflict punishment, strip them
                    naked, beat them with rods, and strike off their heads. Whilst during all this
                    time, the father, his looks and his countenance, presented a touching spectacle,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Animo patris,</hi> the strength of his mind, though that
                        of a father, being even more conspicuous, &amp;c. So Drakenborch understands
                        the passage, —this sternness of mind, he says, though he was their father,
                        was a more remarkable spectacle than his stern countenance. This character
                        of Brutus, as inferrible from the words thus interpreted, coincides with
                        that given of him by Dionysius and others. I prefer understanding the
                        passage with Crevier, scil. symptoms of paternal affection to his children
                        displaying themselves during the discharge of his duty in superintending the
                        public punishment inflicted on them. </note> the feelings of the father
                    bursting forth occasionally during the office of superintending the public
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> execution. Next after the punishment of
                    the guilty, that there might be a striking example in either way for the
                    prevention of crime, a sum of money was granted out of the treasury as a reward
                    to the discoverer; liberty also and the rights of citizenship were granted
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> him. He is said to have been the first
                    person made free by the Vindicta; some think even that the term vindicta is
                    derived from him. After him it was observed as a rule, that those who were set
                    free in this manner were supposed to be admitted to the rights of Roman
                    citizens. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Previously, by the
                        institution of Servius, only such manumitted slaves were admitted to the
                        rights of citizenship as were registered by their masters in the census.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On these things being announced to him, as
                    they had occurred, Tarquin, inflamed not only with grief for the frustration of
                    such great hopes, but with hatred and resentment also, when he saw that the way
                    was blocked up against stratagem, considering that he should have recourse to
                    war open- <pb n="86" xml:id="p.86"/> ly, went round as a suppliant <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> to the cities of Etruria, <quote> that they should
                        not suffer him, sprung from themselves, of the same blood, exiled and in
                        want, lately in possession of so great a kingdom, to perish before their
                        eyes, with the young men his sons. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That
                        others had been invited to Rome from foreign lands to the throne; that he, a
                        king, extending the Roman empire by his arms, was driven out by those
                        nearest to him by a villanous conspiracy; that they had by violence divided
                        the parts among themselves, because no one individual among them was deemed
                        sufficiently deserving of the kingdom; that they had given up his effects to
                        the people to be pillaged by them, that no one might be free from that
                        guilt. That he was desirous to recover his country and his kingdom, and to
                        punish his ungrateful subjects. That they should bring succour and aid him;
                        that they might also revenge the injuries done to them of old, their legions
                        so often slaughtered, their land taken from them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These arguments prevailed on the people of
                    Veii, and with menaces they declare that now at least, under the conduct of a
                    Roman general, their former disgrace should be wiped off, and what they had lost
                    in war should be recovered. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His name and
                    relation to them induced the people of Tarquinii to take part with him; it
                    seemed an honour that their countrymen should reign at Rome. Therefore the two
                    armies of these two states followed Tarquin in order to recover his kingdom, and
                    to take vengeance upon the Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they
                    entered the Roman territories, the consuls marched to meet them. Valerius led up
                    the foot in a square battalion, and Brutus marched before with his horse to
                    reconnoitre (the enemy). Their cavalry likewise came up first; Aruns, Tarquin's
                    son, commanded it; the king himself followed with the legions. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Aruns, when he knew at a distance by the lictors that it
                    was a consul, and on coming higher discovered for certain that it was Brutus by
                    his face, all inflamed with rage, he cried out, <quote> There is the villain who
                        has banished us from our native country! see how he rides in state adorned
                        with the ensigns of our dignity! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> now
                        assist me, gods, the avengers of kings. </quote> He put spurs to his horse
                    and drove furiously against the consul. Brutus perceived the attack made on him;
                    as it was honourable in these days for the generals to engage in combat, he
                    eagerly offered himself to the combat. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They
                    encountered one another with such furious animosity, neither mind- <pb n="87"
                        xml:id="p.87"/> ful of protecting his own person, provided he could wound
                    his adversary; so that both, transfixed through the buckler by the blow from the
                    opposite direction, fell lifeless from their horses, entangled together by the
                    two spears. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The engagement between the rest
                    of the horse commenced at the same time, and soon after the foot came up. There
                    they fought with doubtful success, and as it were with equal advantage, and the
                    victory doubtful. The right wings of both armies were victorious, and the left
                    worsted. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Veientians, accustomed to be
                    discomfited by the Roman soldiers, were routed and put to flight. The
                    Tarquinienses, who were a new enemy, not only stood their ground, but even on
                    their side obliged the Romans to give way. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the issue of this battle, so great a
                    terror seized Tarquin and the Etrurians, that both the armies, the Veientian and
                    Tarquinian, giving up the matter as impracticable, departed to their respective
                    homes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They annex strange incidents to this
                    battle, —that in the silence of the next night a loud voice was emitted from the
                    Arsian wood; that it was believed to be the voice of Silvanus: these words were
                    spoken, <quote> that more of the Etrurians by one <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">Uno plus Tuscorum.</hi>
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek"> 'Ws e(ni\plei/ous e/nth=| ma/xh| teqnh/kasi
                                Tur)r(hnw=n h(= 'Pwmai/wn. </foreign>
                        </note> had fallen in the battle; that the Roman was victorious in the war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Certainly the Romans departed thence as
                    victors, the Etrurians as vanquished. For as soon as it was light, and not one
                    of the enemy was now to be seen, P. Valerius the consul collected the spoils,
                    and returned thence in triumph to Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His
                    colleague's funeral he celebrated with all the magnificence then possible. But a
                    far greater honour to his death was the public sorrow, singularly remarkable in
                    this particular, that the matrons mourned him a year, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">A year,</hi> scil. of ten months. </note> as a parent,
                    because he had been so vigorous an avenger of violated chastity. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Afterwards the consul who survived, so changeable are
                    the minds of the people, from great popularity, encountered not only jealousy,
                    but suspicion, originating in an atrocious charge. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Report represented that he aspired to the crown, because he
                    had not substituted a colleague in the room of Brutus, and was building a house
                    on the summit of Mount Velia, that there would be there an impregnable fortress
                    on an elevated and well-for- <pb n="88" xml:id="p.88"/> tified place. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When these things, thus circulated and believed,
                    affected the consul's mind with indignation, having summoned the people to an
                    assembly, he mounts the rostrum, after lowering the fasces. It was a grateful
                    sight to the multitude that the insignia of authority were lowered to them, and
                    that an acknowledgment was made, that the majesty and power of the people were
                    greater than that of the consul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they
                    were called to silence, Valerius highly extolled the good fortune of his
                    colleague, <quote> who after delivering his country had died vested with the
                        supreme power, fighting bravely in defence of the commonwealth, when his
                        glory was in its maturity, and not yet converted into jealousy. That he
                        himself, having survived his glory, now remained as an object of accusation
                        and calumny; that from the liberator of his country he had fallen to the
                        level of the Aquilii and Vitellii. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Will no
                        merit then, says he, ever be so tried and approved by you, as to be exempted
                        from the attacks of suspicion. Could I apprehend that myself, the bitterest
                        enemy of kings, should fall under the charge of a desire of royalty?
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Could I believe that, even though I
                        dwelt in the very citadel and the Capitol, that I could be dreaded by my
                        fellow citizens? Does my character among you depend on so mere trifle? Is my
                        integrity so slightly founded, that it makes more matter where I may be,
                        than what I may be. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The house of Publius
                        Valerius shall not stand in the way of your liberty, Romans; the Velian
                        mount shall be secure to you. I will not only bring down my house into the
                        plain, but I will build it beneath the hill, that you may dwell above me a
                        suspected citizen. Let those build on the Velian mount to whom liberty is
                        more securely intrusted than to P. Valerius. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Immediately all the materials were brought
                    down to the foot of the Velian mount, and the house was built at the foot of the
                    hill where the temple of Victory now stands. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this laws were passed, which not only
                    cleared him of all suspicions of aiming at the regal power, but had so contrary
                    a tendency, that they made him popular. From thence he was surnamed Poplicola.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Above all, the laws regarding an appeal to
                    the people against the magistrates, and that devoting the life and property of
                    any one who should form a design of assuming regal authority, were grateful to
                    the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And after he had passed these
                    while sole consul, so <pb n="89" xml:id="p.89"/> that the merit in them was
                    exclusively his own, he then held an assembly for the election of a new
                    colleague. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Sp. Lucretius was elected consul,
                    who being very old, and his strength being inadequate to discharge the consular
                    duties, dies in a few days. M. Horatius Pulvillus was substituted in the room of
                    Lucretius. In some old writers I find no mention of Lucretius as consul; they
                    place Horatius immediately after Brutus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I
                    believe that, because no important event signalized his consulate, it has been
                    unnoticed. Jupiter's temple in the Capitol had not yet been dedicated; the
                    consuls Valerius and Horatius cast lots which should dedicate it. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> It fell by lot to Horatius. Publicola departed to the
                    war of the Veientians. The friends of Valerius were more annoyed than they
                    should have been, that the dedication of so celebrated a temple should be given
                    to Horatius. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Horatii being of the
                            <hi rend="italics">minores patres.</hi> Nieb. i. p. 533. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having endeavoured by every means to prevent
                    that, when all other attempts had been tried in vain, when the consul was now
                    holding the door-post during his offering of prayer to the gods, they suddenly
                    announce to him the shocking intelligence that his son was dead, and that his
                    family being defiled <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Funesta familia,</hi> as having in it an unburied corpse.
                        Thus Misenus, whilst unburied, <hi rend="italics">incestat funere
                            classem.</hi> Virg. Aen. vi. 150. </note> he could not dedicate the
                    temple. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Whether he did not believe the fact,
                    or possessed such great firmness of mind, is neither handed down for certain,
                    nor is a conjecture easy. Diverted from his purpose at this intelligence in no
                    other way than to order that the body should be buried, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> He here rejected the omen. Cic. i. 7, 14.; auguria aut
                            <hi rend="italics">oblativa</hi> sunt, quae non poscuntur, aut <hi
                            rend="italics">impetrativa,</hi> quae optata veniunt. The latter could
                        not be rejected. </note> he goes through the prayer, and dedicates the
                    temple. These were the transactions at home and abroad the first year after the
                    expulsion of the kings. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After this P.
                    Valerius, a second time, and Titus Lucretius, were elected consuls. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time the Tarquins had fled to Lars
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Lar.</hi> This is generally understood to have been a
                        title of honour equivalent to our term <hi rend="italics">Lord.</hi>
                    </note> Porsena, king of Clusium. There, mixing advice with their entreaties,
                        <quote> They sometimes besought him not to suffer them, who were descended
                        from the Etrurians, and of the same blood and name, to live in exile and
                        poverty; at other times they advised him not to let this commencing practice
                        of expelling <pb n="90" xml:id="p.90"/> kings pass unpunished. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> That liberty has charms enough in itself;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and unless kings defend their crowns
                        with as much vigour as the people pursue their liberty, that the highest
                        must be reduced to a level with the lowest; there will be nothing exalted,
                        nothing distinguished above the rest; and hence there must be an end of
                        regal government, the most beautiful institution both among gods and men. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Porsena, thinking that it would be an honour
                    to the Tuscans both that there should be a king at Rome, and especially one of
                    the Etrurian nation, marched towards Rome with a hostile army. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Never before on any other occasion did so great terror
                    seize the senate; so powerful was the state of Clusium at the time, and so great
                    the renown of Porsena. Nor did they only dread their enemies, but even their own
                    citizens, lest the common people, through excess of fear, should, by receiving
                    the Tarquins into the city, accept peace even if purchased with slavery.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Many conciliatory concessions were
                    therefore granted to the people by the senate during that period. Their
                    attention, in the first place, was directed to the markets, and persons were
                    sent, some to the Volscians, others to Cumae, to buy up corn. The privilege
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Arbitrium</hi> signifies not only the
                            <quote>privilege,</quote> but the <quote>rent</quote> paid for such
                        privilege, or right of monopoly. </note> of selling salt, also, because it
                    was farmed at a high rent, was all taken into the hands of government, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Was all taken into the hands of government.</hi> In my
                        version of this passage I have conformed to the emendation of the original
                        first proposed by Gronovius, and admitted by Stroth and Bekker; scil. <hi
                            rend="italics">in publicum omne sumptum.</hi> —They did not let these
                        salt-works by auction, but took them into their own management, and carried
                        them on by means of persons employed to work on the public account. These
                        salt-works, first established at Ostia by Ancus, were, like other public
                        property, farmed out to the publicans. As they had a high rent to pay, the
                        price of salt was raised in proportion; but now the patricians, to curry
                        favour with the plebeians, did not let the salt-pits to private tenants, but
                        kept them in the hands of public labourers, to collect all the salt for the
                        public use; and appointed salesmen to retail it to the people at a cheaper
                        rate. See Stocker's ed. </note> and withdrawn from private individuals; and
                    the people were freed from port-duties and taxes; that the rich, who were
                    adequate to bearing the burden, should contribute; that the poor paid tax enough
                    if they educated their <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> children. This
                    indulgent care of the fathers accordingly kept the whole state in such concord
                    amid the subsequent se- <pb n="91" xml:id="p.91"/> verities in the siege and
                    famine, that the highest abhorred the name of king not more than the <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> lowest; nor was any single individual afterwards so
                    popular by intriguing practices, as the whole senate then was by their excellent
                    government. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some parts seemed secured by the walls, others
                    by the interposition of the Tiber. The Sublician bridge well nigh afforded a
                    passage to the enemy, had there not been one man, Horatius Cocles, (that defence
                    the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> fortune of Rome had on that day,) who,
                    happening to be posted on guard at the bridge, when he saw the Janiculum taken
                    by a sudden assault, and that the enemy were pouring down from <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> thence in full speed, and that his own party, in
                    terror and confusion, were abandoning their arms and ranks, laying hold of them
                    one by one, standing in their way, and appealing to the faith of gods and men,
                    he declared, <quote> That their flight would avail them nothing if they deserted
                        their post; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> if they passed the bridge and
                        left it behind them, there would soon be more of the enemy in the Palatium
                        and Capitol than in the Janiculum; for that reason he advised and charged
                        them to demolish the bridge, by their sword, by fire, or by any means
                        whatever; that he would stand the shock of the enemy as far as could be done
                        by one man. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then advances to the first entrance of the
                    bridge, and being easily distinguished among those who showed their backs in
                    retreating from the fight, facing about to engage the foe hand to hand, by his
                    surprising bravery he terrified the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two
                    indeed a sense of shame kept with him, Sp. Lartius and T. Herminius, men eminent
                    for their birth, and renowned for their gallant exploits. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> With them he for a short time stood the first storm of the
                    danger, and the severest brunt of the battle. But as they who demolished the
                    bridge called upon them to retire, he obliged them also to withdraw to a place
                    of safety on a small portion of the bridge still left. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then casting his stern eyes round all the officers of the
                    Etrurians in a threatening manner, he sometimes challenged them singly,
                    sometimes reproached them all; <quote> the slaves of haughty tyrants, who,
                        regardless of their own freedom, came to oppress the liberty of others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They hesitated for a considerable time,
                    looking round one at the other, to commence the fight; shame then put the army
                    in motion, and a shout being raised, they hurl their weapons from all sides on
                    their single adversary; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and when they all
                    stuck in <pb n="92" xml:id="p.92"/> the shield held before him, and he with no
                    less obstinacy kept possession of the bridge with firm step, they now
                    endeavoured to thrust him down from it by one push, when at once the crash of
                    the falling bridge, at the same time a shout of the Romans raised for joy at
                    having completed their purpose, checked their ardour with sudden panic.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then Cocles says, <quote> Holy father
                        Tiberinus, I pray that thou wouldst receive these arms, and this thy
                        soldier, in thy propitious stream. </quote> Armed as he was, he leaped into
                    the Tiber, and amid showers of darts hurled on him, swam across safe to his
                    party, having dared an act which is likely to obtain more fame than credit with
                    posterity. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The state was grateful towards
                    such valour; a statue was erected to him in the comitium, and as much land was
                    given to him as he ploughed around in one day. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> The zeal of private individuals also was conspicuous among the public
                    honours. For, amid the great scarcity, each person contributed something to him
                    according to his supply at home, depriving himself of his own support. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Porsena being repulsed in his first attempt,
                    having changed his plans from a siege to a blockade, after he had placed a
                    garrison in Janiculum, pitched his camp in the plain and on the banks of the
                    Tiber. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then sending for boats from all parts,
                    both to guard the river, so as not to suffer any provision to be conveyed to
                    Rome, and also to transport his soldiers across the river, to plunder different
                    places as occasion required; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> in a short time
                    he so harassed the entire country round Rome, that not only every thing else
                    from the country, but even their cattle, was driven into the city, and nobody
                    durst venture thence without the gates. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                    liberty of action was granted to the Etrurians, not more through fear than from
                    policy; for Valerius, intent on an opportunity of falling unawares upon a number
                    of them, and when straggling, a remiss avenger in trifling matters, reserved the
                    weight of his vengeance for more important occasions. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Wherefore, to decoy the pillagers, he ordered his men to
                    drive their cattle the next day out at the Esquiline gate, which was farthest
                    from the enemy, presuming that they would get intelligence of it, because during
                    the blockade and famine some slaves would turn traitors and desert. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly they were informed of it by a deserter,
                    and parties more numerous than usual, in hopes of seizing the entire body,
                    crossed the river. <pb n="93" xml:id="p.93"/> Then P. Valerius commanded T.
                    Herminius, with a small body of <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> men, to lie
                    concealed two miles from the city, on the Gabian road, and Sp. Lartius, with a
                    party of light-armed troops, to post himself at the Colline gate till the enemy
                    should pass by, and then to throw himself in their way so that there may be no
                    return to the river. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The other consul, T.
                    Lucretius, marched out of the Naevian gate with some companies of soldiers;
                    Valerius himself led some chosen cohorts down from the Cœlian mount, and they
                    were first descried by the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Herminius,
                    when he perceived the alarm, rose out of the ambush and fell upon the rear of
                    the Tuscans, who had charged Valerius. The shout was returned on the right and
                    left, from the Colline gate on the one hand, and the Naevian on the other.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By this stratagem the plunderers were put
                    to the sword between both, they not being a match in strength for fighting, and
                    all the ways being blocked up to prevent escape: this put an end to the
                    Etrurians strolling about in so disorderly a manner. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nevertheless the blockade continued, and there
                    was a scarcity of corn, with a very high price. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Porsena entertained a hope that by continuing the siege he should take the
                    city, when C. Mucius, a young nobleman, to whom it seemed a disgrace that the
                    Roman people, when enslaved under kings, had never been confined within their
                    walls in any war, nor by any enemy, should now when a free people be blocked up
                    by <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> these very Etrurians whose armies they
                    had often routed, thinking that such indignity should be avenged by some great
                    and daring effort, at first designed of his own accord to penetrate into the
                    enemy's camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, being afraid if he went
                    without the permission of the consuls, or the knowledge of any one, he might be
                    seized by the Roman guards and brought back as a deserter, the circumstances of
                    the city at the time justifying the charge, he went to the senate: <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Fathers,</quote> says he, <quote> I intend to cross the Tiber, and enter
                        the enemy's camp, if I can; not as a plunderer, or as an avenger in our turn
                        of their devastations. A greater deed is in my mind, if the gods assist.
                    </quote> The senate approved his design. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                    set out with a sword concealed under his garment. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> When he came thither, he stationed himself among the
                    thickest of the crowd, near the king's tribunal. There, when the soldiers were
                    receiving their pay, and the king's <pb n="94" xml:id="p.94"/> secretary sitting
                    by him, dressed nearly in the same style, was busily engaged, and to him they
                    commonly addressed themselves, being afraid to ask which of them was Porsena,
                    lest by not knowing the king he should discover on himself, as fortune blindly
                    directed the blow, he killed the secretary instead of the king. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When, as he was going off thence where with his bloody
                    dagger he had made his way through the dismayed multitude, a concourse being
                    attracted at the noise, the king's guards immediately seized and brought him
                    back standing alone before the king's tribunal; <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> even then, amid such menaces of fortune, more capable of inspiring dread than
                    of feeling it, <quote>I am,</quote> says he, <quote> a Roman citizen, my name is
                        Caius Mucius; an enemy, I wished to slay an enemy, nor have I less of
                        resolution to suffer death than I had to inflict it. Both to act and to
                        suffer with fortitude is a Roman's part. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Nor have I alone harboured such feelings towards you; there is after me a
                        long train of persons aspiring to the same honour. Therefore, if you choose
                        it, prepare yourself for this peril, to contend for your life every hour; to
                        have the sword and the enemy in the very entrance of your pavilion; this is
                        the war which we the Roman youth declare against you; <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> dread not an army in array, nor a battle; the affair
                        will be to yourself alone and with each of us singly. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the king, highly incensed, and at the
                    same time terrified at the danger, in a menacing manner, commanded fires to be
                    kindled about him, if he did not speedily explain the plots, which, by his
                    threats, he had darkly insinuated against him; <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> Mucius said, <quote> Behold me, that you may be sensible of how little
                        account the body is to those who have great glory in view; </quote> and
                    immediately he thrusts his right hand into the fire that was lighted for the
                    sacrifice. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When he continued to broil it as
                    if he had been quite insensible, the king, astonished at this surprising sight,
                    after he had leaped from his throne and commanded the young man to be removed
                    from the altar, says, <quote> Be gone, having acted more like an enemy towards
                        thyself than me. I would encourage thee to persevere in thy valour, if that
                        valour stood on the side of my country. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> I
                        now dismiss you untouched and unhurt, exempted from the right of war.
                    </quote> Then Mucius, as if making a return for the kindness, says, "Since
                    bravery is honoured by you, so that you have obtained by kindness that which you
                    could not by <pb n="95" xml:id="p.95"/> threats, three hundred of us, the chief
                    of the Roman youth, have conspired to attack you in this manner. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> It was my lot first. The rest will follow, each in
                    his turn, according as the lot shall set him forward, unless fortune shall
                    afford an opportunity of you. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mucius being dismissed, to whom the cognomen
                    of Scaevola was afterwards given, from the loss of his right hand, ambassadors
                    from Porsena followed him to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The risk of
                    the first attempt, from which nothing had saved him but the mistake of the
                    assailant, and the risk to be encountered so often in proportion to the number
                    of conspirators, made so strong an impression upon him, that of his own accord
                    he made propositions of peace to the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Mention was made to no purpose regarding the restoration of the Tarquinii to the
                    throne, rather because he had been unable to refuse that to the Tarquinii, than
                    from not knowing that it would be refused to him by the Romans. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The condition of restoring their territory to the
                    Veientians was obtained by him, and the necessity of giving hostages in case
                    they wished the garrison to be withdrawn from the Janiculum was extorted from
                    the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Peace being concluded on these
                    terms, Porsena drew his troops out of the Janiculum, and marched out of the
                    Roman territories. The fathers gave Mucius, as a reward of his valour, lands on
                    the other side of the Tiber, which were afterwards called the Mucian meadows.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By this honour paid to valour the women
                    were excited to merit public distinctions. As the camp of the Etrurians had been
                    pitched not far from the banks of the Tiber, a young lady named Claelia, one of
                    the hostages, deceiving her keepers, swam over the river, amidst the darts of
                    the enemy, at the head of a troop of virgins, and brought them all safe to their
                    relations. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the king was informed of this,
                    at first highly incensed, he sent deputies to Rome to demand the hostage
                    Claelia; that he did not regard the others; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    and afterwards, being changed into admiration of her courage, he said,
                        <quote>that this action surpassed those of Cocles and Mucius,</quote> and
                    declared, <quote> as he would consider the treaty as broken if the hostage were
                        not delivered up, so, if given up, he would send her back safe to her
                        friends. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Both sides kept their faith: the Romans
                    restored their pledge of peace according to treaty; and with the king of Etruria
                    merit found not only security, <pb n="96" xml:id="p.96"/> but honour; and, after
                    making encomiums on the young lady, promised to give her, as a present, half of
                    the hostages, and that she should choose whom she pleased. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> When they were all brought out, she is said to have pitched
                    upon the young boys below puberty, which was both consonant to maiden delicacy,
                    and by consent of the hostages themselves it was deemed reasonable, that that
                    age which was most exposed to injury should be freed from the enemy's hand.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The peace being re-established, the
                    Romans marked the uncommon instance of bravery in the woman, by an uncommon kind
                    of honour, an equestrian statue; (the statue representing) a lady sitting on
                    horseback was placed at the top of the Via Sacra. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Inconsistent with this so peaceful a departure
                    of the Etrurian king from the city, is the custom handed down from the ancients,
                    and which continues down to our times among other usages at public sales, (I
                    mean) that of selling the goods of king Porsena; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> the origin <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">The origin.</hi> Niebuhr mentions a more probable one.
                        See Nieb. i. p. 541; ii. p. 204. </note> of which custom must either have
                    occurred during the war, and was not relinquished in peace, or it must have
                    increased from a milder source than the form of expression imports, of selling
                    the goods in a hostile manner. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of the accounts
                    handed down, the most probable is, that Porsena, on retiring from the Janiculum,
                    made a present to the Romans of his camp well stored with provisions conveyed
                    from the neighbouring and fertile fields of Etruria, the city being then
                    exhausted by the long siege; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that this, lest
                    it should be carried away in a hostile manner, by the people being admitted in,
                    was then sold, and called the goods of Porsena, the expression rather importing
                    gratitude for the gift, than an auction of the king's property, which never even
                    was in the power of the Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Porsena,
                    after ending the Roman war, that his army might not seem to have been led into
                    these parts without effecting any thing, sent his son Aruns with a part of his
                    forces to besiege Aricia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The matter not being
                    expected, the Aricians were at first terrified; afterwards assistance, which was
                    sent for from the people of Latium and Cumae, inspired so much hope, that they
                    ventured to meet them in the field. At the commencement of the battle the
                    Etrurians attacked the Aricians so furiously, that they routed them at the first
                    onset. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the Cuman cohorts, op- <pb n="97"
                        xml:id="p.97"/> posing stratagem to force, moved off a little to one side,
                    and when the enemy were carried beyond them in great disorder, they faced about
                    and charged them in the rear. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By this means
                    the Etrurians, when they had almost got the victory, were enclosed and cut to
                    pieces. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Niebuhr thinks, that from
                        this defeat of the Etrurians may be dated the commencement of the recovery
                        of their liberty by the Romans, and that the flight of the Roman hostages,
                        the sale of Porsena's goods, &amp;c. were subsequent to it. </note> A very
                    small part of them, having lost their general, because they had no nearer
                    refuge, came to Rome without their arms, in the condition and with the air of
                    suppliants. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There they were kindly received
                    and provided with lodgings. When their wounds were cured, many of them went home
                    and told the kind hospitality they had met with. Affection for their hosts and
                    for the city detained many at Rome; a place was assigned them to dwell in, which
                    they have ever since called the Tuscan Street. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then P. Lucretius and P. Valerius Publicola
                    were elected consuls. This year ambassadors came from Porsena for the last time,
                    regarding the restoration of Tarquin to the throne. And when they were answered,
                    that the senate would send deputies to the king; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> some of the principal persons of that order were forthwith despatched to
                    represent to him <quote> that it was not because the answer could not have been
                        given in a few words, that the royal family would not be received, that
                        select members of the senate had been deputed to him, rather than an answer
                        given to his ambassadors at Rome; but (it was done) that all mention of the
                        matter might be put an end to for evermore, and that their minds might not
                        be disturbed amid so many mutual acts of kindness, by his requiring what was
                        adverse to the liberty of the Roman people, and by their denying to him to
                        whom they would willingly deny nothing, unless they would submit to their
                        own ruin. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the Roman people were not
                        now under a kingly government, but in a state of freedom, and were firmly
                        determined rather to open their gates to enemies than to kings. That it was
                        the wish of all, that their city might have the same period of existence as
                        their freedom in that city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Wherefore, if
                        he wished Rome to be safe, they entreated that he would suffer it to be
                        free. </quote> The king, overcome by modesty, says, "Since it is your firm
                    and fixed <pb n="98" xml:id="p.98"/> resolve, I will neither tease you by
                    repeatedly urging these same subjects more frequently, nor will I disappoint the
                    Tarquinii by holding out hopes of aid which it is not in my power to give them;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> whether they have need of peace, or of
                    war, let them seek another place from here for their exile, that nothing may
                    disturb the peace between you and me. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To these
                    kind promises he added actions still more friendly, for he delivered up the
                    remainder of the hostages, and restored to them the land of the Veientians,
                    which had been taken from them by the treaty concluded at Janiculum. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Tarquin, all hopes of return being now cut off, went
                    to Tusculum to live in exile with his son-in-law Mamilius Octavius. Thus the
                    peace between Porsena and the Romans was inviolably preserved. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> M. Valerius and P. Posthumius were chosen
                    consuls. This year war was carried on successfully against the Sabines; the
                    consuls received the honour of a triumph. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Upon
                    this the Sabines made preparations for war on a larger scale. To make head
                    against them, and lest any sudden danger might arise from Tusculum, (whence they
                    suspected a war, though it was not yet declared,) P. Valerius was created consul
                    a fourth time, and T. Lucretius a second time. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    A disturbance arising among the Sabines, between the advisers of war and of
                    peace, transferred from thence some additional strength to the Romans.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For Attus Clausus, afterwards called at
                    Rome Appius Claudius, when he himself, being an adviser of peace, was hard put
                    to it by those who abetted the war, and was not a match for the faction, fled
                    from Regillum to Rome, accompanied by a great number of clients. The rights of
                    citizenship and land on the other side of the Anio were conferred on them.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was called the old Claudian tribe, and
                    was increased by the addition of some tribesmen who had come from that country.
                    Appius, being chosen into the senate, was soon after advanced to the highest
                    dignity of that order. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls having
                    entered the territories of the Sabines with a hostile army, after they had, both
                    by laying waste their country, and afterwards by defeating them in battle, so
                    weakened the power of the enemy, that they had no reason to dread their taking
                    up arms again for a long time, returned to Rome in triumph. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The following year, Agrippa Menenius and P. Posthumius
                    being consuls, P. Valerius, al- <pb n="99" xml:id="p.99"/> lowed by universal
                    consent to be the ablest man in Rome, in the arts both of peace and war, died in
                    the height of glory, but so poor, that means to defray the expenses of his
                    funeral were wanting: he was buried at the public charge. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The matrons mourned for him as they had done for Brutus.
                    The same year two Latin colonies, Pometia and Cora, revolted to the Auruncians.
                    War was commenced against the Auruncians, and after defeating a numerous army of
                    them who boldly met the consuls entering their frontiers, the whole Auruncian
                    war was confined to Pometia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor, after the
                    battle was over, did they refrain from slaughter more than in the heat of the
                    action; for a greater number were slain than taken, and the prisoners they put
                    to death indiscriminately. Nor did the enemy, in their resentment, spare even
                    the three hundred hostages which they had received. This year also the consuls
                    triumphed at Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following consuls, Opiter Virginius and
                    Sp. Cassius, first endeavoured to take Pometia by storm, and afterwards by
                    raising vineae and other works. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But the
                    Auruncians, prompted more by an irreconcilable hatred against them, than induced
                    by hopes of success, or by a favourable opportunity, sallied out of the town,
                    and though more of them were armed with lighted torches than swords, filled all
                    places with fire and slaughter. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After they had
                    burnt down the vineae, slain and wounded many of the enemy, they were near
                    killing one of the consuls, who had been thrown from his horse and severely
                    wounded (which of them authors do not mention). Upon this they returned to Rome,
                    foiled in their object; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the consul was left
                    among many more who were wounded with very uncertain hopes of his recovery.
                    After a short time, sufficient for curing their wounds and recruiting their
                    army, they marched against Pometia with redoubled fury and augmented strength.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When, the vineae having been repaired and
                    the other apparatus of war, the soldiers were on the point of scaling the walls,
                    the town surrendered. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Yet though the town had
                    surrendered, the leading men of the Auruncians, with no less cruelty than if it
                    had been taken by assault, were beheaded indiscriminately; the others who were
                    colonists were sold by auction, the town was razed, and the land sold.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls obtained a triumph more from
                    having severely gratified their revenge, than in con- <pb n="100" xml:id="p.100"
                    /> sequence of the importance of the war thus brought to a close. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following year had Postumus Cominius and
                    T. Lartius for consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On this year, during
                    the celebration of the games at Rome, as some of the courtesans were being
                    carried off by some of the Sabine youth in a frolic, a mob having assembled, a
                    scuffle ensued, and almost a battle; and from this inconsiderable affair the
                    whole nation seemed inclined to a renewal of hostilities. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Besides the dread of the Latin war, this accession was
                    further made to their fears; certain intelligence was received that thirty
                    different states had entered into a confederacy against them, at the instigation
                    of Octavius Mamilius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While the city was
                    perplexed amid this expectation of such important events, mention was made for
                    the first time of nominating a dictator. But in what year or who the consuls
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Nec quibus consulibus parum creditum sit,</hi> scil.
                        fides non habita fuerit. Arnold in his Roman Hist. considers this to have
                        been the true cause of creating a dictator. </note> were in whom confidence
                    was not reposed, because they were of the Tarquinian faction, (for that also is
                    recorded,) or who was elected dictator for the first time, is not satisfactorily
                    established. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Among the oldest writers however
                    I find that Titus Lartius was appointed the first dictator, and Spurius Cassius
                    master of the horse. They chose men of consular dignity, for so the law, made
                    for the election of a dictator, ordained. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For
                    this reason, I am more inclined to believe that Lartius, who was of consular
                    rank, was annexed to the consuls as their director and master, rather than
                    Manius Valerius, the son of Marcus and grandson of Volesus, who had not yet been
                    consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For, had they intended to choose a
                    dictator from that family in particular, they would much rather have chosen his
                    father, Marcus Valerius, a consular person, and a man of distinguished merit.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the creation of the dictator first at
                    Rome, when they saw the axes carried before him, great awe struck the common
                    people, so that they became more submissive to obey orders. For neither was
                    there now, as under the consuls who possessed equal power, the assistance of one
                    of the two, nor was there appeal, nor was there any resource any where but in
                    attentive submission. The creation of a dictator at Rome terrified the Sabines,
                    and the more effectually, because <pb n="101" xml:id="p.101"/> they thought he
                    was created on their account. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics"> En <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> magis quod propter
                            se. </hi> From this one would be disposed to suspect that the dictator
                        was created to take on him the management of war. See Nieb. p. 553, and
                        Niebhr. Epit. by Twiss, Append. p. 355. </note> Wherefore they sent
                    ambassadors to sue for peace, to whom, <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> when
                    earnestly entreating the dictator and senate to pardon the young men's offence,
                    an answer was given that the young men could easily be forgiven, but not the old
                    men, who continually raised one war after another. Nevertheless they continued
                    to treat about <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> a peace, and it would have
                    been grated, if the Sabines would bring themselves to make good the expenses
                    incurred on the war (for that was demanded). War was proclaimed; a tacit truce
                    kept the year quiet. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Servius Sulpicius and M. Tullius were consuls
                    the next year: nothing worth mentioning happened. Then T. Aebutius and C.
                    Vetusius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In their consulship, Fidenae was
                    besieged, Crustumeria taken, and Praeneste revolted from the Latins to the
                    Romans. Nor was the Latin war, which had been fomenting for several years, any
                    longer deferred. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A. Postumius dictator, and T.
                    Aebutius his master of the horse, marching with a numerous army of horse and
                    foot, met the enemy's forces at the lake Regillus, in the territory of Tusculum,
                    and, because it was heard that the Tarquins were <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> in the army of the Latins, their rage could not be
                    restrained, but they must immediately come to an engagement. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the battle was more obstinate and fierce than
                    usual. For the generals were present not only to direct matters by their orders,
                    but even charged one another, exposing their own persons. And there was hardly
                    any of the principal officers of either side who came off unwounded except the
                    Roman dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As Postumius was drawing up
                    his men and encouraging them in the first line, Tarquinius Superbus, though now
                    enfeebled by age, spurred on his horse with great fury to attack him; but being
                    wounded in the side, he was carried off by a patty of his own men to a place of
                    safety. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the other wing also, Aebutius,
                    master of the horse, had charged Octavius Mamilius; nor was his approach
                    unobserved by the Tusculan general, who also briskly spurred on his horse to
                    encounter him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And such was their impetuosity
                    as they advanced with hostile spears, that Aebutius was run through the arm and
                    Mamilius struck on the breast. The Latins received the latter into their <pb
                        n="102" xml:id="p.102"/> second line; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but
                    as Aebutius was not able to wield his lance with his wounded arm, he retired
                    from the battle. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Latin general, not in
                    the least discouraged by his wound, stirs up the fight; and because he saw his
                    own men begin to give ground, sent for a company of Roman exiles to support
                    them, commanded by Tarquin's son. This body, inasmuch as they fought with
                    greater fury from having been banished from their country, and lost their
                    estates, restored the battle for a short time. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Romans were beginning to give ground
                    on that side, M. Valerius, brother to Poplicola, having observed young Tarquin
                    boldly figuring away at the head of his exiles, fired with the renown of his
                    family, that the slaying of the princes might belong to the same family whose
                    glory their expulsion had been, clapped spurs to his <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> horse, and with his javelin presented made towards Tarquin.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Tarquin retired from his violent enemy
                    into a battalion of his own men. As Valerius rushed rashly into the line of the
                    exiles, one of them ran him sideways through the body, and as the horse was in
                    no way retarded by the wound of his rider, the expiring Roman fell to the
                    ground, his arms falling over him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Postumius
                    the dictator, on seeing so distinguished a man slain, the exiles advancing
                    boldly in a body, and his own men disheartened and giving ground, gives the
                    signal to <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> his own cohort, a chosen body of
                    men which he kept for the defence of his person, to treat every Roman soldier
                    whom they should see fly from the battle as an enemy. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Upon this the Romans, by reason of the danger on both
                    sides, turned from their flight against the enemy, and, the battle being
                    restored, the dictator's cohort now for the first time engaged in the fight, and
                    with fresh vigour and undaunted resolution falling on the wearied exiles, cut
                    them to pieces. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here another engagement took
                    place between the leading officers. The Latin general, on seeing the cohort of
                    the exiles almost surrounded by the Roman dictator, advanced in haste to the
                    front with some companies of the body of reserve. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> T. Herminius, a lieutenant-general, having seen them moving
                    in a body, and well knowing Mamilius, distinguished from the rest by his armour
                    and dress, encountered the leader of the enemy with a force so much superior to
                    that wherewith the general of the horse had lately done, that at one thrust <pb
                        n="103" xml:id="p.103"/> he ran him through the side and slew him;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and while stripping the body of his enemy,
                    he himself received a wound with a javelin; and though brought back to the camp
                    victorious, yet he died during the first dressing of it. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Then the dictator flies to the cavalry, entreating them in
                    the most pressing terms, as the foot were tired out with fighting, to dismount
                    from their horses and join the fight. They obeyed his orders, dismounted, flew
                    to the front, and taking their post at the first line, cover themselves with
                    their targets. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The infantry immediately
                    recovered courage, when they saw the young noblemen sustaining a share of the
                    danger with them, the mode of fighting being now assimilated. Thus at length
                    were the Latins beaten back, and their line giving way, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> By giving up the advantage of their horses, and
                        forgetting their superiority of rank. </note> they retreated. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The horses were then brought up to the cavalry that
                    they might pursue the enemy, and the infantry likewise followed. On this, the
                    dictator, omitting nothing (that could conciliate) divine or human aid, is said
                    to have vowed a temple to Castor, and likewise to have promised rewards to the
                    first and second of the soldiers who should enter the enemy's camp. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> And such was their ardour, that the Romans took the
                    camp with the same impetuosity wherewith they had routed the enemy in the field.
                    Such was the engagement at the lake Regillus. The dictator and master of the
                    horse returned to the city in triumph. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For the next three years there was neither
                    settled peace nor open war. The consuls were Q. Claelius and T. Lartius. After
                    them A. Sempronius and M. Minucius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In their
                    consulship, a temple was dedicated to Saturn, and the Saturnalia appointed to be
                    kept as a festival. Then A. Postumius and T. Virginius were chosen consuls.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In some authors I find that the battle at
                    the lake Regillus was not fought till this year, and that A. Postumius, because
                    the fidelity of his colleague was suspected, laid down his office, and thereupon
                    was created dictator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Such great mistakes of
                    dates perplex one with the history of these tines, the magistrates being
                    arranged differently in different writers, that you cannot determine what
                    consuls succeeded certain consuls, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Qui consules secundum quosdam, who were the consuls that came after certain
                        consuls. </note> nor in what particular year every remarkable action <pb
                        n="104" xml:id="p.104"/> happened, by reason of the antiquity, not only of
                    the facts, but also <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> of the historians. Then
                    Ap. Claudius and P. Servilius were elected consuls. This year was remarkable for
                    the news of Tarquin's death. He died at Cumae, whither he had fled to the tyrant
                    Aristodemus, after the reduction of the power <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    of the Latins. The senate and people were elated by this news. But with the
                    senators their satisfaction was too extravagant, for by the chief men among them
                    oppression began to be practised on the people to whom they <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> had to that day been attentive to the utmost of their
                    power. The same year the colony which king Tarquin had sent to Signia was
                    recruited by filling up the number of the colonists. The tribes at Rome were
                    increased to twenty-one. And the temple of Mercury was dedicated the fifteenth
                    of May. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the Latin war, there had been neither
                    peace nor war with the nation of the Volscians; for both the Volscians had
                    raised auxiliary troops to send to the Latins had not so much expedition been
                    used by the Roman dictator, and the Roman employed this expedition that he might
                    not have to contend in one and the same battle with the Latin and the Volscian.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In resentment of this, the consuls marched
                    their army into the Volscian territory; the unexpected proceeding alarmed the
                    Volscians, who dreaded no chastisement of mere intention; unmindful of arms,
                    they gave three hundred children of the principal men of Cora and Pometia as
                    hostages. Upon this the legions were withdrawn without coming to any action.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Not long after their natural disposition
                    returned to the Volscians, now delivered of their fears; they again make secret
                    preparation for war, having taken the Hernicians into an alliance with them.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They send ambassadors in every direction
                    to stir up Latium. But the recent defeat received at the lake Regillus, could
                    scarcely restrain the Latins from offering violence to the ambassadors through
                    resentment and hatred of any one who would advise them to take up arms. Having
                    seized the Volscians, they brought them to Rome. They were there delivered up to
                    the consuls, and information was given that the Volscians and Hernicians were
                    making preparations for war against the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The matter being referred to the senate, it was so gratifying to the senators
                    that they both sent back six thousand prisoners to the Latins, and referred to
                    the new magistrates the business regarding the treaty, which had <pb n="105"
                        xml:id="p.105"/> been almost absolutely refused them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Upon this indeed the Latins were heartily glad at what they
                    had done, th advisers of peace were in high esteem. They send a crown of gold to
                    the Capitol as an offering to Jupiter. Along with the ambassadors and the
                    offering there came a great crowd, consisting of the prisoners who had been sent
                    back to their friends. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They proceed to the
                    houses of those persons with whom each had been in servitude, and return thanks
                    for their having been generously kept and treated during their calamity. They
                    then form connexions of hospitality. And never at any former time was the Latin
                    name more closely united to the Roman state, either by public or private ties. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But both the Volscian war was threatening, and
                    the state, being disturbed within itself, glowed with intestine animosity
                    between the senate and people, chiefly on account of those confined for debt.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They complained loudly, that whilst
                    fighting abroad for liberty and dominion, they were captured and oppressed at
                    home by their fellow citizens; and that the liberty of the people was more
                    secure in war than in peace, among enemies than among their fellow citizens; and
                    this feeling of discontent, increasing of itself, the striking sufferings of an
                    individual still further aggravated. A certain person advanced in years threw
                    himself into the forum with all the badges of his miseries on him. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> His clothes were all over squalid, the figure of his
                    body still more shocking, being pale and emaciated. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In addition, a long beard and hair had impressed a savage
                    wildness on his countenance; in such wretchedness he was known notwithstanding,
                    and they said that he had been a centurion, and compassionating him they
                    mentioned openly other distinctions (obtained) in the service: he himself
                    exhibited scars on his breast, testimonies of honourable battles in several
                    places. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To persons repeatedly inquiring,
                    whence that garb, whence that ghastly appearance of body, (the multitude having
                    now assembled around him almost like a popular assembly,) he says <quote> that
                        whilst serving in the Sabine war, because he had not only been deprived of
                        the produce of his land in consequence of the depredations of the enemy, but
                        also his residence had been burned down, all his effects pillaged, his
                        cattle driven off, a tax imposed on him at a time very distressing to him,
                        he had incurred debt; that this debt, aggravated by usury, had <pb n="106"
                            xml:id="p.106"/> stripped him first of his father's and grandfather's
                        farm, then of his other property; lastly that a pestilence, as it were, had
                        reached his person. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That he was taken by
                        his creditor, not into servitude, but into a house of correction and a place
                        of execution. </quote> He then showed his back disfigured with the marks of
                    stripes still recent. At the hearing and seeing of this a great uproar takes
                    place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The tumult is now no longer confined to
                    the forum, but spreads through the entire city. Those who were confined for
                    debt, and those who were now at their liberty, hurry into the streets from all
                    quarters and implore the protection of the people. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> In no place is there wanting a voluntary associate of
                    sedition. They run through all the streets in crowds to the forum with loud
                    shouts. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such of the senators as happened to be
                    in the forum, fell in with this mob with great peril to themselves; nor would
                    they have refrained from violence, had not the consuls, P. Servilius and Ap.
                    Claudius, hastily interfered to quell the disturbance. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The multitude turning towards them, and showing their
                    chains and other marks of wretchedness, said that they deserved all this,
                    taunting them (the consuls) each with the military services performed by
                    himself, one in one place, and another in another. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They require them with menaces, rather than as suppliants,
                    to assemble the senate, and stand round the senate-house in a body, determined
                    themselves to be witnesses and directors of the public counsels. Very few of the
                    senators, whom chance had thrown in the way, were forced to attend the consuls;
                    fear prevented the rest from coming not only to the house, but even to the
                    forum. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Nor could any thing be done by reason
                    of the thinness of the senate. Then indeed the people began to think their
                    demand was eluded, and the redress of their grievances delayed; that such of the
                    senators as had absented themselves did so not through chance or fear, but on
                    purpose to obstruct the business. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That the
                    consuls themselves trifled with them, that their miseries were now a mere
                    subject of mockery. By this time the sedition was come to such a height, that
                    the majesty of the consuls could hardly restrain the violence of the people.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Wherefore, uncertain whether they
                    incurred greater danger by staying at home, or venturing abroad, they came at
                    length to the senate; but though the house was at length full, a want of
                    agreement manifested itself, not only among the fathers, but even between the
                    consuls <pb n="107" xml:id="p.107"/> themselves. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Appius, a man of violent temper, thought the matter was to
                    be done by the authority of the consuls, and that if one or two were seized, the
                    rest would be quiet Servilius, more inclined to moderate measures, thought that
                    while their minds were in this ferment, it would be both more safe and more easy
                    to bend than to break them. Amidst these debates, another terror of a more
                    serious nature presented itself. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some Latin horse came full speed to Rome, with
                    the alarming news that the Volscians were marching with a hostile army, to
                    besiege the city, the announcement of which (so completely had discord made the
                    state two from one) affected the senators and people in a far different manner.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The people exulted with joy, and said,
                    that the gods were come as avengers of the tyranny of the fathers. They
                    encouraged one another not to enrol their names, that it was better that all
                    should perish together, than that they should perish alone. That the patricians
                    should serve as soldiers, that the patricians should take up arms, so that the
                    perils of war should remain with those with whom the advantages were. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> But the senate, dejected and confounded by the
                    two-fold terror, that from their own countrymen, and that from the enemy,
                    entreated the consul Servilius, whose temper was more conciliating, that he
                    would extricate the commonwealth beset with such great terrors. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then the consul, dismissing the senate, proceeds into the
                    assembly. There he shows them that the senate were solicitous that care should
                    be taken for the people's interest: but their alarm for the whole commonwealth
                    had interrupted their deliberation regarding that which was no doubt the
                    greatest part, but yet only a part; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> nor could
                    they, when the enemy were almost at the gates, allow any thing to take
                    precedence of war: nor, if there should be some respite, was it either to the
                    credit of the people not to have taken up arms in defence of their country
                    unless they first receive a recompence, nor consistent with the dignity of the
                    senators that they adopted measures of relief for the distresses of their
                    countrymen through fear rather than afterwards from inclination. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> He gave additional confidence to the assembly by an
                    edict, by which he ordained that no one "should detain a Roman citizen either in
                    chains or in prison, so as to hinder his enrolling his name under the consuls.
                    And that nobody should either seize or sell the goods of any <pb n="108"
                        xml:id="p.108"/> soldier, while he was in the camp, or arrest his children
                    or grandchildren. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This ordinance being
                    published, the debtors under arrest who were present immediately entered their
                    names, and crowds of persons hastening from all quarters of the city from their
                    confinement, as their creditors had no right to detain their persons, ran
                    together into the forum to take the military oath. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> These made up a considerable body of men, nor was the
                    bravery or activity of the others more conspicuous in the Volscian war. The
                    consul led out his army against the enemy, and pitched his camp at a little
                    distance from them. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next night the Volscians, relying on the
                    dissension among the Romans, made an attempt on their camp, to see if any
                    desertion or treachery might be resorted to during the night. The sentinels on
                    guard perceived them; the army was called up, and the signal being given they
                    ran to arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thus that attempt of the
                    Volscians was frustrated; the remainder of the night was dedicated to repose on
                    both sides. The next morning at daybreak the Volscians, having filled the
                    trenches, attacked the rampart. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And already
                    the fortifications were being demolished on every side, when the consul,
                    although all on every side, and more especially the debtors, cried out that he
                    should give the signal, having delayed a little while for the purpose of trying
                    the feelings of the soldiers, when their great ardour became sufficiently
                    apparent, having at length given the signal for sallying forth, he lets out the
                    soldiers now impatient for the fight. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the
                    very first onset the enemy were routed; the rear of them who fled was harassed,
                    as long as the infantry was able to overtake them; the cavalry drove them in
                    consternation to their very camp. In a little time the camp itself was taken and
                    plundered, the legions having surrounded it, as the panic had driven the
                    Volscians even from thence also. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the next
                    day the legions being led to Suessa Pometia, whither the enemy had retreated, in
                    a few days the town is taken; when taken, it was given up for plunder: by these
                    means the needy soldiers were somewhat relieved. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> The consul leads back his victorious army to Rome with the greatest glory to
                    himself: as he is setting out for Rome, the deputies of the Ecetrans, (a part)
                    of the Volscians, alarmed for their state after the taking of Pometia, come to
                    him. By a decree of <pb n="109" xml:id="p.109"/> the senate peace is granted
                    them, but their land is taken from them. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately after the Sabines also caused an
                    alarm to the Romans; but it was rather a tumult than a war. It was announced in
                    the city during the night that a Sabine army had advanced as far as the river
                    Anio, plundering the country: that the country houses there were pillaged and
                    burnt down indiscriminately. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A. Postumius, who
                    had been dictator in the Latin war, was immediately sent against them with all
                    the horse. The consul Servilius followed him with a chosen body of foot.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The cavalry cut off most of the
                    stragglers; nor did the Sabine legion make any resistance against the foot when
                    they came up with them. Being tired both by their march and their plundering the
                    country in the night, and a great number of them being surfeited with eating and
                    drinking in the cottages, they had scarcely sufficient strength for flight.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Sabine war being thus heard of and
                    finished in one night, on the following day, amid sanguine hope of peace being
                    secured in every quarter, ambassadors from the Auruncians come to the senate,
                    proclaiming war unless the troops are withdrawn from the Volscian territory.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The army of the Auruncians had set out
                    from home simultaneously with the ambassadors; the report of which having been
                    seen not far from Aricia, excited such a tumult among the Romans, that neither
                    the senate could be consulted in regular form, nor could they, while themselves
                    taking up arms, give a pacific answer to those advancing against them in arms.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They march to Aricia with a determined
                    army, come to an engagement not far from thence, and in one battle put an end to
                    the war. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the defeat of the Auruncians, the people
                    of Rome, victorious in so many wars within a few days, were expecting the
                    promises of the consul and the engagement of the senate (to be made good). But
                    Appius, both through his natural pride, and in order to undermine the credit of
                    his colleague, issued his decrees regarding borrowed money, with all possible
                    severity. And from this time, both those who had been formerly in confinement
                    were delivered up to their creditors, and others also were taken into custody.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When this happened to a soldier, he
                    appealed to the colleague, and a crowd gathered about Servilius: they
                    represented to him his promises, severally <pb n="110" xml:id="p.110"/>
                    upbraided him with their services in war, and with the scars they had received.
                    They loudly called upon him to lay the matter before the senate, and that, as
                    consul, he would relieve his fellow citizens, as a general, his soldiers.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These remonstrances affected the consul,
                    but the situation of affairs obliged him to back out; so completely had not only
                    his colleague, but the whole body of the patricians, adopted an entirely
                    opposite course. And thus, by acting a middle part, he neither escaped the odium
                    of the people, nor gained the favour of the senators. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The fathers looked upon him as a weak, popularity-hunting
                    consul, and the people considered him as a deceiver. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> And it soon appeared that he was as odious to them as
                    Appius himself. A dispute had happened between the consuls, as to which should
                    dedicate the temple of Mercury. The senate referred the affair from themselves
                    to the people, and ordained that to whichsoever of them the dedication should be
                    granted by order of the people, he should preside over the markets, establish a
                    company of merchants, and perform the functions of a pontifex maximus.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The people gave the dedication of the
                    temple to M. Laetorius, the centurion of the first legion, that it might plainly
                    appear to have been done not so much out of respect to a person on whom an
                    honour above his rank had been conferred, as to affront the consuls. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Upon this one of the consuls particularly, and the
                    senators, were highly incensed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the people
                    had acquired courage, and proceeded in a manner quite different from what they
                    had at first intended. For when they despaired of redress from the consuls and
                    senate, upon seeing a debtor led to the court, they flew together from all
                    quarters. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And neither the decree of the consul
                    could be heard in consequence of the noise and clamour, nor, when he had
                    pronounced the decree, did any one obey it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    All was managed by violence, and the entire dread and danger with respect to
                    personal liberty, was transferred from the debtors to the creditors, who were
                    severally abused by the crowd in the very sight of the consul. In addition to
                    all this, the dread of the Sabine war spread, and when a levy was decreed,
                    nobody gave in his name; Appius being enraged, and bitterly inveighing against
                    the ambitious arts of his colleague, who by his popular silence was betraying
                    the republic, and besides his not passing sentence against the debtors, likewise
                    neglected to raise the levies, after they <pb n="111" xml:id="p.111"/> had been
                    voted by the senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Yet he declared, that
                        <quote> the commonwealth was not entirely deserted, nor the consular
                        authority altogether debased. That he alone would vindicate both his own
                        dignity and that of the senators. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When a daily mob, emboldened by
                    licentiousness, stood round him, he commanded a noted ringleader of the sedition
                    to be apprehended. He, as the lictors were carrying him off, appealed to the
                    people; nor would the consul have allowed the appeal, because there was no doubt
                    regarding the judgment of the people, had not his obstinacy been with difficulty
                    overcome, rather by the advice and influence of the leading men, than by the
                    clamours of the people; so much resolution he had to bear the weight of their
                    odium. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The evil gained ground daily, not only
                    by open clamours, but, which was far more dangerous, by a secession and by
                    secret meetings. At length the consuls, so odious to the commons, went out of
                    office: Servilius liked by neither party, Appius highly esteemed by the
                    senators. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then A. Virginius and T. Vetusius enter on the
                    consulship. Upon this the commons, uncertain what sort of consuls they were to
                    have, held nightly meetings, some of them upon the Esquiline, and others upon
                    the Aventine hill, that they might not be confused by hasty resolutions in the
                    forum, or take their measures inconsiderately and without concert. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consuls, judging this proceeding to be of
                    dangerous tendency, as it really was, laid the matter before the senate. But
                    they were not allowed after proposing it to take the votes regularly; so
                    tumultuously was it received on all sides by the clamours and indignation of the
                    fathers, at the consuls throwing on the senate the odium of that which should
                    have been put down by consular authority. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That if there really were magistrates in the republic, there would have
                        been no council in Rome but the public one. That the republic was now
                        divided and split into a thousand senate-houses and assemblies, some of
                        which were held on the Esquiline, others on the Aventine hill. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> That one man, in truth such as Appius Claudius,
                        for that that was more than a consul, would in a moment disperse these
                        private meetings. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the consuls, thus rebuked, asked them,
                        <quote> What they desired them to do, for that they would act with as much
                        energy and vigour as the senators wished, </quote> they resolve that they
                    should push on the levies as briskly as possible, that the people were become
                    insolent from want of em- <pb n="112" xml:id="p.112"/> ployment. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> When the house broke up, the consuls ascend the
                    tribunal and summon the young men by name. But none of them made any answer, and
                    the people crowding round them, as if in a general assembly, said, <quote> That
                        the people would no longer be imposed on. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        They should never list one soldier till the public faith was made good. That
                        liberty should be restored to each before arms were given, that they might
                        fight for their country and fellow citizens, and not for arbitrary lords. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls fully understood the orders they
                    had received from the senate, but they saw none of those who had talked so big
                    within the walls of the senate-house present themselves to take any share with
                    them in the public odium. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A desperate contest
                    with the commons seemed at hand. Therefore, before they would have recourse to
                    extremities, they thought it advisable to consult the senate a second time. Then
                    indeed the younger senators flocked in a hurry round the chairs of the consuls,
                    commanding them to abdicate the consulate, and resign an office which they had
                    not courage to support. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having sufficiently tried both <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The determination of the plebeians and
                        senators.</note> ways, the consuls at length said, <quote> Conscript
                        fathers, lest you may say that you were not forewarned, a great disturbance
                        is at hand. We require that they who accuse us most severely of cowardice,
                        would assist us in raising the levies; we shall proceed according to the
                        resolution of the most intrepid amongst you, since it so pleases you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They return to their tribunal, and on purpose
                    commanded one of the most factious of the people, who stood in their view, to be
                    called upon by name. When he stood mute, and a number of men stood round him in
                    a ring, to prevent his being seized, the consuls sent a lictor to him.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He being repulsed, such of the fathers as
                    attended the consuls, exclaiming against it as an intolerable insult, ran in a
                    hurry from the tribunal to assist the lictor. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But when the violence was turned from the lictor, who suffered nothing else but
                    being prevented from seizing him, against the fathers, the riot was quelled by
                    the interposition of the consuls, in which however, without stones or weapons,
                    there was more noise and angry words than mischief done. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate, called in a tumultuous manner, is consulted in
                    a manner still <pb n="113" xml:id="p.113"/> more tumultuous; such as had been
                    beaten, calling out for an inquiry, and the most violent members declaring their
                    sentiments no less by clamours and noise than by their votes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At length, when their passion had subsided, the consuls
                    reproaching them with there being as much disorderly conduct in the senate as in
                    the forum, the house began to vote in regular order. There were three different
                    opinions: P. Virginius did not make the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">rem non vulgabat,</hi> was not for extending the relief
                        to all. </note> matter general. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He voted
                    that they should consider only those who, relying on the promise of P. Servilius
                    the consul, had served in a war against the Auruncans and Sabines. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Titius Largius was of opinion, <quote> That it was
                        not now a proper time to reward services only. That all the people were
                        immersed in debt, and that a stop could not be put to the evil, unless
                        measures were adopted for all. And that if the condition of different
                        parties be different, the divisions would rather be thereby inflamed than
                        composed. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius, who was naturally severe,
                    and, by the hatred of the commons on the one hand, and praises of the senators
                    on the other, was become quite infuriated, said, <quote> That these riots
                        proceeded not from distress, but from licentiousness. That the people were
                        rather wanton than violent. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That this
                        terrible mischief took its rise from the right of appeal; since threats, not
                        authority, was all that belonged to the consuls, while permission was given
                        to appeal to those who were accomplices in the crime. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Come, </quote> added he, <quote> let us create a
                        dictator from whom there lies no appeal; this madness, which hath set every
                        thing in a flame, will immediately subside. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> Let any one dare then to strike a lictor, when he shall know that his
                        back, and even his life, are in the power of that person whose authority he
                        has insulted. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To many the opinion of Appius appeared, as it
                    really was, severe and violent. On the other hand, those of Virginius and
                    Largius were not safe for the precedent they established; especially they
                    thought that of Largius so, as it would destroy all credit. The opinion of
                    Virginius was reckoned to be most moderate, and a happy medium between the other
                    two. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But through the spirit of faction and a
                    regard of private interest, which always have and always will obstruct the
                    public councils, Appius prevailed, and was himself near being created dictator;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> which step would certainly have alienated
                        <pb n="114" xml:id="p.114"/> the commons at this most dangerous juncture,
                    when the Volsci, the Aequi, and the Sabines happened to be all in arms at the
                    same time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the consuls and elder senators
                    took care that this office, in its own nature uncontrollable, should be
                    committed to a man of moderate temper. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                    choose Manius Valerius, son of Volesus, dictator. The people, though they saw
                    that this magistrate was created against themselves, yet as they had got the
                    right of appeal by his brother's law, dreaded nothing oppressive or tyrannical
                    from that family. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> An edict of the dictator's,
                    which was almost the same with that published by the consul Servilius,
                    afterwards confirmed their minds. But judging it safer to confide in both the
                    man and in the absolute power with which he was vested, they gave in their
                    names, desisting from all contest. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Ten legions
                    were levied, a greater army than had ever been raised before. Each of the
                    consuls had three legions assigned him, and the dictator commanded four.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor could the war be deferred any longer.
                    The Aequi had made incursions upon the Latin territory; the deputies of the
                    Latins begged the senate either to send them assistance, or to allow them to arm
                    themselves for the purpose of defending their own frontiers. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> It seemed safer that the Latins should be defended without
                    arming, than to allow them to take up arms again. Wherefore Vetusius the consul
                    was sent to their assistance; this immediately put a stop to the devastations.
                    The Aequi retired from the plains, and depending more on the advantage of the
                    ground than on their arms, secured themselves on the summits of the mountains.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The other consul, having marched against
                    the Volsci, in order that he too might not waste time, challenged the enemy to
                    pitch their camp nigh to his, and to risk an engagement by ravaging their lands.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Both armies stood in order of battle
                    before their lines in a plain between the two camps. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The Volsci had considerably the advantage in number.
                    Accordingly they rushed on to the fight, in a careless manner, and as if
                    contemptuously. The Roman consul neither advanced his forces, and not suffering
                    the enemy's shouts to be returned, he ordered them to stand still with their
                    spears fixed in the ground, and when the enemy came up, to draw their swords and
                    fall upon them with all their force. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    Volsci, wearied with running and shouting, set upon the Romans as if they had
                    been quite be- <pb n="115" xml:id="p.115"/> numbed through fear; but when they
                    found the vigorous resistance that was made, and saw their swords glittering
                    before their face, they turned their backs in great disorder, just as if they
                    had fallen into an ambuscade. Nor had they strength sufficient even for flight,
                    as they had advanced to the battle in full speed. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans, on the other hand, as they had not stirred from
                    their ground in the beginning of the action, being fresh and vigorous, easily
                    overtook the enemy, who were weary, took their camp by assault, and after
                    driving them thence, pursued them to Velitrae, into which the conquered and
                    conquerors entered in a body. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> By the
                    promiscuous slaughter which was here made of all ranks, there was more blood
                    spilt than in the battle itself. Quarter was given to a small number of them,
                    who threw down their arms and surrendered. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these things are going on among the
                    Volsci, the dictator routs, puts to flight, and strips of their camp, the
                    Sabines, where by far the most serious part of the war lay. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> By a charge of his cavalry he had thrown into confusion the
                    centre of the enemy's line, where, by the wings extending themselves too far,
                    they had not strengthened their line by a suitable depth of files. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">i. e. by deepening the files.</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The infantry fell upon them in this confusion,
                    by one and the same charge their camp was taken and the war concluded. There was
                    no other battle in those times more memorable than this since the action at the
                    lake Regillus. The dictator is borne into the city in triumph. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Besides the usual honours, a place in the circus was
                    assigned to him and his descendants, to see the public games; a curule chair was
                    fixed in that place. The lands of Velitrae were taken from the conquered Volsci:
                    colonists were sent from the city to Velitrae, and a colony planted there. Soon
                    after there was an engagement with the Aequi, but contrary to the wish of the
                    consul, because they had to approach the enemy by disadvantageous ground.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the soldiers complaining that the war
                    was on purpose spun out, that the dictator might resign his office before they
                    returned home to the city, and so his promises might fall to the ground without
                    effect, as those of the consul had done before, forced him at all hazards to
                    march his army up the hill. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This imprudent
                    step, by the cowardice of the enemy, turned out successfully; for before the
                    Romans came <pb n="116" xml:id="p.116"/> within reach of a dart, the Aequi,
                    quite amazed at their boldness, abandoned their camp, which was situated in a
                    very strong position, and ran down into the valleys on the opposite side. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>On the opposite side.</quote> Gronovius proposes instead of <hi
                            rend="italics">adversus</hi> to read <hi rend="italics">aversas:</hi>
                        scil. the valleys <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> behind them, or in their
                        rear. </note> In it abundance of booty was found, and the victory was a
                    bloodless one. Matters being thus successfully managed in war in three different
                    directions, anxiety respecting the event of their domestic differences had left
                    neither the senators nor the people. With such powerful influence, and with such
                    art <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> also, had the money-lenders made their
                    arrangements, so as to disappoint not only the people, but even the dictator
                    himself. For Valerius, after the return of the consul Vetusius, first of all
                    matters brought before the senate that relating to the victorious <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> people, and proposed the question, what it was their
                    determination should be done with respect to those confined for debt. And when
                    this motion was rejected, <quote>I am not acceptable,</quote> says he, <quote>
                        as an adviser of concord. You will ere long wish, depend on it, that the
                        commons of Rome had patrons similar to me. For my part, I will neither
                        further disappoint my fellow citizens, <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        nor will I be dictator to no purpose. Intestine dissensions, foreign wars,
                        caused the republic to require such a magistrate. Peace has been secured
                        abroad, it is impeded at home. I will be a witness to disturbance as a
                        private citizen rather than as dictator. </quote> Then quitting the
                    senate-house, he abdicated his <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> dictatorship.
                    The case appeared to the commons, that he had resigned his office indignant at
                    the treatment shown to them. Accordingly, as if his engagements to them had been
                    fully discharged, since it had not been his fault that they were not made good,
                    they attended him when returning to his home with approbation and applause. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fear then seized the senators lest, if the
                    army should be dismissed, secret meetings and conspiracies would be renewed;
                    wherefore though the levy had been held by the dictator, yet supposing that, as
                    they had sworn obedience to the consuls, the soldiers were bound by their oath,
                    under the protext of hostilities being renewed by the Aequi, they ordered the
                    legions to be led out of the city; by which proceeding the sedition was
                    hastened. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And it is said that at first <pb
                        n="117" xml:id="p.117"/> it was in contemplation to put the consuls to
                    death, that they might be discharged from their oath: but that being afterwards
                    informed that no religious obligation could be dissolved by a criminal act,
                    they, by the advice of one Sicinius, retired, without the orders of the consuls,
                    to the sacred mount, beyond the river Anio, three miles from the city:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> this account is more general than that
                    which Piso has given, that the secession was made to the Aventine. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> There without any leader, their camp being fortified
                    with a rampart and trench, remaining quiet, taking nothing but what was
                    necessary for sustenance, they kept themselves for several days, neither being
                    attacked, nor attacking others. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Great was the
                    panic in the city, and through mutual fear all was suspense. The people left in
                    the city dreaded the violence of the senators; the senators dreaded the people
                    remaining in the city, uncertain whether they should prefer them to stay or to
                    depart; but how long would the multitude which had seceded, remain quiet?
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> what were to be the consequences then, if,
                    in the mean time, any foreign war should break out? <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> they certainly considered no hope left, save in the concord
                    of the citizens; this should be restored to the state by fair or by unfair
                    means. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was resolved therefore that there
                    should be sent as ambassador to the people, Menenius Agrippa, an eloquent man,
                    and one who was a favourite with the people, because he derived his origin from
                    them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He being admitted into the camp, is said
                    to have related to them merely the following story in that antiquated and
                    uncouth style; <quote> At a time when all the parts in the human body did not,
                        as now, agree together, but the several members had each its own scheme, its
                        own language, the other parts, indignant that every thing was procured for
                        the belly by their care, labour, and service; that the belly, remaining
                        quiet in the centre, did nothing but enjoy the pleasures afforded it.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They conspired accordingly, that the
                        hands should not convey food to the mouth, nor the mouth receive it when
                        presented, nor the teeth chew it: whilst they wished under the influence of
                        this feeling to subdue the belly by famine, the members themselves and the
                        entire body were reduced to the last degree of emaciation. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Thence it became apparent that the service of the belly
                        was by no means a slothful one; that it did not so much receive nourishment
                        as supply it, sending to all parts of the body this blood by which we <pb
                            n="118" xml:id="p.118"/> live and possess vigour, distributed equally to
                        the veins when prefected by the digestion of the food. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> By comparing in this way how similar the
                    intestine sedition of the body was to the resentment of the people against the
                    senators, he made an impression on the minds of the multitude. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then a commencement was made to treat of a
                    reconciliation, and among the conditions it was allowed, <quote> that the
                        commons should have their own magistrates, with inviolable privileges, who
                        should have the power of bringing assistance against the consuls, and that
                        it should not be lawful for any of the patricians to hold that office. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thus two tribunes of the commons were created,
                    Caius Licinius and L. Albinus. These created three colleagues for themselves. It
                    is clear that among these was Sicinius, the adviser of the sedition; with
                    respect to two, who they were is not so clear. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There are some who say, that only two tribunes were elected on the sacred mount,
                    and that there the devoting law was passed. During the secession of the commons,
                    Sp. Cassius and Postumus Cominius entered on the consulship. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> During their consulate, the treaty with the Latin states
                    was concluded. To ratify this, one of the consuls remained at Rome; the other
                    being sent to the Volscian war, routs and puts to flight the Volscians of
                    Antium, and continuing his pursuit of them, now that they were driven into the
                    town of Longula, he takes possession of the town. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Next he took Polusca, also belonging to the Volscians; then
                    he attacked Corioli with all his force. There was then in the camp, among the
                    young noblemen, C. Marcius, a youth distinguished both for intelligence and
                    courage, who afterwards attained the cognomen of Coriolanus. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When, as the Roman army was besieging Corioli, and was
                    wholly intent on the townspeople, whom they kept shut up, without any
                    apprehension of war threatening from without, the Volscian legion, setting out
                    from Antium, suddenly attacked them, and, at the same time the enemy sallied
                    forth from the town, Marcius happened to be on guard. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He with a chosen body of men not only repelled the attack
                    of those who had sallied out, but boldly rushed in through the open gate, and
                    having cut down all in the part of the city nearest him, and having hastily
                    seized some fire, threw it in the houses adjoining to the wall. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Upon this the shouts of the townsmen mingling with the
                    wailings of the women and <pb n="119" xml:id="p.119"/> children, occasioned by
                    the first fright, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> I have here adopted
                        the reading of Stocker and others, scil. <hi rend="italics">ad terrorem, ut.
                            solet, primum ortus.</hi>
                    </note> as is usual, both increased the courage of the Romans, and dispirited
                    the Volscians, seeing the city captured to the relief of which they had come.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus the Volsci of Antium were defeated,
                    the town of Corioli was taken. And so much did Marc us by his valour eclipse the
                    reputation of the consul, that had not the treaty concluded with the Latins by
                    Sp. Cassius alone, because his colleague was absent, served as a memorial of it,
                    it would have been forgotten that Postumus Cominius had conducted the war with
                    the Volscians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The same year dies Agrippa
                    Menenius, a man during all his life equally a favourite with the senators and
                    commons, still more endeared to the commons after the secession. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> To this man, the mediator and umpire in restoring
                    concord among his countrymen, the ambassador of the senators to the commons, the
                    person who brought back the commons to the city, were wanting the expenses of
                    his funeral. The people buried him by the contribution bution of a sextans from
                    each person. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> T. Geganius and P. Minutius were next elected
                    consuls. In this year, when every thing was quiet from war abroad, and the
                    dissensions were healed at home, another much more serious evil fell upon the
                    state; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> first a scarcity of provisions, in
                    consequence of the lands lying untilled during the secession of the commons;
                    then a famine such as befals those who are besieged. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> And it would have ended in the destruction of the slaves at
                    least, and indeed some of the commons also, had not the consuls adopted
                    precautionary measures, by sending persons in every direction to buy up corn,
                    not only into Etruria on the coast to the right of Ostia, and through the
                    Volscians along the coast on the left as far as Cumae, but into Sicily also, in
                    quest of it. So far had the hatred of their neighbours obliged them to stand in
                    need of aid from distant countries. When corn had been bought up at Cumae, the
                    ships were detained in lieu of the property of the Tarquinii by the tyrant
                    Aristodemus, who was their heir. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Among the
                    Volsci and in the Pomptine territory it could not even be purchased. The corn
                    dealers themselves incurred danger from the violence of the inhabitants. Corn
                    came from Etruria by the Tiber: by means of this the people were supported. Amid
                        <pb n="120" xml:id="p.120"/> this distressing scarcity they would have been
                    harassed by a very inconvenient war, had not a dreadful pestilence attacked the
                    Volsci when about to commence hostilities. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    minds of the enemy being alarmed by this calamity, so that they were influenced
                    by some terror, even after it had abated, the Romans both augmented the number
                    of their colonists at Velitrae, and despatched a new colony to the mountains of
                    Norba, to serve as a barrier in the Pomptine district. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then in the consulship of M. Minucius, and A. Sempronius, a
                    great quantity of corn was imported from Sicily, and it was debated in the
                    senate at what rate it should be given to the commons. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Many were of opinion, that the time was come for putting
                    down the commons, and for recovering those rights which had been wrested from
                    the senators by secession and violence. In particular, Marcius Coriolanus, an
                    enemy to tribunitian power, says, <quote> If they desire the former rate of
                        provisions, let them restore to the senators their former rights. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Why do I, after being sent under the yoke, after
                        being, as it were, ransomed from robbers, behold plebeian magistrates, and
                        Sicinius invested with power? Shall I submit to these indignities longer
                        than is necessary? Shall I, who would not have endured King Tarquin,
                        tolerate Sicinius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Let him now secede, let
                        him call away the commons. The road lies open to the sacred mount and to
                        other hills. Let them carry off the corn from our lands, as they did three
                        years since. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Let them have the benefit of
                        that scarcity which in their frenzy they have occasioned. I will venture to
                        say, that, brought to their senses by these sufferings, they will themselves
                        become tillers of the lands, rather than, taking up arms and seceding, they
                        would prevent them from being tilled. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It is not so easy to say whether it should
                    have been done, as I think that it might have been practicable for the senators,
                    on the condition of lowering the price of provisions, to have rid themselves of
                    both the tribunitian power, and all the restraints imposed on them against their
                    will. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> i. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> e. I think it might have been done; whether it would
                        have been right to do so, it is not so easy to decide. Livy means to say
                        that it was possible enough for the senators, by lowering the price of corn,
                        to get rid of the tribunes, &amp;c. Such a judgment is easily formed; it is
                        not, however, he says, so easy to determine, whether it would have been
                        expedient to follow the advice of Coriolanus. </note>
                    <pb n="121" xml:id="p.121"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This proposal both appeared to the senate too
                    harsh, and from exasperation well nigh drove the people to arms: <quote> that
                        they were now assailed with famine, as if enemies, that they were defrauded
                        of food and sustenance, that the foreign corn, the only support which
                        fortune unexpectedly furnished to them, was being snatched from their mouth,
                        unless the tribunes were given up in chains to C. Marcius, unless he glut
                        his rage on the backs of the commons of Rome. That in him a new executioner
                        had started up, who ordered them to die or be slaves. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> An assault would have been made on him as he
                    left the senate-house, had not the tribunes very opportunely appointed him a day
                    for trial; by this their rage was suppressed, every one saw himself become the
                    judge, the arbiter of the life and death of his foe. At first Marcius heard the
                    threats of the tribunes with contempt. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> —
                        <quote> That the right to afford aid, not to inflict punishment, had been
                        granted to that office; that they were tribunes of the commons and not of
                        the senators. </quote> But the commons had risen with such violent
                    determination, that the senators were obliged to extricate themselves from
                    danger by the punishment of one. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> i.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> e. the senate found themselves reduced
                        to the necessity of delivering one up to the vengeance of the people, in
                        order to save themselves from the further consequences of plebeian rage.
                    </note> They resisted however, in spite of popular odium, and employed, each
                    individual his own powers, and all those <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> of
                    the entire order. And first, the trial was made whether they could upset the
                    affair, by posting their clients (in several places), by deterring individuals
                    from attending meetings and cabals. Then they all proceeded in a body (you would
                    suppose that all the senators were on their trial) earnestly entreating the
                    commons, that if <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> they would not acquit as
                    innocent, they would at least pardon as guilty, one citizen, one senator. As he
                    did not attend on the day appointed, they persevered in their resentment. Being
                    condemned in his absence, he went into exile to the Volsci, threatening his
                    country, and even then breathing all the resentment of an enemy. The Volsci
                    received him kindly on his arrival, and treated him still more kindly every day
                    in proportion as his resentful feelings towards his countrymen became more
                    striking, and one <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> time frequent complaints,
                    another time threats were heard. He lodged with Attius Tullus. He was then the
                    chief man of <pb n="122" xml:id="p.122"/> the Volscian people, and always a
                    determined enemy of the Romans. Thus, when old animosity stimulated the one,
                    recent resentment the <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> other, they concert
                    schemes for (bringing about) a war with Rome. They did not at once believe that
                    their people could be persuaded to take up arms, so often unsuccessfully tried.
                    That by the many frequent wars, and lastly, by the loss of their youth in the
                    pestilence, their spirits were now broken; that they must have recourse to art,
                    in a case where animosity had become blunted from length of time, that their
                    feelings might become exasperated by some fresh cause of resentment. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened that preparations were being made
                    at Rome for a repetition of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The
                        same as the Circenses.</note> great games; the cause of repeating them was
                    this: on the morning of the games, the show not yet being commenced, a master of
                    a family, after flogging his slave loaded with a neck-yoke, had driven him
                    through the middle of the circus; after this the games were commenced, as if
                    that circumstance bore no relation to religion. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Not long after Tit. Atinius, a plebeian, had a dream. Jupiter seemed to him
                    to say; <quote> that the person who danced previous to the games had displeased
                        him; unless these games were renewed on a splendid scale, that the city
                        would be in danger; that he should go and announce these things to the
                        consuls. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Though his mind was not altogether free from
                    superstitious feelings, his respectful awe of the dignity of the magistrates
                    overcame his religious fear, lest he might pass into the mouths of people as a
                    laughing-stock. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This delay cost him dear; for
                    he lost his son within a few days; and lest the cause of this sudden calamity
                    should be doubtful, that same phantom, presenting itself to him sorrowful in
                    mind, seemed to ask him, whether he had received a sufficient requital for his
                    contempt of the deity; that a still heavier one awaited him, unless he went
                    immediately and delivered the message to the consuls. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The matter was now still more pressing. Hesitating,
                    however, and delaying he was at length overtaken by a severe stroke of disease,
                    a sudden paralysis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then indeed the anger of
                    the gods aroused him. Wearied out therefore by his past sufferings and by those
                    threatening him, having convened a meeting of his friends, after he had detailed
                    to them all he had seen and heard, and Jupiter's <pb n="123" xml:id="p.123"/>
                    having so often presented himself to him in his sleep, the threats and anger of
                    heaven realized <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Realized —repraesentatas</hi> —quasi praesentes factas,
                        oculis subjectas —presented as it were to the sight. — <hi rend="italics"
                            >Rasch.</hi>
                    </note> in his own calamities, by the unhesitating assent of all who were
                    present he is conveyed in a litter into the <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    forum to the consuls; frown thence being conveyed into the senate-house, after
                    he had stated those same particulars to the senators, to the great surprise of
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> all, behold another miracle: he who had
                    been conveyed into the senate-house deprived of the use of all his limbs, is
                    recorded to have returned home on his own feet after he discharged his duty. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate decreed that the games should be
                    celebrated on as grand a scale as possible. To these games a great number of
                    Volscians came by the advice of Attius Tullus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Before the games were commenced, Tullus, as had been concerted at home with
                    Marcius, comes to the consuls. He tells them that there were matters on which he
                    wished to treat with them in private concerning the commonwealth. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> All witnesses being removed, he says, <quote> With
                        reluctance I say that of my countrymen which is rather disparaging. <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">Sequius sit</hi>
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> —otherwise than as it should be.
                        </note> I do not however come to allege against them any thing as having
                        been committed by them, but to guard against their committing any thing. The
                        minds of our people are far more fickle than I could <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> wish. We have felt that by many disasters; seeing that
                        we are still preserved, not through our own deserts, but through your
                        forbearance. There is now here a great multitude of Volscians. The games are
                        going on; the city will be intent on the <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        exhibition. I remember what has been committed in this city on a similar
                        occasion by the youth of the Sabines. My mind shudders lest any thing should
                        be committed inconsiderately and rashly. I considered, that these matters
                        should be mentioned before-hand to you, <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        consuls. With regard to myself, it is my determination to depart hence home
                        immediately, lest, if present, I may be affected by the contagion of any
                        word or deed. </quote> Having said this, he <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> departed. When the consuls laid before the senate the matter, doubtful with
                    respect to proof, though from credible authority, the authority more than the
                    thing its lf, as usually happens, urged them to adopt even needless precau- <pb
                        n="124" xml:id="p.124"/> tions; and a decree of the senate being passed,
                    that the Volscians should quit the city, criers are sent in different directions
                    to order them all to depart before <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> night. A
                    great panic struck them at first as they ran about to their lodgings to carry
                    away their effects. Afterwards, when setting out, indignation arose in their
                    breasts: <quote> that they, as if polluted with crime and contaminated, were
                        driven away from the games, on festival days, from the converse in a manner
                        of men and gods. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As they went along in an almost continuous
                    body, Tullus having preceded them to the fountain of Ferentina, accosting the
                    chiefs among them according as each arrived, by asking questions and expressing
                    indignation, he led both themselves, who greedily listened to language congenial
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Audientes secunda irae verba</hi> —attentively listening
                        to words which fanned (or chimed in with) their anger. — <hi rend="italics"
                            >St.</hi>
                    </note> to their angry <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> feelings, and through
                    them the rest of the multitude, into a plain adjoining to the road. There having
                    commenced an address after the manner of a public harangue, he says, <quote>
                        Though you were to forget the former ill treatment of the Roman people and
                        the calamities of the nation of the Volsci, and all other such matters, with
                        what feelings do <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> you bear this outrage
                        offered you to-day, whereon they have commenced their games by insulting us?
                        Have you not felt that a triumph has been had over you this day? that you,
                        when departing, were a spectacle to all, citizens, foreigners, <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> so many neighbouring states? that your wives,
                        your children were exhibited before the eyes of men? What do you suppose to
                        have been the sentiments of those who heard the voice of the crier? what of
                        those who saw you departing? what of those who met this ignominious
                        cavalcade? what, except that we are identified with some enormous guilt by
                        which we should profane the games, and render an expiation necessary; that
                        for this reason <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> we are driven away from
                        the residences of these pious people, from their converse and meeting? what,
                        does it not strike you that we still live because we hastened our departure?
                        if this is a departure and not a flight. And do you not consider this to be
                        the city of enemies, where if you had delayed a single day, you must have
                        all died? War has been <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> declared against
                        you; to the heavy injury of those who declared it, if you are men. </quote>
                    Thus, being <pb n="125" xml:id="p.125"/> both already charged with resentment,
                    and incited (by this harangue) they went severally to their homes, and by
                    instigating each his own state, they succeeded in making the entire Volscian
                    nation revolt. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The generals selected for that war by the
                    unanimous choice of all the states were Attius Tullus and Caius Marcius; in the
                    latter of whom their chief hope was reposed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    And this hope he by no means disappointed: so that it clearly appeared that the
                    Roman commonwealth was more powerful by reason of its generals than its army.
                    Having marched to Circeii, he expelled from thence the Roman colonists, and
                    delivered that city in a state of freedom to the Volscians. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> From thence passing across the country through byroads into
                    the Latin way, he deprived the Romans of their recently acquired towns,
                    Satricum, Longula, Polusca, Corioli. He next retook Lavinium: he then took in
                    succession Corbio, Vitellia, Trebia, Lavici, and Pedum: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Lastly he marches from Pedum to the city, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Scil. Rome. Dionysius narrates the
                        expedition of Coriola us in a different order from that given by Livy, and
                        says that he approached the city twice. Niebuhr, ii. p. 94, n. 535, thinks
                        that the words <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        <quote>passing across the country into the Latin way</quote> (in Latinam
                        viam transversis itineribus transgressus) have been transposed from their
                        proper place, <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and that they should come in
                        after <quote>he then took,</quote> &amp;c. (tune deinceps). </note> and
                    having pitched his camp at the Cluilian trenches five miles from the city, he
                    from thence ravages the Roman territory, guards being sent among the devastators
                    to preserve the lands of the patricians intact; <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> whether as being incensed chiefly against the plebeians, or in order that
                    dissension might arise between the senators and the people. And this certainly
                    would have arisen, so powerfully did the tribunes, by inveighing against the
                    leading <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> men of the state, incite the
                    plebeians, already sufficiently violent of themselves; but their apprehensions
                    of the foe, the strongest bond of concord, united their minds, distrustful and
                    rancorous though they were. The only matter not agreed on was this, that the
                    senate and consuls rested their hopes on nothing else than on arms; the
                    plebeians preferred any <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> thing to war. Sp.
                    Nautius and Sex. Furius were now consuls. Whilst they were reviewing the
                    legions, posting guards along the walls and other places where they had
                    determined th t there should be posts and watches, a vast multitude of persons
                    de- <pb n="126" xml:id="p.126"/> manding peace terrified them first <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> by their seditious clamour; then compelled them to
                    convene the senate, to consider the question of sending ambassadors to C.
                    Marcius. The senate entertained the question, when it became evident that the
                    spirits of the plebeians were giving way, and ambassadors being sent to Marcius
                    concerning peace, brought back <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> a harsh
                    answer: <quote> If their lands were restored to the Volscians, that they might
                        then consider the question of peace; if they were disposed to enjoy the
                        plunder of war at their ease, that he, mindful both of the injurious
                        treatment of his countrymen, as well as <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        of the kindness of strangers, would do his utmost to make it appear that his
                        spirit was irritated by exile, not crushed. </quote> When the same persons
                    are sent back a second time, they are not admitted into the camp. It is recorded
                    that the priests also, arrayed in their insignia, went as suppliants to the
                    enemy's camp; and that they did not influence his mind more than the
                    ambassadors. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the matrons assemble in a body around
                    Veturia, the mother of Coriolanus, and his wife, Volumnia: whether that was the
                    result of public counsel, or of the women's fear, I cannot ascertain. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> They certainly carried their point that Veturia, a
                    lady advanced in years, and Volumnia, leading her two sons by Marcius, should go
                    into the camp of the enemy, and that women should defend by entreaties and tears
                    a city which men were unable to defend by arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> When they reached the camp, and it was announced to Coriolanus, that a great
                    body of women were approaching, he, who had been moved neither by the majesty of
                    the state in its ambassadors, nor by the sanctity of religion so strikingly
                    addressed to his eyes and understanding in its priests, was much more obdurate
                    against the women's tears. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then one of his
                    acquaintances, who recognised Veturia, distinguished from all the others by her
                    sadness, standing between her daughter-in-law and grandchildren, says,
                        <quote>Unless my eyes deceive me, your mother, children, and wife, are
                        approaching.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Coriolanus, almost like one bewildered,
                    rushing in consternation from his seat, offered to embrace his mother as she met
                    him, the lady, turning from entreaties to angry rebuke, says, <quote> Before I
                        receive your embrace, let me know whether I have come to an enemy or to a
                        son; whether I am in your camp a captive or a mother? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Has length of life and a hapless old age reserved <pb
                            n="127" xml:id="p.127"/> me for this —to behold you an exile, then an
                        enemy? Could you lay waste this land, which gave you birth and nurtured you?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though you had come with an incensed
                        and vengeful mind, did not your resentment subside when you entered its
                        frontiers? When Rome came within view, did it not occur to you, within these
                        walls my house and guardian gods are, my mother, wife, and children?
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So then, had I not been a mother, Rome
                        would not be besieged: had I not a son, I might have died free in a free
                        country. But I can now suffer nothing that is not more discreditable to you
                        than distressing to me; nor however wretched I may be, shall I be so long.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Look to these, whom, if you persist,
                        either an untimely death or lengthened slavery awaits. </quote> Then his
                    wife and children embraced him: and the lamentation proceeding from the entire
                    crowd of women, and their bemoaning themselves and their country, at length
                    overcame the man; then, after embracing his family, he sends them away; he moved
                    his camp farther back from the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then,
                    after he had drawn off his troops from the Roman territory, they say that he
                    lost his life, overwhelmed by the odium of the proceeding: different writers say
                    by different modes of death: I find in Fabius, far the most ancient writer, that
                    he lived even to old age; he states positively, that advanced in years he made
                    use of this phrase, <quote>That exile bore much heavier on the old man.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The men of Rome were not remiss in awarding
                    their praises to the women, so truly did they live without detracting from the
                    merit of others; a temple was built also and dedicated to female Fortune, to
                    serve as a monument. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Volscians afterwards
                    returned in conjunction with the Aequi into the Roman territory: but the Aequi
                    would no longer have Attius Tullus as their leader; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> hence from dispute, whether the Volscians or the Aequi
                    should give a general to the allied army, a sedition, and afterwards a furious
                    battle arose. There the good fortune of the Roman people destroyed the two
                    armies of the enemy, by a contest no less bloody than obstinate. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> T. Sicinius and C. Aquillius were made consuls. The
                    Volsci fell as a province to Sicinius; the Hernici (for they too were in arms)
                    to Aquillius. That year the Hernici were defeated; they came off with respect to
                    the Volscians on equal terms. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Sp. Cassius and Proculus Virginius were next
                    made consuls; a treaty was struck with the Hernici; two-thirds of <pb n="128"
                        xml:id="p.128"/> their land were taken from them: of this the consul Cassius
                    was about to distribute one half among the Latins, the other half among the
                    commons. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To this donation he was adding a
                    considerable portion of land, which, though public property, he alleged was
                    possessed by private individuals. This proceeding alarmed several of the
                    senators, the actual possessors, at the danger of their property; the senators
                    felt, moreover, a solicitude on public grounds, that the consul by his donation
                    was establishing an influence dangerous to liberty. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Then, for the first time, the Agrarian law was proposed,
                    which even down to our own recollection was never agitated without the greatest
                    commotions in the state. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The other consul
                    resisted the donation, the senators seconding him, nor were all the commons
                    opposed to him; they had at first begun to despise a gift which was extended
                    from citizens to allies: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> in the next place
                    they frequently heard the consul Virginius in the assemblies as it were
                    prophesying — "that the gift of his colleague was pestilential —that those lands
                    were sure to bring slavery to those who should receive them; that the way was
                    paving to a throne. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For why was it that the
                    allies were included, and the Latin nation? What was the object of a third of
                    the land that had been taken being given back to the Hernici so lately our
                    enemies, except that instead of Coriolanus being their leader they may have
                    Cassius? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The dissuader and opposer of the
                    agrarian law now began to be popular. Both consuls then vied with each other in
                    humouring the commons. Virginius said that he would suffer the lands to be
                    assigned, provided they were assigned to no one but to a Roman citizen.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Cassius, because in the agrarian donation
                    he sought popularity among the allies, and was therefore lowered in the
                    estimation of his countrymen, in order that by another donation he might
                    conciliate their affections, ordered that the money received for the Sicilian
                    corn should be refunded to the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That
                    indeed the people rejected as nothing else than a present bribe for regal
                    authority: so strongly were his gifts spurned in the minds of men, as if they
                    possessed every thing in abundance, in consequence of their inveterate
                    suspicions of his aiming at sovereign power. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    As soon as he went out of office, it is certain that he was condemned and put to
                    death. There are some who represent his father as the person who inflicted the
                    punishment: that <pb n="129" xml:id="p.129"/> he, having tried him at home,
                    scourged him and put him to death, and consecrated his son's private property to
                    Ceres; that out of this a statue was set up and inscribed, <quote>given from the
                        Cassian family.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In some authors I find it stated, and that is
                    more probable, that a day of trial was assigned him for high treason, by the
                    questors, Kaeso Fabius and Lucius Valerius; and that he was condemned by the
                    decision of the people; that his house was demolished by a public decree: this
                    is the area before the temple of Tellus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But
                    whether that trial was private or public, he was condemned in the consulship of
                    Ser. Cornelius and Q. Fabius. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The resentment of the people against Cassius
                    was not of long duration. The allurements of the agrarian law, now that its
                    proposer was gone, were of themselves gaining ground in their minds; and this
                    feeling was further heightened by the parsimonious conduct of the senators, who,
                    the Volsci and Aequi having been defeated that year, defrauded the soldiers of
                    the booty; whatever was taken from the enemy, the consul Fabius sold, and lodged
                    the proceeds in the treasury. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Fabian name
                    was odious to the commons on account of the last consul: the senate however
                    succeeded in having Kaeso Fabius elected consul with L. Aemilius. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The commons, still further incensed at this, stirred
                    up foreign war by exciting disturbance at home; civil dissensions were then
                    interrupted by war. The senators and commons uniting, under the conduct of
                    Aemilius, conquered in battle the Volsci and Aequi who renewed hostilities.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The retreat, however, destroyed more of
                    the enemy than the battle; so perseveringly did the horse pursue them when
                    routed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During the same year, on the ides of
                    July, the temple of Castor was dedicated: it had been vowed during the Latin war
                    in the dictatorship of Posthumius: his son, who was elected duumvir for that
                    special purpose, dedicated it. In that year also the minds of the people were
                    excited by the charms of the agrarian law. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    tribunes of th people were for enhancing the popular power (vested in them) by
                    promoting the popular law. The senators, considering that there was enough and
                    more than enough of frenzy in the multitude without any additional incitement,
                    viewed with horror largesses and all inducements to temerity: the senators found
                    in the consuls most energetic abettors in making resistance. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> That portion of the commonwealth therefore pre- <pb n="130"
                        xml:id="p.130"/> vailed; and not for the present only, but for the
                    forthcoming year they succeeded in bringing in M. Fabius, Kaeso's brother, as
                    consul, and one still more detested by the commons for his persecution of Sp.
                    Cassius, L. Valerius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In that year also there
                    was a contest with the tribunes. The law proved to be a' vain project, and the
                    abettors of the law mere boasters, by their holding out a gift that was not
                    realized. The Fabian name was from thence held in high repute, after three
                    successive consulates, and all as it were uniformly exercised in contending with
                    the tribunes; accordingly, the honour remained for a considerable time in that
                    family, as being right well placed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A
                    Veientian war was then commenced; the Volscians, too, renewed hostilities; but
                    for foreign wars their strength was almost more than sufficient, and they abused
                    it by contending among themselves. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To the
                    distracted state of the public mind were added prodigies from heaven, exhibiting
                    almost daily threats in the city and in the country, and the soothsayers,
                    consulted by the state and by private individuals, one while by means of
                    entrails, another by birds, declared that there was no other cause for the
                    divine anger, but that the ceremonies of religion were not duly attended to.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These terrors, however, terminated in
                    this, that Oppia, a vestal virgin, being found guilty of a breach of chastity,
                    was made to suffer punishment. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius and C. Julius were then made
                    consuls. During this year the dissension at home was not abated, and the war
                    abroad was more desperate. Arms were taken up by the Aequans; the Veientes also
                    entered the territory of the Romans committing devastations; the solicitude
                    about which wars increasing, Kaeso Fabius and Sp. Fusius are created consuls.
                    The Aequi were laying siege to Ortona, a Latin city. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Veientes, now satiated with plunder, threatened that
                    they would besiege Rome itself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Which terrors,
                    when they ought to assuage, increased still further the bad feelings of the
                    commons: and the custom of declining the military service was now returning, not
                    of their own accord; but Sp. Licinius, a tribune of the people, thinking that
                    the time was come for forcing the agrarian law on the patricians by extreme
                    necessity, had taken on him the task of obstructing the military preparations.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But all the odium of the tribunitian power
                    was turned on the author; nor did the consuls rise up against him <pb n="131"
                        xml:id="p.131"/> more zealously than his own colleagues; and by their
                    assistance the consuls hold the levy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> An army
                    is raised for the two wars at the same time; one is given to Fabius to be led
                    against the Aequi, the other to Furius against the Veientians. And with respect
                    to the Veientians, nothing was done worthy of mention. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Fabius had much more trouble with his countrymen than with
                    the enemy: that one man himself, as consul, sustained the commonwealth, which
                    the army was betraying, as far as in them lay, through their hatred of the
                    consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For when the consul, in addition to
                    his other military talents, which he exhibited amply in his preparations for and
                    conduct of war, had so drawn up his line that he routed the enemy's army solely
                    by a charge of his cavalry, the infantry refused to pursue them when routed:
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and though the exhortation of their
                    general, whom they hated, could not move them, neither could even their own
                    infamy, and the present public disgrace and subsequent danger, if the enemy
                    should recover courage, oblige them to quicken their pace, or even to stand in
                    order of battle, if nothing else. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Without
                    orders they face about, and with a sorrowful air (you would suppose them beaten)
                    they return to the camp, execrating at one time their general, at another time
                    the services rendered by the cavalry. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor
                    were any remedies sought by the general for this so pestilent an example; so
                    true is it that the most distinguished talents are more likely to be deficient
                    in the tact of managing their countrymen than in that of conquering an enemy.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consul returned to Rome, not having
                    so much increased his military glory as irritated and exasperated the hatred of
                    his soldiers towards him. The patricians, however, succeeded in having the
                    consulship remain in the Fabian family. They elect M. Fabius consul: Cn. Manlius
                    is assigned as a colleague to Fabius. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year also had a tribune as a proposer of
                    the agrarian law. It was Titus Pontificius: he pursuing the same course, as if
                    it had succeeded with Sp. Licinius, obstructed the levy for a little time.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The patricians being once more perplexed,
                    Appius Claudius asserts <quote> that the tribunitian power was put down last
                        year: for the present by the very act, for the future by the precedent
                        established, and since it was found that it could be rendered ineffective by
                        its own strength; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for that there never
                        would be wanting a tribune who would both be willing to obtain a victory for
                        himself over <pb n="132" xml:id="p.132"/> his colleague, and the favour of
                        the better party by advancing the public weal. That both a plurality of
                        tribunes, if there were need of such plurality, would be ready to assist the
                        consuls; and that even one would be sufficient against all. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Only let the consuls and leading members of the senate
                        take care to gain over, if not all, at least some of the tribunes, to the
                        commonwealth and the senate. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senators, convinced by the counsels of
                    Appius, both collectively addressed the tribunes with kindness and civility, and
                    the men of consular rank, according as each possessed personal influence over
                    them individually, partly by conciliation, partly by authority, prevailed so far
                    as to make them consent that the powers of the tribunitian office should be
                    beneficial to the state; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and by the aid of
                    four tribunes against one obstructor of the public good, the consuls complete
                    the levy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They then set out to the Veientian
                    war, to which auxiliaries had flocked from all parts of Etruria, collected not
                    so much for the sake of the Veientians, as because they had formed a hope that
                    the Roman state might be destroyed by internal discord. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> And in the councils of all the states of Etruria the
                    leading men openly stated, <quote> that the Roman power was eternal, unless they
                        were distracted by disturbances among themselves. That this was the only
                        poison, this the bane discovered for powerful states, to render great
                        empires mortal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That this evil, a long
                        time retarded, partly by the wise measures of the patricians, partly by the
                        forbearance of the commons, had now proceeded to extremities. That two
                        states were now formed out of one: that each party had its own magistrates,
                        its own laws. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That though at first they
                        were accustomed to be turbulent during the levies, still that these same
                        individuals had ever been obedient to their commanders during war; that
                        military discipline being still retained, no matter what might be the state
                        of the city, it had been possible to withstand the evil; that now the custom
                        of not obeying their superior followed the Roman soldier even to the camp.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That in the last war in the very
                        field, in the very heat of battle, by consent of the army the victory was
                        voluntarily surrendered to the vanquished Aequi: that the standards were
                        deserted, the general abandoned on the field, and that the army had returned
                        to the camp without orders. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> That without
                        doubt, if perseverance were used, Rome might be conquered by her own
                        soldiery. <pb n="133" xml:id="p.133"/> That nothing else was necessary than
                        to declare and make a show of war: that the fates and the gods would of
                        themselves manage the rest. </quote> These hopes had armed the Etrurians,
                    who in many vicissitudes had been vanquished and victors. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman consuls also dreaded nothing else,
                    than their own strength, and their own arms. The recollection of the destructive
                    precedent set in the last war, deterred them from bringing matters to such a
                    pass as that they should have to fear two armies at the same time. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly they kept within their camp, avoiding
                    this double danger: <quote> that delay and time itself would soften down
                        resentment, and bring a right way of thinking to their minds. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Veientian enemy and the Etrurians
                    proceeded with so much the greater precipitation; they provoked them to battle,
                    first riding up to the camp and challenging them; at length, when they produced
                    no effect by reviling as well the consuls themselves as the army, they stated,
                        <quote> that the pretence of internal dissension was assumed as a cloak for
                        this cowardice; and that the consuls distrusted as much the courage as the
                        obedience of their soldiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That silence
                        and inaction among men in arms were a novel form of sedition. </quote>
                    Besides this they threw out reproaches, both true as well as false, on the
                    upstart quality of their race and origin. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Whilst they vociferated these reproaches beneath the very rampart and gates, the
                    consuls bore them without impatience: but at one time indignation, at another
                    time shame, distracted the breasts of the ignorant multitude, and diverted their
                    attention from intestine evils; they were unwilling that the enemy should come
                    off unpunished; they were unwilling that success should accrue to the patricians
                    or the consuls; foreign and domestic hatred struggled for mastery in their
                    breasts; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> at length the former prevail, so
                    haughtily and insolently did the enemy revile them; they crowd in a body to the
                    general's tent; they demand battle, they require that the signal be given.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls confer together as if to
                    deliberate; they continue the conference for a long time; they were desirous of
                    fighting, but that desire must be checked and concealed, that by opposition and
                    delay they might increase the ardour of the soldiery once roused. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> An answer is returned, <quote> that the latter in
                        question was premature, that it was not yet time for fighting: that they
                        should keep within their camp. </quote> They then issue a <pb n="134"
                        xml:id="p.134"/> proclamation, <quote> that they should abstain from
                        fighting; that if any one fought without orders, they should punish him as
                        an enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they were thus dismissed, their eagerness
                    for fighting increases in proportion as they think that the consuls were less
                    disposed for it; the enemies moreover come up much more insolently, as soon as
                    it was known that the consuls had determined not to fight. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For they supposed <quote> that they might insult them with
                        impunity; that their arms were not intrusted to the soldiery. That the
                        matter would explode in a violent mutiny; that a termination had come to the
                        Roman empire. </quote> Relying on these hopes, they run up to the gates,
                    heap reproaches on them, with difficulty refrain from assaulting the camp.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Now indeed the Romans could no longer
                    endure these insults; they crowd from every quarter of the camp to the consuls:
                    they no longer, as formerly, make their demand with reserve, through the
                    mediation of the centurions of the first rank; but all proceed indiscriminately
                    with loud clamours. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The affair was now ripe;
                    still they put it off. Fabius then, his colleague giving way in consequence of
                    his dread of mutiny being now augmented by the uproar, after he had commanded
                    silence by sound of trumpet, says, <quote> that these men are able to conquer,
                        Cneius Manlius, I know; that they are willing they themselves have prevented
                        me from knowing. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It is therefore resolved
                        and determined not to give the signal, unless they swear that they will
                        return victorious from this battle. The soldier has once deceived the Roman
                        consul in the field, the gods he never will deceive. </quote> There was a
                    centurion, Marcus Flavoleius, one of the foremost in demanding battle; he says,
                        <quote>M. Fabius, I will return victorious from the field.</quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> If he deceived, he invokes the anger of
                    father Jove, Mars Gradivus, and of the other gods. After him the entire army
                    severally take the same oath. The signal is given to them when sworn; they take
                    up arms, go into battle, full of rage and of hope. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> They bid the Etrurians now to cast their reproaches; they
                    severally require that the enemy, once so ready with the tongue, should now
                    stand before them armed as they were. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> On that
                    day the bravery of all, both commons and patricians, was extraordinary: the
                    Fabian name, the Fabian race shone forth most conspicuous: they are determined
                    to recover in that battle the affections of the commons, which during many civil
                    con- <pb n="135" xml:id="p.135"/> tests had been alienated from them. The line
                    of battle is formed; nor do the Veientian foe and the Etrurian legions decline
                    the contest. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An almost certain hope was entertained that
                    they would no more fight with them than they had don with the Aequi; that even
                    some more serious attempt was not to be despaired of, considering the irritated
                    state of their feelings, and the very critical occasion. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The affair turned out altogether differently; for never
                    before in any other war did the Roman soldiers enter the field with more
                    determined minds (so much had the enemy exasperated them by taunts on the one
                    hand, and the consuls by delay on the other). The <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> Etrurians had scarcely time to form their ranks, when the
                    javelins having been thrown away at random, in the first hurry, rather than
                    discharged with aim, the battle had now come to close fighting, even to swords,
                    where the fury of war is most desperate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Among
                    the foremost the Fabian family was distinguished for the sight it afforded and
                    the example it presented to their fellow citizens; one of these, Q. Fabius, (he
                    had been consul two years before,) as he was advancing at the head of his men
                    against a dense body of Veientians, and whilst engaged amid numerous parties of
                    the enemy, and therefore not prepared for it, was transfixed with a sword
                    through the breast by a Tuscan who presumed on his bodily strength and skill in
                    arms: on the weapon being extracted, Fabius fell forward on the wound.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both armies felt the fall of this one man,
                    and the Roman began in consequence to give way, when the consul Marcus Fabius
                    leaped over the body as it lay, and holding up his buckler, said, <quote> Is
                        this what you swore, soldiers, that you would return to the camp in flight?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> are you thus more afraid of your most
                        dastardly enemies, than of Jupiter and Mars, by whom you have sworn? But I
                        who have not sworn will either return victorious, or will fall fighting here
                        beside thee, Q. Fabius. </quote> Then Kaeso Fabius, the consul of the
                    preceding year, says to the consul, <quote> Brother, is it by these words you
                        think you will prevail on them to fight? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        the gods by whom they have sworn will prevail n them. Let us also, as men of
                        noble birth, as is worthy of the Fabian name, enkindle the courage of the
                        soldiers by fighting rather than by exhorting. </quote> Thus the two Fabii
                    rush forward to the <pb n="136" xml:id="p.136"/> front with presented spears,
                    and brought on with them the whole line. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle being restored on one side, Cn.
                    Manlius, the consul, with no less ardour, encouraged the fight on the other
                    wing. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Where an almost similar result took
                    place; for as the soldiers undauntedly followed Q. Fabius on the one wing, so
                    did they follow Manlius on this, as he was driving the enemy now nearly routed,
                    and when he, having received a severe wound, retired from the battle, they fell
                    back, supposing that he was slain, and would have given way, had not the other
                    consul, galloping at full speed to that quarter with some troops of horse,
                    supported their drooping energies, crying out that his colleague was still
                    alive, that he himself was now come victorious, having routed the other wing.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Manlius also shows himself to restore the
                    battle. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The well-known voices of the two
                    consuls rekindle the courage of the soldiers; at the same time too the enemy's
                    line was now weakened, whilst, relying on their superior numbers, they draw off
                    their reserve and send them to storm the camp. This being assaulted without much
                    resistance, whilst they lose time in attending to plunder rather than to
                    fighting, the Roman triarii, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        triarii were veteran soldiers of approved valour: they formed the third
                        line, whence their name. </note> who had not been able to sustain the first
                    shock, having sent an account to the consuls of the present position of
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> affairs, return in a compact body to the
                    Praetorium, and of themselves renew the battle. The consul Manlius also having
                    returned to the camp, <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and posted soldiers at
                    all the gates, had blocked up every passage against the enemy. This desperate
                    situation aroused the fury rather than the bravery of the Etrurians; for when
                    rushing on wherever hope held out the prospect of escape, they had frequently
                    advanced with fruitless efforts; one body of young men makes an attack on the
                    consul himself, conspicuous from his arms. The first weapons were intercepted by
                    those who stood around him; afterwards their force could not be sustained. The
                    consul falls, having received <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> a mortal wound,
                    and all around him are dispersed. The courage of the Etrurians rises. Terror
                    drives the Romans in dismay through the entire camp; and matters would have come
                    to extremities, had not the lieutenant-generals, hastily <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="137" xml:id="p.137"/> seizing the body of the consul, opened a passage
                    for the enemy at one gate. Through this they rush out; and going away in the
                    utmost disorder, they fall in with the other consul, who had been victorious;
                    there again they are slain and routed <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> in every
                    direction. A glorious victory was obtained, saddened however by two so
                    illustrious deaths. The consul, therefore, on the senate voting him a triumph,
                    replied, that <quote> if the army could triumph without their general,
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> he would readily accede to it in
                        consideration of their distinguished behaviour in that war: that for his own
                        part, his family being plunged in grief in consequence of the death of his
                        brother Q. Fabius, and the commonwealth being in some degree bereaved by the
                        loss of one of her consuls, he would not accept the laurel blasted by public
                        and private grief. </quote> The triumph thus resigned was more distinguished
                    than any triumph actually enjoyed; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> so true it
                    is, that glory refused in due season sometimes returns with accumulated lustre.
                    He next celebrates the two funerals of his colleague and brother, one after the
                    other, he himself acting as panegyrist in the case of both, when by ascribing to
                    them his own deserts, he himself obtained the greatest share of them. And not
                    unmindful of that which he had conceived at the commencement of his consulate,
                    namely, the regaining the <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> affection of the
                    people, he distributes the wounded soldiers among the patricians to be cured.
                    Most of them were given to the Fabii: nor were they treated with greater
                    attention in any other place. From this time the Fabii began to be popular, and
                    that not by any practices except such as were beneficial to the state. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly Kaeso Fabius, having been elected
                    consul with T. Virginius not more with the zealous wishes of the senators than
                    of the commons, attended neither to wars, nor levies, nor any other object,
                    until the hope of concord being now in some measure commenced, the feelings of
                    the commons might be consolidated with those of the senators as soon as
                    possible. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Wherefore at the commencement of the
                    year he proposed: <quote> that before any tribune should stand forth as an
                        abettor of the agrarian law, the patricians themselves should be beforehand
                        with them in performing their duty; that they should distribute among the
                        commons the land taken from the enemy in as equal a proportion as possible;
                        that it was but just that those should obtain it, by whose blood and sweat
                            <pb n="138" xml:id="p.138"/> it was obtained. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The patricians rejected the proposal with
                    scorn; some even complained that the once brilliant talents of Kaeso were now
                    becoming wanton, and were waning through excess of glory. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> There were afterwards no factions in the city. The Latins
                    were harassed by the incursions of the Aequi. Kaeso being sent thither with an
                    army, passes into the very territory of the Aequi to depopulate it. The Aequi
                    retired into the towns, and kept themselves within the walls: on that account no
                    battle worth mentioning was fought. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But a blow
                    was received from the Veientian foe through the temerity of the other consul;
                    and the army would have been all cut off, had not Kaeso Fabius come to their
                    assistance in time. From that time there was neither peace nor war with the
                    Veientians; their proceedings had now come very near to the form of that of
                    brigands. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They retired from the Roman troops
                    into the city; when they perceived that the troops were drawn off, they made
                    incursions into the country, alternately evading war by quiet, quiet by war.
                    Thus the matter could neither be dropped altogether, nor brought to a
                    conclusion; and other wars were impending either at the moment, as from the
                    Aequi and Volsci, who remained inactive no longer than until the recent smart of
                    their late disaster should pass away; or it was evident that the Sabines, ever
                    hostile, and all Etruria would put themselves in motion: <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> but the Veientians, a constant rather than a formidable
                    enemy, kept their minds in constant uneasiness by their insults more frequently
                    than by any danger apprehended from them; a matter which could at no time be
                    neglected, and which suffered them not to direct their attention to any other
                    object. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the Fabian family addressed the
                    senate; the consul speaks in the name of the family: <quote> Conscript fathers,
                        the Veientian war requires, as you know, a constant rather than a strong
                        force. Do you attend to other wars: assign the Fabii as enemies to the
                        Veientians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> We pledge ourselves that the
                        majesty of the Roman name shall be safe in that quarter. That war, as the
                        property of our family, it is our determination to conduct at our own
                        private expense. Let the republic be spared the expense of soldiers and
                        money there. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The warmest thanks were returned to them. The
                    consul, leaving the senate-house, accompanied by the Fabii in a body, who had
                    been standing in the porch of the senate-house, returned home. Being ordered to
                    attend <pb n="139" xml:id="p.139"/> on the following day in arms at the consul's
                    gate, they retire to their homes. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The rumour spreads through the entire city;
                    they extol the Fabii to the skies by their encomiums. <quote> That a single
                        family had taken on them the burden of the state: that the Veientian war had
                        now become a private concern, a private quarrel. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> If there were two families of the same strength in the
                        city, let them demand, the one the Volsci for itself, the other the Aequi;
                        that all the neighbouring states might be subdued, the Roman people all the
                        time enjoying profound peace. </quote> The day following, the Fabii take up
                    arms; they assemble where they had been ordered. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> The consul coming forth in his paludamentum, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Before a consul set out on any expedition, he offered
                        sacrifices and prayers in the Capitol; and then, laying aside his consular
                        gown, marched out of the city, dressed in a military robe of state, called
                        Paludamentum. </note> beholds his entire family in the porch drawn up in
                    order of march; being <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> received into the
                    centre, he orders the standards to be carried forward. Never did an army march
                    through the city, either smaller in number, or more distinguished in fame and in
                    the admiration of all men. Three hundred and six soldiers, all patricians, all
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> of the one stock, not one of whom the
                    senate would reject as a leader in its palmiest days, proceeded on their march,
                    menacing destruction to the Veientian state by the prowess of a single family. A
                    crowd followed, partly belonging to their kinsmen and friends, who contemplated
                    in mind no moderation <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> either as to their hopes
                    or anxiety, but every thing on the highest scale; partly consisting of
                    individuals not connected with their family, aroused by solicitude for the
                    public weal, all <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> enraptured with esteem and
                    admiration. They bid them <quote> proceed in the brave resolve, proceed with
                        happy omens, bring back results proportioned to their undertaking: thence to
                        expect consulships and triumphs, all rewards, all honours from them.
                    </quote> As they passed the Capitol and the citadel, and the other sacred
                    edifices, they offer up prayers to all the gods that presented themselves to
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> their sight, or to their mind: that
                        <quote> they would send forward that band with prosperity and success, and
                        soon send them back safe into their country to their parents. </quote> In
                    vain were these prayers sent up. Having set out on <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> their luckless road by the right-hand postern of the
                    Carmental gate, they arrive at the river Cremera: his ap- <pb n="140"
                        xml:id="p.140"/> peared a favourable situation for fortifying a post. L.
                    Aemilius and C. Servilius were then created consuls. And as long as there was
                    nothing else to occupy them but mutual devastations, the Fabii were not only
                    sufficiently able <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> to protect their garrison,
                    but through the entire tract, as far as the Etrurian joins the Roman territory,
                    they protected all their own districts and ravaged those of the enemy, spreading
                    their forces along both frontiers. There was afterwards an intermission, though
                    not of long duration, to these depredations: whilst both the Veientians, having
                    sent for an army from Etruria, assault the post <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> at the Cremera, and the Roman troops, led thither by L. Aemilius the consul,
                    come to a close engagement in the field with the Etrurians; although the
                    Veientians had scarcely time to draw up their line: for during the first alarm,
                    whilst the ranks are posting themselves behind their respective banners and they
                    are stationing their reserves, a brigade of Roman cavalry charging them suddenly
                    in flank, took away all opportunity not only of commencing the fight, but even
                    of standing their ground. Thus being driven back to the Red <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Rocks, (there they pitched their camp,) they suppliantly
                    sue for peace; for the obtaining of which they were sorry, from the natural
                    inconsistency of their minds, before the Roman garrison was drawn off from the
                    Cremera. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Again the Veientian state had to contend with
                    the Fabii without any additional military armament [on either side]; and there
                    were not merely incursions into each other's territories, or sudden attacks on
                    those making the incursions, but they fought repeatedly in the open field, and
                    in pitched battles: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and one family of the
                    Roman people oftentimes gained the victory over an entire Etrurian state, one of
                    the most powerful at that time. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This at first
                    appeared mortifying and humiliating to the Veientians: then (they formed) a
                    design, suggested by the circumstance, of surprising their daring enemy by an
                    ambuscade; they were even glad that the confidence of the Fabii was increasing
                    by their great success. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Wherefore cattle were
                    frequently driven in the way of the plundering parties, as if they had come
                    there by mere accident, and tracts of land were abandoned by the flight of the
                    peasants; and troops of armed men sent to prevent the devastations retreated
                    more frequently from pretended than from real fear. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> And now the Fabii had such a contempt for the enemy, as to
                        <pb n="141" xml:id="p.141"/> believe that their invincible arms could not be
                    withstood either in any place or on any occasion: this presumption carried them
                    so far, that at the sight of some cattle at a distance from Cremera, with an
                    extensive plain lying between, they ran down to it (although few troops of the
                    enemy were observed); and when incautious and in disorderly haste they had
                    passed the ambuscade placed on either side of the very road; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> and when dispersed in different directions they began to
                    carry off the cattle straying about, as is usual when they are frightened, the
                    Veientians rise up suddenly from their ambuscade, and the enemy were in front
                    and on every side. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first the shout that was
                    raised terrified them; then weapons assailed them from every side; and, the
                    Etrurians closing, they also were compelled, hemmed in as they now were by a
                    compact body of soldiers, to contract their own circle within a narrower
                    compass; which circumstance rendered striking both their own paucity of numbers,
                    and the superior numbers of the enemy, the ranks being crowded in a narrow
                    space. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the plan of fighting, which they
                    had directed equally against every part, being now relinquished, they all
                    incline their forces towards one point; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> in
                    that direction straining every effort both with their bodies and arms, they
                    forced a passage by forming a wedge. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The way
                    led to a hill of moderate acclivity; here they first halted: presently, as soon
                    as the higher ground afforded them time to gain breath, and to recover from so
                    great a panic, they repulsed them as they advanced up; and the small band by the
                    advantage of the ground was gaining the victory, had not a party of the
                    Veientians, sent round the ridge of the hill, made their way to the summit; thus
                    again the enemy obtained the higher ground; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    all the Fabii were killed to a man, and the fort was taken: it is agreed on all
                    hands that the three hundred and six were cut off; that one <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">This statement is rejected by Niebuhr
                        entirely</note> only, who nearly attained the age of puberty, was left as a
                    stock for the Fabian race; and that he was destined to prove the greatest
                    support in the dangerous emergencies of the Roman people both at home and in
                    war. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the time when this disaster was received,
                    C. Horatius and T. Menenius were consuls. Menenius was immediately sent against
                    the Etrurians, elated with victory. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then too
                    an unsuc- <pb n="142" xml:id="p.142"/> cessful battle was fought, and the enemy
                    took possession of the Janiculum: and the city would have been besieged,
                    scarcity of provisions bearing hard upon them in addition to the war, (for the
                    Etrurians had passed the Tiber,) had not the consul Horatius been recalled from
                    the Volsci; and so closely did that war approach the very walls, that the first
                    battle was fought near the temple of Hope with doubtful success, and a second
                    time at the Colline gate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There, although the
                    Romans had the advantage in a slight degree only, yet that contest rendered the
                    soldiers better for future battles by restoring to them their former courage.
                    Aulus Virginius and Sp. Servilius are created consuls. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> After the defeat sustained in the last battle, the
                    Veientians declined an engagement. Ravages were committed, and they made
                    incursions in every direction on the Roman territory from the Janiculum as if
                    from a fortress; no where were the cattle or the husbandmen safe. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> They were afterwards entrapped by the same stratagem
                    as that by which they had entrapped the Fabii: having pursued some cattle that
                    had been driven on designedly for the purpose of decoying them, they fell into
                    an ambuscade; in proportion as they were more numerous, the slaughter was
                    greater. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The violent resentment resulting from
                    this disaster was the cause and commencement of one still greater: for having
                    crossed the Tiber by night, they attempted to assault the camp of the consul
                    Servilius; being repulsed from thence with great slaughter, they with difficulty
                    made good their retreat into the Janiculum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The consul himself also crosses the Tiber, fortifies his camp at the foot of the
                    Janiculum: at break of day on the following morning, both from being somewhat
                    elated by the success of the battle of the day before, more however because the
                    scarcity of corn forced him into measures which, though dangerous, (he adopted)
                    because they were more expeditious, he rashly marched his army up the steep
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> of the Janiculum to the camp of the
                    enemy, and being repulsed from thence with more disgrace than he had repulsed
                    them on the preceding day, he was saved, both himself and his army, by the
                    intervention of his colleague. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Etrurians
                    (hemmed in) between the two armies, when they presented their rear to the one
                    and the other by turns, were entirely cut off. Thus the Veientian war was
                    crushed by a fortunate act of temerity. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Together with the peace, provisions returned
                    to the city <pb n="143" xml:id="p.143"/> in greater abundance, both by reason of
                    corn having been brought in from Campania, and, as soon as the fear felt by each
                    of future famine left them, that corn being brought forward which had been
                    hoarded up. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then their minds once more became
                    licentious from their present abundance and ease, and their former subjects of
                    complaint, now that there were none abroad, they sought for at home; the
                    tribunes began to excite the commons by their poison, the agrarian law: they
                    roused them against the senators who opposed it, and not only against them as a
                    body, but also against particular individuals. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Q. Considius and T. Genucius, the proposers of the agrarian law, appoint a day
                    of trial for T. Menenius: the loss of the fort of Cremera, whilst the consul had
                    his standing camp at no great distance from thence, was the charge against him.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They crushed him, though both the senators
                    had exerted themselves in his behalf with no less earnestness than in behalf of
                    Coriolanus, and the popularity of his father Agrippa was not yet forgotten.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The tribunes, however, went no further
                    than a fine: though they had arraigned him for a capital offence, they imposed
                    on him, when found guilty, a fine of two thousand <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    This proved fatal. They say that he could not submit to the disgrace, and to the
                    anguish of mind (occasioned by it): that, in consequence, he was taken off by
                    disease. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another senator, Sp. Servilius, being
                    soon after arraigned, as soon as he went out of office, a day of trial having
                    been appointed for him by the tribunes, L. Caedicius and T. Statius, at the very
                    commencement of the year, in the consulship of C. Nautius and P. Valerius, did
                    not, like Menenius, meet the attacks of the tribunes with supplications from
                    himself and the patricians, but with firm reliance on his own integrity, and his
                    personal influence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The battle With the
                    Etrurians at the Janiculum was the charge against him also: but being a man of
                    an intrepid spirit, as he had formerly acted in the case of public peril, so now
                    in that which was personal to himself, he dispelled the danger by boldly facing
                    it, by confuting not only the tribunes but the commons also, by a bold speech,
                    and upbraiding them with the condemnation and death of T. Menenius, by the good
                    offices of whose father the commons were formerly re-established, and were now
                    in possession of those laws and those magistrates, by' means of which they then
                    exercised their insolence; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> his colleague <pb
                        n="144" xml:id="p.144"/> Virginius also, who was brought forward as a
                    witness, aided him by assigning to him a share of his own deserts; the
                    condemnation of Menenius however was of greater service to him (so much had they
                    changed their minds). </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The contests at home were now concluded. A
                    Veientian war broke out, with whom the Sabines had united their forces. The
                    consul P. Valerius, after auxiliaries were sent for from the Latins and
                    Hernicians, being despatched to Veii with an army, immediately attacks the
                    Sabine camp, which had been pitched before the walls of their allies: and
                    occasioned such great consternation, that while, dispersed in different
                    directions, they sally forth to repel the assault of the enemy, the gate which
                    the Romans first attacked was taken; then within the rampart there was rather a
                    carnage than a battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From the camp the alarm
                    spreads into the city; the Veientians run to arms in as great a panic as if Veii
                    had been taken: some come up to the support of the Sabines, others fall upon the
                    Romans, who had directed all their force against the camp. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For a little while they were disconcerted and thrown into
                    confusion; then they too forming two fronts make a stand: and the cavalry, being
                    commanded by the consul to charge, routs the Etrurians and puts them to flight;
                    and in the same hour two armies and two of the most influential and powerful of
                    the neighbouring states were vanquished. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Whilst these transactions are going on at Veii, the Volsci and Aequi had pitched
                    their camp in the Latin territory, and laid waste their frontiers. The Latins,
                    by their own exertions, being joined by the Hernicians, without either a Roman
                    general or Roman auxiliaries, stripped them of their camp. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Besides recovering their own effects, they obtained immense
                    booty. The consul C. Nautius, however, was sent against the Volsci from Rome.
                    The custom, I suppose, was not pleasing for allies to carry on wars with their
                    own forces and under their own direction without a Roman general and troops.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There was no kind of injury or indignity
                    that was not practised against the Volsci; nor could they be prevailed on
                    however to come to an engagement in the field. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Furius and Caius Manlius were the next
                    consuls. The Veientians fell to Manlius as his province. War however did not
                    take place: a truce for forty years was granted them at their request, corn and
                    pay for the soldiers <pb n="145" xml:id="p.145"/> being demanded of them.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Disturbance at home immediately succeeds
                    to peace abroad: the commons were, goaded by the tribunes with the excitement of
                    the agrarian law. The consuls, nothing intimidated by the condemnation of
                    Menenius, nor by the danger of Servilius, resist with their utmost might; Cn.
                    Genucius, a tribune of the people, arraigned the consuls on their going out of
                    office. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Lucius Aemilius and Opiter Virginius
                    enter on the consulate. Instead of Virginius I find Vopiscus Julius consul in
                    some annals. In this year (whatever consuls it had) Furius and Manlius, being
                    summoned to trial before the people, go about in suppliant garb not more to the
                    commons than to the younger patricians; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> they
                    advise, they caution them <quote> to keep themselves from honours and the
                        administration of public affairs, and that they would consider the consular
                        fasces, the praetexta and curule chair, as nothing else than the decorations
                        of a funeral; that when covered with these fine insignia, as with fillets,
                        they were doomed to death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But if the
                        charms of the consulate were so great, they should rest satisfied that the
                        consulate was held in captivity and crushed by the tribunitian power; that
                        every thing was to be done at the nod and command of the tribune by the
                        consul, as if he were a tribune's beadle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        If he stir, if he have reference to the patricians, if he should think for a
                        moment that there existed any other party in the state but the commons, let
                        him place before his eyes the banishment of Caius Marcius, the condemnation
                        and death of Menenius. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Fired by these discourses, the patricians from
                    that time held their consultations not in public, but in private, and withdrawn
                    from the knowledge of the many; where when this one point was agreed on, that
                    the accused must be rescued whether by just or unjust means, every proposition
                    that was most desperate was most approved; nor was an actor wanted for any deed
                    however daring. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly on the day of
                    trial, when the people stood in the forum in anxious expectation, they at first
                    began to feel surprised that the tribune did not come down; then when the delay
                    was now becoming more suspicious, they considered that he was deterred by the
                    nobles, and they complained that the public cause was abandoned and betrayed.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At length those who had been waiting
                    before the gate of the tribune's residence, bring word that he was found dead in
                    his house. As soon as rumour spread this <pb n="146" xml:id="p.146"/> through
                    the whole assembly, just as an army disperses on the fall of its general, so did
                    they separate in different directions. The principal panic seized the tribunes,
                    now warned by their colleague's death what little aid the devoting laws afforded
                    them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor did the patricians bear their joy
                    with sufficient moderation; and so far was any of them from feeling compunction
                    at the guilty act, that even those who were innocent wished to be considered to
                    have perpetrated it, and it was openly declared that the tribunitian power
                    should be subdued by chastisement. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately after this victory of a most
                    ruinous precedent a levy is proclaimed; and the tribunes being now overawed, the
                    consuls accomplish the matter without any opposition. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Then indeed the commons became enraged more on account of
                    the silence of the tribunes than the command of the consuls: and they said
                        <quote> there was an end of their liberty: that they were come back again to
                        the old condition of things; that the tribunitian power had died along with
                        Genucius and was buried with him; that other means must be devised and
                        practised, by which to resist the patricians; and that the only method for
                        that was that the people should defend themselves, since they now had no
                        other aid. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That four-and- twenty lictors
                        waited on the consuls; and that these very individuals were from among the
                        commons; that nothing could be more despicable, nor weaker, if there were
                        only persons who could despise them; that each person magnified those things
                        and made them objects of terror to himself. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they had excited each other by these
                    discourses, a lictor was despatched by the consuls to Volero Publilius, a man
                    belonging to the commons, because he stated, that having been a centurion he
                    ought not to be made a common soldier. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Volero
                    appeals to the tribunes. When one came to his assistance, the consuls order the
                    man to be stripped and the rods to be got ready. <quote>I appeal to the
                        people,</quote> says Volero, <quote> since tribunes had rather see a Roman
                        citizen scourged before their eyes, than themselves be butchered by you in
                        their bed. </quote> The more vehemently he cried out, the more violently did
                    the lictor tear off his clothes and strip him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Then Volero, being both himself of great bodily strength, and being aided by his
                    partisans, having repulsed the lictor, when the shouts of those indignant in his
                    behalf became very intense, betook himself into the <pb n="147" xml:id="p.147"/>
                    thickest part of the crowd, crying out, <quote> I appeal, and implore the
                        protection of the commons; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> assist me,
                        fellow citizens; assist me, fellow soldiers; there is no use in waiting for
                        the tribunes, who themselves stand in need of your aid. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The men, being much excited, prepare as it
                    were for battle; and it became manifest that there was urgent danger, that
                    nothing would be held sacred by any one, that there would no longer exist any
                    public or private right. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the consuls
                    faced this so violent storm, they soon experienced that majesty without strength
                    had but little security; the lictors being maltreated, the fasces broken, they
                    are driven from the forum into the senate-house, uncertain how far Volero would
                    push his victory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After that, the disturbance
                    subsiding, when they had ordered the senate to be convened, they complain of the
                    outrages committed on themselves, of the violence of the people, the daring of
                    Volero. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Many violent measures having been
                    proposed, the elder members prevailed, who recommended that the unthinking
                    rashness of the commons should not be met by the passionate resentment of the
                    patricians. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commons having espoused the interest of
                    Volero, with great warmth choose him, at the next election, tribune of the
                    people for that year, which had Lucius Pinarius and Publius Furius for consuls;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and, contrary to the opinion of all men,
                    who thought that he would let loose his tribuneship in harassing the consuls of
                    the preceding year, postponing private resentment to the public interest,
                    without assailing the consuls even by a single word, he proposed a law to the
                    people that plebeian magistrates should be elected at the comitia by tribes.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A matter of no trifling moment was now
                    being brought forward, under an aspect at first sight by no means alarming; but
                    one which in reality deprived the patricians of all power to elect whatever
                    tribunes they pleased by the suffrages of their clients. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The patricians used all their energies in resisting this
                    proposition, which was most pleasing to the commons; and though none of the
                    college could be induce by the influence either of the consuls or of the chief
                    member of the senate to enter a protest against it, the only means of resistance
                    which now existed; yet the matter, important as it was by its own weight, is
                    spun out by contention till the following year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The commons re-elect Volero as tribune. The senators, considering that the
                    question would be carried to the <pb n="148" xml:id="p.148"/> very extreme of a
                    struggle, elect to the consulate Appius Claudius, the son of Appius, who was
                    both hated by and hated the commons, ever since the contests between them and
                    his father. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Titus Quintius is assigned to him
                    as his colleague. In the very commencement of the year no other question took
                    precedence of that regarding the law. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But
                    though Volero was the inventor of it, his colleague, Laetorius, was both a more
                    recent abettor of it, as well as a more energetic one. Whilst Volero confined
                    himself to the subject of the law, avoiding all abuse of the consuls, he
                    commenced with accusing Appius and his family, as having ever been most
                    overbearing and cruel towards the Roman commons, contending that he had been
                    elected by the senators, not as consul, but as executioner, to harass and
                    torture the people; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> his rude tongue, he being
                    a military man, was not sufficient to express the freedom of his sentiments.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Language therefore failing him, he says,
                        <quote> Romans, since I do not speak with as much readiness as I make good
                        what I have spoken, attend here tomorrow. I will either die here before your
                        eyes, or will carry the law. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the following day the tribunes take
                    possession of the temple; the consuls and the nobility take their places in the
                    assembly to obstruct the law. Laetorius orders all persons to be removed, except
                    those going to vote; the young nobles kept their places, paying no regard to the
                    officer; then Laetorius orders some of them to be seized. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The consul Appius insisted <quote> that the tribune had no
                        jurisdiction over any one except a plebeian; for that he was not a
                        magistrate of the people in general, but only of the commons; <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> for that even he himself could not, according to
                        the usage of their ancestors, by virtue of his authority remove any person;
                        because the words run thus, <hi rend="italics">if ye think proper, depart,
                            Romans.</hi>
                    </quote> He was able to disconcert Laetorius by arguing fluently and
                    contemptuously concerning the right. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    tribune therefore, burning with rage, sends his beadle to the consul; the consul
                    sends his lictor to the tribune, exclaiming that he was a private individual,
                    without power and without magistracy; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and the
                    tribune would have been roughly treated, had not both the entire assembly risen
                    up with great warmth in behalf of the tribune against the consul, and a rush of
                    persons belonging to the multitude, which was now much excited, taken place from
                    the entire city into the forum. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Appius,
                    however, withstood <pb n="149" xml:id="p.149"/> so great a storm with obstinacy,
                    and the contest would have ended in a battle, not without blood, had not
                    Quintius, the other consul, after giving it in charge to the men of consular
                    dignity to remove his colleague from the forum by force, if they could not do it
                    otherwise, himself assuaged the enraged people by entreaties, and implored the
                    tribunes to dismiss the assembly. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That they should give their passion time to cool; that delay would not
                        deprive them of their power, but would add prudence to strength; and that
                        the senators would be under the control of the people, and the consul under
                        that of the senators. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With difficulty the people were pacified by
                    Quintius: with much more difficulty was the other consul by the patricians.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The assembly of the people being at length
                    dismissed, the consuls convene the senate; where, though fear and resentment by
                    turns had produced a diversity of opinions, the more they were recalled, after
                    the lapse of time, from violence to reflection, the more averse did they become
                    to a continuance of the dispute, so that they returned thanks to Quintius,
                    because by his exertions the disturbance had been quieted. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Appius is requested <quote> to consent that the consular
                        dignity should be merely so great as it could be in a peaceably conducted
                        state; that as long as the tribune and consuls were drawing all power, each
                        to his own side, no strength was left between; that the object aimed at was
                        in whose hands the commonwealth should be, distracted and torn as it was,
                        rather than that it should be safe. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Appius, on the contrary, called gods and men
                    to witness that <quote> the commonwealth was betrayed and abandoned through
                        cowardice; that it was not the consul that was wanting to the senate, but
                        the senate to the consul; that more oppressive laws were now being submitted
                        to than were sanctioned on the sacred mount. </quote> Overcome however by
                    the unanimous feeling of the senators, he desisted: the law is carried without
                    opposition. </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then for the first time the tribunes were
                    elected in the comitia by tribes. Piso said that three were added to the number,
                    whereas there had been only two before. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                    names the tribunes also, Caius Sicinius, Lucius Numitorius, Marcus Duilius,
                    Spurius Icilius, Lucius Mecilius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> During the
                    disturbance at Rome, a war with the Volscians and Aequans broke out; they had
                    laid waste the lands, so that if any secession <pb n="150" xml:id="p.150"/> of
                    the people should take place, they might find a refuge with them. The
                    differences being afterwards settled, they removed their camp backwards. Appius
                    Claudius was sent against the Volscians; the Aequans fell to Quintius as his
                    province. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The severity of Appius was the same
                    in war as at home, being more unrestrained because he was free from tribunitian
                    control. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He hated the commons with more than
                    his father's hatred: he had been defeated by them: when he was set up as the
                    only consul to oppose the tribunitian influence, a law was passed, which former
                    consuls obstructed with less effort, amid hopes of the senators by no means so
                    great (as those formed of him). His resentment and indignation at this, excited
                    his imperious temper to harass the army by the rigour of his command; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> nor could it (the army) however be subdued by any
                    means; such a spirit of opposition had they imbibed. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They executed every measure slowly, indolently,
                    negligently, and with stubbornness: neither shame nor fear restrained them. If
                    he wished the army to move on with expedition, they designedly went more slowly:
                    if he came up to them to encourage them in their work, they all relaxed the
                    energy which they before exerted of their own accord: <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> when he was present they cast down their eyes, they
                    silently cursed him as he passed by; so that his mind, invulnerable to plebeian
                    hatred, was sometimes moved. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> All kind of harsh
                    treatment being tried in vain, he no longer held any intercourse with the
                    soldiers; he said the army was corrupted by the centurions; he sometimes
                    gibingly called them tribunes of the people and Voleros. </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> None of these circumstances were unknown to
                    the Volscians, and they pressed on with so much the more vigour, hoping that the
                    Roman army would entertain the same spirit of opposition against Appius, which
                    they had formerly entertained against the consul Fabius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But they were much more violent against Appius than against
                    Fabius. For they were not only unwilling to conquer, like Fabius' army, but they
                    wished to be conquered. When led out to the field, they made for their camp in
                    an ignominious flight, nor did they stand their ground until they saw the
                    Volscians advancing to their fortifications, and making dreadful havoc on the
                    rear of their army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then the obligation to
                    fight was wrung from them, in order that the victorious enemy should be
                    dislodged from <pb n="151" xml:id="p.151"/> their lines; yet it was sufficiently
                    plain that the Roman soldiers were only unwilling that their camp should be
                    taken; some of them gloried in their own defeat and disgrace. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When the determined spirit of Appius, undaunted by these
                    things, wished to exercise severity still further, and he summoned a meeting,
                    the lieutenant-generals and tribunes flock around him, advising him <quote> that
                        he would not determine on venturing a trial of an authority, the entire
                        strength of which lay in the acquiescence of those who were to obey.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the soldiers generally refused to
                        come to the assembly, and that their clamours were heard in every direction
                        demanding that the camp should be removed from the Volscian territory. That
                        the victorious enemy were but a little time ago almost at the very gates and
                        rampart; and that not merely a suspicion, but a manifest indication of a
                        grievous disaster presented itself to their eyes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Yielding at length, (since they would gain
                    nothing save a delay of punishment,) having prorogued the assembly, after he had
                    given orders that their march should be proclaimed for the following day, he, at
                    the first dawn, gave the signal for departure by sound of trumpet. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When the army, having just got clear of the camp,
                    were forming themselves, the Volscians, as being aroused by the same signal,
                    fall upon those in the rear; from whom the alarm spreading to the van,
                    confounded both the battalions and ranks with such consternation, that neither
                    the generals' orders could be distinctly heard, nor the lines be drawn up, no
                    one thinking of any thing but flight. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In such
                    confusion did they make their way through heaps of dead bodies and of arms, that
                    the enemy ceased to pursue sooner than the Romans to fly. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The soldiers being at length collected from their scattered
                    rout, the consul, after he had in vain followed his men for the purpose of
                    rallying them, pitched his camp in a peaceful part of the country; and an
                    assembly being convened, after inveighing not without good reason against the
                    army, as traitors to military discipline, deserters of their posts, frequently
                    asking them, one by one, where were their standards, where their arms;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> he first beat with rods and then beheaded
                    those soldiers who had thrown down their arms, the standard-bearers who
                        <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> had lost their standards, and moreover
                    the centurions, and those with the double allowance, who had left their ranks.
                    With respect to the rest of the multitude, every tenth man was drawn by lot for
                    punishment. <pb n="152" xml:id="p.152"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In a contrary manner to this, the consul and
                    soldiers in the country of the Aequans vied with each other in courtesy and acts
                    of kindness: both Quintius was naturally milder in disposition, and the
                    ill-fated severity of his colleague caused him to indulge more in his own good
                    temper. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This, such great cordiality between
                    the general and his army, the Aequans did not venture to meet; they suffered the
                    enemy to go through their lands committing devastations in every direction. Nor
                    were depredations committed more extensively in that quarter in any preceding
                    war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Praises were also added, in which the
                    minds of soldiers find no less pleasure than in rewards. The army returned more
                    reconciled both to their general, and also on account of the general to the
                    patricians; stating that a parent was assigned to them, a master to the other
                    army by the senate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The year now passed, with
                    varied success in war, and furious dissensions at home and abroad, was rendered
                    memorable chiefly by the elections by tribes; the matter was more important from
                    the victory in the contest entered into, than from any real advantage;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for there was more of dignity abstracted
                    from the elections themselves by the exclusion of the patricians, than there was
                    influence either added to the commons or taken from the patricians. </p>
                <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A more turbulent year <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Niebuhr, ii. p. 231, thinks that it was in this year
                        the Icilian law was passed, according to which, any person interrupting the
                        proceedings of the tribunes, rendered himself liable to capital punishment.
                        — <hi rend="italics">Twiss.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> next followed, Lucius Valerius, Tiberius
                    Aemilius being consuls, both by reason of the struggles between the different
                    orders concerning the agrarian law, as well as on account of the trial of Appius
                    Claudius; for whom, as a most active <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> opposer
                    of the law, and as one who supported the cause of the possessors of the public
                    land, as if a third consul, Marcus Duilius and Caius Sicinius appointed a day of
                    trial. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Several charges were brought
                        against Appius, according to Dion. ix. 54, who also states that he did not
                        die of any disease, but that he laid violent hands on himself. — <hi
                            rend="italics">Ruperti.</hi>
                    </note> Never before was an accused person so hateful to the commons brought to
                    trial before the people; overwhelmed with <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    their resentment on his own account, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The original has <hi rend="italics">plenus suarum —irarum,</hi> —that is,
                        the anger not of Appius against the commons, but of <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> the commons against him. </note> and also on account of
                    his father. The patricians too seldom made equal exertions in behalf of any one:
                        <quote> that the champion of the senate, and <pb n="153" xml:id="p.153"/>
                        the assertor of their dignity, opposed to all the storm of the tribunes and
                        commons, was exposed to the resentment of the commons, merely for having
                        exceeded bounds in the contest. </quote> Appius Claudius himself was the
                    only one of the patricians who made light both of the tribunes and commons and
                    his own trial. Neither the threats of the commons, nor the entreaties of the
                    senate, could ever persuade him not only to change his garb, or address persons
                    as a suppliant, but not even so far as to soften or relax any thing from the
                    usual asperity of his style, when his cause was to be pleaded before the people.
                    The expression of his countenance was the same; the same stubbornness in his
                    looks, the same spirit of <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> pride in his
                    language; so that a great part of the commons felt no less awe of Appius when
                    arraigned, than they had felt of him when consul. He pleaded his cause once, and
                    with the same spirit of an accuser which he had been accustomed to adopt on all
                    occasions: and <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> he so far astounded both the
                    tribunes and the commons by his intrepidity, that, of their own accord, they
                    postponed the day of trial; then they allowed the matter to be protracted. Nor
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> was the time now very distant; before,
                    however, the appointed day came, he dies of some disease; and when the tribunes
                    of the people endeavoured to impede his funeral panegyric, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Conf. Nieb. ii. n. 754. It may be well to mention that
                        Niebuhr considered that this account regarding the death of <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> Appius was all fictitious. The Greek writers,
                        scil. Dion. ix. 54, Zonar. vii. 17, state that he laid violent hands on
                        himself. </note> the commons would not allow that the last day of so great a
                    man should be defrauded of the usual honours; and they listened to the panegyric
                    of him when dead with as patient ears, as they had listened to the charges
                    brought against him when living, and attended his funeral in vast numbers. </p>
                <milestone n="62" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year the consul Valerius, having
                    marched an army against the Aequans, when he could not entice the enemy to an
                    engagement, set about assaulting their camp. A violent storm sent down from
                    heaven with thunder and hail prevented him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Then, on a signal for a retreat being given, their surprise was excited by the
                    return of such fair weather, that they felt a scruple a second time to attack a
                    camp which was defended as it were by some divine power; all the rage of war was
                    turned on the devastation of the land. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    other consul, Aemilius, conducted the war against the Sabines. There also, <pb
                        n="154" xml:id="p.154"/> because the enemy confined themselves within their
                    walls, the lands were laid waste. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, by the
                    burning not only of the country-houses, but of the villages also, which were
                    thickly inhabited, the Sabines being aroused, after they met the depredators, on
                    retreating from an engagement left undecided, on the following day removed their
                    camp into a safer situation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This seemed a
                    sufficient reason to the consul why he should leave the enemy as conquered,
                    departing thence the war being still unfinished. </p>
                <milestone n="63" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these wars, whilst dissensions still
                    continued at home, Titus Numicius Priscus, Aulus Virginius, were elected
                    consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The commons appeared determined no
                    longer to brook a delay of the agrarian law, and extreme violence was on the eve
                    of being resorted to, when it was ascertained from the burning of the
                    country-houses and the flight of the peasants that the Volscians were at hand:
                    this circumstance checked the sedition that was now ripe and almost breaking
                    out. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls, having been instantly forced
                    to the war by the senate, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the
                        original we read <hi rend="italics">coacti extemplo ab senatu.</hi> Niebuhr
                        considers this reading to be corrupt, and <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        is satisfied that the correct reading is <hi rend="italics">coacto extemplo
                            senatu.</hi> See ii. n. 555. </note> after leading forth the youth from
                    the city, rendered the rest of the commons more quiet. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> And the enemy indeed, having done nothing else except
                    alarming the Romans by groundless fear, depart with great precipitation.
                    Numicius marched to Antium against the Volscians, Virginius against the Aequans.
                    Here a signal overthrow being well nigh received <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> from an ambuscade, the bravery of the soldiers restored (the Roman)
                    superiority, which had been endangered through the carelessness of the consul.
                    The general conducted affairs better against the Volscians. The enemy were
                    routed in the first engagement, and forced to fly into the city of Antium,
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> a very wealthy place considering those
                    times; the consul, not venturing to attack it, took from the people of Antium
                    another town, Ceno, which was by no means so wealthy. Whilst the Aequans and
                    Volscians engage the attention of the Roman armies, the Sabines advanced in
                    their devastations even to the gates of the city: then they themselves, a few
                    days after, received from the two armies heavier losses than they had
                    occasioned, the two consuls having entered their territories under exasperated
                    feelings. <pb n="155" xml:id="p.155"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="64" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the year there was some
                    peace, but, as frequently at other times, disturbed by contests between the
                    patricians and commons. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The exasperated
                    commons refused to attend the consular elections: Titus Quintius, Quintus
                    Servilius, were elected consuls by the patricians and their dependents: the
                    consuls have a year similar to the preceding, the commencement embroiled, and
                    afterwards tranquil by external war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    Sabines marching across the plains of Crustuminum with great rapidity, after
                    carrying fire and sword along the banks of the Anio, being repulsed when they
                    had come up nearly to the Colline gate and the walls, drove off however great
                    booty of men and cattle: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the consul Servilius,
                    having pursued them with a determined army, was unable to come up with the main
                    body itself on the champaign country; he carried his devastation however so
                    extensively, that he left nothing unmolested by war, and returned after
                    obtaining plunder much exceeding that carried off by the enemy. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The public interest was supported extremely well against
                    the Volscians also by the exertions as well of the general as of the soldiers.
                    First they fought a pitched battle, on equal ground, with great slaughter and
                    much bloodshed on both sides: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and the Romans,
                    because the fewness of their numbers was more likely to make the loss felt,
                    would have given way, had not the consul, by a well-timed fiction, re-animated
                    the army, crying out that the enemy were flying on the other wing; making a
                    charge, they, by supposing that they were victorious, became so. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The consul, fearing lest by pressing too far he might
                    renew the contest, gave the signal for a retreat. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A few days intervened; rest being taken on both sides as if
                    by a tacit suspension of arms; during these days a vast number of persons from
                    all the states of the Volscians and Aequans came to the camp, certain that the
                    Romans would depart during the night, if they should perceive them. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly about the third watch they come to attack
                    the camp. Quintius having allayed the confusion which the sudden panic had
                    occasioned, after ordering the soldiers to remain quiet in their tents, leads
                    out a cohort of the Hernician for an advance guard: <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> the trumpeters and horneteers he mounts on horseback, and
                    commands them to sound their trumpets before the rampart, and to keep the enemy
                    in suspense till daylight: during the rest of the night every thing was so quiet
                        <pb n="156" xml:id="p.156"/> in the camp, that the Romans had even the
                    advantage of sleep. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The sight of the armed
                    infantry, whom they both considered to be more numerous than they were, and to
                    be Romans, the bustle and neighing of the horses, which became restless, both
                    from the strange riders placed on them, and moreover from the sound of the
                    trumpets frightening them, kept the Volscians intently awaiting an attack of the
                    enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="65" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When day dawned, the Romans, invigorated and
                    refreshed with sleep, on being marched out to battle, at the first onset
                    overpowered the Volscians, wearied from standing and want of rest; though the
                    enemy rather retired than were routed, because in the rear there were hills to
                    which there was a secure retreat, the ranks behind the first line being
                    unbroken. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul, when they came to the
                    uneven ground, halts his army; the soldiers were kept back with difficulty; they
                    cried out and demanded to be allowed to pursue the enemy now discomfited. The
                    cavalry, crowding around the general, proceed more violently: they cry out that
                    they would proceed before the first line. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Whilst the consul hesitates, relying on the valour of his men, yet having little
                    confidence in the place, they all cry out that they would proceed; and execution
                    followed the shout. Fixing their spears in the ground, in order that they may be
                    lighter to ascend the steeps, they run upwards. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> The Volscians, having discharged their missile weapons at the first onset,
                    fling the stones lying at their feet on them as they advanced upwards, and
                    having thrown them into confusion by incessant blows, they drove them from the
                    higher ground: thus the left wing of the Romans was nearly overborne, had not
                    the consul dispelled their fear by exciting a sense of shame as they were just
                    retreating, chiding at the same time their temerity and their cowardice. At
                    first they stood their ground with determined firmness; then, according as their
                    strength carried them against those in possession of the ground, they venture to
                    advance themselves; and by renewing the shout they encourage the whole body to
                    move on; then again making a new effort, they force their way up and surmount
                    the disadvantage of the ground. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They were on
                    the point of gaining the summit of the eminence, when the enemy turned their
                    backs, and the pursued and pursuers with precipitate speed rushed into the camp
                    almost in a body. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In this consternation the
                    camp is taken; <pb n="157" xml:id="p.157"/> such of the Volscians as were able
                    to make their escape, take the road to Antium. The Roman army also was led to
                    Antium; after being invested for a few days it surrenders without any additional
                    force of the besiegers, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Additional force of the,</hi> &amp;c. Crevier understands
                        this to signify that the Romans did not employ a greater <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> force for besieging Antium, than they had employed the
                        preceding year, and which at that time seemed insufficient for the purpose.
                        Others understand the words to signify that they surrendered without waiting
                        for the Romans to make any additional efforts to take the town. </note> but
                    because their spirits had sunk ever since the unsuccessful battle and the loss
                    of their camp. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
