<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 1-2 - 2</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books I and II With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1919</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="book">
                <head>Book II</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THE new liberty enjoyed by the Roman people,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note>
                    their achievements in peace and war, annual magistracies, and laws superior in
                    authority to men will henceforth be my theme. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This liberty was the more grateful as the last king had been so great a tyrant.
                    For his predecessors so ruled that there is good reason to regard them all as
                    successive founders of parts, at least, of the City, which they added to serve
                    as new homes for the numbers they had themselves recruited. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This statement is too sweeping, for
                        Livy nowhere attributes any enlargement of the City to Numa. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor is there any doubt that the same Brutus
                    who earned such honour by expelling the haughty Tarquinius, would have acted in
                    an evil hour for the commonwealth had a premature eagerness for liberty led him
                    to wrest the power from any of the earlier kings. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> For what would have happened if that rabble of shepherds
                    and vagrants, having deserted their own peoples, and under the protection of
                    inviolable sanctuary having possessed themselves of liberty, or at least
                    impunity, had thrown off their fear of kings only to be stirred by the ruffling
                    storms of tribunician demagogues, breeding quarrels with the senators of a city
                    not their own, <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> before ever the pledges of wife
                    and children and love of the very place and soil (an affection of slow growth)
                    had firmly united their aspirations? The nation would have crumbled away with
                    dissension before it had matured. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But it was
                    favoured by the mild restraint of the government, which nursed it up to the
                    point <pb n="p.221"/> where its ripened powers enabled it to bear good <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note> fruit of
                    liberty. Moreover you may reckon the beginning of liberty as proceeding rather
                    from the limitation of the consuls' authority to a year than from any diminution
                    of their power compared with that which the kings had exercised. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> All the rights of the kings and all their insignia
                    were possessed by the earliest consuls; only one thing was guarded against —that
                    the terror they inspired should not be doubled by permitting both to have the
                    rods. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Brutus was the first to have them, with
                    his colleague's consent, and he proved as determined in guarding liberty as he
                    had been in asserting it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To begin with, when
                    the people were still jealous of their new freedom, he obliged them to swear an
                    oath that they would suffer no man to be king in Rome, lest they might later be
                    turned from their purpose by the entreaties or the gifts of princes. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> In the next place, that the strength of the senate
                    might receive an added augmentation from the numbers of that order, he filled up
                    the list of the Fathers, which had been abridged by the late king's butcheries,
                    drawing upon the foremost men of equestrian rank until he had brought the total
                    up to three hundred. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> From that time, it is
                    said, was handed down the custom of summoning to the senate the Fathers and the
                    Enrolled, the latter being the designation of the new senators, who were
                    appointed. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Later any senator might be
                        called <hi rend="italics">pater conscriptus,</hi> and it is possible that
                        Livy and Festus (p. 254 M) were misled in supposing that originally the <hi
                            rend="italics">patres</hi> were one class of senators and the <hi
                            rend="italics">conscripti</hi> another. See Conway's note. </note> This
                    measure was wonderfully effective in promoting harmony in the state and
                    attaching the plebs to the Fathers. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Livy appears to have assumed that the new senators were plebeians, but this
                        is almost certainly wrong. The first definite notice of a plebeian senator
                        occurs at v. xii. 11 ( <date value="-400">400 B.C.</date> ). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Matters of worship then received attention.
                    Certain public sacrifices had habitually been performed by the kings in person,
                    and that their <pb n="p.223"/> absence might nowhere be regretted, a <quote>
                        king of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            509</note> sacrifices </quote> was appointed. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This priesthood they made subordinate to the pontifex, lest
                    the office, in conjunction with the title, might somehow prove an obstacle to
                    liberty, which was at that time their chief concern. Perhaps the pains they took
                    to safeguard it, even in trivial details, may have been excessive. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> For the name of one of the consuls, though he gave no
                    other offence, was hateful to the citizens. <quote> The Tarquinii had become too
                        used to sovereignty. It had begun with Priscus; Servius Tullius had then
                        been king; but not even this interruption had caused Tarquinius Superbus to
                        forget the throne or regard it as another's; as though it had been the
                        heritage of his family, he had used crime and violence to get it back;
                        Superbus was now expelled, but the supreme power was in the hands of
                        Collatinus. The Tarquinii knew not how to live as private citizens. Their
                        name was irksome and a menace to liberty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Beginning in this way, with a cautious
                    sounding of sentiment, the talk spread through the entire nation, and the plebs
                    had become anxious and suspicious, when Brutus summoned them to an assembly.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There he first of all recited the oath
                    which the people had taken, that they would suffer no king in Rome, nor any man
                    who might be dangerous to liberty. This oath they must uphold, he said, with all
                    their might, nor make light of anything which bore upon it. He spoke with
                    reluctance, on the man's account, nor would he have broken silence unless he had
                    been forced to do so by his love of country. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman people did not believe that they had recovered absolute freedom. The
                    royal family, the royal name <pb n="p.225"/> were not only present in the state,
                    but were <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note>
                    actually in authority, an obstacle and a stumbling-block in the way of liberty.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>This fear,</quote> he cried, <quote> do you yourself remove, Lucius
                        Tarquinius, of your own free will! We are mindful —we confess it —that you
                        drove out the kings; complete the good work you have begun, and rid us of
                        the royal name. Your possessions shall not only be granted you by the
                        citizens, at my instance, but if they are in any way inadequate they shall
                        be generously increased. Depart our friend, and relieve the state of what
                        is, perhaps, an idle fear. The people are persuaded that with the family of
                        Tarquinius the kingship will vanish from amongst us. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consul was at first prevented from
                    uttering a word by his astonishment at this strange and unexpected turn; then,
                    when he tried to speak, the chief men of the state surrounded him, and with many
                    entreaties made the same request. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The others
                    had little influence over him, but when Spurius Lucretius, his superior in years
                    and dignity, and his father-in-law besides, began to urge him, with mingled
                    entreaty and advice, to permit himself to yield to the unanimous wish of his
                    fellow-citizens, Collatinus became <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> alarmed
                    lest when his year of office should have ended, his misfortunes might be
                    increased by the confiscation of his property and the addition of yet other
                    ignominies. He therefore resigned the consulship, and transferring all his
                    possessions to Lavinium, withdrew from the Roman state. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> In pursuance of a resolution of the senate, Brutus proposed
                    to the people a measure which decreed the exile of all the Tarquinian race. To
                    be his colleague the centuriate comitia, under his presidency, elected Publius
                    Valerius, who had helped him to expel the kings. </p>
                <pb n="p.227"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although no one doubted that the Tarquinii
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note>
                    would presently go to war, their attack was delayed beyond all expectation;
                    while a thing men did not fear at all, to wit a treasonable plot, almost cost
                    Rome her liberty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There were among the young
                    men a number of youths, the sons of families not unimportant, whose pleasures
                    had been less confined under the monarchy, who, being of the same age as the
                    young Tarquinii, and their cronies, had grown used to the untrammelled life of
                    princes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This licence they missed, now that
                    all enjoyed equal rights, and they had got into the way of complaining to each
                    other that the liberty of the rest had resulted in their own enslavement. A king
                    was a man, from whom one could obtain a boon, whether it were just or unjust;
                    there was room for countenance and favour; a king could be angry, could forgive,
                    could distinguish between friend and enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The law was a thing without ears, inexorable, more salutary and serviceable to
                    the pauper than to the great man; it knew no relaxation or indulgence, if one
                    exceeded bounds; and, inasmuch as man is so prone to blunder, it was dangerous
                    to rely on innocence alone. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thanks to such
                    reflections, they were already infected with disloyalty when envoys from the
                    royal family appeared, who without saying anything about the return of the
                    Tarquinii, sought merely to recover their property. The senate, having given
                    them a hearing, debated the question for several days; for they feared that if
                    they refused to make restitution it would be a pretext for war, if they
                    consented it would be to furnish means and assistance for its prosecution.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Meantime the envoys were <pb n="p.229"/>
                    exerting themselves to a different purpose. Ostensibly <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note> seeking to recover the
                    property, they secretly laid their plans for winning back the kingdom; and, as
                    if in furtherance of their apparent object, they went about sounding the
                    disposition of the youthful nobles. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To those
                    who gave them a friendly hearing they delivered letters from the Tarquinii, and
                    plotted with them to admit the royal family secretly by night into the City.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The brothers Vitellii and Aquilii were the
                    first to be entrusted with the project. A sister of the Vitellii had married the
                    consul Brutus, and there were sons of this marriage who were now young men,
                    Titus and Tiberius; these were also admitted by their uncles to a share in the
                    design. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There were besides several other young
                    nobles taken into the secret, but their names are lost in antiquity. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The senate meantime had acquiesced in the opinion of
                    those who were in favour of giving back the property. This very fact gave the
                    agents of the exiles an excuse for lingering in the City, for the consuls had
                    granted them time for obtaining vehicles with which to carry away the belongings
                    of the royal family. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All this time they spent
                    in consultation with the conspirators, whom they urged and at length persuaded
                    to give them letters for the Tarquinii: for otherwise how could the princes be
                    convinced that the statements of their agents regarding matters of such
                    importance were to be relied on? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These
                    letters, being given as a pledge of sincerity, furnished clear proof of the
                    crime, For on the eve of the envoys' setting out to rejoin their masters it
                    happened that they were dining at the house of the Vitellii, where the
                    conspirators, having dismissed all witnesses, had much talk together, naturally
                    enough, about their <pb n="p.231"/> new design. This conversation one of the
                    slaves <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note>
                    overheard. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He had for some time perceived what
                    was in the wind, but was waiting for the opportunity which the delivery of the
                    letters to the envoys would provide, that their seizure might make good his
                    accusation. When he saw that the letters had been given, he laid the matter
                    before the consuls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls left their
                    houses, arrested the agents and the conspirators, and, without making any
                    disturbance, completely crushed the plot, being especially careful not to lose
                    the letters. The traitors were thrown into prison forthwith. As for the envoys,
                    it was uncertain for a little while what would be done with them, but,
                    notwithstanding they appeared to have deserved no less than to be treated as
                    enemies, the law of nations nevertheless prevailed. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The question of the royal property, which they
                    had before voted to return, was laid before the Fathers for fresh consideration.
                    This time anger won the day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They refused to
                    return it, and refused to confiscate it to the state, but gave it up to the
                    plebeians to plunder, that having had their fingers in the spoils of the princes
                    they might for ever relinquish hope of making their peace with them. The land of
                    the Tarquinii, lying between the City and the Tiber, was consecrated to Mars and
                    became the Campus Martius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It happened, they
                    say, that there was then standing upon it a crop of spelt, ripe for the harvest.
                    Since this produce of the land might not, for religious reasons, be consumed,
                    the grain was cut, straw and all, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ordinarily the Roman farmer cut the stalk close to the ear, but this time it
                        was cut near the ground, that the crop might be completely destroyed.
                    </note> by a large body of men, who were set to work upon it simultaneously, and
                    was carried in baskets and thrown into the Tiber, then flowing with a feeble
                    current, as is usually the case in midsummer. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    So the heaps <pb n="p.233"/> of grain, caught in the shallow water, settled down
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note> in
                    the mud, and out of these and the accumulation of other chance materials such as
                    a river brings down, there was gradually formed an island. Later, I suppose,
                    embankments were added, and work was done, to raise the surface so high above
                    the water and make it strong enough to sustain even temples and porticoes.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the chattels of the princes had been
                    pillaged, sentence was pronounced and punishment inflicted upon the traitors —a
                    punishment the more conspicuous because the office of consul imposed upon a
                    father the duty of exacting the penalty from his sons, and he who ought to have
                    been spared even the sight of their suffering was the very man whom Fortune
                    appointed to enforce it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Bound to the stake
                    stood youths of the highest birth. But the rest were ignored as if they had been
                    of the rabble: the consul's sons drew all eyes upon themselves. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Men pitied them for their punishment not more than for the
                    crime by which they had deserved that punishment. To think that those young men,
                    in that year of all others, when their country was liberated and her liberator
                    their own father, and when the consulship had begun with the Junian family,
                    could have brought themselves to betray all —the senate, the plebs, and all the
                    gods and men of Rome —to one who had formerly been a tyrannical king and was
                    then an enemy exile! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls advanced to
                    their tribunal and dispatched the lictors to execute the sentence. The culprits
                    were stripped, scourged with rods, and beheaded, while through it all men gazed
                    at the expression on the father's face, where they might clearly read a father's
                    anguish, as he administered the nation's retribution. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When the <pb n="p.235"/> guilty had suffered, that the
                    example might be in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        509</note> both respects a notable deterrent from crime, the informer was
                    rewarded with money from the treasury, emancipation, and citizenship. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> He is said to have been the first to be freed by the
                        <hi rend="italics">vindicta.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A staff with which the slave was
                        touched in the ceremony of manumission. The etymology suggested in the next
                        sentence is wrong; <hi rend="italics">Vindicius,</hi> like <hi
                            rend="italics">vindicta,</hi> is derived from <hi rend="italics"
                            >vindex.</hi>
                    </note> Some think that even the word <hi rend="italics">vindicta</hi> was
                    derived from his name, which they suppose to have been Vindicius. From his time
                    onwards it was customary to regard those who had been freed by this form as
                    admitted to citizenship. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When these occurrences had been faithfully
                    reported to Tarquinius, he was stirred not only by disappointment at the
                    collapse of so great hopes, but also by hatred and anger. He saw that the way
                    was now closed against trickery, and believed it was time to contrive an open
                    war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He therefore went about as a suppliant
                    amongst the cities of Etruria, directing his prayers chiefly to the Veientes and
                    the Tarquinienses. Reminding them that he had come from them and was of the same
                    blood as themselves, and that exile and poverty had followed hard upon his loss
                    of what had been but now great power, he besought them not to let him perish,
                    with his youthful sons, before their very eyes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Others had been called in from abroad to be kings in Rome: he himself, while
                    actually king, and enlarging Rome's sway by war, had been driven out by his
                    next-of-kin in a wicked conspiracy. His enemies, perceiving that no single
                    claimant was fit to be king, had seized and usurped the power amongst
                    themselves, and had given up his goods to be plundered by the people, that none
                    might be without a share in the guilt. He wished to regain his country and his
                    sovereignty, and to punish the ungrateful Romans. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Let them <pb n="p.237"/> succour and support him, and
                    avenge, as well, their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 509</note> own long-standing grievances, the oft-repeated destruction
                    of their armies, and seizure of their lands. This last plea moved the men of
                    Veii, and they cried out with threatenings that they ought, at all events with a
                    Roman for their commander, to wipe out their disgraces and recover what they had
                    lost in war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Tarquinienses were influenced
                    by his name and kinship: it seemed a fine thing to them that one of their blood
                    should be king in Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So it came about that
                    two armies, representing two nations, followed Tarquinius, to regain his kingdom
                    for him and to chastise the Romans. When they had come into Roman territory the
                    consuls went out to meet the enemy: Valerius led the foot in defensive
                    formation; Brutus, with the cavalry, went ahead to scout. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> In the same fashion the enemy's horse headed their march,
                    commanded by Arruns Tarquinius, the king's son, while the king himself followed
                    with the legions. Arruns, perceiving a long way off by the consul's lictors that
                    it was he, and then, as they drew nearer together, recognizing Brutus more
                    unmistakably by his countenance, blazed with resentment. <quote>Yonder,</quote>
                    he cried, <quote> is the man who drove us into exile from our native land. Look!
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He is himself decked out with our
                        trappings, as he comes proudly on! O gods, avengers of kings, be with us!
                    </quote> Spurring his horse, he charged straight at the consul. Brutus saw that
                    he was the object of the man's attack. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In
                    those days it was to a general's credit to take part in the actual fighting, so
                    he eagerly accepted the challenge, and they rushed at one another with such
                    desperation, neither of them taking thought for his own defence if only he might
                    wound his adversary, that <pb n="p.239"/> each was pierced right through his
                    shield by the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        509</note> other's thrust, and, impaled upon the two spears, they fell dying
                    from their horses. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the same time the rest
                    of the cavalry as well began to fight, and not long after the infantry also
                    appeared. In this battle the advantage was divided, and the fortune of war
                    seemed equally balanced: the right wing on each side was victorious, while the
                    left was defeated. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Veientes, used to
                    being beaten by the Roman troops, were routed and dispersed; the men of
                    Tarquinii, a new enemy, not only stood their ground, but drove back the Roman
                    forces which opposed them. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Yet despite the indecisive character of the
                    battle, so great a panic came over Tarquinius and the Etruscans that they gave
                    up the enterprise for lost, and that same night both armies, the Veientine and
                    the Tarquiniensian, marched off every man to his own home. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> To the story of this fight common report adds a prodigy:
                    that in the silence of the following night a loud voice was heard coming out of
                    the Arsian forest, which was believed to be the voice of Silvanus, and that this
                    was what he said: <quote> The Tuscans have lost one more man in the battle-line;
                        the Romans are conquerors in the war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At all events the Romans left the field like
                    victors, and the Etruscans like an army that has been defeated. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> For when it grew light and not a single enemy was to be
                    seen, Publius Valerius the consul gathered up the spoils and returned in triumph
                    to Rome. His colleague's funeral he celebrated with all the pomp then possible;
                    but a far greater honour to the dead man was the general grief, which was
                    particularly conspicuous inasmuch as the matrons mourned a year for him, as for
                    a father, because <pb n="p.241"/> he had been so spirited an avenger of outraged
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note>
                    modesty. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Soon after this the surviving consul, so
                    fickle are the affections of the mob, became unpopular; not only did the people
                    dislike him, but they actually suspected him and made cruel charges against him.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was noised about that he was aspiring
                    to the power of a king, since he had not caused a colleague to be elected in the
                    place of Brutus, and was building a house on the highest part of the Velia, an
                    elevated position of natural strength, men said, which he was converting into an
                    impregnable citadel. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The frequency of these
                    remarks and the general acceptance they met with, shamefully unjust as they
                    were, distressed the consul. He summoned the people to a council, and with
                    lowered fasces <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Bundles of rods which
                        symbolized the magistrate's authority to scourge, as the axes ( <hi
                            rend="italics">secures</hi> ) did his right to put to death. </note>
                    mounted the speaker's platform. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was a
                    welcome spectacle to the multitude when they beheld the emblems of authority
                    there abased before them, in acknowledgment that the people's majesty and power
                    were superior to the consul's. Then, bidding them attend, the consul extolled
                    the good fortune of his colleague, who, after his country had thrown off the
                    yoke, had held the highest office in her gift, and, fighting for the state, at
                    the height of a reputation as yet untarnished by envy, had met his death. He had
                    himself outlived his glory, and survived to face accusations and ill-will.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From being the saviour of his country he
                    had sunk to the level of the Aquilii and Vitellii. <quote>Will there never be
                        worth and merit, then,</quote> he exclaimed, <quote> so established in your
                        minds that suspicion cannot wrong it? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Could I possibly have feared that I, well known as the bitterest enemy of
                        kings, should myself incur the charge of <pb n="p.243"/> seeking kingly
                        power? Could I have believed that, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                            type="margin">B.C. 509</note> though I dwelt in the very Citadel and on
                        the Capitol itself, I could be feared by my fellow-citizens? Can so trivial
                        a cause ruin my reputation with you? Does your confidence rest on so slight
                        a foundation that it makes more difference where I am than who I am?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There shall be no menace in the house
                        of Publius Valerius to your liberties, Quirites; your Velia shall be safe. I
                        will not only bring my house down on to level ground, but will even place it
                        under a hill, that you may live above me, the citizen whom you suspect. Let
                        those build on the Velia who can better be trusted with men's liberty than
                        can Publius Valerius! </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Immediately the materials were all brought
                    down below the Velia, and the house was erected where the temple of Vica Pota is
                    now, at the bottom of the slope. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laws were then proposed which not only cleared
                    the consul from the suspicion of seeking kingly power, but took such an opposite
                    turn that they even made him popular and caused him to be styled Publicola, the
                    People's Friend. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Above all, the law about
                    appealing from the magistrates to the people, and the one that pronounced a
                    curse on the life and property of a man who should plot to make himself king,
                    were welcome to the commons. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he had
                    carried through these measures alone, that he might enjoy without a rival all
                    the favour arising out of them, he finally held an election to choose a
                    colleague for the unexpired term. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The choice
                    fell upon Spurius Lucretius, who by reason of his great age was no longer strong
                    enough for the duties of the consulship, and died within a few days. They
                    elected in Lucretius's place Marcus Horatius <pb n="p.245"/> Pulvillus.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In some ancient authorities I do not find
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 509</note>
                    Lucretius given as consul, but Brutus is followed immediately by Horatius; I
                    suppose that because no exploit lent distinction to Lucretius's consulship men
                    forgot it. </p>
                <p> The temple of Jupiter on the Capitol had not yet been dedicated. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Valerius and Horatius the consuls drew lots to
                    determine which should do it. Horatius received the lot, and Publicola set out
                    to conduct the war against the Veientes. With more bitterness than was
                    reasonable, the friends of Valerius resented that the dedication of so famous a
                    temple should be given to Horatius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They tried
                    in all sorts of ways to hinder it, but their schemes all came to naught.
                    Finally, when the consul's hand was on the door-post and he was in the midst of
                    his prayers to the gods, they broke in upon the ceremony with the evil tidings
                    that his son was dead, averring that whilst the shadow of death was over his
                    house he could not dedicate a temple. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Whether
                    he did not believe the news to be true, or possessed great fortitude, we are not
                    informed with certainty, nor is it easy to decide. Without permitting himself to
                    be diverted from his purpose by the message, further than to order that the body
                    should be buried, he kept his hand upon the doorpost, finished his prayer, and
                    dedicated the temple. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such were the achievements, at home and in the
                    field, of the first year after the expulsion of the kings. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next Publius Valerius (for the second time)
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 508</note> and
                    Titus Lucretius were made consuls. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Dion. Hal. (v. 21) says that Valerius was consul for the <hi rend="italics"
                            >third</hi> time, and Horatius for the second time, when the war with
                        Porsinna came. Mommsen thought the MSS. had lost these names, and proposed
                        to insert them directly after those in the text. But in chap. xi. 8, T.
                        Lucretius is still the colleague of Valerius. </note> By this time the
                    Tarquinii had sought refuge with Lars <pb n="p.247"/> Porsinna, king of Clusium.
                    There they mingled advice <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 508</note> and entreaty, now imploring him not to permit
                    them, Etruscans by birth and of the same blood and the same name as himself, to
                    suffer the <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> privations of exile, and again even
                    warning him not to allow the growing custom of expelling kings to go unpunished.
                    Liberty was sweet enough in itself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Unless the
                    energy with which nations sought to obtain it were matched by the efforts which
                    kings put forth to defend their power, the highest would be reduced to the level
                    of the lowest; there would be nothing lofty, nothing that stood out above the
                    rest of the state; there was the end of monarchy, the noblest institution known
                    to gods or men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Porsinna, believing that it
                    was not only a safe thing for the Etruscans that there should be a king at Rome,
                    but an honour to have that king of Etruscan stock, invaded Roman territory with
                    a hostile army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Never before had such fear
                    seized the senate, so powerful was Clusium in those days, and so great
                    Porsinna's fame. And they feared not only the enemy but their own citizens, lest
                    the plebs should be terror-stricken and, admitting the princes into the City,
                    should even submit to enslavement, for the sake of peace. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Hence the senate at this time granted many favours to the
                    plebs. The question of subsistence received special attention, and some were
                    sent to the Volsci and others to Cumae to buy up corn. Again, the monopoly of
                    salt, the price of which was very high, was taken out of the hands of
                    individuals and wholly assumed by the government. Imposts and taxes were removed
                    from the plebs that they might be borne by the well-to-do, who were equal to the
                    burden: the poor paid dues enough if they reared children. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Thanks to this <pb n="p.249"/> liberality on the part of
                    the Fathers, the distress <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 508</note> which attended the subsequent blockade and
                    famine was powerless to destroy the harmony of the state, which was such that
                    the name of king was not more abhorrent to the highest than to the lowest;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> nor was there ever a man in after years
                    whose demagogic arts made him so popular as its wise governing at that time made
                    the whole senate. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the enemy appeared, the Romans all, with
                    one accord, withdrew from their fields into the City, which they surrounded with
                    guards. Some parts appeared to be rendered safe by their walls, others by the
                    barrier formed by the river Tiber. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The bridge
                    of piles almost afforded an entrance to the enemy, had it not been for one man,
                    Horatius Cocles; he was the bulwark of defence on which that day depended the
                    fortune of the City of Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He chanced to be
                    on guard at the bridge when Janiculum was captured by a sudden attack of the
                    enemy. He saw them as they charged down on the run from Janiculum, while his own
                    people behaved like a frightened mob, throwing away their arms and quitting
                    their ranks. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Catching hold first of one and
                    then of another, blocking their way and conjuring them to listen, he called on
                    gods and men to witness that if they forsook their post it was vain to flee;
                    once they had left a passage in their rear by the bridge, there would soon be
                    more of the enemy on the Palatine and the Capitol than on Janiculum. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> He therefore warned and commanded them to break down
                    the bridge with steel, with fire, with any instrument at their disposal; and
                    promised that he would himself receive the onset of the enemy, so far as it
                    could be withstood by a single body. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then,
                    striding to the <pb n="p.251"/> head of the bridge, conspicuous amongst the
                    fugitives <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        508</note> who were clearly seen to be shirking the fight, he covered
                    himself with his sword and buckler and made ready to do battle at close
                    quarters, confounding the Etruscans with amazement at his audacity. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Yet were there two who were prevented by shame from
                    leaving him. These were Spurius Larcius and Titus Herminius, both famous for
                    their birth and their deeds. With these he endured the peril of the first rush
                    and the stormiest moment of the battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                    after a while he forced even these two to leave him and save themselves, for
                    there was scarcely anything left of the bridge, and those who were cutting it
                    down called to them to come back. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then,
                    darting glances of defiance around at the Etruscan nobles, he now challenged
                    them in turn to fight, now railed at them collectively as slaves of haughty
                    kings, who, heedless of their own liberty, were come to overthrow the liberty of
                    others. They hesitated for a moment, each looking to his neighbour to begin the
                    fight. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then shame made them attack, and with
                    a shout they cast their javelins from every side against their solitary foe. But
                    he caught them all upon his shield, and, resolute as ever, bestrode the bridge
                    and held his ground; and now they were trying to dislodge him by a charge, when
                    the crash of the falling bridge and the cheer which burst from the throats of
                    the Romans, exulting in the completion of their task, checked them in mid-career
                    with a sudden dismay. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then Cocles cried,
                        <quote> O Father Tiberinus, I solemnly invoke thee; receive these arms and
                        this soldier with propitious stream! </quote> So praying, all armed as he
                    was, he leaped down into the river, and under a shower of missiles swam across
                    unhurt <pb n="p.253"/> to his fellows, having given a proof of valour which
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 508</note> was
                    destined to obtain more fame than credence with posterity. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The state was grateful for so brave a deed: a statue of
                    Cocles was set up in the comitium, and he was given as much land as he could
                    plough around in one day. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Private citizens
                    showed their gratitude in a striking fashion, in the midst of his official
                    honours, for notwithstanding their great distress everybody made him some gift
                    proportionate to his means, though he robbed himself of his own ration. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Porsinna, repulsed in his first attempt, gave
                    up the plan of storming the City, and determined to lay siege to it. Placing a
                    garrison on Janiculum, he pitched his camp in the plain by the banks of the
                    Tiber. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He collected ships from every quarter,
                    both for guarding the river, to prevent any corn from being brought into the
                    City, and also to send his troops across for plundering, as the opportunity
                    might present itself at one point or another; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    and in a short time he made all the territory of the Romans so unsafe that not
                    only were they forced to bring all their other property inside the walls, but
                    even their flocks too, nor did anybody dare to drive them outside the gates.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This great degree of licence was permitted
                    to the Etruscans not so much from timidity as design. For Valerius the consul,
                    who was eager for an opportunity of assailing a large number at once, when they
                    should be scattered about and not expecting an attack, cared little to avenge
                    small aggressions, and reserved his punishment for a heavier blow. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly, to lure forth plunderers, he issued
                    orders to his people that on the following day a large number of them should
                    drive out their flocks by the <pb n="p.255"/> Esquiline Gate, which was the most
                    remote from the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        508</note> enemy, believing that they would hear of it, since the blockade
                    and famine were causing desertions on the part of faithless slaves. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> And in fact the enemy did hear of it from a
                    deserter's report, and crossed the river in much greater force than usual, in
                    the hope of making a clean sweep of the booty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently Publius Valerius directed Titus Herminius to lie in ambush with a
                    small force two miles out on the Gabinian Way, and Spurius Larcius with a body
                    of light-armed youths to take post at the Colline Gate, until the enemy should
                    pass, and then to throw themselves between him and the river, cutting off his
                    retreat. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the two consuls, Titus Lucretius
                    went out by the Naevian Gate with several maniples of soldiers, Valerius himself
                    led out some picked cohorts by way of the Caelian Mount. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Where there was a gate called <hi rend="italics">Porta
                            Caelimontana,</hi> south of the <hi rend="italics">Porta Esquilina.</hi>
                        v </note> These last were the first to be seen by the enemy. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Herminius had no sooner perceived that the skirmish
                    was begun than he rushed in from his ambush and fell upon the rear of the
                    Etruscans, who had turned to meet Valerius. On the right hand and on the left,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> From the standpoint of the
                        inhabitants of the city, looking eastward from the walls. </note> from the
                    Naevian Gate and from the Colline, an answering shout was returned. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Thus the raiders were hemmed in and cut to pieces,
                    for they were no match for the Romans in fighting strength, and were shut off
                    from every line of retreat. This was the last time the Etruscans roamed so far
                    afield. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The blockade went on notwithstanding. The corn
                    was giving out, and what there was cost a very high price, and Porsinna was
                    beginning <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> to have hopes that he would take the
                    City by sitting still, when Gaius Mucius, a young Roman noble, thinking it a
                    shame that although the Roman People had not, in <pb n="p.257"/> the days of
                    their servitude when they lived under <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 508</note> kings, been blockaded in a war by any enemies,
                    they should now, <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> when free, be besieged by
                    those same Etruscans whose armies they had so often routed, made up his mind
                    that this indignity must be avenged by some great and daring deed. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> At first he intended to make his way to the enemy's
                    camp on his own account. Afterwards, fearing that if he should go unbidden by
                    the consuls and without anyone's knowing it, he might chance to be arrested by
                    the Roman sentries and brought back as a deserter —a charge which the state of
                    the City would confirm —he went before the senate. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>I wish,</quote> said he, <quote> to cross the river, senators, and enter,
                        if I can, the enemy's camp —not to plunder or exact reprisals for their
                        devastations: I have in mind to do a greater deed, if the gods grant me
                        their help. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Fathers approved. Hiding a sword under his
                    dress, he set out. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Arrived at the camp, he
                    took up his stand in the thick of the crowd near the royal tribunal. It happened
                    that at that moment the soldiers were being paid; a secretary who sat beside the
                    king, and wore nearly the same costume, was very busy, and to him the soldiers
                    for the most part addressed themselves. Mucius was afraid to ask which was
                    Porsinna, lest his ignorance of the king's identity should betray his own, and
                    following the blind guidance of Fortune, slew the secretary instead of the king.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As he strode off through the frightened
                    crowd, making a way for himself with his bloody blade, there was an outcry, and
                    thereat the royal guards came running in from every side, seized him and dragged
                    him back before the tribunal of the king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But
                    friendless as he was, even then, when <pb n="p.259"/> Fortune wore so menacing
                    an aspect, yet as one <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 508</note> more to be feared than fearing, <quote>I am a Roman
                        citizen,</quote> he cried; <quote> men call me Gaius Mucius. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> I am your enemy, and as an enemy I would have
                        slain you; I can die as resolutely as I could kill: both to do and to endure
                        valiantly is the Roman way. Nor am I the only one to carry this resolution
                        against you: behind me is a long line of men who are seeking the same
                        honour. Gird yourself therefore, if you think it worth your while, for a
                        struggle in which you must fight for your life from hour to hour with an
                        armed foe always at your door. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Such is
                        the war we, the Roman youths, declare on you. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Fear no serried ranks, no battle; it will be between
                        yourself alone and a single enemy at a time. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The king, at once hot with resentment and
                    aghast at his danger, angrily ordered the prisoner to be flung into the flames
                    unless he should at once divulge the plot with which he so obscurely threatened
                    him. Whereupon Mucius, exclaiming, <quote> Look, that you may see how cheap they
                        hold their bodies whose eyes are fixed upon renown! </quote> thrust his hand
                    into the fire that was kindled for the sacrifice. When he allowed his hand to
                    burn as if his spirit were unconscious of sensation, the king was almost beside
                    himself with wonder. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He bounded from his seat
                    and bade them remove the young man from the altar. <quote>Do you go
                        free,</quote> he said, <quote> who have dared to harm yourself more than me.
                        I would invoke success upon your valour, were that valour exerted for my
                        country; since that may not be, I release you from the penalties of war and
                        dismiss you scathless and uninjured. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then Mucius, as if to requite his generosity,
                    answered, <quote> Since you hold bravery <pb n="p.261"/> in honour, my gratitude
                        shall afford you the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                            >B.C. 508</note> information your threats could not extort: we are three
                        hundred, the foremost youths of Rome, who have conspired to assail you in
                        this fashion. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I drew the first lot; the
                        others, in whatever order it falls to them, will attack you, each at his own
                        time, until Fortune shall have delivered you into our hands. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The release of Mucius, who was afterwards
                    known as Scaevola, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        <quote>Left-handed.</quote>
                    </note> from the loss of his right hand, was followed by the arrival in Rome of
                    envoys from Porsinna. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king had been so
                    disturbed, what with the hazard of the first attack upon his life, from which
                    nothing but the blunder of his assailant had preserved him, and what with the
                    anticipation of having to undergo the danger as many times more as there were
                    conspirators remaining, that he voluntarily proposed terms of peace to the
                    Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In these terms Porsinna suggested, but
                    without effect, that the Tarquinii should be restored to power, more because he
                    had been unable to refuse the princes this demand upon their behalf than that he
                    was ignorant that the Romans would refuse it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    In obtaining the return of their lands to the Veientes he was successful; and
                    the Romans were compelled to give hostages if they wished the garrison to be
                    withdrawn from Janiculum. On these terms peace was made, and Porsinna led his
                    army down from Janiculum and evacuated the Roman territory. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Fathers bestowed on Gaius Mucius, for his bravery, a
                    field across the Tiber, which was later known as the Mucian Meadows. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now when courage had been thus distinguished,
                    even the women were inspired to deeds of patriotism. Thus the maiden Cloelia,
                    one of the hostages, eluded <pb n="p.263"/> the sentinels, when it chanced that
                    the Etruscans had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        508</note> encamped not far from the bank of the Tiber, and heading a band
                    of girls swam the river and, under a rain of hostile darts, brought them all
                    back in safety to their kinsmen in Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When
                    this had been reported to the king, he was at first enraged and sent emissaries
                    to Rome to demand that the hostage Cloelia be given up, for he made no great
                    account of the others. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then, admiration
                    getting the better of anger, he asserted that her feat was a greater one than
                    those of Cocles and Mucius, and declared that although in case the hostage was
                    not returned he should regard the treaty as broken, yet if she were restored to
                    him he would send her back safe and inviolate to her friends. Both parties kept
                    their word. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Romans returned the pledge of
                    peace, as the treaty required; and the Etruscan king not only protected the
                    brave girl but even honoured her, for after praising her heroism he said that he
                    would present her with half the hostages, and that she herself should choose the
                    ones she wished. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When they had all been
                    brought out it is said that she selected the young boys, because it was not only
                    more seemly in a maiden, but was unanimously approved by the hostages
                    themselves, that in delivering them from the enemy she should give the
                    preference to those who were of an age which particularly exposed them to
                    injury. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When peace had been established the
                    Romans rewarded this new valour in a woman with a new kind of honour, an
                    equestrian statue, which was set up on the summit of the Sacred Way, and
                    represented the maiden seated on a horse. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This peaceful departure of the Etruscan king
                    from Rome is inconsistent with the custom handed down from antiquity even to our
                    own age, <pb n="p.265"/> among other formalities observed at sales of booty,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 508</note> of
                    proclaiming <quote>the goods of King Porsinna.</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Such a practice must either have arisen during
                    the war and have been retained when peace was made, or else have had its origin
                    in some kindlier circumstance than would be suggested by the notice that an
                    enemy's goods were to be sold. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The most
                    credible of the traditional explanations is that when Porsinna retired from
                    Janiculum he handed over his camp, well stocked with provisions brought in from
                    the neighbouring fertile fields of Etruria, as a gift to the Romans, who were
                    then in a destitute condition after the long siege. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> These supplies were then sold, lest, if people were given a
                    free hand, they might plunder the camp like an enemy; and they were called the
                    goods of Porsinna rather by way of implying thankfulness for the gift than an
                    auction of the king's property, which was not even in the possession of the
                    Roman People. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On relinquishing his campaign against the
                    Romans, Porsinna was unwilling that he should appear to have led his army into
                    that region to no purpose, and accordingly sent a part of his forces, under his
                    son Arruns, to besiege Aricia. At first the Aricini were paralysed with
                    surprise. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Afterwards the auxiliaries whom they
                    called in from the Latin peoples, and also from Cumae, so encouraged them that
                    they ventured to measure their strength with the enemy in the open field. When
                    the battle began, the attack of the Etruscans was so impetuous that they routed
                    the Aricini at the first charge. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Cumaean
                    levies, employing skill to meet force, swerved a little to one side, and when
                    the enemy had swept by them, faced about and attacked them in the rear, with the
                        <pb n="p.267"/> result that the Etruscans, caught between two lines, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 508</note> almost in
                    the moment of victory, were cut to pieces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A
                    very small number of them, having lost their leader and finding no nearer
                    refuge, drifted to Rome, unarmed and with all the helplessness and the dejected
                    aspect of suppliants. There they were kindly received and were quartered about
                    among the citizens. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When their wounds had
                    healed, some departed for their homes to report the hospitality and kindness
                    they had met with, but many were persuaded to remain in Rome by the affection
                    they felt for their hosts and for the City. To these a place of residence was
                    allotted which was afterwards called the Vicus Tuscus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Spurius Larcius and Titus Herminius were the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 507-506</note>
                    next consuls, and after them came Publius Lucretius and Publius Valerius
                    Publicola. In the latter year an embassy was sent to Rome for the last time by
                    Porsinna to negotiate for the restoration of Tarquinius to power. To these
                    envoys the senate replied that they would send representatives to the king, and
                    they forthwith dispatched those of the Fathers who were held in the highest
                    esteem. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It would not have been impossible,
                    they said, to reply shortly that the royal family would not be received. It was
                    not for that reason that they had preferred to send chosen members of the senate
                    to him rather than to give their answer to his ambassadors in Rome. But they had
                    desired that for all time discussion of that question might be ended, and that
                    where there were so great obligations on both sides there might not be mutual
                    irritation, from the king's seeking that which was incompatible with the liberty
                    of the Roman people, while the Romans, unless they were willing <pb n="p.269"/>
                    to sacrifice their existence to their good nature, denied <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 507-506</note> the request of a man
                    whom they would not willingly have denied anything. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman people were not living under a monarchy, but were
                    free. They had resolved to throw open their gates to enemies sooner than to
                    kings; in this prayer they were all united, that the day which saw the end of
                    liberty in their City might also see the City's end. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They therefore entreated him, if he desired the welfare of
                    Rome, to permit her to be free. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The king,
                    yielding to his better feelings, made answer: <quote> Since this is your fixed
                        resolve, I will neither importune you with repeated insistence upon a
                        hopeless plea, nor will I deceive the Tarquinii with the hope of aid which
                        it is not in my power to grant. Let them seek elsewhere, whether war or
                        peace be their object, for a place of exile, that nothing may hinder my
                        being at peace with you. </quote> His words were followed by yet more
                    friendly deeds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The hostages remaining in his
                    hands he returned, and he gave back the Veientine land which he had taken from
                    the Romans by the treaty made on Janiculum. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Tarquinius, cut off from all hope of returning, departed for Tusculum, to spend
                    his exile in the home of his son-in-law, Mamilius Octavius. The Romans enjoyed
                    an unbroken peace with Porsinna. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consulship of Marcus Valerius and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 505-503</note>
                    Publius Postumius. This year a successful war was waged against the Sabines, and
                    the consuls triumphed. More elaborate preparations for war were then made by the
                    Sabines. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To confront them, and to prevent any
                    sudden peril arising from Tusculum, in which quarter hostility, though not
                    openly avowed, was none the <pb n="p.271"/> less suspected, Publius Valerius was
                    made consul for <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        505-503</note> the fourth time and Titus Lucretius for the second.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A schism which occurred between the
                    advocates of war and those of peace amongst the Sabines resulted in the transfer
                    of some part of their strength to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For Attius Clausus, afterwards known at Rome as Appius Claudius, himself a
                    champion of peace, was hard bested by the turbulent war-party, and finding
                    himself no match for them, left Inregillus, with a large band of clients, and
                    fled to Rome. These people were made citizens and given land across the Anio.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The <quote>Old Claudian Tribe</quote> was
                    the name used later, when new tribesmen had been added, to designate those who
                    came from this territory. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> By <date
                            value="-241">241 B.C.</date> the number of tribes had grown to
                        thirty-five. After this date no new tribes were added, but newly
                        incorporated districts were assigned to one or another of the already
                        existing tribes. Thus certain members of the Claudian Tribe lived elsewhere
                        than in the district <quote>across the Anio,</quote> and those who came to
                        Rome for elections from the original seat of the tribe were called the
                            <quote>Old Claudian Tribe.</quote> See note in Conway's edition of this
                        Book. </note> Appius, having been enrolled in the senate, came in a short
                    time to be regarded as one of its leading members. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls led an army into the country of the Sabines,
                    and by wasting their fields, and afterwards by a battle, so crushed the enemy's
                    strength that there could be no fear for a long time of any outbreak of
                    hostilities in that region. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They then returned
                    to Rome and triumphed. Publius Valerius, universally regarded as the foremost
                    citizen, both in military and in civil qualities, died in the following year,
                    when Agrippa Menenius and Publius Postumius were consuls. He was a man of
                    extraordinary reputation, but so poor that money was wanting for his burial, and
                    it was furnished from the treasury of the state. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> He was mourned by the matrons as Brutus had been. In the same year two Latin
                    colonies, Pometia and Cora, revolted to the Aurunci. The <pb n="p.273"/> Aurunci
                    were the first to be attacked. Upon the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 505-503</note> defeat of the great
                    army which had boldly issued forth to meet the invasion of their territory by
                    the consuls, the whole weight of the Auruncan war fell upon Pometia. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> After the battle, as well as during its progress, no
                    quarter was given. The slain had somewhat outnumbered the prisoners, and the
                    prisoners were indiscriminately slaughtered. Even the hostages, of whom three
                    hundred had been received, were not spared in the rage of war. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy has nowhere told us about these
                        hostages. In chap. xxii. 2 the same towns give the same number of hostages.
                        Obviously he has made distinct episodes out of different versions of the
                        same story, misled no doubt by the different dates assigned by different
                        annalists to the affair of Pometia. </note> This year also a triumph was
                    celebrated at Rome. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls of the next year, Opiter <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 502</note> Verginius
                    and Spurius Cassius, attempted to capture Pometia, first by assault and then by
                    the use of mantlets and other engines. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Against
                    their besiegers the Aurunci, rather of an implacable hatred than for any hope or
                    opportunity offered, rushed out, armed with firebrands for the most part,
                    instead of swords, and carried death and flames in all directions. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The mantlets were burned, many of their enemies were
                    wounded or slain, and one of the consuls —which one the historians do not add
                    —was seriously wounded, thrown from his horse, and almost killed. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans then marched home, defeated. Amongst the
                    many wounded they brought the consul, hovering betwixt life and death. When a
                    short time had elapsed, long enough for healing wounds and recruiting the army,
                    they returned, with heightened resentment and also with augmented forces, to the
                    attack of Pometia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They had repaired their
                    mantlets and the rest of their equipment, and they were already upon the <pb
                        n="p.275"/> point of sending their men against the walls when <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 502</note> the town
                    capitulated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the fate of the Aurunci was
                    no less awful from their having surrendered their city than if it had been
                    stormed. Their chief men were beheaded, and the rest of the colonists were sold
                    as slaves. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Literally <quote>under the
                            crown,</quote> meaning a chaplet placed on the head of a captive as an
                        indication that he was a part of the spoils. </note> The town was razed; its
                    land was sold. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls obtained a triumph,
                    more because they had heavily avenged Rome's wrongs than because of the
                    magnitude of the war which they had successfully concluded. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year after had as its consuls Postumius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 501</note>
                    Cominius and Titus Largius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this year,
                    during the celebration of the games at Rome, the Sabine youths, in a spirit of
                    wantonness, forcibly abducted certain harlots. Men gathered hastily and there
                    was a brawl which was almost a battle, and, trifling as its origin was, it
                    seemed to threaten a fresh outbreak of the war. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Despite the apparently conclusive victory recorded in
                        chap. xvi. 6. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Besides the Sabine peril, it was generally
                    known that the thirty Latin cities had already conspired, at the instigation of
                    Octavius Mamilius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These grave apprehensions
                    having occasioned a general anxiety, the appointment of a dictator was
                    suggested, for the first time. But there is no general agreement as to the year,
                    or which consuls were distrusted as being of the Tarquinian faction —for this is
                    included in the tradition —or who it was that was first named dictator.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the oldest writers, however, I find it
                    said that Titus Largius was the first to be made dictator, and that Spurius
                    Cassius was <pb n="p.277"/> master of the horse. They chose men of consular
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 501</note>
                    rank, for so the law prescribed which had been passed to regulate the selection
                    of a dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I am therefore the more
                    disposed to believe that Largius, a consular, rather than Manius Valerius, the
                    son of Marcus and grandson of Volesus, a man who had not yet held the
                    consulship, was assigned to be the director and superior of consuls; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and indeed if men had been specially desirous of
                    choosing the dictator from that family, they would much sooner have selected
                    Marcus Valerius the father, a man of proven worth and an ex-consul. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they had named a dictator for the first
                    time at Rome, and men saw the axes borne before him, a great fear came over the
                    plebs and caused them to be more zealous in obeying orders. For there was no
                    recourse in this case, as with the consuls, who shared the powers of their
                    office equally, to the assistance of the man's colleague, nor was there any
                    appeal nor any help anywhere but in scrupulous obedience. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> But in <date value="-300">300 B.C.</date> a <hi
                            rend="italics">lex Valeria de provocatione</hi> gave the people the
                        right to appeal from the dictator. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Sabines, too, were inspired with fear by
                    the appointment of the dictator, especially since they believed that it was on
                    their account that he had been created. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly they sent legates to treat for peace. When they requested the
                    dictator and the senate to pardon an error committed by young men, the answer
                    was given that to pardon young men was possible, but not old men who contrived
                    one war after another. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nevertheless
                    negotiations for peace were begun, and it would have been granted to the
                    Sabines, could they have made up their minds to guarantee, as the Romans
                    demanded, the sum which had been expended for the war. Hostilities were
                    declared, but a tacit truce preserved a state of peace through the year. </p>
                <pb n="p.279"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the consulship of Servius Sulpicius and
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 500-499</note>
                    Manius Tullius nothing worthy of note occurred. They were succeeded by Titus
                    Aebutius and Gaius Vetusius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During their year
                    of office Fidenae was besieged, Crustumeria taken; Praeneste went over from the
                    Latins to the Romans, and it was no longer possible to postpone the Latin war,
                    which had now been smouldering for several years. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Aulus Postumius as dictator, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Postumius had not held the consulship, which in chap.
                        xviii. 5 Livy stated to have been a necessary qualification for the
                        dictatorship. </note> and Titus Aebutius as master of the horse, set out
                    with large forces of infantry and cavalry, and at Lake Regillus, in the
                    territory of Tusculum, met the enemy's advancing column. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans had learned that the Tarquinii were with the
                    Latin army, and were so enraged that they could not be withheld from instantly
                    attacking, and the battle itself, in consequence of this report, was fought with
                    a good deal more determination and bitterness than any other had been.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For the leaders were not only in the field
                    to direct the engagement with their strategy, but joined battle and fought in
                    their own persons. Almost none of the nobles on either side came off unscathed,
                    except the Roman dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Postumius was in
                    the front rank encouraging his men and forming them, when Tarquinius Superbus,
                    though now burdened with years and broken in strength, rode full-tilt against
                    him. But the old man received a thrust in the side, and his followers rushed in
                    and rescued him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Similarly on the other wing,
                    Aebutius, the master of the horse, charged Octavius Mamilius. But the Tusculan
                    commander <pb n="p.281"/> saw him coming, and he too spurred his horse to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 500-499</note> the
                    encounter; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and so great was the force in their
                    levelled lances as they met, that the arm of Aebutius was transfixed, while
                    Mamilius was struck in the breast. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Mamilius
                    was received by the Latins within their second line: Aebutius, being unable to
                    manage a weapon with his wounded arm, retired from the battle. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The Latin leader, not a jot discouraged by his wound, urged
                    on the fighting, and, because he saw that his men were in retreat, called up a
                    cohort of Roman exiles, commanded by a son of Lucius Tarquinius, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Of the sons of Tarquinius, Sextus's
                        death is mentioned in I. lx. 2 and that of Arruns in II. vi. 9. This must
                        therefore have been Titus (I. lvi. 6). </note> and these, fighting with
                    greater fury on account of the loss of their property and native land, restored
                    the battle for a while. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Romans were now beginning to give way
                    in that part of the field, Marcus Valerius, Publicola's brother, espied the
                    young Tarquinius, who was boldly inviting attack in the front rank of the
                    exiles. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Valerius found in his brother's glory
                    an additional incentive, and resolving that the family which had the honour of
                    expelling the tyrants should also gain the credit for their death, he dug his
                    spurs into his charger and rode at Tarquinius with levelled spear. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Tarquinius drew back within the company of his
                    followers to avoid his desperate antagonist. Valerius was plunging blindly into
                    the exiles' line when one of them attacked him in the flank and ran him through
                    the body. But the rider's wound did not check the career of his horse, and the
                    dying Roman came down in a heap upon the ground with his arms upon him.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the dictator Postumius perceived that
                    so brave a soldier had fallen, that the exiles <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    were advancing boldly at the double, and that his troops were checked and were
                    giving <pb n="p.283"/> ground, he issued orders to his own cohort, a picked
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 500-499</note>
                    body of men which he kept about his person as a guard, that if they saw any
                    Roman running away they should treat him as an enemy. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Being thus between two dangers, the Romans faced about to
                    meet the foe, and the battle-line was formed again. The cohort of the dictator
                    then entered the engagement for the first time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> With fresh strength and spirit they attacked the weary exiles and cut them to
                    pieces. Then began another combat between leaders. The Latin general, perceiving
                    that the cohort of the exiles was nearly cut off by the Roman dictator, took a
                    few companies of his reserves and hurried them to the front. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> As they came marching up, Titus Herminius, the lieutenant,
                    caught sight of them, and in their midst, conspicuous in dress and
                    accoutrements, he saw and recognized Mamilius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Whereupon he hurled himself upon the enemy's commander with so much more
                    violence than the master of the horse had done a little before, that not only
                    did he pierce Mamilius through the side and slay him with a single lunge, but in
                    the act of stripping the body of his antagonist he was himself struck by a
                    hostile javelin, and after being borne off in the moment of victory to the Roman
                    camp, expired just as they began to dress his wound. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator then dashed up to the knights and besought
                    them, since the foot-soldiers were exhausted, to dismount and enter the fight.
                    They obeyed: they leaped down from their horses, hastened to the front, and
                    covered the front-rankers with their shields. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    It restored at once the courage of the foot to see the young nobles on even
                    terms with themselves and sharing in the danger. Then at last the <pb n="p.285"
                    /> Latins received a check, and their battle-line was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 500-499</note> forced to yield.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The knights had their horses brought up
                    that they might be able to pursue the enemy, and they were followed by the
                    infantry. Then the dictator, neglecting no help, divine or human, is said to
                    have vowed a temple to Castor, and to have promised rewards to the soldiers who
                    should be first and second to enter the camp of the enemy; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> and so great was the ardour of the Romans, that with a
                    single rush they routed their opponents and took their camp. Such was the battle
                    at Lake Regillus. The dictator and his master of the horse returned to the City
                    and triumphed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For the next three years there was neither
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 498-495</note>
                    a stable peace nor war. The consuls Quintus Cloelius and Titus Larcius were
                    followed by Aulus Sempronius and Marcus Minucius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> In the latter year a temple to Saturn was dedicated and the
                    Saturnalia was established as a festal day. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Saturnalia proper fell on December 17, though as
                        many as seven days came to be devoted to the popular celebration of the
                        festival (Macrobius, I. X. 24), which was a sort of carnival. As an old
                        Italic feast it probably originated earlier than Livy thought. See Macrobius
                        I. viii. 1. </note> Next Aulus Postumius and Titus Verginius were made
                    consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was not until this year, according
                    to some authorities I have consulted, that the battle of Lake Regillus was
                    fought. They say that Aulus Postumius, because his colleague was of doubtful
                    loyalty, resigned the consulship, and was then made dictator. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> One is involved in so many uncertainties regarding dates by
                    the varying order of the magistrates in different lists that it is impossible to
                    make out which consuls followed which, or what was done in each particular year,
                    when not only events but even authorities are so shrouded in antiquity. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.287"/>
                <p> At the next election Appius Claudius and Publius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 495</note> Servilius were chosen
                    consuls. This year was marked by the announcement of Tarquinius's death. He died
                    at Cumae, whither he had gone to the court of Aristodemus after the downfall of
                    the Latin cause. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These tidings cheered the
                    Fathers and encouraged the plebs. But the Fathers were too inconsiderate, in
                    consequence of their rejoicing at this event; and the plebs, who up to this time
                    had been most studiously deferred to, began to feel the oppression of the
                    nobles. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same year the colony of Signia,
                    which King Tarquinius had planted, was recruited with new colonists and
                    established for the second time. At Rome twenty-one tribes were formed. The
                    temple of Mercury was consecrated on the fifteenth of May. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With the Volscian race there had been during
                    the Latin war neither peace nor open hostilities; for while the Volsci had
                    raised levies to send to the aid of the Latins, had the Roman dictator not moved
                    quickly, yet the Romans did move quickly, that they might not have to fight both
                    nations in the same battle Upon this quarrel the consuls led their legions into
                    the country of the Volsci, who, not expecting to be held to account for their
                    design, were surprised and overwhelmed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                    had no thought of resisting, and surrendered as hostages three hundred children
                    of the nobility of Cora and Pometia, and so the legions were withdrawn without a
                    conflict. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Yet it was not long before the
                    Volsci, being relieved of their alarm, resumed their native duplicity; again
                    they made secret preparations for war, and formed a military alliance with the
                    Hernici, while they also sent out envoys, this <pb n="p.289"/> way and that, to
                    instigate the Latins to rebellion. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 495</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the disaster which had recently befallen
                    the Latins at Lake Regillus so filled them with rage and hate against anyone who
                    advised them to go to war, that they did not even abstain from violating an
                    embassy, but seized the Volsci and brought them to Rome. There they delivered
                    them up to the consuls with the information that the Volsci and the Hernici were
                    preparing to attack the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When this
                    service had been reported to the senate the Fathers were so grateful that they
                    released to the Latins six thousand captives, and referred the question of a
                    treaty, which they had all but refused in perpetuity, to the incoming
                    magistrates. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Neither captives nor
                        treaty were mentioned in chap. XX., and Livy seems here to be following a
                        different authority, possibly Valerius of Antium, whom at XXXIII. X. 8 he
                        accuses of exaggerating numbers. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then, indeed, the Latins rejoiced at the
                    action they had taken, and the advocates of peace were in great repute. They
                    sent a golden crown as a gift to the Capitoline Jupiter. With the envoys who
                    brought the gift came the captives who had been restored to their friends, a
                    vast attendant multitude. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Proceeding to the
                    homes of those whom they had severally served, they thanked them for the
                    liberality and consideration which had been shown them in their adversity, and
                    entered into covenants of hospitality with them. Never before had there been so
                    close a union, both official and personal, between the Latin name and the Roman
                    state. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But not only was war with the Volsci imminent;
                    the citizens were at loggerheads among themselves, and internal dissensions
                    between the Fathers and the plebs had burst into a blaze of hatred, chiefly on
                    account of those who had been bound over to service for their debts. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The word <hi rend="italics">nexus</hi>
                        was used (1) of one who had borrowed money by <quote>binding</quote> himself
                        to work out the debt as a virtual slave of his creditor, if unable to repay
                        the money; (2) of one so <quote>bound</quote> and actually serving. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These men complained loudly that while they
                    were abroad <pb n="p.291"/> fighting for liberty and dominion they had been
                    enslaved <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 495</note>
                    and oppressed at home by fellow-citizens, and that the freedom of the plebeians
                    was more secure in war than in peace, amongst enemies than amongst citizens.
                    This bitter feeling, which was growing spontaneously, the notable calamity of
                    one man fanned into a flame. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Old, and bearing
                    the marks of all his misfortunes, the man rushed into the Forum. His dress was
                    covered with filth, and the condition of his body was even worse, for he was
                    pale and half dead with emaciation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Besides
                    this, his straggling beard and hair had given a savage look to his countenance.
                    He was recognized nevertheless, despite the hideousness of his appearance, and
                    the word went round that he had commanded companies; yet other military honours
                    were openly ascribed to him by the compassionate bystanders, and the man himself
                    displayed the scars on his breast which bore testimony to his honourable service
                    in various battles. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they asked the reason
                    of his condition and his squalor, he replied, while the crowd gathered about him
                    much as though it were an assembly, that during his service in the Sabine war
                    not only had the enemy's depredations deprived him of his crops, but his cottage
                    had been burnt, all his belongings plundered, and his flocks driven off.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then the taxes had been levied, in an
                    untoward moment for him, and he had contracted debts. When these had been
                    swelled by usury, they had first stripped him of the farm which had been his
                    father's and his grandfather's, then of the remnants of his property, and
                    finally like an infection they had attacked his person, and he had been carried
                    off by his creditor, not to slavery, but to the prison and the <pb n="p.293"/>
                    torturechamber. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then showed them his back,
                    disfigured <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        495</note> with the wales of recent scourging. The sight of these things and
                    the man's recital produced a mighty uproar. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The disturbance was no longer confined to the Forum, but spread in all
                    directions through the entire City. Those who had been bound over, whether in
                    chains or not, broke out into the streets from every side, and implored the
                    Quirites to protect them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At no point was
                    there any lack of volunteers to join the rising; everywhere crowds were
                    streaming through the different streets and shouting as they hurried to the
                    Forum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Great was the peril of those senators
                    who happened to be in the Forum and fell in with the mob, which would not indeed
                    have stopped short of violence had not the consuls, Publius Servilius and Appius
                    Claudius, hurriedly intervened to put down the insurrection. But the crowd
                    turned on them and displayed their chains and other hideous tokens. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> These, they cried, were the rewards they had earned,
                    and they bitterly rehearsed the campaigns they had each served in various
                    places. They demanded, in a manner much more threatening than suppliant, that
                    the consuls should convene the senate; and they surrounded the Curia, that they
                    might them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> selves witness and control the
                    deliberations of the state. The consuls succeeded in collecting only a few of
                    the senators whom chance had thrown in their way. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The rest were afraid to enter not only the Curia but even
                    the Forum, and nothing could be done because those present were too few. Whereat
                    the people concluded they were being flouted and put off, and that the missing
                    senators were absent not from accident, nor fear, but with the intent to hinder
                    action, and that the consuls themselves were paltering; <pb n="p.295"/> nor did
                    they doubt that their misery was made a <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 495</note> jest. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> A little more and not even the majesty of the consuls could
                    have held in check the angry crowd, when the absent Fathers, uncertain whether
                    they should incur more danger by holding back or by coming forward, finally came
                    into the senate, and the required number being at length assembled, not only the
                    senators, but even the consuls themselves were unable to agree. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Appius, a headstrong man, was for settling the
                    matter by the exercise of consular authority; when one or two men had been
                    arrested, the others, he said, would calm down. Servilius, more inclined to
                    gentle measures, believed that it was safer, as well as easier, to assuage their
                    fury than to quell it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the midst of the debate a greater alarm
                    arose from a new quarter, for some Latin horsemen galloped up with the
                    disquieting news that a Volscian army was advancing to attack the City. This
                    report awoke very different feelings —so completely had their dissensions
                    divided the state into two —in the Fathers and the plebs. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The commons were jubilant; they said that the gods were
                    taking a hand in punishing the arrogance of the senators. They encouraged one
                    another not to give in their names; it would be better to perish all together
                    than alone. Let the Fathers serve, let the Fathers take up arms, that those
                    might incur the hazards of war who received its rewards. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The Curia, on the other hand, was downcast and dismayed. In
                    their twofold fear —of their fellow-citizens and of the enemy —they begged
                    Servilius the consul, whose character appealed more to the people than did that
                    of his colleague, that he would extricate the state from <pb n="p.297"/> the
                    fearful perils with which it was beset. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 495</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thereupon the consul adjourned the senate and
                    went before the people. There he declared that the Fathers were anxious to
                    consult the interests of the plebs, but that their deliberations concerning that
                    very important part —but only a part after all —of the state had been broken off
                    by their fears for the entire nation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was
                    impossible, when the enemy was almost at the city gates, to consider anything
                    before the war; and even if there should be some slight respite in that regard,
                    it was neither to the credit of the plebs to refuse to arm for their country,
                    unless they should first receive a recompense, nor honourable to the Fathers to
                    be driven by fear into passing measures for the relief of their fellow-citizens
                    which they would have passed later of their own free will. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He then confirmed his speech by a proclamation in which he
                    commanded that no one should hold a Roman citizen in chains or durance so that
                    he should not be able to give in his name to the consuls, and that none should
                    seize or sell a soldier's property so long as he was in camp, or interfere with
                    his children or his grandchildren. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this
                    edict had been published, the debtors who were present at once enlisted, and
                    from every quarter, all over the City, they hastened from the houses where their
                    creditors no longer had the right to detain them, and rushed into the Forum to
                    take the military oath. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was a great throng,
                    nor were there any soldiers whose courage and usefulness in the Volscian war
                    were more conspicuous. The consul led his troops against the enemy, and pitched
                    his camp at a short distance from theirs. </p>
                <pb n="p.299"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next night the Volsci, relying on the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 495</note> lack
                    of harmony among the Romans, attacked their camp on the chance that the darkness
                    might encourage desertions or treachery. But the sentries perceived them, the
                    army was roused, and, the signal being given, rushed to arms. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Thus the design of the Volsci came to naught, and the
                    remainder of the night was devoted by both armies to sleeping. On the following
                    day at dawn the Volsci filled up the trenches and assaulted the rampart, and
                    soon they were everywhere pulling down the palisades. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> On every side the consul's men were clamouring for the
                    signal —none more loudly than the debtors. He waited a moment, to test the
                    temper of the soldiers. When there could no longer be any doubt of their great
                    ardour, he finally gave the command for a sortie and released them, eager for
                    the fray. At the very first onset the enemy were routed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> While they ran, the foot-soldiers struck at them from
                    behind as long as they could keep up the pursuit; then the horsemen drove them
                    panic-stricken clear to their camp. Soon the camp itself had been surrounded by
                    the legions, and when the Volsci had fled from it in terror, it was taken and
                    plundered. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next day Servilius led his forces
                    to Suessa Pometia, where the enemy had taken refuge, and within a few days took
                    the town and gave it up to be sacked. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        But it had already been razed, as we read in chap. xvii. 6 — another
                        indication that Livy is reproducing different versions of the same story
                        (see chap. xvi. 9 and note). </note> This yielded some slight relief to the
                    soldiers, who needed it <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> badly. The consul led
                    his army back to Rome, with great honour to himself. As he was setting out on
                    his return thither ambassadors approached him from <pb n="p.301"/> the Volsci of
                    Ecetra, who were alarmed at their own <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 495</note> prospects, in view of the capture of Pometia.
                    A decree of the senate granted them peace, but took away their land. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Directly after this the Sabines also caused an
                    alarm at Rome —for it was indeed a turmoil rather than war. One night the City
                    got word that a Sabine army bent on pillage had come as near as the river Anio,
                    and was there plundering and burning farmhouses right and left. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans at once dispatched in that direction all their
                    cavalry, under Aulus Postumius, who had been dictator in the Latin war. He was
                    followed by the consul Servilius with a picked body of foot-soldiers. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Many stragglers were cut off by the cavalry and, when
                    the column of infantry drew near, no resistance was offered by the Sabine
                    troops. Exhausted not only by their march but by their night of pillage as well,
                    a great part of them had gorged themselves in the farmhouses with food and wine,
                    and had scarcely vigour enough to run away. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A single night having sufficed for hearing of
                    the Sabine war and ending it, men's hopes next day ran high that peace was now
                    assured in every quarter, when legates from the Aurunci appeared before the
                    senate to say that unless the territory of the Volsci were evacuated they should
                    declare war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Auruncan army had set out
                    from home at the same time with the legates, and the report that it had already
                    been seen not far from Aricia threw Rome into such a state of confusion that it
                    was impossible to bring the matter regularly before the senate, or to return a
                    peaceful answer to a people who had already drawn the sword, while they
                    themselves were also arming. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They marched on
                    Aricia in fighting order, joined <pb n="p.303"/> battle with the Aurunci not far
                    from the town, and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        495</note> in a single engagement finished the war. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having routed the Aurunci, and having been,
                    within a few days, victorious in so many wars, the Romans were looking for the
                    help which the consul had promised and the senate guaranteed, when Appius,
                    partly out of native arrogance, partly to discredit his colleague, began to
                    pronounce judgment with the utmost rigour in suits to recover debts. In
                    consequence, not only were those who had been bound over before delivered up to
                    their creditors, but others were bound over. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Whenever this happened to a soldier he would appeal to the other consul. The
                    people flocked to the house of Servilius: it was he who had made them promises;
                    it was he whom they reproached, as each rehearsed his services in the wars and
                    displayed the scars he had received. They demanded that he should either lay the
                    matter before the senate or lend his aid as consul to his fellow-citizens, as
                    general to his soldiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They moved the consul
                    by this plea, but the situation forced him to temporize, so vehemently was the
                    other side supported, not only by his colleague, but by the entire party of the
                    nobles. And so he steered a middle course, and neither avoided the dislike of
                    the plebs nor gained the goodwill of the Fathers. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> These considered him a pusillanimous consul and an
                    agitator, while the commons held him to be dishonest; and it was soon apparent
                    that he was as cordially hated as Appius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls had got into a dispute as to which should dedicate the temple to
                    Mercury. The senate referred the case to the people for decision. Whichever
                    consul should, by command of the people, be entrusted with the dedication was to
                    have charge <pb n="p.305"/> of the corn-supply, to establish a guild of
                    merchants, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Mercury was the patron of
                        trade.</note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 495</note> and
                    perform the solemn rites in the presence of the <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> pontifex. The people assigned the dedication to Marcus Laetorius, a centurion
                    of the first rank —a choice which would readily be understood as intended not so
                    much to honour Laetorius, to whom a commission had been given which was too
                    exalted for his station in life, as to humiliate the <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> consuls. Appius and the Fathers were furious then, if they
                    had not been before; but the plebeians had plucked up heart and threw themselves
                    into the struggle with far more spirit than they had shown at <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> first. For, despairing of help from consuls and senate,
                    they no sooner beheld a debtor being haled away than they flew to his assistance
                    from every <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> side. It was impossible for the
                    consul's decree to be heard above the din and shouting, and when it had been
                    pronounced nobody obeyed it. Violence was the order of the day, and fear and
                    danger had quite shifted from the debtors to the creditors, who were singled out
                    and maltreated by large numbers in full sight of the <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> consul. To crown these troubles came the fear of a Sabine
                    invasion. A levy was decreed, but no one enlisted. Appius stormed and railed at
                    the insidious arts of his colleague, who, he said, to make himself popular, was
                    betraying the state by his inactivity; and to his refusal to give judgment for
                    debt was adding a fresh offence in refusing to hold the levy as the senate had
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> directed. Nevertheless the welfare of the
                    state was not wholly forgotten, nor the authority of the consulate abandoned; he
                    would himself, single-handed, assert both his own and the senate's <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> majesty. When the usual daily throng of lawless men
                    was standing about him, he gave orders <pb n="p.307"/> to seize one who was a
                    conspicuous leader in their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 495</note> disturbances. The lictors were already
                    dragging the man away, when he appealed; nor would the consul have granted the
                    appeal, for there was no question what the decision of the people would be, had
                    not his obstinacy been with difficulty overcome, more by the advice and
                    influence of the nobles than by the popular outcry, so steeled was he to endure
                    men's <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> hate. From that moment the trouble grew
                    worse each day, and not only were there open disturbances, but what was far more
                    pernicious, secret gatherings and conferences. At last the consuls whom the
                    plebeians so hated went out of office. Servilius had the goodwill of neither
                    party, but Appius was in high esteem with the senators. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aulus Verginius and Titus Vetusius then <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 494</note> entered
                    upon the consulship. Whereat the plebs, uncertain what sort of consuls they
                    would prove to be, held nightly gatherings, some on the Esquiline and other son
                    the Aventine, lest if they met in the Forum they might be frightened into
                    adopting ill-considered measures, and manage all their business rashly and at
                    haphazard. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This seemed to the consuls, as
                    indeed it was, a mischievous practice. They laid the matter before the Fathers,
                    but their report could not be discussed in an orderly fashion, so tumultuously
                    was it received, with shouts from every part of the house and expressions of
                    indignation from the senators, that a thing which ought to have been settled by
                    an exercise of consular authority should be invidiously referred by the consuls
                    to the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was evident that if only
                    there were magistrates in the nation there would have been no assembly in Rome
                    but the assembly of the people; as it was, the <pb n="p.309"/> government was
                    broken up into a thousand separate <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 494</note> curias and meetings. One single <hi
                        rend="italics">man</hi> —a more significant word than <hi rend="italics"
                        >consul</hi> —of the type of Appius Claudius, would have dispersed those
                    assemblages in a moment. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the consuls,
                    thus upbraided, asked the Fathers what then they desired them to do, and
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> promised that their conduct of the matter
                    should be no whit less strenuous and stern than the senate wished, it was
                    resolved that they should hold a levy with the utmost severity: it was idleness
                    that made the plebeians lawless. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having
                    adjourned the senate, the consuls mounted the tribunal and cited the young men
                    by name. When no one answered to his name, the crowd, which surrounded the
                    speaker as in a public meeting, declared that it was impossible to deceive the
                    commons any longer; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the consuls would never
                    have a single soldier unless a public guarantee were given: liberty must first
                    be restored to every man before arms were given him, that he might fight for his
                    country and his fellow-citizens, not for a master. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> It was clear to the consuls what the senate had bidden them
                    do; but of all those who had uttered truculent speeches within the walls of the
                    curia they found not one at their side to share their odium, and they saw before
                    them a terrible struggle with the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly they thought it best, before proceeding to extremities, to consult
                    the senate a second time. When it met, the youngest senators all rushed up in
                    hot haste to the seats of the consuls, bidding them to abdicate their office and
                    to lay down an authority which they lacked the spirit to support. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having sufficiently weighed both the courses
                    open to them, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> (1) to persuade the
                        senate to content the people; (2) to coerce the people. </note> the consuls
                    finally said: <quote> Lest you should say that you had not been warned, <pb
                            n="p.311"/> Conscript Fathers, we are on the verge of a great mutiny.
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 494</note>
                        We demand that those who are loudest in accusing us of cowardice stand by us
                        while we hold the levy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The most severe
                        amongst you, since such is your pleasure, shall guide our procedure.
                    </quote> They returned to the tribunal, and purposely commanded to cite by name
                    one of those who were present. When he stood still without answering, in the
                    midst of a little knot of men who, fearing the possibility of violence, had
                    gathered round him, the consuls sent a lictor to him. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The lictor was driven back. Whereupon, with a cry of
                        <quote>Shame!</quote> the senators who were attending the consul rushed down
                    from the tribunal to assist the lictor. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But
                    when the mob turned from the officer, whom they had merely prevented from
                    arresting the man, and assailed the senators, the consuls intervened and checked
                    the brawl, in which no stones had been thrown nor any weapons used, and there
                    were more shouts and expressions of rage than hurts. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate was convened in confusion, and they deliberated
                    in still greater confusion. Those who had been roughly handled demanded an
                    investigation, and all the more violent members urged the resolution, not only
                    with speeches but with shouts and uproar. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When
                    at length their passions had subsided, and the consuls berated them for showing
                    as little sanity in the Curia as the people had shown in the Forum, they began
                    to deliberate in an orderly manner. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Three
                    proposals were made. Publius Verginius advised against a general relief: only
                    those who, relying on the promise of Publius Servilius the consul, had fought in
                    the Volscian, Auruncan, and Sabine wars should, he thought, be considered.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Titus Largius held that this was no time
                    for merely requiting services; <pb n="p.313"/> the whole commons was submerged
                    in debt, and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        494</note> the situation could not be remedied unless provision were made
                    for all; indeed, if some were treated in one way and some in another, it would
                    heighten the discontent instead of allaying it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Appius Claudius, naturally harsh, and rendered savage by the hatred of the
                    plebs on the one hand and the praises of the Fathers on the other, said that it
                    was not misery but licence that had stirred up so great a hubbub, and that
                    wantonness was what ailed the plebs rather than anger. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> That was precisely the mischief which the appeal
                    occasioned; for the consuls might threaten but could not command, when those who
                    had shared in the guilt might be constituted the court of appeal. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Come,</quote> said he, <quote> let us appoint a dictator, from whom there
                        is no appeal. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At once this frenzy which
                        has now set everything ablaze will be stilled. Let anybody strike a lictor
                        then, knowing that the right to scourge and behead him rests with that one
                        man whose majesty he has violated! </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Many felt, and with reason, that the proposal
                    of Appius was stern and cruel; on the other hand those of Verginius and Largius
                    were inexpedient because of the precedent; particularly that of Largius, since
                    it destroyed all credit. The most reasonable and moderate plan, in its regard
                    for both sides, was held to be that of Verginius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But owing to party spirit and consideration for private
                    interests, things which have always been hurtful to public deliberations and
                    always will be, Appius prevailed, and came very near <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> to being himself appointed dictator, a step which would
                    infallibly have estranged the commons, and that at a most dangerous moment,
                    since the Volsci, the Aequi, and the Sabines were all, as it <pb n="p.315"/>
                    chanced, up in arms at once. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But the consuls
                    and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 494</note> the
                    older senators saw to it that a magistracy rendered formidable by its paramount
                    authority should be committed to a man of gentle disposition, and chose for
                    dictator Manius Valerius, son of Volesus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    plebs, though they perceived that it was against themselves that the creation of
                    a dictator was aimed, still, since it was through a law proposed by a brother of
                    Valerius that they possessed the right of <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    appeal, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> That is to say, in general;
                        from a dictator, however, there was no appeal until a later period. </note>
                    they had no fear of any harsh or oppressive act on the part of one of that
                    family. An edict which the dictator soon promulgated strengthened their
                    confidence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It conformed essentially to the
                    edict of Servilius; but Valerius and the office he held commanded greater
                    confidence, and, ceasing to struggle, men gave in their names. So large an army
                    had never been enrolled before. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Ten legions
                    were embodied; each consul was given three of these, and the dictator had four. </p>
                <p> Nor could war be deferred any longer, for the Aequi had invaded Latin territory.
                    Emissaries from the Latins begged the senate either to send them help or permit
                    them to take up arms themselves in defence of their country. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Apparently the Latins, perhaps after
                        the battle of Lake Regillus (chap. xix. f.), had been denied the right to
                        make war, save at the pleasure of the Romans. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It seemed safer that the Latins should be
                    defended without arming them, than that they should be suffered to resume their
                    weapons. Vetusius the consul was dispatched to them, and this ended the
                    pillaging. The Aequi left the fields, and trusting more to situation than to
                    arms, secured themselves on the summits of the ridges. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The other consul marched against the Volsci. Lest he too
                    might waste his time, he provoked the <pb n="p.317"/> enemy, chiefly by ravaging
                    their lands, to bring their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 494</note> camp nearer and do battle with him. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> In the plain between the camps the two armies formed
                    their lines, each in front of its own stockade. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> In numbers the Volsci were somewhat superior, and accordingly they came on in
                    a loose and careless order. The Roman consul did not advance, nor did he allow a
                    response to the enemy's shout. He commanded his men to plant their spears in the
                    ground and stand still until the enemy had come to close quarters; then they
                    were to assail them with all their might, and settle the question with the
                    sword. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Volsci, weary with running and
                    shouting, hurled themselves upon the Romans, who seemed to be numb with fear.
                    But when the attackers found that their charge was firmly met and saw the swords
                    flash in their faces, they were no whit less confounded than if they had fallen
                    into an ambush, and turned and fled; and even flight was beyond their strength,
                    since they had been running as they entered the battle. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans on the contrary, having stood at ease at the
                    beginning of the fight, were fresh and strong; they readily caught up with the
                    exhausted Volsci, and having taken their camp with a rush, pursued their enemies
                    beyond it to Velitrae, where vanquished and victors burst into the city in one
                    body. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> More blood was shed there, in the
                    promiscuous slaughter of all sorts of people, than had been in the battle
                    itself. A very few were granted quarter, having come without arms and given
                    themselves up. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were going on in the
                    Volscian country, the dictator put to rout the Sabines —by far Rome's most
                    important enemy —and captured their camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Attacking with his cavalry, he <pb n="p.319"/> made havoc of their centre,
                    which, in extending <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        494</note> their wings too widely, they had unduly weakened; and in the
                    midst of the disorder the infantry assailed them. By a single rush the camp was
                    captured and the war ended. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From the time of
                    the fight at Lake Regillus no other battle of those days was more famous. The
                    dictator entered the City in triumph. In addition to the customary honours a
                    place was assigned him in the circus, for himself and his descendants, to
                    witness the games, and a curule chair was put there for him. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> That this apparently unique distinction
                        was actually conferred on the Valerii is confirmed by an honorary
                        inscription ( <hi rend="italics">C.I.L.</hi> i. 284). </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Volsci, having been conquered, were
                    deprived of the Veliternian land; colonists were sent from the City to Velitrae
                    and a colony was planted. Soon after this there was a battle with the Aequi,
                    though the consul was against it, for it was necessary to approach the enemy
                    from unfavourable ground; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but his men accused
                    him of dragging out the campaign in order that the dictator might relinquish his
                    office before their return to the City, and his promises thus come to naught, as
                    the consul's promises had done before. Vetusius was thus driven to order an
                    advance at random, up the mountains which confronted him. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> This ill-advised measure the enemy's cowardice turned into
                    success, for before the Romans had come within a spear's throw, the Aequi,
                    appalled at their audacity, abandoned the camp which they had maintained in a
                    highly defensible position, and threw themselves down into the valleys on the
                    other side. There the Romans gained considerable booty and a bloodless victory. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though a threefold success had thus been
                    gained in the war, neither senators nor plebeians had been relieved of their
                    anxiety respecting the outcome of <pb n="p.321"/> affairs at home, so great was
                    the artfulness, as well <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 494</note> as influence, with which the money-lenders had laid their
                    plans to baffle not only the commons but even the dictator himself. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> For after the return of the consul Vetusius, the
                    first business which Valerius brought before the senate was in behalf of the
                    victorious people, that the senate might declare its policy regarding the
                    treatment of those bound over for debt. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This
                    resolution having failed to pass, the dictator said: <quote> I do not please you
                        in urging harmony. You will soon wish, I warrant you, that the Roman plebs
                        had men like me for their spokesmen. For my own part I will not be the means
                        of further disappointing my fellow citizens, nor will I be dictator to no
                        purpose. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Internal strife and foreign war
                        made this office necessary to the nation; peace has been secured abroad, but
                        at home it is being thwarted; I will play my part as a private citizen
                        rather than as a dictator, when the mutiny breaks out. </quote> So saying he
                    left the Curia and laid down his office. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It
                    was evident to the people that resentment of their wrongs had caused him to
                    resign the magistracy. And so, as though he had kept his pledge (for it had not
                    been his fault that it was not being carried out), they attended him as he
                    retired to his house with manifestations of favour and approval. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereupon the senators became alarmed, fearing
                    that if the army should be disbanded there would again be secret gatherings and
                    conspiracies. And so, although the levy had been held by order of the dictator,
                    yet because the men had been sworn in by the consuls they regarded the troops as
                    bound by their oath, and, under the pretext that the Aequi <pb n="p.323"/> had
                    recommenced hostilities, gave orders to lead the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 494</note> legions out of the City.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This brought the revolt to a head. At
                    first it is said, there was talk of killing the consuls, that men might thus be
                    freed from their oath; but when it was explained to them that no sacred
                    obligation could be dissolved by a crime, they took the advice of one Sicinius,
                    and without orders from the consuls withdrew to the Sacred Mount, which is
                    situated across the river Anio, three miles from the City. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> —This version of the story is more general than that given
                    by Piso, namely that the Aventine was the place of their secession. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy appears to have had the other
                        tradition in mind when he wrote iii. liv. 9. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> —There, without any leader, they fortified
                    their camp with stockade and trench, and continued quietly, taking nothing but
                    what they required for their subsistance, for several days, neither receiving
                    provocation nor giving any. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was a great
                    panic in the City, and mutual apprehension caused the suspension of all
                    activities. The plebeians, having been abandoned by their friends, feared
                    violence at the hands of the senators; the senators feared the plebeians who
                    were left behind in Rome, being uncertain whether they had rather they stayed or
                    went. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Besides, how long would the seceding
                    multitude continue peaceable? What would happen next if some foreign war should
                    break out in the interim? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Assuredly no hope
                    was left save in harmony amongst the citizens, and this they concluded they must
                    restore to the state by fair means or foul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    They therefore decided to send as an ambassador to the commons Agrippa Menenius,
                    an eloquent man and dear to the plebeians as being one of themselves by birth.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> If Menenius was a plebeian, it is
                        improbable that he was also, as Livy rather implies, a senator. <hi
                            rend="italics">cf.</hi> i. 11 and note. </note> On being admitted to the
                    camp he is said merely to have related the following apologue, in the quaint and
                    uncouth <pb n="p.325"/> style of that age: <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In
                    the days when man's members <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 494</note> did not all agree amongst themselves, as is
                    now the case, but had each its own ideas and a voice of its own, the other parts
                    thought it unfair that they should have the worry and the trouble and the labour
                    of providing everything for the belly, while the belly remained quietly in their
                    midst with nothing to do but to enjoy the good things which they bestowed upon
                    it; they therefore conspired together that the hands should carry no food to the
                    mouth, nor the mouth accept anything that was given it, nor the teeth grind up
                    what they received. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While they sought in this
                    angry spirit to starve the belly into submission, the members themselves and the
                    whole body were reduced to the utmost weakness. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Hence it had become clear that even the belly had no idle task to perform,
                    and was no more nourished than it nourished the rest, by giving out to all parts
                    of the body that by which we live and thrive, when it has been divided equally
                    amongst the veins and is enriched with digested food —that is, the blood.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Drawing a parallel from this to show how
                    like was the internal dissension of the bodily members to the anger of the plebs
                    against the Fathers, he prevailed upon the minds of his hearers. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The same apologue is found in Xenophon,
                            <hi rend="italics">Mem.</hi> II. iii. 18; Cicero, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Off.</hi> III. v. 22; and St. Paul, <hi rend="italics">Cor.</hi> I.
                        xii. 12. </note>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Steps <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 493</note> were then taken towards
                    harmony, and a compromise was effected on these terms: the plebeians were to
                    have magistrates of their own, who should be inviolable, and in them should lie
                    the right to aid the people against the consuls, nor should any senator be
                    permitted to take this magistracy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And so they
                    chose two <quote>tribunes of the people,</quote> Gaius Licinius and Lucius
                    Albinus. These appointed three others to be their colleagues. Amongst the
                    latter, <pb n="p.327"/> Sicinius, the promoter of the revolt, was one, as all
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 493</note>
                    agree; the identity of the other two is less certain. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Some hold that there were only two tribunes elected on the
                    Sacred Mount, and that the law of inviolability was enacted there. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In either case the number was five from
                        the year 471 on (lviii. 1), till it was raised to ten in the year 457.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p> During the secession of the plebs Spurius Cassius and Postumus Cominius entered
                    upon their consulship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In this year a treaty
                    was made with the Latin peoples. In order to make this treaty one of the consuls
                    remained in Rome, while the other was dispatched to the Volscian war, and
                    defeated and put to flight the Volsci of Antium. Forcing them to take refuge in
                    the town of Longula, he followed them up and captured the place. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Thence he proceeded to take Polusca, another Volscian
                    town, after which he directed a strong attack upon Corioli. There was in camp at
                    that time amongst the young nobles Gnaeus Marcius, a youth of active mind and
                    ready hand, who afterwards gained the surname of Coriolanus. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans were laying siege to Corioli and were intent
                    upon the townspeople shut up within the walls, with no thought of danger from
                    any attack which might be impending from without, when they found themselves
                    suddenly assailed by a Volscian army from Antium, and simultaneously by the
                    besieged, who made a sortie from the town. It happened that Marcius was on
                    guard. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Taking a picked body of men he not only
                    repelled the sally, but boldly forced his way through the open gate, and having
                    spread carnage through the adjacent part of the town, caught up a firebrand on
                    the spur of the moment, and threw it upon the buildings which <pb n="p.329"/>
                    overhung the wall. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thereupon the townspeople
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 493</note>
                    raised a shout, mingled with such a wailing of women and children as is
                    generally heard at the first alarm. This brought new courage to the Romans and
                    covered the Volsci with confusion —as was natural when the city which they had
                    come to relieve was taken. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus the men of
                    Antium were routed, and Corioli was won. So completely did the glory of Marcius
                    overshadow the consul's fame, that, were it not for the record on a bronze
                    column of the treaty with the Latins which was struck by Spurius Cassius alone,
                    in the absence of his colleague, men would have forgotten that Postumus Cominius
                    had waged war on the Volsci. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That same year saw the death of Agrippa
                    Menenius, a man who throughout his life had been equally beloved by patricians
                    and plebeians, and who after the secession was even dearer to the commons.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This mediator and umpire of civil
                    harmony, this ambassador of the senators to the people, this restorer of the
                    plebs to Rome, did not leave sufficient wealth to pay for a funeral. He was
                    buried by the commons, who contributed a <hi rend="italics">sextans</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A <hi rend="italics">sextans</hi> was
                        the sixth part of an as, or pound of copper. </note> each to the cost. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls next chosen were Titus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 492-491</note>
                    Geganius and Publius Minucius. This year, though there was no war to occasion
                    trouble from without and the breach at home had been healed, another and a much
                    more serious misfortune befell the nation; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for
                    first the price of corn went up, from men's failure to cultivate the fields
                    during the withdrawal of the plebs; and this was followed by a famine, such as
                    comes to a beleaguered city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It would have
                    meant starvation for the slaves, at least, and the plebeians, had not the
                    consuls met the situation by sending <pb n="p.331"/> agents far and wide to buy
                    up corn, not only to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 492-491</note> Etruria, northwards along the coast from Ostia, and
                    south past the Volsci by sea, all the way to Cumae, but even to Sicily —so far
                    afield had the enmity of Rome's neighbours driven her to seek for help.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When grain had been purchased at Cumae the
                    ships were held back by Aristodemus, the tyrant, in satisfaction for the
                    property of the Tarquinii, whose heir he was. Among the Volsci and Pomptini the
                    agents could not even make any purchases, and they were actually in danger from
                    the violence of the people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From the Tuscans
                    corn came in by way of the Tiber, and with this the plebs were kept alive. A
                    disastrous war would have been added to the distresses arising from the scarcity
                    of provisions, had not a grievous pestilence descended upon the Volsci just as
                    they were beginning hostilities. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Its ravages
                    so terrified the enemy that even after the worst of it was over they did not
                    fully recover from their fear, and the Romans increased the number of colonists
                    at Velitrae and sent out a new colony to Norba, in the mountains, as a
                    stronghold for the Pomptine country. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Next year, in the consulship of Marcus
                    Minucius and Aulus Sempronius, a large quantity of grain was imported from
                    Sicily, and the senate debated at what price it should be sold to the plebeians.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Many thought the time had come for
                    repressing the commons, and resuming the rights which they had violently
                    extorted from the Fathers by secession. Conspicuous among these was Marcius
                    Coriolanus, an enemy to the tribunician power, who said: <quote> If they want
                        corn at the old price let them restore to the senate its ancient rights.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Why do I see plebeian magistrates, why
                        do I, after being sent beneath <pb n="p.333"/> the yoke and ransomed, as it
                        were, from brigands, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                            >B.C. 492-491</note> behold Sicinius in power? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Shall I endure these humiliations any longer than I
                        must? When I would not brook Tarquinius as king, must I brook Sicinius? Let
                        him secede now and call out the plebs; the way lies open to the Sacred Mount
                        and the other hills. Let them seize grain from our fields as they did two
                        years ago. Let them enjoy the corn-prices they have brought about by their
                        own madness. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I make bold to say that this
                        evil plight will so tame them that they will sooner till the land themselves
                        than withdraw under arms and prevent its cultivation by others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It is not so easy to say whether it would
                    have been right to do this, as it is clear, I think, that it lay within the
                    Fathers' power to have made such conditions for reducing the price of corn as to
                    have freed themselves from the tribunician authority and all the terms which
                    they had unwillingly agreed to. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Even the senate deemed the proposal too <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 491</note> harsh, and
                    the plebs were so angry that they almost resorted to arms. Starvation, they
                    said, was now being employed against them, as though they were public enemies,
                    and they were being defrauded of their food and sustenance; the imported corn,
                    their only supply, unexpectedly bestowed on them by Fortune, was to be snatched
                    from their mouths unless the tribunes should be delivered up in chains to Gnaeus
                    Marcius, unless he should work his will on the persons of the Roman plebeians;
                    in him a new executioner had risen up against them, who bade them choose between
                    death and slavery. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he came out from the
                    Curia they would have set upon him, had not the tribunes, in the nick of time,
                    appointed a day to try him; whereupon their anger subsided, <pb n="p.335"/> for
                    every man saw that he was himself made his <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 491</note> enemy's judge, and held
                    over him the power of life and death. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With
                    contempt at first Marcius heard the threats of the tribunes, alleging that the
                    right to help, not to punish, had been granted to that office, and that they
                    were tribunes not of the Fathers, but of the plebs. But the commons had risen in
                    such a storm of anger that the Fathers had to sacrifice one man to appease them.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For all that, they resisted the hatred of
                    their adversaries and called upon the private resources of the several senators,
                    as well as the strength of the entire order. At first they tried, by posting
                    their clients <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The clients were a
                        class distinct both from the plebs and the patricians. To the latter they
                        stood in the feudal relation of vassal to lord. They were perhaps originally
                        citizens of conquered towns, and were recruited by manumissions and
                        immigration. </note> here and there, to frighten persons from coming
                    together for deliberation, in the hope that they might thereby break up their
                    plans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then they came out in a body —you would
                    have said all the members of the senate were on their trial —and entreated the
                    plebs to release to them one citizen, one senator; if they were unwilling to
                    acquit him as innocent let them give him up, though guilty, as a favour.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But when Marcius himself, on the day
                    appointed for the hearing, failed to appear, men's hearts were hardened against
                    him. Condemned in his absence, he went into exile with the Volsci, uttering
                    threats against his country, and even then breathing hostility. When he came
                    among the Volsci they received him with a kindness which increased from one day
                    to the next, in proportion as he allowed a greater hatred of his own people to
                    appear, and was more and more frequently heard to utter both complaints and
                    threats. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His host was Attius Tullius, at that
                    time by far the foremost of the Volscian name and ever unfriendly to the Romans.
                    And so, spurred on, the one by his inveterate hatred and <pb n="p.337"/> the
                    other by fresh resentment, they took counsel <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 491</note> together how they might
                    make war on Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They believed that it would
                    be no easy matter to induce the Volscian commons to take up the arms which they
                    had so often unluckily essayed; the destruction of their young men in
                    oft-repeated wars, and finally by the plague, had, they supposed, broken their
                    spirit; artifice must be invoked, where hate had grown dull with lapse of time,
                    that they might find some new cause of anger to exasperate men's hearts. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It so happened that at Rome preparations were
                    making to repeat the Great Games. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Roman Games (cf. I. xxxv. 9). </note> The
                    reason of the repetition was as follows: at an early hour of the day appointed
                    for the games, before the show had begun, a certain householder had driven his
                    slave, bearing a yoke, through the midst of the circus, scourging the culprit as
                    he went. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The games had then been begun, as
                    though this circumstance had in no way affected their sanctity. Not long after,
                    Titus Latinius, a plebeian, had a dream. He dreamt that Jupiter said that the
                    leading dancer at the games <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the slave who had been scourged through the
                        circus. </note> had not been to his liking; that unless there were a
                    sumptuous repetition of the festival the City would be in danger; that Latinius
                    was to go and announce this to the consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Though the man's conscience was by no means at ease, nevertheless the awe he
                    felt at the majesty of the magistrates was too great; he was afraid of becoming
                    a laughing-stock. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Heavy was the price he paid
                    for his hesitation, for a few days later he lost his son. Lest this sudden
                    calamity should leave any uncertainty as to its cause in the mind of the
                    wretched man, the same phantom appeared again before him in his dreams, and
                    asked <pb n="p.339"/> him, as he thought, whether he had been sufficiently <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 491</note> repaid for
                    spurning the gods; for a greater recompense was at hand unless he went quickly
                    and informed the consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This brought the
                    matter nearer home. Yet he still delayed and put off going, till a violent
                    attack of illness suddenly laid him low. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then
                    at last the anger of the gods taught him wisdom. And so, worn out with his
                    sufferings, past and present, he called a council of his kinsmen and explained
                    to them what he had seen and heard, how Jupiter had so often confronted him in
                    his sleep, and how the threats and anger of the god had been instantly fulfilled
                    in his own misfortunes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then, with the
                    unhesitating approval of all who were present, he was carried on a litter to the
                    consuls in the Forum; and thence, by their command, to the Curia, where he had
                    no sooner told the same story to the Fathers, greatly to the wonder of them all,
                    when — lo, another miracle! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For it is related
                    that he who had been carried into the senate-house afflicted in all his members,
                    returned home, after discharging his duty, on his own feet. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Games of the greatest possible splendour were
                    decreed by the senate, and to see them came, at the suggestion of Attius
                    Tullius, a host of Volsci. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Before the
                    beginning of the spectacle Tullius, in pursuance of the plan he and Marcius had
                    formed at home, went to the consuls and told them that he had something of
                    public importance which he wished to discuss with them in private. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> When the bystanders had been removed, <quote>I am
                        loath,</quote> he said, <quote> to tell concerning my countrymen what may
                        discredit them. Still I do not come to charge them with having committed any
                        crime, but to put you on your <pb n="p.341"/> guard lest they should commit
                        one. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The disposition <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 491</note> of our people is far
                        more fickle than I could wish. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Many
                        disasters have taught us the truth of this, since it is not to our own
                        merit, but to your patience, that we owe our preservation. A great crowd of
                        Volsci is now in Rome; there are games; the citizens will be intent upon the
                        spectacle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I remember what the Sabine
                        youths did in this City on the same opportunity arising; I tremble lest
                        something ill-advised and rash may happen. It has seemed to me that both on
                        our account and on yours I ought to tell you this beforehand, consuls.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For my own part I intend to go home at
                        once, lest being on the spot I might be implicated in some act or word and
                        be compromised. </quote> With this he departed. The consuls laid before the
                    senate this vague warning which came from so reliable a source. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> It was the source, as often happens, rather than the story,
                    which induced them to take precautions, even though they might prove
                    superfluous. The senate decreed that the Volsci should leave the City, and
                    heralds were sent about to command them all to depart before nightfall.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At first they were stricken with a great
                    alarm, as they hurried this way and that to the houses of their hosts to get
                    their things. But when they had started, their hearts swelled with indignation,
                    that like malefactors and polluted persons, they should have been driven off
                    from the games at a time of festival, and excluded, in a way, from intercourse
                    with men and gods. <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As they journeyed on in an almost unbroken
                    line, Tullius, who had gone ahead, arrived before them at the source of the
                    Ferentina. There, when any of their chief men arrived, he met them with words of
                    complaint and <pb n="p.343"/> indignation. These leaders, eagerly drinking in
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 491</note>
                    words with which he ministered to their anger, he conducted and, thanks to their
                    influence, the rest of the throng also, to a field which lay below the road.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There he launched out upon a speech like a
                    general's harangue. <quote>Though you should forget all else,</quote> he cried,
                        <quote> the ancient wrongs done by the Roman People and the disasters that
                        have overtaken the Volscian race, with what feelings, pray, can you bear the
                        insult which this day has brought to us, making our humiliation serve as the
                        opening of their festival? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Or did you not
                        feel that they were triumphing over you to-day? That you furnished a
                        spectacle to everybody when you departed —to the citizens, to the strangers,
                        to all the neighbouring nations? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That your
                        wives and children were made a mock in the eyes of the world? What of those
                        who heard the words of the herald? What of those who saw us going away? What
                        of those who have met this ignominious procession? What think you they all
                        supposed, but that we were certainly attainted of some sin; that because,
                        were we to be present at the spectacle, we should pollute the games and
                        incur the god's displeasure —for that reason we were being expelled from the
                        seat of the righteous and from their gathering and their council? <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Moreover, does it not occur to you that we are
                        alive because we hastened to depart? —if, indeed, this is a departure and
                        not rather a flight. And this City —do you not regard it as a city of
                        enemies, when if you had delayed there a single day, you would all have had
                        to die? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> War has been declared upon you,
                        and greatly shall they rue it who have been responsible, if you are men.
                    </quote> So, their spontaneous anger fanned to a <pb n="p.345"/> flame, they
                    dispersed to their several homes, and, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 491</note> every man arousing his own people, they
                    brought about a revolt of the entire Volscian name. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As generals for this war the nations all <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 488</note> agreed in
                    choosing Attius Tullius and Gnaeus Marcius, the Roman exile, who inspired rather
                    more hope than did his colleague. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This hope he
                    by no means disappointed, so that it was easy to see that Rome's commanders were
                    a greater source of strength to her than her armies were. Marching first to
                    Circei, he drove out the Roman colonists from that city and turned it over, thus
                    liberated, to the Volsci. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He took Satricum,
                    Longula, Polusca, and Corioli, places which the Romans had recently acquired.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then recovered Lavinium, and then,
                    passing over by cross-roads into the Latin Way, captured in succession Corbio,
                    Vetelia, Trebium, Labici, and Pedum. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From
                    Pedum he finally led his army against Rome and, pitching his camp at the
                    Cluilian Trenches, five miles from the City, laid waste the Roman territory from
                    that base, sending out guards with the pillagers to preserve intact the farms of
                    the patricians, whether from anger at the plebs, or to sow dissension between
                    them and the Fathers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And no doubt it would
                    have sprung up, so vehemently did the tribunes seek by their <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> accusations to rouse the already headstrong commons against
                    the nation's leaders, but dread of invasion, the strongest bond of harmony,
                    tended to unite their feelings, however they might suspect and dislike one
                    another. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this one point they were unable to
                    agree, that the senate and the consuls saw no hope anywhere but in arms, while
                    the plebs preferred anything to war. Spurius Nautius and Sextus <pb n="p.347"/>
                    Furius were now consuls. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy implies
                        that they were not the immediate successors of the consuls for 491, and in
                        fact he seems to have omitted two sets, Q. Sulpicius Camerinus and Serg.
                        Larcius Flavus (490), and C. Julius Iulus and P. Pinarius Rufus (489),
                        though at III. xxxiii. 1 and v. liv. 5 he reckons in these two years. The
                        missing names are supplied by Dion. Hal. vii. 68 and viii. 1. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> While they were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 488</note> reviewing their levies and
                    distributing garrisons about the walls and the other places where they had seen
                    fit to place pickets and sentries, a great multitude of people demanding peace
                    first terrified them with their rebellious clamour, and then forced them to call
                    the senate together and propose the sending of envoys to Gnaeus Marcius. The
                    Fathers consented to propose it when they saw that the plebeians were growing
                    discouraged, and ambassadors were sent to Marcius to treat for peace. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Stern was the answer they brought back. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> If the land of the Volsci were restored to them the
                    question of peace could be taken up; if the Romans wished to enjoy the spoils of
                    war without doing anything, he would forget neither the wrong his
                    fellow-citizens had done him nor the kindness of his hosts, but would strive to
                    show that exile had quickened his courage, not broken it. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> When the same envoys were sent back a second time, they
                    were denied admittance to the camp. Even priests, wearing the appropriate
                    fillets, are said to have gone as suppliants to the enemy's camp, where they
                    were no more able than the envoys had been to alter the determination of
                    Marcius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the married women gathered in large <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 488-487</note>
                    numbers at the house of Veturia, the mother of Coriolanus, and Volumnia, his
                    wife. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whether this was public policy or
                    woman's fear I cannot find out; in any case they prevailed with them that both
                    Veturia, an aged woman, and Volumnia should take the two little sons of Marcius
                    and go with them to the camp of the enemy; and that, since the swords of the men
                    could not defend the City, the women should defend it with their prayers and
                    tears. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they reached <pb n="p.349"/> the
                    camp, and the word came to Coriolanus that a <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 488-487</note> great company of women
                    was at hand, at first, as might have been expected of one whom neither the
                    nation's majesty could move, as represented in its envoys, nor the awfulness of
                    religion, as conveyed to heart and eye by the persons of her priests, he showed
                    even greater obduracy in resisting women's tears. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then one of his friends, led by Veturia's conspicuous
                    sadness to single her out from amongst the other women, as she stood between her
                    son's wife and his babies, said: <quote>Unless my eyes deceive me, your mother
                        is here and your wife and children.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Coriolanus started up like a madman from his
                    seat, and running to meet his mother would have embraced her, but her entreaties
                    turned to anger, and she said: <quote> Suffer me to learn, before I accept your
                        embrace, whether I have come to an enemy or a son; whether I am a captive or
                        a mother in your camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Is it this to which
                        long life and an unhappy old age have brought me, that I should behold in
                        you an exile and then an enemy? Could you bring yourself to ravage this
                        country, which gave you birth and reared you? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Did not your anger fall from you, no matter how hostile
                        and threatening your spirit when you came, as you passed the boundary? Did
                        it not come over you, when Rome lay before your eyes: ' Within those walls
                        are my home and my gods, my mother, my wife, and my children?' <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> So then, had I not been a mother Rome would not
                        now be besieged! Had I no son I should have died a free woman, in a free
                        land! <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But I can have nothing now to suffer
                        which could be more disgraceful to you or more miserable for myself; nor,
                        wretched though I am, shall I be so for long: it is these you must consider,
                        for whom, if you keep on, untimely death or <pb n="p.351"/> long enslavement
                        is in store. </quote> The embraces of his <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 488-487</note> wife and children,
                    following this speech, and the tears of the entire company of women, and their
                    lamentations for themselves and their country, at last broke through his
                    resolution. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He embraced his family and sent
                    them back, and withdrew his forces from before the City. Having then led his
                    army out of Rome's dominions he is said to have perished beneath the weight of
                    resentment which this act caused, by a death which is variously described. I
                    find in Fabius, by far the oldest authority, that Coriolanus lived on to old
                    age. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At least he reports that this saying was
                    often on his lips, that exile was a far more wretched thing when one was old.
                    There was no envy of the fame the women had earned, on the part of the men of
                    Rome —so <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> free was life in those days from
                    disparagement of another's glory —and to preserve its memory the temple of
                    Fortuna Muliebris was built and dedicated. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For another account of Coriolanus, see Dion. Hal. viii.
                        12 and viii. 17-56. </note>
                </p>
                <p> Afterwards the Volsci again invaded Roman soil, in conjunction with the Aequi,
                    but these would no longer put up with Attius Tullius for their general.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Whereupon the dispute as to whether the
                    Volsci or the Aequi should furnish a commander for the allied army, led to a
                    quarrel, and this to a bloody battle. There the good fortune of the Roman People
                    destroyed two hostile armies in one struggle, which was no less ruinous than it
                    was obstinately fought. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The consulship of Titus Sicinius and Gaius
                    Aquilius. Sicinius got the Volscian war for his command, and Aquilius that with
                    the Hernici —for they too were up in arms. This year the Hernici were conquered,
                    while the campaign against the Volsci was indecisive. </p>
                <pb n="p.353"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Spurius Cassius and Proculus Verginius were
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 486-485</note>
                    then made consuls. A treaty was struck with the Hernici, and two-thirds of their
                    land was taken from them. Of this the consul Cassius proposed to divide one half
                    amongst the Latins and the other half amongst the plebeians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> To this gift he wished to add some part of that land which,
                    he charged, was held by individuals, although it belonged to the state.
                    Whereupon many of the Fathers, being themselves in possession of the land, took
                    fright at the danger which threatened their interests. But the senators were
                    also concerned on public grounds, namely, that the consul by his largesses
                    should be building up an influence perilous to liberty. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This was the first proposal for agrarian legislation, and
                    from that day to within living memory it has never been brought up without
                    occasioning the most serious disturbances. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    other consul resisted the largess, and the Fathers supported him; nor were the
                    commons solidly against him, for to begin with, they had taken offence that the
                    bounty had been made general, being extended to include allies as well as
                    citizens; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and again, they often heard the
                    consul Verginius declare in his speeches, as though he read the future, that
                    destruction lurked in the gift proposed by his colleague; that those lands would
                    bring servitude to the men who should receive them, and were being made a road
                    to monarchy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For what reason had there been,
                    he asked, in including the allies and the Latin name, and in restoring to the
                    Hernici, who had been enemies a short time before, a third of the land which had
                    been taken from them, if it were not that these tribes might have Cassius in the
                    room of Coriolanus for their captain? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Popular
                        <pb n="p.355"/> favour now began to go over to the opponent and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 486-485</note> vetoer
                    of the land-legislation. Each consul then began, as if vying with the other, to
                    pamper the plebs. Verginius said that he would permit lands to be assigned,
                    provided they were assigned to none but Roman citizens. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Cassius, having by his proposed agrarian grants made a bid
                    for the support of the allies and thereby lowered himself in the eyes of the
                    Romans, desired to regain the affection of his fellow-citizens by another
                    donation, and proposed that the money received from the Sicilian corn should be
                    paid back to the people. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But this the people
                    spurned, as a downright attempt to purchase regal power; to such an extent did
                    their instinctive suspicion of monarchy render them scornful of his gifts, as if
                    they had possessed a superfluity of everything; and Cassius had no sooner laid
                    down his office than he was condemned and executed, as all authorities agree.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There are those who say that his father
                    was responsible for his punishment: that he tried the case in his house, and
                    that, after causing his son to be scourged and put to death, he consecrated to
                    Ceres his personal property, from the proceeds of which a statue was made and
                    inscribed <quote>the gift of the Cassian family.</quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I find in certain authors, and this is the
                    more credible account, that the quaestors Caeso Fabius and Lucius Valerius
                    brought him to trial for treason, and that he was found guilty by judgment of
                    the people and his house pulled down by popular decree. Its site is now the open
                    space in front of the temple of Tellus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But
                    whether it was a domestic or a state trial, he was condemned in the consulship
                    of Servius Cornelius and Quintus Fabius. </p>
                <pb n="p.357"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was not long before the people forgot <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 484-483</note> the
                    anger they had felt against Cassius. The inherent attractiveness of the agrarian
                    legislation appealed to them on its own account, when its author had been
                    removed, and their desire for it was enhanced by the meanness of the Fathers,
                    who after the defeat in that year of the Volsci and the Aequi defrauded the
                    soldiers of their booty. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whatever was taken
                    from the enemy Fabius sold and placed the proceeds in the public treasury. The
                    Fabian name was hateful to the plebs, on the last consul's account; nevertheless
                    the patricians succeeded in procuring the election of Caeso Fabius to that
                    office, along with Lucius Aemilius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This
                    increased the rancour of the plebeians, and by their seditions at home they
                    brought about a foreign war. The war then caused domestic strife to be
                    interrupted, while with one mind and purpose patricians and plebeians met the
                    rebellious Volsci and Aequi and, led by Aemilius, defeated them in a successful
                    action. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Yet more of the enemy perished in
                    flight than in the battle, so relentlessly did the cavalry pursue their routed
                    forces. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Castor's temple was dedicated the same
                    year, on the fifteenth of July. It had been vowed during the Latin war by
                    Postumius, the dictator. His son, being made duumvir for this special purpose,
                    dedicated it. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The temple was erected
                        in honour of both Castor and Pollux, but was commonly referred to by the
                        name of the former alone ( <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Cicero, <hi
                            rend="italics">Mil.</hi> 91). The <hi rend="italics">duumviri</hi> were
                        a committee of two, appointed to oversee the construction and dedication of
                        a temple when the man who had vowed it died without accomplishing his task.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The desires of the plebs were this year again
                    excited by the charms of the land-law. The tribunes of the plebs endeavoured to
                    recommend their democratic office by a democratic law, while the senators, who
                    thought there was frenzy enough and to spare in the populace, without rewarding
                    it, shuddered at <pb n="p.359"/> the thought of land-grants and encouragements
                    to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 484-483</note>
                    rashness. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The most strenuous of leaders were
                    at hand for the senatorial opposition, in the persons of the consuls. Their
                    party was therefore victorious and not only won an immediate success but,
                    besides, elected as consuls for the approaching year Marcus Fabius, Caeso's
                    brother, and one whom, on account of the prosecution of Spurius Cassius, the
                    people hated even more, namely, Lucius Valerius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> This year also there was a conflict with the tribunes. Nothing came of the
                    legislation, and its supporters fell into contempt, from boasting of a measure
                    which they could not carry through. The Fabii were thence-forward held in great
                    repute, after their three successive consulships, which had all without
                    interruption been subjected to the proof of struggles with the tribunes;
                    accordingly the office, as if well invested, was permitted to remain some time
                    in that family. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the next four
                        years, making seven successive years in all, the Fabii were represented in
                        the consulate. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> War then broke out with Veii, and the Volsci
                    revolted. But for foreign wars there was almost a superabundance of resources,
                    and men misused them in quarrelling amongst themselves. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> To increase the general anxiety which was now felt,
                    portents implying the anger of the gods were of almost daily occurrence in the
                    City and the country. For this expression of divine wrath no other reason was
                    alleged by the soothsayers, when they had enquired into it both officially and
                    privately, sometimes by inspecting entrails and sometimes by observing the
                    flight of birds, than the failure duly to observe the rites of religion.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These alarms at length resulted in the
                    condemnation of Oppia, a Vestal virgin, for unchastity, and her punishment. </p>
                <pb n="p.361"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius and Gaius Julius were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 482-480</note> then
                    made consuls. This year there was no less discord at home, and the menace of war
                    was greater. The Aequi took up arms, and the Veientes even made a foray into
                    Roman territory. During the increasing anxiety occasioned by these campaigns
                    Caeso Fabius and Spurius Furius were elected to the consulship. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Ortona, a Latin city, was being besieged by the Aequi;
                    while the Veientes, who by this time had their fill of rapine, were threatening
                    to attack Rome itself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These alarms, though
                    they should have restrained the animosity of the plebeians, actually heightened
                    it; and they resumed their custom of refusing service, though not of their own
                    initiative; for it was Spurius Licinius, tribune of the plebs, who, deeming that
                    the moment had come for forcing a land-law on the patricians by the direst
                    necessity, had undertaken to obstruct the preparations for war. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But he drew upon his own head all the odium attaching to
                    the tribunician office, nor did the consuls inveigh against him more fiercely
                    than did his own colleagues, and with their help the consuls held a levy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Armies were enlisted for two wars at the
                    same time; the command of one, which was to invade the Aequi, was given to
                    Fabius, while with the other Furius was to oppose the Veientes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Against the Veientes nothing worth recording was
                    accomplished; and in the Aequian campaign Fabius had somewhat more trouble with
                    his fellow-Romans than with the enemy. That one man, the consul himself,
                    preserved the state, which the army in its hatred of the consul would, so far as
                    it was able, have betrayed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For when the
                    consul, besides the many other instances of good generalship which he displayed
                    in <pb n="p.363"/> preparing for the war and in his conduct of it, had so <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 482-480</note> drawn
                    up the battle-line that a charge of the cavalry alone sufficed to rout the
                    enemy's army, the foot refused to pursue the flying foe; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> nor could even their own sense of guilt —to say nothing of
                    the exhortation of their hated general, —nor even the thought of the immediate
                    disgrace to all, and the danger they must presently incur if the enemy should
                    recover his courage, compel them to quicken their pace, or, if nothing else, to
                    stand in their ranks. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Contrary to orders they
                    retreated and returned to their camp, in such dejection that you would have
                    supposed them beaten, now uttering execrations against their leader and now
                    against the efficient services of the horse. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Ruinous though their example was, the general found no remedy for it; so true is
                    it that noble minds are oftener lacking in the qualities by which men govern
                    their fellow-citizens than in those by which they conquer an enemy. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The consul returned to Rome, having purchased more
                    hatred of his irritated and embittered soldiers than won increase in military
                    fame. Nevertheless the Fathers held out for the retention of the consulship in
                    the Fabian family. Marcus Fabius was the man they elected, and they gave him
                    Gnaeus Manlius as a colleague. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year also had a tribune who advocated
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> a
                    land-law, Tiberius Pontificius. He set out on the same path that Spurius
                    Licinius had trodden, as though Licinius had been successful, and for a time
                    obstructed the levy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senators were again
                    thrown into consternation, but Appius Claudius told them that the tribunician
                    power had been overcome the year before, actually for the time being, and
                    potentially <pb n="p.365"/> for ever, since a way had been discovered for <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> employing
                    its resources to its own undoing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For there
                    would always be some tribune who would be willing to gain a personal victory
                    over his colleague, and obtain the favour of the better element, while doing the
                    nation a service. There would be a number of tribunes, if a number should be
                    needed, who would be ready to help the consuls; and a single one was enough,
                    though opposed to all the rest. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Only let the
                    consuls, and the leading senators as well, make a point of winning over, if not
                    all, at any rate some of the tribunes to the state and the senate. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Acting on the instructions of Appius, the Fathers
                    began as a class to address the tribunes in a courteous and kindly manner; and
                    those who were of consular rank, when it happened that any of them had any
                    private claim upon an individual tribune, brought it about, in part by personal
                    influence, in part by political, that those officials were disposed to use their
                    powers for the good of the state; and four of them, as against one who would
                    have hindered the general good, assisted the consuls to hold the muster. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The army then set out for a war with the
                    Veientes, <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> to whose help forces had rallied
                    from every quarter of Etruria, not so much roused by goodwill towards the men of
                    Veii as by hopes that civil discord might effect the downfall of the Roman
                    state. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And indeed the leading men in the
                    councils of all the Etrurian peoples were wrathfully complaining that there
                    would be no end to the power of the Romans unless factional quarrels should set
                    them to fighting amongst themselves. They asserted that this was the only
                    poison, the only decay which had been found to work upon <pb n="p.367"/> opulent
                    states, so as to make great empires transitory. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For a long time the Romans had withstood this
                    evil, thanks partly to the prudence of the senate, partly to the patience of the
                    plebs; but they had now come to a crisis. Two states had been created out of
                    one: each faction had its own magistrates, its own laws. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At first, though they had a way of fiercely opposing the
                    levies, yet when war began they had obeyed their generals. No matter what the
                    condition of things in the City, so long as military discipline held it had been
                    possible to make a stand; but now the fashion of disobeying magistrates was
                    following the Roman soldier even to his camp. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    In their latest war, when the army was already drawn up for battle, and at the
                    very instant of conflict, they had with one accord actually handed over the
                    victory to the conquered Aequi, had deserted their standards, had left their
                    general on the field, and had returned, against his orders, to their camp.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Assuredly if her enemies pressed forward
                    they could vanquish Rome by means of her own soldiers. There needed nothing more
                    than to make a declaration and a show of war; Fate and the gods would of their
                    own will do the rest. Such were the hopes which had led the Etruscans to take up
                    arms, after many a shifting hazard of defeat and victory. <milestone n="45"
                        unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman consuls also felt that they had
                    nothing else to dread but their own forces and their own arms. The recollection
                    of the heinous example set in the last war deterred them from offering battle in
                    a situation where they would be in danger from two armies at the same time.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly they kept within their camp,
                    restrained by the thought of so grave a peril: time and circumstances would
                    perhaps assuage the anger of the men <pb n="p.369"/> and bring them to their
                    senses. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Their enemies the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> Veientes
                    and the other Etruscans were for that reason the more in haste to act; they
                    attempted to provoke the Romans to fight, at first by riding up to their camp
                    and challenging them to come out, and finally, when they gained nothing by this,
                    by shouting insults both at the consuls themselves and at the army. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> They said that their pretended want of harmony
                    amongst themselves had been resorted to in order to conceal their fear, and that
                    the consuls distrusted the courage of their men even more than their loyalty; it
                    was a strange kind of mutiny where armed men were silent and inactive.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To these taunts they added others upon the
                    newness of their race and origin, partly false and partly true. This abuse,
                    noisily uttered beneath the very rampart and the gates, was endured
                    unconcernedly enough by the consuls. But the inexperienced rank and file,
                    stirred now by indignation and now by shame, were diverted from the thought of
                    their domestic troubles; they were unwilling that their enemies should go
                    unpunished; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> they were unwilling that the
                    patricians, that the consuls should obtain a success; hatred of the foe
                    contended in their bosoms with hatred of their fellow-citizens. At length the
                    former feeling got the upper hand, so proud and insolent was the jeering of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They gathered in crowds at the
                    praetorium, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The headquarters of the
                        consul, who was originally called praetor. </note> demanded battle,
                    requested that the signal should be given. The consuls, as though considering
                    the matter, put their heads together and conferred for a long time. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They desired to fight, but it was needful to keep
                    back their desire and conceal it, that by opposition and delay they might
                    stimulate to fury the already eager soldiery. The men were therefore told that
                    the <pb n="p.371"/> thing was premature, that the time for battle had <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> not yet
                    come; that they must keep within the camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Then the consuls issued an order to abstain from fighting, declaring that if any
                    man fought without orders they should treat him as an enemy. Dismissed with
                    these words, the less inclination the soldiers discovered in the consuls the
                    greater became their own eagerness for the fray. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> They were still further exasperated by the enemy, who were
                    much bolder even than before, when the consuls' determination not to fight
                    became known: it was clear that they could insult the Romans with impunity;
                    their soldiers were not trusted with weapons, the affair would culminate in
                    absolute mutiny, and the end of the Roman power had come. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Relying on these convictions, they charged up to the gates,
                    flung gibes at their defenders, and scarcely refrained from assaulting the camp.
                    At this the Romans could no longer brook their insults; from all over the camp
                    they came running to the consuls. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> There were
                    no more cautious requests, preferred through the chief centurions, but on all
                    sides arose a general clamour. The time was ripe; nevertheless the consuls hung
                    back. Then Fabius, when his colleague, beginning to fear mutiny, was on the
                    point of yielding to the growing tumult, commanded silence by a trumpet-blast
                    and said: <quote> I know, Gnaeus Manlius, that these men have the power to
                        conquer, but their will to do so I know not; and for this they are
                        themselves to blame. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I am therefore
                        resolved and determined not to give the signal unless they swear that they
                        will return victorious from this engagement. Once, in a battle, the soldiers
                        betrayed a Roman consul: they will never betray the gods. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> There was a centurion named <pb n="p.373"/>
                    Marcus Flavoleius, who had been among the foremost <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> in demanding battle.
                        <quote>I will return victorious from the field, Marcus Fabius,</quote> he
                    cried, and invoked the wrath of Father Jupiter, Mars Gradivus, and the other
                    gods, if he failed to keep his vow. The same pledge was then taken in order by
                    the entire army, each man invoking its penalties upon himself. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> When they had sworn, the signal sounded. They armed and
                    entered the fight, angry and confident. Now let the Etruscans fling their
                    taunts! <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Now —they all cried —now, when they
                    were armed, let the lip-bold enemy face them! On that day they all showed
                    splendid courage, both commoners and nobles, but the Fabian name was especially
                    distinguished. In the course of many political struggles they had estranged the
                    plebs, and they resolved to regain their goodwill in that battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The line was drawn up, nor did the Veientes
                    and the Etruscan levies shun the encounter. They felt almost certain that the
                    Romans would no more fight with them than they had fought with the Aequi. That
                    they might even be guilty of some greater enormity, exasperated as they were,
                    and possessed of a critical opportunity, was not too much to hope. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> But it turned out quite otherwise. For there had
                    never been a war when the Romans went into battle with a keener hostility —so
                    embittered had they been, on the one hand by the enemy's insults, on the other
                    by the procrastination of the consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    Etruscans had barely had time to deploy when their enemies, who in the first
                    excitement' had rather cast their javelins at random than fairly aimed them,
                    were already come to sword-strokes at close quarters, where fighting is the
                    fiercest. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Fabian clan was <pb n="p.375"/>
                    conspicuous among the foremost, a spectacle and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> encouragement to their
                    fellow-citizens. One of them, the Quintus Fabius who had been consul three years
                    before, was leading the attack on the closely marshalled Veientes, when a
                    Tuscan, exulting in his strength and skill at arms, caught him unawares in the
                    midst of a crowd of his enemies and drove his sword through his breast. As the
                    blade was withdrawn Fabius fell headlong upon his wound. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> It was but the fall of one man, but both armies felt it;
                    and the Romans were giving way at that point, when Marcus Fabius the consul
                    leaped over the prostrate corpse and, covering himself with his target, cried,
                        <quote> Was this your oath, men, that you would return to your camp in
                        flight? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Do you then fear the most
                        dastardly of foes more than Jupiter and Mars, by whom you swore? But I,
                        though I have sworn no oath, will either return victorious or fall fighting
                        here by you, Quintus Fabius! </quote> To this speech of the consul Caeso
                    Fabius, consul of the year before, made answer, <quote> Think you that your
                        words will persuade them to fight, brother? <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> The gods will persuade them, by whom they have sworn. And let us, as is
                        meet for nobles, as is worthy of the name of Fabius, kindle by fighting
                        rather than by exhortation the courage of our soldiers! </quote> With that
                    the two Fabii rushed into the press with levelled spears and carried the whole
                    line forward with them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thus the fortune of the day was retrieved in
                    one part of the field. On the other wing Gnaeus Manlius the consul was urging on
                    the fight with no less vigour, when almost the same thing happened. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For as Quintus Fabius had done on the <pb n="p.377"/>
                    other flank, so here the consul Manlius was personally <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> leading the attack upon
                    the enemy, whom he had almost routed, for his soldiers followed him valiantly,
                    when he was severely wounded and retired from the fighting line. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> His men believed him to be dead, and faltered; and
                    they would have yielded the position, had not the other consul ridden up at a
                    gallop, with some few troops of horse, and calling out that his colleague was
                    alive, and that he himself had defeated and routed the other wing and was come
                    to help them, in that way put a stop to their wavering. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Manlius also showed himself among them, helping to restore
                    the line; and the soldiers, recognizing the features of their two consuls,
                    plucked up courage. At the same time the battle-line of the enemy was now less
                    strong, for, relying on their excess of numbers, they had withdrawn their
                    reserves and dispatched them to storm the Roman camp. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There, having forced an entrance without encountering much
                    opposition, they were frittering away their time, their thoughts more taken up
                    with the booty than with the battle, when the Roman reserves, which had been
                    unable to withstand the first onset, sent word to the consuls how things stood,
                    and then closed up their ranks, returned to the praetorium, and of themselves
                    resumed the battle. Meanwhile Manlius the consul had ridden back to the camp,
                    and by posting men at all the gates had cut off the enemy's egress. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> In desperation at this turn the Etruscans had been
                    inflamed to the point rather of madness than of recklessness. For when, as they
                    rushed in whatever direction there seemed a prospect of escape, they had made
                    several charges to no purpose, one band of youths made a dash at the consul
                    himself, whose arms made him <pb n="p.379"/> conspicuous. Their first discharge
                    of javelins was parried <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 480</note> by the soldiers who surrounded him, but after that there
                    was no withstanding their violence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul
                    fell, mortally wounded, and all about him fled. The Etruscans grew more reckless
                    than before; the Romans were driven, quaking with terror, right across the camp,
                    and their case would have been desperate, had <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    not the lieutenants caught up the body of the consul and opened a way for the
                    enemy by one of the gates. By that they burst forth, and escaping in a
                    disordered column, fell in the way of the other, the victorious consul, where
                    they were again cut to pieces, and dispersed in all directions. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> A victory of great importance had been won, but it was
                    saddened by the death of two so famous men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The consul therefore made answer to the senate, when it would have voted him a
                    triumph, that if the army could triumph without its general, its services in
                    that war had been so remarkable that he would readily grant his consent; as for
                    himself, when his family was in mourning for the death of Quintus Fabius his
                    brother, and the state was half orphaned by the loss of the other consul, he
                    would not accept a laurel which was blighted with national and private sorrow.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No triumph ever celebrated was more
                    famous than was his refusal to accept a triumph, so true is it that a seasonable
                    rejection of glory sometimes but increases it. The consul then solemnized, one
                    after the other, the funerals of his colleague and his brother, and pronounced
                    the eulogy of each; but while yielding their meed of praise to them, he gained
                    for himself the very highest praises. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Nor was
                    he unmindful of that policy which he had adopted in the beginning of his
                    consulship, of winning the affections of the plebs, but billeted the <pb
                        n="p.381"/> wounded soldiers on the patricians, to be cared for. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 480</note> To the
                    Fabii he assigned the largest number, nor did they anywhere receive greater
                    attention. For this the Fabii now began to enjoy the favour of the people, nor
                    was this end achieved by aught but a demeanour wholesome for the state. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senators were now therefore not <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 479</note> more
                    forward than the plebeians in choosing Caeso Fabius to be consul, along with
                    Titus Verginius. On taking office his first concern was neither war nor the
                    raising of troops nor anything else, save that the prospect of harmony which had
                    been already partly realized should ripen at the earliest possible moment into a
                    good understanding between the patricians and the plebs. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore proposed at the outset of his term that before
                    one of the tribunes should rise up and advocate a land-law, the Fathers
                    themselves should anticipate him by making it their own affair and bestowing the
                    conquered territory upon the plebs with the utmost impartiality; for it was
                    right that they should possess it by whose blood and toil it had been won.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senators scorned the proposal, and
                    some even complained that too much glory was spoiling and dissipating that
                    vigorous intellect which Caeso had once possessed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In the sequel there were no outbreaks of strife and faction
                    in the City, but the Latins were plagued with incursions of the Aequi. Thither
                    Caeso was dispatched with an army, and passed over into the Aequians' own
                    country to lay it waste. The Aequi retired to their towns and kept within their
                    walls. For this reason there was no memorable battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the Veientes inflicted a defeat on the
                    Romans owing to the rashness of the other consul; and the <pb n="p.383"/> army
                    would have been destroyed if Caeso Fahius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 479</note> had not come, in the nick
                    of time, to its rescue. Thenceforward there was neither peace nor war with the
                    Veientes, but something very like freebooting. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    In the face of the Roman legions they would retreat into their city; when they
                    perceived the legions to be withdrawn they would make raids upon the fields,
                    evading war by a semblance of peace, and peace in turn by war. Hence it was
                    impossible either to let the whole matter go or to end it. Other wars, too, were
                    immediately threatening —like the one with the Aequi and the Volsci, who would
                    observe peace only so long as the suffering involved in their latest defeat was
                    passing away, —or were soon to be begun, by the always hostile Sabines and all
                    Etruria. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the enmity of the Veientes,
                    persistent rather than perilous, and issuing in insults oftener than in danger,
                    kept the Romans in suspense, for they were never permitted to forget it or to
                    turn their attention elsewhere. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the
                    Fabian clan went before the senate, and the consul said, speaking for the clan:
                        <quote> A standing body of defenders rather than a large one is required,
                        Conscript Fathers, as you know, for the war with Veii. Do you attend to the
                        other wars, and assign to the Fabii the task of opposing the Veientes. We
                        undertake that the majesty of the Roman name shall be safe in that quarter.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It is our purpose to wage this war as
                        if it were our own family feud, at our private costs: the state may dispense
                        with furnishing men and money for this cause. </quote> The thanks of the
                    Fathers were voted with enthusiasm. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    consul came out from the senate-house, and escorted by a column of the Fabii,
                    who had halted in the vestibule of the curia while awaiting <pb n="p.385"/> the
                    senate's decision, returned to his house. After <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 479</note> receiving the command to
                    present themselves armed next day at the consul's threshold, they dispersed to
                    their homes. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news spreads to every part of the City
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 479-478</note>
                    and the Fabii are lauded to the skies. Men tell how a single family has taken
                    upon its shoulders the burden of a state, how the war with Veii has been turned
                    over to private citizens and private arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If
                    there were two other clans of equal strength in the City, the one might
                    undertake the Volsci, the other the Aequi, and the Roman People might enjoy the
                    tranquillity of peace, while all the neighbouring nations were being subdued. On
                    the following day the Fabii arm and assemble at the designated place. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The consul, coming forth in the cloak of a general,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The crimson <hi rend="italics"
                            >paludamentum.</hi>
                    </note> sees his entire clan drawn up in his vestibule, and being received into
                    their midst gives the order to march. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Never
                    did an army march through the City less in number or more distinguished by the
                    applause and the wonder of men: three hundred and six soldiers, all patricians,
                    all of one blood, no one of whom you would have rejected as a leader, and who
                    would have made an admirable senate in any period, were going out to threaten
                    the existence of the Veientine nation with the resources of a single house.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They were followed by a throng partly made
                    up of people belonging to them, their kinsmen and close friends, whose thoughts
                    were busy with no mean matters, whether of hope or of fear, but with boundless
                    possibilities; partly of those who were moved with concern for the commonwealth,
                    and were beside themselves with enthusiasm and amazement. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Go,</quote> they cry, <quote> in your valour, go with good <pb n="p.387"
                        /> fortune, and crown your undertaking with success as <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 479-478</note> great! </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They bid them look forward to receiving
                    consulships at their hands for this work, and triumphs, and all rewards and all
                    honours. As they pass by the Capitol and the citadel and the other temples, they
                    beseech whatever gods present themselves to their eyes and their thoughts to
                    attend <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that noble band with blessings and
                    prosperity, and restore them soon in safety to their native land and their
                    kindred. Their prayers were uttered in vain. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Setting out by the Unlucky Way, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A
                        name afterwards given to the arch from the result of this expedition.
                    </note> the right arch of the Porta Carmentalis, they came to the river Cremera,
                    a position which seemed favourable for the erection of a fort. </p>
                <p> Lucius Aemilius and Gaius Servilius were then chosen consuls. And so long as
                    nothing more than plundering was afoot the Fabii were not only an adequate
                    garrison for the fort, but in all that region where the Tuscan territory marches
                    with the Roman they afforded universal security to their own countrymen and
                    annoyance to the enemy, by ranging along the border on both sides. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Then came a brief interruption to these
                    depredations, while the men of Veii, having called in an army from Etruria,
                    attacked the post on the Cremera, and the Roman legions, led thither by Lucius
                    Aemilius the consul, engaged them in a pitched battle; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> though in truth the Veientes had scarcely time to draw up a
                    battle-line, for at the first alarm, while the ranks were falling in behind the
                    standards and the reserves were being posted, a division of Roman cavalry made a
                    sudden charge on their flank and deprived them of the power not only of
                    attacking first, but even of standing their ground. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> And so they were driven back upon Saxa Rubra, where they
                    had their camp, and sued for peace. It <pb n="p.389"/> was granted, but their
                    instinctive fickleness caused <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 479-478</note> them to weary of the pact before the Roman
                    garrison was withdrawn from the Cremera. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Again the Fabii were pitted against the people
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 477</note> of
                    Veii. No preparations had been made for a great war, yet not only were raids
                    made upon farming lands, and surprise attacks upon raiding parties, but at times
                    they fought in the open field and in serried ranks; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and a single clan of the Roman People often carried off the
                    victory from that most mighty state, for those days, in all Etruria. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> At first the Veientes bitterly resented this; but
                    they presently adopted a plan, suggested by the situation, for trapping their
                    bold enemy, and they even rejoiced as they saw that the frequent successes of
                    the Fabii were causing them to grow more rash. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And so they now and then drove flocks in the way of the invaders, as if they had
                    come there by accident; and the country folk would flee from their farms and
                    leave them deserted; and rescuing parties of armed men, sent to keep off
                    pillagers, would flee before them in a panic more often feigned than real. By
                    this time the Fabii had conceived such scorn for the enemy that they believed
                    themselves invincible and not to be withstood, no matter what the place or time.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This confidence so won upon them that on
                    catching sight of some flocks at a distance from the Cremera, across a wide
                    interval of plain, they disregarded the appearance here and there of hostile
                    arms, and ran down to capture them. Their rashness carried them on at a swift
                    pace past an ambuscade which had been laid on both sides of their very road.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They had scattered this way and that and
                    were seizing the flocks, which had dispersed in all directions, as they do if
                    terrified, <pb n="p.391"/> when suddenly the ambush rose up, and enemies were
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 477</note> in
                    front and on every side of them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> First the
                    shout which echoed all along the Etruscan line filled them with consternation,
                    and then the javelins began to fall upon them from every quarter; and as the
                    Etruscans drew together and the Romans were now fenced in by a continuous line
                    of armed men, the harder the enemy pressed them the smaller was the space within
                    which they themselves were forced to <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> contract
                    their circle, a thing which clearly revealed both their own fewness and the vast
                    numbers of the Etruscans, whose ranks were multiplied in the narrow space.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Romans then gave up the fight which
                    they had been directing equally at every point, and all turned in one direction.
                    Thither, by dint of main strength and arms, they forced their way with a wedge.
                    Their road led up a gentle acclivity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There
                    they at first made a stand; presently, when their superior position had afforded
                    them time to breathe and to collect their spirits after so great a fright, they
                    actually routed the troops which were advancing to dislodge them; and a handful
                    of men, with the aid of a good position, were winning the victory, when the
                    Veientes who had been sent round by the ridge emerged upon the crest of the
                    hill, thus giving the enemy the advantage again. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The Fabii were all slain to a man, and their fort was
                    stormed. Three hundred and six men perished, as is generally agreed; one, who
                    was little more than a boy in years, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This was that Fabius, according to the legend, who was to become consul ten
                        years later! See III. X. </note> survived to maintain the Fabian stock, and
                    so to afford the very greatest help to the Roman People in its dark hours, on
                    many occasions, at home and in the field. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this disaster befel, Gaius Horatius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 477-476</note> and
                    Titus Menenius had begun their consulship. <pb n="p.393"/> Menenius was at once
                    sent out to confront the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 477-476</note> Etruscans, elated by their victory. Again the Roman
                    arms were unsuccessful, and Janiculum was taken by the enemy. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They would also have laid siege to Rome, which was
                    suffering not only from war but from a scarcity of corn —for the Etruscans had
                    crossed the Tiber —had not the consul Horatius been recalled from the Volscian
                    country; and so nearly did that invasion approach the very walls of the City
                    that battles were fought first at the temple of Hope, where the result was
                    indecisive, and again at the Colline Gate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There, although the advantage to the Roman side was but slight, still the
                    engagement restored their old-time spirit to the troops and made them the better
                    soldiers for the battles that were to come. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Aulus Verginius and Spurius Servilius were
                    made consuls. After the defeat the Veientes had suffered in the last fight, they
                    avoided a battle and took to pillaging. From Janiculum, as from a citadel, they
                    sent out expeditions far and wide into the territory of the Romans; there was no
                    security anywhere for flocks or country-folk. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    After a time they were caught by the same trick with which they had caught the
                    Fabii. Having pursued the flocks which had been driven out here and there on
                    purpose to lure them on, they plunged into an ambush, and as their numbers
                    exceeded those of the Fabii so did their losses. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> This disaster threw them into a violent rage, which proved the cause and the
                    beginning of a greater reverse. For they crossed the Tiber in the night and
                    assaulted the camp of the consul Servilius. There they were routed with heavy
                    losses and regained Janiculum with difficulty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Forthwith the <pb n="p.395"/> consul himself crossed the Tiber and fortified a
                    camp <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 477-476</note>
                    beneath the hill. Next day at dawn, partly because he was emboldened by the
                    successful battle of the day before, but more because the want of corn drove him
                    to the rashest kind of measures, provided only they were speedy, he was
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> so reckless as to lead his army up
                    Janiculum to the enemy's camp, and after suffering a more disgraceful repulse
                    than he had administered the day before, owed his own rescue and that of his
                    army to the arrival of his colleague. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Caught
                    between two lines, the Etruscans turned their backs first on one and then on the
                    other, and were cut down with great slaughter. Thus the Veientine invasion was
                    defeated by a lucky temerity. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There came to the City with the return of
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 476-475</note>
                    peace a relaxation in the corn-market; for not only was grain imported from
                    Campania, but now that each had ceased to fear for his own future want, men
                    brought out the stores which they had concealed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> As a consequence of plenty and idleness a spirit of licence again began to
                    affect men's minds, and they began to seek at home for the old troubles which
                    were no longer to be met with abroad. The tribunes roused the plebs to madness
                    with their usual poison, a land-law. The Fathers resisted, but the tribunes
                    incited the people against them, not as a body merely, but as individuals.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Quintus Considius and Titus Genucius, the
                    proposers of the agrarian measure, cited Titus Menenius to appear for trial.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> What was the charge? Perhaps that
                        he had failed to support the Fabii; perhaps that he had lost Janiculum by
                        his incompetence. </note> He had incurred the dislike of the plebs owing to
                    the loss of the outpost on the Cremera, when he as consul had occupied a
                    permanent camp not far away; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and this
                    unpopularity was his undoing, though the senators exerted themselves in his
                    behalf no less <pb n="p.397"/> than they had done for Coriolanus, and though the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 476-475</note>
                    favour enjoyed by his father Agrippa had not yet passed away. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> In respect to the penalty the tribunes showed restraint;
                    though they had charged him with a capital offence, they fixed the fine of the
                    condemned at two thousand <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi> But it cost him his
                    life; they say that he could not endure the shame and grief, and from this cause
                    fell ill and died. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another man was then put upon his trial,
                    namely Spurius Servilius. He had laid down the consulship and been succeeded by
                    Gaius Nautius and Publius Valerius, when he was cited, in the very beginning of
                    the year, by the tribunes Lucius Caedicius and Titus Statius. Unlike Menenius,
                    he did not meet the attacks of the tribunes with entreaties, preferred by
                    himself or the senators, but with high confidence in his innocence and
                    popularity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He, too, was accused in connection
                    with the battle against the Etruscans at Janiculum. But the fiery courage of the
                    man had not been more in evidence in the nation's hour of peril than it was then
                    in his own, and he confuted not only the tribunes but the plebs, upbraiding
                    them, in a daring speech, with the condemnation and death of Menenius, to whose
                    father, he declared, the plebs formerly owed their restoration and the
                    possession of those very magistrates and laws which were the tools of their
                    cruelty. This boldness swept away the danger. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He was helped, too, by Verginius, his colleague, who, being called as a witness,
                    shared his own credit with Servilius. But the trial of Menenius stood him in
                    even better stead, so great a revulsion of feeling had set in. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Domestic strife was at an end; but war broke
                    out with the Veientes, with whom the Sabines had united their arms. Publius
                    Valerius the consul was <pb n="p.399"/> dispatched to Veii with an army to which
                    had been <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        476-475</note> added auxiliaries from the Latins and the Hernici. He at once
                    advanced upon the Sabine camp, which had been established in front of the walls
                    of their allies, and threw the enemy into such confusion that, while they were
                    running out in small groups, some one way and some another, to repel the attack
                    of the Romans, he captured the gate against which he had directed his first
                    assault. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> What followed within the stockade was
                    a massacre rather than a battle. The sounds of confusion in the camp penetrated
                    even to the city, and the frightened inhabitants ran hastily to their weapons,
                    as though Veii had been surprised. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some went
                    to the rescue of the Sabines, others assailed the Romans, who were wholly
                    preoccupied with the camp. For a moment the Romans were disconcerted and thrown
                    into disorder; then they, too, faced both ways and made a stand, and the horse
                    which the consul sent into the fight dispersed and routed the Etruscans.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In one and the same hour two armies, two
                    of the greatest and most powerful neighbouring nations, were defeated. </p>
                <p> While these victories were being won at Veii, the Volsci and the Aequi had
                    encamped on Latin soil, and had laid waste the country. These the Latins, acting
                    independently, with the assistance of the Hernici, but without either general or
                    aid from Rome, despoiled of their camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Immense booty, in addition to property of their own which they recovered, fell
                    into their hands. Nevertheless a consul, Gaius Nautius, was sent from Rome
                    against the Volsci. The precedent, I suppose, of allies waging wars, without a
                    Roman commander and army, by means of their own forces and their own strategy,
                    was not welcome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.401"/> There was no species of disaster or indignity which <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 476-475</note> was
                    not visited upon the Volsci, yet they could not be forced into giving battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Furius and Gaius Manlius were the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 474-473</note> next
                    consuls. To Manlius fell the command against the Veientes. But there was no war;
                    a truce for forty years was granted, at their solicitation, and corn and a
                    money-indemnity were exacted of them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    foreign peace was immediately succeeded by quarrels at home. The land-law with
                    which the tribunes goaded the plebs excited them to the pitch of madness. The
                    consuls, not a jot intimidated by the condemnation of Menenius, not a jot by the
                    danger of Servilius, resisted the measure with the utmost violence. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> As their term expired, Gnaeus Genucius, a plebeian
                    tribune, haled them to trial. </p>
                <p> Lucius Aemilius and Opiter Verginius entered upon the consulship. Vopiscus
                    Julius I find given as consul in certain annals, instead of Verginius. This year
                    —whoever its consuls were —Furius and Manlius went about among the people as men
                    accused, in garments of mourning, seeking out the younger patricians, as well as
                    the plebeians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They advised them, they warned
                    them to forbear from office-holding and the administration of the public
                    business; as for the consular fasces, the purple-bordered toga, and the curule
                    chair, —these they should regard in no other light than as the pageantry of
                    burial; for splendid insignia, like the fillets placed on victims, doomed the
                    wearer to death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But if the consulship was so
                    alluring to them, let them recognize at once that it had been fettered and
                    enslaved by the might of the tribunes; that the consul, as though an attendant
                    upon those officials, must be subject in all <pb n="p.403"/> he did to their
                    beck and call; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> if he should bestir <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 474-473</note>
                    himself, if he should show consideration for the patricians, if he should
                    believe that the state comprised any other element than the plebs —let him call
                    to mind the exile of Gnaeus Marcius, the condemnation of Menenius and his death.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Fired by these speeches, the senators
                    began to hold councils, no longer publicly, but in private, where the people
                    could not learn their plans. In these deliberations there was but one guiding
                    principle, that by fair means or foul the defendants must be got off. The more
                    truculent a suggestion was, the greater was the favour it evoked, and an agent
                    was not wanting for the most daring crime. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Well then, on the day of the trial the plebeians were in the Forum, on tiptoe
                    with expectation. At first they were filled with amazement because the tribune
                    did not come down; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> from his home: the Forum was lower than the
                        residential parts of Rome. </note> then, when at length his delay began to
                    look suspicious, they supposed he had been frightened away by the nobles, and
                    fell to complaining of his desertion and betrayal of the people's cause;
                    finally, those who had presented themselves at the tribune's vestibule brought
                    back word that he had been found dead in his house. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When this report had spread through all the gathering, the
                    crowd, like an army which takes to flight at the fall of its general, melted
                    away on every side. The tribunes were particularly dismayed, for the death of
                    their colleague warned them how utterly ineffectual to protect them were the
                    laws that proclaimed their sanctity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor did
                    the senators place a proper restraint upon their satisfaction; so far, indeed,
                    was anyone from repenting of the guilty deed that even the innocent desired to
                    be thought its authors, and men openly asserted that chastisement must be
                    employed to curb the power of the tribunes. </p>
                <pb n="p.405"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately following this pernicious victory
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 473</note> a
                    levy was proclaimed, which the timorousness of the tribunes allowed the consuls
                    to push through without ever a veto. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But this
                    time the commons were fairly roused to anger, more by the silence of the
                    tribunes than by the consuls' power. They declared that it was all up with their
                    liberty; that men had gone back to their old ways; that with Genucius the
                    tribunician power had suffered death and burial. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> They must adopt another course and other plans to resist the patricians; but
                    the only way was this: that the plebs should undertake their own defence, since
                    they had no one else to help them. Twenty-four lictors were all the retinue of
                    the consuls, and even these were plebeians. Nothing was more contemptible or
                    weaker, if there were any to contemn; it was every man's own imagination that
                    made them great and awe-inspiring. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They had
                    incited one another with arguments of this sort when the consuls sent a lictor
                    to arrest Volero Publilius, a plebeian, who, on the ground that he had been a
                    centurion, denied their right to make him a common soldier. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy mentions another instance of a
                        conscript's objecting to serve in a rank lower than that he had previously
                        held, in XLII. xxxiii. 3; but it does not appear that the men had any
                        prescriptive right in the matter. </note> Volero called upon the tribunes.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When no one came to aid him, the consuls
                    gave orders to strip the man and get out the rods. <quote>I appeal,</quote>
                    cried Volero, <quote> to the people, since the tribunes would rather a Roman
                        citizen should be scourged with rods before their eyes than themselves be
                        murdered in their beds by you. </quote> But the more boldly he shouted the
                    more roughly the lictor fell to tearing off his clothes and stripping him.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then Volero, who was himself a powerful
                    man and was helped by those he had called to his assistance, beat off the lictor
                    and, choosing the place where the uproar of his sympathisers <pb n="p.407"/> was
                    the angriest, plunged into the thick of the crowd, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 473</note> calling out, <quote> I
                        appeal, and implore the protection of the plebs; help, citizens! <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> help, fellow-soldiers! It is useless for you to
                        wait for the tribunes, who themselves stand in need of aid from you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In their excitement men made ready as if to
                    fight a battle, and it was evident that anything might happen, that nobody would
                    respect any right, whether public or private. The consuls, exposed to this
                    furious tempest, were quickly convinced of the insecurity of majesty when
                    unaccompanied with force. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The lictors were
                    roughly handled and their rods were broken, while the consuls themselves were
                    driven out of the Forum into the Curia, with no means of knowing how far Volero
                    might use his victory. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Afterwards, when the
                    uproar began to die away, they summoned the Fathers into the senate-house and
                    complained of the insults they had suffered, the violence of the plebs, and
                    Volero's outrageous conduct. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Though many
                    daring opinions were expressed, the wishes of the older men prevailed, who had
                    no mind to a conflict between an angry senate and a reckless plebs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Volero, having been taken into favour by <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 472-471</note> the
                    plebs, was at the next election made plebeian tribune for that year which had
                    Lucius Pinarius and Publius Furius for consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> And contrary to the expectation of all, who believed that he would employ his
                    tribuneship in persecuting the consuls of the preceding year, he set the general
                    welfare above his private grievance, and without attacking the consuls by so
                    much as a word, brought a bill before the people providing that plebeian
                    magistrates should be chosen in the tribal assembly. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> It is not clear how Livy supposed that these officials
                        had formerly been elected. Perhaps Volero merely aimed at securing by legal
                        sanction what the state had always recognized in practice, viz. that
                        plebeian magistrates should be chosen by none but plebeians. But this was
                        not Livy's view, as is clear from lviii. 1. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was no trivial matter which he proposed
                    under this form, which at <pb n="p.409"/> first sight appeared so harmless, but
                    one that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        472-471</note> completely deprived the patricians of the power of using
                    their clients' votes to select what tribunes they liked. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This measure was extremely welcome to the plebs; the
                    Fathers opposed it with all their might, yet the only effectual resistance —to
                    wit, a veto by some member of the tribunician college —neither consuls nor
                    nobles were sufficiently influential to command. Nevertheless the legislation,
                    which its very importance rendered difficult, was drawn out by party strife to
                    the end of the year. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The plebs re-elected
                    Volero tribune: the senators, thinking the quarrel was sure to proceed to
                    extremities, made Appius Claudius, son of Appius, consul, a man whose
                    unpopularity with the plebs and hostility towards them went back to the
                    struggles between their fathers. For colleague they gave him Titus Quinctius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The new year was no sooner begun than
                    discussion of the law took precedence of everything else, and it was urged not
                    only by its author, Volero, but by his colleague Laetorius as well, whose
                    advocacy of it was at once fresher and more acrimonious. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He was emboldened by the great reputation he enjoyed as a
                    soldier, since no one of that generation surpassed him in physical prowess.
                    While Volero spoke of nothing but the law, and forbore to inveigh against the
                    consuls' persons, Laetorius launched out into an arraignment of Appius and his
                    family, as most cruel and arrogant towards the Roman plebs. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> But when he strove to show that the patricians had elected,
                    not a consul, but an executioner, to harass and torture the plebeians, the
                    inexperienced tongue of the soldier was inadequate to express his audacity and
                    spirit. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Accordingly when words began to fail
                    him he cried, <pb n="p.411"/>
                    <quote> Since speech is not so easy for me, Quirites, as it is <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 472-471</note> to
                        make good what I have spoken, be at hand tomorrow. I will either die here in
                        your sight or carry through the law. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The tribunes were the first on the scene next
                    day, and possessed themselves of the rostra; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The word <hi rend="italics">templum</hi> might be
                        applied to any space duly marked off by augural ceremonies. Here it means
                        the speakers' platform in the <hi rend="italics">comitium.</hi>
                    </note> the consuls and nobles took their stand in the assembly, with the
                    purpose of obstructing the passage of the law. Laetorius ordered the removal of
                    all but those who were voting. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The youthful
                    nobles stayed where they were and would not give way at the officer's behest.
                    Then certain of them were ordered by Laetorius to be seized. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The consul Appius declared that the tribune had no
                    authority over anybody but a plebeian, seeing that he was not a magistrate of
                    the people, but of the plebs; and even if he were, he could not, consistently
                    with the custom of the Fathers, command the removal of anyone, by virtue of his
                    authority, since the formula ran thus: <quote>If it seems good to you, depart,
                        Quirites.</quote> It was an easy matter to throw Laetorius into a passion by
                    these contemptuous remarks about his rights. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    It was therefore in a blaze of anger that the tribune dispatched his attendant
                    to the consul; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> while the consul sent his
                    lictor to the tribune, crying out that Laetorius was a private citizen, without
                    power, and no magistrate; and the tribune would have been mishandled, had not
                    the whole assembly rallied fiercely to his support against the consul, while men
                    rushed into the Forum from all over the City, in an excited throng. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Still, Appius was obstinately holding out, despite
                    the fury of the tempest, and a sanguinary battle would have ensued, if
                    Quinctius, the other consul, had not entrusted the senators of consular rank
                    with the task of getting his colleague out <pb n="p.413"/> of the Forum, by
                    force, if they could not achieve <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 472-471</note> it otherwise; while he himself now
                    appealed to the raging populace with soothing entreaties, and now besought the
                    tribunes to dismiss the council. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Let them
                    give their anger time: time would not rob them of their power, but would add
                    wisdom to their strength; the Fathers would be subject to the people, and the
                    consul to the Fathers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was hard for Quinctius to still the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 471</note> plebs;
                    much harder for the senators to quiet the other consul. At length the council of
                    the plebs was adjourned, and the consuls convened the senate. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> At this meeting alternating hope and fear gave rise to
                    conflicting opinions. But in proportion as their passions cooled with the lapse
                    of time and gave way to deliberation, their minds more and more revolted from
                    the struggle; insomuch that they passed a vote of thanks to Quinctius, because
                    it was due to him that the quarrel had been abated. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They desired Appius to be content that the majesty of the
                    consul should be no greater than was compatible with harmony in the state,
                    pointing out that while tribunes and consuls were each striving to carry things
                    his own way there was no strength left in the nation at large, and the
                    commonwealth was torn and mangled, the question being rather in whose power it
                    was than how it might be safe. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Appius, on the
                    other hand, called gods and men to witness that the state was being betrayed
                    through cowardice, and abandoned; that it was not the consul who was failing the
                    senate, but the senate the consul; that harder terms were being accepted than
                    had been accepted on the Sacred Mount. Nevertheless he was borne down by the
                    senate's unanimity and held his peace. <pb n="p.415"/> The law was passed
                    without opposition. <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 471</note> for the first time tribunes were elected in
                    the tribal assembly. That their number was also increased by three, as if there
                    had been only two before, is stated by Piso. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    He also gives the names of the tribunes: Gnaeus Siccius, Lucius Numitorius,
                    Marcus Duillius, Spurius Icilius, Lucius Maecilius. </p>
                <p> While Rome was thus distracted, the Volsci and the Aequi began war. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> They had laid waste the fields in order that the
                    plebeians, if they should secede, might find a refuge with them. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> To <hi rend="italics">lay waste</hi>
                        Roman lands they must first <hi rend="italics">enter</hi> them, and the
                        purpose clause depends really upon this implied meaning of <hi
                            rend="italics">vastaverant.</hi>
                    </note> Then, when the matter was settled, they withdrew their camp. Appius
                    Claudius was sent against the Volsci; to Quinctius fell the command against the
                    Aequi. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In his conduct in the field Appius
                    displayed the same violence that he had shown in Rome, and it now had freer play
                    because it was not hampered by the tribunes. He hated the plebs with a hatred
                    that surpassed his father's: What? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Had he been
                    beaten by them? Was it in his consulship, who had been chosen as pre-eminently
                    fitted to resist the tribunician power, that a law had been passed which former
                    consuls had prevented, with less effort and by no means so much hope of success
                    on the part of the patricians? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His wrath and
                    indignation at this thought drove his fierce spirit to torment the army with a
                    savage exercise of authority. Yet he was unable by any violence to subdue them,
                    so deeply had their spirits drunk of opposition. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Sloth, idleness, neglect, and obstinacy were in all they did. Neither shame
                    nor fear restrained them. If he wished the column to advance more rapidly they
                    deliberately retarded their pace; <pb n="p.417"/> if he stood by to encourage
                    their work, they would <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 471</note> all relax the industry they had manifested of their own
                    accord. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In his presence they sunk their gaze;
                    as he passed by they cursed him under their breath; till that proud spirit,
                    which the hatred of the plebs had never broken, was at times disturbed.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After exhausting every species of severity
                    without effect, he would have no more to do with the men; the centurions, he
                    said, had corrupted the army, and he sometimes sneeringly dubbed them
                        <quote>tribunes of the plebs</quote> and <quote>Voleros.</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Every one of these circumstances was known to
                    the Volsci, and they pressed their enemy the harder, hoping that the Roman army
                    would exhibit the same spirited opposition to Appius which it had evinced
                    towards the consul Fabius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But Appius found
                    his men far more unruly than had Fabius; for not only were they unwilling to
                    conquer, as the Fabian army had been, but they wished to be conquered. Being
                    drawn out into battle-order, they basely fled and sought their camp; nor did
                    they make a stand until they saw the Volsci advancing against their
                    fortifications and inflicting a disgraceful slaughter upon their rearguard.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This compelled them to exert themselves
                    and fight, with the result that the enemy was dislodged from the stockade in the
                    moment of victory. Yet it was evident enough that the capture of their camp was
                    the only thing at which the Roman soldiers balked, and that elsewhere they
                    rejoiced at their own defeat and ignominy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    These things in no wise daunted the haughty spirit of Appius. But when he would
                    have gone further and have vented his rage upon the army, and was issuing orders
                    for an assembly, the lieutenants and tribunes gathered hurriedly about <pb
                        n="p.419"/> him and warned him upon no account to seek a test <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 471</note> of his
                    authority, when its effectiveness all depended on the goodwill of those obeying
                    it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The men, they reported, were saying that
                    they would not go to be harangued, and everywhere voices were overheard
                    demanding that the camp be removed from Volscian territory. The victorious enemy
                    had a little while before been almost in their gates and on their wall, and a
                    great disaster was not merely to be apprehended, but was openly hovering before
                    their eyes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Giving way at last, since the
                    soldiers were gaining nothing but a postponement of their punishment, he
                    relinquished the idea of an assembly, and commanded a march for the following
                    day. At daybreak he caused the signal for departure to be sounded on the
                    trumpet. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the very instant when the column
                    was getting clear of the camp, the Volsci, as though set in motion by the same
                    signal, fell upon their rear. Thence the confusion spread to the van, and the
                    panic so disordered the standards and the ranks that it was impossible either to
                    hear commands or to form a line. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nobody
                    thought of anything but flight, and so demoralised was the rout, as the men
                    escaped over fallen bodies and discarded weapons, that the enemy sooner ceased
                    to pursue than the Romans to flee. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When at
                    last the soldiers had been collected from their scattered flight, the consul,
                    who had followed his men in a vain attempt to call them back, pitched his camp
                    on friendly soil. Then he summoned an assembly and soundly rated them, not
                    without reason, as an army which had been false to military discipline and had
                    deserted its standards. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Asking them all in
                    turn where their arms and where their standards were, he caused the unarmed
                    soldiers and <pb n="p.421"/> the standard-bearers who had lost their standards,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 471</note> and
                    in <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> addition to these the centurions and the
                    recipients of a double ration <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This
                        was granted in recognition of unusual valour. So the Victoria Cross is
                        accompanied by a small stipend. </note> who had quitted their ranks, to be
                    scourged with rods and beheaded; of the remaining number every tenth man was
                    selected by lot for punishment. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To contrast with all this, in the Aequian
                    campaign there subsisted between consul and soldiers an emulation of goodwill
                    and kindness. Not only was it natural to Quinctius to be more gentle, but the
                    unfortunate harshness of his colleague had given him the more reason to be
                    content with his own disposition. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Against this
                    complete harmony between commander and army the Aequi ventured no opposition,
                    but suffered their enemies to devastate their fields at will; and in fact no
                    previous war had ever yielded a larger booty from that country. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This was all given to the troops, and to the spoils were
                    added encomiums, which are no less efficacious than rewards in rejoicing a
                    soldier's heart. Not only their leader, but for their leader's sake the Fathers,
                    too, were looked upon with greater kindness by the army when they returned. They
                    declared that to them the senate had given a parent, to the other army a tyrant. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Varying fortune in war, grievous discord at
                    home and in the field, had characterized the year just ended; but it was chiefly
                    distinguished by the tribal assembly, a matter more important because the men
                    had won a victory in the struggle which they had undertaken than in its
                    practical results; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for the loss of dignity to
                    the assembly itself, caused by the removal from it of the patricians, was
                    greater than the gain in strength by the plebeians or the loss of it by the
                    Fathers. </p>
                <pb n="p.423"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A stormier year succeeded, under the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 470</note> consuls
                    Lucius Valerius and Titus Aemilius, partly owing to strife between the classes
                    about the land-law, partly to the trial of Appius Claudius. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He was the bitterest opponent of the law, and was upholding
                    the claim of those who had possession of the public domain as if he had been a
                    third consul, when Marcus Duillius and Gnaeus Siccius lodged an accusation
                    against him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Never before had a defendant whom
                    the plebs so detested been brought to trial before the people, burdened as he
                    was with men's hatred, both of himself and of his father. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The patricians, for their part, had not lightly put forth
                    such exertions in behalf of any man. They felt that the champion of the senate
                    and the guardian of their own dignity, who had stood firm against all sorts of
                    tribunician and plebeian outbreaks, though he had possibly gone too far in the
                    heat of the struggle, was being exposed to the angry commons. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Alone amongst the Fathers, Appius Claudius himself regarded
                    tribunes, plebs, and his own trial with perfect unconcern. He was not one whom
                    the threats of the plebeians or the entreaties of the senate could ever prevail
                    upon, I do not say to put on mourning, or to seek men out with appeals for
                    mercy, but even to soften and subdue in a slight degree the accustomed sharpness
                    of his tongue, though it was before the people he must plead. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> There was the same expression on his countenance, the same
                    arrogance in his glance, the same fire in his speech; so markedly, in fact, that
                    a great part of the plebs feared Appius no less when a defendant than they had
                    feared him as consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Once only did he plead
                    his cause, in the tone he had been wont to use on all occasions, namely, that of
                    a <pb n="p.425"/> prosecutor; and so completely did his firmness <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 470</note> overwhelm
                    the tribunes and the commons that they themselves voluntarily adjourned the
                    trial to a later day, and then allowed the affair to drag. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The interval was not very long, but before the appointed
                    day came round Appius fell sick and died. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    his eulogy was being pronounced, the tribunes of the plebs attempted to
                    interfere, but the plebs were not willing that the funeral-day of so great a man
                    should be defrauded of the customary honours. They listened to his praises with
                    as great goodwill, now he was dead, as they had heard the living man accused,
                    and attended his burial in crowds. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="62" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same year Valerius the consul, having
                    marched with an army against the Aequi, was unable to entice the enemy into a
                    battle, and directed an assault upon their camp. This was foiled by an awful
                    storm that descended upon them with hail and claps of thunder. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Their amazement was soon increased, on the signal for
                    retreat being given, by the reappearance of so tranquil and cloudless a sky,
                    that, as though some god had defended the camp, they scrupled to attack it a
                    second time, and directed all their hostility towards devastating the fields.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The other consul, Aemilius, conducted a
                    campaign in the Sabine country. There, too, the enemy kept within his walls, and
                    the Romans laid waste his fields. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Afterwards,
                    by setting fire not only to farmhouses but even to the villages, where the
                    people lived close together, they aroused the Sabines, who, having met the
                    pillagers and fought a drawn battle with them, next day withdrew their camp to a
                    safer position. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This seemed to the consul a
                    sufficient pretext for leaving the enemy, as conquered, and he retired ere the
                    campaign had fairly begun. </p>
                <pb n="p.427"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="63" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these wars were going on and there <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 469</note> was still
                    discord at home, Titus Numicius Priscus and Aulus Verginius were elected
                    consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was clear that the plebs would
                    endure no further postponement of the land-law, and were preparing to use
                    violent measures, when the approach of a Volscian army was announced by the
                    smoke which rose from burning farmhouses and by the flight of the country
                    people. By this circumstance the insurrection, which was already matured and on
                    the point of breaking out, was repressed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls, being at once commanded to do so by the senate, led the young men out
                    of the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> City to the war, a policy which
                    diminished the restlessness of the plebeians who were left behind. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> As for the enemy, they did no more than cause the
                    Romans a needless panic, and hastily retreated. Numicius marched to Antium
                    against the Volsci, Verginius against the Aequi. In the Aequian campaign an
                    ambush nearly resulted in a severe defeat for the Romans, but the courage of the
                    soldiers restored the day, which the carelessness of the consul had almost lost.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Volscian expedition was better
                    directed: the enemy were routed in the first engagement and driven in flight to
                    Antium, a very opulent city for those days. This place the consul did not
                    venture to assail, but he captured from the Antiates another town, named Caeno,
                    of far less wealth. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While the Aequi and Volsci
                    kept the Roman armies busy, the Sabines advanced clear to the gates of the City
                    on a plundering raid. A few days after this they themselves had to confront two
                    armies, for both the consuls indignantly invaded their borders, and they
                    suffered greater losses than they had themselves inflicted. </p>
                <pb n="p.429"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="64" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the year there was a
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 469-468</note>
                    brief season of peace, but, as always on other occasions, a peace distracted by
                    the strife of patricians and plebeians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    angry plebs refused to take part in the consular elections: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Held in the centuriate comitia.</note>
                    by the votes of the patricians and their clients Titus Quinctius and Quintus
                    Servilius were chosen consuls. They experienced a year like the preceding one:
                    dissensions, to begin with, then a foreign war and tranquillity. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The Sabines executed a rapid march across the
                    Crustuminian plains, bringing fire and sword to the country about the river
                    Anio. When almost at the Colline Gate and the City walls they were beaten back,
                    yet they carried off immense spoils of men and cattle. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Servilius the consul pursued them with an army, and though
                    he could not overtake the column itself on ground which was suitable for
                    offering battle, he devastated the country so extensively as to leave nothing
                    untouched by the ravages of war, and returned with many times the plunder which
                    the Romans had lost. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Operations in the
                    Volscian country, too, were very successful, thanks both to the general and to
                    his soldiers. First, there was a pitched battle in the open field, with enormous
                    numbers killed and wounded on both sides. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    Romans indeed, whose fewness made them feel their loss more sensibly, would have
                    fallen back, had it not been for a salutary falsehood told by the consul, who
                    shouted that the enemy were running away on the other wing, and so aroused the
                    spirits of his troops. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Romans charged and,
                    believing themselves to be conquering, they conquered. The consul feared lest by
                    pressing the enemy too hard he might cause a renewal of the struggle. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> He therefore gave the signal for the recall. For a
                    few <pb n="p.431"/> days both sides rested, as if they had tacitly agreed <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 469-468</note> on a
                    truce. Meanwhile a great force of men came in from all their tribes to the camp
                    of the Volsci and Aequi. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They made no question
                    but that the Romans, if they had perceived them, would retreat in the night, and
                    accordingly at about the third watch <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The Romans divided the night into four equal watches, beginning at sunset.
                    </note> they came to attack the camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Quinctius stilled the tumult which the sudden alarm had raised, and bidding the
                    soldiers remain quietly in their tents, led out a cohort of Hernici to an
                    outpost, and mounting trumpeters and buglers upon horses, ordered them to blow
                    their instruments in front of the rampart and keep the enemy in suspense till
                    daybreak. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For the remainder of the night all
                    was so peaceful in camp that the Romans were even able to sleep. But the Volsci,
                    beholding armed foot-soldiers, whom they supposed to be more numerous than they
                    were, and to be Romans; and hearing the stamping and neighing of the horses,
                    which were infuriated not only at finding unaccustomed riders on their backs,
                    but also by the blare of the trumpets, were kept on the alert in anticipation of
                    an attack. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="65" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as it was light, the Romans, who <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 468</note> were fresh
                    and had enjoyed a good sleep, were led out into line of battle. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Volsci, weary from standing and from loss of sleep,
                    were driven back at the first assault; though it was rather a retreat than a
                    rout, for behind them were hills, to which, under cover of the first line, they
                    withdrew safely and in good order. The consul ordered a halt when his army
                    reached rising ground. The infantry could hardly be restrained, noisily
                    demanding permission to press on after the fleeing enemy. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Still more ardent were the cavalry. They swarmed about the
                    general, and shouted that <pb n="p.433"/> they were going on before the
                    standards. While the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 468</note> consul was hesitating, feeling certain of the valour of his
                    troops but doubtful of the ground, the men cried out that they were going, and
                    instantly made good their word. Planting their spears in the ground, that they
                    might be the lighter for the ascent, they went up at a run. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Volsci, having discharged their javelins at the first
                    onset, picked up the stones which lay about under their feet, and flung them at
                    their enemies as they mounted. Confused by this rain of missiles from above, the
                    left wing of the Romans was nearly overwhelmed, and had already begun to
                    retreat, when the consul, reproaching them at once with rashness and with
                    cowardice, succeeded in shaming them out of their fear. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> First they made a resolute stand; then, after holding their
                    ground and returning blow for blow, they even dared to press forward and,
                    renewing their cheers, set their line in motion; then with another rush they
                    struggled upward and scaled the height; and they were just emerging upon the
                    summit of the ridge, when the enemy turned and fled. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Running at full speed, and almost in one body, the pursued
                    and the pursuers reached the Volscian camp, which was captured in the panic.
                    Those of the Volsci who succeeded in escaping made for Antium, and to Antium
                    marched the Roman army also. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After a blockade
                    of a few days the place surrendered; the besiegers had not delivered any new
                    attack, but the Volsci had lost heart from the moment of their unsuccessful
                    battle and the capture of their camp. </p>
                <pb n="p.435"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
