<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Respecting the Answers of the Soothsayers </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <pb n="68"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO RESPECTING THE ANSWERS OF THE SOOTHSAYERS. ADDRESSED TO
                THE SENATE.</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>This speech was spoken towards the close of the year after the last speech, but
                    it follows it in nearly all editions, as it relates in some degree to the same
                    subject. In the early part of the summer many prodigies were reported to have
                    happened in the neighborhood of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>.
                    And the senate consulted the soothsayers as to the cause of them, and as to the
                    means of averting their consequences. The soothsayers made answer, that the
                    solemn shows and plays had been negligently exhibited; that sacred places had
                    been treated as profane; that ambassadors had been ill-treated and slain; that
                    good faith and oaths had been disregarded, and ancient and secret sacrifices
                    neglected and profaned. That these prodigies had been sent as warnings by the
                    gods, lest the Romans should bring evil on themselves and on their country by
                    continuing their disorderly conduct and dissensions. That therefore the evils
                    must be amended, or removed as far as possible, and supplications made to
                            <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>,
                            <persName><surname>Saturn</surname></persName>,
                            <persName><surname>Neptune</surname></persName>, and the other gods. </p>
                <p>After this answer had been received, Clodius, who was now aedile, called the
                    people together, and made them a speech to prove that the evils which had
                    especially offended the gods were the tyrannical conduct of Cicero, and the
                    restoration of his house, after it had been consecrated to the service of
                    religion. Cicero replied to this harangue the next day in the senate, arguing
                    that all the offenses which could have excited the displeasure of the gods were
                    much more fairly imputable to Clodius than to him; and after exculpating
                    himself, and dwelling on the outrages of which Clodius had notoriously been
                    guilty, he exhorted all citizens of all classes to lay aside their mutual
                    animosities, as the only way of regaining the favour of the gods and their
                    former prosperity.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>Yesterday, O conscript fathers, when I was greatly moved by the thoughts of your
                dignity, and of the great attendance of the Roman knights to whom a senate was
                given, I thought myself bound to check the shameless impudence of Publius Clodius,
                when he was hindering the cause of the publicans from being proceeded with by the
                most foolish possible <pb n="69"/> questions, and was studying to save Publius
                Tullio the Syrian and was, even before your eyes selling himself to him to whom,
                indeed, he had already been entirely sold. Therefore I checked the man in his frenzy
                and exultation, the very moment that I gave him a hint of the danger of a public
                trial; and by two half-uttered words I bridled all the violence and ferocity of that
                gladiator. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But he, ignorant what sort of men the consuls were, pale and fuming with me burst on
                a sudden out of the senate house, with some broken and empty threats and with those
                denunciations with which he used to terrify us in the time of
                        <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName> and Gabinius. And when I began
                to press upon him, as he was departing, I received the greatest reward of my
                exertions by all of you rising up at the same time with me, and by all the publicans
                thronging round me to escort me. But that senseless man stopped on a sudden out of
                countenance, colourless, and voiceless; then he looked back; and, as soon as he
                beheld Cnaeus Lentulus<note anchored="true">This is not the same Lentulus as had
                    been consul the preceding year. This was Cnaeus Cornelius Lentulus Marcellinus;
                    the former consul was Publius Cornelius Lentulus Spinther.</note> the consul, he
                fell down almost on the threshold of the senate house from the recollection, I
                imagine, of his dear friend Gabinius and from regret for
                        <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName>. And why need I speak at all of
                his unbridled and headlong fury? He cannot be wounded by me with more severe
                language than he was on the instant being crushed and overwhelmed at the very moment
                of his acting in that manner by Publius Servilius. And even if I were able to equal
                the extraordinary and almost divine energy and dignity of that man, still I cannot
                doubt that those weapons which out enemy hurled at him would appear less powerful
                and less sharp than those which the colleague of his father aimed at him. <milestone
                    n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But still I wish to explain the principles of my conduct to those men who thought
                that I was carried away yesterday by my indignation, and that, out of passion, I
                made a wider digression than the deliberate calmness of a philosopher allowed. I did
                nothing in anger nothing from not being able to restrain my temper nothing which I
                had not maturely considered and determined on a long time before. For I, O conscript
                fathers, have always professed myself an enemy to those two men who were bound to
                have defended and were <pb n="70"/> able to have preserved both me and the republic;
                and who though they were called to the performance of their duty as consuls by the
                very ensigns of their office, and to the preservation of my safety, not only by your
                authority but even by your prayers, first of all deserted, then betrayed, and last
                of all opposed me; and, having received the rewards of their nefarious covenant,
                wished utterly to overwhelm and destroy me together with the republic; and who,
                during the time of their magistracy and command, bloody and fatal that it was, were
                neither able to defend the walls of our allies from chastisement, nor to inflict
                chastisement on the cities of the enemy; but who bore along into all my houses and
                lands, razing, and conflagration, and destruction, and depopulation, and
                devastation, to the great enriching of themselves with my plunder. <milestone n="4"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Against these furies and firebrands, with these destructive monsters and pests, which
                have been (I may almost say) desolating this empire, I do say that I have undertaken
                inexpiable war; and yet, even that is not as great as my sufferings and those of my
                relations require, though it may be enough to satisfy your indignation and that of
                all virtuous men. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But my hatred towards Clodius is not greater this day than it was then, when I knew
                that he was scorched, as it were, by those most holy fires, and that he had escaped
                in female attire from the house of the Pontifex Maximus, after attempting an act of
                most atrocious licentiousness. Then, I say, then I perceived, and foresaw long
                beforehand, how great a tempest was being raised, how great a storm was threatening
                the republic. I saw that that ill-omened wickedness, that that intolerable audacity
                of a young man, mad, nobly born, and disgraced as he was, could not be hindered from
                breaking through the bounds of tranquillity; that that evil would certainly break
                out some day or other to the destruction of the state, if it were allowed to remain
                unpunished. There has not been much since to add to my detestation of that man.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For he has not done anything against me out of
                hatred to me, but out of hatred to strictness, out of hatred to dignity, out of
                hatred to the republic. He has not insulted me more than he has the senate, or the
                Roman knights, or all good men, or the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>. Lastly, he has not behaved more wickedly towards me than he
                has towards the immortal gods. In truth, he has polluted those gods with his <pb
                    n="71"/> impiety whom no one before ever did. Towards me his disposition has
                been the same as that of his dear friend Catiline would have been, if he had been
                victorious. Therefore, I never thought it necessary for me to prosecute him, any
                more than that blockhead, whose very nation we should be ignorant of if he did not
                himself say that he was a Ligurian. For why should I pursue this animal, this beast,
                bribed by the food and acorns thrown him by my enemy? a fellow, who, if he had only
                sense to know to what wickedness he has bound himself, would be, I doubt not, most
                wretched; but if he is not aware of it there is some danger lest he may save himself
                by the excuse of stupidity. </p>
            <p><milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There is also this consideration which weighs with
                me that, according to universal expectation, that man seems devoted and marked out
                as the victim of that most gallant and most illustrious man Titus Annius; from whom
                it would be a scandalous thing for me to snatch the credit which is destined for,
                and already openly promised to him, when it is owing to his exertions that I myself
                have recovered my own dignity and safety. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>In truth, as that great man, Publius Scipio, appears to me to have been born for the
                overthrow and destruction of <placeName key="tgn,7016143">Carthage</placeName>, he
                being the only man who, at last, as it were, by a special decree of destiny, did
                overthrow it after it had been besieged, attacked, undermined, and almost taken by
                many generals; so Titus Annius appears to have been born, and to have been given to
                the republic, by a sort of divine munificence as it were for the express purpose of
                repressing and extinguishing and utterly destroying that pest of the state. He alone
                has discovered the way not only of defeating but also of fettering an armed citizen
                who was driving the citizens away, some by the sword, some by stones, was confining
                others to their houses and alarming the whole city, the senate house, the forum, and
                all the temples with bloodshed and conflagration. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                I will never, with my own free will, take out of the hands of this man, being so
                good a man as one who has deserved so well of me and of his country, that criminal
                of all men in the world, whose enmity be has not only encountered, but has even
                sought for out of a regard for my safety. But if, even now that he is entangled in
                all the dangers of the laws, surrounded by the hatred of all virtuous men, and <pb
                    n="72"/> hemmed in on all sides by the expectation or punishment which cannot be
                long delayed, still, hesitating and hampered as he is, he persists in rushing on,
                and making attacks upon me, I will resist him, and gaining the consent, or, perhaps,
                the assistance of <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>, I will frustrate his
                endeavours; as I did yesterday, when, while he was threatening me in dumb show, as I
                was standing near him, I just said one word about the beginning of legal proceedings
                and a trial. He sat down. He did not say a word. Suppose he had brought a charge
                against me, as he had threatened, I should have instantly taken steps to have him
                summoned to appear before the praetor in three days. And let him restrain himself
                with the idea that if he is content with those acts of wickedness which he has
                already committed, he is already dedicated to
                    <persName><surname>Milo</surname></persName>; but if he aims any dart against
                me, that then I shall immediately employ all the weapons of the courts of justice
                and of the laws. </p>
            <p><milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And a little time ago, O conscript fathers, he held
                an assembly, and made a speech which was directed wholly against me. And I will tell
                you the argument and sentiment which ran through the whole of his speech. And when
                you have been sufficiently amused at the fellow's impudence, I will give you the
                details of everything that then took place. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Publius Clodius, O conscript fathers, made a long speech about religious observances,
                and sacrifices, and ceremonies. Publius Clodius, I say, complained that the
                sacrifices and religious rites were neglected, profaned, and polluted. It is no
                wonder if this seems to you an absurdity. Indeed the very assembly which he himself
                had convened laughed at the idea of a man, who has been pierced, as be himself is in
                the habit of boasting, with two hundred resolutions of the senate against him, every
                one of which was passed against him because of matters connected with religion,—of
                that fellow who carried his adulteries to the shrine of the Good Goddess herself;
                and who profaned those sacred rites which may not be seen without impiety by the
                eyes of a man even unintentionally, not only by the view of a man, but by lust and
                wickedness, complaining in a public assembly about the neglect of religion.
                Therefore they are now expecting another speech from him on the subject of chastity.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For what difference does it make whether, when
                just driven from the most holy of altars, he makes complaints of the state of the
                sacrifices and religious observances; <pb n="73"/> or whether, having just left his
                sister's bed-chamber, he speaks in defence of modesty and chastity? In his harangue
                he recited the lately received answer of the soothsayers about the noises which have
                been heard; in which among many other things it is stated, (as you have heard
                yourselves,) that holy and sacred places had been treated as common. Under that head
                he said that my house was intended, which had been consecrated by that holiest of
                pontiffs, Publius Clodius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I am delighted at not
                only having a reasonable pretext for, but being even under an absolute necessity of
                speaking about this prodigy, which I am not sure that I may not call the most
                important one that has for many years been reported to this body. For you find that
                by every part of this prodigy and of this answer, we have been warned, I may almost
                say by the voice of the all-good and all-powerful
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName> himself, of the wickedness
                and frenzy of that man, and of the immense dangers which are impending over the
                state. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But first of all I will clear up the
                objections made on the score of religion in the case of my own house, if I am able
                to do so truly, and without leaving the least doubt in any one's mind; but if the
                very slightest scruple on the subject exists in any one's mind, I will obey the
                prodigies sent by the immortal gods, and comply with what is required by the
                reverence due to them not only with a patient but even with a willing mind.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But what house is there in the whole city so clear and free from all suspicion of
                being a consecrated building as this? Although your houses, O conscript fathers, and
                those of all the other citizens, are, for much the greater part of them, free from
                all religious obligation, yet my house is the only one in the whole city which has
                been pronounced to be so by the decision of all the tribunals. For I appeal to you,
                O Lentulus and to you, O Philippus. After this reply was received from the
                soothsayers, the senate decreed that you should refer the question of hallowed and
                consecrated spots to this order of the senate. Can you put any question to them
                concerning my house? which (as I have said) is the only one in the whole of the city
                which has been pronounced by every tribunal in it to be free from every sort of
                religious obligation; which at first my enemy himself; even in the time of that
                storm and nocturnal darkness which was overwhelming the republic, when he had set
                down all his other wicked actions with that <pb n="74"/> foul pen of his dipped in
                the mouth of Sextus Clodius, did not mark with one single letter indicating any
                religions liability. And in the second place, the Roman people, whose power is
                supreme in all matters in the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign>,
                and by the suffrage of every age and every rank of men, ordered it to remain in the
                same condition in which it had previously been. </p>
            <p><milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Afterwards, O conscript fathers, not because the
                matter was doubtful, but in order to cut off every argument from this furious man,
                if he chose to remain any longer in this city which he was anxious to destroy, you
                passed a decree that a reference should be made to the college of pontiffs as to the
                religious liability of my house. What obligation can there possibly be from our
                greatest doubts and most serious religious apprehensions, as to which we may not be
                relieved by the answer and dictum of Publius Servilius or Marcus Lucullus alone? In
                all matters concerning the public sacrifices, or the great games, or the ceremonies
                of the household gods, and of Vesta, the mother of the city, or even concerning that
                great sacrifice itself which is performed for the safety of the Roman people, and
                which since the first foundation of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>
                has never been profaned except by the wickedness of this single holy guardian of
                religion, whatever three pontiffs have decided, has at all times appeared to the
                Roman people, and to the senate, and to the immortal gods themselves, sufficiently
                holy, sufficiently august, sufficiently religious. But Publius Lentulus being both
                consul and pontiff, and Publius Servilius, and Marcus Lucullus, and Quintus
                Metellus, and Marcus Glabrio, and Marcus Messala, and Lucius Lentulus, the priest of
                Mars, and Publius Galba, and Quintus Metellus Scipio, and Caius Fannius, and Marcus
                Lepidus, and Lucius Claudius, the king of the sacrifices, and Marcus Scaurus, and
                Marcus Crassus, and Caius Curio, and Sextus Caesar, the priest of
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, and Quintus Cornelius, and
                Publius Albinovanus, and Quintus Terentius, the lesser<note anchored="true"
                    >Originally the number of pontiffs was four, or, including the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Pontifex Maximus</foreign>, five. In the year B.C. <date
                        when="-0300">300</date> the Ogulnian law raised the number from four to
                    eight; in the year B.C. <date when="-0081">81</date> Sulla increased the number
                    to fifteen, including the Pontifex Maximus; and after him Julius Caesar
                    increased the number to sixteen. Besides these there were other pontiffs
                    distinguished as <foreign xml:lang="la">minores</foreign>, of whom three are
                    mentioned here; the nature of whose office seems rather uncertain; but it
                    appears probable that it was a name of late introduction, and applied to the
                    secretaries of the pontiffs when the real pontiffs had begun to neglect their
                    duties, and to leave the greater part of them to be performed by their
                    secretaries. <foreign xml:lang="la">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict Ant. v. <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Pontifex</foreign>.</note> pontiffs, having investigated <pb
                    n="75"/> the case after it had been argued before them on two separate
                occasions, in the presence of a great number of the noblest and wisest of the
                citizens, all unanimously pronounced my house free from all religious obligation.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="13" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I say that so numerous a meeting of the college has never decided on any subject, not
                even concerning the rights or life of a vestal virgin, ever since the establishment
                of sacred ceremonies, though their antiquity is the same as that of the city itself;
                although when an investigation into any crime is taking place it is of consequence
                that as many as possible should be present. For the interpretation of a law given by
                the priests is on such a footing that it has the same force as a decision of the
                judges. An explanation of what is required by religion can be properly given by one
                single experienced priest; but in a case of a trial for life, such a proceeding
                would be harsh and unjust. Nevertheless, you will find this to be the case, that a
                greater number of pontiffs were assembled when they decided on the question
                concerning my house, than had ever met on any question concerning the ceremonies of
                the vestal virgins. The next day the senate in a very full house, when you, O
                Lentulus, being the consul elect, made the motion, and Publius Lentulus and Quintus
                Metellus, the consuls, put it to the senate, when all the pontiffs who belonged to
                this order were present and when those who had precedence, from the distinctions
                which had been conferred on them by the Roman people, had made many speeches
                concerning the decision of the college, and when all of them had assisted in drawing
                up the decree,—the senate, I say, voted that my house appeared, according to the
                decision of the pontiffs, to be free from all religious liability.<milestone n="14"
                    unit="section"/> Is this then the place which of all others the soothsayers
                appear to intend to speak of as sacred, which is the only one of all private
                buildings in the whole city which has this argument to advance in support of its
                rights, that it has been adjudged not to be sacred by those very men who preside
                over all sacred things?</p>
            <p>However, refer the matter to them, as you are bound to do <pb n="76"/> according to
                the resolution of the senate. Either the investigation will be allotted to you who
                were the first to pronounce an opinion respecting this house, and who have
                pronounced it free from all religious liability; or the senate itself will decide,
                which has already decided in the fullest possible house, that one single priest
                alone dissenting; or else, what will certainly be done, it will be referred back to
                the pontiffs, to whose authority, integrity, and prudence our ancestors entrusted
                all sacred and religious observances, whether private or public. What then can these
                men decide different from what they have already decided? There are many houses in
                this city, O conscript fathers; I do not know whether they are not nearly all held
                by thoroughly good titles, but still they are only private titles, titles derived
                from inheritance, from prescription, from purchase, or from mortgage. But I assert
                that there is no other house whatever equally fenced round by private title and
                incontestable rights, and at the same time by every sort of public law of the
                highest authority, both human and divine. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For in
                the first place it was built by the authority of the senate, with the public money;
                and in the second place it has been fenced round and fortified against the impious
                violence of this gladiator by numerous resolutions of the senate. <milestone n="8"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>At first a commission was given to those same magistrates in the preceding year, to
                whom at times of the greatest peril the whole republic is usually recommended, to
                take care that I was to be allowed to proceed in building without any hindrance from
                violence. Afterwards, when that fellow had brought devastation on my estate with
                stones, and fire, and sword, the senate voted that those who had acted in that
                manner were liable to be proceeded against by the laws concerning violence which are
                in force against those who have attacked the whole republic. But when you put the
                question, O you best and bravest of consuls within the memory of man, the same
                senate in a very full house decreed, that whoever injured my house would be acting
                against the interests of the republic. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I say that
                there never were so many resolutions of the senate passed about any public work,
                monument or temple, as about my house, the only house since the first foundation of
                the city which the senate has thought ought to be built at the public expense,
                released from all religious <pb n="77"/> obligation by the pontiffs, defended by the
                magistrates, and put under the protection of the judges who were to punish all who
                injured it. On account of his immense services to the republic, a house at
                    <placeName key="perseus,Velia">Velia</placeName> was given by a public vote to
                Publius Valerius. But my house was restored to me on the <placeName
                    key="tgn,3000935">Palatine Hill</placeName>. He had a spot of ground given him.
                I had walls also and a roof. He had a house given to him which he was to defend by
                his rights as a private citizen; but I had one which all the magistrates were
                ordered to protect with the public force of the city. And if I had all this owing to
                my own exertions, or if I had received it from any other persons except you, I would
                not mention it before you, lest I might appear to be boasting too much. But as all
                these things have been given me by you, and as they are now being attacked by the
                tongue of that man by whose hand they were formerly overthrown, when you restored
                them with your own hands to me and to my children, I am not speaking of my own
                actions but of yours; nor am I afraid lest this public mention of all your kindness
                to me should appear to be not so much grateful as arrogant. <milestone n="17"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Although, if indeed a certain indignation which I cannot help feeling were to lead me
                who have exerted myself so much in the cause of the public safety at times to
                speaking some what boastfully when refuting the aspersions of wicked men who would
                not excuse me for so doing? For I did see yesterday someone murmuring: and people
                said that he declared that he could not endure me because when I was asked by that
                foul traitor to his country to what city I belonged, I answered, with the approval
                of you and of the Roman knights also, that I belonged to a city which could not do
                without me. He, I imagine, groaned at this. What then was I to answer? (I ask that
                very man who cannot endure me.) That I was a Roman citizen? It would have been a
                truly learned answer. Should I have held my tongue? That would have been a betrayal
                of my own cause. Can any man when it is attempted to excite odium against him with
                respect to important affairs, reply with sufficient dignity to the abuse of his
                enemy without some praise of himself? But no doubt he himself, when he is attacked,
                not only answers as well as he can, but is even glad to be prompted by his friends
                and to have an answer suggested to him. <pb n="78"/>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="18" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But since I have now said enough respecting my own case, let us see now what it is
                that the soothsayers say. For I confess that I have been greatly moved both by the
                magnitude of the prodigies, and by the solemnity of the answer, and by the unanimous
                and consistent language of the soothsayers. Nor am I a man who,—though I may perhaps
                appear to some men to be more addicted to the study of literature than the rest of
                those are who are occupied about state affairs as much as myself—at all incline to
                derive delight from or to pursue those branches of learning which have a tendency to
                divert and deter our minds from the study of religion. But in the first place, I
                have our ancestors as my leaders and tutors in paying proper respect to
                religion,—men whose wisdom appears to me to have been so great, that those men are
                sufficiently, and more than sufficiently prudent, who are able—I will not say to
                equal their prudence, but to be thoroughly aware how great it was; who thought that
                the stated and regular ceremonies were provided for by the establishment of the
                Pontificate, that due authority for the performance of all actions was to he derived
                from the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, that the ancient prophecies of
                our destinies were contained in the books of the prophets of Apollo, and the
                explanations of prodigies in the system of the Etrurians; and this last is of such
                weight that within our own recollection they have predicted to us in no obscure
                language, first of all those fatal beginnings of the Italian war, and after that the
                imminent danger and almost destruction of the time of Sulla and Cinna, and very
                lately this recent conspiracy for burning the city and destroying the empire.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> In the next place, I knew that the most
                learned and the wisest men have both said many things and have left behind them many
                written books concerning the divine power of the immortal gods. And although I see
                that those books are written with a godlike eloquence, still they are such that our
                ancestors appear to have taught those things to the writers, and not to have learnt
                of them. In truth, who is there so senseless as either, when he looks up to heaven,
                not to feel that there are gods, or to think that those things are done by chance
                which are done with such wisdom, that scarcely any one by any amount of skill can
                comprehend their order and necessary dependence on each other? or, when he has
                arrived at the knowledge that there are gods, not to understand that all this <pb
                    n="79"/> mighty empire has been originated, and increased, and preserved by
                their divine authority? Let us, O conscript fathers, think as highly of ourselves as
                we please; and yet it is not in numbers that we are superior to the Spaniards, nor
                in personal strength to the Gauls, nor in cunning to the Carthaginians, nor in arts
                to the Greeks, nor in the natural acuteness which seems to be implanted in the
                people of this land and country, to the Italian and Latin tribes; but it is in and
                by means of piety and religion, and this especial wisdom of perceiving that all
                things are governed and managed by the divine power of the immortal gods, that we
                have been and are superior to all other countries and nations. <milestone n="10"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="20" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Wherefore, not to say any more about a doubtful matter, give, I pray you, your
                thoughts and attention, and do not lend your ears alone to the language of the
                soothsayers: “Because a noise and roaring has been heard in the Latin district.” I
                say nothing of the soothsayers, I say nothing of that ancient system, given, as men
                report, to Etruria by the immortal gods themselves; but cannot we ourselves be
                soothsayers here? “A certain obscure noise, and a horrible rattling of arms, has
                been heard in a neighbouring and suburban district.” Who is there of all those
                giants, whom the poets relate to have waged war against the immortal gods, so
                impious as not to confess that by this novel and mighty commotion the gods are
                foreshowing and predicting something important to the Roman people? Concerning that
                matter it is written down that entreaties are to be addressed to
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, Saturn, Neptune, Tellus,
                and the gods of heaven.<milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Well, I hear what gods
                have been offended and to whom atonement is due; but I want to know on account of
                what offences committed by men they have been offended. “On account of the games
                having been carelessly exhibited and polluted.” What games? I appeal to you, O
                Lentulus; for the sacred cars and chariots, the singing, the sports, the libations,
                and feasts of the public games belong to your priesthood; and I appeal to you, O
                pontiffs, to whom those who prepare the banquet for the all-good and all-powerful
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName> report it if anything has
                been neglected or done improperly, and if you give sentence that it shall be so,
                those ceremonies are celebrated anew and repeated over again. What games are they
                which have been exhibited without due diligence? By what wickedness, by what sort of
                    <pb n="80"/> crime have they been polluted? You will answer on behalf of
                yourself; and of your colleagues, and of the college of pontiffs, that none of these
                things have been treated contemptuously through the carelessness of anyone, or
                polluted by any wickedness, but that all the solemnities and practices of the games
                have been attended to with a proper observance of all necessary things, and with the
                strictest performance of all the usual ceremonies. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="22" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>What games, then, are they which the soothsayers say have not been performed with due
                diligence, and have been polluted? Those of which the immortal gods themselves and
                the blessed mother Cybele chose you—you, O Cnaeus Lentulus, by the hands of whose
                ancestor she was originally received—to be a spectator. And unless you had chosen to
                be a spectator of the Megalesia on that day, I do not know whether we should have
                been allowed to be give and to complain of these things. For an enormous multitude
                of slaves in a state of great excitement, collected out of all the streets by this
                religious aedile, burst in on a sudden upon the stage from all the arch-ways and
                doors at a given signal. Your virtue,—yours, I say, O Cnaeus Lentulus,—was at that
                crisis shown to be equal to that formerly displayed by your ancestor as a private
                individual. The senate standing up, and the Roman knights and all virtuous men,
                followed you, and your name and your command, and your voice, aspect, and authority,
                when he had handed over the senate and people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName>, hampered by the dense body in which they were sitting,
                chained as it were to the spectacle, and hindered by the crowd and narrow space, to
                a multitude of slaves and buffoons. </p>
            <p><milestone n="23" unit="section"/> Shall we say that, if a sacred dancer stops, or a
                flute-player has on a sudden ceased to play, or if a boy<note anchored="true">It is
                    inferred from this passage that the boys assisting at these games might not be
                    orphans.</note> with both father and mother alive has ceased to touch the
                ground, or has lost his hold of the sacred car, or of the reins, or if an aedile has
                used a wrong word or made the slightest mistake, then the games have not been duly
                celebrated, and those mistakes are forced to be expiated and the minds of the
                immortal gods are appeased by their repetition; and yet if the games are suddenly
                changed from a scene of joy to one of terror,—if they have been, not interrupted,
                but broken up and put an <pb n="81"/> end to,—if those days of festival turned out
                nearly fatal to the through the wickedness of that man who wished to turn the games
                into a time of grief,—shall we doubt what games that noise warns us have been
                polluted? <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> And if we wish to recollect those
                things which have been handed down to us traditionally about each of the gods, we
                have heard that this mighty Mother; whose games were thus violated and polluted, and
                turned almost to a massacre and to the destruction of the city, does roam over the
                fields and through the groves with a certain degree of noise and roaring. <milestone
                    n="12" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>She, then, she it is, who has displayed to the Roman people these tokens of
                wickedness, and revealed to them these indications of danger. For why should I speak
                of those games which our ancestors ordered to be performed and celebrated on the
                    <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine Hill</placeName>, in front of the temple,
                in the very sight of the mighty Mother, on the day of the Megalesia?<note
                    anchored="true">The Megalesia were the great festivals in honour of Cybele,
                    celebrated in April, on the anniversary of the day when her statue was brought
                    from Pessenus. They lasted six days, and were among the most important of all
                    the festivities of the sort which were held at <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                        >Rome</placeName>. <foreign xml:lang="la">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant.
                    v. <foreign xml:lang="la">Megalesia</foreign>.</note> which are in their
                institution and in the manner in which they are celebrated, above all other games
                chaste, solemn, and holy; in which games that great man Publius Africanus the elder,
                in his second consulship, gave for the first time the senate a place in front of the
                seats belonging to the people. Why need I tell how that foul pestilence polluted
                these games when if any freeman came near them either as a spectator or from some
                motive of religion, he was driven back by force and no matron approached them
                because of the number and violence of the slaves? And so these games—the reverence
                paid to which is so great that the goddess did not come to this city without having
                been sent for from the most distant countries,—which are the only games which have
                not even a Latin name, so that by their very name the religion is declared to have
                been a foreign one and imported hither and to have been undertaken in the name of
                the mighty Mother,—these games, I say, were celebrated by slaves, and had slaves
                alone for the spectators, and in every part, in this man's aedileship, were the
                Megalesia of slaves. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> O ye immortal gods! How
                could you speak more plainly to us if you were living <pb n="82"/> among and
                associating with us? You show us and plainly tell us that those games were profaned.
                What can be mentioned more deformed, polluted, altered and perverted, than for the
                whole body of slaves, as if they had been liberated by the permission of the
                magistrates, to be turned loose into one theatre, and set as guards over another, so
                that one body of spectators might be exposed to the power of slaves, and that the
                other might consist entirely of slaves? If during the games a swarm of bees had come
                on the stage, we should think it necessary to send for the soothsayers out of
                Etruria; and shall we all see on a sudden such vast swarms of slaves let loose upon
                the Roman people, blocked up and shut in, and not be moved by that? And perhaps, in
                the case of a swarm of bees, the soothsayers would warn us from the written books of
                the Etruscans to guard against the slaves. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> That
                then which we should guard against, if indicated by some disjointed prodigy
                admitting of divers interpretations, shall we not be afraid of when it is its own
                prodigy, and when the danger is in that very thing from which danger is dreaded?
                Were such the Megalesia which your father celebrated? Did your uncle celebrate them
                in such a manner as this? And then he makes mention to me of his family, when he
                would rather celebrate the games after the fashion of Athenio or Spartacus, than
                like Caius or Appius Claudius. When these great men were celebrating games, they
                ordered all the slaves to depart from the theatre. But you turned slaves into one,
                and turned free men out of the other. Therefore they, who formerly used to be
                separated from free men by the voice of the herald, now, at your games, separated
                free men from themselves not by their voice, but by force. <milestone n="13"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Did not even this occur to you, being a priest so well acquainted with the Sibylline
                oracles, that our ancestors derived these games from the Sibylline books? if those
                books are yours, which you consult with imperious intentions, and read with profane
                eyes, and handle with polluted hands. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> Formerly,
                then, by the advice of this prophetess, when <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName> was wearied by the Punic war and harassed by Hannibal, our
                ancestors imported that sacred image and those sacred rites from <placeName
                    key="tgn,7002613">Phrygia</placeName>, and established them at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, where they were received by that man who
                was adjudged to be the most virtuous of all the Roman people, Publius Scipio Nasica,
                and <pb n="83"/> by the woman who was considered the chastest of the matrons, Quinta
                Claudia; the old-fashioned strictness of whose sacrifice on that occasion your
                sister is considered to have imitated in a wonderful manner. Did, then, neither your
                ancestors, connected as they were with these religious ceremonies, nor the
                priesthood itself, by which all these religious observances were established, nor
                the curule aedileship, which above all things is accustomed to uphold this worship,
                influence you to abstain from polluting those most holy games with every sort of
                crime, and polluting them with infamy, and involving them in guilt? <milestone
                    n="28" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But why do I wonder? when, having taken a bribe, you ravaged <placeName
                    key="tgn,6004655">Pessinus</placeName> itself, the habitation and home of the
                mother of the gods, and sold to Brogitarus—a fellow half <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName>, half Greek, a profligate and impious man,
                whose agents, while you were tribune, used to pay you the money for your share of
                the work in the temple of Castor—the whole of that place and the temple; when you
                dragged the priest from the very altar and cushion of the goddess; when you
                perverted those omens which all antiquity, which Persians, and Syrians, and all
                kings who have ever reigned in <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> have always venerated with the
                greatest piety; which, last of all; our own ancestors considered so sacred, that
                though we had the city and all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>
                crowded with temples, still our generals in our most important and most perilous
                wars used to offer their vows to this goddess, and to pay them in <placeName
                    key="tgn,6004655">Pessinus</placeName> itself, at that identical principal altar
                and on that spot and in that temple. </p>
            <p><milestone n="29" unit="section"/> And when Deiotarus was protecting this temple in
                the most holy manner with the deepest feelings of religion—Deiotarus, of all allies
                the most faithful to this empire and the most devoted to our name—you gave it to
                Brogitarus as I have said before, having sold it to him for a sum of money. And yet
                you order this Deiotarus who has been repeatedly declared by the senate worthy of
                the name of king and adorned with the testimony of many most illustrious generals in
                his favour, to be styled king together with Brogitarus. But one of them has been
                called king by the decision of the senate through my instrumentality. Brogitarus has
                been called king by you for money. And I will think him a king, indeed, if he has
                any means of paying you what you <pb n="84"/> have trusted him with on his note of
                hand. For there are many royal qualities in Deiotarus; this was the most royal of
                all, that he gave you no money; that he did not repudiate that portion of your law
                which agreed with the decision of the senate, namely that he was a king; that he
                recovered <placeName key="tgn,6004655">Pessinus</placeName>, which had been
                impiously violated by you and stripped of its priest and its sacrifices, in order to
                maintain it in its accustomed religion; that he does not suffer the ceremonies which
                have been received as handed down from the most remote antiquity, to be polluted by
                Brogitarus; and that he prefers to let his son-in-law be deprived of your
                liberality, rather than to allow that temple to lose the ancient reverence due to
                its religious character. </p>
            <p>But to return to these answers of the soothsayers, the first of which is that
                respecting these games; who is there who does not confess that the whole of that
                answer and prophecy was delivered with reference to that fellow's games? <milestone
                    n="14" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="30" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>The answer about sacred and holy places comes next. Oh, the marvellous impudence of
                the man! do you dare to make mention of my house? Entrust your own to the consuls,
                or the senate, or the college of pontiffs; and mine, as I have said before, has been
                declared by all these three decisions to be free from all religions liability. But
                in that house which you keep possession of after having slain Quintus Seius, a Roman
                knight and most excellent man, in the most open manner, I say that there was a
                shrine and altars. I will prove and establish this fact by the registers of the
                censors, and by the recollection of many individuals. Only let this question be
                discussed, (and it must be referred to you by virtue of that resolution of the
                senate which has lately been passed,) and I have plenty to say on the subject of
                religious places. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/> When I have spoken of your
                house,—in which, however, a chapel has been put up in such a way that another built
                it, and you have only got to pull it down,—then I will see whether it is necessary
                for me to speak also of other places. For some people think that it belongs to me to
                open the armoury of the temple of Tellus. They say that it is not long ago that it
                was open, and I recollect it myself. Now they say that the most holy part of it, and
                the place entitled to the greatest reverence, is occupied by a private vestibule.
                There are many considerations which influence me,—<pb n="85"/>namely, this, that the
                temple of Tellus is put particularly under my care; and that he who took away that
                armoury said that my house, which was declared free by the decision of the pontiffs,
                had been adjudged to his brother. I am influenced also at this time of dearness of
                provisions, of barrenness of the lands, and of scarcity of the crops, by the
                reverence due to Tellus; and all the more, because, on account of this same prodigy,
                an atonement is said to be due to Tellus. <milestone n="32" unit="section"/> Perhaps
                we are speaking of old stones; although, if this is not laid down in the civil law,
                still by the law of nature and the common rights of nations the principle has been
                established, that mortals cannot acquire a prescriptive right to anything as against
                the immortal gods. <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But we will pass over all things of old date. Shall we also pass over those things
                which are done at the present time; which we see ourselves? Who knows not that
                Lucius Piso at this very time has been removing a great and most holy chapel of
                Diana on the Coeliculan hill? Men who live close to that spot are in court. There
                are many even belonging to this body who once a year have regularly performed the
                sacrifices of their family in that very chapel in their appointed place. And do we
                ask what places the immortal gods are regretting, what it is they are meaning, of
                what it is that they are speaking? Are we ignorant that some most holy chapels were
                undermined, blocked up, knocked down, and defiled in the most unseemly possible
                    manner?<milestone n="33" unit="section"/> Were you able to render my house the
                property of the gods? With what feelings? You have lost all feeling. With what hand?
                With that with which you pulled it down. With what voice? With that with which you
                ordered it to be set on fire. By what law? By one which you did not venture to
                propose even at the time when you were doing everything with impunity. With what
                cushion? That which you polluted with your adulteries. With what image? That which
                you took off from a harlot's tomb and placed on the monument of a general. What has
                my house which is connected with anything religious except that it touches the wall
                of an impious and sacrilegious man? Therefore that none of my people may be able
                unintentionally to look into your house I will raise the roof higher not in order
                that I may look down upon you, but that you may not be able to see that city which
                you were desirous to destroy. <pb n="86"/>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="34" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But let us now examine the rest of the clauses of the answers of the
                soothsayers.—“That ambassadors have been slain contrary to all divine and human
                law.” What is this? I see here a mention of the deputies from <placeName
                    key="perseus,Alexandria">Alexandria</placeName>; and I cannot refute it. For my
                feelings are, that the privileges of ambassadors are not only fenced round by human
                protection, but are also guarded by divine laws. But I ask of that man, who, as
                tribune, filled the forum with judges whom he took out of the prisons,—by whose will
                every dagger is now guided and every cup of poison dispensed,—who has made a regular
                bargain with Hermarchus of <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>,—whether
                he is at all aware that one most active adversary of Hermarchus, of the name of
                Theodosius, having been sent as ambassador to the senate from a free city, was
                assassinated with a dagger? and I know to a certainty that that cannot have appeared
                less scandalous to the immortal gods than the case of the Alexandrians. <milestone
                    n="35" unit="section"/> Nor am I now attributing every action of this sort to
                you alone. There would be greater hope of safety if there were no other wicked man
                but you; but there are more, and on this account you feel more confidence, and we
                almost distrust the protection of the law. Who is there who is not aware that Plato,
                a man of high character and high rank in his own country, came from Orestis, which
                is a free part of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, to <placeName
                    key="tgn,7011182">Thessalonica</placeName>, as an ambassador to our general, as
                he called himself? and this great general of ours, being angry at not being able to
                extort money from him, threw him into prison, and sent his own physician to him, who
                in a most infamous and barbarous manner cut the veins of an ambassador, an ally, a
                friend, and a freeman. He did not wish his own forces to be made bloody by crime;
                but he polluted the name of the Roman people with such guilt that it cannot be
                expiated by any means but his own punishment. What sort of executioner must we think
                that this man has in his train, when he uses even his physicians not to procure
                health but to inflict death? <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="36"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But let us read what follows. “That good faith and oaths have been disregarded.” What
                this means by itself, I cannot easily explain; but from that which follows, I
                suspect that it refers to the manifest perjury of your judges, from whom, some time
                ago, the money which they had received would have been taken away, if they had not
                entreated the protection of the senate. And this is the reason why I <pb n="87"/>
                imagine that they are the persons alluded to, because I lay it down as a fact that
                that is the most remarkable and notorious perjury ever committed in this city and
                yet that you yourself are not threatened with the punishment of perjury by those men
                with whom you conspired. <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>And I see that in the answers of the soothsayers this is added: “But the ancient and
                secret sacrifices have been performed with less than due diligence and have been
                polluted.” Are they the soothsayers who say this or the gods of our country and our
                household gods? I suppose there are many persons to whom a suspicion of this guilt
                attaches;—who but this one man? Is it mentioned obscurely what sacrifices have been
                polluted? What can be expressed in a plainer, more dignified or more solemn manner?
                “Ancient and secret.” I say that Lentulus, a dignified and eloquent orator, did not
                when he was accusing you, make use of any expressions more frequently than these
                which now are extracted from the Etruscan books and turned against and applied to
                you. In truth what sacrifice is there so ancient as this, which we have received
                from the kings and which is contemporary with the city itself? But what is so secret
                as that which excludes not only all curious eyes but even all accidental ones? Which
                not only no wickedness, but which even no unintentional chance can penetrate? That
                sacrifice no one, ever since the world began, has ever profaned, no one has ever
                approached no one has ever disregarded no man has ever thought of beholding without
                horror before Publius Clodius. It is performed by the vestal virgins; it is
                performed on behalf of the Roman people; it is performed in the house of a supreme
                magistrate; it is performed with incredible solemnity; it is performed to that
                goddess whose very name it is not lawful for men to know, and whom that fellow calls
                Good, because she has pardoned him such enormous wickedness <milestone n="18"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>She has not pardoned you, believe me. No; unless, perchance, you think yourself
                pardoned because the judges dismissed you after they had squeezed and drained
                everything out of you, acquitted by their decision, condemned by all the rest of the
                citizens; or because you have not been deprived of your eyes, as is, according to
                the common belief the consequence of such impiety. <milestone n="38" unit="section"
                /> For what man ever intentionally <pb n="88"/> beheld those sacred rites before
                you, so as to enable any one to know what punishment followed that guilt? Could the
                blindness of your eyes be a greater injury to you than that blindness of your lust?
                Do not even you feel that those winking eyes of your ancestor<note anchored="true"
                    >Appius Claudius, surnamed Caecus, or the Blind.</note> were more desirable for
                you than these glowing eyes of your sister? But, if you observe carefully, you will
                see that though you have as yet escaped the punishment of men, you have not escaped
                that of the gods. Men have defended you in a most shameful affair; men have praised
                you though most infamous and most guilty; men, for a bribe, have acquitted you by
                their decision, though you all but confessed your guilt; men have felt no
                indignation at the injuries inflicted on themselves by your lust; men have supplied
                you with arms, some wishing them to be used against me, and others afterwards
                intending them to he employed against that invincible citizen. I will quite admit
                all the kindnesses which men have shown you, and that you need not wish for greater.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/> But what greater punishment can be inflicted
                on man by the immortal gods than frenzy and madness? unless, perhaps, you think that
                those persons, whom in tragedies you see tortured and destroyed by wounds and agony
                of body, are enduring a more terrible form of the wrath of the immortal gods than
                those who are brought on the stage in a state of insanity. Those howlings and groans
                of Philoctetes are not so pitiable (sad though they be) as that exultation of
                Athamas, or that dream of those who have slain their mother. You, when you are
                uttering your frantic speeches to the assembly—when you are destroying the houses of
                the citizens—when you are driving virtuous men from the forum with stones—when you
                are hurling burning firebrands at your neighbours' houses—when you are setting fire
                to holy temples —when you are stirring up the slaves—when you are throwing the
                sacred rites and games into confusion—when you see no difference between your wife
                and your sister—when you do not perceive whose bed it is that you enter—when you go
                ranting and raging about—you are then suffering that punishment which is the only
                one appointed by the immortal gods for the wickedness of men. For the infirmity of
                our bodies is of itself liable to many accidents; moreover, the body itself is often
                destroyed by some very trivial cause; and <pb n="89"/> the darts of the gods are
                fixed in the minds of impious men. Wherefore you are more miserable while you are
                hurried into every sort of wickedness by your eyes, than you would be if you had no
                eyes at all. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="40" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>But since enough has been said of all these offences which the soothsayers say have
                been committed, let us see now what these same soothsayers say that we are being
                warned of at this time by the immortal gods. They warn us “to take care that
                bloodshed and danger be not brought upon the senators and chief men of the state,
                through the discord and dissension of the nobles; and that our senators do not
                become disheartened from being deprived of support by which the provinces may fall
                under the power of a single master, and our armies be defeated, and a great loss of
                power ensue.” All these are the words of the soothsayers, I am not adding any thing
                of my own. Who then of the nobles is it who is causing this discord? The same man
                and that not by any force of his own genius or wisdom but by some blundering of ours
                which he—for it was not very much concealed—easily perceived. For this consideration
                makes the present distress of the republic the more shameful, that even by him it is
                not afflicted in such a way that it may seem to fall like a brave man in battle,
                having received honourable wounds in front from a gallant foe. </p>
            <p><milestone n="41" unit="section"/> Tiberius Gracchus overturned the constitution of
                the state, a man of such great force of character, and eloquence, and dignity, that
                he fell short in no respect of the surpassing and eminent virtue of his father, and
                of his grandfather, Africanus, except in the fact of his revolting from the senate.
                Caius Gracchus followed in his steps. How great was his genius! how great his
                energy! how impetuous his eloquence! so that all men grieved that all those good
                qualities and accomplishments were not joined to a better disposition and to better
                intentions. Lucius Saturninus himself was so furious and almost insane a man, that
                he was an admirable leader,—perfect in exciting and inflaming the minds of the
                ignorant. For why should I speak of Publius Sulpicius? whose dignity, and sweetness,
                and emphatic conciseness in speaking was so great that he was able by his oratory to
                lead even wise men into error, and virtuous men into pernicious sentiments. To be
                battling with these men, and to be duly struggling with them <pb n="90"/> for the
                safety of the country, was a very annoying thing to those men who were at that time
                the governors of the republic, but still that annoyance had a certain sort of
                dignity in it. <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="42" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>But as for this man, about whom I am now saying so much, O ye immortal gods! what is
                he? what is his influence? what is there about him to give so great a city, if it
                does fall, (may the gods avert the omen!) the comfort of at least seeming to have
                been overthrown by a man? a fellow who, from the moment of his father's death, made
                his tender age subservient to the lusts of wealthy buffoons; when he had satiated
                their licentiousness, then he turned to the domestic seduction of his own sister;
                then, when he had become a man, he devoted himself to the concerns of a province,
                and to military affairs, and suffered insults from the pirates; he satisfied the
                lusts even of Cilicians and barbarians: afterwards, having in a most wicked manner
                tampered with the army of Lucius Lucullus, he fled from thence, and at <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, the moment of his arrival there, he began
                to compound with his own relations not to prosecute them, and received money from
                Catiline to prevaricate in the most shameless manner. From thence he went into
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000070">Gaul</placeName> with Murena; in which province he
                forged wills of dead people, murdered wards, and made bargains and partnerships or
                wickedness with many. When he returned from <placeName key="tgn,1000070"
                    >Gaul</placeName>, he appropriated to himself all that most fruitful and
                abundant source of gain which is derived from the <placeName key="tgn,7006964"
                    >Campus Martius</placeName>, in such a manner that he (a man wholly devoted to
                the people!) cheated the people in a most scandalous manner, and also (merciful man
                that he is!) put the canvassers of the different tribes to death at his own house in
                the most cruel manner. Then came his quaestorship, so fatal to the republic, to our
                sacrifices, to our religions observances, to your authority, and to the public
                courts of justice; in which he insulted gods and men, virtue, modesty, the authority
                of the senate, every right both human and divine, and the laws and the tribunals of
                the country. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/> And this was his first step; this
                (alas for the miserable times and for our senseless discords!) was the first step of
                Publius Clodius towards the conduct of the affairs of the republic; this was the
                path by which he first began to approach and mount up to his present boast of being
                a friend of the people. For <pb n="91"/> the unpopularity arising from the treaty at
                    <placeName key="tgn,7017511">Numantia</placeName>, at the making of which he had
                been present as quaestor to Caius Mancinus the consul, and the severity displayed by
                the senate in repudiating that treaty, were a constant source of grief and fear to
                Tiberius Gracchus; and that circumstance alienated him, a brave and illustrious man,
                from the wisdom of the senators. And Caius Gracchus was excited by the death of his
                brother, by affection for him, by indignation, and by the greatness of his own mind,
                to seek to exact vengeance for the slaughter of a member of his family. We know that
                Saturninus was led to confess himself a friend of the people out of indignation,
                because at a time of great dearness of provisions, the senate removed him while he
                was quaestor from the superintendence of the corn market which belonged to him by
                virtue of his office, and appointed Marcus Scaurus to manage that business. And it
                was the breeze of popularity which carried Sulpicius further than he intended, after
                he had set out in a good cause, and had resisted Caius Julius when seeking to obtain
                the consulship contrary to the laws. <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="44" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>All these men had a reason,—not an adequate one, indeed, (for no one can have an
                adequate reason for proving a bad citizen to the republic,) but still they had a
                serious reason, and one connected with some indignation of mind not unbecoming to a
                man. Publius Clodius came out as a popular character from saffron gowns and turbans,
                and woman's slippers, and purple bands, and stomachers, and singing, and iniquity,
                and adultery. If the women had not caught him in this dress, if he had not been
                allowed to escape by the indulgence of the maid servants, from a place which it was
                impious for him to enter, the Roman people would have lost their devoted friend, the
                republic would have been deprived of so energetic a citizen. It is in consequence of
                this insane conduct, amid our dissensions, for which we are by these recent
                prodigies admonished by the immortal gods, that one of the patricians has been taken
                from their number to be made a tribune of the people, in direct violation of the
                laws. <milestone n="45" unit="section"/> That which, the year before, his brother
                Metellus and the senate, which even then was unanimous, had refused, and in the most
                rigorous manner rejected with one voice and one mind, Cnaeus Pompeius being the
                first to declare his opinion; (so greatly, after the dissensions of the nobles of
                which we are now <pb n="92"/> reminded, were circumstances disturbed and altered;)
                that which his brother when consul opposed being done,—which his kinsman and
                companion, a most illustrious man, who had refused to speak in his favour when he
                was accused, had utterly prevented,—was now effected for him, owing to the
                dissensions of the nobles, by that man as consul, who, of all others, was bound to
                be his greatest enemy; and he said that he had done it by the advice of that man
                whose authority no one could repent having followed. A most shameful and grievous
                firebrand was thrown into the republic. Your authority was aimed at; and the dignity
                of the most honourable orders in the city, and the unanimity of all virtuous men,
                and in short, the entire constitution of the state. For these things were certainly
                attacked when that flame kindled at that time was directed against me, who had been
                the principal investigator of these matters. I bore the brunt of the attack, and I
                alone suffered on behalf of my country; but still I bore it so that you, while you
                were surrounded by the same flames, saw me wounded first and burning, as it were, in
                your defence. <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="46" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>The dissensions were not appeased; but the unpopularity of those men, by whom we
                thought that our cause was espoused, even increased. So, after a time, the very same
                men being the movers, and Pompeius the chief man, who roused <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> willing to be roused, and the Roman people
                which regretted me, and you who demanded me back, to take measures for my safety,
                employing not only his authority but even his prayers, I was restored. Let there be
                an end of discord, let us at last find rest from our long dissensions. No, that pest
                will not allow it; he summons these assemblies, he throws everything into confusion
                and disorder, selling himself sometimes to one party, sometimes to another; and yet
                not in such a manner that any one thinks himself the more praiseworthy for being
                praised by him; though at the same time they are glad that those whom they do not
                like, are abused by him. And I do not marvel at this fellow; for what else can he
                do? I do marvel at those wise and respectable men; in the first place, that they so
                easily allow any illustrious man who has deserved well of the republic to be
                attacked by the voice of a most profligate man; in the second place, that they
                think, (it would be a most disastrous thing for themselves if the fact <pb n="93"/>
                were so,) that the real glory and dignity of any one can be impaired by the abuse of
                an abandoned and worthless man; and lastly, that they do not see, what however, they
                do seem to me to have some suspicion of, that those frantic and desultory attacks of
                his may some day or other be turned against themselves. <milestone n="47"
                    unit="section"/> And it is owing to this undue alienation of some persons from
                others that those arrows now stick in the republic which, as long as they stuck in
                me alone, I bore,—with pain, indeed, but still not as thinking them of any great
                importance. Could that fellow, if he had not first given himself up to those men
                whose minds he thought were alienated from your authority,—if he had not, admirable
                authority that he is! extolled them to the skies with his panegyric,—if he had not
                threatened that he would let loose the army of Caius Caesar (though in that he spoke
                falsely, but no one contradicted him,) that he would, I say set on that army with
                hostile standards against the senate-house if he had not cried out that he was doing
                what he was by the assistance of Cnaeus Pompeius, and at the instigation of Marcus
                Crassus,—if he had not declared (the only word of truth that he spoke) that the
                consuls had united their cause with him;—could he, I say, ever have been so cruel an
                enemy to me or so wicked a disturber of the republic? <milestone n="23"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="48" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>After that, when he saw you recovering your breath after your fear of bloodshed, when
                he saw your authority rising again above the waves of that slavery, and the
                recollection of, and regret for me, getting more vivid, then he began on a sudden to
                sell himself to you, though with the most treacherous design. Then he began to say,
                both here in this house and in the assemblies of the people, that the Sullan laws
                had been passed in opposition to the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>;
                among which laws was that <foreign xml:lang="la">lex curiata</foreign> on which the
                whole of his tribuneship depended, though he was too frantic to see that. He brought
                forward that most fearless man Marcus Bibulus. He asked him whether he had not
                always been observing the heavens when Caius Caesar was carrying those laws? He
                replied, that he always had been observing them at that time. He asked the augurs
                whether laws which had been passed under these circumstances had been duly passed?
                They said, such a proceeding was irregular. Some people, virtuous men, and men who
                had done great service to me, began to extol him; utterly ignorant I imagine, of the
                lengths to which his <pb n="94"/> madness could carry him. He proceeded further. He
                began to inveigh against Cnaeus Pompeius, the originator, as he was accustomed to
                boast, of all his designs. He gained great popularity in the people's eyes.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/> But then, when he had become elated by the
                hope that he might be able—as he had by his abominable wickedness crushed, as he
                fancied him who, though in the garb of peace, had proved the suppressor of domestic
                war—to put down also that great man who had been the conqueror of our foreign wars
                and foreign enemies, then was seized in the temple of Castor that wicked dagger
                which was nearly the destroyer of this empire. Then he, against whom no enemy's city
                had ever long continued shut—he, who had always broken through all straits, trampled
                on all heights, crushed, by his energy and valour, the opposing weapons of every
                foe, was himself besieged at home; and, by the counsels which he adopted, relieved
                me from the reproaches cast on my timidity by some ignorant people. For if it was
                miserable rather than disgraceful to Cnaeus Pompeius, that bravest of all men who
                have ever been born, not to be able to go abroad in the sight of men, and to be
                secluded from all public places, as long as that fellow was tribune of the people,
                and to put up with his threats, when he said in the public assembly that he wished
                to build a second piazza in Carinae,<note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >Carinae</foreign> was the name of one of the finest streets in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. It is mentioned as such by Virgil,
                        (<bibl n="Verg. A. 8.361"><title>Aen.</title> viii. 361</bibl>): <quote
                        xml:lang="la">
                        <l>Passimque armenta videbant </l>
                        <l>Romanoque foro, et lautis mugire Carinis.</l>
                    </quote> And in that street was Pompey's house.</note> to correspond to the one
                on the <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine Hill</placeName>; certainly, for me to
                leave my house was grievous as far as my own private grief was concerned, but
                glorious if you look only at the interests of the republic. <milestone n="24"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="50" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>You see, then, that this fellow, when, as far as his own efforts went, he had been
                long since overthrown and crushed, was aroused again by the mischievous discords of
                the nobles; and the first beginnings of his fury were upheld by those who at that
                time appeared alienated from you. It is by these detractors and enemies that the
                remainder of the acts of his tribuneship have been defended, even since that
                tribuneship was over. They are the men who resisted that pest <pb n="95"/> being
                removed from the republic; they prevented his being prosecuted; they resisted his
                being reduced to the condition of a private citizen. Is it possible that any
                virtuous men could have cherished in their bosom and have taken pleasure in, that
                poisonous and deadly viper? By what bribe were they cajoled? I wish, say they, that
                there should be some one in the assembly to disparage Pompeius. Can he disparage him
                by his abuse? I wish that that great man, who has contributed so greatly to my
                safety, may receive what I say in the same spirit as I say it. At all events, I will
                say what I feel. I declare to God, that there was no time that fellow appeared to be
                detracting so much from his exceeding dignity as when he was extolling him with the
                most extravagant praises. <milestone n="51" unit="section"/> Was Caius Marius, I
                pray you, more illustrious when Caius Glaucia was praising him, or when he became
                angry afterwards and abused him? Or, was this madman, who has been so long rushing
                headlong on punishment and destruction, more foul-mouthed and shameless when
                accusing Pompeius than he had been when reviling the whole senate? But I do marvel
                that though the former conduct may have been pleasing to angry men, the other course
                should not have been odious to such good citizens. But, lest this should any longer
                please excellent men, let them just read this harangue of his, of which I speak: in
                which, shall I say, he extols, or rather debases Pompeius? Undoubtedly he extols
                him, and says, that he is the only man in the city worthy of the glory of this
                empire; and hints that he is an exceedingly great friend of his, and that they are
                entirely reconciled. <milestone n="52" unit="section"/> And although I do not
                exactly know what he means yet I am sure that, if he were a friend to Pompeius, he
                would not praise him. For, if he were his greatest enemy, what could he do more to
                diminish his credit? Let those, who were glad that he was an enemy to Cnaeus
                Pompeius, and who, on that account winked at his numerous and enormous crimes, and
                who sometimes even accompanied his unbridled and furious acts of frenzy with their
                applause, observe how quickly he has turned round. For now he is praising him; he is
                inveighing against those men to whom he previously sold himself. What do you suppose
                he will do if a door to reconciliation with him should become really open to him,
                when he is so eager to spread a belief in such a reconciliation? <pb n="96"/>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="53" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>What other dissensions among the nobles can I suppose are pointed out by the immortal
                gods? For by this expression Publius Clodius is surely not meant nor any one of his
                gang or of his counselors. The Etruscan books have certain names which may fit some
                of that class of citizens. “Worthless men, rejected candidates,” as you shall
                presently hear, they call them, whose minds and estates are ruined, and utterly
                alienated from the general welfare. Wherefore when the immortal gods warn us of the
                discords of the nobles, they speak of the dissensions between illustrious citizens
                who have deserved well of the republic. When they predict danger and slaughter to
                the chief men, they leave Clodius safe enough, a man who is as far from the chief
                men as he is from virtuous or holy men. It is for you and for your safety, O most
                illustrious and most virtuous citizens, that they see that it behoves them to
                consult and to provide. <milestone n="54" unit="section"/> Slaughter of the chief
                men is indicated; that is added which must inevitably follow the death of the
                nobles. We are warned to take care that the republic does not fall under the
                absolute dominion of a single individual. And even if we were not led to this fear
                by the warning of the gods, still we ourselves, of our own accord, by our own senses
                and conjectures, should he forced to entertain it. For there is not usually any
                other termination to dissensions between eminent and powerful men, except either
                universal destruction, or the domination of the victorious party, or regal power.
                Lucius Sulla, a most noble and gallant consul, quarreled with Caius Marius, a most
                illustrious citizen. Each of these men, when defeated, fell so completely that the
                conqueror became a king. Cinna quarreled with his colleague Octavius. To each of
                these men prosperity gave kingly power, and adversity brought death. The same Sulla
                became victorious a second time. <milestone n="55" unit="section"/> And that time,
                beyond all question, he exercised regal power, though he re-established the
                republic. There is at this moment a hatred not concealed but implanted deeply, and
                burnt as it were into their minds, subsisting between men of the very highest rank.
                The chief men of the state are at variance. Every occasion is eagerly caught at.
                That party which is not so powerful as the other is nevertheless waiting for some
                change of fortune and for some favourable opportunity. That party which without
                dispute is the more powerful, is still perhaps at times afraid of the <pb n="97"/>
                designs and opinions of its enemies. Let this discord be which are foreshown by
                these prodigies will be banished from the state. In a moment that serpent which is
                at present lurking about here will emerge and be brought to light, and will be
                strangled, and crushed, and die. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>For the soothsayers warn us to take care that the republic is not injured by secret
                designs. What designs are more secret than those of that man who dared to say in the
                public assembly that a suspension of the courts of justice ought to be proclaimed;
                that the jurisdiction of the judges ought to be interrupted, and the treasury shut
                and all trials put an end to? Unless perhaps you think that all this confusion and
                overthrow of the constitution could occur to him all on a sudden, while in the
                rostrum, and that he was not speaking after mature deliberation. The man is full of
                wine, lust, and sleep, full of the most inconsiderate and insane rashness; but still
                it was in his nocturnal vigils, and in a numerous company, that that suspension of
                justice was planned and concocted. Remember, O conscript fathers, that your ears
                were being experimented on by that expression, and that a most mischievous road was
                being made to them by accustoming you to hear it. <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>These words follow: “That more honour must not he given to worthless citizens and
                rejected candidates.” Let us see who are the rejected candidates; for I will show
                you afterwards who are the worthless citizens. But still all men must allow that
                this expression suits that man above all other who is beyond all question the most
                worthless of all mortals. Who then, are the rejected candidates? Not, I imagine,
                they who some time or other have failed to attain some honour more by the fault of
                the city than by their own. For that is a thing which has frequently happened to
                many most excellent citizens and most honourable men. Those are the rejected
                candidates meant, whom, when they were proceeding to the most violent measures, when
                they were preparing exhibitions of gladiators contrary to the laws, when they were
                bribing in the most open manner, not only strangers, but even their own relations,
                their neighbours, the men of their own tribe, towns-people and countrymen, all
                rejected. We are warned not to confer any additional honours on these men. It ought
                to be <pb n="98"/> a very acceptable admonition that they give us; but still the
                Roman people itself, of its own accord, without any warning on the part of the
                soothsayers, has provided against this evil. <milestone n="57" unit="section"/> O
                you worthless men, beware; and there is a great multitude of you; but still this man
                is the leader and chief of the whole band. In truth, if any poet of splendid genius
                were to wish to bring on the stage one most worthless man, deformed with all sorts
                of imaginary vices collected from all quarters, he would not, I pledge myself, be
                able to discover one disgraceful quality which did not exist in this man, and he
                would pass over many which are deeply implanted and firmly rooted in him. <milestone
                    n="27" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>In the first place nature attaches us to our parents, and to the immortal gods, and
                to our country. For at one and the same time we are brought forth to the light, and
                we are strengthened so as to grow by the breath of heaven which we feel around us,
                and we are established in a certain abode as citizens and free men. That fellow has
                jumbled in confusion the name of his parents, and his family sacrifices, and the
                memory of his family, and his family itself, by the assumption of the name of
                Fonteius. He has with unpardonable wickedness thrown into confusion the fires of the
                gods, their thrones, and tables, their secret hearths in the inmost recesses of the
                house, and sacrifices which were previously secret, and not only unseen by men, but
                even unheard-of by them; and besides all this he has set fire to the temple of those
                goddesses by whose aid people come to bring assistance in the case of other fires.
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Why should I mention his country? when in the first place by violence and arms, and
                dread of personal danger, he drove away from the city and from all the protection
                afforded him by his country that citizen whom you had decided over and over again to
                have been the saviour of his country. In the second place, having overthrown the
                companion of the senate, as I have always said, but its leader as he used to call
                him, he by violence, bloodshed, and conflagration, threw into confusion the senate
                itself, the mainstay of the general safety and of the public good sense; he
                abolished two laws, the Aelian and Fufian laws, which were of especial advantage to
                the state; he extinguished the censorship; he took away the power of intercession;
                he abolished the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>; he armed <pb n="99"/>
                the consuls, the companions of his wickedness, with the treasury, and provinces, and
                an army; he sold the kings who were in existence, and he called men kings who were
                not so; he drove Cnaeus Pompeius to his house with violence and arms; he overthrew
                the monuments of our generals; he threw down the houses of his enemies; he inscribed
                his own name on your monuments. The wicked deeds which have been done by him to the
                injury of his country are innumerable. Why need I tell what he has done to
                individual citizens, whom he has slain? Why need I count up the allies whom he has
                plundered? or the generals whom he has betrayed? or the armies with which he has
                tampered? <milestone n="59" unit="section"/> Why need I mention what enormous
                wickednesses they are which he has been guilty of towards himself, and towards his
                own relations? Who ever showed less mercy to the camp of an enemy than he has shown
                to every part of his own person? What ship in a public river was ever so open to all
                men as his youth was? What spendthrifts ever lived in so unrestrained a manner with
                prostitutes as he did with his own sisters? In short what enormous Charybdis could
                the poets ever describe or ever imagine, capable of swallowing down such whirlpools
                as the plunder of the Byzantines and Brogitari which that fellow has sucked down? or
                what Scylla with such conspicuous and hungry hounds as the Gellii, and Clodii, and
                Titii with which you see that fellow devouring the rostrum itself? <milestone n="60"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore, and that is the last sentence in the answers of the soothsayers, “Beware
                that the constitution of the republic be not changed.” In truth it is only with
                difficulty, even if we prop it up on all sides, that the constitution, already
                undermined and resting on all our shoulders, will be able to be kept together.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>This state was once so firm and so vigorous that it could withstand the indifference
                of the senate, or even the assaults of the citizens. Now it cannot. There is no
                treasury. Those who have contracted for the revenues do not enjoy them; the
                authority of the chief men has fallen; the agreement between the different orders of
                the state is torn asunder; the courts of justice are destroyed; the votes are all
                arranged and divided so as to be under the power of a few; the courage of the
                virtuous citizens, formerly ready at a <pb n="100"/> nod from our order, exists no
                longer. <milestone n="61" unit="section"/> Henceforth in vain will you look for a
                citizen who will expose himself to unpopularity for the welfare of his country. We
                can then preserve even this state of things which now exists, such as it is, by no
                other means than by unanimity; for although we may become better off, that cannot
                even be hoped for as long as he is unpunished. And if we are to be worse off than we
                are, there is but one step slower, that of death or slavery. And the immortal gods
                themselves warn us against allowing ourselves to be thrust down into that abyss,
                since all human counsels have long since failed. </p>
            <p>And I, O conscript fathers, should not have undertaken this speech, so melancholy and
                so serious; not but that owing to the honours conferred on me by the Roman people,
                and to the numberless distinctions which you have heaped upon me, I am both bound
                and able to support this character and to play this part; but still, when every one
                else was silent, I should willingly have remained silent too. All this speech which
                I have made has not proceeded from my authority, but from my regard for the general
                religion. My words have, perhaps, been too many, but the whole sentiment has
                proceeded from the soothsayers. And either you ought never to have referred the
                prodigies which have been reported to you to them at all, or else you must be
                influenced by their answers. <milestone n="62" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But if other more ordinary and more trifling occurrences have often influenced us,
                shall not the express voice of the immortal gods influence every one's mind? Do not
                think that really possible, which you often see in plays, that some god descending
                from heaven can approach the assemblies of men, and abide on earth, and converse
                with men. Consider the description of noise which the Latins have reported. Remember
                that prodigy also, which has not as yet been formally reported, that at almost the
                same time a terrible earthquake is said to have taken place in the Picenian
                district, at <placeName key="perseus,Potentia">Potentia</placeName>, with many other
                terrible circumstances;—these things which we foresee you will fear as impending
                over the city. <milestone n="63" unit="section"/> In truth, this ought almost to be
                considered as the voice and speech of the immortal gods, when the world itself and
                the air and the earth tremble with a certain unusual agitation, and prophecy to us
                with an unprecedented and incredible sound. <pb n="101"/> On this emergency we must
                appoint atonements and prayers as we are ordered; but it is easy to address prayers
                to those beings who of their own accord point out to us the path of safety. Our own
                internal quarrels and dissensions must be terminated by ourselves. </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
