<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 34</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="book">
                <head>Close of the Macedonian War</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the State was preoccupied by serious
                        wars, some hardly yet over and others threatening, an incident occurred
                        which though unimportant in itself resulted in a violent party conflict.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two of the tribunes of the plebs, M.
                        Fundanius and L. Valerius, had brought in a proposal to repeal the Oppian
                        Law. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This law had been made on the motion
                        of M. Oppius, a tribune of the plebs, during the consulship of Q. Fabius and
                        Tiberius Sempronius, when the strain of the Punic War was most severely
                        felt. It forbade any woman to have in her possession more than half an ounce
                        of gold, to wear a dress of various colours or to ride in a two-horsed
                        vehicle within a mile of the City or of any Roman town unless she was going
                        to take part in some religious function. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The two Brutuses-M. Junius and T. Junius-both tribunes of the plebs,
                        defended the law and declared that they would not allow it to be repealed;
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> many of the nobility came forward to
                        speak in favour of the repeal or against it; the Capitol was crowded with
                        supporters and opponents of the proposal; the matrons could not be kept
                        indoors either by the authority of the magistrates or the orders of their
                        husbands or their own sense of propriety. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        They filled all the streets and blocked the approaches to the Forum; they
                        implored the men who were on their way thither to allow the women to resume
                        their former adornments now that the commonwealth was flourishing and
                        private fortunes increasing every day. Their numbers were daily augmented by
                        those who came up from the country towns. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        At last they ventured to approach the consuls and praetors and other
                        magistrates with their demands. One of the consuls at all events was
                        inexorably opposed to their request-M. Porcius Cato. He spoke as follows in
                        defence of the law: </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If we had, each one of us, made it a rule
                        to uphold the rights and authority of the husband in our own households we
                        should not now have this trouble with the whole body of our women.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As things are now our liberty of
                        action, which has been checked and rendered powerless by female despotism at
                        home, is actually crushed and trampled on here in the Forum, and because we
                        were unable to withstand them individually we have now to dread their united
                        strength. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I used to think that it was a
                        fabulous story which tells us that in a certain island the whole of the male
                        sex was extirpated by a conspiracy amongst the women; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> there is no class of women from whom the gravest
                        dangers may not arise, if once you allow intrigues, plots, secret cabals to
                        go on. I can hardly make up my mind which is worse, the affair itself or the
                        disastrous precedent set up. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The latter
                        concerns us as consuls and magistrates; the former has to do more with you,
                        Quirites. Whether the measure before you is for the good of the commonwealth
                        or not is for you to determine by your votes; this tumult amongst the women,
                        whether a spontaneous movement or due to your instigation, M. Fundanius and
                        L. Valerius, certainly points to failure on the part of the magistrates, but
                        whether it reflects more on you tribunes or on the consuls I do not know.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It brings the greater discredit on you
                        if you have carried your tribunitian agitation so far as to create unrest
                        among the women, but more disgrace upon us if we have to submit to
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> laws being imposed upon us through
                        fear of a secession on their part, as we had to do formerly on occasions of
                        the secession of the plebs. It was not without a feeling of shame that I
                        made my way into the Forum through a regular army of women. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Had not my respect for the dignity and modesty of some
                        amongst them, more than any consideration for them as a whole, restrained me
                        from letting them be publicly rebuked by a consul, I should have said, 'What
                        is this habit you have formed of running abroad and blocking the streets and
                        accosting men who are strangers to you? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Could you not each of you put the very same question to your husbands at
                        home? Surely you do not make yourselves more attractive in public than in
                        private, to other women's husbands more than to your own? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> If matrons were kept by their natural modesty within
                        the limits of their rights, it would be most unbecoming for you to trouble
                        yourselves even at home about the laws which may be passed or repealed
                        here.' Our ancestors would have no woman transact even private business
                        except through her guardian, they placed them under the tutelage of parents
                        or brothers or husbands. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> We suffer them
                        now to dabble in politics and mix themselves up with the business of the
                        Forum and public debates and election contests. What are they doing now in
                        the public roads and at the street corners but recommending to the plebs the
                        proposal of their tribunes and voting for the repeal of the law. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Give the reins to a headstrong nature, to a
                        creature that has not been tamed, and then hope that they will themselves
                        set bounds to their licence if you do not do it yourselves. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> This is the smallest of those restrictions which
                        have been imposed upon women by ancestral custom or by laws, and which they
                        submit to with such impatience. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> What they
                        really want is unrestricted freedom, or to speak the truth, licence, and if
                        they win on this occasion what is there that they will not attempt? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Call to mind all the regulations
                        respecting women by which our ancestors curbed their licence and made them
                        obedient to their husbands, and yet in spite of all those restrictions you
                        can scarcely hold them in. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If you allow
                        them to pull away these restraints and wrench them out one after another,
                        and finally put themselves on an equality with their husbands, do you
                        imagine that you will be able to tolerate them? From the moment that they
                        become your fellows they will become your masters. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> But surely, you say, what they object to is having a
                        new restriction imposed upon them, they are not deprecating the assertion of
                        a right but the infliction of a wrong. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> No,
                        they are demanding the abrogation of a law which you enacted by your
                        suffrages and which the practical experience of all these years has approved
                        and justified. This they would have you repeal; that means that by
                        rescinding this they would have you weaken all. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> No law is equally agreeable to everybody, the only
                        question is whether it is beneficial on the whole and good for the majority.
                        If everyone who feels himself personally aggrieved by a law is to destroy it
                        and get rid of it, what is gained by the whole body of citizens making laws
                        which those against whom they are enacted can in a short time repeal?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I want, however, to learn the reason
                        why these excited matrons have run out into the streets and scarcely keep
                        away from the Forum and the Assembly. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Is
                        it that those taken prisoners by Hannibal-their fathers and husbands and
                        children and brothers-may be ransomed? The republic is a long way from this
                        misfortune, and may it ever remain so! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Still, when this did happen, you refused to do so in spite of their dutiful
                        entreaties. But, you may say, it is not dutiful affection and solicitude for
                        those they love that has brought them together; they are going to welcome
                        Mater Idaea on her way from Phrygian Pessinus. What pretext in the least
                        degree respectable is put forward for this female insurrection? <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> 'That we may shine,' they say, 'in gold and
                        purple, that we may ride in carriages on festal and ordinary days alike, as
                        though in triumph for having defeated and repealed a law after capturing and
                        forcing from you your votes.' </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "You have often heard me complain of the
                        expensive habits of women and often, too, of those of men, not only private
                        citizens but even magistrates, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> and I
                        have often said that the community suffers from two opposite vices-avarice
                        and luxury-pestilential diseases which have proved the ruin of all great
                        empires. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The brighter and better the
                        fortunes of the republic become day by day, and the greater the growth of
                        its dominion-and now we are penetrating into Greece and Asia, regions filled
                        with everything that can tempt appetite or excite desire, and are even
                        laying hands on the treasures of kings-so much the more do I dread the
                        prospect of these things taking us captive rather than we them. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> It was a bad day for this City, believe me, when
                        the statues were brought from Syracuse. I hear far too many people praising
                        and admiring those which adorn Athens and Corinth and laughing at the clay
                        images of our gods standing in front of their temples. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> I for my part prefer these gods who are propitious to
                        us, and I trust that they will continue to be so as long as we allow them to
                        remain in their present abodes. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the days of our forefathers Pyrrhus
                        attempted, through his ambassador Cineas, to tamper with the loyalty of
                        women as well as men by means of bribes. The Law of Oppius in restraint of
                        female extravagance had not then been passed, still not a single woman
                        accepted a bribe. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What do you think was
                        the reason? The same reason which our forefathers had for not making any law
                        on the subject; there was no extravagance to be restrained. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Diseases must be recognised before remedies are
                        applied, and so the passion for self-indulgence must be in existence before
                        the laws which are to curb it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What called
                        out the Licinian Law which restricted estates to 500 jugera except the keen
                        desire of adding field to field? What led to the passing of the Cincian Law
                        concerning presents and fees except the condition of the plebeians who had
                        become tributaries and taxpayers to the senate? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> It is not therefore in the least surprising that
                        neither the Oppian nor any other law was in those days required to set
                        limits to the expensive habits of women when they refused to accept the gold
                        and purple that was freely offered to them. If Cineas were to go in these
                        days about the City with his gifts, he would find women standing in the
                        streets quite ready to accept them. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> There are some desires of which I cannot
                        penetrate either the motive or the reason. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> That what is permitted to another should be forbidden to you may
                        naturally create a feeling of shame or indignation, but when all are upon
                        the same level as far as dress is concerned why should any one of you fear
                        that you will not attract notice? The very last things to be ashamed of are
                        thriftiness and poverty, but this law relieves you of both since you do not
                        possess what it forbids you to possess. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        The wealthy woman says, 'This levelling down is just what I do not tolerate.
                        Why am I not to be admired and looked at for my gold and purple? <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Why is the poverty of others disguised under
                        this appearance of law so that they may be thought to have possessed, had
                        the law allowed it, what it was quite out of their power to possess?' </p>
                    <p> Do you want, Quirites, to plunge your wives into a rivalry of this nature,
                        where the rich desire to have what no one else can afford, and the poor,
                        that they may not be despised for their poverty, stretch their expenses
                        beyond their means? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Depend upon it, as
                        soon as a woman begins to be ashamed of what she ought not to be ashamed of
                        she will cease to feel shame at what she ought to be ashamed of. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> She who is in a position to do so will get what
                        she wants with her own money, she who cannot do this will ask her husband.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The husband is in a pitiable plight
                        whether he yields or refuses; in the latter case he will see another giving
                        what he refused to give. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Now they are
                        soliciting other women's husbands, and what is worse they are soliciting
                        votes for the repeal of a law, and are getting them from some, against the
                        interest of you and your property and your children. When once the law has
                        ceased to fix a limit to your wife's expenses, you will never fix one. Do
                        not imagine that things will be the same as they were before the law was
                        made. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> It is safer for an evil-doer not to
                        be prosecuted than for him to be tried and then acquitted, and luxury and
                        extravagance would have been more tolerable had they never been interfered
                        with than they will be now, just like wild beasts which have been irritated
                        by their chains and then released. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> I give
                        my vote against every attempt to repeal the law, and pray that all the gods
                        may give your action a fortunate result." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this the tribunes of the plebs who
                        had announced their intention of vetoing the repeal spoke briefly to the
                        same effect. Then L. Valerius made the following speech in defence of his
                        proposal: "If it had been only private citizens who came forward to argue in
                        favour of, or against, the measure we have brought in, I should have awaited
                        your votes in silence as I should have considered that enough had been said
                        on either side. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But now, when a man of
                        such weight of character as M. Porcius, our consul, is opposing our bill,
                        not simply by exerting his personal authority which, even had he remained
                        silent, would have had very great influence, but also in a long and
                        carefully thought out speech, it is necessary to make a brief reply.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He spent, it is true, more time in
                        castigating the matrons than in arguing against the bill, and he even left
                        it doubtful whether the action of the matrons which he censured was due to
                        their own initiative or to our instigation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> I shall defend the measure and not ourselves, for that was thrown out as
                        a suggestion rather than as an actual charge. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Because we are now enjoying the blessings of peace and
                        the commonwealth is flourishing and happy, the matrons are making a public
                        request to you that you will repeal a law which was passed against them
                        under the pressure of a time of war. He denounces this action of theirs as a
                        plot, a seditious movement, and he sometimes calls it a female secession.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I know how these and other strong
                        expressions are selected to bolster up a case, and we all know that, though
                        naturally of a gentle disposition, Cato is a powerful speaker and sometimes
                        almost menacing. What innovation have the matrons been guilty of by publicly
                        assembling in such numbers for a cause which touches them so closely?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Have they never appeared in public
                        before? I will quote your own 'Origines' against you. Hear how often they
                        have done this and always to the benefit of the State. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> "At the very beginning, during the reign
                        of Romulus, after the capture of the Capitol by the Sabines, when a pitched
                        battle had begun in the Forum, was not the conflict stopped by the matrons
                        rushing between the lines? And when after the expulsion of the kings the
                        Volscian legions under their leader Caius Marcius had fixed their camp at
                        the fifth milestone from the City, was it not the matrons who warded off
                        that enemy by whom otherwise this City would have been laid in ruins?
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When it had been captured by the
                        Gauls, how was it ransomed? By the matrons, of course, who by general
                        agreement brought their contributions to the treasury. And without searching
                        for ancient precedents, was it not the case that in the late war when money
                        was needed the treasury was assisted by the money of the widows? <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Even when new deities were invited to help us in
                        the hour of our distress did not the matrons go in a body down to the shore
                        to receive Mater Idaea? You say that they were actuated by different motives
                        then. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It is not my purpose to establish
                        the identity of motives, it is sufficient to clear them from the charge of
                        strange unheard-of conduct. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And yet, in
                        matters which concern men and women alike, their action occasioned surprise
                        to no one; why then should we be surprised at their taking the same action
                        in a cause which especially interests them? But what have they done?
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> We must, believe me, have the ears of
                        tyrants if, whilst masters condescend to listen to the prayers of their
                        slaves we deem it an indignity to be asked a favour by honourable women.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "I come now to the matter of debate. Here
                        the consul adopted a twofold line of argument, for he protested against any
                        law being repealed and in particular against the repeal of this law which
                        had been passed to restrain female extravagance. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> His defence of the laws as a whole seemed to me such as
                        a consul ought to make and his strictures on luxury were quite in keeping
                        with his strict and severe moral code. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Unless, therefore, we show the weakness of both lines of argument there is
                        some risk of your being led into error. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As
                        to laws which have been made not for a temporary emergency, but for all time
                        as being of permanent utility, I admit that none of them ought to be
                        repealed except where experience has shown it to be hurtful or political
                        changes have rendered it useless. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But I
                        see that the laws which have been necessitated by particular crises are, if
                        I may say so, mortal and subject to change with the changing times.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Laws made in times of peace war
                        generally repeals, those made during war peace rescinds, just as in the
                        management of a ship some things are useful in fair weather and others in
                        foul. As these two classes of laws are distinct in their nature, to which
                        class would the law which we are repealing appear to belong? <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Is it an ancient law of the kings, coeval with
                        the City, or, which is the next thing to it, did the decemviri who were
                        appointed to <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> codify the laws inscribe it
                        on the Twelve Tables as an enactment without which our forefathers thought
                        that the honour and dignity of our matrons could not be preserved, and if we
                        repeal it shall we have reason to fear that we shall destroy with it the
                        self-respect and purity of our women? Who does not know that this is quite a
                        recent law passed twenty years ago in the consulship of Q. Fabius and
                        Tiberius Sempronius? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If the matrons led
                        exemplary lives without it, what danger can there possibly be of their
                        plunging into luxury if it is repealed? If that law had been passed with the
                        sole motive of limiting female excesses there might be some ground for
                        apprehension that the repeal might encourage them, but the circumstances
                        under which it was passed will reveal its object. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal was in Italy; he had won the
                        victory of Cannae; he was now master of Tarentum, Arpi and Capua; there was
                        every likelihood that he would bring his army up to Rome. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Our allies had fallen away from us, we had no reserves
                        from which to make good our losses, no seamen to render our navy effective,
                        and no money in the treasury. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> We had to
                        arm the slaves and they were bought from their owners on condition that the
                        purchase money should be paid at the end of the war; the contractors
                        undertook to supply corn and everything else required for the war, to be
                        paid for at the same date. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> We gave up our
                        slaves to act as rowers in numbers proportionate to our assessment and
                        placed all our gold and silver at the service of the State, the senators
                        setting the example. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Widows and minors
                        invested their money in the public funds and a law was passed fixing the
                        maximum of gold and silver coinage which we were to keep in our houses. Was
                        it at such a crisis as this that the matrons were so given to luxury that
                        the Oppian Law was needed to restrain them, when, owing to their being in
                        mourning, the sacrificial rites of Ceres had been intermitted and the senate
                        in consequence ordered the mourning to be terminated in thirty days?
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Who does not see that the poverty and
                        wretched condition of the citizens, every one of whom had to devote his
                        money to the needs of the commonwealth, were the real enactors of that law
                        which was to remain in force as long as the reason for its enactment
                        remained in force? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> If every decree made
                        by the senate and every order made by the people to meet the emergency is to
                        remain in force for all time, why are we repaying to private citizens the
                        sums they advanced? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Why are we making
                        public contracts on the basis of immediate payment? Why are slaves not being
                        purchased to serve as soldiers, and each of us giving up our slaves to serve
                            <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> as rowers as we did then? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "All orders of society, all men will feel
                        the change for the better in the condition of the republic; are our wives
                        alone to be debarred from the enjoyment of peace and prosperity? <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> We, their husbands, shall wear purple, the toga
                        praetexta will mark those holding magisterial and priestly offices, our
                        children will wear it, with its purple border; the right to wear it belongs
                        to the magistrates in the military colonies and the municipal towns.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor is it only in their lifetime that
                        they enjoy this distinction; when they die they are cremated in it. You
                        husbands are at liberty to wear a purple wrap over your dress, will you
                        refuse to allow your wives to wear a purple mantle? Are the trappings of
                        your horses to be more gorgeous than the dress of your wives? <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Purple fabrics, however, become frayed and worn
                        out, and in their case I recognise some reason, though a very unfair one,
                        for his opposition; but what is there to offend with regard to gold, which
                        suffers no waste except on the cost of working it? On the contrary, it
                        rather protects us in the time of need and forms a resource available for
                        either public or private requirements, as you have learnt by experience.
                        Cato said that there was no individual rivalry amongst them since none
                        possessed what might make others jealous. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        No, but most certainly there is general grief and indignation felt among
                        them when they see the wives of our Latin allies permitted to wear ornaments
                        which they have been deprived of, when <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        they see them resplendent in gold and purple and driving through the City
                        while they have to follow on foot, just as though the seat of empire was in
                        the Latin cities and not in their own. This would be enough to hurt the
                        feelings of men, what then think you must be the feelings of poor little
                        women who are affected by small things? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Magistracies, priestly functions, triumphs, military decorations and
                        rewards, spoils of war-none of these fall to their lot. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Neatness, elegance, personal adornment, attractive
                        appearance and looks-these are the distinctions they covet, in these they
                        delight and pride themselves; these things our ancestors called the ornament
                        of women. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What do they lay aside when they
                        are in mourning except their gold and purple, to resume them when they go
                        out of mourning? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> How do they prepare
                        themselves for days of public rejoicing and thanksgiving beyond assuming
                        richer personal adornment? I suppose you think that if you repeal the Oppian
                        Law, and should wish to forbid anything which the law forbids now, it will
                        not <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> be in your power to do so, and that
                        some will lose all legal rights over their daughters and wives and sisters.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> No; women are never freed from
                        subjection as long as their husbands and fathers are alive; they deprecate
                        the freedom which orphanhood and widowhood bring. They would rather leave
                        their personal adornment to your decision than to that of the law.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It is your duty to act as their
                        guardians and protectors and not treat them as slaves; you ought to wish to
                        be called fathers and husbands, instead of lords and masters. The consul
                        made use of invidious language when he spoke of female sedition and
                        secession. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Do you really think there is
                        any danger of their seizing the Sacred Mount as the exasperated plebs once
                        did, or of their taking possession of the Aventine? Whatever decision you
                        come to, they in their weakness will have to submit to it. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The greater your power, so much the more moderate ought
                        you to be in exercising it." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After these speeches in support of and
                        against the law the women poured out into the streets the next day in much
                        greater force and went in a <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> body to the
                        house of the two Brutuses, who were vetoing their colleagues' proposal, and
                        beset all the doors, nor would they desist till the tribunes had abandoned
                        their opposition. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was no doubt now
                        that the tribes would be unanimous in rescinding the law. It was abrogated
                        twenty years after it had been made. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After
                        this matter was settled Cato at once left the City and with twenty-five
                        ships of war, five of which belonged to the allies, sailed to the port of
                        Luna, where the army had also received orders to muster. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He had published an edict through the whole length of
                        the coast requiring ships of every description to be assembled at Luna, and
                        there he left orders that they should follow him to the Port of the
                        Pyrenees, it being his intention to advance against the enemy with his full
                        naval strength. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Sailing past the Ligurian
                        coast and the Gulf of Gaul, they assembled there by the appointed day. Cato
                        sailed on to Rhoda and expelled the Spanish garrison who were holding the
                        fort. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From Rhoda a favourable wind brought
                        him to Emporiae. Here he disembarked the whole of his force with the
                        exception of the crews of the vessels. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At that time Emporiae consisted of two
                        towns divided by a wall. One was inhabited by Greeks who had, like the
                        people of Massilia, originally come from Phocaea; the other contained a
                        Spanish population. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As the Greek town was
                        almost entirely open to the sea its walls were less than half a mile in
                        circuit; the Spanish town, further back from the sea, had walls with a
                        circuit of three miles. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A third element in
                        the population was formed by some Roman colonists who had been settled there
                        by the deified Caesar after the final defeat of Pompey's sons. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> At the present day all have been fused into one
                        municipal body by the grant of Roman citizenship, in the first instance to
                        the Spaniards and then to the Greeks. Anyone who saw how the Greeks were
                        exposed to attacks on the one side from the open sea and from the Spaniards
                        on the other side might wonder what there was that afforded them protection.
                        Discipline was the guardian of their weakness, a quality which among
                        stronger nations is best maintained by fear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> They kept that portion of the wall which faced inland extremely well
                        fortified, only one gate was situated on that side and it was always guarded
                        night and day by one of the magistrates. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        During the night one-third of the citizens were on duty on the walls, not
                        simply as a matter of routine or regulation, they kept up their watches and
                        patrols as if an enemy were at their gates. No Spaniards were allowed within
                        their city, nor did they themselves venture outside their walls without
                        proper precautions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The exits to the sea
                        were open to all. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They never went out
                        through the gate which faced the Spanish town unless a large number went
                        together, and it was generally the body who had mounted guard on the walls
                        the night before. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The object of their
                        going outside this gate was as follows: the Spaniards, unfamiliar with the
                        sea, were glad to purchase the goods which the Greeks received from abroad
                        and at the same time to sell the products of their fields to them. Owing to
                        the need of this mutual intercourse the Spanish city was always open to the
                        Greeks. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> An additional security was found
                        in the friendship of Rome, under whose shelter they lay and to which they
                        were quite as loyal as the Massilians, though their strength and resources
                        were so much less. On this occasion they gave the consul and his army a
                        hearty welcome. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Cato made a short stay
                        there, and while he was gaining intelligence as to the strength and position
                        of the enemy he spent the interval in exercising his troops, that they might
                        not waste their time. It happened to be the time of the year when the
                        Spaniards had their corn stored in the barns. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Cato forbade the army contractors to supply any corn to
                        the troops, and sent them back to Rome with the remark, "War feeds itself."
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then, advancing from Emporiae, he
                        laid the enemy's fields waste with fire and sword, and spread terror and
                        flight in all directions. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this time M. Helvius, who was on
                        his way from Further Spain with a force of 6000 men sent by the praetor
                        Appius Claudius to escort him, fell in with <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> an immense body of Celtiberians near the town of
                        Iliturgi. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Valerius states that they
                        amounted to 20,000 men and that 12,000 were killed, the town of Iliturgi
                        taken and all the adult males put to the sword. After this Helvius reached
                        Cato's camp and as the country was now safe he sent his escort back to
                        Further Spain and on his arrival at Rome celebrated his victory by entering
                        the City in ovation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He brought into the
                        treasury 732 pounds' weight of uncoined silver, 17,023 Spanish denarii, and
                        11,943 of Oscan silver. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The reason why the
                        senate refused him a triumph was that he had fought under another man's
                        auspices and in another man's province. Moreover he did not return till two
                        years after he had given up his command, for after handing over the
                        administration to his successor, Q. Minucius, he was detained in the
                        province by a long and dangerous illness. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        In consequence of this he entered the City only two months before Q.
                        Minucius celebrated his triumph. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        latter brought home 34,800 pounds' weight of silver, 73,000 denarii, and
                        278,000 of Oscan silver. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul in Spain was encamped not far
                        from Emporiae. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here he was approached by
                        three envoys from Bilistages, the chief of the Ilergetes, one of them the
                        chief's son. They reported that their strongholds were being attacked and
                        they were hopeless of making a successful resistance unless the Roman
                        general sent a force: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> 3000 men would be
                        sufficient; the enemy would not stay to fight if such a large body of troops
                        came into the field. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul told them
                        that he was greatly concerned for their danger and their fears, but his
                        numbers were by no means sufficient to allow of his reducing his strength by
                        dividing his forces while the enemy were so near and he was daily expecting
                        to have to fight a pitched battle with them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> On hearing this the envoys flung themselves in tears at the consul's feet
                        and implored him not to desert them in an hour of such sore distress.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Where could they, they cried, go if
                        they were repulsed by the Romans? They had no allies, no hope of succour
                        anywhere else in the world. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They could
                        have avoided this danger had they been willing to break faith and make
                        common cause with the rest of their countrymen. No threats, no intimidation
                        had moved them so long as they hoped to find sufficient help and support
                        from the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If there was none to be
                        had, if their request was refused by the consul, they called gods and men to
                        witness that, against their will and through sheer compulsion, they would
                        have to desert the cause of Rome lest they should suffer what the Saguntines
                        had suffered. They would rather perish with the rest of the Spaniards than
                        meet their fate alone. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys were dismissed for the day
                        without receiving any reply. The consul passed an anxious night trying to
                        decide between the two alternatives: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> he
                        did not want to desert his allies nor did he want to weaken his army, a
                        course which might possibly delay the decisive conflict, or, if it should
                        come on, endanger his success. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He finally
                        made up his mind not to part with any of his troops lest the enemy should
                        inflict some humiliation upon him, and he decided to hold out the hope of
                        assistance to his allies instead of actually giving it. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He reflected that promises have often been as effective
                        as performance, especially in war; to the man who believes that he has help
                        to fall back upon it is just the same as if he had it, his very belief
                        nerves him to hope and to dare. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next
                        day he gave his reply to the envoys, and assured them that though he was
                        afraid of weakening his force for the benefit of others, he nevertheless
                        made more account of the critical and dangerous position they were in than
                        he did of his own. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then ordered a third
                        of the men in each cohort to cook the food, which they were to take on board
                        in good time, and orders were at the same time issued for the ships to be
                        ready to sail in three days' time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He told
                        two of the envoys to report these measures to Bilistages and the Ilergetes;
                        the third, the chief's son, he succeeded, by his affability and the presents
                        he gave him, in keeping with him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        envoys did not leave until they saw the soldiers actually on board, then, no
                        longer feeling any doubts, they spread far and wide amongst friends and foes
                        the news of the approach of Roman succour. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consul had kept up appearances
                        long enough he recalled the soldiers from the ships, and as the season for
                        active operations was now approaching, he fixed his camp at a distance of
                        three miles from Emporiae. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From this
                        position he sent his men into the enemy's fields in quest of plunder, first
                        in one quarter and then in another as occasion served, leaving only a small
                        guard in the camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They generally started
                        at night in order to cover as great a distance from the camp as possible and
                        also to take the enemy by surprise. This kind of thing was a training for
                        the new levies and led to the capture of numerous prisoners, till the enemy
                        no longer ventured outside the defences of their forts. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When he had thoroughly tested the temper of his own men
                        and that of the enemy he ordered the military tribunes and prefects of the
                        allies, as well as all the cavalry and centurions, to appear on parade and
                        addressed them as follows: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "You have often
                        wished for the time when you might have an opportunity of displaying your
                        courage; that time has now come. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So far
                        your operations have resembled those of marauders rather than of warriors,
                        now you shall join issue with the enemy in a regular battle. Henceforth you
                        will be allowed, instead of ravaging fields, to drain cities of their
                        wealth. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the Carthaginian commanders
                        and armies were in Spain, our fathers had not a single soldier here, and yet
                        they insisted upon a clause being added to the treaty fixing the Ebro as the
                        boundary of their dominion. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Now, when a
                        consul, two praetors and three Roman armies are occupying Spain, and not a
                        single Carthaginian has been seen in this province for the last ten years,
                        our dominion on this side of the Ebro has been lost to us. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> It is your duty to win this back by your arms and
                        courage and to compel a nation, which starts a war in a spirit of
                        recklessness rather than of steady determination, to submit once more to the
                        yoke which it has cast off." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After these
                        words of encouragement he announced that he should lead them that night
                        against the enemy's camp. They were then dismissed to take food and rest.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After attending to the auspices the consul
                        started at midnight in order that he might take up the position which he
                        intended to secure before the enemy were aware of his movements. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> He led his troops round to the rear of the
                        enemy's camp and formed them into line at daybreak, after which he sent
                        three cohorts right up to the hostile rampart. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Startled by the appearance of the Romans behind their
                        lines, the barbarians flew to arms. Meanwhile the consul briefly addressed
                        his men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "There is no hope," he said,
                        "anywhere but in courage, and indeed I have taken care that there shall not
                        be. Between us and our camp is the enemy, and behind us enemy country. The
                        noblest course is also the safest, and that is to rest all your hopes in
                        your valour." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then he ordered the cohorts
                        to be recalled that their feigned retreat might draw the natives out of
                        their camp. His anticipations were realised. They thought that the Romans
                        had retired through fear, and bursting out of their camp they covered with
                        their numbers the whole of the ground between their camp and the Roman line
                        of battle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst they were hurriedly
                        forming their ranks the consul, whose dispositions were completed, commenced
                        the attack. The cavalry on the two wings were the first to get into action,
                        but those on the right were immediately repulsed and their hasty retirement
                        created alarm amongst the infantry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On
                        seeing this, the consul ordered two picked cohorts to be taken round the
                        enemy's right and to show themselves in his rear before the infantry became
                        engaged. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This menace to the enemy made the
                        battle a more even one; still, the right wing, both cavalry and infantry,
                        had become so demoralised that the consul seized some of them with his own
                        hand and turned them towards the foe. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As
                        long as the action was confined to the discharge of missiles it was equally
                        contested on both sides, but now the Roman right where the panic and flight
                        began was with difficulty holding its ground; the left, on the other hand,
                        was pressing back the barbarians in front, and the cohorts in the rear were
                        creating a panic amongst them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When they
                        had discharged their iron javelins and fire darts they drew their swords and
                        the fighting became more furious. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They
                        were no longer wounded by chance hits from a distance, but foot to foot with
                        the foe they had only their strength and courage to trust to. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Finding that his men were becoming
                        exhausted, the consul rekindled their courage by bringing up the reserves
                        from the second line. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The front was
                        re-formed, and these fresh troops attacking the wearied enemy with fresh
                        weapons made a fierce charge in a dense body and broke their lines, and once
                        broken they soon scattered in flight and rushed through the fields in the
                        direction of their camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When Cato saw the
                        whole battleground filled with fugitives he galloped back to the second
                        legion which was stationed in reserve, ordered the standards to be borne
                        before him and the whole legion to follow him at the double to attack the
                        hostile camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When a man in his eagerness
                        ran out of his rank the consul rode up and struck him with his sparus and
                        ordered the military tribunes and centurions to chastise him. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The attack on the camp had already begun, but the
                        Romans were unable to reach the stockade, as they were held up by stones and
                        stakes and every description of missile. The appearance of the fresh legion
                        put heart into the assailants and made the enemy fight still more
                        desperately in front of their breastwork. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The consul surveyed the whole position that he might find out where there
                        was the weakest resistance and therefore the best chance of breaking
                        through. He saw that the defenders were in least force at the left-hand gate
                        of their camp, and to this point he directed the hastati and principes of
                        the second legion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The defenders who were
                        holding the gate could not withstand their charge, and when the others saw
                        the enemy within their lines they abandoned all further attempts to retain
                        their camp and flung away their arms and standards. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Many were killed at the gates, jammed together by the
                        crowding in the narrow space, and whilst the soldiers of the second legion
                        were cutting the enemy from behind, the rest plundered the camp. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias says that more than 40,000 of the
                        enemy were killed that day. Cato, who certainly does not depreciate his own
                        merits, says that many were killed, but does not give the actual numbers.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> (He is considered to have done three
                        things on that day which deserve praise. One was his leading his army round
                        the hostile camp into a position far from his ships and his own camp where
                        his men had nothing to trust to but their courage, and also joining battle
                        with the enemy on both sides of him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        second was his maneuver of throwing the cohorts on the enemy's rear. The
                        third was his order to the second legion to advance in battle formation
                        right up to the gate of the camp while the rest of his troops were scattered
                        in pursuit of the enemy.) <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After this
                        battle the consul's victorious advance was uninterrupted. When the signal
                        had been given to retire and he had withdrawn his men loaded with spoil into
                        camp, he allowed them a few hours' rest and then led them off to harry the
                        fields. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As the enemy had been scattered in
                        flight they extended their depredations over a wider extent of country,
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> and this action contributed no less
                        than the battle to force the inhabitants of Spanish Emporiae and the
                        settlers amongst them to surrender; many from other communities who had
                        taken refuge in Emporiae also surrendered. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The consul addressed them all in kind terms and dismissed them to their
                        homes. He at once resumed his advance, and wherever his army marched
                        delegates from the various communities met him to make their surrender.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By the time he reached Tarraco the
                        whole of Spain on this side the Ebro had been subjugated and the soldiers
                        belonging to the Roman and allied troops who had through various mishaps
                        been made prisoners in Spain were brought by the natives as a gift to the
                        consul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then a rumour was spread that the
                        consul intended to take his army into Turdetania, and it was even
                        reported-quite falsely-that he had actually marched against the secluded
                        dwellers in the mountains. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On this idle
                        and absolutely groundless rumour seven fortified places belonging to the
                        Bergistani revolted. The consul reduced them to submission without any
                        serious fighting. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After he had returned
                        to Tarraco and before he made any further advance these same people again
                        revolted and again they were subdued, but they were not treated so
                        leniently. They were all sold into slavery to prevent any further
                        disturbance of peace. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the meantime the praetor, P. Manlius,
                        marched into Turdetania with the army which he had taken over from his
                        predecessor Q. Minucius and, in addition, the force which Appius Claudius
                        Nero had commanded in Further Spain. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        Turdetani are considered the least warlike of all the Spanish tribes;
                        nevertheless, trusting to their numbers, they ventured to oppose the Roman
                        armies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A cavalry charge threw them at
                        once into disorder; the infantry encounter was hardly a contest, the
                        seasoned troops, familiar with the tactics of the enemy, left no doubt as to
                        the issue of the fight. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Still, that battle
                        did not end the war. The Turduli hired a force of 10,000 Celtiberian
                        mercenaries and prepared to carry on hostilities with foreign arms.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While this was going on, the consul,
                        seriously perturbed by the rising of the Bergistani, and convinced that all
                        the other tribes would do the same whenever they had the chance, disarmed
                        the whole of the Spanish population on this side of the Ebro. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> This step aroused such bitter feeling that many
                        of them destroyed themselves, for they were a brave and high-spirited
                        nation, and did not think life worth living without the possession of arms.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On this being reported to the consul
                        he summoned the senators in all the cities to meet him. "It is not," he told
                        them, "more in our interest than in yours that you should abstain from
                        hostilities; hitherto your wars have always involved more suffering for the
                        Spaniards than toil and trouble for the Romans. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> I know of only one way in which this can be prevented,
                        and that is to put it out of your power to commence hostilities. I am
                        anxious to attain that result with as little harshness as possible.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> You must help me in this matter with
                        your advice. I shall adopt no plan more gladly than the one which you
                        yourselves suggest." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As they remained
                        silent, he said he would give them a few days for deliberation. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> After they had been summoned to a second
                        conference, at which they still remained silent, he levelled the walls of
                        all their cities in a single day, and during his advance against those which
                        were still refractory he received the submission of all the cities in each
                        district into which he came. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The sole
                        exception was Segestica, and this important and wealthy city he took by
                        storm. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The subjugation of the enemy was a more
                        difficult task for Cato than it had been for those generals who had entered
                        Spain for the first time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Spaniards
                        went over to them because they were sick of the domination of Carthage, but
                        Cato had, so to speak, to reclaim them like slaves who had asserted and
                        enjoyed freedom. He found commotion everywhere, some tribes were in arms,
                        others were having their cities besieged to drive them into revolt, and had
                        it not been for his timely succour their powers of resistance must have been
                        exhausted. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the consul was a man of
                        such force and energy that he took up and executed single-handed the
                        greatest and smallest tasks alike; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> he not
                        only thought out and gave directions as to what was best to be done, but he
                        carried most of his measures through personally. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Over no one in the army did he exercise severer
                        discipline than over himself; in his frugal mode of life, in his incessant
                        vigilance and hard work he rivalled the meanest of his soldiers. The only
                        privilege he enjoyed in his army was his rank and authority. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Turdetani, as I have already stated,
                        were employing Celtiberian mercenaries, and this added to the praetor's
                        difficulties in his campaign against them. He wrote to Cato for assistance
                        and the consul marched his legions thither, and found on arrival that the
                        Celtiberians and the Turdetani were occupying separate camps. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> With the Turdetanian patrols encounters commenced
                        at once and the Romans always came off victorious, however desultory the
                        fighting. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians were treated
                        differently; the consul ordered the military tribunes to go to them and give
                        them the choice of three courses: to go over to the Romans and receive
                        double the pay that they were to get <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                        from the Turdetanians, or to depart to their homes under a guarantee from
                        the Roman Government that they should not suffer for having joined
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> their enemies, or, if they were in
                        any case bent on war, to fix a time and place where they could decide the
                        matter by arms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians asked for
                        a day's grace for consultation. A council was held, but owing to the
                        presence of the Turdetani and the confusion and disorder which prevailed, no
                        decision could be arrived at. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whilst the
                        question of war or peace was still in suspense the Romans <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> were bringing provisions from the fields and fortified
                        villages of the enemy, and often entered their entrenchments as many as ten
                        at a time, just as though there was a tacit truce admitting of general
                        intercourse. As the consul could not induce the enemy to fight, he sent some
                        light-armed cohorts on a plundering expedition into a part of the country
                        which had not yet suffered spoliation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        next marched to Segestia with the view of attacking it, as he heard that all
                        the baggage and personal belongings of the Celtiberians had been left there.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As, however, nothing would make them
                        move, he returned <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> with an escort of
                        seven cohorts to the Ebro, after discharging the arrears of pay to his own
                        men and to the praetor's army as well. The whole of his army he left in the
                        praetor's camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Small as the force was which he had with
                        him, the consul captured several towns; the Sedetani, the Ausetani, and the
                        Suessetani went over to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Lacetani,
                        a remote forest tribe, remained in arms, partly through their native love of
                        fighting and partly through the fear of retribution from the tribes friendly
                        to Rome, amongst whom they had made plundering raids whilst the consul was
                        occupied with the war against the Turdetani. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> It was for this reason that the consul brought up to attack them not only
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> his Roman cohorts but also the
                        troops of the friendly tribes who had their own accounts to settle with
                        them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their town was considerably greater
                        in length than in breadth. The consul halted his men a little less than half
                        a mile from the place. Leaving some picked cohorts on guard with strict
                        orders not to move from the spot till he returned to them, he led the rest
                        of his force round to the further side of the town. His auxiliaries were
                        mostly Suessetani, and he ordered them to advance up to the walls for the
                        assault. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As soon as the Lacetani
                        recognised their arms and standards and remembered how often they had raided
                        their fields with impunity and routed and scattered them in battle they
                        flung open their gates and all in a body rushed upon them. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The Suessetani did not wait for their battle-shout,
                        much less their charge. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consul
                        expected this, and on seeing what had happened he galloped close under the
                        enemy's walls back to his cohorts and hurried them up to a part of the town
                        where all was silence and solitude, as the defenders had gone off in pursuit
                        of the Suessetani. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The whole place passed
                        into his hands before the Lacetani returned. Finding that they had nothing
                        left them but their arms, they soon surrendered. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The victorious consul at once led his army
                        against Vergium, a fortified place which served mainly as a haunt and
                        shelter for brigands who were in the habit of raiding the peaceable
                        districts of the province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Vergestanus,
                        the chief, came over to the consul and on his own behalf and that of his
                        fellow-townsmen disavowed any complicity with them. He and his friends could
                        take no part in public affairs, when the brigands had been once admitted
                        they made themselves masters of the whole place. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The consul directed him to return home and make up some
                        plausible reason for his absence. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then,
                        when he saw the Romans approaching the walls and the brigands fully occupied
                        in defending them, he was not to forget to seize the citadel with his
                        sympathisers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Vergestanus carried out his
                        instructions and the brigands found themselves menaced by a double danger,
                        on the one side by the Romans who were scaling the walls and on the other by
                        the seizure of the citadel. When the consul had gained possession of the
                        town he gave orders for those who had held the citadel to be set at liberty,
                        together with all their relations, and to retain their property; <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> the rest of the townsfolk be made over to the
                        quaestor to be sold as slaves, and the brigands were summarily executed.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After the province was pacified Cato
                        organised the working of the iron and silver mines so satisfactorily that
                        they produced a considerable revenue, and the province in consequence became
                        constantly richer. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For these successful
                        operations the senators decreed a three days' thanksgiving. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this summer the other consul, L.
                        Valerius Flaccus, fought a successful action in Gaul with a body of Boii
                        near the forest of Litanae; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> 8000 Gauls are
                        stated to have been killed; the rest, abandoning all further resistance,
                        dispersed to their homes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> During the
                        remainder of the summer the consul kept his army around the Po in the
                        neighbourhood of Placentia and Cremona, and repaired the ravages which had
                        been made in war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Such was the position of
                        affairs in Spain and Italy. In Greece T. Quinctius had made such use of his
                        time through the winter that, with the exception of the Aetolians who had
                        not received the rewards of victory which they expected and were quite
                        incapable of remaining quiet for any length of time, the whole of Greece was
                        supremely happy in the enjoyment of <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the
                        blessings of peace and liberty, and was filled with admiration at the
                        moderation and justice and self-control which the Roman general displayed in
                        the hour of victory no less than at the courage and ability he had shown in
                        war. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At this juncture there was handed to him
                        the decree of the senate declaring war on Nabis the Lacedaemonian. After
                        reading it he summoned a meeting of delegates from every State in Greece to
                        be held in Corinth. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was attended by
                        representatives from all quarters, even the Aetolians put in an appearance.
                        The consul addressed the gathering in the following terms: <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> "The war against Philip was conducted by the Romans and
                        the Greeks with a common aim and united action, though each had their own
                        grounds of quarrel. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He had broken off
                        friendly relations with Rome by first assisting her enemies the
                        Carthaginians and then by attacking her allies in this country. Towards you
                        his conduct has been such that, if we could have forgotten our own wrongs,
                        those inflicted on you would have been a sufficient justification for war.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Today's deliberation, however, solely
                        concerns yourselves. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The question I am
                        laying before you is whether you are willing that Argos, which as you know
                        has been taken possession of by Nabis, should remain under his rule, or
                        whether you think it right that a city of such antiquity and renown,
                        situated <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> in the heart of Greece, should
                        be restored to liberty and placed in the same condition as all the other
                        cities in the Peloponnese and the mainland of Greece. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> This question, as you see, is one that you must decide
                        wholly for yourselves; it in no way touches the Romans except so far as the
                        servitude of any one city deprives them of the full and untarnished glory of
                        effecting the liberation of Greece." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Roman commander's speech others
                        were asked to express their views. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        Athenian delegate began by expressing the utmost gratitude for the services
                        which the Romans had rendered to Greece. He pointed out that they had given
                        assistance against Philip in answer to most pressing appeals, but their
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> offer of help against Nabis was
                        purely spontaneous, and he expressed strong indignation against remarks
                        which some <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> had made who had tried to
                        belittle these great services and thrown out dark hints about the future
                        when they ought rather to have expressed their grateful acknowledgments for
                        the past. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was obvious that this was a
                        hit at the Aetolians, and Alexander, their foremost citizen, replied with a
                        bitter attack upon the Athenians, who, he said, had in old days been the
                        first champions of liberty and were now betraying the common cause and
                        trying to curry favour for themselves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        then protested against the action of the Achaeans in first fighting under
                        Philip's banner and then, when his fortunes declined, turning renegades and
                        after capturing Corinth scheming to get possession of Argos. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, he declared, were the first to
                        oppose Philip, they had always been allies of Rome, and though it was laid
                        down in the treaty that after Philip was conquered their cities and
                        territories should be restored, they were fraudulently kept out of Echinus
                        and Pharsalus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He accused the Romans of
                        hypocrisy, for after their ostentatious and empty proclamation of liberty to
                        Greece they were holding Chalcis and Demetrias with their garrisons,
                        although while Philip hesitated to withdraw his garrisons from those cities
                        they were always protesting that <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> as long
                        as Demetrias, Chalcis and Corinth were held by him Greece could never be
                        free. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And now they were putting forward
                        Argos and Nabis as an excuse for keeping their armies in Greece. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Let them carry their armies back to Italy, the
                        Aetolians would guarantee that Nabis would withdraw his garrison from Argos
                        either voluntarily or for a consideration, otherwise they would forcibly
                        compel him to submit to the will of a united Greece. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This pretentious harangue called up
                        Aristaenus, the captain-general of the Achaean League. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> "I pray," he began, "that Jupiter Optimus Maximus and
                        Queen Juno, the tutelary deities of Argos, may never allow that city to be a
                        bone of contention between the tyrant of Lacedaemon and the robbers of
                        Aetolia, or suffer more after you have recovered it than it did when he
                        captured it. No intervening sea protects us from these brigands. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> What, then, will be our fate, T. Quinctius, if
                        they make a stronghold for themselves in the very heart of Greece? They have
                        nothing Greek about them but the language, any more than they have anything
                        human about them but the form and appearance of men; their customs and rites
                        are more horrid than those of any barbarians, nay, even than those of savage
                        beasts. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We ask you therefore, Romans, to
                        rescue Argos from Nabis and settle the affairs of Greece in such a way that
                        you may leave this country at peace and security even against the robber
                        practices of the Aetolians." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A general
                        outcry against the Aetolians arose, and the Roman commander said that he
                        would have replied to their charges had he not seen that the delegates were
                        all so incensed against them that they needed to be calmed rather than
                        excited further. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He should now put the
                        question, "What do you decide as to war with Nabis, if he does not restore
                        Argos to the Achaeans?" There was a unanimous decision in favour of war, and
                        he impressed upon them the duty of each city sending a contingent in
                        proportion to their strength. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He also sent
                        an envoy to the Aetolians, not so much in the expectation of compliance with
                        his demands as to make them disclose their real sentiments, and in this he
                        succeeded. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The military tribunes received orders to
                        bring up the army from Elatia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Envoys from
                        Antiochus arrived about the same time to negotiate an alliance; Quinctius
                        told them that he could express no opinion in the absence of the ten
                        commissioners; the envoys would have to go to Rome and consult the senate.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the arrival of the troops from
                        Elatia he proceeded to Argos. Near Cleonae he was met by Aristaenus with
                        10,000 Achaean infantry and the united armies encamped not far from that
                        place, and the following day marched down into the plain of Argos and
                        selected a site for their camp some four miles distant from the city.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The commander of the Lacedaemonian
                        garrison was Pythagoras, son-in-law and also brother-in-law of the tyrant.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Just before the arrival of the Romans
                        he had considerably strengthened the defences of the citadels-Argos
                        possessed two-and other points which appeared weak or vulnerable. Whilst
                        carrying out these tasks, however, he was quite unable to disguise the alarm
                        he felt at the appearance of the Romans, and his fears of a foreign foe were
                        aggravated by disturbances at home. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There
                        was an Argive named Damocles, a young man of more courage than prudence.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He got hold of those who seemed likely
                        to support him, and after binding them by an oath discussed the question of
                        expelling the garrison, and in his efforts to strengthen the conspiracy was
                        somewhat incautious in testing the sincerity of those whom he addressed.
                        While he was conferring with his supporters one of the commandant's
                        officials summoned him to appear before him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> Seeing that his designs were betrayed, he appealed to his
                        fellow-conspirators who were present to take arms with him rather than be
                        tortured to death. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He went off accordingly
                        with a few followers to the forum, calling upon all who had the safety of
                        their State at heart to follow him as the champion of their liberty. He did
                        not induce a single person to move, for they saw that there was no chance of
                        success at the time nor any hope of sufficient support. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> While thus appealing loudly to the bystanders he was
                        surrounded by the Lacedaemonians and killed together with his supporters.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Others were arrested afterwards, and
                        many of these were put to death; a few were imprisoned. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> During the following night several were lowered by
                        cords from the walls and fled to the Romans. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These men assured Quinctius that if the
                        Roman army had been at their gates the movement would have succeeded, and if
                        he moved his camp nearer to the city the Argives would rise. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> He sent forward some light troops, cavalry and
                        infantry, and the Lacedaemonians sallied out to meet them. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They met near the Cylarabis, a gymnasium not three
                        hundred paces from the city, and the Lacedaemonians were without much
                        trouble driven back behind their walls. The Roman general then fixed his
                        camp at the spot where the battle had taken place and remained there for a
                        day on the watch in case any fresh movement was started. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When he saw that the citizens were paralysed by fear,
                        he summoned a council of war to consider the question of attacking Argos.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> All with the exception of Aristaenus
                        were agreed that as Argos was the sole cause of the war, so it ought
                        certainly to be the starting-point. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This
                        was very far from what Quinctius wanted, and when Aristaenus spoke in
                        opposition to the unanimous sense of the council he listened to him with
                        unmistakable signs of approval. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He wound
                        up the discussion by stating that it was on behalf of the Argives that war
                        had been begun, and he could not imagine anything less consistent than to
                        leave the real enemy alone and attack Argos. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> As far as he was concerned he should direct all his efforts against
                        Lacedaemon and its tyrant, the head and front of the war. </p>
                    <p> After the council broke up he sent some cohorts of light troops, infantry
                        and cavalry, to collect corn. All that was ripe was cut and carried off;
                        what was still green was trampled down and spoilt to prevent the enemy from
                        using it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then he commenced his march, and
                        after crossing Mount Parthenius and leaving Tegea on his right he encamped
                        on the third day at Caryae, and here he awaited the allied contingents
                        before entering the enemy's country; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> 1500
                        Macedonian troops came in from Philip and 400 Thessalian cavalry. He had now
                        an adequate force, but he was still detained as he was waiting for the corn
                        which had been requisitioned from the cities in the neighbourhood.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A large naval force was also
                        concentrating; L. Quinctius had arrived from Leucas with 40 ships; there
                        were 18 decked ships from Rhodes; Eumenes was cruising amongst the Cyclades
                        with 10 decked ships, 30 despatch-boats and various others of smaller build.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Even refugees from Lacedaemon itself,
                        driven away by the tyrant's violence and disregard of all law, gathered in
                        large numbers at the Roman camp in the hope of recovering their country. The
                        number of those expelled by the various tyrants who for several generations
                        held Lacedaemon was very considerable. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        The principal man among the refugees was Agesipolis, and the sovereignty of
                        Lacedaemon belonged by right to his family. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                        /> He had been expelled when only an infant by Lycurgus, who became tyrant
                        after the death of Cleomenes, the first of the Lacedaemonian tyrants. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although Nabis was confronted by so
                        serious a war both by land and sea, and a just comparison of his own
                        strength with that of the enemy left him hardly any hope of success, he did
                        not give up the struggle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He called up
                        1000 picked troops from Crete in addition to the 1000 he had already; there
                        were 10,000 of his own subjects under arms including the garrisons in the
                        country districts, and he also fortified the city of Sparta with rampart and
                        fosse. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To prevent any internal disturbance
                        he kept the citizens in check by the fear of ruthless punishment, as he
                        could not expect them to desire a tyrant's safety and success. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> There were certain citizens whom he suspected,
                        and after marching all his forces on to a level space called the Dromos he
                        then assembled the Lacedaemonians in front of him, ordering them to lay down
                        their arms, and surrounding them with his armed bodyguard. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He then explained briefly why he ought to be excused
                        for feeling grave apprehensions and <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        taking strict precautions at such a critical time, and he pointed out that
                        it was in their own interest that any persons whom the present state of
                        affairs brought under suspicion should be prevented from doing mischief
                        rather than punished for having done it. He should therefore keep certain
                        persons in custody until the storm which was threatening had passed over.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If he was sufficiently on his guard
                        against domestic treason he would have all the less cause to fear a foreign
                        foe, and when the enemy had been repulsed they would at once be set at
                        liberty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then directed the names of
                        some eighty of the principal men of military age to be called over, and as
                        each answered to his name he ordered him into custody. During the night they
                        were all put to death. The Helots are a class who from early times have
                        occupied the fortified villages in the country districts and worked on the
                        land. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some of these were now charged with
                        attempted desertion and after being whipped through all the streets were put
                        to death. The terror thus created so completely quelled the population that
                        all attempts at revolution were at an end. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> Nabis kept his troops within their lines, as he did not feel himself a
                        match for the enemy in the field and he was afraid to leave the city in such
                        a state of suspense and uncertainty. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As his preparations were now completed,
                        Quinctius broke up his camp and on the second day reached Sellasia on the
                        river Oenus, the place where Antigonus, King of Macedon, was said to have
                        fought with Cleomenes, tyrant of the Lacedaemonians. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> On hearing that the descent into the valley was by a
                        difficult and narrow path, he sent an advance party by a short circuit over
                        the heights to make a road, and thus by a fairly broad and open route he
                        arrived at the Eurotas, which flows almost under the very walls of Sparta.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans were measuring out
                        the site of their camp, and Quinctius had ridden forward with some infantry
                        and cavalry, they were attacked by the tyrant's auxiliary troops. They were
                        not prepared for anything of the kind, as they had met with no opposition on
                        their march; the country through which they passed might have been a
                        friendly territory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For some time there
                        was considerable confusion, the cavalry calling for help from the infantry
                        and the infantry from the cavalry, no man feeling any confidence in himself.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At last the standards of the legions
                        appeared in sight, and then those who a moment before had been spreading
                        alarm were now driven in disorder back to the city. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans fell back just beyond the range of missiles
                        from the walls and stood for some time in line of battle, but as none of the
                        enemy came out against them they returned to camp. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The next day Quinctius led his army along the river
                        past the city to the foot of Mount Menelaus. The legionary cohorts marched
                        in front and the light infantry and the cavalry closed the column.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nabis was keeping his mercenaries, his
                        sole hope, drawn up under their standards inside the city wall, ready to
                        attack the Roman rear. </p>
                    <p> As soon as the end of the column had gone by they made the same tumultuous
                        dash as on the previous day from different points. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Appius was in command of the rear and had told his men
                        beforehand what to expect. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He rapidly
                        faced about, and bringing the whole column into line presented an unbroken
                        front to the enemy. So the two armies met one another in battle order, and
                        for some time there was a regular action. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        At length Nabis' men began to waver and finally took to flight. The rout
                        would not have been so complete had not the Achaeans who were pursuing them
                        been familiar with the country. They inflicted heavy losses upon them and
                        deprived most of the scattered fugitives of their arms. Quinctius fixed his
                        camp near Amyclae. This city lay in a populous and fertile district and he
                        laid the whole of it waste. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> None of the
                        enemy, however, ventured outside their gates, and he shifted his camp to the
                        bank of the Eurotas and from there he carried devastation throughout the
                        district which stretched from the foot of Taygetus to the sea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Quinctius in the meantime was
                        securing the towns on the coast, in some cases by voluntary surrender, in
                        others by threats or force. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Gytheum was
                        the great seaport of Lacedaemonia, and when he learnt that the Romans were
                        in camp at no great distance from the sea Lucius determined to attack it
                        with his united strength. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In those days it
                        was a strong city with a large mixed population of citizens and aliens and
                        was thoroughly equipped with all the apparatus for war. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Lucius was attempting a far from easy task, and very
                        opportunely for him Eumenes and the Rhodian fleet appeared on the scene.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The immense number of seamen which had
                        been drawn from the three fleets constructed in a few days all that was
                        required for an attack upon the city, which was fortified on its landward as
                        well as its seaward side. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The testudines
                        had been brought up and the wall was being undermined; in other places it
                        was being battered by the rams. One turret had been brought down by repeated
                        blows and the wall adjacent had fallen with it. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> To draw off the enemy from the breach thus caused, the
                        Romans delivered an assault from the harbour, where the ground was more
                        level, while at the same time they attempted to fight their way over the
                        ruins of the wall. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They had almost
                        succeeded in penetrating at this point when the assault was suddenly stopped
                        as a prospect presented itself of the city being surrendered, a prospect,
                        however, which soon vanished. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Two men,
                        Dexagoridas and Gorgopas, shared the command of the city between them.
                        Dexagoridas had sent to the Roman general to say that he would deliver up
                        the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the time and manner of
                        procedure had been settled he was put to death by Gorgopas as a traitor, and
                        the latter, now in sole command, offered a more determined resistance. The
                        assault would have become much more difficult had not Quinctius appeared
                        with a body of 4000 picked troops. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When
                        he had shown himself with his army drawn up on the brow of a hill not far
                        from the city, whilst Lucius on the other side was pressing the assault with
                        his siege works both by land and Sea, Gorgopas was driven to despair and
                        compelled to take the very course which in the case of <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> another he had punished with death. After stipulating
                        for the withdrawal of the <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> soldiers who
                        had formed his garrison he handed the city over to Quinctius. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Before the surrender of Gytheum, Pythagoras, who
                        had been left in command at Argos, transferred the custody of the city to
                        Timocrates of Pellene and joined Nabis at Sparta with 1000 mercenary troops
                        and 2000 Argives. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nabis was thoroughly alarmed at the
                        appearance of the Roman fleet and the loss of the towns on the coast, but as
                        long as Gytheum was held by his men he accepted the situation though with
                        faint hopes of success. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When, however, he
                        heard that it too had passed into the hands of the Romans he realised the
                        hopelessness of his position with the enemy all round his frontiers and the
                        sea entirely closed to him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He saw that he
                        must yield to circumstances, and accordingly he sent a herald to the Roman
                        camp to find out whether they would allow him to send envoys to them.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His request was granted, and
                        Pythagoras was sent to the general for the sole purpose of asking him to
                        meet the tyrant in conference. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        military council was convened and they were unanimously of opinion that a
                        conference should be granted and the time and place were settled. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The two principals proceeded to some rising
                        ground midway between their camp accompanied by small escorts. Here the
                        escorts were left well in view of the troops on both sides and Nabis went
                        forward with some of his bodyguard, whilst <milestone n="7??" unit="section"
                        /> Quinctius advanced to meet him accompanied by his brother, Eumenes,
                        Sosilaus the Rhodian, Aristaenus, the captain-general of the Achaeans, and
                        the military tribunes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was left to the tyrant to decide
                        whether he would speak first or not, and he began the discussion in the
                        following speech: "Titus Quinctius and all who are present: If I could have
                        discovered for myself the reason why you have declared war against me or
                        actually commenced it, I should have awaited in silence the issue of my
                        fortunes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But as things are now I cannot
                        control myself sufficiently to refrain from asking, before I perish, why I
                        am to perish. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If you were what the
                        Carthaginians are reported to be, a people for whom the honourable
                        observance of treaties possesses no sanctity, I should not be surprised at
                        your considering it a matter of small moment in what way you treat me.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when I look at you I see that you
                        are Romans who hold treaties to be the most solemn of all religious
                        obligations, and fidelity to allies the most sacred of human duties.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When I look at myself I hope I am
                        still the man who in common with the rest of the Lacedaemonians is bound to
                        you by an age-long treaty of alliance and who renewed in the recent war with
                        Philip the personal tie of friendship. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        But, you say, I have violated and destroyed it by holding the city of the
                        Argives. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> How shall I justify this? By
                        appealing to facts or to the circumstances of the time? As to the facts I
                        have a double defence, for it was the townsmen themselves who invoked my aid
                        and put the place in my hands; I did not occupy it by force, I accepted it
                        and that too when Philip's partisans were in power, not when it was your
                        ally. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The circumstance of time clears me
                        too, because it was when I was actually holding Argos that the alliance
                        between us was formed, and the stipulation was not that I should withdraw my
                        garrison from Argos, but only that I should furnish assistance to you in the
                        war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In this question of Argos I most
                        certainly have the best of the argument both on the ground of equity and
                        justice-for I took a city which belonged not <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> to you but to your enemy, not by force but at the wish
                        of the inhabitants-and also on the strength of your own admission, for under
                        the terms of peace you left Argos to me. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But however that may be, the title of
                        'tyrant' and the arbitrary acts of a tyrant, such as summoning slaves to
                        freedom and settling the poverty-stricken masses on the land, are alleged
                        against me. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As to the title I can make
                        this reply, whatever my character is I am the same man with whom you
                        yourself, T. Quinctius, entered into alliance. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Then, I remember, you called me 'king,' now I see that
                        you have dubbed me 'tyrant.' Now, if I had altered the designation of my
                        rule, I should have to defend my inconsistency; as you are altering it, you
                        must justify yours. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As to my augmenting
                        the civil population by freeing the slaves and dividing up the land amongst
                        the poor and needy, I can defend myself against this charge also by pleading
                        the time at which I did it. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Whatever
                        these measures were I had carried them out when you contracted alliance with
                        me and accepted my assistance in the war with Philip. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> But even supposing that I had carried them out to-day,
                        I do not ask how I could have injured you or disturbed the amity between us,
                        I content myself with asserting that I have acted in accordance with our
                        ancestral laws and customs. Do not weigh what is done in Lacedaemon by your
                        own institutions. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> There is no necessity
                        for going into details. You select your cavalry as you do your infantry,
                        according to their assessment; you will have a few preeminent for their
                        wealth and the mass of the population subject to them. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> Our legislator would not have the government in the
                        hands of a small class such as you designate your senate, nor would he allow
                        any one order to be preponderant in the State; he believed that an equality
                        of rank and fortune was necessary in order that there might be a large
                        number of men to bear arms for their country. I have spoken at greater
                        length, I confess, than is usual with my countrymen. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> It could have been put very briefly-I have done nothing
                        since I formed a league of amity with you which should make you regret it."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this the Roman commander replied: "It
                        is not with you that we entered into friendship and alliance, but with
                        Philip, the rightful and legitimate king of Lacedaemon. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> His right to the crown has been usurped by the tyrants
                        who ruled there while we were preoccupied by, first, the Punic War, then
                        with wars in Gaul and elsewhere, just as you have usurped it during this war
                        with Macedon. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> What greater inconsistency
                        could there be than for those who waged war against Philip for the
                        liberation of Greece to form a league of unity with a tyrant, and a tyrant,
                        too, who has always treated his subjects with the utmost oppression and
                        cruelty? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In fact, even if you had not
                        seized and were not now holding Argos by dishonest practices, it would still
                        have been incumbent on us, whilst liberating the rest of Greece, to restore
                        Lacedaemon also to her old free constitution and to those laws which you
                        spoke about just now as though you put yourself on a par with Lycurgus.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Are we to make it our care that your
                        garrisons shall be withdrawn from Iasos and Bargyliae and at the same time
                        leave Argos and Lacedaemon, two of the most famous cities and at one time
                        the lights of Greece, prostrate beneath your feet, and so let their
                        servitude sully our title as the liberators of Greece? You say the
                        sympathies of the Argives were with Philip. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> Well, we release you from any obligation to be angry with them so far as
                        we are concerned. We have sufficient evidence that the blame for that rests
                        upon some two or at the most three persons, not upon the citizens as a
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> body, just, in fact, as the
                        invitation given to you and your troops and your admission into the citadel
                        was in no way whatever the act of their government. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> We know that the Thessalians and Phocians and Locrians
                        were unanimous in their support of Philip, and yet we have given them their
                        freedom in common with the rest of Greece; what, pray, do you suppose we
                        shall do in the case of the Argives, who as a State were innocent of any
                        complicity with him? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> You said that the enfranchisement of the
                        slaves and the assignment of land to the needy were brought up as charges
                        against you, and they are certainly serious ones, but what are they in
                        comparison with the crimes committed by you and your adherents day by day?
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Produce an assembly where men are
                        free to speak their minds, at either Argos or Lacedaemon, if you want to
                        hear a true description of your unbridled tyranny. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Not to mention earlier instances, what about the
                        massacre which that son-in-law of yours, Pythagoras, perpetrated in Argos
                        almost before my very eyes? What about the murders you yourself committed
                        when I was close to your frontiers? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Come
                        now, order those prisoners to be produced whom you arrested in the Assembly
                        after promising in the hearing of all present that they should be kept in
                        custody. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Let their unhappy relatives know
                        that those whom they are mourning are still alive. But you say, 'Even if
                        these things are so, what have they got to do with you Romans?' Would you
                        use this language to the liberators of Greece? <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> To those who, to effect this liberation have crossed
                        the sea and carried on war by sea and land? 'At all events,' you say, 'I
                        have not injured you directly or violated your friendship and alliance.' How
                        many instances do you want me to allege of your having done this? <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> I do not want to bring many forward, I will sum
                        them up briefly. What acts, then, constitute a violation of friendship?
                        These two, most of all-to treat my allies as enemies, and to make common
                        cause with my enemies. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Both of these
                        things you have done. Though you were our ally you seized by force a city in
                        alliance with us, namely Messene, which had been admitted to our friendship
                        and enjoyed precisely the same privileges as Lacedaemon. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> And further, you not only concluded an alliance with
                        Philip, our enemy, but you actually established a relationship with him
                        through Philocles, one of his viceroys. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        In open hostility to us, you infested the sea round Malea with your
                        piratical barques, and have seized and put to death almost more Roman
                        citizens than Philip, so that our transports, which were supplying our
                        armies, found coasting along the Macedonian shores safer than rounding the
                        Cape of Malea. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Forbear henceforth, if you
                        please, to talk about your loyal observance of treaties; <milestone n="20"
                            unit="section"/> drop the language of a citizen and speak as a tyrant
                        and an enemy." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aristaenus followed. He advised and even
                        implored Nabis to take the course which was safest for himself and his
                        fortunes while he had the opportunity. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        alluded by name to several who after ruling as tyrants in the surrounding
                        cities had been deposed on the restoration of liberty and had passed a safe
                        and even an honoured old age amongst their fellow-citizens. Further
                        discussion was put an end to by the approach of night. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The next day Nabis said that he would evacuate Argos
                        and withdraw his garrison whenever the Romans wished, and would also
                        surrender the prisoners and deserters. Should any further demands be made,
                        he requested that they might be put in writing in order that he might
                        consult his friends about them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Time was
                        allowed him for the purpose, and Quinctius on his side also called the
                        friendly cities into council. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The majority
                        were in favour of continuing the war and getting rid of the tyrant; for they
                        felt certain that the freedom of Greece would never be safe otherwise.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They declared that it would have been
                        better not to commence war against him than to abandon it after it had
                        begun, for Nabis would be in <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> a much
                        stronger position if he could assume that his usurpation was sanctioned by
                        Rome, and his example would incite many in other cities to plot against the
                        liberties of their fellow-citizens. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The general himself was more inclined to
                        peace. He saw clearly that if the enemy were driven within his walls there
                        was nothing for it but a siege, and a long <milestone n="9??" unit="section"
                        /> one too, for it was not Gytheum they would have to attack-that place had,
                        however, been surrendered, not stormed-but Lacedaemon, a city exceptionally
                        strong in men and arms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> His one hope had
                        been, so he told the council, that on the approach of his army a
                        revolutionary outbreak might occur, but though the citizens saw the
                        standards carried up to the gates no one stirred. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He went on to inform them that Villius had returned
                        from his mission to Antiochus and reported that they could no longer depend
                        upon maintaining peace with him, as he had landed in Europe with a far
                        larger force, both military and naval, than on the former occasion.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If he, Quinctius, employed his army
                        in investing Lacedaemon, what other troops, he asked, would he have
                        available for war against so strong and powerful a monarch? <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> This was what he gave out in public; his secret
                        motive was the fear that when the new consuls balloted for their provinces
                        Greece might fall to one of them, and the <milestone n="14??" unit="section"
                        /> war which he had begun so victoriously might be brought to a triumphant
                        close by his successor. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As his arguments failed to make any
                        impression on the allies he tried another course, and by apparently falling
                        in with their view he brought them over to his own. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> "Well and good," he continued, "let us undertake the
                        siege of Lacedaemon, if such is your resolve. Do not close your eyes,
                        however, to the fact that the investment of a city is a slow business and
                        often wearies out the besiegers sooner than the besieged, and you must now
                        face the certainty of having to pass the winter round the walls of
                        Lacedaemon. If these tedious processes only involved toil and danger I
                        should urge you to prepare yourselves in mind and body to sustain them.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But a vast outlay will be necessary
                        for the siege works and engines and artillery which will be required for the
                        investment <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> of so great a city, and
                        supplies for you and for us will have to be collected against the winter.
                        So, to prevent your suddenly finding yourselves in difficulties, and
                        abandoning to your shame a task after you have undertaken it, <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> I am of opinion that you ought to write to your
                        respective cities and find out what they really intend doing and what
                        resources they possess. Of auxiliary troops I have enough and more than
                        enough, the greater our number the greater our requirements. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The enemy's territory contains nothing now but
                        the bare soil, and besides, winter will be here, making it difficult to
                        bring supplies from a distance." <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This
                        speech at once reminded them of the evils they had to take account of in
                        their own cities, the indolence, the jealousy, the malicious way in which
                        those remaining at home spoke about those on active service, the
                        unrestrained liberty which hindered united action, the low state of their
                        national exchequers and <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the
                        niggardliness displayed by individuals in contributing towards public
                        expenses. So they quickly changed their minds and left it to the <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> commander-in-chief to do what he thought best
                        in the interest of Rome and the allies. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After consultation with his staff officers
                        and military tribunes, Quinctius put into writing the conditions on which
                        peace was to be made with the tyrant. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        There was to be a truce for six months between Nabis and his opponents-the
                        Romans, Eumenes and the Rhodians. T. Quinctius and Nabis were each to send
                        forthwith commissioners to Rome to secure the confirmation of the peace by
                        the senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The armistice was to commence
                        from the day on which the document containing the conditions was handed to
                        Nabis, and within ten days from that date he was to withdraw all his
                        garrisons from Argos and the other towns in Argive territory and the places
                        were to be handed over, evacuated and free, to the Romans. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> No slaves were to be removed from those places, whether
                        they had belonged to the king or the public authorities or private
                        individuals, and if any had previously been so removed they were to be duly
                        restored to their owners. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nabis was to
                        return the ships he had taken from the maritime cities, and he himself was
                        not to possess any vessel beyond two light barques with not more than
                        sixteen oars. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All the cities allied with
                        Rome were to have their prisoners and deserters restored to them, and all
                        the property which the people of Messene could collect together and identify
                        was to be given back to them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Further, he
                        was to allow the Lacedaemonian refugees to have their wives and children
                        with them, provided that no woman should be forced to join her husband
                        whilst in exile against her will. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Such of
                        the tyrant's mercenaries as had gone back to their homes or deserted to the
                        Romans were to have all their property restored to them. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He was not to possess a single city in Crete, those
                        which he had held he was to deliver up to the Romans, nor was he to form
                        alliances with or make war against any of the Cretan cities, or anyone else.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All the cities which he had to
                        surrender, and all who had voluntarily accepted the suzerainty of Rome, were
                        to be relieved of the presence of his garrisons; neither he nor his subjects
                        were in any way to interfere with them. He was not to build a walled town or
                        fortified post either on his own soil or elsewhere. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> As a guarantee for the due observance of these
                        conditions he was to give five hostages to be selected by the Roman
                        commander-one being his own son-and he was to pay an indemnity of 100
                        talents of silver at once and an annual instalment of 50 talents for the
                        next eight years. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Roman camp had been moved nearer
                        the city, these conditions were sent to Lacedaemon. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> None of them, of course, were very agreeable to the
                        tyrant, though he was relieved to find that nothing was said about
                        repatriating the refugees, but what he resented most of all was being
                        deprived of his ships and his seaports. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The sea had been a great source of profit to him as long as he could infest
                        the whole Maleatic coastline with his pirate ships, and, moreover, the men
                        drawn from the maritime cities furnished him with by far the finest of his
                        troops. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had discussed the conditions
                        privately with his friends, but as courtiers are untrustworthy in all other
                        matters, so are they especially in keeping secrets, and the consul's demands
                        soon became generally known. They were not objected to so strongly by the
                        great body of the citizens as they were by the different individuals who
                        were immediately affected by them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those
                        who had married the wives of the political exiles and those who had
                        appropriated any of their property were as indignant as though they were to
                        lose what belonged to themselves, instead of restoring what belonged to
                        others. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The slaves who had been freed by
                        the tyrant saw not only their liberty gone but an even worse slavery
                        awaiting them if they had to pass into the power of their enraged masters.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The mercenary troops were angry at
                        losing their pay when peace was established, and they saw no chance of
                        returning to their own cities, which were as bitterly opposed to the
                        supporters of tyrants as to the tyrants themselves. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They began by gathering together and
                        discussing their grievances, and at last they flew to arms. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The tyrant saw from this outbreak that the populace
                        were sufficiently excited for his purpose, and he called a public assembly.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As he went separately through the
                        consul's demands and added some of his own invention which were more
                        burdensome and humiliating, each item called forth angry protests, at one
                        time from the whole assembly, at another from separate groups. When he had
                        finished he asked the people what answer they wished him to give, or what
                        action he was to take. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The whole assembly
                        almost with one voice forbade him to return any answer and insisted that the
                        war should go on. As usual with the crowd they encouraged one another by
                        saying that they hoped for the best and that Fortune helped the brave.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Encouraged by the general voice, the
                        tyrant gave out that Antiochus and the Aetolians would assist them, and he
                        meanwhile had enough troops to stand a siege. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Nobody now still talked of peace, and unable to remain
                        quiet any longer they ran off to attack the enemy's advanced posts. The
                        offensive movements of small bodies of skirmishers and the discharge of
                        their missiles removed any doubt from the minds of the Romans that war was
                        inevitable. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For four days slight actions
                        took place without any decisive result, but on the fifth day the fighting
                        almost amounted to a regular battle and the <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> Lacedaemonians were driven back into their town in such
                        a state of demoralisation that some of the Roman soldiers in hot pursuit
                        entered the city at places where at that time there was no wall. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the fear thus inspired had checked all
                        further offensive on the part of the enemy, Quinctius saw that there was
                        nothing left but to invest the place, and after despatching officers to
                        bring up the whole of the naval contingent from Gytheum, he proceeded with
                        his military tribunes to ride round the city and examine its position.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Sparta had formerly been unwalled, but
                        in recent years the various tyrants had protected those parts which were
                        level and exposed by a wall; the higher and less accessible positions were
                        defended by permanent military posts instead of fortifications. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> When the consul had made a thorough inspection of
                        the place he saw that he would have to employ the whole of his force in the
                        attack. Accordingly he completely invested the city with Roman and allied
                        troops, mounted and unmounted; in fact, his entire military and naval
                        strength, amounting to 50,000 men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some
                        were carrying scaling ladders, others fire, others the different things with
                        which to attack and still more to appal the enemy. Orders were issued for
                        all to raise the battle-shout and rush straight forward to the assault at
                        the same moment so that the Lacedaemonians, threatened on every side, would
                        not know where first to meet the attack or where assistance would be most
                        required. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Quinctius formed his main army
                        into three divisions: the first was to deliver the assault in the
                        neighbourhood of the Phoebeum; the second towards the Dictynneum; the third
                        at the place called the Heptagoniae. All these points were unprotected by
                        walls. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Though the city was now encompassed
                        on every side by so menacing a foe the tyrant was most energetic in its
                        defence; wherever shouts arose on some sudden onset, when breathless
                        messengers came asking for help, he either hurried to the threatened spot
                        himself or sent others to assist. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When,
                        however, demoralisation and panic had set in everywhere, he completely lost
                        his nerve, and was unable either to give the necessary orders or to listen
                        to the messages that came; he not only lost all power of judgment, but was
                        almost beside himself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As long as they were in the narrow streets
                        the Lacedaemonians stood their ground against the Romans, and three separate
                        actions were going on at different places, but as the struggle became more
                        intense it became more unequal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        Lacedaemonians were carrying on the fight with missiles, against which the
                        Romans were easily able to protect themselves by their large shields, and
                        whilst some fell harmlessly others came with little force. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Owing to the confined space and the crowding together
                        they had no room to run before hurling their missiles to give them greater
                        force, nor could they keep a firm and steady footing while they tried to
                        throw them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> None of the darts which the
                        enemy flung penetrated the bodies and very few the shields of the Romans.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some wounds were caused by the enemy
                        who were on higher ground around them, but soon their advance exposed them
                        to an unlooked-for attack from the houses, not only darts but even tiles
                        being hurled upon them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On this they held
                        their shields above their heads and closed up so that with shield joined to
                        shield there might be no room for a chance missile or even for one thrown at
                        close range to penetrate. In this testudo formation they went on. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For a short time the Romans were held up
                        by the narrowness of the streets as they and the enemy were closely packed
                        together, but when they got into a broader thoroughfare they pushed the
                        enemy back and were able to advance, and the violence of their attack made
                        further resistance impossible. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the
                        Lacedaemonians had once turned to flight and were making for the higher
                        parts of the city, Nabis, in a state of distraction as though the city was
                        actually taken, was looking <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> round for
                        some way of escape, but Pythagoras, who in all other respects was showing
                        the spirit and leadership of a general, was now the one man who saved the
                        city from capture. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He gave orders for the
                        buildings nearest the walls to be set alight and they instantly burst into
                        flames, the townsmen, who at other times would naturally have helped to
                        extinguish them, fanning the conflagration. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> The roofs collapsed upon the Romans, broken tiles and pieces of burning
                        wood struck the soldiers, the flames spread far and wide, and the smoke
                        caused them alarm out of all proportion to the danger incurred. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Those who were still outside the city making the
                        final assault fell back from the walls; those who were already within,
                        afraid of being cut off by the outbreak of fire in their rear, retired, and
                        Quinctius, seeing the state of matters, sounded the retreat. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Recalled from the assault when the city was all
                        but captured, they returned to camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius came to the conclusion that he
                        would gain more from playing on the enemy's fears than by what he had
                        hitherto achieved, and he kept them in a constant state of alarm for three
                        successive days by harassing them with attacks and throwing up barriers at
                        certain points to close the avenues of escape. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Driven at last to submission by this perpetual menace,
                        the tyrant sent Pythagoras once more to open negotiations. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> At first Quinctius refused to see him and ordered him
                        to quit the camp, but when he assumed a suppliant tone and fell on his
                        knees, the consul granted him an audience. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        He began by leaving everything at the absolute discretion of the Romans, but
                        he gained nothing by taking this line, which was regarded as idle and
                        leading to no result. Finally it was arranged that, conditionally upon the
                        acceptance of the terms which had a few days previously been presented in
                        writing, there should be a suspension of hostilities; the money and the
                        hostages were accepted. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While the siege
                        was going on message after message reached Argos announcing the imminent
                        capture of Lacedaemon, and the spirits of the population were raised higher
                        by the departure of Pythagoras with the main strength of his garrison.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Feeling contempt for the few still
                        remaining, they expelled them from the citadel under the direction of a man
                        called Archippus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Timocrates of Pellene
                        was allowed to leave under a safe-conduct owing to the clemency and
                        moderation he had shown as commandant. After granting peace to the tyrant,
                        and dismissing Eumenes and the Rhodians and sending his brother Lucius back
                        to the fleet, Quinctius went to Argos, where he found everybody very happy.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The famous Nemean Games, the most popular
                        of all their festivals, had been suspended by he Argives owing to the
                        sufferings of the war, but on the arrival of the Roman commander with his
                        army they manifested their delight by ordering the Games to be celebrated
                        and making the general himself the president. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> There were many circumstances which enhanced their
                        joy-those of their fellow-citizens whom Pythagoras had lately removed and
                        those whom Nabis had previously carried off had now been brought back from
                        Lacedaemon; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> those who had succeeded in
                        escaping after the discovery of the plot by Pythagoras and the consequent
                        bloodshed had returned home; once more after a long interval they had their
                        liberty restored, and they saw with their own eyes the Romans who were the
                        authors of its restoration and who for their sake had undertaken the war
                        with the tyrant. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Moreover, on the very day
                        the Nemean Games were exhibited the voice of the herald confirmed by public
                        proclamation "the liberty of the Argives." The satisfaction which the
                        Achaeans felt at the restoration of Argos to their league was considerably
                        impaired by the fact that Lacedaemon was left in servitude to the tyrant,
                        who remained as a thorn in their side. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As
                        for the Aetolians, they were perpetually harping upon the subject at every
                        meeting of their council. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They declared
                        that the war was not at an end till Philip had evacuated every city in
                        Greece; Lacedaemon was left to the tyrant, but her rightful king, who was in
                        the Roman camp, and the noblest of her citizens would have to live in exile;
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Rome had made herself the minister to
                        his tyranny. Quinctius led his forces back to Elatia, which had been his
                        starting-point for the Spartan War. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Some
                        authorities state that the tyrant did not conduct operations by making
                        sorties from the town, but after fixing his camp face <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> to face with that of the Romans and waiting for a
                        considerable time in expectation of assistance from the Aetolians, he was in
                        the end compelled to give battle owing to the Romans attacking his foragers.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In that battle they state that he was
                        defeated and lost his camp and so was driven to ask for peace, after losing
                        14,000 in killed and wounded and more than 4000 who were made prisoners.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The despatch from T. Quinctius reporting
                        his operations at Lacedaemon and one from M. Porcius, the consul in Spain,
                        reached Rome almost simultaneously. A three days' thanksgiving was ordered
                        by the senate on behalf of each of them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The consul, L. Valerius, who after routing the Boii near the Litanean forest
                        had no further trouble in his province, returned to Rome for the elections.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The new consuls were P. Cornelius
                        Scipio Africanus and Tiberius Sempronius Longus. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Their fathers had both been consuls in the first year
                        of the Second Punic War. The election of praetors followed. Those elected
                        were P. Cornelius Scipio, the two Cornelii-Merenda and Blasio-Cneius
                        Domitius Ahenobarbus, Sextus Digitius, and T. Juventius Thalna. After the
                        elections were over the consul went back to his province. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> During the year the people of Ferentinum tried to claim
                        the right of those Latins who had been enrolled in Roman colonies to be
                        deemed Roman citizens. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Those who had given
                        in their names had been assigned to the colonies of Puteoli, Salernum and
                        Buxentum, and on the strength of this assumed the status of Roman citizens.
                        The senate decided that they were not Roman citizens. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the year of office of
                        the new consuls the envoys from Nabis arrived in Rome. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> An audience of the senate was granted them outside the
                        City in the temple of Apollo. They asked that the treaty of peace which had
                        been arranged with T. Quinctius might be confirmed, and their request was
                        granted. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the allocation of provinces
                        came under discussion there was a large attendance of senators, and the
                        general opinion was that as the wars in Spain and Macedonia had come to an
                        end Italy should be assigned to both consuls as their province. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Scipio was of opinion that one consul was enough
                        for Italy, the other ought to have Macedonia assigned to him. He pointed out
                        that a serious war was impending with Antiochus, who had deliberately landed
                        in Europe. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> What, Scipio asked, did they
                        suppose he would do when he was invited to commence hostilities by the
                        Aetolians on the one side, who were undoubtedly hostile, and on the other
                        side urged on by Hannibal, the commander so renowned for the defeats he had
                        inflicted on the Romans? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While the
                        consular provinces were being discussed the praetors balloted for their
                        provinces. Cneius Domitius received the urban jurisdiction and T. Juventius
                        that over aliens. To P. Cornelius was allotted Further Spain, and Hither
                        Spain to Sextus Digitius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of the two
                        Cornelii, Blasio was appointed to Sicily and Merenda to Sardinia. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> It was decided not to send a fresh army to
                        Macedonia, the one which was there was to be brought back by Quinctius and
                        disbanded, as was also the army with M. Porcius Cato in Spain. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Italy was decreed as the province of both
                        consuls, and they were empowered to raise two legions in the City in order
                        that after the disbandment of the two armies which the senate had decreed
                        there might be in all eight Roman legions. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the previous year a Sacred Spring had
                        been observed, and the Pontifex Maximus P. Licinius reported to the
                        pontifical college that its observance had not been properly carried out.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The college authorised him to bring
                        the matter to the notice of the senate, and they decided that there should
                        be an entirely fresh observance under the direction of the pontiffs.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Great Games, which had been vowed
                        at the same time, were also ordered to be celebrated, and the usual outlay
                        incurred upon them. The victims to be offered included all the cattle born
                        between 1st March and 1st May during the consulship of P. Cornelius and
                        Tiberius Sempronius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then came the
                        election of the censors. The new censors, Sextus Aelius Paetus and C.
                        Cornelius Cethegus, selected, as their predecessors had done, P. Scipio as
                        leader of the senate. Only three senators in all were removed from the roll,
                        none of whom had enjoyed curule honours. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Another thing which added immensely to their popularity with the patricians
                        was the order they issued to the curule aediles, requiring them to reserve
                        special places for the senators at the Roman Games; previously they sat
                        amongst the crowd. Very few of the equestrian order were deprived of their
                        horses, nor did the censors treat any order in the State harshly. The Hall
                        of Liberty and the Villa Publica were also restored and enlarged by these
                        censors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Sacred Spring and the Games,
                        vowed by Servius Sulpicius Galba, were duly carried out. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Q. Pleminius, who for his many crimes against gods and
                        men at Locri had been thrown into prison, seized the opportunity whilst all
                        were preoccupied with the spectacle of the Games to get together a number of
                        men who were to set the City on fire at various points during the night so
                        that he might break out of gaol during the confusion created. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The plot was disclosed by some of his accomplices
                        and the information laid before the senate. Pleminius was thrown into the
                        lowest dungeon and put to death. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the year a number of Roman citizens
                        were settled as colonists in Puteoli, Volturnum and Liternum; three hundred
                        were assigned to each place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Similar
                        settlements were made in Salernum and Buxentum. The commissioners who
                        supervised the emigration were Tiberius Sempronius Longus who was consul at
                        the time, M. Servilius and Q. Minucius Thermus. The land distributed amongst
                        them had formed part of the domain of Capua. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> A colony of Roman citizens was also established at Sipontum on land which
                        had belonged to Arpi. The commissioners in this case were D. Junius Brutus,
                        M Baebius Tamphilus and M. Helvius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Roman
                        citizens were also sent as colonists to Tempsa and Croto; the territory of
                        the former had been taken from the Brutii, who had expelled the Greeks from
                        it; Croto was still held by the Greeks. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The commissioners for the colonisation at Croto were Cneius Octavius, L.
                        Aemilius Paulus and C. Laetorius; those for Tempsa were L. Cornelius Merula
                        and C. Salonius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some portents appeared in
                        Rome this year and others were announced from various places. In the Forum,
                        the Comitium and the Capitol drops of blood were seen; there were several
                        showers of mud, and the head of the statue of Vulcan appeared to be on fire.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was reported that the river Nar had
                        flowed with milk, that boys of respectable parents at Ariminum had been born
                        without eyes or nose, and one in the district of Picenum without hands or
                        feet. These portents were expiated as directed by the pontiffs. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Sacrifices were also offered for nine days in
                        consequence of a report from the people of Hadria that a shower of stones
                        had fallen on their soil. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> L. Valerius, who was still in command in
                        Gaul, fought a hotly contested action with the Insubrians and the Boii; the
                        latter had crossed the Po in order to rouse the Insubrians to arms.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His colleague M. Porcius Cato
                        celebrated his triumph over the Spaniards during this period. In the
                        procession there were carried 25,000 pounds of unwrought silver, 12,300
                        silver denarii, 540 of Oscan coinage, and 1200 pounds' weighs of gold. To
                        each of the infantry soldiers he distributed 270 ases and treble the amount
                        to the cavalry. On arriving in his province Tiberius Sempronius marched his
                        troops first of all into the country of the Boii. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Boiorix was their chief at the time, and after he and
                        his <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> two brothers had induced the whole
                        nation to resume hostilities he fixed his camp in an exposed position in the
                        open country to show that they were prepared to fight if they were invaded.
                        When the consul became aware of the numbers and confidence of the enemy he
                        sent to his colleague asking him, if he thought he could do so, to hasten to
                        his assistance, and he would by one means or another delay an action till he
                        came. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The same reason which led the consul
                        to delay made the Gauls seek an early decision, for their confidence was
                        increased by their enemy's hesitation and they determined to engage him
                        before the two consuls united their forces. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> For two days, however, they merely stood ready for battle in case there
                        was any advance from the Roman camp; on the third day they went up to the
                        rampart and attacked the camp simultaneously on all sides. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul ordered his men instantly to
                        seize their weapons, and for a few minutes kept them standing under arms,
                        partly to encourage the unthinking confidence of the <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> enemy and also to allow of his distributing the troops
                        at the different gates from which each body was to make the sortie.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The two legions were ordered to
                        advance through the principal gates, but the Gauls blocked the exits in such
                        dense masses that they could not emerge. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The struggle went on for a long time in the confined space; it was not so
                        much fighting with their right hands and swords as pushing with their
                        shields and bodies, the Romans trying to force a way for their standards,
                        the Gauls endeavouring to get into the camp, or at all events to keep the
                        Romans from getting out. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Neither the one
                        side nor the other could make any advance until Q. Victorius, a centurion of
                        the first rank, <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> and C. Atilius, a
                        military tribune, the former belonging to the second legion, the latter to
                        the fourth, did what had often been tried in desperate struggles, and
                        snatching the standards from the bearers flung them amongst the enemy.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In their effort to recover the
                        standards the men of the second legion were the first to force their way out
                        of the camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They were now fighting outside the rampart
                        while the fourth legion were still held up in their gate. Suddenly a new
                        alarm arose on the opposite side of the camp. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The Gauls had broken through the quaestorian gate, and
                        after meeting with the most obstinate resistance had killed the quaestor, L.
                        Postumius Tympanus, M. Atinius and P. Sempronius, praefects of allies, and
                        nearly 200 men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This side of the camp was
                        in the enemy's hands until one of the "special cohorts" which had been sent
                        by the consul to defend the quaestorian gate drove them out of the camp
                        after killing many of them, and stopped those who were breaking in.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Almost at the same moment the fourth
                        legion, with two of the special cohorts, forced their way out of another
                        gate. So there were three separate actions going on simultaneously on
                        different sides of the camp, and the confused shouts which arose called off
                        the attention of the combatants from their own struggle to the doubtful
                        position of their comrades. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Up to noonday
                        the battle was fought with equal strength on both sides, and almost equal
                        hopes of victory. But the heat and the exertion told upon the Gauls with
                        their soft and perspiring bodies, utterly incapable as they were of enduring
                        thirst, and compelled them to beat a retreat. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The few who still stood their ground were charged by
                        the Romans and driven in rout to their camp. Then the consul gave the signal
                        to retire; most of the men obeyed it, but some in their eagerness for battle
                        and in the hope of securing the hostile camp pushed on to the rampart.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Gauls, deriding this weak force,
                        rushed in a body out of their camp. Now it was the Romans who were routed,
                        and those who refused to return to camp at the consul's order were driven
                        thither by their fears. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So first on one
                        side and then on the other victory and flight alternated. The Gauls,
                        however, lost as many as 11,000 men, the Romans 5000. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They retired into the most distant part of
                        their country; the consul led his legions to Placentia. Some writers assert
                        that Scipio formed a junction with his colleague and marched through the
                        fields of the Boii and the Ligurians, plundering as he went, until the
                        forests and marshes forbade further progress; others, on the contrary, state
                        that he returned to Rome to conduct the elections without doing anything
                        worth recording. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> T. Quinctius had returned
                        to his former quarters at Elatia, and he spent the whole winter in
                        administering justice and reforming the judicial procedure. He also made
                        changes in the political arrangements which had been imposed on the cities
                        by the lawless tyranny of Nabis and his lieutenants, and which by augmenting
                        the power of his own party crushed the rights and liberties of the others.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the beginning of spring he went to
                        Corinth, where he had summoned a general meeting of the allies.
                        Representatives from all the States were present, so that it was practically
                        a Pan-Hellenic council. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He began his
                        address by reminding them of the friendly relations which had from the first
                        existed between the Romans and the Greeks as a nation and the work which had
                        been done by himself and the commanders who had been in Macedonia before
                        him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His speech was listened to with
                        universal approbation except where he alluded to the treatment of Nabis.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was felt by those present to be
                        quite inconsistent with the part of a Liberator of Greece to leave the
                        tyrant as a scourge to his own country and a terror to all the surrounding
                        States. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius was quite aware of their
                        feelings on this question, and he frankly admitted that he would not have
                        listened to any overtures of peace if this course would not have involved
                        the destruction of Lacedaemon. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As matters
                        were, since Nabis could not be crushed without ruining a city of the first
                        importance it seemed better to leave him weakened and almost entirely
                        deprived of any power to injure others rather than allow this city to
                        succumb from the effect of remedies too strong for it and perish in the very
                        process of recovering its liberty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After
                        this review of the past he went on to announce his intention of leaving for
                        Italy, taking the whole of his army with him. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He told them that in less than ten days they would hear
                        that the troops in occupation of Demetrias and Chalcis had been withdrawn,
                        and they would see with their own eyes Acrocorinthus evacuated and handed
                        over to the Achaeans immediately. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This
                        would show the whole world whether it was the Romans who were in the habit
                        of telling lies or the Aetolians, who in their public speeches had spread
                        abroad the notion <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> that it was a mistake
                        to entrust their liberties to Rome and that they had only changed their
                        Macedonian for Roman masters. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But that
                        people never cared in the least what they said or what they did. He advised
                        the other States to measure their friends by their deeds and not by their
                        words, and so learn whom to trust and whom to beware of. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They must use their liberty in moderation; under proper
                        restraints liberty was a blessing to individuals and communities alike; in
                        excess it was a danger to others and led to recklessness and violence on the
                        part of those who possessed it. The nobility, together with the various
                        classes of society in the different cities, must study to preserve internal
                        harmony, and the States as a whole must endeavour after mutual concord.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As long as they were of one mind
                        neither king nor tyrant would ever be strong enough to hurt them, but
                        discord and sedition gave every advantage to those who were seeking to
                        destroy their liberty, since the party which was worsted in a domestic
                        struggle would rather join hands with a foreigner than submit to a
                        fellow-citizen. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It must be their care to
                        defend and maintain the freedom which had been won for them by foreign arms
                        and restored to them on the faith of a foreign power. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Then the Roman people would know that the gift of
                        liberty had been made to those who were worthy of it and that their boon had
                        been well bestowed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These sentiments, such as a father might
                        have uttered called forth tears of joy from all who heard them, and for some
                        time the voice of <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the speaker was
                        drowned amidst the expressions of approval and the exhortations which the
                        audience addressed to each other to let these words sink into their hearts
                        and minds as though they were the words of an oracle. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> At last, when silence was restored, he asked them to
                        find out any Roman citizens who were living as slaves amongst them and send
                        them within two months' time to him in Thessaly. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> They would not, he felt sure, think it right or
                        honourable for their liberators to be in the position of slaves in the land
                        which they had liberated. They all exclaimed that among the other things for
                        which they were grateful they thanked him especially for reminding them of
                        so sacred and imperative a duty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was
                        an immense number who had been made prisoners in the Punic War, and as they
                        were not ransomed by their countrymen Hannibal sold them as slaves.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That they were very numerous is
                        evident from what Polybius says. He asserts that this undertaking cost the
                        Achaeans 100 talents, as they fixed the price to be paid to the owners at
                        500 denarii a head. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On this reckoning
                        Achaia must have held 1200 of them; you can estimate proportionally what was
                        the probable number throughout Greece. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        assembly was still sitting when, on looking round, they saw the troops
                        coming from Acrocorinthus; they marched straight through to the gate and
                        left the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The general followed them
                        amidst universal applause and shouts of "Saviour and Liberator." Then taking
                        his final leave of them he returned to Elatia by the same route by which he
                        had come. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> From there he despatched Appius
                        Claudius with the whole of his forces, they were to march through Thessaly
                        and Epirus to Oricum and wait for him there, as he intended to sail from
                        there with his army to Italy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His brother
                        Lucius, who was in command of the fleet, received written instructions to
                        collect ships from every part of the Greek coast. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He then proceeded to Chalcis and withdrew
                        the forces in occupation not only from that city, but from Oreus and Eretria
                        as well. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here he summoned a convention of
                        all the cities in Euboea, and after reminding them of the condition in which
                        he found them and the condition in which he was <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> leaving them, sent them back to their homes. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Going on to Demetrias, he withdrew his troops
                        from that place amidst the same enthusiasm on the part of the citizens as at
                        Corinth and Chalcis. He then resumed his progress into Thessaly, where the
                        cities had not only to be liberated but also brought back from confusion and
                        chaos into some tolerable form of government. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> This state of confusion arose from the disorders of the
                        time and the violence and lawlessness introduced by Philip, but it was due
                        quite as much to the quarrelsome character of the people, who never
                        conducted public proceedings of any kind, whether elections or conventions
                        or councils, without tumult and riot. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Quinctius selected the senate and the judges mostly from the propertied
                        classes and placed power in the hands of those whose interest it was to keep
                        everything in peace and security. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After thus traversing Thessaly he went on
                        through Epirus to Oricum, his starting place for Italy. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> From this point the whole of his army was carried
                        across to Brundisium, and from Brundisium they marched through the whole
                        length of Italy to the City in what was almost a triumphal procession, of
                        which the captured spoils formed as large a part as the troops themselves.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On his reaching Rome the senate met
                        outside the City to receive his report and they gladly decreed the triumph
                        he had so well earned. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Its celebration
                        lasted three days. On the first day he had carried through the City the arms
                        and armour and the bronze and marble statues; those taken from Philip were
                        more numerous than those which he had secured in the various cities.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the second day all the gold and
                        silver, coined and uncoined, were borne in the procession. There were 18,000
                        pounds of uncoined and unwrought silver and 270 of silver plate, including
                        vessels of every description, most of them embossed and some exquisitely
                        artistic. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There were also some made of
                        bronze. In addition to these there were ten silver shields. Of the silver
                        coinage 84,000 were Attic pieces, known as tetrachma, each nearly equal in
                        weight to four denarii. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The gold weighed
                        3714 pounds, including one shield made entirely of gold, and there were
                        14,514 coins from Philip's mint. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the
                        third day's procession were carried 114 golden coronets, the gifts of
                        various cities, and before the victor's chariot went the sacrificial victims
                        and many noble prisoners and hostages, amongst the latter Philip's son
                        Demetrius and Armenes the son of the Lacedaemonian tyrant. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Then came Quinctius himself in his chariot followed by
                        a long train of soldiers, as the whole of his army had been brought back
                        from the province. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Each infantryman
                        received a largess of 250 ases, each centurion twice as much, and each
                        cavalryman treble the amount. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A striking
                        feature in the procession was furnished by those who had been rescued from
                        slavery, and who with shaven heads followed <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> their deliverer. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of the year Q. Aelius Tubero,
                        a tribune of the plebs, acting on a resolution of the senate, brought a
                        proposal before the plebs, which was adopted, for the settlement of two
                        Latin colonies, one in Bruttium and the other in the territory of Thurium.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The commissioners who were to
                        supervise the settlement were appointed for three years. Those who were to
                        make the arrangements in Bruttium were Q. Naevius, M. Minucius Rufus and M.
                        Furius Crassipes; those put in charge of the Thurium settlement were A.
                        Manlius, Q. Aelius and L. Apustius. The elections in which they were chosen
                        were held by the City praetor, Cn. Domitius, in the Capitol. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> A number of temples were dedicated this year. One
                        was the temple of Juno Matuta in the Forum Olitorium. This had been vowed
                        four years previously and its building contracted for by C. Cornelius during
                        his consulship, and he dedicated it when he was censor. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Another was the temple of Faunus; the aediles C.
                        Scribonius and Cn. Domitius had contracted for its building two years before
                        out of the money raised by fines, and Cn. Domitius dedicated it when he was
                        City praetor. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Q. Marcius Rulla dedicated a
                        temple to Fortuna Primigenia on the Quirinal, having been made duumvir for
                        the purpose. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> P. Sempronius Sophus had
                        vowed it in the Punic War ten years previously, when he was consul, and he
                        had made the contract for it during his censorship. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> C. Servilius also dedicated a temple to Jupiter on the
                        Island, which had been vowed six years before in a war with the Gauls by the
                        praetor L. Furius Purpurio, who when consul signed the contract for its
                        construction. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> P. Scipio returned from his province of
                        Gaul to conduct the elections. The new consuls were L. Cornelius Merula and
                        Q. Minucius Thermus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The praetors were
                        elected on the following day; they were L. Cornelius Scipio, M. Fulvius
                        Nobilior, C. Scribonius, M. Valerius Messala, L. Porcius Licinus and C.
                        Flaminius. Atilius Serranus and L. Scribonius Libo were the first aediles
                        who made the Megalesia scenic Games. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It
                        was when these same aediles exhibited the Roman Games that the senate for
                        the first time sat apart from the people. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        This, like all innovations, excited much comment. Some regarded it as a
                        tribute which had long been due to the highest order in the State;
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> others considered that whatever
                        enhanced the greatness of the patricians detracted from the dignity of the
                        people, and that all such distinctions as mark off the different orders in
                        the State impair the concord and liberty which all ought equally to enjoy.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For 557 years the spectators had sat
                        promiscuously, what, people asked, had happened all of a sudden that the
                        patricians refused to have the plebeians amongst them? Why should a rich man
                        object to a poor man sitting by his side? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        It was a piece of unheard-of arrogance neither adopted nor wished for by any
                        other senate in the world. Even Africanus himself, who when consul was
                        responsible for the change, was said to have regretted it. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> So distasteful is any departure from ancient usage; so
                        much do men prefer to stand in the old ways except where they are clearly
                        condemned by experience. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the year of office of
                        the new consuls there were such frequent reports of the occurrence of
                        earthquakes that men grew tired not only of the subject itself, but also of
                        the suspension of business which was ordered on account of it. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> No meeting of the senate could be held nor any
                        public proceedings conducted, as the consuls were entirely occupied with
                        sacrifices and expiations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At last the
                        decemvirs received instructions to consult the Sacred Books, and in
                        accordance with their injunctions a three days' intercession was proclaimed.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Prayers were offered at all the
                        shrines, the suppliants wearing laurel wreaths, and a notice was issued
                        requiring all the members of a family to offer up their prayers together.
                        The senate authorised the consuls to publish an edict forbidding anyone to
                        report an earthquake on any day on which business had been suspended on
                        account of one already reported. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After
                        this the consuls balloted for their provinces. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Gaul fell to Cornelius and Liguria to Minucius. The
                        praetors' ballot resulted in C. Scribonius receiving the City jurisdiction,
                        M. Valerius that over aliens, L. Cornelius Sicily, L. Porcius Sardinia, C.
                        Flaminius Hither Spain and M. Fulvius Further Spain. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls were not looking forward to
                        any war during their year of office, when a despatch arrived from M.
                        Cincius, the commandant of Pisae, announcing a rising in Liguria. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Warlike resolutions had been passed in all the
                        councils of the nation, and 20,000 Ligurians were now in arms. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> They had ravaged the country round Luna, and
                        after crossing the frontiers of Pisae had traversed the whole length of the
                        coast. Minucius, to whom the province of Liguria had been allotted, acting
                        on <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the instructions of the senate,
                        mounted the Rostra and issued an edict for the two City legions which had
                        been enrolled the year before to muster in ten days' time at Arretium, their
                        place would be taken by two legions which he was going to raise. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He also notified the magistrates and officers of
                        those Latin and allied communities which were bound to furnish troops that
                        they should attend upon him in the Capitol. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> Here he arranged with them what contingent each city <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> should supply in proportion to the number of men they
                        had of military age, the total being fixed at 15,000 infantry and 500
                        cavalry. They were then instructed to start for home at once and raise their
                        troops without a moment's delay. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Fulvius
                        and Flaminius were each reinforced with Roman troops to the number of 3000
                        infantry and 100 cavalry and also 5000 infantry and 200 cavalry furnished by
                        the Latins and allies, and the praetors were ordered to disband the old
                        soldiers as soon as they arrived in their provinces. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Large numbers of the soldiers in the City legions urged
                        the tribunes of the plebs to investigate the cases of the men who pleaded
                        either length of service or ill-health as reasons why they should not be
                        called up. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This matter was quite thrown
                        aside by a despatch from Tiberius Sempronius, in which he stated that a body
                        of 10,000 Ligurians had appeared in the neighbourhood of Placentia and had
                        wasted the country with fire and sword up to the very walls of the colony
                        and the banks of the Po, and the Boii also were contemplating a revival of
                        hostilities. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In view of this announcement the senate
                        decreed that a state of emergency had arisen, and that they disapproved of
                        the tribunes investigating the soldiers' grievance and so preventing them
                        from assembling in obedience to the edict. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> They further ordered that the men of the allied contingents who had
                        served under P. Cornelius and Tiberius Sempronius and had been disbanded by
                        them should reassemble on the day which L. Cornelius named and in whatever
                        place in Etruria he notified to them. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Whilst on his way to his province the consul was to enlist and arm and take
                        with him whatever men he thought fit in the towns and country districts
                        through which he passed, and he was empowered to disband any of them
                        whenever he wanted to do so. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="57" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the consuls had raised the necessary
                        troops and left for their provinces, T. Quinctius requested the senate to
                        listen to his report of the arrangements which he had made in concert with
                        the ten commissioners, and if they thought good to ratify and confirm them.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They would, he said, be in a better
                        position to do this if they heard the statements of the envoys who had come
                        from every State in Greece as well as those who had come from the three
                        kings. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These deputations were introduced
                        to the senate by the City praetor, Caius Scribonius, and they all met with a
                        favourable reception. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As the negotiations
                        with Antiochus were somewhat protracted they were entrusted to the ten
                        commissioners, some of whom had been with the king either in Asia or in
                        Lysimachia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> T. Quinctius was authorised to
                        hear the envoys in the presence of the commissioners and make such a reply
                        as was consistent with the interests and the honour of the Roman people.
                        Menippus and Hegesianax were the leaders of the embassy, and the former was
                        the spokesman. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He professed himself at a
                        loss to understand what difficulty or complications his mission could create
                        as he had simply come to ask that friendly relations might be established
                        and an alliance formed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were three
                        kinds of treaties by means of which States and monarchs came to terms with
                        one another. In one case the conditions were dictated to those who had been
                        vanquished in war, for when everything had been surrendered to the one who
                        was the stronger in arms he had the absolute right to say what they might
                        retain and of what they were to be deprived. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> In the second case powers who have been equally matched in war form a
                        league of peace and amity on equal terms, for then they arrive at a mutual
                        understanding in respect of claims for indemnity, and where proprietorship
                        has been disturbed by the war, matters are adjusted either in accordance
                        with the former legal status or as is most convenient to the contracting
                        parties. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The third class of treaties
                        comprises those made by States which have never been enemies and who unite
                        in forming a league of friendship; no conditions are either imposed or
                        accepted, for these only exist between victors and vanquished. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> It was this latter kind of league that Antiochus
                        was seeking, and he (the speaker) was surprised that the Romans should think
                        it just and fair to impose conditions upon the king as to which of the
                        cities in Asia they decided should be free and autonomous and which should
                        pay tribute, and in the case of some forbidding the king to garrison them.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> These were terms on which to make
                        peace with Philip their enemy, not a treaty of alliance with Antiochus, who
                        was their friend. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="58" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following was Quinctius' reply: "Since
                        it pleases you to draw these distinctions and to enumerate the various ways
                        in which friendly relations can be established, I too will lay down the two
                        conditions apart from which, you may tell your king, no friendship with Rome
                        can be established. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One is this-if he does
                        not wish us to concern ourselves with the cities of Asia, he must himself
                        keep his hands off every part of Europe. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The other is this-if instead of confining himself within the frontiers of
                        Asia he crosses over into Europe, the Romans will be perfectly justified in
                        protecting their friendship with those cities where it exists and in winning
                        new ones." <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hegesianax replied: "Surely it
                        is an unworthy suggestion to say that Antiochus is excluded from the cities
                        of Thrace and the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> Chersonese which his
                        great-grandfather Seleucus won most gloriously after defeating Lysimachus,
                        who fell in the battle, and some of which Antiochus himself recovered by
                        force of arms from the Thracians who had taken possession of them, whilst
                        others which had been deserted, like Lysimachia, he repeopled with tillers
                        of the soil, and where they had been burnt or laid in ruin he rebuilt them
                        at a vast expense. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What resemblance could
                        there be between the renunciation by Antiochus of his right to cities which
                        had been acquired or recovered in this way and the non-interference of the
                        Romans in Asia, which had never belonged to them? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Antiochus was asking for the friendship of Rome, but it
                        was such a friendship as would bring him honour, not shame." <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> On this Quinctius observed: "As it is a question
                        of honour-a question which ought to be the sole, or at all events the
                        primary, one for the foremost nation in the world and for a monarch so great
                        as yours, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> which course appears to you
                        the more honourable, to desire the freedom of all the Greek cities wherever
                        they are or to keep them tributary and in bondage? <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> If Antiochus thinks that he is acting honourably in
                        claiming the lordship of cities which his great-grandfather held by the
                        right of war, a right which his father and <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> grandfather never asserted, the Roman people also
                        consider that their sense of honour and consistency forbid them to abandon
                        their championship of the liberties of Greece. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> As they liberated Greece from Philip, so it is their
                        intention to liberate the Greek cities in Asia from Antiochus. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Colonies were not founded in Aeolis and Ionia to
                        be in bondage to monarchs, but that their stock might multiply and a nation
                        of ancient lineage be propagated throughout the world." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="59" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As Hegesianax hesitated and could not deny
                        that the cause of liberty carried a more honourable title than that of
                        slavery, P. Sulpicius, the senior of the ten commissioners, said: "Let us
                        have no more beating about the bush; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        choose one of the two conditions which Quinctius has just put forward so
                        clearly; choose or drop this idle plea of friendship." <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> "It is not our wish," said Menippus, "nor is it in our
                        power to enter into any compact by which the sovereign rule of Antiochus
                        will be impaired." <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The next day Quinctius
                        introduced to the senate all the deputations from Greece and Asia, in order
                        that they might learn the attitude of the Romans and that of Antiochus
                        towards the cities of Greece. He laid his own demands before them and then
                        those of the king, and told them to report to their governments that the
                        Romans would <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> show the same courage and
                        fidelity in vindicating their liberties against Antiochus, if he did not
                        quit Europe, which they had shown in liberating them from Philip. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> On this Menippus earnestly begged Quinctius and
                        the senate not to precipitate a decision which might, when once taken, throw
                        the world into confusion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He asked them to
                        take time for reflection and allow the king to do the same. When the
                        conditions were reported to him, he would take them into consideration and
                        would obtain some modification of them or make some concessions for the sake
                        of peace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So the whole matter was
                        postponed and it was decided that the same commissioners should be sent to
                        the king who had been with him at Lysimachia, namely P. Sulpicius, P.
                        Villius and P. Aelius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="60" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scarcely had they started on their mission
                        when envoys came from Carthage with the intelligence that Antiochus was
                        undoubtedly preparing for war with the advice and assistance of Hannibal,
                        and apprehensions were felt as to the outbreak of a war with Carthage at the
                        same time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As was stated above, Hannibal,
                        a fugitive from his native country, had reached the court of Antiochus,
                        where he was treated with great distinction, the only motive for this being
                        that the king had long been meditating a war with Rome, and no one could be
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> more qualified to discuss the
                        subject with him than the Carthaginian commander. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He had never wavered in his opinion that the war should
                        be conducted on Italian soil; Italy would furnish both supplies and men to a
                        foreign foe. But, he argued, if that country remained undisturbed and Rome
                        were free to employ the strength and resources of Italy beyond its
                        frontiers, no monarch, no nation could meet her on equal terms. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> He wanted 100 decked ships and a force of 10,000
                        infantry and 1000 cavalry; he would take the fleet to Africa first as he
                        felt confident of being able to persuade the Carthaginians to enter upon
                        another war, and if they hung back he would raise up war against Rome in
                        some part of Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king should cross
                        over into Europe with the rest of his army and keep his troops somewhere in
                        Greece, not actually sailing for Italy, but prepared to do so; this would
                        give a sufficient impression of the magnitude of the war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="61" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had brought the king over to his
                        view, he thought he ought to prepare his countrymen, but he would not run
                        the risk of sending a written communication lest it should be intercepted
                        and his plans discovered. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During his visit
                        to Ephesus he had picked up a Tyrian servant named Aristo and, as he had
                        experience of the intelligent way in which he executed less important
                        commissions, Hannibal decided to make use of him. By means of bribes and
                        lavish promises, which the king himself endorsed, he was induced to go to
                        Carthage with instructions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hannibal
                        supplied him with a list of those whom it was necessary to interview, and he
                        also provided him with secret signs by which they might know that he had
                        really been commissioned by Hannibal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As
                        the man was constantly going about Carthage, Hannibal's enemies found out
                        the reason for his <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> visit quite as soon
                        as his friends, and the matter became the subject of conversation at social
                        gatherings and in the clubs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At last it
                        gave rise to discussion in the senate, where various speakers asserted that
                        nothing was gained by Hannibal's banishment if he was able to form
                        treasonable designs, and by carrying on an agitation amongst the citizens
                        threaten the peace and security of the State. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They declared that one Aristo, a Tyrian stranger, had
                        come furnished with instructions from Hannibal and Antiochus, that men who
                        were well known were holding furtive colloquies with him every day, and that
                        a mischief was being secretly hatched which would soon break out and bring
                        about universal ruin. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There was a general
                        outcry and all present demanded that Aristo should be summoned and
                        questioned as to the object of his visit, and unless he explained it, sent
                        with a deputation to Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "We have
                        suffered enough," they said, "for one man's recklessness; if private
                        citizens offend it will be at their own risk, the State must be preserved
                        from the taint and even from the suspicion of guilt." </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When Aristo appeared he endeavoured to
                        clear himself by relying mainly on the fact that he had brought nothing in
                        the shape of a letter to anyone. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Still he
                        did not give a satisfactory explanation of the object of his visit, and what
                        caused him most embarrassment was the allegation that his interviews were
                        confined to the members of the Barcine party. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> On this a heated discussion arose, one side demanding
                        his arrest and detention as a spy, the other asserting that there was no
                        ground for such irregular action, and it would form a bad precedent if
                        visitors from abroad were to be apprehended for no reason whatever.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The same thing would happen to the
                        Carthaginians at Tyre and the other commercial cities which they so largely
                        frequented. The debate was adjourned. Aristo, having to do with
                        Carthaginians, adopted a Carthaginian stratagem. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Early in the evening he hung up a placard in the
                        busiest part of the city over the tribunal where the magistrates sat day by
                        day. In the third watch of the night he boarded a vessel and fled away. When
                        the suffetes took their seats the next morning to administer justice they
                        saw the placard, took it down and read it. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                        /> It stated that Aristo's instructions were not intended for private
                        citizens; they were public and addressed to the "elders"-for so they
                        designated their senate. As this involved the whole government there was
                        less eagerness to investigate the few cases where suspicion fell. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> It was, however, decided that a deputation
                        should be sent to Rome to report the affair to the consuls and the senate
                        and at the same time lay a complaint against Masinissa. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="62" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Masinissa saw that the Carthaginians
                        were falling into bad odour with Rome and at variance amongst themselves-the
                        leaders of the Barcine party suspected by the senate owing to their
                        interviews with Aristo, <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> and the senate
                        suspected by the people in consequence of the notice which Aristo had put
                        up-he thought it a good opportunity for attacking them. The coastal district
                        which skirts the Lower Syrtis is called Emporia. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> It is a very fertile country and there is one city in
                        it-Leptis-which alone paid Carthage tribute to the extent of a talent a day.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This district Masinissa overran and
                        ravaged from end to end and occupied parts of it, so that it appeared
                        doubtful whether it belonged to him or to the Carthaginians. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> On learning that they had sent envoys to Rome to
                        meet the charges which had been made against them, and also to complain of
                        his conduct, he too sent a deputation to strengthen the suspicions against
                        Carthage and also to question the right of that government to exact tribute
                        from the district which he had invaded. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The Carthaginians were received in audience first, and their account of the
                        Tyrian stranger made the senate feel anxious lest they should be involved in
                        war with both Antiochus and Carthage at the same time. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> What strengthened their suspicions most of all was the
                        fact that after deciding to arrest Aristo and send him to Rome they had
                        neglected to keep either him or his ship under guard. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Then came the argument with Masinissa's representatives
                        as to the territory in dispute. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        Carthaginians rested their case on the adjudication of Scipio, as the
                        district lay within the frontiers of what, after his victory, he declared to
                        be Carthaginian territory, and they also relied on Masinissa's own
                        admission. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When Aphthires was a fugitive
                        from his kingdom and was roaming with a body of Numidians in the
                        neighbourhood of Cyrenae, Masinissa who was pursuing him asked permission to
                        traverse that district, showing thereby that he had no doubt as to its
                        belonging to Carthage. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Numidians contended that false
                        statements had been made as to Scipio's delimitation. If the origin of any
                        rights they claimed was inquired into, what ground in all Africa really
                        belonged to the Carthaginians? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When they
                        landed on its shores and sought a settlement they were granted as much land
                        on which to build their city as they could enclose within an ox-hide cut
                        into strips. Whatever ground they had gained outside Bursa they had gained
                        by violence and robbery. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As to the
                        territory in question, it was impossible for them to prove that it had been
                        in their possession from the beginning or even for any considerable length
                        of time. The Carthaginians and the kings of Numidia laid alternate claims to
                        it as opportunity offered; it always became the possession of those who for
                        the time being were the strongest in arms. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                        /> They begged the senate to let matters remain in the same state in which
                        they were before Carthage became the enemy or Masinissa the friend and ally
                        of Rome, and not to prevent him who was able to hold it from doing so.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The reply given to both parties was
                        to the effect that the senate would send a commission to Africa to settle
                        the dispute on the spot. The commissioners were P. Scipio Africanus, C.
                        Cornelius Cethegus and M. Minucius Rufus. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        After surveying the locality and hearing both sides they decided for neither
                        of them and left the whole question in abeyance. Whether they did this of
                        their own motion or whether they had received instructions to do so is
                        uncertain. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> What is certain is that under
                        the circumstances it was a matter of expediency that the question should
                        remain unsettled. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Had it not been so
                        Scipio, either through his knowledge of the facts or his personal influence
                        with both the contending parties, could have settled it by a nod. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
