<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    34</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1490" xml:id="p.1490"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXXIV.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> The Oppian law, respecting the dress of the women, after much debate, re-
                        pealed, notwithstanding it was strenuously supported by Marcus Porcius Cato,
                        the consul. The consul's successes in Spain. Titus Quinctius Flamininus
                        finishes the war with the Lacedaemonians and the tyrant Nabis; makes peace
                        with them, and restores liberty to Argos. Separate seats at the public
                        games, for the first time, appointed for the senators. Colonies sent forth.
                        Marcus Porcius Cato triumphs on account of his successes in Spain. Further
                        successes in Spain against the Boians and Insubrian Gauls. Titus Quinctius
                        Flamininus, having subdued Philip, king of Macedonia, and Nabis, the
                        Lacedaemonian tyrant, and restored all Greece to freedom, triumphs for three
                        days. Carthaginian ambassa- dors bring intelligence of the hostile designs
                        of Antiochus and Hannibal. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> AMID the serious concerns of important wars,
                    either scarcely brought to a close or impending, an incident intervened, trivial
                    indeed to be mentioned, but which, through the zeal of the parties concerned,
                    issued in a violent contest. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Marcus Fundanius
                    and Lucius Valerius, plebeian tribunes, proposed to the people the repealing of
                    the Oppian law. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This law, which had been
                    introduced by Caius Oppias, plebeian tribune, in the consulate of Quintus Fabius
                    and Tiberius Sempronius, during the heat of the Punic war, enacted that <quote>
                        no woman should possess more than half an ounce of gold, or wear a garment
                        of various colours, or ride in a carriage drawn by horses, in a city, or any
                        town, or any place nearer thereto than one mile; except on occasion of some
                        public religious solemnity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcus and Publius Junius Brutus, plebeian
                    tribunes, supported the Oppian law, and declared, that they would never suffer
                    it to be repealed; while many of the nobility stood forth to argue for and
                    against the motion proposed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Capitol was
                    filled with crowds, who favoured or opposed the law; nor could the matrons be
                    kept at home, either by advice or shame, nor even by the commands of their
                    husbands; but beset every street and pass in the city, beseeching the men as
                    they went down to the forum, that in the present flourishing state of the
                    commonwealth, when the private fortune of all was daily in- <pb n="1491"
                        xml:id="p.1491"/> creasing, they would suffer the women to have their former
                    ornaments of dress restored. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This throng of
                    women increased daily, for they arrived even from the country towns and
                    villages; and they had at length the boldness to come up to the consuls,
                    praetors, and magistrates, to urge their request. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> One of the consuls, however, they found especially
                    inexorable — Marcus Porcius Cato, who, in support of the law proposed to be
                    repealed, spoke to this effect: — </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If, Romans, every individual among us had
                    made it a rule to maintain the prerogative and authority of a husband with
                    respect to his own wife, we should have less trouble with the whole sex.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But now, our privileges, overpowered at
                    home by female contumacy, are, even here in the forum, spurned and trodden under
                    foot; and because we are unable to withstand each separately, we now dread their
                    collective body. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I was accustomed to think it
                    a fabulous and fictitious tale, that, in a certain island, the whole race of
                    males was utterly extirpated by a conspiracy of the women. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But the utmost danger may be apprehended equally from
                    either sex, if you suffer cabals, assemblies, and secret consultations to be
                    held: scarcely, indeed, can I determine, in my own mind, whether the act itself,
                    or the precedent that it affords, is of more pernicious tendency. The latter of
                    these more particularly concerns us consuls, and the other magistrates: the
                    former, yourselves, my fellow-citizens. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For,
                    whether the measure proposed to your consideration be profitable to the state or
                    not, is to be determined by you, who are about to go to the vote. As to the
                    outrageous behaviour of these women, whether it be merely an act of their own,
                    or owing to your instigations, Marcus Fundanius and Lucius Valerius, it
                    unquestionably implies culpable conduct in magistrates. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> I know not whether it reflects greater disgrace on you,
                    tribunes, or on the consuls: on you certainly, if you have, on the present
                    occasion, brought these women hither for the purpose of raising tribunitian
                    seditions; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> on us, if we suffer laws to be
                    imposed on us by a secession of women, as was done formerly by that of the
                    common people. It was not without painful emotions of shame, that I, just now,
                    made my way into the forum through the midst of a band of women. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Had I not been restrained by respect for the modesty
                    and dignity of some individuals among them, rather than of the whole number, and
                    been unwilling that they should be <pb n="1492" xml:id="p.1492"/> seen rebuked
                    by a consul, I should have said to them, 'What sort of practice is this, of
                    running out into public, besetting the streets, and addressing other women's
                    husbands? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Could not each have made the same
                    request to her husband at home? Are your blandishments more seducing in public
                    than in private; and with other women's husbands, than with your own? <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Although if the modesty of matrons confined them
                    within the limits of their own rights, it did not become you, even at home, to
                    concern yourselves about what laws might be passed or repealed here.' Our
                    ancestors thought it not proper that women should perform any, even private
                    business, without a director; but that they should be ever under the control of
                    parents, brothers, or husbands. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> We, it seems,
                    suffer them, now, to interfere in the management of state affairs, and to
                    introduce themselves into the forum, into general assemblies, and into
                    assemblies of election. For, what are they doing, at this moment, in your
                    streets and lanes? What, but arguing, some in support of the motion of the
                    plebeian tribunes; others, for the repeal of the law? <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Will you give the reins to their intractable nature, and
                    their uncontrolled passions, and then expect that themselves should set bounds
                    to their licentiousness, when you have failed to do so? <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> This is the smallest of the injunctions laid on them by
                    usage or the laws, all which women bear with impatience: <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> they long for liberty; or rather, to speak the truth, for
                    unbounded freedom in every particular. For what will they not attempt, if they
                    now come off victorious? </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Recollect all the institutions respecting the
                    sex, by which our forefathers restrained their undue freedom, and by which they
                    subjected them to their husbands; and yet, even with the help of all these
                    restrictions, you can scarcely keep them within bounds. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> If, then, you suffer them to throw these off one by one, to
                    tear them all asunder, and, at last, to be set on an equal footing with
                    yourselves, can you imagine that they will be any longer tolerable by you?
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The moment they have arrived at an
                    equality with you, they will have become your superiors. But, forsooth, they
                    only object to any new law being made against them: they mean to deprecate, not
                    justice, but severity. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nay, their wish is,
                    that a law which you have admitted, established by your suffrages, and confirmed
                    by the practice and experience of so many years to be beneficial, should <pb
                        n="1493" xml:id="p.1493"/> now be repealed; that is, that, by abolishing one
                    law, you should weaken all the rest. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No law
                    perfectly suits the convenience of every member of the community: the only
                    consideration is, whether, upon the whole, it be profitable to the greater part.
                    If, because a law proves obnoxious to a private individual, that circumstance
                    should destroy and sweep it away, to what purpose is it for the community to
                    enact general laws, which those, with reference to whom they were passed, could
                    presently repeal? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I should like, however, to
                    hear what this important affair is which has induced the matrons thus to run out
                    into public in this excited manner, scarcely restraining from pushing into the
                    forum and the assembly of the people. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Is it to
                    solicit that their parents, their husbands, children, and brothers may be
                    ransomed from captivity under Hannibal? By no means: and far be ever from the
                    commonwealth so unfortunate a situation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Yet,
                    even when such was the case, you refused this to their prayers. But it is not
                    duty, nor solicitude for their friends; it is religion that has collected them
                    together. They are about to receive the Idaean Mother, coming out of Phrygia
                    from Pessinus! What motive, that even common decency will allow to be mentioned,
                    is pretended for this female insurrection? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Why, say they, that we may shine in gold and purple; that, both on festal and
                    common days, we may ride through the city in our chariots, triumphing over
                    vanquished and abrogated law, after having captured and wrested from you your
                    suffrages; and that there may be no bounds to our expenses and our luxury. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Often have you heard me complain of the profuse expenses of the women
                        —often of those of the men; and that not only of men in private stations,
                        but of the magistrates: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and that the state
                        was endangered by two opposite vices, luxury and avarice; those pests, which
                        have been the ruin of all great empires. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        These I dread the more, as the circumstances of the commonwealth grow daily
                        more prosperous and happy; as the empire increases; as we have now passed
                        over into Greece and Asia, places abounding with every kind of temptation
                        that can inflame the passions; and as we have begun to handle even royal
                        treasures: so much the more do I fear that these matters will bring us into
                        captivity, rather than we them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Believe
                        me, those statues from Syracuse were brought into this city with hostile
                        effect. I already <pb n="1494" xml:id="p.1494"/> hear too many commending
                        and admiring the decorations of Athens and Corinth, and ridiculing the
                        earthen images of our Roman gods that stand on the fronts of their temples.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For my part I prefer these gods,
                        —propitious as they are, and I hope will continue to be, if we allow them to
                        remain in their own mansions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the
                        memory of our fathers, Pyrrhus, by his ambassador Cineas, made trial of the
                        dispositions, not only of our men, but of our women also, by offers of
                        presents: at that time the Oppian law, for restraining female luxury, had
                        not been made; and yet not one woman accepted a present. What, think you,
                        was the reason? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That for which our
                        ancestors made no provision by law on this subject: there was no luxury
                        existing which needed to be restrained. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As
                        diseases must necessarily be known before their remedies, so passions come
                        into being before the laws which prescribe limits to them. What called forth
                        the Licinian law, restricting estates to five hundred acres, but the
                        unbounded desire for enlarging estates? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        What the Cincian law, concerning gifts and presents, but that the plebeians
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Previous to the passing of
                            the Cincian law, about ten years before this time, the advocates who
                            pleaded in the courts received fees and presents: and as all or most of
                            these were senators, the plebeians are here represented as tributary to
                            the senate. By the above law they were forbidden to receive either fees
                            or presents. </note> had become <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        vassals and tributaries to the senate? It is not therefore in any degree
                        surprising, that no want of the Oppian law, or of any other, to limit the
                        expenses of the women, was felt at that time, when they refused to receive
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> gold and purple that was thrown in
                        their way, and offered to their acceptance. If Cineas were now to go round
                        the city with his presents, he would find numbers of women standing in the
                        public streets to receive them. There are some passions, the causes or
                        motives <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> of which I can no way account
                        for. For that that should not be lawful for you which is permitted to
                        another, may perhaps naturally excite some degree of shame or indignation;
                        yet, when the dress of all is alike, why should any one of you fear, lest
                        she should not be an object of observation? Of all kinds of shame, the
                        worst, surely, is <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> the being ashamed of
                        frugality or of poverty; but the law relieves you with regard to both; since
                        that which you have not it is unlawful for you to possess. This
                        equalization, says the rich matron, is <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        the very thing that I cannot endure. Why do not I make <pb n="1495"
                            xml:id="p.1495"/> a figure, distinguished with gold and purple? Why is
                        the poverty of others concealed under this cover of a law, so that it should
                        be thought that, if the law permitted, they would have such things as they
                        are not now able to procure? Romans, do you wish to excite among your wives
                        an emulation of this sort, that the rich <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        should wish to have what no other can have; and that the poor, lest they
                        should be despised as such, should extend their expenses beyond their means?
                        Be assured, that when a woman once begins to be ashamed of what she ought
                        not to be ashamed <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> of, she will not be
                        ashamed of what she ought. She who can, will purchase out of her own purse;
                        she who cannot, will ask her husband. Unhappy is the husband, both he who
                        complies with the <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> request, and he who
                        does not; for what he will not give himself, he will see given by another.
                        Now, they openly solicit <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> favours from
                        other women's husbands; and, what is more, solicit a law and votes. From
                        some they obtain them; although, with regard to yourself, your property, or
                        your children, they would be inexorable. So soon as the law shall cease to
                        limit the expenses of your wife, you yourself will never be able to do so.
                        Do not suppose that the matter will hereafter be in the same state in which
                        it was before the law was made on the subject. It is safer that a wicked man
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> should even never be accused, than
                        that he should be acquitted; and luxury, if it had never been meddled with,
                        would be more tolerable than it will be, now, like a wild beast, irritated
                        by having been chained, and then let loose. My opinion is, that the Oppian
                        law ought, on no account, to be repealed. Whatever determination you may
                        come to, I pray all the gods to prosper it. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After him the plebeian tribunes, who had
                    declared their intention of protesting, added a few words to the same purport.
                    Then Lucius Valerius spoke thus in support of the measure which he himself had
                    introduced: —"If private persons only had stood forth to argue for and against
                    the proposition which we have submitted to your consideration, I for my part,
                    thinking enough to have been said on both sides, would have waited in silence
                    for your determination. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But since a person of
                    most respectable judgment, the consul, Marcus Porcius, has reprobated our
                    motion, not only by the influence of his opinion, which, had he said nothing,
                    would carry very great weight, but also in a long and careful discourse, it be-
                        <pb n="1496" xml:id="p.1496"/> comes necessary to say a few words in answer.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He has spent more words in rebuking the
                    matrons, than in arguing against the measure proposed; and even went so far as
                    to mention a doubt, whether the matrons had committed the conduct which he
                    censured in them spontaneously or at our instigation. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> I shall defend the measure, not ourselves: for the consul
                    threw out those insinuations against us, rather for argument's sake, than as a
                    serious charge. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He has made use of the terms
                    cabal and sedition; and, sometimes, secession of the women: because the matrons
                    had requested of you, in the public streets, that, in this time of peace, when
                    the commonwealth is flourishing and happy, you would repeal a law that was made
                    against them during a war, and in times of distress. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> I know that these and other similar strong expressions, for
                    the purpose of exaggeration, are easily found; and, mild as Marcus Cato is in
                    his disposition, yet in his speeches he is not only vehement, but sometimes even
                    austere. What new thing, let me ask, have the matrons done in coming out into
                    public in a body on an occasion which nearly concerns themselves? <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Have they never before appeared in public? I will
                    turn over your own Antiquities, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Alluding to a treatise by Cato, upon the antiquities of Italy, entitled
                            <quote>Origines,</quote> which is the word used here by Valerius.
                    </note> and quote <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> them against you. Hear, now,
                    how often they have done the same, and always to the advantage of the public. In
                    the earliest period of our history, even in the reign of Romulus, when the
                    Capitol had been taken by the Sabines, and a pitched battle <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> was fought in the forum, was not the fight stopped by the
                    interposition of the matrons between the two armies? When, after the expulsion
                    of the kings, the legions of the Volscians, under the command of Marcius
                    Coriolanus, were encamped at the fifth stone, did not the matrons turn away that
                    army, which would have overwhelmed this city? Again, when Rome was taken by the
                    Gauls, whence was the city ransomed? Did not the matrons, by unanimous
                    agreement, bring their gold into the public treasury? In the late war, not to go
                    back <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> to remote antiquity, when there was a
                    want of money, did not the funds of the widows supply the treasury? And when
                    even new gods were invited hither to the relief of our distressed affairs, did
                    not the matrons go out in a body to the sea-shore to receive the Idaean Mother?
                    The cases, you will say, are dis- <pb n="1497" xml:id="p.1497"/> similar. It is
                    not <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> my purpose to produce similar instances;
                    it is sufficient that I clear these women of having done any thing new. Now,
                    what nobody wondered at their doing in cases which <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> concerned all in common, both men and women, can we wonder
                    at their doing in a case peculiarly affecting themselves? But what have they
                    done? We have proud ears, truly, <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> if, though
                    masters disdain not the prayers of slaves, we are offended at being asked a
                    favour by honourable women. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "I come now to the question in debate, with
                    respect to which the consul's argument is twofold: for, first, he is displeased
                    at the thought of any law whatever being repealed; and then, particularly, of
                    that law which was made to restrain female luxury. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> His former argument, in support of the laws in general,
                    appeared highly becoming of a consul; and that on the latter, against luxury,
                    was quite conformable to the rigid strictness of his morals. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There is, therefore, a danger lest, unless I shall show
                    what, on each subject, was inconclusive, you may probably be led away by error.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For while I acknowledge, that of those
                    laws which are instituted, not for any particular time, but for eternity, on
                    account of their perpetual utility, not one ought to be repealed; unless either
                    experience evince it to be useless, or some state of the public affairs render
                    it so; I see, at the same time, that those laws which particular seasons have
                    required, are mortal, (if I may use the term,) and changeable with the times.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those made in peace are generally repealed
                    by war; those made in war, by peace; as in the management of a ship, some
                    implements are useful in good weather, others in bad. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> As these two kinds are thus distinct in their nature, of
                    which kind does that law appear to be which we now propose to repeal? Is it an
                    ancient law of the kings, coeval with the city itself? <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Or, what is next to that, was it written in the twelve
                    tables by the decemvirs, appointed to form a code of laws? <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Is it one, without which our ancestors thought that the
                    honour of the female sex could not be preserved? and, therefore, have we also
                    reason to fear, that, together with it, we should repeal the modesty and
                    chastity of our females? Now, is there a man among you who does not know that
                    this is a new law, passed not more than twenty years ago, in the consulate of
                    Quintus Fabius and Tiberius Sempronius? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And
                    as, without <pb n="1498" xml:id="p.1498"/> it, our matrons sustained, for such a
                    number of years, the most virtuous characters, what danger is there of their
                    abandoning themselves to luxury on its being repealed? For, if that law had been
                    passed for the purpose of setting a limit to the passions of the sex, there
                    would be reason to fear lest the repeal of it might operate as an incitement to
                    them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But the real reason of its being
                    passed, the time itself will show. Hannibal was then in Italy, victorious at
                    Cannae: he already held possession of Tarentum, of Arpi, of Capua, and seemed
                    ready to bring up his army to the city of Rome. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Our allies had deserted us. We had neither soldiers to fill up the legions,
                    nor seamen to man the fleet, nor money in the treasury. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Slaves, who were to be employed as soldiers, were purchased
                    on condition of their price being paid to the owners at the end of the war. The
                    farmers of the revenues had declared, that they would contract to supply corn
                    and other matters, which the exigencies of the war required, to be paid for at
                    the same time. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> We gave up our slaves to the
                    oar, in numbers proportioned to our properties, and paid them out of our own
                    incomes. All our gold and silver, in imitation of the example given by the
                    senators, we dedicated to the use of the public. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Widows and minors lodged their money in the treasury. It
                    was provided by law that we should not keep in our houses more than a certain
                    quantity of wrought gold or silver, or more than a certain sum of coined silver
                    or brass. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> At such a time as this, were the
                    matrons so eagerly engaged in luxury and dress, that the Oppian law was
                    requisite to repress such practices; when the senate, because the sacrifice of
                    Ceres had been omitted, in consequence of all the matrons being in mourning,
                    ordered the mourning to end in thirty days? Who does not clearly see, that the
                    poverty and distress of the state, requiring that every private person's money
                    should be converted to the use of the public, enacted that law, with intent that
                    it should remain in force so long only as the cause of enacting the law should
                    remain? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> For if all the decrees of the senate
                    and orders of the people, which were then made to answer the necessities of the
                    times, are to be of perpetual obligation, why do we refund their money to
                    private persons? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Why do we contract for
                    public works for ready money? Why are not slaves brought to serve in the army?
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Why do not we, private subjects, supply
                    rowers as we did then? <pb n="1499" xml:id="p.1499"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Shall, then, every other class of people, every indi- vidual, feel the
                        improvement in the condition of the state; and shall our wives alone reap
                        none of the fruits of the public peace and tranquillity? <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Shall we men have the use of purple, wearing the
                        purple-bordered gown in magistracies and priests' offices? Shall our
                        children wear gowns bordered with purple? Shall we allow the privilege of
                        wearing the toga praetexta to the magistrates of the colonies and borough
                        towns, and to the very lowest of them here at Rome, the superintendents of
                        the streets; and not only of wearing such an ornament of distinction while
                        alive, but of being buried with it when dead; and shall we interdict the use
                        of purple to women alone? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when you,
                        the husband, may wear purple in your great coat, will you not suffer your
                        wife to have a purple mantle? Shall your horse be more splendidly
                        caparisoned than your wife is clothed? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But
                        with respect to purple, which will be worn out and consumed, I can see an
                        unjust, indeed, but still a sort of reason, for parsimony; but with respect
                        to gold, in which, excepting the price of the workmanship, there is no
                        waste, what objection can there be? It rather serves as a reserve fund for
                        both public and private exigencies, as you have already experienced. He says
                        there will be no emulation between individuals, when no one is possessed of
                        it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But, in truth, it will be a source of
                        grief and indignation to all, when they see those ornaments allowed to the
                        wives of the Latin confederates of which they themselves have been deprived;
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> when they see those riding through the
                        city in their carriages, and decorated with gold and purple, while they are
                        obliged to follow on foot, as if the seat of empire were in the country of
                        the others, not in their own. This would hurt the feelings even of men, and
                        what do you think must be its effect on those of weak women, whom even
                        trifles can disturb? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Neither offices of
                        state, nor of the priesthood, nor triumphs, nor badges of distinction, nor
                        military presents, nor spoils, can fall to their share. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Elegance of appearance, and ornaments, and dress, these
                        are the women's badges of distinction; in these they delight and glory;
                        these our ancestors called the women's world. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> What else do they lay aside when in mourning, except
                        their gold and purple? And what else do they resume when the mourning is
                        over? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> How do they distinguish themselves
                        on occasion of public thanksgivings and <pb n="1500" xml:id="p.1500"/>
                        supplications, but by adding unusual splendour of dress? But then, (it may
                        be said,) if you repeal the Oppian law, should you choose to prohibit any of
                        those particulars which the law at present prohibits, you will not have it
                        in your power; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> your daughters, wives, and
                        even the sisters of some, will be less under control. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The bondage of women is never shaken off without the
                        loss of their friends; and they themselves look with horror on that freedom
                        which is purchased with the condition of the widow or the orphan. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Their wish is, that their dress should be under
                        your regulation, not under that of the law; and it ought to be your wish to
                        hold them in control and guardianship, not in bondage; and to prefer the
                        title of father or husband to that of master. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The consul just now made use of some invidious terms,
                        calling it a female sedition and secession; because, I suppose, there is
                        danger of their seizing the sacred mount, as formerly the angry plebeians
                        did; or the Aventine. Their feeble nature must submit to whatever you think
                        proper to enjoin; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> and, the greater power
                        you possess, the more moderate ought you to be in the exercise of your
                        authority. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although all these considerations had been
                    urged against the motion and in its favour, the women next day poured out into
                    public in much greater numbers, and in <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> a
                    body beset the doors of the tribunes who had protested against the measure of
                    their colleagues; nor did they retire until this intervention was withdrawn.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was then no further doubt but that
                    every one of the tribes would vote for the repeal of the law. Thus was this law
                    annulled, in the twentieth year after it had been made. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The consul Marcus Porcius, as soon as the Oppian law was
                    abolished, sailed immediately, with twenty-five ships of war, of which five
                    belonged to the allies, to the port of Luna, where he ordered the troops to
                    assemble; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and having sent an edict along the
                    sea-coast, to collect ships of every description, at his departure from Luna he
                    left orders that they should follow him to the harbour of Pyrenaeus, as he
                    intended to proceed thence against the enemy with his collective fleet.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They accordingly, after sailing by the
                    Ligurian mountains and the Gallic bay, congregated together on the day
                    appointed. From thence they went to Rhoda, and forcibly dislodged a garrison of
                    Spaniards that were in that fortress. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From
                    Rhoda they proceeded with a <pb n="1501" xml:id="p.1501"/> favourable wind to
                    Emporiae, and there landed all the forces, excepting the crews of the ships. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At that time, as at present, Emporiae
                    consisted of two towns, separated by a wall. One was inhabited by Greeks from
                    Phocaea, whence the Massilians also derive their origin; the other by Spaniards.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Greek town, being open towards the
                    sea, had but a small extent of wall, not above four hundred paces in circuit;
                    but the Spanish town, being farther back from the sea, had a wall three thousand
                    paces in circumference. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A third kind of
                    inhabitants was added by the deified Caesar settling a Roman colony there, after
                    the final defeat of the sons of Pompey. At present they are all incorporated in
                    one mass; the Spaniards first, and, at length, the Greeks; having been adopted
                    into the Roman citizenship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whoever had, at
                    that period, observed the Greeks exposed on one side to the open sea, and on the
                    other to the Spaniards, a fierce and warlike race, would have wondered by what
                    cause they were preserved. Deficient in strength, they guarded against danger by
                    regular discipline; of which, among even more powerful people, the best
                    preservative is fear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That part of the wall
                    which faced the country, they kept strongly fortified, having but one gate, at
                    which some one of the magistrates was continually on guard. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> During the night, a third part of the citizens kept watch
                    on the walls, posting their watches, and going their rounds, not merely from the
                    force of custom, or in compliance with the law, but with as much vigilance as if
                    an enemy were at their gates. They never admitted any Spaniard into the city,
                    nor did they go outside the walls without precaution. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The passage to the sea was open to every one: but, through
                    the gate, next to the Spanish town, none ever passed, but in a large body; these
                    were generally the third division, which had watched on the walls the preceding
                    night. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The cause of their going out was this:
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the Spaniards, ignorant of maritime
                    affairs, were fond of trafficking with them, and glad of an opportunity of
                    purchasing, for their own use, the foreign goods, which the others imported in
                    their ships; and, at the same time, of finding a market for the produce of their
                    lands. The desire of this mutual intercourse caused the Spanish town to be
                    freely open to the Greeks. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They were thus the
                    more protected as being sheltered under the friendship of the Romans, which they
                    cultivated with as <pb n="1502" xml:id="p.1502"/> much cordial zeal, though not
                    possessed of equal resources, as the Massilians. On this account they received
                    the consul, and his army, with kindness and cordiality. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Cato staid there a few days, until he could learn what
                    force the enemy had, and where they lay; and, not to be idle during even that
                    short delay, he spent the whole time in exercising his men. It happened to be
                    the season of the year when the Spaniards had the corn in their barns.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He therefore ordered the purveyors not to
                    purchase any corn, and sent them home to Rome, saying, that the war would
                    maintain itself. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then, setting out from
                    Emporiae, he laid waste the lands of the enemy with fire and sword, spreading
                    terror and flight through the whole country. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time, as Marcus Helvius was going
                    home from Farther Spain, with an escort of six thousand men, given him by the
                    praetor, Appius Claudius, the Celtiberians, with a very numerous force, met him
                    near the city of Illiturgi. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Valerius says,
                    that they had twenty thousand effective men; that twelve thousand of them were
                    killed, the town of Illiturgi taken, and all the adult males put to the sword.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Helvius, soon after, arrived at the camp
                    of Cato; and as the region was now free from enemies, he sent back the escort to
                    Farther Spain, and proceeded to Rome, where, on account of his successful
                    services, he entered the city with an ovation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He carried into the treasury, of silver bullion, fourteen thousand pounds'
                    weight; of coined, seventeen thousand and twenty-three denarii; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 549 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 14 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi>
                    </note> and Oscan <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Osca, now Huesca,
                        was a city in Spain, remarkable for silver mines near it. </note> denarii,
                    one hundred and twenty thousand four hundred and thirty-eight. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 659 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 9 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The reason for which the senate refused him a
                    triumph was, because he fought under the auspices, and in the province, of
                    another. He had returned, moreover, two years after the expiration of his
                    office, because after he had resigned the government of the province to Quintus
                    Minucius, he was detained there, during the succeeding year, by a severe and
                    tedious sickness; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he therefore entered the
                    city in ovation, only two months before his successor, Quintus Minucius, enjoyed
                    a triumph. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The latter also brought into the
                    treasury thirty-four thousand <pb n="1503" xml:id="p.1503"/> eight hundred
                    pounds' weight of silver, seventy-eight thousand denarii, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 2430 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 11 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 3 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and of Oscan denarii two hundred and seventy-eight thousand. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 8889 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, in Spain, the consul lay encamped
                    at a small distance from Emporiae. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thither
                    came three ambassadors from Bilistages, chieftain of the Ilergetians, one of
                    whom was his son, representing, that <quote> their fortresses were besieged, and
                        that they had no hopes of being able to hold out, unless the Roman troops
                        came to their assistance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Three thousand
                        men, </quote> they said, <quote>would be sufficient;</quote> and they added,
                    that, <quote>if such a force came to their aid, the enemy would not keep their
                        ground.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To this the consul answered, that <quote> he
                        was truly concerned for their danger and their fears; but that he had by no
                        means so great an amount of forces, as that, while there lay in his
                        neighbourhood such a powerful force of the enemy, with whom he daily
                        expected a general engagement, he could safely diminish his strength by
                        dividing his troops. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The ambassadors, on hearing this, threw
                    themselves at the consul's feet, and with tears conjured him <quote> not to
                        forsake them at such a perilous juncture. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        For, if rejected by the Romans, to whom could they apply? They had no other
                        allies, no other hope on earth. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They might
                        have escaped the present hazard, if they had consented to forfeit their
                        faith, and to conspire with the rest; but no menaces, no appearances of
                        danger, had been able to shake their constancy, because they hoped to find
                        in the Romans abundant succour and support. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> If there was no further prospect of this, if it was refused them by the
                        consul, they called gods and men to witness, that reluctantly and under
                        compulsion they must change sides, to avoid such sufferings as the
                        Saguntines had undergone; and that they would perish together with the other
                        states of Spain, rather than alone. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They were thus dismissed on that day without
                    any positive answer. During the following night, the consul's thoughts were
                    greatly perplexed and divided. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He was
                    unwilling to abandon these allies, yet equally so to diminish his army, which
                    might either oblige him to decline a battle, or occasion danger in an
                    engagement. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was firmly resolved, however,
                    not to lessen his forces, lest he should in the mean time suffer some disgrace
                    from the enemy; and there- <pb n="1504" xml:id="p.1504"/> fore he judged it
                    expedient, instead of real succour, to hold out hopes to the allies. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> For he considered that, in many cases, but especially
                    in war, mere appearances have had all the effect of realities; and that a
                    person, under a firm persuasion that he can command resources, virtually has
                    them; that by that very confidence he was insured in his hopes and efforts.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next day he told the ambassadors, that
                        <quote> although he was afraid to lend a part of his forces to others, and
                        so to weaken his own, yet that he was giving more attention to their
                        circumstances and danger than to his own. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then gave orders to the third part of the
                    soldiers of every cohort, to make haste and prepare victuals, which they were to
                    carry with them on board ships, and that the vessels should be got in readiness
                    against the third day. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He desired two of the
                    ambassadors to carry an account of these proceedings to Bilistages and the
                    Ilergetians; but, by kind treatment and presents, he prevailed on the
                    chieftain's son to remain with him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    ambassadors did not leave the place until they saw the troops embarked on board
                    the ships; then reporting this at home as a matter of certainty, they spread,
                    not only among their own people, but likewise among the enemy, a confident
                    assurance of the approach of Roman succours. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, when a specious appearance had
                    been sufficiently exhibited, ordered the soldiers to be recalled from the ships;
                    and, as the season of the year now approached when it would be proper to enter
                    on action, he pitched a winter camp at the distance of three miles from
                    Emporiae. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From this post he frequently led out
                    his troops to ravage the enemy's country; sometimes to one quarter, sometimes to
                    another, as opportunity offered, leaving only a small guard in the camp.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They generally began their march in the
                    night, that they might proceed as far as possible from the camp, and surprise
                    the enemy unawares; and this practice disciplined the new-raised soldiers, and
                    great numbers of the enemy were cut off; so that they no longer dared to venture
                    beyond the walls of their forts. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he had
                    made himself thoroughly acquainted with the temper of the enemy, and of his own
                    men, he ordered the tribunes and the praefects, with all the horsemen and
                    centurions, to be called together, and addressed them thus: <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> The time is arrived, which you have often wished for, when you might
                        have an opportunity of <pb n="1505" xml:id="p.1505"/> displaying your
                        valour. Hitherto you have waged war rather as marauders than as regular
                        troops; you shall now meet your enemies hand to hand, in regular fight.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Henceforward you will have it in your
                        power, instead of pillaging country places, to exhaust the treasures of
                        cities. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Our fathers, at a time when the
                        Carthaginians had in Spain both commanders and armies, and had themselves
                        neither commander nor soldiers there, nevertheless insisted on its being an
                        article of treaty, that the river Iberus should be the boundary of their
                        empire. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Now, when two praetors of the
                        Romans, when a consul, and three armies are employed in Spain, and, for near
                        ten years past, no Carthaginian has been in either of its provinces, yet we
                        have lost that empire on the hither side of the Iberus. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> This it is your duty to recover by your valour and
                        arms; and to compel this nation, which is in a state rather of giddy
                        insurrection than of steady warfare, to receive again the yoke which it has
                        shaken off. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After thus generally exhorting them, he gave
                    notice, that he intended to march by night to the enemy's camp; and then
                    dismissed them to take refreshment. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At midnight, after having given his attention
                    to the auspices, he began his march, that he might take possession of such
                    ground as he chose, before the enemy should observe him. Having led his troops
                    beyond their camp, he formed them in order of battle, and at the first light
                    sent three cohorts close to their very ramparts. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The barbarians, surprised at the Romans appearing on their rear, ran hastily
                    to arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the mean time, the consul observed
                    to his men, <quote> Soldiers, you have no room for hope, but in your own
                        courage; and I have, purposely, taken care that it should be so. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The enemy are between us and our camp; behind us
                        is an enemy's country. What is most honourable, is likewise safest; namely,
                        to place all our hopes in our own valour. </quote> He then ordered the
                    cohorts to retreat, in order to draw out the barbarians by the appearance of
                    flight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Every thing happened as he had
                    expected. The enemy, thinking that the Romans retired through fear, rushed out
                    of the gate, and filled the whole space between their own camp and the line of
                    their adversaries. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While they were hastily
                    marshalling their troops, the consul, who had all his in readiness, and in
                    regular array, attacked them when in disorder. He caused the cavalry from <pb
                        n="1506" xml:id="p.1506"/> both wings to advance first to the charge: but
                    those on the right were immediately repulsed, and, retiring in disorder, spread
                    confusion among the infantry also. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On seeing
                    this, the consul ordered two chosen cohorts to march round the right flank of
                    the enemy, and show themselves on their rear, before the two lines of infantry
                    could close. The alarm which this gave the enemy, which had been thrown to a
                    disadvantage by the cowardice of the Roman horse, restored the fight to an
                    equality. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But such a panic had taken
                    possession of both the cavalry and infantry of the right wing, that the consul
                    laid hold of several with his own hand, and turned them about with their faces
                    to the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As long as the fight was carried
                    on with missile weapons, success was doubtful; and on the right wing, where the
                    disorder and flight had first began, the Romans with difficulty kept their
                    ground. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On their left wing, the barbarians
                    were both hard pressed in in front; and looked back, with timidity, at the
                    cohorts that threatened their rear. But when, after discharging their iron darts
                    and large javelins, they drew their swords, the battle, in a manner, began anew.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They were no longer wounded by random
                    blows from a distance, but, closing foot to foot, placed all their hope in
                    courage and strength. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consul's men were now spent with
                    fatigue, he reanimated their courage by bringing up into the fight some
                    subsidiary cohorts from the second line. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These
                    formed a new front, and being fresh themselves, and with fresh weapons attacking
                    the wearied enemy in the form of a wedge, by a furious onset they first forced
                    their way through them; and then, when they were once broken, scattered them and
                    put them to flight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They returned towards
                    their camp across the fields with all the speed they could make. When Cato saw
                    the rout become general, he rode back to the second legion, which had been
                    posted in reserve, and ordered the standards to be borne before it, and that it
                    should advance in quick motion, and attack the camp of the enemy. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> If any of them, through too much eagerness, pushed
                    forward beyond his rank, he himself rode up and struck them with his javelin,
                    and also ordered the tribunes and centurions to chastise them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> By this time the camp of the enemy was attacked, though the
                    Romans were kept off from the works by stones, poles, and weapons of every sort.
                    But, on the arrival of the fresh legion, <pb n="1507" xml:id="p.1507"/> the
                    assailants assumed new courage, and the enemy fought with redoubled fury in
                    defence of their rampart. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul
                    attentively examined every place himself, that he might break in at that quarter
                    where he saw the weakest resistance. At a gate on the left, he observed that the
                    guard was thin, and thither he led the first-rank men and spearmen of the second
                    legion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The party posted at the gate were not
                    able to withstand their assault; while the rest, seeing the enemy within the
                    rampart, abandoned the defence of the camp, and threw away their standards and
                    arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Great numbers were killed at the gates,
                    being stopped in the narrow passages by the throng of their own men; and the
                    soldiers of the second legion cut off the hindmost, while the rest were
                    plundering the camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> According to the account
                    of Valerius Antias, there were above forty thousand of the enemy killed on that
                    day. Cato himself, who was certainly no disparager of his own merits, says that
                    a great many were killed, but he specifies no number. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The conduct of' Cato on that day is judged
                    deserving of commendation in three particulars. First, in leading round his army
                    so far from his camp and fleet, as to fight the battle in the very middle of the
                    enemy, that his men might look for no safety but in their courage. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Secondly, in throwing the cohorts on the enemy's
                    rear. Thirdly, in ordering the second legion, when all the rest were disordered
                    by the eagerness of their pursuit, to advance at a full pace to the gate of the
                    camp, in compact and regular order under their standards. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He delayed not to improve his victory; but having sounded a
                    retreat, and brought back his men laden with spoil, he allowed them a few hours
                    of the night for rest; and then led them out to ravage the country. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> They spread their depredations the wider, as the
                    enemy were dispersed in their flight; and this circumstance, no less than the
                    defeat of the preceding day, obliged the Spaniards of Emporiae, and those of
                    their neighbourhood, to make a submission. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Many also, belonging to other states, who had made their escape to Emporiae,
                    surrendered; all of whom the consul received with kindness, and after refreshing
                    them with victuals and wine, dismissed to their several homes. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He quickly decamped thence, and wherever the army proceeded
                    on its march, he was met by ambassadors, surrendering their respective states;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> so that, by the <pb n="1508"
                        xml:id="p.1508"/> time when he arrived at Tarraco, all Spain on this side of
                    the Ebro was in a state of perfect subjection; and the Roman prisoners, and
                    those of their allies and the Latin confederates, who by various chances had
                    fallen into the hands of the enemies in Spain, were brought back by the
                    barbarians, as an offering to the consul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A
                    rumour afterwards spread abroad, that Cato intended to lead his army into
                    Turditania; and it was given out, with equal falsehood, that he meant to proceed
                    to the remote inhabitants of the mountains. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On
                    this groundless, unauthenticated report, seven forts of the Bergistans revolted;
                    but the Roman, marching thither, reduced them to subjection without any battle
                    worthy of narration. Not very long after, when the consul returned to Tarraco,
                    and before he removed to any other place, the same persons revolted again.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They were again subdued; but, on this
                    second reduction, met not the same mild treatment; they were all sold by
                    auction, that they might not any oftener disturb the peace. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time, the praetor, Publius
                    Manlius, having received the army from Quintius Minucius, whom he had succeeded,
                    and joined to it the old army of Appius Claudius Nero, from Farther Spain,
                    marched into Turditania. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of all the Spaniards,
                    the Turditanians are reckoned the least warlike; nevertheless, relying on their
                    great numbers, they went to oppose the march of the Romans. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The cavalry, having been sent forward, at once broke their
                    line; and with the infantry there was hardly any conflict. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The veteran soldiers, well acquainted with the enemy and
                    their manner of fighting, effectually decided the battle. This engagement,
                    however, did not terminate the war. The Turdulans hired ten thousand
                    Celtiberians, and prepared to carry on the war with foreign troops. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, meanwhile, alarmed at the rebellion of
                    the Bergistans, and suspecting that the other states would act in like manner
                    when occasion offered, took away their arms from all the Spaniards on this side
                    of the Iberus; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> which proceeding affected them
                    so deeply, that many laid violent hands on themselves; this fierce race
                    considering that, without arms, life was of no value. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> When this was reported to the consul, he summoned before
                    him the senators of every one of the states, to whom he spoke thus: <quote> It
                        is not more our interest than it is your own, that you should not rebel;
                        since your insurrections have, hitherto, always drawn more mis- <pb n="1509"
                            xml:id="p.1509"/> fortune on the Spaniards than labour on the Roman
                        armies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To prevent such things happening
                        in future, I know but one method, which is, to put it out of your power to
                        rebel. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I wish to effect this in the
                        gentlest way, and that you would assist me therein with your advice. I will
                        follow none with greater pleasure than what yourselves shall offer. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They all remaining silent, he told them that
                    he would give them a few days' time to consider the matter. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When, on being called together, even in the second meeting,
                    they uttered not a word, in one day he razed the walls of all their fortresses;
                    and marching against those who had not yet submitted, he received in every
                    country, as he passed through, the submission of all the neighbouring states.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Segestica alone, an important and opulent
                    city, he reduced by works and engines. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Cato had greater difficulties to surmount, in
                    subduing the enemy, than had those commanders who came first into Spain; for
                    this reason, that the Spaniards, through disgust at the Carthaginian government,
                    came over to their side; whereas he had the task of enforcing their submission
                    to slavery, in a manner, after they had been in full enjoyment of liberty.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Besides, he found the whole province in a
                    state of commotion; insomuch, that some were in arms, and others were compelled
                    to join in the revolt by being besieged, nor would they have been able to hold
                    out any longer if they had not received timely succour. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But so vigorous was the spirit and capacity of the consul,
                    that there was no kind of business, whether great or small, which he did not
                    himself attend to and perform; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and he not only
                    planned and ordered, but generally executed in person such measures as were
                    expedient; nor did he practise a more strict and rigorous discipline over any
                    one than over himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In spare diet,
                    watching, and labour, he vied with the meanest of his soldiers; nor, excepting
                    the honour of his post, and the command, had he any peculiar distinction above
                    the rest of the army. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians, summoned forth by the enemy
                    for hire, as above mentioned, rendered the war in Turditania more difficult to
                    the praetor, Publius Manlius. The consul, therefore, in compliance with a letter
                    from the praetor, led his legions thither. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    Celtiberians and Turditanians were lying in separate camps at the approach of
                    the Romans, who began immediately to skirmish with the Turditanians, making <pb
                        n="1510" xml:id="p.1510"/> attacks on their advanced guards; and they
                    constantly came off victorious from every engagement, however rashly undertaken.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul ordered some military tribunes
                    to enter into a conference with the Celtiberians, and to offer them their choice
                    of three proposals: first, to come over, if they wished, it, to the Romans, and
                    receive double the pay for which they had agreed with the Turditanians:
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the second, to depart to their own homes,
                    on receiving assurance, under the sanction of <milestone n="5??" unit="section"
                    /> the public faith, that it should not operate to their injury that they had
                    joined the enemies of the Romans: the third was, that, if they were absolutely
                    determined on war, they should appoint a day and place to decide the matter with
                    him by arms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Celtiberians desired a day's
                    time for consideration; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and an assembly was
                    held, but in great confusion, from the Turditanians mingling in it, so that no
                    resolution could be come to. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Although it was
                    uncertain whether there was to be war or peace with the Celtiberians, the
                    Romans, nevertheless, just as though the latter were determined on, brought
                    provisions from the lands and forts of the enemy, and soon ventured to go within
                    their fortifications, relying on private truces, as they would on a common
                    intercourse established by authority. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the
                    consul found that he could not entice the enemy to a battle, he first led out a
                    number of cohorts, lightly accoutred, in regular order, to ravage a part of the
                    country which was yet unhurt; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> then hearing
                    that all the baggage of the Celtiberians was deposited at Saguntia, he proceeded
                    thither to attack that town, but was unable, notwithstanding, to provoke them to
                    stir. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Paying, therefore, his own troops and
                    those of Minucius, he left the bulk of his army in the praetor's camp, and, with
                    seven cohorts, returned to the Iberus. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With that small force he took several towns.
                    The Sidetonians, Ausetanians, and Suessetanians came over to his side.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Lacetanians, a remote and wild nation,
                    still remained in arms; partly through their natural ferocity, and partly
                    through consciousness of guilt, in having laid waste, by sudden incursions, the
                    country of the allies, while the consul and his army were employed in the war
                    with the Turditanians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He therefore marched to
                    attack their capital, not only with the Roman cohorts, but also with the troops
                    of the allies, who were justly incensed against them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The town <pb n="1511" xml:id="p.1511"/> was stretched out
                    into considerable length, but had not proportionable breadth. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> At the distance of about four hundred paces from it he
                    halted, and leaving there a party composed of chosen cohorts, he charged them
                    not to stir from that spot until he himself should come to them; and then he led
                    round the rest of the men to the farther side of the town. The greater part of
                    his auxiliary troops were Suessetanians, and these he ordered to advance and
                    assault the wall. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Lacetanians, knowing
                    their arms and standards, and remembering how often they had themselves, with
                    impunity, committed every kind of outrage and insult in their territory, how
                    often defeated and routed them in pitched battles, hastily threw open a gate,
                    and all, in one body, rushed out against them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Suessetanians scarcely stood their shout, much less their onset; <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> and the consul, on seeing this happen, just as he had
                    foreseen, galloped back under the enemy's wall to his cohorts, brought them up
                    quickly to that part of the city where all <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    was silence and solitude, in consequence of the Lacetanians having sallied out
                    on the Suessetanians, and took possession of every part of it before the
                    Lacetanians returned; who, having nothing now left but their arms, soon
                    surrendered themselves also. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The conqueror marched thence, without delay,
                    to the fort of Vergium. This was, almost entirely, a receptacle of robbers and
                    plunderers, and thence incursions were made on the peaceable parts of the
                    province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One of the principal inhabitants
                    deserted out of the place to the consul, and endeavoured to excuse himself and
                    his countrymen; alleging, that <quote> the management of affairs was not in
                        their hands; for the robbers, having gained admittance, had reduced the fort
                        entirely under their own power. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul ordered him to return home, and
                    pretend some plausible reason for having been absent; and then, <quote> when he
                        should see him advancing to the walls, <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                        and the robbers intent on defending the city, to seize the citadel with such
                        men as favoured his party. </quote> This was executed according to his
                    directions. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The double alarm, from the Romans
                    scaling the walls in front, and the citadel being seized on their rear, at once
                    entirely confounded the barbarians. The consul, having taken possession of the
                    place, ordered, that those who had secured the citadel should, with their
                    relations, be set at liberty, and enjoy their pro- <pb n="1512" xml:id="p.1512"
                    /> perty, the rest of the natives he commanded the quaestor to sell; and he put
                    the robbers to death. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having restored quiet in
                    the province, he settled the iron and silver mines on such a footing, that they
                    produced a large revenue; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and, in consequence
                    of the regulations then made, the province daily increased in riches. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> On account of these services performed in Spain, the
                    senate decreed a supplication for three days. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this summer, the other consul, Lucius
                    Valerius Flaccus, fought a pitched battle with a body of the Boians in Gaul,
                    near the forest of Litanae, and gained a complete victory. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Eight thousand of the Gauls are said to have been slain;
                    the rest, desisting from further opposition, retired quietly to their several
                    villages and lands. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> During the remainder of
                    the summer, the consul kept his army near the Po, at Placentia and Cremona, and
                    repaired the buildings in these cities which had been demolished in the war.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While the affairs of Italy and Spain were
                    in this posture, Titus Quinctius had spent the winter in Greece, in such a
                    manner, that, excepting the Aetolians, who neither had gained rewards of victory
                    adequate to their hopes, nor were capable of being long contented with a state
                    of quiet, all Greece, being in full enjoyment of the blessings of peace and
                    liberty, were highly pleased with their present state; and they admired not more
                    the Roman general's bravery in arms, than his temperance, justice, and
                    moderation in victory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And now a decree of the
                    senate was brought to him, containing a denunciation of war against Nabis the
                    Lacedaemonian. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On reading it, Quinctius
                    summoned a convention of deputies from all the allied states, to be held, on a
                    certain day, at Corinth. Whither when many persons of the first rank came
                    together, from all quarters, forming a very full assembly, from which even the
                    Aetolians were not absent, he addressed them in this manner: — <quote> The
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Romans and Greeks, in the war which
                        they waged against Philip, were united in affections and councils, and they
                        had each no less their separate reasons for entering into it. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> For he had violated friendship with the Romans;
                        first by aiding our enemies, the Carthaginians; and then by attacking our
                        allies here: and, towards you, his conduct was such, that even if we had
                        been willing to forget our own injuries, those offered by him to you would
                        have constituted a sufficient occasion of war. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> But the business to be considered this day <pb n="1513"
                            xml:id="p.1513"/> has relation wholly to yourselves: <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> for the subject which I propose to your consideration
                        is, whether you choose to suffer Argos, which, as you know, has been seized
                        by Nabis, to remain under his dominion; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        or whether you judge it reasonable, that a city of such high reputation and
                        antiquity, seated in the centre of Greece, should be restored to liberty,
                        and placed in the same state with the rest of the cities of Peloponnesus and
                        of Greece. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This question, as you see,
                        merely respects yourselves; it concerns not the Romans in any degree,
                        excepting so far as the one city being left in subjection to tyranny hinders
                        their glory, in having liberated Greece, from being full and complete.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If, however, you are not moved by
                        regard for that city, nor by the example, nor by the danger of the contagion
                        of that evil spreading wider, we, for our parts, shall rest content. On this
                        subject I desire your opinions, resolved to abide by whatever the majority
                        of you shall determine. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the address of the Roman general, the
                    several deputies proceeded to give their opinions. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The ambassador of the Athenians extolled, to the utmost of
                    his power, and expressed the greatest gratitude for the kindness of the Romans
                    towards Greece, <quote> in having, when applied to for assistance, brought them
                        succours against Philip; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and now, without
                        being applied to, voluntarily offering assistance against the tyrant Nabis. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He at the same time severely censured the
                    conduct of some, who, in their discourses, <quote> depreciated those kindnesses,
                        and propagated evil surmises of the future, when it would better become them
                        rather to return thanks for the past. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was evident that this was pointed at the
                    Aetolians: wherefore Alexander, deputy of that nation, having first inveighed
                    against the Athenians, who, having formerly been the most strenuous supporters
                    of liberty, now betrayed the general cause, for the sake of recommending
                    themselves by flattery. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then complained
                    that <quote> the Achaeans, formerly soldiers of Philip, and lately, on the
                        decline of his fortune, deserters from him, had regained possession of
                        Corinth, and were so acting as that they might acquire Argos; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> while the Aetolians, who had first opposed their
                        arms to Philip, who had always been allies of the Romans, and who had
                        stipulated by treaty, that, on the Macedonian being conquered, the lands and
                        cities should be theirs, were defrauded of Echinus and <pb n="1514"
                            xml:id="p.1514"/> Pharsalus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He charged the Romans with insincerity,
                    because, <quote> while they put forth empty professions of establishing liberty,
                        they held possession of Demetrias and Chalcis by their garrisons; <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> though, when Philip hesitated to withdraw his
                        garrisons from those places, they always urged against him, that the
                        Grecians would never be free while Demetrias, Chalcis, and Corinth were in
                        the hands of the others. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And, lastly,
                        that they named Argos and Nabis merely as a pretext for remaining in Greece,
                        and keeping their armies there. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Let them
                        carry away their legions to Italy; and the Aetolians were ready to
                        undertake, either that Nabis should voluntarily withdraw his forces from
                        Argos, on terms; or they would compel him by force of arms to comply with
                        the unanimous judgment of Greece. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This arrogant speech called up, first,
                    Aristaenus, praetor of the Achaeans, who said: — <quote> Forbid <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> it, Jupiter, supremely good and great, and imperial
                        Juno, the tutelar deity of Argos, that that city should be staked as a prize
                        between the Lacedaemonian tyrant and the Aetolian plunderers, under such
                        unhappy circumstances, that its being retaken by you should be productive of
                        more calamitous consequences than its capture by him. Titus Quinctius, the
                        sea lying between us, does not secure us from those robbers; what then will
                        become of us, should they procure themselves a stronghold in the centre of
                        Peloponnesus? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They have nothing Grecian
                        but the language, as they have nothing human but the shape. They live under
                        customs and rites more brutally savage than any barbarians, nay, than wild
                        beasts themselves. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Wherefore, Romans, we
                        beseech you, not only to recover Argos from Nabis, but also to establish the
                        affairs of Greece on such a footing, as to leave these countries adequately
                        secured from the robberies of the Aetolians. </quote> The rest concurring in
                    these censures on the Aetolians, the Roman general said, that <quote> he had
                        himself intended to have answered them, but that he perceived all so highly
                        incensed against those people, that the general resentment required rather
                        to be appeased than irritated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Satisfied,
                        therefore, with the sentiments entertained of the Romans, and of the
                        Aetolians, he would simply put this question: What was the general opinion
                        concerning war with Nabis, in case of his refusing to restore Argos to the
                        Achaeans? </quote> When all had pronounced for war, he recommended to them,
                        <pb n="1515" xml:id="p.1515"/> to send in their shares of auxiliary troops,
                    each state in proportion to its ability. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                    even sent an ambassador to the Aetolians; rather to make them disclose their
                    sentiments, which was the actual result, than with any hope of obtaining their
                    concurrence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He gave orders to the military
                    tribunes, to bring up the army from Elatia. To the ambassadors of Antiochus,
                    who, at this time, proposed to treat of an alliance, he answered, that <quote>
                        he could say nothing on the subject in the absence of the ten ambassadors.
                        They must go to Rome, and apply to the senate. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as the troops arrived from Elatia,
                    Quinctius set out to lead them towards Argos. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    When near Cleonae he was met by the praetor, Aristaenus, with ten thousand
                    Achaean foot and one thousand horse; and having joined forces, they pitched
                    their camp at a small distance from thence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Next day they marched down into the plains of Argos, and fixed their post about
                    four miles from that city. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The commander of
                    the Lacedaemonian garrison was Pythagoras, the tyrant's son-in-law, and his
                    wife's brother; who, on the approach of the Romans, posted strong guards in both
                    the citadels, for Argos has two, and in every other place that was commodious
                    for defence, or exposed to danger. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But, while
                    thus employed, he could by no means dissemble the dread inspired by the approach
                    of the Romans; and, to the alarm from abroad, was added an insurrection within.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There was an Argive, named Damocles, a
                    youth of more spirit than prudence, who held conversations, with proper persons,
                    on a design of expelling the garrison; at first, with the precaution of imposing
                    an oath, but afterwards, through his eager desire to add strength to the
                    conspiracy, he estimated people's sincerity with too little caution. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> While he was in conference with his accomplices, an
                    officer, sent by the commander of the garrison, summoned him to appear before
                    him, and he perceived that his design was betrayed; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> on which, exhorting the conspirators, who were present, to
                    take arms with him, rather than be tortured to death, he went on with a few
                    companions towards <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the forum, crying out to
                    all who wished the preservation of the state, to follow him as the vindicator
                    and author of their liberty. He could prevail on none to join him; for they saw
                    no prospect of any attainable advantage, and much less any sufficiently powerful
                    support. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While he exclaimed in this <pb
                        n="1516" xml:id="p.1516"/> manner, the Lacedaemonians surrounded him and his
                    party, and put them to death. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Many others
                    were afterwards seized, the greater part of whom were executed, and the
                    remaining few thrown into prison. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> During the
                    following night, great numbers, letting themselves down from the walls by ropes,
                    came over to the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As these men affirmed, that if the Roman army
                    had been at the gates, this commotion would not have ended without effect;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and that, if the camp was brought nearer,
                    the Argives would not remain inactive; Quinctius sent some horsemen and
                    infantry, lightly accoutred, who, meeting at the Cylarabis, a place of exercise,
                    less than three hundred paces from the city, a party of Lacedaemonians, who
                    sallied out of a gate, engaged them, and, without much difficulty, drove them
                    back into the town; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the Roman general
                    encamped on the very spot where the battle had been fought. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> There he passed one day, on the look-out if any new
                    commotion might arise; but perceiving that the inhabitants were quite depressed
                    by fear, he called a council concerning the besieging of Argos. All the deputies
                    of Greece, except Aristaenus, were of one opinion, that, as that city was the
                    sole object of the war, with it the war should commence. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This was by no means agreeable to Quinctius; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> but he listened, with evident marks of approbation,
                    to Aristaenus, arguing in opposition to the joint opinion of all the rest; while
                    he himself added, that "as the war was undertaken in favour of the Argives,
                        <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> against the tyrant, what could be less
                    proper than to leave the enemy in quiet, and lay siege to Argos? For his part,
                    he was resolved to point his arms against the main object of the war, Lacedaemon
                    and the tyrant. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then dismissed the meeting,
                    and sent out light-armed cohorts to collect forage. Whatever was ripe in the
                    adjacent country, they reaped, and brought together; and what was green they
                    trod down and destroyed, that the enemy might not subsequently get it.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then proceeded over Mount Parthenius,
                    and, passing by Tegaea, encamped on the third day at Caryae; where he waited for
                    the auxiliary troops of the allies, before he entered the enemy's territory.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Fifteen hundred Macedonians came from
                    Philip, and four hundred horsemen of the Thessalians; and now the Roman general
                    had no occasion to wait for more auxiliaries, having abundance; but he was
                    obliged to stop for supplies of <pb n="1517" xml:id="p.1517"/> provisions, which
                    he had ordered the neighbouring cities to furnish. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> He was joined also by a powerful naval force; Lucius
                    Quinctius had already come from Leucas, with forty ships; eighteen ships of war
                    had arrived from the Rhodians; and king Eumenes was cruising among the Cyclades,
                    with ten decked ships, thirty barks, and smaller vessels of various sorts.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Of the Lacedaemonians themselves, also, a
                    great many, who had been driven from home by the cruelty of the tyrants, came
                    into the Roman camp, in hopes of being reinstated in their country; for the
                    number was very great of those who had been banished by the several despots,
                    during many generations, since they first got Lacedaemon into their power.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The principal person among the exiles was
                    Agesipolis, to whom the sovereignty of Lacedaemon belonged in right of his
                    birth; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> but who had been driven out when an
                    infant by Lycurgus, after the death of Cleomenes, who was the first tyrant of
                    Lacedaemon. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although Nabis was enclosed between such
                    powerful armaments on land and sea, and, on a comparative view of his own and
                    his enemy's strength, could scarcely conceive any degree of hope; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> yet he did not desist from the war, but brought, from
                    Crete, a thousand chosen young men of that country in addition to a thousand
                    whom he had before; he had, besides, under arms, three thousand mercenary
                    soldiers, and ten thousand of his countrymen, with the peasants, who belonged to
                    the fortresses. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He fortified the city with a
                    ditch and rampart; and lest any intestine commotion should arise, curbed the
                    people's spirits by fear, punishing them with extreme severity, as he could not
                    hope for good wishes towards a tyrant. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As he
                    had his suspicions respecting some of the citizens, he drew out all his forces
                    to a field called Dromos, (the course,) and ordered the Lacedaemonians to be
                    called to an assembly without their arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He
                    then formed a line of armed men round the place where they were assembled,
                    observing briefly, <quote> that he ought to be excused, if, at such a juncture,
                        he feared and guarded against every thing that might happen; <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> and that, if the present state of affairs
                        subjected any to suspicion, it was their advantage to be prevented from
                        attempting any design, rather than to be punished for attempting it: he
                        therefore intended, </quote> he said, <quote> to keep certain persons in
                        custody, until the storm, which then threatened, should <pb n="1518"
                            xml:id="p.1518"/> have passed over; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        and would discharge them as soon as the enemy should have been driven away,
                        from whom the danger would be less, when proper precaution was taken against
                        internal treachery. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He then ordered the names of about eighty of
                    the principal young men to be called over, and as each answered to his name, he
                    put them in custody. On the night following, they were all put to death.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Some of the Helotes, a race of rustics,
                    who have been feudal vassals even from the earliest times, being charged with an
                    intention to desert, they were driven with stripes through all the streets, and
                    put to death. The terror which this excited so confounded the multitude, as to
                    deter them from all attempts to effect a revolution. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He kept his forces within the fortifications, knowing that
                    he was not a match for the enemy in the field; and, besides, he was afraid to
                    leave the city, while all men's minds were in a state of such suspense and
                    uncertainty. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius, when all his preparations were now
                    sufficiently made, decamped; and, on the second day, came to Sellasia, on the
                    river Œnus, on the spot where it is said Antigonus, king of Macedonia, fought a
                    pitched battle with Cleomenes, tyrant of Lacedaemon. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Being told that the ascent from thence was difficult, and
                    the passes narrow, he made a short circuit by the mountains, sending forward a
                    party to make a road, and came, by a tolerably broad and open passage, to the
                    river Eurotas, where it flows almost immediately under the walls of the city.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here, the tyrant's auxiliary troops
                    attacked the Romans, while they were forming their camp, together with Quinctius
                    himself, (who, with a division of cavalry and light troops, had advanced beyond
                    the rest,) and threw them into a state of alarm and confusion; not expecting any
                    thing of the kind, as no one had opposed them throughout their whole march, and
                    they had passed, as it were, through a friendly territory. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The disorder lasted a considerable time, the infantry
                    calling for aid on the cavalry, and the cavalry on the infantry, each having but
                    little confidence in himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At length, the
                    foremost ranks of the legions came up; and no sooner had the cohorts of the
                    vanguard taken part in the fight, than those who had lately been an object of
                    dread were driven back in terror into the city. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> The Romans, retiring so far from the wall as to be out of the reach of
                    weapons, stood there for some time in battle-array; and then, none of the <pb
                        n="1519" xml:id="p.1519"/> enemy coming out against them, retired to their
                    camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Next day Quinctius led on his army in
                    regular order along the bank of the river, passed the city, to the foot of the
                    mountain of Menelaus, the legionary cohorts marching in front, and the cavalry
                    and light infantry bringing up the rear. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nabis
                    kept his mercenary troops, on whom he placed his whole reliance, in readiness,
                    and drawn up in a body, within the walls, intending to attack the rear of the
                    enemy; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and, as soon as the last of their
                    troops passed by, these rushed out of the town, from several places at once,
                    with as great fury as the day before. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    rear was commanded by Appius Claudius, who having beforehand prepared his men to
                    expect such an event, that it might not come upon them unawares, instantly made
                    his troops face about, and presented an entire front to the enemy. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> A regular engagement, therefore, took place, as if
                    two complete lines had encountered, and it lasted a considerable time; but at
                    length Nabis's troops betook themselves to flight, which would have been
                    attended with less dismay and danger, if they had not been closely pressed by
                    the Achaeans, who were well acquainted with the ground. These made dreadful
                    havoc, and dispersing them entirely, obliged the greater part to throw away
                    their arms. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Quinctius encamped near Amyclae;
                    and afterwards, when he had utterly laid waste all the pleasant and thickly
                    inhabited country round the city, not one of the enemy venturing out of the
                    gates, he removed his camp to the river Eurotas. From thence he ravaged the
                    valley lying under Taygetus, and the country reaching as far as the sea. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time, Lucius Quinctius got
                    possession of the towns on the sea-coast; of some, by their voluntary surrender;
                    of others, by fear or force. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then, learning
                    that the Lacedaemonians made Gythium the repository of all their naval stores,
                    and that the Roman camp was at no great distance from the sea, he resolved to
                    attack that town with his whole force. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was,
                    at that time, a place of considerable strength; well furnished with great
                    numbers of native inhabitants and settlers from other parts, and with every kind
                    of warlike stores. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Very seasonably for
                    Quinctius, when commencing an enterprise of no easy nature, king Eumenes and the
                    Rhodian fleet came to his assistance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The vast
                    multitude of seamen, collected out of the three fleets, finished in a <pb
                        n="1520" xml:id="p.1520"/> few days all the works requisite for the siege of
                    a city so strongly fortified, both on the land side and on that next the sea.
                    Covered galleries were soon brought up; the wall was undermined, and, at the
                    same time, shaken with battering- rams. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By the
                    frequent shocks given with these, one of the towers was thrown down, and, by its
                    fall, the adjoining wall on each side was laid flat. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans, on this, attempted to force in, both on the
                    side next the port, to which the approach was more level than to the rest,
                    hoping to divert the enemy's attention from the more open passage, and, at the
                    same time, to enter the breach caused by the falling of the wall. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They were near effecting their design of penetrating
                    into the town, when the assault was suspended by the prospect which was held out
                    of the surrender of the city. This, however, was subsequently dissipated.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Dexagoridas and Gorgopas commanded there,
                    with equal authority. Dexagoridas had sent to the Roman general a message that
                    he would give up the city; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and, after the
                    time and the mode of proceeding had been agreed on, he was slain as a traitor by
                    Gorgopas, and the defence of the city was maintained with redoubled vigour by
                    this single commander. The further prosecution of the siege would have been much
                    more difficult, had not Titus Quinctius arrived with a body of four thousand
                    chosen men. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He showed his army in order of
                    battle, on the brow of a hill at a small distance from the city; and, on the
                    other side, Lucius Quinctius plied the enemy hard with his engines, both on the
                    quarter of the sea, and of the land; on which Gorgopas was compelled to adopt
                    that proceeding, which, in the case of another, he had punished with death.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After stipulating for liberty to carry
                    away the soldiers <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> whom he had there as a
                    garrison, he surrendered the city to Quinctius. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> Previous to the surrender of Gythium, Pythagoras, who had been left as
                    commander at Argos, having intrusted the defence of the city to Timocrates of
                    Pellene, with a thousand mercenary soldiers, and two thousand Argives, came to
                    Lacedaemon and joined Nabis. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Although Nabis had been greatly alarmed at the
                    first arrival of the Roman fleet, and the surrender of the towns on the
                    sea-coast, yet, as long as Gythium was held by his troops, he had quieted his
                    apprehensions with that scanty hope; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but when
                    he heard that Gythium, too, was given up to the Ro- <pb n="1521" xml:id="p.1521"
                    /> mans, and saw that he had no room for any kind of hope on the land, where
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> every place round was in the hands of
                    the enemy, and that he was totally excluded from the sea, he considered that he
                    must yield to fortune. He first sent a messenger into the Roman camp, to learn
                    whether permission would be given to send ambassadors. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This being consented to, Pythagoras came to the general,
                    with no other commission than to propose a conference between that commander and
                    the tyrant. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A council was summoned on the
                    proposal, and every one present agreeing in opinion that a conference should be
                    granted, a time and place were appointed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They
                    came, with moderate escorts, to some hills in the interjacent ground; and
                    leaving their cohorts there, in posts open to the view of both parties, they
                    went down to the place of meeting; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nabis
                    attended by a select party of his body-guards; Quinctius by his brother, king
                    Eumenes, Sosilaus, the Rhodian, Aristaenus, praetor of the Achaeans, and a few
                    military tribunes. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the tyrant, having the choice given him
                    either to speak first or to listen, began thus: <quote> Titus Quinctius, and you
                        who are present, if I could collect from my own reflections the reason of
                        your having either declared or actually made war against me, I should have
                        waited in silence the issue of my destiny. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        But in the present state of things, I could not repress my desire of
                        knowing, before I am ruined, the cause for which my ruin is resolved on.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And in truth, if you were such men as
                        the Carthaginians are represented to be,-men who considered the obligation
                        of faith, pledged in alliances, as in no degree sacred, I should not wonder
                        if you were the less scrupulous with respect to your conduct towards me.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, instead of that, when I look at
                        you, I perceive that you are Romans: men who allow treaties to be the most
                        solemn of religious acts, and faith, pledged therein, the strongest of human
                        ties. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, when I look back at myself, I
                        am confident I am one who, as a member of the community, am, in common with
                        the rest of the Lacedaemonians, included in a treaty subsisting with you, of
                        very ancient date; and likewise have, lately, during the war with Philip,
                        concluded anew, in my own name, a personal friendship and alliance with you.
                        But it appears I have violated and cancelled that treaty, by holding
                        possession of the city of Argos. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In what
                        manner shall I defend this? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By the
                        consideration of the fact, <pb n="1522" xml:id="p.1522"/> or of the time.
                        The consideration of the fact furnishes me with a twofold defence: for, in
                        the first place, in consequence of an invitation from the inhabitants
                        themselves, and of their voluntary act of surrender, I accepted the
                        possession of that city, and did not seize it by force. In the next place, I
                        accepted it, when the city was in league with Philip, not in alliance with
                        you. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the consideration of the time
                        acquits me, inasmuch as when I was in actual possession of Argos, the
                        alliance was entered into between you and me, and you stipulated that I
                        should send you aid against Philip, not that I should withdraw my garrison
                        from that city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In this dispute,
                        therefore, so far as it relates to Argos, I have unquestionably the
                        advantage, both from the equity of the proceeding, as I gained possession of
                        a city which belonged not to you, but to your enemy; and as I gained it by
                        its own voluntary act, and not by forcible compulsion; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> and also from your own acknowledgment; since, in the
                        articles of our alliance, you left Argos to me. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But then, the name of tyrant, and my conduct, are
                        strong objections against me: that I call forth slaves to a state of
                        freedom; that I carry out the indigent part of the populace, and give them
                        settlements in lands. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> With respect to the
                        title by which I am styled, I can answer thus: That, let me be what I may, I
                        am the same now that I was at the time when you yourself, Titus Quinctius,
                        concluded an alliance with me. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I
                        remember, that I was then styled king by you; now, I see, I am called
                        tyrant. If, therefore, I had since altered the style of my office, I might
                        have an account to render of my fickleness: as you choose to alter it, that
                        account should be rendered by you. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As to
                        what relates to the augmenting the number of the populace, by giving liberty
                        to slaves, and the distribution of lands to the needy; on this head, too, I
                        might defend myself by a reference to time. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                        /> These measures, of what complexion soever they are, I had practised
                        before you formed friendship with me, and received my aid in the war against
                        Philip. But, if I did the same things, at this moment, I would not say to
                        you, how did I thereby injure you, or violate the friendship subsisting
                        between us? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> but that, in so doing, I
                        acted agreeably to the practice and institutions of my ancestors. Do not
                        estimate what is done at Lacedaemon by the standard of your own laws and
                        constitution. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> There is no necessity for
                        comparing <pb n="1523" xml:id="p.1523"/> particular institutions: you are
                        guided in your choice of a horseman, by the quantity of his property; in
                        your choice of a foot soldier, by the quantity of his property; and your
                        plan is, that a few should abound in wealth, and that the body of the people
                        should be in subjection to them. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Our
                        lawgiver did not choose that the administration of government should be in
                        the hands of a few, such as you call a senate; or that this or that order of
                        citizens should have a superiority over the rest: but he considered that, by
                        equalizing the property and dignity of all, he should multiply the number of
                        those who were to bear arms for their country. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> I acknowledge that I have enlarged on these matters,
                        beyond what consists with the conciseness customary with my countrymen, and
                        that the sum of the whole might be comprised in few words: that, since I
                        first commenced a friendship with you, I have given you no just cause to
                        repent it. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman general answered: <quote> We never
                        contracted any friendship or alliance with you, but with Pelops, the right
                        and lawful king of Lacedaemon: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> whose
                        authority, while the Carthaginian, Gallic, and other wars, succeeding one
                        another, kept us constantly employed, the tyrants, who after him held
                        Lacedaemon under forced subjection, usurped into their own hands, as did you
                        also during the late war with Macedonia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        For what could be less fitting, than that we, who were waging war against
                        Philip, in favour of the liberty of Greece, should contract friendship with
                        a tyrant, and a tyrant the most cruel and violent towards his subjects that
                        ever existed? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But, even supposing that you
                        had not either seized or held Argos by iniquitous means, it would be
                        incumbent on us, when we are giving liberty to all Greece, to reinstate
                        Lacedaemon also in its ancient freedom, and the enjoyment of its own laws,
                        which you just now spoke of, as if you were a rival of Lycurgus. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Shall we take pains to make Philip's garrisons
                        evacuate Tassus and Bargylii; and shall we leave Lacedaemon and Argos, those
                        two most illustrious cities, formerly the lights of Greece, under your feet,
                        that their continuance in bondage may tarnish our title of deliverers of
                        Greece? But the Argives took part with Philip: we excuse you from taking any
                        concern in that cause, so that you need not be angry with them on our
                        behalf. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> We have received sufficient proof,
                        that the guilt of that proceeding is chargeable <pb n="1524" xml:id="p.1524"
                        /> on two only, or, at most, three persons, and not on the state; just,
                        indeed, as in the case of the invitation given to you and to your army, and
                        your reception into the citadel, not one step was taken by public authority.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We know, that the Thessalians,
                        Phocians, and Locrians, with unanimous consent, joined in espousing the
                        cause of Philip; yet we have given liberty to them in common with the rest
                        of Greece. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> How then can you suppose we
                        shall conduct ourselves towards the Argives, who are acquitted of having
                        publicly authorized misconduct? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> You said,
                        that your inviting slaves to liberty, and the distribution of lands among
                        the indigent, were objected to you as crimes; and crimes, surely, they are,
                        of no small magnitude. But what are they in comparison with those atrocious
                        deeds, that are daily perpetrated by you and your adherents, in continual
                        succession? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Show us a free assembly of
                        the people, either at Argos or Lacedaemon, if you wish to hear a true
                        recital of the crimes of the most abandoned tyranny. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> To omit all other instances of older date, what a
                        massacre did your son-in-law, Pythagoras, make at Argos almost before my
                        eyes! What another did you yourself perpetrate, when I was nearly within the
                        confines of the Lacedaemonians! <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Now, give
                        orders, that the persons whom you took out of the midst of an assembly, and
                        committed to prison, after declaring, in the hearing of all your countrymen,
                        that you would keep them in custody, be produced in their chains, that their
                        wretched parents may know that those are alive, for whom, under a false
                        impression, they are mourning. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Well, but
                        you say, though all these things were so, Romans, how do they concern you?
                        Can you say this to the deliverers of Greece; to people who crossed the sea,
                        and have maintained a war on sea and land, to effect its deliverance?
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Still you tell us, you have not
                        directly violated the alliance, or the friendship established between us.
                        How many instances must I produce of your having done so? <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> But I will not go into a long detail; I will bring the
                        matter to a short issue. By what acts is friendship violated? Most
                        effectually by these two: by treating our friends as foes; and by uniting
                        yourself with our enemies. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Each of these
                        has been done by you. For Messene, which had been united to us in
                        friendship, by one and the same bond of alliance with Lacedaemon, you, while
                        professing yourself our ally, reduced to subjection by force of <pb n="1525"
                            xml:id="p.1525"/> arms, though you knew it was in alliance with us;
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> and you contracted with Philip, our
                        professed enemy, not only an alliance, but even an affinity, through the
                        intervention of his general, Philocles: <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        and waging actual war against us, with your piratical ships, you made the
                        sea round Malea unsafe, and you captured and slew more Roman citizens almost
                        than Philip himself; and to our ships conveying provisions to our armies the
                        coast of Macedonia itself was less dangerous, than the promontory of Malea.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Cease, therefore, to vaunt your good
                        faith, and the obligations of treaties; <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                        and, dropping a popular style of discourse, speak as a tyrant, and as an
                        enemy. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Aristaenus then began, at first to advise, and
                    afterwards even to beseech Nabis, while it was yet in his power, and he had the
                    opportunity, to consider what was best for himself and his interests. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> He then mentioned the names of several tyrants in the
                    neighbouring states who had resigned their authority, and restored liberty to
                    their people, and afterwards spent among their fellow citizens not only a secure
                    but an honoured old age. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These observations
                    having been reciprocally made and listened to, the approach of night broke up
                    the conference. Next day Nabis said, that he was willing to cede Argos, and
                    withdraw his garrison, since such was the desire of the Romans, and to deliver
                    up the prisoners and deserters; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and if they
                    demanded any thing further, he requested that they would set it down in writing,
                    that he might deliberate on it with his friends. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Thus the tyrant gained time for consultation; and Quinctius also, on his
                    part, called a council, to which he summoned the chiefs of the allies. The
                    greatest part were of opinion, that <quote> they ought to persevere in the war,
                        and that the tyrant should be altogether got rid of; <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> otherwise the liberty of Greece would never be secure.
                        That it would have been much better never to have entered on the war than to
                        drop it after it was begun; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for this would
                        be a kind of approbation of his tyrannical usurpation, and which would
                        establish <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> him more firmly, as giving the
                        countenance of the Roman people to his ill-acquired authority, and that he
                        would quickly spirit up many in other states to plot against the liberty of
                        their countrymen. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The wishes of the general himself tended
                    rather to peace; for he saw that, as the enemy was shut up in the town, nothing
                    remained but a siege, and that must be very tedious. For it was not Gythium that
                    they <pb n="1526" xml:id="p.1526"/> must besiege, though even that place had
                    been gained by capitulation, not by assault; but Lacedaemon, a city most
                    powerful in men and arms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The only hope which
                    they could have formed was, that, on the first approach of their army,
                    dissensions and insurrections might have been raised within: but, though the
                    standards had been seen to advance almost to the gates, not one person had
                    stirred. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To this he added, that <quote>
                        Villius the ambassador, returning from Antiochus, brought intelligence, that
                        the peace was an unsound one; and that the king had come over into Europe
                        with a much more powerful armament by sea and land than before. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Now, if the army should be engaged in the siege
                        of Lacedaemon, with what other forces could the war be maintained against a
                        king of his great power and strength? </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These arguments he urged openly; but beneath
                    all this there lay a concealed anxiety lest one of the new consuls should be
                    appointed to the province of Greece; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and then
                    the honour of terminating the war, in which he had proceeded so far, must be
                    yielded to a successor. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Finding that he could not, by opposition, make
                    any alteration in the sentiments of the allies, by pretending to go over to
                    their opinion, he led them all into a concurrence in his plan. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Be it so,</quote> said he, <quote> and may success attend us: let us lay
                        siege to Lacedaemon, since that is your choice. However, as a business so
                        slow in its progress, as you know the besieging of cities to be, very often
                        wears out the patience of the besiegers sooner than that of the besieged,
                        you ought at once to make up your minds to this, that we must pass the
                        winter under the walls of Lacedaemon. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If
                        this delay involved only toil and danger, I would recommend to you to
                        prepare your minds and bodies to support these. But, in the present case,
                        vast expenses also will be requisite for the construction of works, for
                        machines and engines, sufficient <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> for the
                        siege of so great a city, and for procuring stores of provisions for the
                        winter to serve you and us: therefore, to prevent your being suddenly
                        disconcerted, or shamefully deserting an enterprise which you had engaged
                        in, I think it will be necessary <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> for you
                        to write home to your respective states, and learn what degree of spirit and
                        of strength each possesses. Of auxiliary troops I have a sufficient number,
                        and to spare; but the more numerous we are, the more numerous will be our
                        wants. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The country of the enemy has
                        nothing left but the naked soil. <pb n="1527" xml:id="p.1527"/> Besides, the
                        winter is at hand, which will render it difficult to convey what we may
                        stand in need of from distant places. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This speech first turned their thoughts to the
                    domestic evils prevailing in their several states; the indolence of those who
                    remained at home; the envy and misrepresentations to which those who were
                    serving abroad were liable; that a state of freedom was a difficult one in which
                    to procure unanimity; the want of public funds, and people's backwardness to
                    contribute out of their private property. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Their inclinations being thus suddenly changed, they gave full power to the
                    general, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> to do whatever he judged conducive
                    to the general interest of the Roman people and their allies. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Quinctius, consulting only his
                    lieutenant-generals and military tribunes, drew up the following conditions on
                    which peace should be made with the tyrant: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That there should be a suspension of arms for six months, between Nabis
                        on one part, and the Romans, king Eumenes, and the Rhodians on the other.
                        That Titus Quinctius and Nabis should immediately send ambassadors to Rome,
                        in order that the peace might be ratified by authority of the senate.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That, whatever day a written copy of
                        these conditions should be delivered to Nabis, on that day should the
                        armistice commence; and, within ten days after, his garrisons should be
                        withdrawn from Argos, and all other towns in the territory of the Argives;
                        all which towns should be entirely evacuated, restored to freedom, and
                        delivered to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That no slave,
                        whether belonging to the king, the public, or a private person, be removed
                        out of any of them; and if any had been removed before, that they be
                        faithfully restored to their owners. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That
                        he should return the ships, which he had taken from the maritime states; and
                        should not have any other than two barks; and these to be navigated with no
                        more than sixteen oars. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That he should
                        restore to all the states in alliance with the Roman people, the prisoners
                        and deserters in his hands; and to the Messenians, all the effects that
                        could be discovered, and which their possessors could own. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> That he should, likewise, restore to the exiled
                        Lacedaemonians their children, and their wives, who chose to follow their
                        husbands; provided that no woman should be obliged, against her will, to go
                        with her husband into exile. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That such of
                        the mercenary soldiers of Nabis as had deserted him, and gone either to
                        their own <pb n="1528" xml:id="p.1528"/> countries or to the Romans, should
                        have all their effects faithfully returned to them. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> That he should hold possession of no city in the island
                        of Crete; and that such as were then in his possession should be given up to
                        the Romans. That he should not form any alliance, or wage war, with any of
                        the Cretan states, or with any other. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        That he should withdraw all his garrisons from those cities, which he should
                        give up, and which had put themselves, and their country, under the dominion
                        and protection of the Roman people; and should take care that, in future, he
                        should restrain both himself and his subjects from molesting them.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That he should not build any town or
                        fort in his own, or any other territory. That, to secure the performance of
                        these conditions, he should give five hostages, such as the Roman general
                        should choose, and among them his own son: and should pay, at present, one
                        hundred talents of silver; and fifty talents, annually, for eight years.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These articles were put into writing, and sent
                    into Lacedaemon, the camp having been removed, and brought nearer to the town.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The tyrant saw nothing in them that gave
                    him much satisfaction, excepting that, beyond his hopes, no mention had been
                    made of bringing back the exiles. But what mortified him most of all, was, the
                    depriving him of his shipping, and of the maritime towns: for the sea had been a
                    source of great profit to him; his piratical vessels having continually infested
                    the whole coast from the promontory of Malea. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, he found in the young men of those towns recruits for his army, who
                    made by far the best of his soldiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Though
                    he discussed those conditions in private with his confidential friends, yet, as
                    the ministers in the courts of kings, faithless in other respects, are
                    particularly so with respect to the concealing of secrets, rumour soon made them
                    all public. The public, in general, expressed not so great a disapprobation of
                    the whole of the terms, as did individuals, of the articles particularly
                    affecting themselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Those who had the wives
                    of the exiles in marriage, or had possessed themselves of any of their property,
                    were provoked, as if they were to lose what was their own, and not to make
                    restitution of what belonged to others. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    slaves, who had been set at liberty by the tyrant, perceived plainly, not only
                    that their enfranchisement would be annulled, but that their servitude <pb
                        n="1529" xml:id="p.1529"/> would be much more severe than it had been
                    before, when they should be again put under the power of their incensed masters.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The mercenary soldiers were dissatisfied,
                    because, in consequence of a peace, their pay would cease; and they knew also,
                    that they could not return among their own countrymen, who detested not tyrants
                    more than they did their abettors. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They at first spoke of these matters, in their
                    circles, with murmurs of discontent; and afterwards, suddenly ran to arms.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From which tumultuous proceeding, the
                    tyrant perceived that the passions of the multitude were of themselves
                    sufficiently inflamed, and immediately ordered a general assembly to be
                    summoned. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here he explained to them the terms
                    which the Romans strove to impose, to which he falsely added others, more severe
                    and humiliating. While, on the mention of each particular, sometimes the whole
                    assembly, sometimes different parties, raised a shout of disapprobation, he
                    asked them, <quote>What answer they wished him to give; or what they would have
                        him do?</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On which all, as it were with one voice, cried
                    out, <quote>To give no answer, to continue the war;</quote> and they began, as
                    is common with a multitude, every one to encourage the rest, to keep up their
                    spirits, and cherish good hopes, observing, that <quote>fortune favours the
                        brave.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Animated by these expressions, the tyrant
                    assured them, that Antiochus, and the Aetolians, would come to their assistance;
                    and that he had, in the mean time, resources abundantly sufficient for the
                    maintenance of a siege. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The very mention of
                    peace had vanished from the minds of all, and unable to contain themselves
                    longer in quiet, they ran out in parties against the advanced guards of the
                    enemy. The sally of these few skirmishers, and the weapons which they threw,
                    immediately removed all doubt from the Romans that the war was to continue.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During the four following days, several
                    slight encounters took place, at first without any decisive result; but, on the
                    fifth day after, in a kind of regular engagement, the Lacedaemonians were
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> beaten back into the town, in such a
                    panic, that several Roman soldiers, pressing close on the rear of the fugitives,
                    entered the city through open spaces, not secured with a wall, of which, at that
                    time, there were several. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Quinctius, having, by this repulse,
                    effectually checked the sallies of the enemy, and being fully convinced <pb
                        n="1530" xml:id="p.1530"/> that he had now no alternative, but must besiege
                    the city, sent persons to bring up all the marine forces from Gythium; and, in
                    the mean time, rode himself, with some military tribunes, round the walls, to
                    take a view of the situation of the place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In
                    former times, Sparta had no wall; of late, the tyrants had built walls in the
                    places where the ground was open and level; but the higher places, and those
                    more difficult of access, they secured by placing guards of soldiers instead of
                    fortifications. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he had sufficiently
                    examined every circumstance, having resolved on making a general assault, he
                    surrounded the city with all his forces, the number of which, Romans and allies,
                    horse and foot, naval and land forces, all together, amounted to fifty thousand
                    men. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some brought scaling-ladders, some
                    fire-brands, some other matters, wherewith they might not only assail the enemy,
                    but strike terror. The orders were, that on raising the shout, all should
                    advance at once, in order that the Lacedaemonians, being alarmed at the same
                    time in every quarter, might be at a loss where, first, to make head, or whither
                    to bring aid. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The main force of his army he
                    formed in three divisions, and ordered one to attack on the side of the Phœbeum,
                    another on that of the Dictynneum, and the third near a place called
                    Heptagoniae, all which are open places without walls. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Though surrounded on all sides by such a violent alarm, the
                    tyrant, at first, attentive to every sudden shout and hasty message, either ran
                    up himself, or sent others, wherever the greatest danger pressed; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> but, afterwards, he was so stunned by the horror and
                    confusion that prevailed all around, as to become incapable either of giving
                    proper directions, or of hearing what was said, and to lose, not only his
                    judgment, but almost his reason. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For some time the Lacedaemonians maintained
                    their ground against the Romans, in the narrow passes; and three armies, on each
                    side, fought, at one time, in different places. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Afterwards, when the heat of the contest increased, the contest was, by no
                    means, an equal one: for the Lacedaemonians fought with missile arms, against
                    which the Roman soldiers, by means of their large shields, easily defended
                    themselves, and many of their blows either missed, or were very weak; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> for, the narrowness of the place causing them to be
                    closely crowded together, they neither had room to discharge their weapons with
                    a previous run, which gives great force to them, nor clear and steady footing
                    while they made their throw <pb n="1531" xml:id="p.1531"/> Of those, therefore,
                    discharged against the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> front of the Romans,
                    none pierced their bodies, few even their shields; but several were wounded by
                    those who surrounded them from higher places. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    And presently, when they advanced a little, they were hurt unawares, both with
                    javelins, and tiles also thrown from the tops of the houses. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> On this they raised their shields over their heads; and
                    joining them so close together as to leave no room for injury from such random
                    casts, or even for the insertion of a javelin, by a hand within reach, they
                    pressed forward under cover of this tortoise fence. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For some time the narrow streets, being thronged with a
                    multitude of their own soldiers, and also of the enemy, considerably retarded
                    the progress of the Romans; but when once, by gradually pushing back the enemy,
                    they gained the wider streets of the city, the impetuosity of their attack could
                    no longer be withstood. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While the
                    Lacedaemonians, having turned their backs, fled precipitately to the higher
                    places, Nabis, being utterly confounded, as if the town were already taken,
                    began to look about for a way to make his escape. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Pythagoras, while in other respects he displayed the spirit
                    and conduct of a general, was now the sole means of saving the city from being
                    taken. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For he ordered the buildings nearest
                    to the wall to be set on fire; and these being instantly in a blaze, those who,
                    on another occasion, would have brought help to extinguish the fire, now helping
                    to increase it, the roofs tumbled on the Romans; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and not only fragments of the tiles, but also the
                    half-burned timber, reached the soldiers: the flames spread wide, and the smoke
                    caused a degree of terror even greater than the danger. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> In consequence, the Romans who were without the city, and
                    were just then making the principal attack, retired from the wall; and those who
                    were within, fearing lest the fire, rising behind them, should put it out of
                    their power to rejoin the rest of the army, began to retreat. Whereupon
                    Quinctius, seeing how matters stood, ordered a general retreat to be sounded.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> —Thus, being at length recalled from a
                    city which they had nearly taken, they returned to their camp. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius, conceiving greater hopes from the
                    fears of the enemy than from the immediate effect of his operations, kept them
                    in a continual alarm during the three succeeding days; sometimes harassing them
                    with assaults, sometimes <pb n="1532" xml:id="p.1532"/> enclosing several places
                    with works, so as to leave no passage open for flight. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> These menaces had such an effect on the tyrant that he
                    again sent Pythagoras to solicit peace. Quinctius, at first, rejected him with
                    disdain, ordering him to quit the camp; but afterwards, on his suppliant
                    entreaties, and throwing himself at his feet, he admitted him to an audience.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The purport of his discourse, at first,
                    was, an offer of implicit submission to the will of the Romans; but this availed
                    nothing, being considered as nugatory and indecisive. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The business was, at length, brought to this issue, that a
                    truce should be made on the conditions delivered in writing a few days before,
                    and the money and hostages were accordingly received. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> While the tyrant was kept shut up by the siege, the
                    Argives, receiving frequent accounts, one after another, that Lacedaemon was on
                    the point of being taken, and having themselves resumed courage on the departure
                    of Pythagoras, with the strongest part of his garrison, looked now with contempt
                    on the small number remaining in the citadel; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and, being headed by a person named Archippus, drove the garrison out. They gave
                    Timocrates, of Pellene, leave to retire, with solemn assurance of sparing his
                    life, in consideration of' the mildness which he had shown in his government.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the midst of this rejoicing, Quinctius
                    arrived, after having granted peace to the tyrant, dismissed Eumenes and the
                    Rhodians from Lacedaemon, and sent back his brother, Lucius Quinctius, to the
                    fleet. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Nemaean games, the most celebrated of all
                    the festivals, and their most splendid public spectacle, had been omitted, at
                    the regular time, on account of the disasters of the war: the state now, in the
                    fulness of their joy, ordered them to be celebrated on the arrival of the Roman
                    general and his army; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and appointed the
                    general, himself, president of the games. There were many circumstances which
                    heightened their happiness: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> their countrymen,
                    whom Pythagoras, lately, and, before that, Nabis, had carried away, were brought
                    home from Lacedaemon; those who on the discovery of the conspiracy by
                    Pythagoras, and when the massacre was already begun, had fled from home, now
                    returned; they saw their liberty restored, after a long interval, and beheld, in
                    their city, the Romans, the authors of its restoration, whose only view, in
                    making war on the tyrant, was the sup- <pb n="1533" xml:id="p.1533"/> port of
                    their interest. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The freedom of the Argives
                    was, also, solemnly announced, by the voice of a herald, on the very day of the
                    Nemaean games. Whatever pleasure the Achaeans felt on Argos being reinstated in
                    the general council of Achaia, it was, in a great measure, alloyed by Lacedaemon
                    being left in slavery, and the tyrant close at their side. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> As to the Aetolians, they loudly railed at that measure in
                    every meeting. They remarked, that <quote> the war with Philip was not ended
                        until he evacuated all the cities of Greece. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> But Lacedaemon was left to the tyrant, while the lawful king, who had
                        been, at the time, in the Roman camp, and others, the noblest of the
                        citizens, must live in exile: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> so that the
                        Roman nation was become a partisan of Nabis in his tyranny. </quote>
                    Quinctius led back his army to Elatia, whence he had set out to the Spartan war.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Some writers say, that the tyrant's method
                    of carrying on hostilities was not by sallies from the city, but that he
                    encamped in the face of the Romans; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and that,
                    after he had declined fighting a long time, waiting for succours from the
                    Aetolians, he was forced to come to an engagement, by an attack which the Romans
                    made on his foragers, when, being defeated in that battle, <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> and beaten out of his camp, he sued for peace, after
                    fifteen thousand of his men had been killed, and more than four thousand made
                    prisoners. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nearly at the same time, arrived at Rome a
                    letter from Titus Quinctius, with an account of his proceedings at Lacedaemon;
                    and another, out of Spain, from Marcus Porcius, the consul; whereupon the senate
                    decreed a supplication, for three days, in the name of each. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The other consul, Lucius Valerius, as his province had
                    remained quiet since the defeat of the Boians at the wood of Litana, came home
                    to Rome to hold the elections. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio Africanus, a second time, and Tiberius Sempronius Longus, were
                    elected consuls. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The fathers of these two had
                    been consuls in the first year of the second Punic war. The election of praetors
                    was then held, and the choice fell on Publius Cornelius Scipio, two Cneius
                    Corneliuses, Merenda and Blasio, Cneius Domitius Aenobarbus, Sextus Digitius,
                    and Titus Juvencius Thalna. As soon as the elections were finished, the consul
                    returned to his province. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The inhabitants of
                    Ferentinum, this year, laid claim to a privilege unheard of before; that Latins,
                    giving in their names for a Roman colony, should be <pb n="1534" xml:id="p.1534"
                    /> deemed citizens of Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some colonists,
                    who had given in their names for Puteoli, Salernum, and Buxentum, assumed, on
                    that ground, the character of Roman citizens; but the senate determined that
                    they were not. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the year, wherein Publius
                    Scipio Africanus, a second time, and Tiberius Sempronius Longus were consuls,
                    two ambassadors from the tyrant Nabis came to Rome. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The senate gave them audience in the temple of Apollo,
                    outside the city. They entreated that a peace might be concluded on the terms
                    settled with Quinctius, and obtained their request. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> When the question was put concerning the provinces, the
                    majority of the senate were of opinion, that, as the wars in Spain and Macedonia
                    were at an end, Italy should be the province of both the consuls; but Scipio
                    contended that one consul was sufficient for Italy, and that Macedonia ought to
                    be decreed to the other; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that <quote> there
                        was every reason to apprehend a dangerous war with Antiochus, for he had
                        already, of his own accord, come into Europe; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and how did they suppose he would act in future, when
                        he should be encouraged to a war, on one hand, by the Aetolians, avowed
                        enemies of their state, and stimulated, on the other, by Hannibal, a general
                        famous for his victories over the Romans? </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While the consular provinces were in dispute,
                    the praetors cast lots for theirs. The city jurisdiction fell to Cneius
                    Domitius; the foreign, to Titus Juvencius: Farther Spain, to Publius Cornelius;
                    Hither Spain, to Sextus Digitius; Sicily, to Cneius Cornelius Blasio; Sardinia,
                    to Cneius Cornelius Merenda. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was resolved,
                    that no new army should be sent into Macedonia, but that the one which was there
                    should be brought home to Italy by Quinctius, and disbanded; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> that the army which was in Spain, under Marcus Porcius
                    Cato, should likewise be disbanded; that Italy should be the province of both
                    the consuls, and that they should raise two city legions; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> so that, after the disbanding of the armies, mentioned in
                    the resolution of the senate, there should be in all eight Roman legions. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A sacred spring had been celebrated, in the
                    preceding year, during the consulate of Marcus Porcius and Lucius Valerius; but
                    Publius Licinius, one of the pontiffs, having made a report, first, to the
                    college of pontiffs, and afterwards. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> under the
                    sanction of the college, to the senate. that it had not <pb n="1535"
                        xml:id="p.1535"/> been duly performed, they resolved, that it should be
                    celebrated anew, under the direction of the pontiffs; and that the great games,
                    vowed together with it, should be exhibited at the same expense which was
                    customary; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that the sacred spring should be
                    deemed to comprehend all the cattle born between the calends of March and the
                    day preceding the calends of May, in the year of the consulate of Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio and Tiberius Sempronius Longus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Then followed the election of censors. Sextus Aelius Paetus, and Caius
                    Cornelius Cethegus, being created censors, named as prince of the senate the
                    consul Publius Scipio, whom the former censors likewise had appointed. They
                    passed by only three senators in the whole, none of whom had enjoyed the honour
                    of a curule office. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They obtained, on another
                    account, the highest degree of credit with that body; for, at the celebration of
                    the Roman games, they ordered the curule aediles to set apart places for the
                    senators, distinct from those of the people, whereas, hitherto, all the
                    spectators used to sit promiscuously. Of the knights, also, very few were
                    deprived of their horses; nor was severity shown towards any rank of men. The
                    gallery of the temple of Liberty, and the Villa Publica, were repaired and
                    enlarged by the same censors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The sacred
                    spring, and the votive games, were celebrated, pursuant to the vow of Servius
                    Sulpicius Galba, when consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While every
                    one's thoughts were engaged by the shows then exhibited, Quintus Pleminius, who,
                    for the many crimes against gods and men committed by him at Locri, had been
                    thrown into prison, procured men who were to set fire by night to several parts
                    of the city at once, in order that, while the town was thrown into consternation
                    by this nocturnal disturbance, the prison might be broken open. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> But this plot was disclosed by some of the accomplices, and
                    the affair was laid before the senate. Pleminius was thrown into a lower
                    dungeon, and there put to death. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this year colonies of Roman citizens were
                    settled at Puteoli, Vulturnum, and Liternum; three hundred men in each place.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Colonies of Roman citizens were likewise
                    established at Salernum and Buxentum. The lands allotted to them had formerly
                    belonged to the Campanians. Tiberius Sempronius Longus, who was then consul,
                    Marcus Servilius, and Quintus Minucius Thermus, were the triumviri who <pb
                        n="1536" xml:id="p.1536"/> settled the colony. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Other commissioners also, Decius Junius Brutus, Marcus
                    Baebius Tamphilus, and Marcus Helvius, led a colony of Roman citizens to
                    Sipontum, into a district which had belonged to the Arpinians. To Tempsa,
                    likewise, and to Croto, colonies of Roman citizens were led out. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The lands of Tempsa had been taken from the
                    Bruttians, who had formerly expelled the Greeks from them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Croto was possessed by Greeks. In ordering these
                    establishments, there were named, for Croto, —Cneius Octavius, Lucius Aemilius
                    Paullus, and Caius Pletorius; for Tempsa, —Lucius Cornelius Merula, and Caius
                    Salonius. Several prodigies were observed at Rome that year, and others
                    reported, from other places. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the forum,
                    comitium, and Capitol, drops of blood were seen, and several showers of earth
                    fell, and the head of Vulcan was surrounded with a blaze of fire. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> It was reported, that a stream of milk ran in the
                    river at Interamna; that, in some reputable families at Ariminum, children were
                    born without eyes and nose; and one, in the territory of Picenum, that had
                    neither hands nor feet. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These prodigies were
                    expiated according to an order of the pontiffs; and the nine days' festival was
                    celebrated, because the Hadrians had sent intelligence that a shower of stones
                    had fallen in their fields. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In Gaul, Lucius Valerius Flaccus, proconsul,
                    in a pitched battle near Mediolanum, completely overthrew the Insubrian Gauls,
                    and the Boians; who, under the command of Dorulacus, had crossed the Po, to
                    rouse the Insubrians to arms. Ten thousand of the enemy were slain. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> About this time his colleague, Marcus Porcius Cato,
                    triumphed over Spain. He carried in the procession twenty-five thousand pounds'
                    weight of unwrought silver, one hundred and three thousand silver denarii, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 3971 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 17 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> five hundred and forty of Oscan silver, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 17 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and one thousand four hundred pounds' weight of gold. Out of the booty,
                    he distributed to each of his soldiers two hundred and seventy <hi
                        rend="italics">asses;</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 17 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 5 1/2
                            <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and three times that amount to each horseman. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Tiberius Sempronius, consul, proceeding to his province,
                    led his legions, first, into the territory of the Boians. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> At this time Boiorix their chieftain, with his two
                    brothers, after having drawn out the whole nation into the field to renew the
                    war, pitched his camp in the open country, that it might be evident that he was
                    prepared to fight in <pb n="1537" xml:id="p.1537"/> case the enemy should pass
                    the frontiers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the consul understood what
                    a numerous force and what a degree of resolution the enemy had, he sent an
                    express to his colleague, requesting him, <quote>if he thought proper, to hasten
                        to join him;</quote> adding, that <quote>he would act on the defensive, and
                        defer engaging in battle, until his arrival.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The same reason which made the consul wish to
                    decline an action, induced the Gauls, whose spirits were raised by the
                    backwardness of their antagonists, to bring it on as soon as possible, that they
                    might finish the affair before the two consuls should unite their forces.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> However, during two days, they did nothing
                    more than stand in readiness for battle, if any should come out against them. On
                    the third, they advanced furiously to the rampart, and assaulted the camp on
                    every side at once. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consul immediately
                    ordered his men to take arms, and kept them quiet, under arms, for some time;
                    both to add to the foolish confidence of the enemy, and to arrange his troops at
                    the gates, through which each party was to sally out. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The two legions were ordered to march by the two principal
                    gates; but, in the very pass of the gates, the Gauls opposed them in such close
                    bodies as to stop up the way. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The fight was
                    maintained a long time in these narrow passes; nor were their hands or swords
                    much employed in the business, but pushing with their shields and bodies, they
                    pressed against each other, the Romans struggling to force their <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> standards beyond the gates, the Gauls, to break
                    into the camp, or, at least, to hinder the Romans from issuing forth. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> However, neither party could make the least
                    impression on the other, until Quintus Victorius, a first centurion, and Caius
                    Atinius, a military tribune, the former of the second, the latter of the fourth
                    legion, had taken a course often tried in desperate conflicts; snatching the
                    standards from the officers who carried them, and throwing them among the enemy.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the struggle to recover the standards,
                    the men of the second legion first made their way out of the gate. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These were now fighting on the outside of the
                    rampart, the fourth legion still entangled in the gate, when a new alarm arose
                    on the opposite side of the camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Gauls
                    had broke in by the Quaestorian gate, and had slain the quaestor, Lucius
                    Postumius, surnamed Tympanus, with Marcus Atinius and Publius Sempronius,
                    praefects of the allies, <pb n="1538" xml:id="p.1538"/> who made an obstinate
                    resistance; and also, near two hundred soldiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> The camp in that part had been taken, when a cohort of those who are called
                    Extraordinaries, having been sent by the consul to defend the Quaestorian gate,
                    killed some who had got within the rampart, drove out the rest, and opposed
                    others who were attempting to break in. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> About
                    the same time, the fourth legion, and two cohorts of Extraordinaries, burst out
                    of the gate; and thus there were three battles, in different places, round the
                    camp; while the various kinds of shouts raised by them, called off the attention
                    of the combatants from their own immediate conflict to the uncertain casualties
                    which threatened their friends. The battle was maintained until mid-day with
                    equal strength, and with nearly equal hopes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    At length, the fatigue and heat so far got the better of the soft relaxed bodies
                    of the Gauls, who are incapable of enduring thirst, as to make most of them give
                    up the fight; and the few who stood their ground, were attacked by the Romans,
                    routed, and driven to their camp. The consul then gave the signal for retreat,
                    on which the greater part retired; but some, eager to continue the fight, and
                    hoping to get possession of the camp, pressed forward to the rampart, on which
                    the Gauls, despising their small number, rushed out in a body. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans were then routed in turn, and compelled, by
                    their own fear and dismay, to retreat to their camp, which they had refused to
                    do at the command of their general. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thus now
                    flight and now victory alternated on both sides. The Gauls, however, had eleven
                    thousand killed, the Romans but five thousand. The Gauls retreated into the
                    heart of their country, and the consul led his legions to Placentia. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Some writers say, that Scipio, after joining his
                    forces to those of his colleague, overran and plundered the country of the
                    Boians and Ligurians, as far as the woods and marshes suffered him to proceed;
                    others, that, without having effected any thing material, he returned to Rome to
                    hold the elections. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius passed the entire winter
                    season of this year at Elatia, where he had established the winter quarters of
                    his army, in adjusting political arrangements, and reversing the measures which
                    had been introduced in the several states under the arbitrary domination of
                    Philip and his deputies, who crushed the rights and liberties of <pb n="1539"
                        xml:id="p.1539"/> others, in order to augment the power of those who formed
                    a faction in their favour. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Early in the spring
                    he came to Corinth, where he had summoned a general convention. Ambassadors
                    having attended from every one of the states, so as to form a numerous assembly,
                    he addressed them in a long speech, in which, beginning from the first
                    commencement of friendship between the Romans and the nation of the Greeks, he
                    enumerated the proceedings of the commanders who had been in Macedonia before
                    him, and likewise his own. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His whole narration
                    was heard with the warmest approbation, except when he came to make mention of
                    Nabis; and then they expressed their opinion, that it was utterly inconsistent
                    with the character of the deliverer of Greece to have left seated, in the centre
                    of one of its most respectable states, a tyrant, who was not only insupportable
                    to his own country, but a terror to all the states in his neighbourhood.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whereupon Quinctius, not unacquainted with
                    this tendency of their feelings, freely acknowledged, that <quote> if the
                        business could have been accomplished without the entire destruction of
                        Lacedaemon, no mention of pence with the tyrant ought ever to have been
                        listened to; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but that, when it was not
                        possible to crush him otherwise than by the utter ruin of this most
                        important city, it was judged more eligible to leave the tyrant in a state
                        of debility, stripped of almost every kind of power to do injury to any,
                        than to suffer the city, which must have perished in the very process
                            <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> of its delivery being effectuated,
                        to sink under remedies too violent for it to support. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To the recital of matters past, he subjoined,
                    that <quote> his intention was to depart shortly for Italy, and to carry with
                        him all his troops; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that they should hear,
                        within ten days, of the garrisons having evacuated Demetrias; and that
                        Chalcis, the citadel of Corinth, should be before their own eyes evacuated
                        to the Achaeans: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that all the world might
                        know whose habit it was to deceive, that of the Romans or the Aetolians, who
                        had spread insinuations, that the cause of liberty had been unwisely
                        intrusted to the Romans, and that they had only received as <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> their masters the Romans in exchange for the
                        Macedonians. But they were men who never scrupled what they either said or
                        did. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The rest of the nations he advised to
                        form their estimate of friends from deeds, not from words; and to satisfy
                        themselves whom they ought to trust, and <pb n="1540" xml:id="p.1540"/>
                        against whom they ought to be on their guard; <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> to use their liberty with moderation: for, when
                        regulated by prudence, it was productive of happiness both to individuals
                        and to states; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but, when pushed to excess,
                        it became not only obnoxious to others, but to the possessors of it
                        themselves an unbridled and headstrong impulse. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He recommended, that those at the head of affairs, and
                        all the several ranks of men in each particular state, should cultivate
                        harmony between themselves; and that all should direct their views to the
                        general interest of the whole. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For, while
                        they acted in concert, no king or tyrant would be sufficiently powerful
                        against them: but discord and dissension gave every advantage to those who
                        might plot against them; as the party worsted in a domestic dispute
                        generally join themselves with foreigners, rather than submit to a
                        countryman of their own. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He then exhorted
                        them, as the arms of others had procured their liberty, and the good faith
                        of foreigners had restored it to them, to apply now their own diligent care
                        to the watching and guarding of it; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that
                        the Roman people might perceive that those on whom they had bestowed liberty
                        were deserving of it, and that their kindness had not been ill placed.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing these admonitions, such as parental
                    tenderness might dictate, every one present shed tears of joy; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and they affected his feelings to such a degree as to
                    interrupt his discourse. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For some time a
                    confused noise prevailed, from those who were expressing their approbation of
                    his words, and charging each other to treasure up those expressions in their
                    minds and hearts, as if they had been uttered by an oracle. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then silence ensuing, he requested of them to make diligent
                    search for such Roman citizens as were in servitude among them, and to send them
                    into Thessaly to him, within two months; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    observing, that <quote> it would not be honourable to themselves, that, in a
                        land restored to liberty, its deliverers should remain in servitude. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To this all exclaimed with acclamations that
                    they returned him thanks on this account in addition to others, that they had
                    been reminded of the discharge of a duty so indispensably incumbent on their
                    gratitude. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There was a vast number of these
                    who had been made <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> prisoners in the Punic
                    war, and sold by Hannibal when their countrymen refused to ransom them.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That they were very numerous, is proved by
                    what Polybius says, that this <pb n="1541" xml:id="p.1541"/> business cost the
                    Achaeans <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> one hundred talents, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 19,375 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note> though they had fixed the price to be paid for each captive, to the
                    owner, so low as five hundred denarii. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > 16 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 11 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For, at that rate, there were one thousand
                    two hundred in Achaia. Calculate now, in proportion to this, how many were
                    probably in all Greece. </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the convention broke up, they saw the
                    garrison march down from the citadel of Corinth, proceed forward to the gate,
                    and depart. The general followed them, accompanied by the whole assembly, who,
                    with loud acclamations, blessed him as their preserver and deliverer. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> At length, taking leave of these, and dismissing
                    them, he returned to Elatia by the same road through which he came. He thence
                    sent Appius Claudius, lieutenant-general, with all the troops, ordering him to
                    march through Thessaly and Epirus, and to wait <milestone n="3??" unit="section"
                    /> for him at Oricum, whence he intended to embark the army for Italy.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He also wrote to his brother, Lucius
                    Quinctius, lieutenant-general, and commander of the fleet, to collect thither
                    transport ships from all the coasts of Greece. He himself proceeded to Chalcis;
                    and, after sending away the garrisons, not only from that city, but likewise
                    from Oreum and Eretria, he held there a congress of the Eubœan states, whom he
                    reminded of the condition in which he had found their affairs, and of that in
                    which he was leaving them; and then dismissed the assembly. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He then proceeded to Demetrias, and removed the garrison.
                    Accompanied by all the citizens, as at Corinth and Chalcis, he pursued his route
                    into Thessaly, where the states were not only to be set at liberty, but also to
                    be reduced from a state of utter anarchy and confusion into some tolerable
                    order; for they had been thrown into confusion, not only through the faults of
                    the times, and the violence and licentiousness of royalty, but also through the
                    restless disposition of the nation, who, from the earliest times, even to our
                    days, have never conducted any election, or assembly, or council, without
                    dissensions and tumult. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He chose both senators
                    and judges, with regard, principally, to their property, and made that party the
                    most powerful in the state to whom it was most important that all things should
                    be tranquil and secure. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had completed these regulations in
                    Thessaly, he went on, through Epirus, to Oricum, whence he intended <pb n="1542"
                        xml:id="p.1542"/> to take his passage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    From Oricum all the troops were transported to Brundusium. From this place to
                    the city, they passed the whole length of Italy, in a manner, like a triumph;
                    the captured effects which they brought with them forming a train as large as
                    that of the troops themselves. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they
                    arrived at Rome, the senate assembled outside the city, to receive from
                    Quinctius a recital of his services; and, with high satisfaction, a well-merited
                    triumph was decreed him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His triumph lasted
                    three days. On the first day were carried in procession, armour, weapons, brazen
                    and marble statues, of which he had taken greater numbers from Philip than from
                    the states of Greece. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the second, gold and
                    silver wrought, unwrought, and coined. Of unwrought silver, there were eighteen
                    thousand pounds' weight; and of wrought, two hundred and seventy thousand;
                    consisting of many vessels of various sorts, most of them engraved, and several
                    of exquisite workmanship; also a great many others made of brass; and, besides
                    these, ten shields of silver. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The coined
                    silver amounted to eighty-four thousand of the Attic coin, called Tetradrachmus,
                    containing each of silver about the weight of four denarii. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 10,849 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of gold there were three thousand seven
                    hundred and fourteen pounds, and one shield wholly of gold: and of the gold coin
                    called Philippics, fourteen thousand five hundred and fourteen. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 936 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the third day were carried golden crowns,
                    presented by the several states, in number one hundred and fourteen; then the
                    victims. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Before his chariot went many
                    illustrious persons, captives and hostages, among whom were Demetrius, son of
                    king Philip, and Armenes, a Lacedaemonian, son of the tyrant Nabis. Then
                    Quinctius himself rode into the city, followed by a numerous body of soldiers,
                    as the whole army had been brought home from the province. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Among these he distributed two hundred and fifty <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 16 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1 1/4
                            <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to each footman, double to a centurion, triple to a horseman. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Those who had been redeemed from captivity added to
                    the grandeur of the procession, walking after him with their <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> heads shaven. </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the latter part of this year Quintus Aelius
                    Tubero, plebeian tribune, in pursuance of a decree of the senate, proposed to
                    the people, and the people ordered, that <quote> two Latin colonies should be
                        settled, one in Bruttium, the other in the ter- <pb n="1543" xml:id="p.1543"
                        /> ritory of Thurium. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For making these settlements commissioners
                    were appointed, who were to hold the office for three years; for Bruttium,
                    Quintus Naevius, Marcus Minucius Rufus, and Marcus Furius Crassipes; and for the
                    district of Thurium, Cneius Manlius, Quintus Aelius, and Lucius Apustius. The
                    assemblies of election to these two appointments were held in the Capitol by
                    Cneius Domitius, city praetor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Several temples
                    were dedicated this year: one of Juno Sospita, in the herb market, vowed and
                    contracted for four years before, in the time of the Gallic war, by Cneius
                    Cornelius, consul; and the same person, now censor, performed the dedication.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Another of Faunus, the building of which
                    had been agreed for two years before, and a fund formed for it out of fines
                    estreated by the aediles, Caius Scribonius and Cneius Domitius; the latter of
                    whom, now city praetor, dedicated it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Quintus
                    Marcius Ralla, constituted commissioner for the purpose, dedicated the temple of
                    Fortuna Primigenia, on the Quirinal Hill. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Publius Sempronius Sophus had vowed this temple ten years before, in the Punic
                    war; and, being afterwards censor, had employed persons to build it. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Caius Servilius, duumvir, also dedicated a temple of
                    Jupiter, in the island. This had been vowed in the Gallic war, six years before,
                    by Lucius Furius Purpureo, who afterwards, when consul, contracted for the
                    building. —Such were the transactions of that year. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Publius Scipio came home from his province of
                    Gaul to choose new consuls. The consular comitia were accordingly held, in which
                    Lucius Cornelius Merula and Quintus Minucius Thermus were chosen. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Next day were chosen praetors, Lucius Cornelius
                    Scipio, Marcus Fulvius Nobilior, Caius Scribonius, Marcus Valerius Messala,
                    Lucius Porcius Licinus, and Caius Flaminius. The curule aediles of this year,
                    Caius Atilius Serranus and Lucius Scribonius, first exhibited the Megalesian
                    theatrical games. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the Roman games,
                    celebrated by these aediles, the senators, for the first time, sat separate from
                    the people, which, as every innovation usually does, gave occasion to various
                    observations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some considered this as <quote>
                        an honour, shown at length to that most respectable body, and which ought to
                        have been done long before; </quote> while others contended, that <quote>
                        every addition made to the grandeur of the senate was a diminution of the
                        dignity of the people; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        <pb n="1544" xml:id="p.1544"/> and that all such distinctions as set the
                        orders of the state at a distance from each other, were equally subversive
                        of liberty and concord. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> During five
                        hundred and fifty-eight years, </quote> they asserted, <quote> all the
                        spectators had sat promiscuously: what reason then had now occurred, on a
                        sudden, that should make the senators disdain to have the commons intermixed
                        with them in the theatre, or make the rich disdain the poor man as a
                        fellow-spectator? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was an unprecedented
                        gratification of pride and over-bearing vanity, never even desired, and
                        never instituted, by the senate of any other nation. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is said, that even Africanus himself at
                    last became sorry for having proposed that matter in his consulship: so
                    difficult is it to bring people to approve of any alteration of ancient customs;
                    they are always naturally disposed to adhere to old practices, except those
                    which experience evidently condemns. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the year, which was the
                    consulate of Lucius Cornelius and Quintus Minucius, such frequent reports of
                    earthquakes were brought, that people grew weary, not only of the matter itself,
                    but of the religious rites enjoined in consequence; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> for neither could the senate be convened, nor the business
                    of the public be transacted, the consuls were so constantly employed in
                    sacrifices and expiations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At last, the
                    decemvirs were ordered to consult the books; and, in pursuance of their answer,
                    a supplication was performed during three days. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> People offered prayers at all the shrines, with garlands on their heads; and
                    an order was published, that all the persons belonging to one family should pay
                    their worship together; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and the consuls, by
                    direction of the senate, published an edict, that, on any day whereon religious
                    rites should be ordered, in consequence of the report of an earthquake, no
                    person should report another earthquake on that day. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then the consuls first, and afterwards the praetors, cast
                    lots for their provinces. Cornelius obtained Gaul; Minucius, Liguria; Caius
                    Scribonius, the city jurisdiction; Marcus Valerius, the foreign; Lucius
                    Cornelius, Sicily; Lucius Porcius, Sardinia; Caius Flaminius, Hither Spain; and
                    Marcus Fulvius, Farther Spain. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the consuls supposed that, for that
                    year, they should have <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> no employment of a
                    military kind, a letter was brought from Marcus Cincius, who was commander at
                    Pisae, announcing, that <quote> twenty thousand armed Ligurians, in con- <pb
                            n="1545" xml:id="p.1545"/> sequence of a conspiracy of that whole
                        nation, formed in the meetings of their several districts, had first wasted
                        the lands of Luna, and then, passing through the territory of Pisae, had
                        overrun the whole sea-coast. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In consequence of this intelligence, the
                    consul Minucius, whose province Liguria was, by direction of the senate,
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> mounted the rostrum, and published
                    orders, that <quote> the two legions, enlisted the year before, should, on the
                        tenth day from that, attend him at Arretium; </quote> and mentioned his
                    intention of levying two legions for the city in their stead. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He likewise gave notice to the magistrates and ambassadors
                    of such of the allies, and of the Latin confederates, as were bound to furnish
                    soldiers, to attend him in the Capitol. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Of
                    these he wrote out a list, amounting to fifteen thousand foot and five hundred
                    horse, proportioning the contingent of <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> each
                    state to the number of its young men, and ordered those present to go directly
                    from the spot to the gate of the city; and, in order to expedite the business,
                    to proceed to raise the men. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To Fulvius and
                    Flaminius were assigned, to each three thousand Roman foot, and a reinforcement
                    of one hundred horse, with five thousand foot of the Latin allies, and two
                    hundred horse; and orders were given to those praetors, to disband the old
                    troops immediately on their arrival in their provinces. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Although great numbers of the soldiers belonging to the
                    city legions had made application to the plebeian tribunes, to take cognizance
                    of the cases of such men as claimed exemption from the service, on account
                    either of having served out their time, or of bad health; yet a letter from
                    Tiberius Sempronius banished all thoughts of such proceeding; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> for in this it was announced that <quote> fifteen thousand
                        of the Ligurians had come into the lands of Placentia, and wasted them with
                        fire and sword, to the very walls of that city and the bank of the Po; and
                        that the Boian nation were looking out for an occasion to rebel. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In consequence of this information, the
                    senate passed a vote, that <quote> there was a Gallic tumult subsisting, and
                        that it would be improper for the plebeian tribunes to take cognizance of
                        the claims of the soldiers, so as to prevent their attending, pursuant to
                        the proclamation; </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and they added an order, that the Latin
                    confederates, who had served in the army of Publius Cornelius and Tiberius
                    Sempronius, and had been discharged by those consuls, should re-assemble, on
                    whatever day and in whatever <pb n="1546" xml:id="p.1546"/> place of Etruria the
                    consul Lucius Cornelius should appoint; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and
                    that the consul Lucius Cornelius, on his way to his province, should enlist,
                    arm, and carry with him all such persons as he should think fit, in the several
                    towns and countries through which he was to pass, and should have authority to
                    discharge such of them, and at such times, as he might judge proper. </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the consuls had finished the levies, and
                    were gone to their provinces, Titus Quinctius demanded, that <quote> the senate
                        should receive an account of the regulations which he, in concert with the
                        ten ambassadors, had settled; and, if they thought proper, ratify them by
                        their authority. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He told them, that <quote> they would
                        accomplish this the more easily, if they were first to give audience to the
                        ambassadors, who had come from all parts of Greece, and a great part of
                        Asia, and to those from the two kings. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These embassies were introduced to the senate
                    by the city praetor, Caius Scribonius, and all received kind answers. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> As the discussion of the affair with Antiochus
                    required too much time, it was referred to the ten ambassadors, some of whom had
                    conferred with the king in Asia, or at Lysimachia. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Directions were given to Titus Quinctius, that, in
                    conjunction with these, he should listen to the representations of the king's
                    ambassadors, and should give them such answer as comported with the dignity and
                    interest of the Roman people. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At the head of
                    the embassy were Menippus and Hegesianax; the former of whom said, that <quote>
                        he could not conceive what intricacy there was in the business of their
                        embassy, as they came simply to ask friendship, and conclude an alliance.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Now, there were three kinds of
                        treaties, by which kings and states formed friendships with each other: one,
                        when terms were dictated to a people vanquished in war; for after all their
                        possessions have been surrendered to him who has proved superior in war, he
                        has the sole power of judging and determining what portion of them the
                        vanquished shall hold, and of what they shall be deprived. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The second, when parties, equally matched in war,
                        conclude a treaty of peace and friendship on terms of equality; for then
                        demands are proposed and restitution made, reciprocally, in a convention;
                        and if, in consequence of the war, confusion has arisen with respect to any
                        parts of their properties, the matter is adjusted on the footing either of
                        an- <pb n="1547" xml:id="p.1547"/> cient right or of the mutual convenience
                        of the parties. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The third kind was, when
                        parties who had never been foes, met to form a friendly union by a social
                        treaty: these neither dictate nor receive terms, for that is the case
                        between a victor and a party vanquished. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        As Antiochus came under this last description, he wondered, he said, that
                        the Romans should think it becoming to dictate terms to him; as to which of
                        the cities of Asia they chose should be free and independent, which should
                        be tributary, and which of them the king's troops and the king himself
                        should be prohibited to enter. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That a
                        peace of this kind might be ratified with Philip, who was their enemy, but
                        not a treaty of alliance with Antiochus, their friend. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this Quinctius answered: <quote> Since you
                        choose to deal methodically, and enumerate the several modes of contracting
                        alliances, I also will lay down two conditions, without which you may tell
                        your king, that there are no means of contracting any friendship with the
                        Roman people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One, that, if he does not
                        choose that we should concern ourselves in the affairs of the cities in
                        Asia, he must himself keep entirely out of Europe. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The other, that if he does not confine himself within
                        the limits of Asia, but passes over into Europe, the Romans will think
                        themselves at full liberty to maintain the friendships which they have
                        already formed with the states of Asia, and also to contract new ones. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On this Hegesianax exclaimed, that <quote>
                        this proposition was unworthy to be listened to, as its tendency was to
                        exclude Antiochus from the cities of Thrace and the Chersonese, —places
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> which his great-grandfather, Seleucus,
                        had acquired with great honour, after vanquishing Lysimachus in war and
                        killing him in battle, and had left to his successors; and part of which,
                        after they had been seized by the Thracians, Antiochus had, with equal
                        honour, recovered by force of arms; as well as others which had been
                        deserted, —as Lysimachia, for instance, he had repeopled, by calling home
                        the inhabitants; —and several, which had been destroyed by fire, and buried
                        in ruins, he had rebuilt at a vast expense. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> What kind of resemblance was there, then, in the cases of Antiochus being
                        ejected from possessions so acquired and so recovered; and of the Romans
                        refraining from intermeddling with Asia, which had never been theirs?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Antiochus wished to obtain the
                        friendship of the Romans; but <pb n="1548" xml:id="p.1548"/> so that its
                        acquisition would be to his honour, and not to his shame. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In reply to this, Quinctius said, — <quote>
                        Since we are deliberating on what would be honourable, and which, indeed,
                        with a people who held the first rank among the nations of the world, and
                        with so great a king, ought to be the sole, or at least the primary object
                        of regard; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> tell me, I pray you, which do
                        you think more honourable, to wish to give liberty to all the Grecian cities
                        in every part of the world; or to make them slaves and vassals? <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Since Antiochus thinks it conducive to his
                        glory, to reduce to slavery those cities, which his great-grandfather held
                        by the right of arms, but which his grandfather or father never occupied as
                        their property; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> while the Roman people,
                        having undertaken the patronage of the liberty of the Greeks, deem it
                        incumbent on their faith and constancy not to abandon it. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> As they have delivered Greece from Philip, so they have
                        it in contemplation to deliver, from Antiochus, all the states of Asia which
                        are of the Grecian race. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For colonies
                        were not sent into Aeolia and Ionia to be enslaved to kings; but with design
                        to increase the population, and to propagate that ancient race in every part
                        of the globe. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hegesianax hesitated, and could not deny,
                    that the cause of liberty carried a more honourable semblance than that of
                    slavery, Publius Sulpicius, who was the eldest of the ten ambassadors, said, —
                        <quote> Let us cut the matter short. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Choose one of the two conditions clearly propounded just now by Quinctius;
                        or deem it superfluous to negotiate about an alliance. </quote> But Menippus
                    replied, <quote> We neither will, nor can, accede to any proposition by which
                        the dominions of Antiochus would be diminished. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Next day, Quinctius brought into the
                    senate-house all the ambassadors of Greece and Asia, in order that they might
                    learn the dispositions entertained by the Roman people, and by Antiochus,
                    towards the Grecian states. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then acquainted
                    them with his own demands, and those of the king; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and desired them to <quote> assure their respective states,
                        that the same disinterested zeal and courage, which the Roman people had
                        displayed in defence of their liberty against the encroachments of Philip,
                        they would, likewise, exert against those of Antiochus, if he should refuse
                        to retire out of Europe. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On this, Menippus earnestly besought Quinctius
                    and the senate, <quote> not to be hasty in forming their <pb n="1549"
                            xml:id="p.1549"/> determination, which, in its effects, might disturb
                        the peace of the whole world; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> to take time
                        to themselves, and allow the king time for consideration; that, when
                        informed of the conditions proposed, he would consider them, and either
                        obtain some relaxation in the terms, or accede to them for the sake of
                        peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly, the business was deferred entire;
                    and a resolution passed, that the same ambassadors should be sent to the king
                    who had attended him at Lysimachia, —Publius Sulpicius, Publius Villius, and
                    Publius Aelius. </p>
                <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scarcely had these begun their journey, when
                    ambassadors from Carthage brought information, that Antiochus was evidently
                    preparing for war, and that Hannibal was employed in his service; which gave
                    reason to fear, that a Punic war might break out at the same time. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Hannibal, on leaving his own country, had gone to
                    Antiochus, as was mentioned before, and was held by the king in high estimation,
                    not so much for his other qualifications, as because, to a person who had long
                    been revolving schemes for a war with Rome, there could not be any fitter
                    participator of his counsels on such a subject. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> His opinion was always one and the same, that the war should be carried on in
                    Italy: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> because <quote> Italy would supply a
                        foreign enemy both with men and provisions; but, if it were left in quiet,
                        and the Roman people were allowed to employ the strength and forces of
                        Italy, in making war beyond the limits of that country, no king or nation
                        would be able to cope with them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He demanded, for himself, one hundred decked
                    ships, ten thousand foot, and one thousand horse. <quote>With this
                        force,</quote> he said, "he would first repair to Africa; and he had
                    confident hopes, that he should be able to prevail on the Carthaginians to
                    revive hostilities. If they should hesitate, he would raise a war against the
                    Romans in some part of Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That the king
                    ought to cross over into Europe with all the rest of his force, and keep his
                    army in some part of Greece; not to pass over immediately into Italy, but to be
                    in readiness to do so; which would sufficiently conduce to the imposing
                    character and the reported magnitude of the war. </p>
                <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had brought the king to agree in his
                    opinion, he judged it necessary to predispose the minds of his countrymen to the
                    same; but he durst not send a letter, lest it might, by some accident, be
                    intercepted, and his plans by that means be discovered. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He had found at Ephesus a Tyrian called <pb n="1550"
                        xml:id="p.1550"/> Aristo, and in several less important commissions, had
                    discovered him to possess a good degree of ingenuity. This man he now loaded
                    with presents and promises of rewards, which were confirmed by the king himself,
                    and sent him to Carthage with messages. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                    told him the names of the persons whom it was necessary that he should see, and
                    furnished him with secret tokens, by which they would know, with certainty, that
                    the messages came from him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On this Aristo's
                    appearing at Carthage, the reason of his coming was not discovered by Hannibal's
                    friends sooner than by his enemies. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At first,
                    the subject was bruited about in their circles and at their tables; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> and at last some persons declared in the senate, that
                        <quote> the banishment of Hannibal answered no purpose, if, while resident
                        in another country, he was still able to propagate designs for changing the
                        administration, and disturbing the quiet of the state by his intrigues.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That a Tyrian stranger, named Aristo,
                        had come with a commission from Hannibal and king Antiochus; that certain
                        men daily held secret conferences with him, and were concocting that in
                        private, the consequences of which would soon break out, to the ruin of the
                        public. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This produced a general outcry, that <quote>
                        Aristo ought to be summoned, and examined respecting the reason of his
                        coming; and if he did not disclose it, to be sent to Rome, with ambassadors
                        accompanying him: that they had already suffered enough of punishment in
                        atonement of the headstrong rashness of one individual; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> that the faults of private citizens should be at their
                        own risk, and the state should be preserved free, not only from guilt, but
                        even from the suspicion of it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Aristo, being summoned, contended for his
                    innocence; and urged, as his strongest defence, that he had brought no letter to
                    any person whatever: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> but he gave no
                    satisfactory reason for his coming, and was chiefly embarrassed by the fact
                    which they urged, that he had conversed solely with men of the Barcine faction.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A warm debate ensued; some earnestly
                    pressing, that he should be immediately seized as a spy, and kept in custody;
                    while others insisted, that there were not sufficient grounds for such violent
                    measures; that <quote> putting strangers into confinement, without reason, was a
                        step that afforded a bad precedent; for that the same would happen to the
                        Carthaginians at Tyre, and other marts, where they frequently traded. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The question was ad- <pb n="1551"
                        xml:id="p.1551"/> journed on that day. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Aristo practised on the Carthaginians a Carthaginian artifice; for having early
                    in the evening hung up a written tablet, in the most frequented place of the
                    city, over the tribunal where the magistrates daily sat, he went on board his
                    ship at the third watch, and fled. Next day, when the suffetes had taken their
                    seats to administer justice, the tablet was observed, taken down, and read.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Its contents were, that <quote> Aristo
                        came not with a private commission to any person, but with a public one to
                        the elders; </quote> by this name they called the senate. The imputation
                    being thus thrown on the state, less pains were taken in searching into the
                    suspicions harboured of a few individuals: <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    however, it was determined, that ambassadors should be sent to Rome, to
                    represent the affair to the consuls and the senate, and, at the same time, to
                    complain of the injuries received from Masinissa. </p>
                <milestone n="62" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Masinissa observed that the Carthaginians
                    were looked on with jealousy by others, and were full of dissensions among
                    themselves; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the nobles being suspected by the
                    senate, on account of their conferences with Aristo, and the senate by the
                    people, in consequence of the information given by the same Aristo, he thought
                    that, at such a conjuncture, he might successfully encroach on their rights; and
                    accordingly he laid waste their country along the sea-coast, and compelled
                    several cities, which were tributary to the Carthaginians, to pay their taxes to
                    him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This tract they call Emporiae; it forms
                    the shore of the lesser Syrtis, and has a fertile soil; one of its cities is
                    Leptis, which paid a tribute to the Carthaginians of a talent a day. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> At this time, Masinissa not only ravaged that whole
                    tract, but, with respect to a considerable part of it, disputed the right of
                    possession with the Carthaginians; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and when he
                    learned that they were sending to Rome, both to justify their conduct, and, at
                    the same time, to make complaints of him, lie likewise sent ambassadors to Rome,
                    to load them with suspicions, and to discuss the right to the taxes. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians were heard first, and their account
                    of the Tyrian stranger gave the senate no small uneasiness, as they dreaded
                    being involved in war with Antiochus and the Carthaginians at the same time.
                    What contributed chiefly to strengthen a suspicion of evil designs, was, that
                    though they had <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> resolved to seize Aristo,
                    and send him to Rome, they had not placed a guard either on himself or his ship.
                    Then be- <pb n="1552" xml:id="p.1552"/> gan the controversy with the king's
                    ambassadors, on the claims of the territory in dispute. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The Carthaginians supported their cause by a boundary
                    claim, urging that <quote> it must belong <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> to
                        them, as being within the limits which Scipio, after conquering the country,
                        had fixed as the boundaries which should be under Carthaginian rule;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and also, by the acknowledgment of
                        the king, who, when he was going in pursuit of Aphir, a fugitive from his
                        kingdom, then hovering about Cyrene, with a party of Numidians, had
                        solicited as a favour a passage through that very district, as being
                        confessedly a part of the Carthaginian dominions. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Numidians insisted, <quote> that they
                        were guilty of misrepresentation, with respect to the limits fixed by
                        Scipio; and if a person chose to recur to the real origin of their property,
                        what title had the Carthaginians to call any land in Africa their own:
                        foreigners and strangers, to whom had been granted precariously, for the
                        purpose of building a city, as much ground as they could encompass with the
                        cuttings of a bull's hide? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Whatever
                        acquisitions they had made beyond Byrsa, their original settlement, they
                        held by fraud and violence; for, in relation to the land in question, so far
                        were they from being able to prove uninterrupted possession, from the time
                        when it was first acquired, that they cannot even prove that they ever
                        possessed it for any considerable time. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        As occasions offered, sometimes they, sometimes the kings of Numidia, had
                        held the dominion of it; and the possession of it had always been held by
                        the party which had the greatest armed force. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> They requested the senate to suffer the matter to
                        remain on the same footing on which it stood before the Carthaginians became
                        enemies to the Romans, or the king of Numidia their friend and ally; and not
                        to interfere, so as to hinder whichever party was able, from keeping
                        possession. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> —The senate resolved to tell the ambassadors
                    of both parties, that they would send persons into Africa to determine the
                    present controversy between the people of Carthage and the king. They
                    accordingly sent Publius Scipio Africanus, Caius Cornelius Cethegus, and Marcus
                    Minucius Rufus; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> who, after viewing the
                    ground, and hearing what could be said on both sides, left every thing in
                    suspense, their opinions inclining neither to one side nor the other. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> Whether they acted in this manner from their own
                    judgment, or because they had been so in- <pb n="1553" xml:id="p.1553"/>
                    structed, is by no means so certain as it is, that as affairs were
                    circumstanced, it was highly expedient to leave the dispute undecided:
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> for, had the case been otherwise, Scipio
                    alone, either from his own knowledge of the business, or the influence which he
                    possessed, and to which he had a just claim on both parties, could, with a nod,
                    have ended the controversy. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
