<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    30</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1283" xml:id="p.1283"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXX.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Scipio, aided by Masinissa, defeats the Carthaginians, Syphax and Hasdrubal,
                        in several battles. Syphax taken by Laelius and Masinissa. Masinissa
                        espouses Sophonisba, the wife of Syphax, Hasdrubal's daughter; being
                        reproved by Scipio, he sends her poison, with which she puts an end to her
                        life. The Carthaginians, reduced to great extremity by Scipio's repeated
                        victories, call Hannibal home from Italy; he holds a conference with Scipio
                        on the subject of peace, and is again defeated by him in battle. The
                        Carthaginians sue for peace, which is granted them. Masinissa reinstated in
                        his kingdom. Scipio returns to Rome; his splendid triumph; is surnamed
                        Africanus. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> CNEIUS SERVILIUS and Caius Servilius Geminus,
                    the consuls in the sixteenth year of the Punic war, having consulted the senate
                    respecting the state, the war, and the provinces, they decreed that the consuls
                    should arrange between themselves, or draw <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    lots, which of them should have the province of Bruttium, to act against
                    Hannibal, and which that of Etruria and Liguria; that the consul to whose lot
                    Bruttium fell should receive the army from Publius Sempronius; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> that Publius Sempronius, who was continued in command as
                    proconsul for a year, should succeed Publius Licinius, who was to return to
                    Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In addition to the other qualifications
                    with which he was adorned in a degree surpassed by no citizen of that time, for
                    in him were accumulated all the perfections of nature and fortune, Licinius was
                    also esteemed eminent in war. He was at once a man of noble family and great
                    wealth; possessing a fine person and great bodily strength. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He was considered an orator of the highest order, both in
                    respect of judicial eloquence, and also when engaged in promoting or opposing
                    any measure in the senate, or before the people. He was also accurately skilled
                    in the pontifical law. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In addition to all
                    these recommendations, the consulship enabled him to acquire military glory. The
                    senate adopted the same course in the decree with respect to the province of
                    Etruria and Li- <pb n="1284" xml:id="p.1284"/> guria as had been observed with
                    regard to Bruttium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcus Cornelius was
                    ordered to deliver his army to the new consul, and with continued command to
                    hold himself the province of Gaul, with those legions which the praetor Lucius
                    Scribonius had commanded the former year. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls then cast lots for their provinces: Bruttium fell to the lot of Caepio,
                    Etruria to the lot of Servilius Geminus. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    provinces of the praetors were then put to the lot. Paetus Aelius obtained the
                    city jurisdiction; Publius Lentulus, Sardinia; Publius Villius, Sicily;
                    Quinctilius Varus, Ariminum, with two legions which had served under Lucretius
                    Spurius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Lucretius also was continued in
                    command that he might complete the building of the town of Genoa, which had been
                    destroyed by Mago the Carthaginian. Publius Scipio was continued in command for
                    a period not limited in point of time, but the object he had to achieve, namely,
                    till the war in Africa had been brought to a termination; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and a decree was passed, ordering a supplication to be made
                    that the circumstance of his crossing over into Africa might be beneficial to
                    the Roman people, the general himself, and his army. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Three thousand men were enlisted for Sicily,
                    and lest any fleet should go thither from Africa, as all the efficient troops
                    that province had possessed had been transported into Africa, it was resolved
                    that the sea-coast of that island should be guarded with forty ships. Villius
                    took with him into Sicily thirteen ships, the rest consisted of the old ones,
                    which were repaired. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Marcus Pomponius, the
                    praetor of the former year, who was continued in command, having been placed at
                    the head of this fleet, put on board the fresh soldiers brought from Italy.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The senate assigned by a decree an equal
                    number of ships to Cneius Octavius, who was also a praetor of the former year,
                    with a similar privilege of command, for the protection of the coast of
                    Sardinia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Lentulus the praetor was ordered to
                    furnish two thousand soldiers to put on board it. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The protection of the coast of Italy was assigned to Marcus
                    Marcius, a praetor of the former year, with the same number of ships; for it was
                    uncertain to what quarter the Carthaginians would send a fleet, though it was
                    supposed that they would attack any quarter which was destitute of defence.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls, in conformity with a decree
                    of the senate, enlisted three thousand soldiers for this fleet, and two city
                    legions with a view to the <pb n="1285" xml:id="p.1285"/> hazards of war.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Spains were assigned to the former
                    generals, Lucius Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus, who were continued in
                    command, and retained their former armies. The operations of the war on the part
                    of the Romans this year were carried on with twenty legions in all, and one
                    hundred and sixty ships of war. The praetors were ordered to proceed to their
                    provinces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Directions were given to the
                    consuls, that before they left the city they should celebrate the great games
                    which Titus Manlius Torquatus, when dictator, had vowed to be exhibited in the
                    fifth year, if the condition of the state remained unaltered. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Accounts of prodigies brought from several places excited
                    fresh superstitious fears in the minds of men. It was believed that crows had
                    not only torn with their beaks some gold in the Capitol, but had even eaten it.
                    At Antium mice gnawed a golden crown. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> An
                    immense quantity of locusts filled the whole country around Capua, nor could it
                    be made appear satisfactorily whence they came. At Reate a foal was produced
                    with five feet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At Anagnia at first scattered
                    fires appeared in the sky, afterwards a vast meteor blazed forth. At Frusino a
                    circle surrounded the sun with a thin line, which was itself afterwards included
                    within the sun's disc which extended beyond it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> At Arpinum the earth sank into an immense gulf, in a place where the ground
                    was level. When one of the consuls was immolating the first victim, the head of
                    the liver was wanting. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These prodigies were
                    expiated with victims of the larger kind. The college of pontiffs gave out to
                    what gods sacrifice was to be made. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After these matters were finished, the consuls
                    and praetors set out for their provinces. All, however, made Africa the great
                    object of their concern, as though it had been allotted to them; whether it was
                    because they saw that the welfare of the state and the issue of the war turned
                    upon the operations there, or that they might oblige Scipio, on whom the whole
                    state was then intent. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly, not only
                    from Sardinia, as has been before mentioned, but from Sicily also and Spain,
                    clothing and corn, and from Sicily arms also, together with every kind of
                    stores, were conveyed thither. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor did Scipio
                    at any time during the winter relax in any of the various military operations in
                    which he was engaged on all sides. He continued the siege of Utica. His camp was
                    within sight of Hasdrubal. The Carthaginians had launched <pb n="1286"
                        xml:id="p.1286"/> their ships, and had a fleet prepared and equipped to
                    intercept his supplies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Amid these occupations
                    he had not even lost sight of his endeavours to regain the friendship of Syphax,
                    whose passion for his bride he thought might now perhaps have become satiated
                    from unlimited enjoyment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From Syphax he
                    received terms of peace with the Carthaginians, with proposals that the Romans
                    should evacuate Africa, and the Carthaginians Italy, rather than any ground of
                    hope that he would desert their cause if the war proceeded. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> For my part I am of opinion, and in this I am countenanced
                    by the majority of writers, that these negotiations were carried on through
                    messengers, rather than that Syphax himself came to the Roman camp to hold a
                    conference, as Antias Valerius relates. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At
                    first the Roman general scarcely allowed these terms to be mentioned, but
                    afterwards, in order that there might exist a plausible pretext for his
                    emissaries to go frequently into the camp of the enemy, he rejected these same
                    terms in a more qualified manner, holding out a hope that they might eventually
                    come to an agreement by agitating the question on both sides. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The winter huts of the Carthaginians, which were
                    constructed from materials hastily collected out of the fields, were almost
                    entirely of wood. The Numidians, particularly, lay for the most part in huts
                    formed of interwoven reeds, and covered with mats, dispersed up and down without
                    any regard to order; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> while some of them,
                    having chosen the situations for their tents without waiting for orders, lay
                    even without the trench and rampart. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These
                    circumstances having been reported to Scipio, gave him hopes that he might have
                    an opportunity of burning the enemy's camp. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In company with the ambassadors whom he sent
                    to Syphax, he also sent some centurions of the first rank, of tried valour and
                    prudence, dressed as servants, in lieu of soldiers' drudges; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> in order that, while the ambassadors were engaged in
                    conference, they might ramble through the camp, one in one direction and another
                    in another, and thus observe all the approaches and outlets, the situation and
                    form both of the camp in general and of its parts; where the Carthaginians lay,
                    where the Numidians, and what was the distance between the camp of Hasdrubal and
                    that of the king; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that they might at the
                    same time acquaint themselves with their customary mode of stationing outposts
                    and watches, and learn <pb n="1287" xml:id="p.1287"/> whether they were more
                    open to stratagem by night or by day. During the frequent conferences which were
                    held, several different persons were purposely sent, in order that every
                    circumstance might be known to a greater number. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> When the more frequent agitation of the matter had given to Syphax a daily
                    increasing hope of peace, and to the Carthaginians through him, the Roman
                    ambassadors at length declared that they were forbidden to return to their
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> general unless a decisive answer was
                    given, and that, therefore, if his own determination was now fixed, he should
                    declare it, or if Hasdrubal and the Carthaginians were to be consulted, he
                    should consult them. That it was time either that an accommodation should be
                    settled or the war vigorously prosecuted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    While Hasdrubal was consulted by Syphax, and the Carthaginians by Hasdrubal, the
                    spies had time to inspect every thing, and Scipio to get together what was
                    necessary for the accomplishment of his project. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> In consequence of the mention and prospect of a peace, neglect arose among
                    the Carthaginians and Numidians, as is usually the case, to take precautions in
                    the mean time that they might not suffer an attack of the enemy. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> At length an answer was returned; and as the Romans
                    appeared excessively eager for peace, advantage was taken of that circumstance
                    to add certain unreasonable conditions, which afforded Scipio a very seasonable
                    pretext for putting an end to the truce according to his wishes; and telling the
                    king's messenger that he would refer the matter to his council, he answered him
                    the next day. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He said, that while he alone had
                    in vain endeavoured to restore peace, no one else had desired it. That he must,
                    therefore, carry word back that Syphax must hope for peace on no other condition
                    than his abandonment of the Carthaginians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Thus he put an end to the truce, in order that he might be free to execute his
                    designs without breaking his faith; and, launching his ships, for it was now the
                    beginning of spring, he put on board machines and engines, with the purpose of
                    assaulting Utica from the sea. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He also sent
                    two thousand men to seize the eminence which commanded that place, and which he
                    had before occupied, at once with the view of turning the attention of the enemy
                    from the design he was endeavouring <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> to
                    effect to another object of concern, <pb n="1288" xml:id="p.1288"/> and to
                    prevent any sally or attack which might be made from the city upon his camp,
                    which would be left with a slight force to protect it, while he himself went
                    against Syphax and Hasdrubal. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having made these preparations, he called a
                    council, and after ordering the spies to give an account of the discoveries they
                    had made, and requesting Masinissa, who was acquainted with every circumstance
                    relating to the enemy, to state what he knew, lastly, he himself laid before the
                    council the plan proposed for the following night. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He gave directions to the tribunes, that when, after the
                    breaking up of the council, the trumpets had sounded, they should immediately
                    march the legions out of the camp. Agreeably to his commands, the standards
                    began to be carried out about sun-set. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About
                    the first watch they formed the troops in marching order. At midnight, for it
                    was seven miles' march, they came up at a moderate pace to the camp of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Here Scipio assigned a part of his
                    forces, together with Masinissa and the Numidians, to Laelius, ordering them to
                    fall upon the camp of Syphax, and throw fire upon it. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Then taking each of the commanders, Masinissa and Laelius,
                    aside, he implored them separately to make up by diligence and care for the
                    absence of that foresight which the night rendered it impossible to exercise.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He said, that he should himself attack
                    Hasdrubal and the Carthaginian camp; but that he should not begin till he saw
                    the fire in that of the king. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor did this
                    delay him long; for when the fire thrown upon the nearest huts had taken effect,
                    immediately communicating with all those which were within the shortest
                    distance, and those connected with them in regular succession, it spread itself
                    throughout the whole camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The confusion and
                    alarm which took place, in consequence of so widely extended a fire breaking out
                    during the night, were as great as might naturally be expected; but as they
                    concluded that it was the effect of chance, and not produced by the enemy, or
                    connected with the war, they rushed out in a disorderly manner, without their
                    arms, to extinguish the <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> flames, and fell in
                    with armed enemies, particularly the Numidians, who on account of their
                    knowledge of the king's camp were placed by Masinissa in convenient places at
                    the openings of the passes. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Many perished in
                    the <pb n="1289" xml:id="p.1289"/> flames in their beds while half asleep; and
                    many, tumbling over one another in their haste to escape, were trampled to death
                    in the narrow passages of the gates. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When first the Carthaginian sentinels, and
                    afterwards the rest, roused by the terrifying effects of a tumult by night,
                    beheld the light emitted from the flames, they also, labouring under the same
                    delusion, imagined that the fire had originated from accidental causes;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> while the shout raised amidst the
                    slaughter and wounds, being of a confused kind, prevented their distinguishing
                    whether it was occasioned by the trepidation of an alarm by night. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, rushing out one and all at every gate,
                    each man taking the nearest road, without their arms, as not suspecting any
                    hostile attack, and carrying with them only such things as might be useful in
                    extinguishing the flames, they fell upon the Roman troops. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> After all these had been slain, not only with the animosity
                    of enemies, but also that no one might escape as a messenger, Scipio immediately
                    attacked the gates, which were unguarded in consequence of the confusion;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and, having thrown fire upon the nearest
                    huts, at first the flames blazed forth with great fury, in several places at
                    once, in consequence of the fire having been applied to different parts, but
                    afterwards extending themselves along the contiguous huts, they suddenly
                    enveloped the whole camp in one general conflagration. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Men and cattle scorched with the flames blocked up the
                    passages of the gates, first in a terrible rush to escape, and afterwards with
                    their prostrate bodies. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Those who got out of
                    the way of the fire were cut off by the sword, and the two camps were involved
                    in one common destruction. The two generals, however, and out of so many
                    thousand troops only two thousand foot and five hundred horsemen, escaped, half
                    armed, a great many of them being wounded and scorched. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Forty thousand men were either slain or destroyed by the
                    flames, and above five thousand captured. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Among the captured were many Carthaginian nobles, eleven senators, with a
                    hundred and seventy-four military standards, above two thousand seven hundred
                    Numidian horses, and six elephants. Eight elephants were destroyed either by
                    fire or sword, and a great quantity of arms taken. All the latter the general
                    dedicated to Vulcan and burnt. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, in his flight, had made for the
                    nearest city <pb n="1290" xml:id="p.1290"/> of the Africans, accompanied by a
                    few attendants; and hither all those who survived, following the footsteps of
                    their general, had betaken themselves. But afterwards, fearing lest he should be
                    given up to Scipio, he quitted that city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Soon
                    after, the Romans were received there with open gates; nor was any act of
                    hostility committed, because the inhabitants had surrendered voluntarily.
                    Shortly after, two other cities were captured and plundered. The booty found
                    there, together with what had been rescued from the camps when burning, and from
                    the flames, was given up to the soldiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Syphax took up a position in a fortified place about eight miles off. Hasdrubal
                    hastened to Carthage, lest the apprehensions occasioned by the recent disaster
                    should lead to any timorous measures. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So great
                    was the consternation created there on the first receipt of the news, that it
                    was fully anticipated that Scipio, suspending his operations against Utica,
                    would immediately lay siege to Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    suffetes, therefore, who form with them an authority similar to the consular,
                    summoned the senate, when the three following opinions were given. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The first proposed, that a decree should be passed to
                    the effect, that ambassadors should be sent to Scipio to treat of peace; the
                    second, that Hannibal should be recalled to defend his country from a war which
                    threatened its annihilation; the third breathed the spirit of Roman constancy
                    under adversity; it recommended that the losses of the army should be repaired,
                    and that Syphax should be exhorted not to abandon the war. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The latter opinion prevailed, because it was that which
                    Hasdrubal, who was present, and all the members of the Barcine faction,
                    preferred. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After this, the levy commenced in
                    the city and country, and ambassadors were despatched to Syphax, who was himself
                    employing every effort to restore the war; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for
                    his wife had prevailed upon him, not, as heretofore, by caresses, powerful as
                    they are in influencing the mind of a lover, but by prayers and appeals to his
                    compassion, imploring him, with streaming eyes, not to betray her father and her
                    country, nor suffer Carthage to be consumed by the same flames which had reduced
                    the camps to ashes. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In addition to this, the
                    ambassadors informed him of a circumstance which had occurred very seasonably to
                    raise their hopes; that they had met with four thousand Celtiberians in the
                    neighbourhood of a city named Abba, a fine body of young <pb n="1291"
                        xml:id="p.1291"/> men who had been enlisted by their recruiting officers in
                    Spain; and that Hasdrubal would very soon arrive with a body of troops by no
                    means contemptible. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly, he not only
                    returned a kind answer to the ambassadors, but also showed them a multitude of
                    Numidian rustics, whom he had lately furnished with arms and horses; and at the
                    same time assured them that he would call out all the youth in his kingdom.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He said, he well knew that the loss
                    sustained had been occasioned by fire, and not by battle, and that he was
                    inferior to his adversary in war who was overcome by force of arms. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> Such was the answer given to the ambassadors; and,
                    after a few days, Hasdrubal and Syphax again united their forces. This army
                    consisted of about thirty-five thousand fighting men. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, considering that Syphax and the
                    Carthaginians could make no further efforts, gave his whole attention to the
                    siege of Utica, and was now bringing up his engines to the walls, when he was
                    diverted from his purpose by a report of the renewal of the war; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> and, leaving small forces merely to keep up the
                    appearence of a siege by sea and land, he set out himself with the main strength
                    of his army to meet the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first he
                    took up his position on an eminence about five miles distant from the king's
                    camp. The next day, coming down with his cavalry into a place called the great
                    plains, which lay at the foot of that eminence, he spent the day in advancing up
                    to the outposts of the enemy, and provoking them by skirmishing attacks.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> During the ensuing two days, irregular
                    excursions were made by both sides alternately, but nothing worthy of notice was
                    achieved. On the fourth day, both sides came down in battle-array. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans placed their principes behind the
                    spearmen, which latter formed the front line, and the triarii they stationed in
                    reserve; the Italian cavalry they opposed to the enemy in the right wing, the
                    Numidians and Masinissa on the left. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Syphax
                    and Hasdrubal, placing the Numidians against the Italian cavalry, and the
                    Carthaginians opposite to Masinissa, received the Celtiberians into the centre
                    of their line, to face the Roman legions. Thus arranged, they then commenced the
                    encounter. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the first charge, both the
                    wings, the Numidians and Carthaginians, were together driven from their ground;
                    for neither could the Numidians, who consisted principally of rustics, sustain
                        <pb n="1292" xml:id="p.1292"/> the shock of the Roman cavalry, nor the
                    Carthaginians, who were also raw soldiers, withstand Masinissa, who, in addition
                    to other circumstances, was rendered formidable by his recent victory.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Celtiberian line, though stript of the
                    support of both the wings, stood their ground; for neither did any hope of
                    safety by flight present itself, as they were ignorant of the country, nor could
                    they expect pardon from Scipio, against whom, though he had deserved well both
                    of them and their nation, they had come into Africa to fight for hire.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Surrounded, therefore, on all sides by the
                    enemy, they died with obstinate resolution, falling one upon another; and, while
                    the attention of all was turned upon them, Syphax and Hasdrubal gained a
                    considerable space of time to effect their escape. The victors, fatigued with
                    the slaughter, which had continued for a greater length of time than the battle,
                    were interrupted by the night. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day Scipio sent Laelius and
                    Masinissa, with all the Roman and Numidian cavalry, and the light infantry, to
                    pursue Syphax and Hasdrubal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He himself, with
                    the main strength of the army, reduced the neighbouring towns, which were all
                    subject to the Carthaginians, some by holding out hopes to them, some by
                    threats, and others by force. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Carthage,
                    indeed, the consternation was extreme; and it was fully anticipated there, that
                    Scipio, who was carrying his arms to the different places around, would, after
                    having rapidly subdued all the neighbouring parts, suddenly attack Carthage
                    itself. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their walls were repaired and
                    protected with outworks; and every man individually exerted himself to the
                    utmost in collecting from the country the requisites for holding out against a
                    protracted siege. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Mention was seldom made of
                    peace, but not so seldom of sending deputies to recall Hannibal. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The majority of them urged that the fleet, which had
                    been equipped to intercept the convoys of the enemy, should be sent to surprise
                    the ships stationed near Utica, which were lying in an unguarded state. It was
                    also urged that they might perhaps overpower the naval camp, which was left
                    under the protection of a trifling force. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They
                    chiefly inclined to the latter plan, though they thought, nevertheless, that
                    deputies should be sent to Hannibal; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for
                    should the operations of the fleet succeed in the highest degree, the siege of
                    Utica would be partially raised, but they had no general <pb n="1293"
                        xml:id="p.1293"/> remaining but Hannibal, and no army but his which could
                    defend Carthage itself. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The ships were
                    therefore launched the following day, and, at the same time, the deputies set
                    out for Italy; and, their position stimulating them, every thing was done with
                    the greatest expedition; each man considering, that the safety of all was
                    betrayed in whatever degree he remitted his own individual exertions. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Scipio, who drew after him an army now encumbered
                    with the spoils of many cities, sent his prisoners, and other booty, to his old
                    camp at Utica, and, as his views were now fixed on Carthage, he seized on Tunes,
                    which was abandoned in consequence of the flight of the garrison. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> This city is about fifteen miles distant from
                    Carthage, being a place secured both by works, and also by its own natural
                    position; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> it may be seen from Carthage, and
                    itself affords a prospect both of that city and of the sea which washes it. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From this place the Romans, while diligently
                    employed in raising a rampart, descried the fleet of the enemy, on its way to
                    Utica from Carthage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Desisting from their
                    work, therefore, orders for marching were given, and the troops began to move
                    with the utmost haste, lest the ships which were turned towards the land, and
                    occupied with the siege, and which were far from being in a condition for a
                    naval battle, should be surprised and overpowered. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> For how could ships, carrying engines and machines, and
                    either converted to the purposes of transports, or brought up to the walls so as
                    to afford the means of mounting up, in lieu of a mound and bridges, resist a
                    fleet, with nothing to impede its movements, furnished with every kind of naval
                    implement, and prepared for action. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Scipio,
                    therefore, contrary to his usual practice in naval engagements, drew the ships
                    of war, which might have been employed in defending the rest, into the rear, and
                    formed them into a line near the land; opposing to the enemy a row of
                    transports, four deep, to serve as a wall; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and, lest these same transports should be thrown into disorder during the
                    confusion of the battle, he bound them together by placing masts and yard-arms
                    across them, from one vessel to the other; and, by means of strong ropes,
                    fastened them together, as it were, by one uninterrupted bond. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> He also laid planks upon them, so as to form a free passage
                    along the line, leaving spaces under these bridges of communication by which the
                        <pb n="1294" xml:id="p.1294"/> vessels of observation might run out towards
                    the enemy, and retreat with safety. Having hastily made these arrangements, as
                    well as the time would permit, he put on board the transports about a thousand
                    picked men, to keep off <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the enemy, with a
                    very large store of weapons, particularly missiles, that they might hold out,
                    however long the contest lasted. Thus prepared, and on the watch, they waited
                    the approach of the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians,
                    who, if they had made haste, would, on the first assault, have surprised their
                    adversaries while every thing was in a state of confusion, from the hurry and
                    bustle attending the preparations, were so dismayed at their losses by land, and
                    thereby <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> had lost so much confidence even in
                    their strength by sea, in which they had the advantage, that, after consuming
                    the day, in consequence of the slow rate at which they sailed, about sun-set
                    they put in to a harbour which the Africans call Ruscino. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The following day, at sun-rise, they drew up their ships
                    towards the open sea, as for a regular naval battle, and with the expectation
                    that the Romans would come out to engage them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> After they had continued stationary for some time, and saw that no movement
                    was made on the part of the enemy, then, at length, they attacked the
                    transports. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The affair bore no resemblance to
                    a naval fight, but rather had the appearance of ships attacking walls. The
                    transports had considerably the advantage in respect of height; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> and as the Carthaginians had to throw their weapons
                    upward, against a mark which was above them, most of them failed of taking
                    effect; while the weapons thrown from the transports from above fell with
                    increased force, and derived additional impetus from their very weight.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The vessels of observation, and even the
                    lighter kind of barks, which went out through the spaces left under the
                    flooring, which formed a communication between the ships, were at first run down
                    by the mere momentum and bulk of the ships of war; <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> and afterwards they proved a hinderance to the troops
                    appointed to keep the enemy off; for as they mixed with the ships of the enemy,
                    they were frequently under the necessity of withholding their weapons for fear,
                    by a misdirected effort, they <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> should fall
                    on their friends. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> At length, beams with iron
                    hooks at their ends, called harpoons, began to be thrown from the Carthaginian
                    upon the Roman ships; and, as they could not cut the harpoons themselves, <pb
                        n="1295" xml:id="p.1295"/> nor the chains suspended by which they were
                    thrown upon their ships, as each of the ships of war of the enemy, being pulled
                        <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> back, drew with it a transport,
                    connected with it by a harpoon, you might see the fastenings by which the
                    transports were joined together rent asunder, and in another part a series of
                    many vessels dragged away together. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> In this
                    manner chiefly were all the bridges of communication torn to pieces, and
                    scarcely had the troops who fought in front time to leap to the second line of
                    ships. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> About six transports were towed away
                    to Carthage, where the joy felt was greater than the occasion warranted; but
                    their delight was increased from the reflection, that, in the midst of so many
                    successive disasters and woes, one event, however trifling, which afforded
                    matter of joy, had unexpectedly occurred; <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    besides which, it was manifest that the Roman fleet would have been well nigh
                    annihilated, had not their own commanders been wanting in diligence, and had not
                    Scipio come up to its assistance in time. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It happened about the same time, that Laelius
                    and Masinissa having arrived in Numidia after a march of about fifteen days, the
                    Massylians, Masinissa's hereditary kingdom, placed themselves under the
                    protection of their king with the greatest joy, as they had long wished him
                    among them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the commanders and garrisons
                    of Syphax had been expelled from thence, that prince kept himself within the
                    limits of his original dominions, but without any intention of remaining quiet.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Subdued by the power of love, he was
                    spurred on by his wife and father-in-law; and he possessed such an abundance of
                    men and horses, that a review of the resources of his kingdom, which had
                    flourished for so many years, was calculated to infuse spirit into a mind even
                    less barbarous and impetuous than his. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore, collecting together all who were fit for service, he distributed
                    among them horses, armour, and weapons. He divided his horsemen into troops, and
                    his infantry into cohorts, as he had formerly learnt from the Roman centurions.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With an army not less than that which he
                    had before, but almost entirely raw and undisciplined, he set out to meet the
                    enemy, and pitched his camp at a short distance from them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> At first a few horsemen advanced cautiously from the
                    outposts to reconnoitre, and being compelled to retire, from a discharge of
                    javelins, they ran <pb n="1296" xml:id="p.1296"/> back to their friends. Then
                    skirmishing parties were sent out from both sides, and the vanquished, fired
                    with indignation, returned to the encounter with increased numbers. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> This is the usual incitement of battles between
                    cavalry, when the victors are joined by more of their party from hope, and the
                    vanquished from resentment. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thus, on the
                    present occasion, the action commencing with a few, at last the whole body of
                    the cavalry on both sides poured out to join in it, from the zeal excited by the
                    contest. While the cavalry only were engaged, it was scarcely possible to
                    withstand the numbers of the Masaesylians, which Syphax sent out in immense
                    bodies. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But afterwards, when the Roman
                    infantry, suddenly coming up between the troops of horse which made way for
                    them, gave stability to their line, and checked the enemy, who were charging
                    furiously, at first the barbarians slackened their speed, then halted, and were
                    in a manner confounded at this novel kind of battle. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At length, they not only retired before the infantry, but
                    were unable to sustain the shock even of the cavalry, who had assumed courage
                    from the support of the infantry. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> By this
                    time the legions also were approaching; when, indeed, the Masaesylians not only
                    dared not await their first charge, but could not bear even the sight of the
                    standards and arms; so powerful was either the recollection of their former
                    defeats, or their present fears. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was then that Syphax, while riding up to
                    the troops of the enemy to try if, either by shame or by exposing his own person
                    to danger, he could stop their flight, being thrown from his horse, which was
                    severely wounded, was overpowered, and being made prisoner, was dragged alive
                    into the presence of Laelius; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> a spectacle
                    calculated to afford peculiar satisfaction to Masinissa. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Cirta was the capital of the dominions of Syphax; to which
                    a great number of men fled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The number of the
                    slain in this battle was not so great as the victory was important, because the
                    cavalry only had been engaged. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Not more than
                    five thousand were slain, and less than half that number were made prisoners in
                    an attack upon the camp, to which the multitude, dismayed at the loss of their
                    king, had fled. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Masinissa declared that
                    nothing could be more highly gratifying to him than, having gained this victory,
                    to go now and visit his hereditary dominions, <pb n="1297" xml:id="p.1297"/>
                    which he had regained after having been kept out of them so long a time; but it
                    was not proper in prosperity any more than in adversity to lose any time.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That if Laelius would allow him to go
                    before him to Cirta with the cavalry and the captive Syphax, he should overpower
                    the enemy while all was in a state of consternation and dismay; and that Laelius
                    might follow with the infantry at a moderate rate. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Laelius assenting, he advanced to Cirta, and ordered the
                    principal inhabitants to be called out to a conference. But as they were not
                    aware of what had befallen their king, he was unable to prevail upon them,
                    either by laying before them what had passed, by threats, or by persuasion,
                    until the king was presented to their view in chains. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> A general lamentation arose at this shocking exhibition,
                    and while some deserted the walls in a panic, others, who sought to ingratiate
                    themselves with the victor, suddenly came to an agreement to throw open the
                    gates. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Masinissa, having sent troops to keep
                    guard near the gates, and at such parts of the wall as required it, that no one
                    might have a passage out to escape by, galloped off to seize the palace.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> While entering the porch, Sophonisba, the
                    wife of Syphax and daughter of Hasdrubal the Carthaginian, met him in the very
                    threshold, and seeing Masinissa in the midst of the armed band, for he was
                    distinguished both by his arms and also by his habiliments, she concluded, as
                    was really the case, that he was the king; and, falling down at his knees, thus
                    addressed him: <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> The gods, together with your own valour and good fortune, have given you
                        the power of disposing of us as you please. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> But if a captive may be allowed to give utterance to the voice of
                        supplication before him who is the sovereign arbiter of her life or death;
                        if she may be permitted to touch his knees and his victorious right hand, I
                        entreat and beseech you by the majesty of royalty, which we also a short
                        time ago possessed; by the name of the Numidian race, which was common to
                        Syphax and yourself; by the guardian deities of this palace, (and O! may
                        they receive you more auspiciously than they sent Syphax from it!)
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> that you would indulge a suppliant by
                        determining yourself whatever your inclination may suggest respecting your
                        captive, and not suffer me to be placed at the haughty and merciless
                        disposal of any Roman. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Were I nothing
                        more than the wife of Syphax, yet would I rather make trial of the honour of
                        a Numidian, <pb n="1298" xml:id="p.1298"/> one born in Africa, the same
                        country which gave me birth, than of a foreigner and an alien. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> You know what a Carthaginian, what the daughter
                        of Hasdrubal, has to fear from a Roman. If you cannot effect it by any other
                        means, I beg and beseech you that you will by my death rescue me from the
                        power of the Romans. </quote> She was remarkably beautiful, and in the full
                    bloom of youth. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Accordingly, while she
                    pressed his right hand, and only implored him to pledge himself that she should
                    not be delivered up to any Roman, her language assuming the character of amorous
                    blandishment rather than <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> entreaty, the
                    heart of the conqueror not only melted with compassion, but, as the Numidians
                    are an excessively amorous race, he became the slave of his captive; and giving
                    his right hand as a pledge for the performance of her request, withdrew into the
                    palace. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> He then set upon reflecting in what
                    manner he could make good his promise; and not being able to hit upon any
                    expedient, his passion suggested to him an inconsiderate and barefaced
                    alternative. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> He ordered that preparations
                    should be instantly made for celebrating the nuptials that very day; in order
                    that he might not leave it at all open to Laelius, or Scipio himself, to adopt
                    any measure respecting her as a captive who had become the wife of Masinissa.
                        <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> After the nuptials were concluded,
                    Laelius came up; and so far was he from dissembling his disapprobation of the
                    proceeding, that at first he would even have had her dragged from the marriage
                    bed and sent with Syphax and the rest of the captives to Scipio: <milestone
                        n="22" unit="section"/> but afterwards, having been prevailed upon by the
                    entreaties of Masinissa, who begged of him to leave it to Scipio to decide which
                    of the two kings should have his fortunes graced by the accession of Sophonisba,
                    he sent away Syphax and the prisoners; and, aided by Masinissa, employed himself
                    in reducing the rest of the cities of Numidia, which were occupied by the king's
                    garrisons. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When it was announced that Syphax was being
                    brought into the camp, the whole multitude poured out, as if to behold a
                    triumphal pageant. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king himself walked
                    first in chains, and a number of Numidian nobles followed. On this occasion
                    every one strove to the utmost to increase the splendour of their victory, by
                    magnifying the greatness of Syphax and the renown of his nation. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>That was the king,</quote> they said, <quote> to whose dignity the two
                        most powerful nations in the <pb n="1299" xml:id="p.1299"/> world, the Roman
                        and the Carthaginian, had paid so much deference, that their own general,
                        Scipio, leaving his province of Spain and his army, sailed into Africa with
                        only two quinqueremes <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> to solicit his
                        friendship; while Hasdrubal, the Carthaginian general, not only visited him
                        in his dominions, but gave him his daughter in marriage. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> That he had in his power two commanders, one a Roman
                        and the other a Carthaginian, at the same time. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That as both the contending parties sought the favour
                        of the immortal gods by the immolation of victims, so had they both equally
                        solicited his friendship. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That he had
                        lately possessed such great power, that after expelling Masinissa from his
                        kingdom, he reduced him to such a state, that his life was protected by a
                        report of his death, and by concealment, while he supported himself in the
                        woods on prey, after the manner of wild beasts. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thus signalized by the observations of the
                    surrounding multitude, the king was brought into the pavilion before Scipio, who
                    was moved by the former condition of the man compared with his present, and
                    particularly by the recollection of their relation of hospitality, his right
                    hand pledged, and the public and private connexion which had been formed between
                    them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These same considerations inspired
                    Syphax also with confidence in addressing the conqueror; for when Scipio asked
                    what had been his object in not only renouncing his alliance with the Romans,
                    but in making war against them without provocation, he fully admitted <quote>
                        that he had indeed done wrong, and acted like a madman; but not at that time
                        only when he took up arms against the Roman people; that was the
                        consummation of his frenzy, not its commencement. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Then it was that he was mad; <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> then it was that he banished from his mind all regard
                        for private friendship and public treaties, when he received a Carthaginian
                        wife into his house. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It was by the flames
                        kindled by those nuptial torches that his palace had been consumed. That
                        fury and pest had by every kind of fascination engrossed his affections and
                        obscured his reason; nor had she rested till she had with her own hands clad
                        him with impious arms against his guest and friend. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Yet ruined and fallen as he was, he derived some
                        consolation in his misfortunes when he saw that that same pest and fury had
                        been transferred to the dwelling and household gods of the man who was of
                        all others his greatest enemy. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That
                        Masinissa <pb n="1300" xml:id="p.1300"/> was neither more prudent nor more
                        firm than Syphax; but even more incautious by reason of his youth. Doubtless
                        he had shown greater folly and want of self-control in marrying her than he
                        himself had. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These words, dictated not merely by the hatred
                    naturally felt towards an enemy, but also by the anguish of jealousy, on seeing
                    the object of his affections in the possession of his rival, affected the mind
                    of Scipio with no ordinary degree of anxiety. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    His accusations against Masinissa derived credibility from the fact of the
                    nuptials having been celebrated in the most violent hurry, almost amid the clash
                    of arms, without consulting or waiting for Laelius, and with such precipitate
                    haste, that on the very day on which he saw the captive enemy he united himself
                    with her in matrimony, and performed the nuptial rite in the presence of the
                    household gods of his enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This conduct
                    appeared the more heinous to Scipio, because when a very young man in Spain he
                    had not allowed himself to be influenced by the beauty of any captive. While
                    ruminating on these circumstances, Laelius and Masinissa came up. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Without making any distinction between them he
                    received them both with a cheerful countenance, and having bestowed upon them
                    the highest commendations before a full assembly of his officers, he took
                    Masinissa aside and thus addressed him: <quote> I suppose, Masinissa, that it
                        was because you saw in me some good qualities that you at first came to me
                        when in Spain, for the purpose of forming a friendship with me, and that
                        afterwards in Africa you committed yourself and all your hopes to my
                        protection. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But of all those virtues, on
                        account of which I seemed to you worthy of your regard, there is not one in
                        which I gloried so much as temperance and the control of my passions. I
                        could wish that you also, Masinissa, had added this to your other
                        distinguished qualities. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There is not,
                        believe me, there is not so much danger to be apprehended by persons at our
                        time of life from armed foes, as from the pleasures which surround us on all
                        sides. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The man who by temperance has
                        curbed and subdued his appetite for them, has acquired for himself much
                        greater honour and a much more important victory than we now enjoy in the
                        conquest of Syphax. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I have mentioned with
                        delight, and I remember with pleasure, the instances of fortitude and
                        courage which you displayed in my absence. As to <pb n="1301"
                            xml:id="p.1301"/> other matters, I would rather that you should reflect
                        upon them in private, than that you should be put to the blush by my
                        reciting them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Syphax was subdued and
                        captured under the auspices of the Roman people; therefore he himself, his
                        wife, his kingdom, his territories, his towns and their inhabitants, in
                        short, every thing which belonged to him, is the booty of the Roman people,
                        and it <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> was proper that the king himself
                        and his consort, even though she had not been a citizen of Carthage, even
                        though we did not see her father commanding the armies of our enemies,
                        should be sent to Rome, and that the senate and people of Rome should judge
                        and determine respecting her who is said to have alienated from us a king in
                        alliance with us, and to have precipitated him into war with us. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Subdue your passions. Beware how you deform many
                        good qualities by one vice, and mar the credit of so many meritorious deeds
                        by a degree of guilt more than proportioned to the value of its object.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While Masinissa heard these observations, he
                    not only became suffused with blushes, but burst into tears; and after declaring
                    that he would submit to the discretion of the general, and imploring him that,
                    as far as circumstances would permit, he would consider the obligation
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> he had rashly imposed upon himself, for
                    he had promised that he would not deliver her into the power of any one, he
                    retired in confusion from the pavilion into his own tent. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There, dismissing his attendants, he spent a considerable
                    time amid frequent sighs and groans, which could be distinctly heard by those
                    who stood around the tent. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At last, heaving a
                    deep groan, he called one of his servants in whom he confided, in whose custody
                    poison was kept, according to the custom of kings, as a remedy against the
                    unforeseen events of fortune, and ordered him to mix some in a cup and carry it
                    to Sophonisba; at the same time informing her that Masinissa would gladly have
                    fulfilled the first obligation which as a husband he owed to her his wife;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but since those who had the power of doing
                    so had deprived him of the exercise of that right, he now performed his second
                    promise, that she should not come alive into the power of the Romans. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> That, mindful of her father the general, of her
                    country, and of the two kings to whom she had been married, she would take such
                    measures as she herself thought proper. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When
                    the servant came to Sophonisba <pb n="1302" xml:id="p.1302"/> bearing this
                    message and the poison, she said, <quote> I accept this nuptial present; nor is
                        it an unwelcome one, if my husband can render me no better service. Tell
                        him, however, that I should have died with greater satisfaction had I not
                        married so near upon my death. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The spirit with which she spoke was equalled
                    by the firmness with which she took and drained the chalice, without exhibiting
                    any symptom of perturbation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When Scipio was
                    informed of this event, fearful lest the high-spirited young man should in the
                    distempered state of his mind adopt some desperate resolution, <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> he immediately sent for him, and at one time
                    endeavoured to solace him, at another gently rebuked him for expiating one act
                    of temerity with another, and rendering the affair more tragical than was
                    necessary. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next day, in order to divert
                    his mind from his present affliction, he ascended his tribunal and ordered an
                    assembly to be summoned, in which having first saluted Masinissa with the title
                    of king, and distinguished him with the highest encomiums, he presented him with
                    a golden goblet, a curule chair, an ivory sceptre, an embroidered gown, and a
                    triumphal vest. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He increased the honour by
                    observing, that among the Romans there was nothing more magnificent than a
                    triumph; and that those who triumphed were not arrayed with more splendid
                    ornaments than those with which the Roman people considered Masinissa alone, of
                    all foreigners, worthy. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He then bestowed the
                    highest commendations upon Laelius also, and presented him with a golden crown,
                    and gave presents to the other military characters proportioned to their
                    respective merits. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> By these honours the
                    king's mind was soothed, and encouraged to hope that he would speedily become
                    master of all Numidia, now that Syphax was removed. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio, having sent Caius Laelius with Syphax
                    and the rest of the prisoners to Rome, with whom went also ambassadors from
                    Masinissa, led his troops back again to Tunes, and completed the fortifications
                    which he had before begun. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians,
                    who had experienced not only a short-lived but almost groundless joy, from their
                    attack upon the fleet, which, under existing circumstances, was tolerably
                    successful, were so dismayed at the account of the capture of Syphax, in whom
                    they reposed almost greater confidence than in Hasdrubal and his army, that now
                    listening no longer to any who advocated war, they sent thirty of their
                    principal elders as <pb n="1303" xml:id="p.1303"/> deputies to solicit peace.
                    With them the council of elders is held in the highest reverence, and has
                    supreme power even to control the senate itself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> When they came into the Roman camp and entered the pavilion, they prostrated
                    themselves after the manner <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> of those who pay
                    profound adoration to kings, adopting the custom, I suppose, from the country
                    from which they derived their origin. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their
                    language corresponded with such abject humiliation, for they did not endeavour
                    to deny their guilt, but charged Hannibal and the favourers of his violent
                    measures with being the originators of it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They implored pardon for their state, which had been now twice brought to the
                    brink of ruin by the temerity of its citizens, and would again owe its safety to
                    the indulgence of its enemies. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They said, the
                    object the Roman people aimed at in the subjugation of their enemies was
                    dominion, and not their destruction; that he might enjoin what he pleased upon
                    them, as being prepared submissively to obey. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Scipio replied, <quote> that he had come into Africa with the hope, and that
                        hope had been increased by the success he had experienced in his operations,
                        that he should carry home victory and not terms of peace. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Still, though he had victory in a manner within his
                        grasp, he would not refuse all accommodation, that all the nations of the
                        world may know that the Roman people both undertake and conclude wars with
                        justice. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The terms of peace which he prescribed were
                    these: <quote> That they should restore the prisoners, deserters, and fugitives;
                        withdraw their armies from Italy and Gaul; give up all claim to Spain;
                        retire from all the islands between Italy and Africa; <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> deliver up all their ships of war except twenty, and
                        furnish five hundred thousand pecks of wheat, and three hundred thousand of
                        barley. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Authors are not agreed as to the sum of money
                    he demanded. In some I find five thousand talents; in others five thousand
                    pounds' weight of silver; in others, that double pay for the troops was
                    required. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Three days,</quote> he said, <quote> shall be allowed to deliberate
                        whether you accept of peace on these terms. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                        /> If you do accept it, make a truce with me, and send deputies to Rome to
                        the senate. </quote> The Carthaginians being thus dismissed, as they thought
                    it proper to accept of any conditions of peace, for their only object was to
                    gain <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> time for Hannibal to cross over into
                    Africa, sent some ambassadors to Scipio to conclude a truce, and others to Rome
                        <pb n="1304" xml:id="p.1304"/> to solicit peace; the latter taking with them
                    a few prisoners, deserters, and fugitives, in order to facilitate the attainment
                    of peace. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laelius with Syphax and the principal Numidian
                    prisoners arrived at Rome several days before, and laying before the senate all
                    the transactions which had occurred in Africa in order, the greatest joy was
                    felt for the present, and the most sanguine anticipations formed of the future.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The sense of the senate being then taken
                    upon the subject, they resolved that the king should be sent to Alba to be kept
                    in custody, and that Laelius should be detained until the arrival of the
                    Carthaginian ambassadors. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A supplication for
                    four days was decreed. The senate breaking up and an assembly of the people
                    being then called, Publius Aelius the praetor, accompanied by Caius Laelius,
                    mounted the rostrum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There, on hearing that
                    the armies of the Carthaginians had been routed, that a king of the greatest
                    renown had been vanquished and made prisoner, that all <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> Numidia had been overrun with brilliant success, the people
                    were unable to refrain from expressing their delight, but manifested their
                    transports by shouts and all the other means usually resorted to by the
                    multitude. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The praetor, therefore, immediately
                    issued orders that the keepers should open all the temples throughout the city,
                    and that the people should be allowed during the whole day to go round and make
                    their adoration to the gods, and return their thanks. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The next day he brought the ambassadors of Masinissa before
                    the senate. They in the first place congratulated the senate on the successes of
                    Scipio <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> in Africa, and then thanked them, not
                    only for having saluted him with the title of king, but for having made him one,
                    by reinstating him in his paternal dominions, where, now that Syphax was
                    removed, he would reign, if it was the pleasure of the senate, without fear or
                    opposition. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Next, for having bestowed upon him
                    the highest commendations in the assembly, and decorated him with the most
                    magnificent presents, of which Masinissa had endeavoured, and would in future
                    endeavour, to render himself worthy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They
                    requested that the senate would by a decree confirm the title of king with the
                    other favours and benefits conferred by Scipio, and, if it were not troublesome,
                    they said, that Masinissa further requested that they would send home the
                    Numidian captives who were de- <pb n="1305" xml:id="p.1305"/> tained at Rome;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for that this boon would procure him the
                    esteem and honour of his countrymen. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On these
                    points the senate replied to the ambassadors, <quote> that they reciprocated the
                        congratulations of the king on the successes in Africa. That Scipio was
                        considered to have acted properly and regularly in saluting him with the
                        title of king, and that the senate applauded and approved of every thing
                        else he had done which was gratifying to Masinissa. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They appointed by a decree what presents the
                    ambassadors should carry to the king; they were, two purple cloaks, each having
                    a golden clasp, and each accompanied with vests and broad purple borders, two
                    horses arrayed with trappings, two suits of equestrian armour with coats of
                    mail, together with tents and other military apparatus such as those usually
                    provided for a consul. These the praetor was directed to send for the king.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The ambassadors were severally presented
                    with not less than five thousand <hi rend="italics">asses,</hi> their attendants
                    with one thousand. Two suits of apparel were presented to each of the
                    ambassadors, and one to each of their attendants and to the Numidians, who were
                    discharged from custody and given back to the king. In addition to these,
                    dwellings, reserved by the state for such purposes, grounds, and entertainment,
                    were assigned to the ambassadors. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same summer during which these decrees
                    were passed at Rome, and these transactions took place in Africa, Publius
                    Quinctilius Varus, the praetor, and Marcus Cornelius, the proconsul, fought a
                    pitched battle with Mago the Carthaginian in the territories of the Insubrian
                    Gauls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The legions of the praetor were in the
                    first line; Cornelius kept his in reserve, riding forward into the front
                    himself, and the praetor and proconsul, leading on the two wings, exhorted the
                    soldiers to attack the enemy with the utmost vigour. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Finding they produced no impression upon the enemy,
                    Quinctilius said to Cornelius: <quote> The battle, as you perceive, does not
                        proceed with spirit, the enemy, having succeeded in their resistance beyond
                        expectation, have become callous to fear, and there is danger lest it should
                        be converted into boldness. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We must stir
                        up a tempest of cavalry if we wish to disorder and drive them from their
                        ground; therefore, either do you sustain the fight in front, and I will lead
                        the cavalry into the action; or else, I will act in the front line and you
                        send out <pb n="1306" xml:id="p.1306"/> the cavalry of the four legions
                        against the enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The proconsul offering to take whichever part
                    of the service the praetor pleased, Quinctilius the praetor, with his son,
                    surnamed Marcus, a spirited youth, went off to the cavalry, and desiring them to
                    mount, instantly led them to the charge. The confusion occasioned by these was
                    increased by a shout raised by the legions; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    nor would the line of the enemy have stood unbroken, had not Mago, as soon as he
                    saw the cavalry in motion, immediately brought into the action his elephants,
                    which he kept in readiness. The horses were so terrified at the snorting, the
                    smell, and appearance of these animals, that the aid of the cavalry was rendered
                    ineffectual. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As the Roman horseman had the
                    advantage in point of efficiency in a close fight, when he could use his javelin
                    and sword hand to hand, so the Numidians had the advantage when throwing their
                    darts from a distance upon enemies borne away from them by their terrified
                    horses. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the same time the twelfth legion,
                    though a great number of them were slain, maintained their ground through shame
                    rather than a reliance on their strength; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but
                    they would not have continued to do so longer, had not the thirteenth legion,
                    brought up into the front line from the reserve, taken up the doubtful conflict.
                    Mago, also, bringing up the Gauls from his reserve, opposed them to the fresh
                    legion. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Gauls being routed without any
                    great effort, the spearmen of the eleventh legion formed themselves into a
                    circular body and charged the elephants, which were now disordering the line of
                    infantry; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and as scarcely one of the javelins
                    which they threw upon them failed of taking effect, as they were close together,
                    they turned them all upon the line of their own party. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Four of them fell overpowered with wounds. It was then that
                    the front line of the enemy gave ground, the whole body of the Roman infantry at
                    the same time rushing forward to increase the panic and confusion, on seeing the
                    elephants turn their backs. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As long as Mago
                    stood in front, the troops stepped back slowly, preserving their ranks and not
                    relaxing their ardour in fighting; but when they saw him falling, from a wound
                    in his thigh, which was transfixed, and carried off the field almost lifeless,
                    in an instant they all betook themselves to flight. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> As many as five thousand of the enemy were slain, and
                    twenty-two military standards captured on that day. Nor did the Romans obtain
                        <pb n="1307" xml:id="p.1307"/> a bloodless victory. Two thousand three
                    hundred of the army of the praetor, by far the greater part of whom belonged to
                    the twelfth legion, were lost. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Two military
                    tribunes, Marcus Cosconius and Marcus Maenius, of the same legion; and of the
                    thirteenth legion also, which joined in the action at its close, Cneius Helvius,
                    a military tribune, fell in restoring the fight; and about twenty-two
                    distinguished horsemen, together with several centurions, were trampled upon and
                    killed by the elephants. The contest would have continued longer, had not the
                    enemy conceded the victory, in consequence of the wound of their general. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mago, setting out during the silence of the
                    succeeding night, and marching as far at a time as his wounds would allow him,
                    reached the sea-coast in the territory of the Ingaunian Ligurians. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Here ambassadors from Carthage, who had put into the
                    Gallic bay a few days before, came to him with directions to cross over into
                    Africa with all speed; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> informing him that his
                    brother Hannibal, for to him also they said ambassadors had gone with similar
                    directions, would do the same, for the affairs of the Carthaginians were not in
                    a condition to admit of their occupying Gaul and Italy with armies. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Mago, not only influenced by the command of the
                    senate and the danger which threatened his country, but fearful also lest the
                    victorious enemy should be upon him if he delayed, and lest the Ligurians
                    themselves, seeing that the Carthaginians were leaving Italy, should pass over
                    to those under whose power they were likely soon to be placed; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> at the same time hoping that his wound would be less
                    irritated by the motion of sailing than marching, and that he would have greater
                    facilities for the cure of it, put his troops on board and set sail. But he had
                    scarcely cleared Sardinia when he died of his wound. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Several also of his ships, which had been dispersed in the
                    main sea, were captured by the Roman fleet which lay near Sardinia. Such were
                    the transactions by sea and land in that part of Italy which is adjacent to the
                    Alps. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul, Caius Servilius, without
                    having performed any memorable achievement in Etruria, his province, and in
                    Gaul, for he had advanced thither also, but having rescued from slavery, which
                    they had endured for now the sixteenth year, his father, Caius Servilius, and
                    his uncle, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> Caius Lutatius, who had been
                    taken by the Boians at the village of Tanetum, returned to Rome with <pb
                        n="1308" xml:id="p.1308"/> his father on one side of him and his uncle on
                    the other, distinguished by family, rather than by public, honours. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> It was proposed to the people, that Caius Servilius
                    should be indemnified for having filled the offices of plebeian tribune and
                    plebeian aedile contrary to what was established by the laws, while his father,
                    who had sat in the curule chair, was still alive, he being ignorant of that
                    circumstance. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This proposition having been
                    carried, he returned to his province. The towns Consentia, Uffugum, Vergae,
                    Besidiae, Hetriculum, Sypheum, Argentanum, Clampetia, and many other
                    inconsiderable states, perceiving that the Carthaginian cause was declining,
                    went over to Cneius Servilius the consul in Bruttium. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The same consul fought a battle with Hannibal, in the
                    territory of Croto. The accounts of this battle are not clear. Valerius Antias
                    states that five thousand men were slain. But this is an event of such
                    magnitude, that either it must be an impudent fiction, or negligently omitted.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It is certain that nothing further was
                    done by Hannibal in Italy; for ambassadors from Carthage, recalling him into
                    Africa, came to him, as it happened, at the same time that they came to Mago. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It is said that when Hannibal heard the
                    message of the ambassadors he gnashed with his teeth, groaned, and scarcely
                    refrained from shedding tears. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After they had
                    delivered the commands with which they were charged, he said: <quote> Those who
                        have for a long time been endeavouring to drag me home, by forbidding the
                        sending of <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> supplies and money to me, now
                        recall me, not indirectly, but openly. Hannibal, therefore, hath been
                        conquered, not by the Roman people, who have been so often slain and routed,
                        but by the Carthaginian senate, through envy and detraction; <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> nor will Publius Scipio exult and glory in this
                        unseemly return so much as Hanno, who has crushed our family, since he could
                        not effect it by any other means, by the ruins of Carthage. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Already had his mind entertained a
                    presentiment of this event, and he had accordingly prepared ships beforehand.
                    Having, therefore, sent a crowd of useless soldiers under pretence of garrisons
                    into the towns in the Bruttian territory, a few of which continued their
                    adherence to him, more through fear than attachment, he transported the strength
                    of his army into Africa. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Many natives of Italy
                    who, refusing to follow him into Africa, had retired to the shrine of Juno
                    Lacinia, which had never been <pb n="1309" xml:id="p.1309"/> violated up to that
                    day, were barbarously massacred in the very temple. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> It is related, that rarely any person leaving his country
                    to go into exile exhibited deeper sorrow than Hannibal did on departing from the
                    land of his enemies; that he frequently looked back upon the shores of Italy,
                    and, arraigning both gods and men, cursed himself and his own head that that he
                    did not lead his troops, while reeking with blood from the victory at Cannae, to
                    Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio, who since his appointment to the
                    office of consul had not looked at the Carthaginian enemy in Italy, had dared,
                    he said, to go and <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> attack Carthage, while
                    he, after slaying a hundred thousand fighting men at Trasimenus and Cannae, had
                    suffered his strength to wear away around Casilinum, Cumae, and Nola, Amid these
                    reproaches and complaints he was borne away from his long occupation of Italy. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time intelligence was brought to
                    Rome that both Mago and Hannibal had taken their departure. But the delight
                    occasioned by this twofold source of joy was diminished by the reflection that
                    their commanders had wanted either spirit or strength sufficient to detain them,
                    for they had been charged by the senate to do so; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and also in consequence of the anxiety they felt for the
                    issue of a contest, in which the whole weight of the war rested on the efforts
                    of one general and his army. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About the same
                    time ambassadors from Saguntum arrived, bringing with them some Carthaginians
                    who had crossed over into Spain for the purpose of hiring auxiliaries, having
                    seized them and the money they had with them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    They laid down in the vestibule of the senate-house two hundred and fifty
                    pounds' weight of gold, and eight hundred of silver. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> After the men had been received and thrown into prison, and
                    the gold and silver returned, the ambassadors were thanked, and received,
                    besides, presents and ships to convey them back into Spain. Some of the older
                    senators then observed, that men were less powerfully affected by prosperity
                    than adversity. That they themselves remembered what terror and consternation
                    had been occasioned by the passage of Hannibal into Italy; what disasters and
                    what lamentations had followed that event. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    When the camp of the enemy was seen from their walls, what vows were poured
                    forth by each and all! <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> How often, extending
                    their hands to heaven, exclamations were heard in their assemblies, Oh! will
                    that <pb n="1310" xml:id="p.1310"/> day ever arrive when we shall behold Italy
                    cleared of her enemies and enjoying the blessings of peace! <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The gods, they said, had at length, in the sixteenth year,
                    granted that favour, and yet there was no one who proposed that thanks should be
                    returned to them for it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That if men received
                    a present blessing so ungratefully, they would not be very mindful of it when it
                    was past. In consequence of this a general shout was raised from every part of
                    the senate-house, that Publius Aelius, the praetor, should lay the matter before
                    the senate, and a decree was <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> passed, that a
                    supplication should be performed at all the shrines for the space of five days,
                    and that a hundred and twenty victims of the larger sort should be immolated.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Laelius and the ambassadors of Masinissa
                    having been by this time dismissed, and intelligence having arrived that
                    ambassadors of the Carthaginians, who were coming to the senate to treat about
                    peace, had been seen at Puteoli, and would proceed thence by land, it was
                    resolved, that Caius Laelius should be recalled, that the negotiations
                    respecting the peace might take place in his presence. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Fulvius Gillo, a lieutenant-general of Scipio,
                    conducted the Carthaginians to Rome; and as they were forbidden to enter the
                    city, they were lodged in a country-house belonging to the state, and admitted
                    to an audience of the senate at the temple of Bellona. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They addressed the senate in nearly the same
                    terms as they had employed before Scipio; laying the whole blame of the war upon
                    Hannibal, and exculpating their state. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                    declared, that he had not only crossed the Alps, but the Iberus also, without
                    the sanction of the senate; and that he had made war not only on the Romans, but
                    previously on the Saguntines also, on his own individual responsibility.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That, if the question were viewed in its
                    proper light, it would be found that the league between the senate and people of
                    Carthage and the Romans remained unbroken up to that day. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, all they had in charge to solicit was, that
                    they might be allowed to continue in the enjoyment of that peace which was last
                    entered into with the consul Caius Lutatius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    When the praetor, according to the custom handed down from their ancestors, had
                    given the fathers permission to ask the ambassadors any questions they might be
                    pleased to put, and the older members who had been present at the making of the
                    treaties had put some one question and others another, the ambassadors <pb
                        n="1311" xml:id="p.1311"/> declared that they were not old enough to
                    recollect, for they were nearly all of them young men. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Upon this every part of the senate-house resounded with
                    exclamations, that with Carthaginian knavery men had been chosen to solicit a
                    renewal of the old peace who did not recollect its terms. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this, the ambassadors having been
                    removed out of the senate-house, the senators began to be asked their opinions.
                    Marcus Livius recommended, that Caius Servilius, the consul nearest home, should
                    be sent for, that he might be present at the proceedings relative to the peace;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for as it was impossible that any subject
                    of deliberation could occur of greater importance than the present, he did not
                    see how it could be discussed, consistently with the dignity of the Roman
                    people, in the absence of one or both of the consuls. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Metellus, who three years before had been consul,
                    and had filled the office of dictator, said that, since Publius Scipio, by
                    destroying the armies and by devastating the lands of the enemy, had reduced
                    them to such a state that they were compelled as supplicants to sue for peace;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and as no one could estimate with more
                    truth the intentions with which it was solicited, than he who was prosecuting
                    the war before the gates of Carthage; the peace should be rejected or adopted on
                    the advice of none other than Scipio. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Valerius Laevinus, who had been twice consul, endeavoured to show that those who
                    had come were spies, and not ambassadors; that they ought to be ordered to
                    depart from Italy; that guards should be sent with them to their very ships, and
                    that Scipio should be written to not to relax in prosecuting the war. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Laelius and Fulvius added, that Scipio had grounded
                    his hopes of effecting a peace on Hannibal and Mago not being recalled from
                    Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He considered that the Carthaginians
                    would practise every species of dissimulation, in expectation of the arrival of
                    those generals and their armies, and then, forgetful of all treaties, however
                    recent, and all gods, would proceed with the war. For these reasons they were
                    the more disposed to adopt the opinion of Levinus. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The ambassadors were dismissed without having accomplished
                    the peace, and almost without an answer. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time Cneius Servilius, the
                    consul, not doubting but that he should enjoy the glory of having restored Italy
                    to a state of peace, pursued Hannibal, whom he consi- <pb n="1312"
                        xml:id="p.1312"/> dered had fled before him, and crossed over into Sicily,
                    with the intention of proceeding thence into Africa. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As soon as this became known at Rome, at first the fathers
                    gave it as their opinion, that the praetor should inform the consul by letter
                    that the senate thought it proper that he should return into Italy; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> but afterwards, the praetor declaring that he would
                    not heed his letter, Publius Sulpicius, who was created dictator for this very
                    purpose, recalled the consul to Italy, in virtue of his superior authority.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The remainder of the year he employed in
                    conjunction with Marcus Servilius, his master of the horse, in going round to
                    the cities of Italy, which had been alienated from the Romans during the war,
                    and in taking cognizance of the cases of each. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    During the time of the truce, Lentulus the praetor sent over into Africa, from
                    Sardinia, a hundred transports with stores, under a convoy of twenty ships of
                    war, without meeting with any injury either from the enemy or storms. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The same good fortune did not attend Cneius Octavius,
                    while crossing over from Sicily with two hundred transports and thirty men of
                    war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having experienced a prosperous voyage
                    until he arrived almost within sight of Africa, at first the wind dropped, but
                    afterwards changing to the south-west, it dispersed his ships in every
                    direction. He himself with the ships of war, having struggled through the
                    opposing billows by the extraordinary exertions of his rowers, made the
                    promontory of Apollo. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The greater part of the
                    transports were driven to Aegimurus, an island filling the mouth of the bay on
                    which Carthage stands, and about thirty miles from the city; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> the rest were driven on shore directly opposite the city,
                    near the warm baths. The whole occurrence was within sight of Carthage, and,
                    accordingly, the people ran in crowds to the forum, from every part of the city.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The magistrates summoned the senate, and
                    the people were yelling in the vestibule of the senate-house, lest so great a
                    booty should escape from their hands and their sight. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Though some urged as an objection the obligation imposed
                    upon them by having solicited peace, and others the restraint occasioned by the
                    existence of a truce, the period of which had not yet expired, it was agreed in
                    an assembly, made up almost of a mixture of the senate and people, that
                    Hasdrubal should cross over to Aegimurus with fifty ships, and, proceeding
                    thence, pick up the Roman ships scattered <pb n="1313" xml:id="p.1313"/> along
                    the coasts and in the different ports. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> First
                    the transports from Aegimurus, and then those from the baths, abandoned by the
                    crews, were towed to Carthage. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors had not as yet returned from
                    Rome, nor was it known whether the Roman senate had pronounced in favour of
                    peace or war; nor as yet had the period of the truce expired. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio, therefore, considering that the malignity of their
                    offence was heightened by the fact, that, though they had solicited peace and a
                    truce, they had cut off all hopes of the former and violated the latter,
                    immediately despatched Lucius Baebius, Lucius Sergius, and Lucius Fabius, as
                    ambassadors to Carthage. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These, having
                    narrowly escaped violence from the assembled multitude, and perceiving that they
                    would be exposed to similar danger on their return, requested of the
                    magistrates, by whose aid they had been protected from violence, to send ships
                    to escort them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Two triremes were assigned
                    them, which, when they had come to the river Bagradas, whence the Roman camp
                    could be seen, returned to Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginian fleet was stationed at Utica, and from this three quadriremes were
                    despatched, which suddenly attacked the Roman quinquereme from the main sea,
                    while doubling the promontory, either owing to a message sent from Carthage that
                    this should be done, or that Hasdrubal, who commanded the fleet, perpetrated the
                    atrocity without public connivance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But
                    neither could they strike it with their beaks from the rapidity with which it
                    evaded them, nor could the fighting men board the higher from lower vessels.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The quinquereme was gallantly defended as
                    long as their weapons lasted; but these failing, and there being now nothing
                    which could save them but the nearness of the land, and the multitude which had
                    poured out from the camp upon the shore, they communicated <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> a rapid motion to the vessel by means of their oars, and
                    running her against the shore with all the force they could, they escaped
                    themselves without injury, and only lost the vessel. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Thus when the truce had been unequivocally violated by
                    repeated acts of villany, Laelius and Fulvius arrived from Rome with the
                    Carthaginian ambassadors. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Scipio told them,
                    that although the Carthaginians had not only broken their faith pledged in the
                    truce, but had also violated the laws of nations in the persons of his
                    ambassadors, yet he would not in their case do any thing unworthy of <pb
                        n="1314" xml:id="p.1314"/> the maxims of the Roman people or his own
                    principles; after saying which, he dismissed the ambassadors and prepared for
                    war. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When Hannibal was now drawing near land,
                    one of the sailors, who was ordered to climb the mast to see what part of the
                    country they were making, said the prow pointed towards a demolished <milestone
                        n="12??" unit="section"/> sepulchre, when Hannibal, recognising the
                    inauspicious omen, ordered the pilot to steer by that place, and putting in his
                    fleet at Leptis, landed his forces there. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the transactions in Africa this
                    year. Those which followed extended themselves into that year in which Marcus
                    Servilius Geminus, who was then master of the horse, and Tiberius Claudius Nero
                    were consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> However, at the close of the
                    former year, deputies from the allied states in Greece having arrived with
                    complaints that their lands had been devastated by the king's garrisons, and
                    that their ambassadors, who had gone into Macedonia to demand restitution, had
                    not been admitted into the presence of Philip; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    and having also brought information that four thousand men were said to have
                    been conveyed over into Africa, under the conduct of Sopater, to assist the
                    Carthaginians, and that a considerable quantity of money had been sent with
                    them; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the senate resolved that ambassadors
                    should be sent to the king to inform him that the fathers considered that these
                    acts were contrary to the treaty. The persons sent were Caius Terentius Varro,
                    Caius Mamilius, and Marcus Aurelius. Three quinqueremes were assigned to them.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This year was rendered remarkable by a
                    most extensive fire, by which the buildings on the Publician hill were burned to
                    the ground, and by the greatness of the floods. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> But still provisions were cheap, not only because, as it was a time of peace,
                    supplies could be obtained from every part of Italy, but also because Marcus
                    Valerius Falto and Marcus Fabius Buteo, the curule aediles, distributed to the
                    people, so much for each street, at the rate of four <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses</hi> a bushel, a great quantity of corn which had been sent out of
                    Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same year died Quintus Fabius
                    Maximus at an advanced age, if, indeed, it be true that he was augur sixty-two
                    years, which some historians relate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was a
                    man unquestionably worthy of the high surname which he bore, even had it begun
                    with him. He surpassed the honours of his father, and equalled those of his
                    grandfather. His grandfather, Rullus, was distinguished by a greater number of
                    victories and more <pb n="1315" xml:id="p.1315"/> important battles; but one
                    antagonist like Hannibal is sufficient to counterbalance them all. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> He was esteemed rather cautious than spirited; and
                    though it may be questioned whether he was naturally dilatory, or whether he
                    adopted that kind of conduct because it was peculiarly suited to the war which
                    he was carrying on, yet nothing can be more clear that he was that one man who
                    by his delay retrieved our affairs, as Ennius says. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius Maximus, his son, was consecrated augur in
                    his room. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In the room of the same, for he
                    held two priesthoods, Servius Sulpicius Galba was consecrated pontiff. The Roman
                    games were repeated for one day, the plebeian were thrice repeated entire by the
                    aediles, Marcus Sextius Sabinus and Cneius Tremellius Flaccus. Both these were
                    elected praetors, and with them Caius Livius Salinator and Caius Aurelius Cotta.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The difference in the accounts of
                    historians renders it uncertain whether Caius Servilius the consul presided in
                    the elections this year, or Publius Sulpicius, nominated dictator by him,
                    because business detained him in Etruria; being engaged, according to a decree
                    of the senate, in making inquisitions respecting the conspiracies of the
                    principal inhabitants. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the following year, Marcus
                    Servilius and Tiberius Claudius, having assembled the senate, consulted them
                    respecting the provinces. As both were desirous of having Africa, they wished
                    Italy and Africa to be disposed of by lots; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    but, principally in consequence of the exertions of Quintus Metellus, Africa was
                    neither assigned to any one nor withheld. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls were ordered to make application to the tribunes of the people, to the
                    effect, that, if they thought proper, they should put it to the people to decide
                    whom they wished to conduct the war in Africa. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    All the tribes nominated Publius Scipio. Nevertheless, the consuls put the
                    province of Africa to the lot, for so the senate had decreed. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Africa fell to the lot of Tiberius Claudius, who was to
                    cross over into Africa with a fleet of fifty ships, all quinqueremes, and have
                    an equal command with Scipio. Marcus Servilius obtained Etruria. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Caius Servilius was continued in command in the same
                    province, in case the senate resolved that the consul should remain at the city.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of the praetors, Marcus Sextus obtained
                    Gaul; which province, together with two legions, Publius Quinctilius Varus was
                    to deliver to him; <pb n="1316" xml:id="p.1316"/> Caius Livius obtained
                    Bruttium, with the two legions which Publius Sempronius, the proconsul, had
                    commanded the former year; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Cneius Tremellius
                    had Sicily, and was to receive the province and two legions from Publius Villius
                    Tappulus, a praetor of the former year; Villius, as propraetor, was to protect
                    the coast of Sicily with twenty men of war, and a thousand soldiers; and Marcus
                    Pomponius was to convey thence to Rome one thousand five hundred soldiers, with
                    the remaining twenty ships. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The city
                    jurisdiction fell to Caius Aurelius Cotta; and the rest of the praetors were
                    continued in command of the respective provinces and armies which they then had.
                    Not more than sixteen legions were employed this year in the defence of the
                    empire. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And, that they might have the gods
                    favourably disposed towards <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> them in all
                    their undertakings and proceedings, it was ordered that the consuls, before they
                    set out to the war, should celebrate those games, and sacrifice those victims of
                    the larger sort, which, in the consulate of Marcus Claudius Marcellus and Titus
                    Quinctius, Titus Manlius, the dictator, had vowed, provided the commonwealth
                    should continue in the same state for the next five years. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The games were exhibited in the circus during four days,
                    and the victims sacrificed to those deities to whom they had been vowed. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, hope and anxiety daily and
                    simultaneously increased; nor could the minds of men be brought to any fixed
                    conclusion, whether it was a fit subject for rejoicing, that Hannibal had now at
                    length, after the sixteenth year, departed from Italy, and left the Romans in
                    the unmolested possession of it, or whether they had not greater cause to fear,
                    from his having transported his army in safety into Africa. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They said that the scene of action certainly was changed,
                    but not the danger. That Quintus Fabius, lately deceased, who had foretold how
                    arduous the contest would be, was used to predict, not without good reason, that
                    Hannibal would prove a more formidable enemy in his own country than he had been
                    in a foreign one; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that Scipio would have
                    to encounter not Syphax, a king of undisciplined barbarians, whose armies
                    Statorius, a man little better than a soldier's drudge, was used to lead; nor
                    his father-in-law, Hasdrubal, that most fugacious general; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> nor tumultuary armies hastily collected out of a crowd of
                    half-armed rustics, but Hannibal, born in a manner <pb n="1317" xml:id="p.1317"
                    /> in the pavilion of his father, that bravest of generals, nurtured and
                    educated in the midst of arms, who served as a soldier formerly, when a boy, and
                    became a general when he had scarcely attained the age of manhood; <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> who, having grown old in victory, had filled Spain,
                    Gaul, and Italy, from the Alps to the strait, with monuments of his vast
                    achievements; who commanded troops who had served as long as he had himself;
                    troops hardened by the endurance of every species of suffering, such as it is
                    scarcely credible that men could have supported; stained a thousand times with
                    Roman blood, and bearing with them the spoils not only of soldiers but of
                    generals. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That many would meet the eyes of
                    Scipio in battle who had with their own hands slain Roman praetors, generals,
                    and consuls; many decorated with crowns, in reward for having scaled walls and
                    crossed ramparts; many who had traversed the captured camps and cities of the
                    Romans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the magistrates of the Roman
                    people had not then so many fasces as Hannibal could have carried before him,
                    having taken them from generals whom he had slain. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> While their minds were harassed by these apprehensions,
                    their anxiety and fears were further increased from the circumstance, that,
                    whereas they had been accustomed to carry on war for several years, in different
                    parts of Italy, and within their view, with languid hopes, and without the
                    prospect of bringing it to a speedy termination, Scipio and Hannibal had
                    stimulated the minds of all, as generals prepared for a final contest.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Even those persons whose confidence in
                    Scipio and hopes of victory were great, were affected with anxiety, increasing
                    in proportion as they saw their completion approaching. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The state of feeling among the Carthaginians was much the
                    same; for, when they turned their eyes on Hannibal, and the greatness of his
                    achievements, they repented having solicited peace; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> but when again they reflected that they had been twice
                    defeated in a pitched battle, that Syphax had been made prisoner, that they had
                    been driven out of Spain and Italy, and that all this had been effected by the
                    valour and conduct of Scipio alone, they regarded him with horror, as a general
                    marked out by destiny, and born, for their destruction. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hannibal had by this time arrived at
                    Adrumetum; <pb n="1318" xml:id="p.1318"/> from which place, after employing a
                    few days there in refreshing his soldiers, who had suffered from the motion by
                    sea, he proceeded by forced marches to Zama, roused by the alarming statements
                    of messengers, who brought word, that all the country around Carthage was filled
                    with armed troops. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Zama is distant from
                    Carthage a five days' journey. Some spies, whom he sent out from this place,
                    being intercepted by the Roman guard, and brought before Scipio, he directed
                    that they should be handed over to the military tribunes, and, after having been
                    desired fearlessly to survey every thing, to be conducted through the camp
                    wherever they chose; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> then, asking them whether
                    they had examined every thing to their satisfaction, he assigned them an escort,
                    and sent them back to Hannibal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal
                    received none of the circumstances which were reported to him with feelings of
                    joy; for they brought word that, as it happened, Masinissa had joined the enemy
                    that very day, with six thousand infantry and four thousand horse; but he was
                    principally dispirited by the confidence of his enemy, which, doubtless, was not
                    conceived without some ground. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    though he himself was the originator of the war, and by his coming had upset the
                    truce which had been entered into, and cut off all hopes of a treaty, yet
                    concluding that more favourable terms might be obtained if he solicited peace
                    while his strength was unimpaired, than when vanquished, he sent a message to
                    Scipio, requesting permission to confer with him. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> I have no means of affirming whether he did this on his own
                    spontaneous suggestion, or by the advice of his state. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Valerius Antias says, that after having been beaten by
                    Scipio in a battle, in which twelve thousand armed men were slain, and one
                    thousand seven hundred made prisoners, he came himself with ten other deputies
                    into the camp to Scipio. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> However, as Scipio
                    did not decline the proposal for a conference, both the generals, by concert,
                    brought their camps forward in order to facilitate their meeting by shortening
                    the distance. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio took up his position not
                    far from the city Naragara, in a situation convenient not only for other
                    purposes, but also because there was a watering place within a dart's throw.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal took possession of an eminence
                    four miles thence, safe and convenient in every respect, except that he had a
                        <pb n="1319" xml:id="p.1319"/> long way to go for water. Here, in the
                    intermediate space, a place was chosen, open to view from all sides, that there
                    might be no opportunity for treachery. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their armed attendants having retired to an
                    equal distance, they met, each attended by one interpreter, being the greatest
                    generals not only of their own times, but of any to be found in the records of
                    the times preceding them, and equal to <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> any
                    of the kings or generals of any nation whatever. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> When they came within sight of each other they remained silent for a short
                    time, thunderstruck, as it were, with mutual admiration. At length Hannibal thus
                    began.: <quote> Since fate hath so ordained it, that I, who was the first to
                        wage war upon the Romans, and who have so often had victory almost within my
                        reach, should voluntarily come to sue for peace, I rejoice that it is you,
                        above all others, from whom it is my lot to solicit it. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> To you, also, amid the many distinguished events of
                        your life, it will not be esteemed one of the least glorious, that Hannibal,
                        to whom the gods had so often granted victory over the Roman generals,
                        should have yielded to you; and that you should have put an end to this war,
                        which has been rendered remarkable by your calamities before it was by ours.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In this also fortune would seem to
                        have exhibited a disposition to sport with events, for it was when your
                        father was consul that I first took up arms; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> he was the first Roman general with whom I engaged in a pitched battle;
                        and it is to his son that I now come unarmed to solicit peace. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> It were indeed most to have been desired, that
                        the gods should have put such dispositions into the minds of our fathers,
                        that you should have been content with the empire of Italy, and we with that
                        of Africa: nor, indeed, even to you, are Sicily and Sardinia of sufficient
                        value to compensate you for the loss of so many fleets, so many armies. so
                        many and such distinguished generals. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But
                        what is past may be more easily censured than retrieved. In our attempts to
                        acquire the possessions of others we have been compelled to fight for our
                        own; and not only have you had a war in Italy, and we also in Africa, but
                        you have beheld the standards and arms of your enemies almost in your gates
                        and on your walls, and we now, from the walls of Carthage, distinctly hear
                        the din of a Roman camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What, therefore,
                        we should most earnestly deprecate, and you should most de- <pb n="1320"
                            xml:id="p.1320"/> voutly wish for, is now the case: peace is proposed at
                        a time when you have the advantage. We who negotiate it are the persons whom
                        it most concerns to obtain it, and we are persons whose arrangements, be
                        they what they will, our states will ratify. All we want is a disposition
                        not averse from peaceful counsels. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As far
                        as relates to myself, time, (for I am returning to that country an old man
                        which I left a boy,) and prosperity, and adversity, have so schooled me,
                        that I am more inclined to follow reason than fortune. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But I fear your youth and uninterrupted good fortune,
                        both of which are apt to inspire a degree of confidence ill comporting with
                        pacific counsels. Rarely does that man consider the uncertainty of events
                        whom fortune hath never deceived. What I was at Trasimenus, and at Cannae,
                        that you are this day. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Invested with
                        command when you had scarcely yet attained the military age, though all your
                        enterprises were of the boldest description, in no instance has fortune
                        deserted you. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Avenging the death of your
                        father and uncle, you have derived from the calamity of your house the high
                        honour of distinguished valour and filial duty. You have recovered Spain,
                        which had been lost, after driving thence four Carthaginian armies.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When elected consul, though all
                        others wanted courage to defend Italy, you crossed over into Africa; where
                        having cut to pieces two armies, having at once captured and burnt two camps
                        in the same hour; having made prisoner Syphax, a most powerful king, and
                        seized so many towns of his dominions and so many of ours, you have dragged
                        me from Italy, the possession of which I had firmly held for now sixteen
                        years. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Your mind, I say, may possibly be
                        more disposed to conquest than peace. I know the spirits of your country aim
                        rather at great than useful objects. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> On
                        me, too, a similar fortune once shone. But if with prosperity the gods would
                        also bestow upon us sound judgment, we should not only consider those things
                        which have happened, but those also which may occur. Even if you should
                        forget all others, I am myself a sufficient instance of every vicissitude of
                        fortune. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> For me, whom a little while ago
                        you saw advancing my standards to the walls of Rome, after pitching my camp
                        between the Anio and your city, you now behold here, bereft of my two
                        brothers, men of consummate bravery, and most renowned generals, standing
                        before the walls of my native <pb n="1321" xml:id="p.1321"/> city, which is
                        all but besieged, and deprecating, in behalf of my own city, those
                        severities with which I terrified yours. In all cases, the most prosperous
                        fortune is least to be depended upon. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                        While your affairs are in a favourable and ours in a dubious state, you
                        would derive honour and splendour from granting peace; while to us who
                        solicit it, it would be considered as necessary rather than honourable. A
                        certain peace is better and safer than a victory in prospect; the former is
                        at your own disposal, the latter depends upon the gods. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> Do not place at the hazard of a single hour the
                        successes of so many years. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> When you
                        consider your own strength, then also place before your view the power of
                        fortune, and the fluctuating nature of war. On both sides there will be
                        arms, on both sides human bodies. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> In
                        nothing less than in war do events correspond (with men's calculations).
                        Should you be victorious in a battle, you will not add so much to that
                        renown which you now have it in your power to acquire by granting peace, as
                        you will detract from it should any adverse event befall you. The chance of
                        a single hour may at once overturn the honours you have acquired and those
                        you anticipate. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> Every thing is at your
                        own disposal in adjusting a peace; but, in the other case, you must be
                        content with that fortune which the gods shall impose upon you. <milestone
                            n="23" unit="section"/> Formerly, in this same country, Marcus Atilius
                        would have formed one among the few instances of good fortune and valour,
                        if, when victorious, he had granted a peace to our fathers when they
                        requested it; but by not setting any bounds to his success, and not checking
                        good fortune, which was elating him, he fell with a degree of ignominy
                        proportioned to his elevation. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> It is
                        indeed the right of him who grants, and not of him who solicits it, to
                        dictate the terms of peace; but perhaps we may not be unworthy to impose
                        upon ourselves the fine. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> We do not refuse
                        that all those possessions on account of which the war was begun should be
                        yours; Sicily, Sardinia, Spain, with all the islands lying in any part of
                        the sea, between Africa and Italy. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> Let us
                        Carthaginians, confined within the shores of Africa, behold you, since such
                        is the pleasure of the gods, extending your empire over foreign nations,
                        both by sea and land. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> I cannot deny that
                        you have reason to suspect the Carthaginian faith, in consequence of their
                        insincerity lately in soliciting a peace and while awaiting the decision.
                            <pb n="1322" xml:id="p.1322"/> The sincerity with which a peace will be
                        observed, depends much, Scipio, on the person by whom it is sought.
                            <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> Your senate, as I hear, refused to
                        grant a peace in some measure because the deputies were deficient in
                        respectability. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/> It is I, Hannibal, who
                        now solicit peace; who would neither ask for it unless I believed it
                        expedient, nor will I fail to observe it for the same reason of expedience
                        on account of which I have solicited it. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                        And in the same manner as I, because the war was commenced by me, brought it
                        to pass that no one regretted it till the gods began to regard me with
                        displeasure; so will I also exert myself that no one may regret the peace
                        procured by my means. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In answer to these things the Roman general
                    spoke nearly to the following effect: <quote> I was aware that it was in
                        consequence of the expectation of your arrival, that the Carthaginians
                        violated the existing faith of the truce and broke off all hope of a peace.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nor, indeed, do you conceal the fact;
                        inasmuch as you artfully withdraw from the former conditions of peace every
                        concession except what relates to those things which have for a long time
                        been in our own power. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But as it is your
                        object, that your countrymen should be sensible how great a burden they are
                        relieved from by your means, so it is incumbent upon me to endeavour that
                        they may not receive, as the reward of their perfidy, the concessions which
                        they formerly stipulated, by expunging them now from the conditions of the
                        peace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Though you do not deserve to be
                        allowed the same conditions as before, you now request even to be benefited
                        by your treachery. Neither did our fathers first make war respecting Sicily,
                        nor did we respecting Spain. In the former case the danger which threatened
                        our allies the Mamertines, and in the present the destruction of Saguntum,
                        girded us with just and pious arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That
                        you were the aggressors, both you yourselves confess, and the gods are
                        witnesses, who determined the issue of the former war, and who are now
                        determining and will determine the issue of the present according to right
                        and justice. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As to myself, I am not
                        forgetful of the instability of human affairs, but consider the influence of
                        fortune, and am well aware that all our measures are liable to a thousand
                        casualties. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But as I should acknowledge
                        that my conduct would savour of insolence and oppression, if I rejected you
                        on your coming in person to solicit peace, be- <pb n="1323" xml:id="p.1323"
                        /> fore I crossed over into Africa, you voluntarily retiring from Italy, and
                        after you had embarked your troops; so now, when I have dragged you into
                        Africa almost by manual force, notwithstanding your resistance and evasions,
                        I am not bound to treat you with any respect. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Wherefore, if in addition to those stipulations on
                        which it was considered that a peace would at that time have been agreed
                        upon, and what they are you are informed, a compensation is proposed for
                        having seized our ships, together with their stores, during a truce, and for
                        the violence offered to our ambassadors, I shall then have matter to lay
                        before my council. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But if these things
                        also appear oppressive, prepare for war, since you could not brook the
                        conditions of peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus, without effecting an accommodation,
                    when they had returned from the conference to their armies, they informed them
                    that words had been bandied to no purpose, that the question must be decided by
                    arms, and that they must accept that fortune which the gods assigned them. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they had arrived at their camps, they
                    both issued orders that their soldiers should get their arms in readiness, and
                    prepare their minds for the final contest; in which, if fortune should favour
                    them, they would continue victorious, not for a single day, but for ever.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Before to-morrow night,</quote> they said, <quote> they would know
                        whether Rome or Carthage should give laws to the world; and that neither
                        Africa nor Italy, but the whole world, would be the prize of victory. That
                        the dangers which threatened those who had the misfortune to be defeated,
                        were proportioned to the rewards of the victors. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For the Romans had not any place of refuge in
                    an unknown and foreign land, and immediate destruction seemed to await Carthage,
                    if the troops which formed her last reliance were defeated. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> To this important contest, the day following, two generals,
                    by far the most renowned of any, and belonging to two of the most powerful
                    nations in the world, advanced, either to crown or overthrow, on that day, the
                    many honours they had previously acquired. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Their minds, therefore, were agitated with the opposite feelings of hope and
                    fear; and while they contemplated at one time their own troops, at another those
                    of their enemy, estimating their powers more by sight than by reason, they saw
                    in them at once the grounds for joy and grief. <pb n="1324" xml:id="p.1324"/>
                    Those circumstances which did not occur to the troops themselves spontaneously,
                    their generals suggested by their admonitions and exhortations. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Carthaginian recounted his achievements in the land of
                    Italy during sixteen years, the many Roman generals and armies annihilated,
                    reminding each individually of the honours he had acquired as he came to any
                    soldier who had obtained distinction in any of his battles. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Scipio referred to Spain, the recent battles in Africa, and
                    the enemy's own confession, that they could not through fear but solicit peace,
                    nor could they, through their inveterate perfidy, abide by it. In addition to
                    this he gave what turn he pleased to his conference with Hannibal, which was
                    held in private, and was therefore open to misrepresentation. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> He augured success that the gods had exhibited the same
                    omens to them on going out to battle on the present occasion, as they had to
                    their fathers when they fought at the islands Aegates. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He told them that the termination of the war, and their
                    hardships, had arrived; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> that they had within
                    their grasp the spoils of Carthage, and the power of returning home to their
                    country, their parents, their children, their wives, and their household gods.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He delivered these observations with a
                    body so erect, and with a countenance so full of exultation, that one would have
                    supposed that he had already conquered. He then drew up his troops, posting the
                    hastati in front, the principes behind them, and closing his rear line with the
                    triarii. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He did not draw up his cohorts in close order,
                    but each before their respective standards; placing the companies at some
                    distance from each other, so as to leave a space through which the elephants of
                    the enemy passing might not at all break their ranks. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Laelius, whom he had employed before as lieutenant-general,
                    but this year as quaestor, by special appointment, according to a decree of the
                    senate, he posted with the Italian cavalry in the left wing, Masinissa and the
                    Numidians in the right. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The open spaces
                    between the companies of those in the van he filled with velites, which then
                    formed the Roman light-armed troops, with an injunction, that on the charge of
                    the elephants they should either retire behind the files, which extended in a
                    right line, or, running to the right and left and placing themselves by the side
                    of those in the van, afford a psssage by which the elephants <pb n="1325"
                        xml:id="p.1325"/> might rush in between weapons on both sides. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Hannibal, in order to terrify the enemy, drew up his
                    elephants in front, and he had eighty of them, being more than he had ever had
                    in any battle; behind these his Ligurian and Gallic auxiliaries, with Balearians
                    and Moors intermixed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the second line he
                    placed the Carthaginians, Africans, and a legion of Macedonians; <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> then, leaving a moderate interval, he formed a
                    reserve of Italian troops, consisting principally of Bruttians, more of whom had
                    followed him on his departure from Italy by compulsion and necessity than by
                    choice. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His cavalry also he placed in the
                    wings, the Carthaginian occupying the right, the Numidian the left. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Various were the means of exhortation employed in an
                    army consisting of a mixture of so many different kinds of men; men differing in
                    language, customs, laws, arms, dress, and appearance, and in the motives for
                    serving. To the auxiliaries, the prospect both of their present pay, and many
                    times more from the spoils, was held out. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    Gauls were stimulated by their peculiar and inherent animosity against the
                    Romans. To the Ligurians the hope was held out of enjoying the fertile plains of
                    Italy, and quitting their rugged mountains, if victorious. The Moors and
                    Numidians were terrified with subjection to the government of Masinissa, which
                    he would exercise with despotic severity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Different grounds of hope and fear were represented to different persons.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The view of the Carthaginians was
                    directed to the walls of their city, their household gods, the sepulchres of
                    their ancestors, their children and parents, and their trembling wives; they
                    were told, that either the destruction of their city and slavery or the empire
                    of the world awaited them; that there was nothing intermediate which they could
                    hope for or fear. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> While the general was thus
                    busily employed among the Carthaginians, and the captains of the respective
                    nations among their countrymen, most of them employing interpreters among troops
                    intermixed with those of different nations, the trumpets and cornets of the
                    Romans sounded; and such a clamour arose, that the elephants, especially those
                    in the left wing, turned round upon their own party, the Moors and Numidians.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Masinissa had no difficulty in increasing
                    the alarm of the terrified enemy, and deprived them of the aid of their cavalry
                    in that wing. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> A few, however, of the beasts
                    which were driven against the <pb n="1326" xml:id="p.1326"/> enemy, and were not
                    turned back through fear, made great havoc among the ranks of the velites,
                    though not without receiving many wounds themselves; <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> for when the velites, retiring to the companies, had made
                    way for the elephants, that they might not be trampled down, they discharged
                    their darts at them, exposed as they were to wounds on both sides, those in the
                    van also keeping up a continual discharge of javelins; until, driven out of the
                    Roman line by the weapons which fell upon them from all quarters, these
                    elephants also put to flight even the cavalry of the Carthaginians posted in
                    their right wing. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Laelius, when he saw the
                    enemy in disorder, struck additional terror into them in their confusion. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian line was deprived of the
                    cavalry on both sides, when the infantry, who were now not a match for the
                    Romans in confidence or strength, engaged. In addition to this there was one
                    circumstance, trifling in itself, but at the same time producing important
                    consequences in the action. On the part of the Romans the shout was uniform, and
                    on that account louder and more terrific; while the voices of the enemy,
                    consisting as they did of many nations of different languages, were dissonant.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans used the stationary kind of
                    fight, pressing upon the enemy with their own weight and that of their arms; but
                    on the other side there was more of skirmishing and rapid movement than force.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, on the first charge, the
                    Romans immediately drove back the line of their opponents; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> then pushing them with their elbows and the bosses of their
                    shields, and pressing forward into the places from which they had pushed them,
                    they advanced a considerable space, as though there had been no one to resist
                    them, those who formed the rear urging forward those in front when they
                    perceived the line of the enemy giving way; which circumstance itself gave great
                    additional force in repelling them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the
                    side of the enemy, the second line, consisting of the Africans and
                    Carthaginians, were so far from supporting the first line when giving ground,
                    that, on the contrary, they even retired, lest their enemy, by slaying those who
                    made a firm resistance, should penetrate to themselves also. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, the auxiliaries suddenly turned their backs,
                    and facing about upon their own party, fled, some of them into the second line,
                    while others slew <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> those who did not receive
                    them into their ranks, since before they did not <pb n="1327" xml:id="p.1327"/>
                    support them, and now refused to receive them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    And now there were, in a manner, two contests going on together, the
                    Carthaginians being compelled to fight at once with the enemy and with their own
                    party. Not even then, however, did they receive into their line the terrified
                    and exasperated troops; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but, closing their
                    ranks, drove them out of the scene of action to the wings and the surrounding
                    plain, lest they should mingle these soldiers, terrified with defeat and wounds,
                    with that part of their line which was firm and fresh. But such a heap of men
                    and arms had filled the space in which the auxiliaries a little while ago had
                    stood, that it was almost more difficult to pass through it than through a close
                    line of troops. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The spearmen, therefore, who
                    formed the front line, pursuing the enemy as each could find a way through the
                    heap of arms and men, and streams of blood, threw into complete disorder the
                    battalions and companies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The standards also
                    of the principes had begun to waver when they saw the line before them driven
                    from their ground. Scipio, perceiving this, promptly ordered the signal to be
                    given for the spearmen to retreat, and, having taken his wounded into the rear,
                    brought the principes and triarii to the wings, in order that the line of
                    spearmen in the centre might be more strong and secure. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Thus a fresh and renewed battle commenced, inasmuch as they
                    had penetrated to their real antagonists, men equal to them in the nature of
                    their arms, in their experience in war, in the fame of their achievements, and
                    the greatness of their hopes and fears. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But
                    the Romans were superior both in numbers and courage, for they had now routed
                    both the cavalry and the elephants, and having already defeated the front line,
                    were fighting against the second. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laelius and Masinissa, who had pursued the
                    routed cavalry through a considerable space, returning very opportunely, charged
                    the rear of the enemy's line. This attack of the cavalry at length routed them.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Many of them, being surrounded, were slain
                    in the field; and many, dispersed in flight through the open plain around, were
                    slain on all hands, as the cavalry were in possession of every part. Of the
                    Carthaginians and their allies, above twenty thousand were slain on that day;
                    about an equal number were captured, with a hundred and thirty-three military
                    standards, and eleven elephants. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of the
                    victors as many as two thousand fell. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Han- <pb
                        n="1328" xml:id="p.1328"/> nibal, slipping off during the confusion, with a
                    few horsemen, came to Adrumetum, not quitting the field till he had tried every
                    expedient both in the battle and before the engagement; having, according to the
                    admission of Scipio, and every one skilled in military science, acquired the
                    fame of having marshalled his troops on that day with singular judgment.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He placed his elephants in the front, in
                    order that their desultory attack, and insupportable violence, might prevent the
                    Romans from following their standards, and preserving their ranks, on which they
                    placed their principal dependence. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then he
                    posted his auxiliaries before the line of Carthaginians, in order that men who
                    were made up of the refuse <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of all nations,
                    and who were not bound by honour but by gain, might not have any retreat open to
                    them in case they fled; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> at the same time that
                    the first ardour and impetuosity might be exhausted upon them, and, if they
                    could render no other service, that the weapons of the enemy might be blunted in
                    wounding them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Next he placed the Carthaginian
                    and African soldiers, on whom he placed all his hopes, in order that, being
                    equal to the enemy in every other respect, they might have the advantage of
                    them, inasmuch as, being fresh and unimpaired in strength themselves, they would
                    fight with those who were fatigued and wounded. The Italians he removed into the
                    rear, separating them also by an intervening space, as he knew not, with
                    certainty, whether they were friends or enemies. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Hannibal, after performing this as it were his last work of
                    valour, fled to Adrumetum, whence, having been summoned to Carthage, he returned
                    thither in the six and thirtieth year after he had left it when a boy;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and confessed in the senate-house that he
                    was defeated, not only in the battle, but in the war, and that there was no hope
                    of safety in any thing but in obtaining peace. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately after the battle, Scipio, having
                    taken and plundered the enemy's camp, returned to the sea and his ships, with an
                    immense booty, news having reached <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> him that
                    Publius Lentulus had arrived at Utica with fifty men of war, and a hundred
                    transports laden with every kind of stores. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Concluding that he ought to bring before Carthage every thing which could
                    increase the consternation already existing there, after sending Laelius to Rome
                    to report his victory, he ordered Cneius Octavius to conduct the legions thither
                    by land; and, setting out himself from Utica with the fresh fleet of Lentulus,
                        <pb n="1329" xml:id="p.1329"/> added to his former one, made for the harbour
                    of Carthage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When he had arrived within a
                    short distance, he was met by a Carthaginian ship decked with fillets and
                    branches of olive. There were ten deputies, the leading men in the state, sent
                    at the instance of Hannibal to solicit peace; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    to whom, when they had come up to the stern of the general's ship, holding out
                    the badges of suppliants, entreating and imploring the protection and compassion
                    of Scipio, the only answer given was, that they must come to Tunes, to which
                    place he would move his camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After taking a
                    view of the site of Carthage, not so much for the sake of acquainting himself
                    with it for any present object, as to dispirit the enemy, he returned to Utica,
                    having recalled Octavius to the same place. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As
                    they were proceeding thence to Tunes, they received intelligence that Vermina,
                    the son of Syphax, with a greater number of horse than foot, was coming to the
                    assistance of the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A part of his
                    infantry, with all the cavalry, having attacked them on their march on the first
                    day of the Saturnalia, routed the Numidians with little opposition; and as every
                    way by which they could escape in flight was blocked up, for the cavalry
                    surrounded them on all sides, fifteen thousand men were slain, twelve hundred
                    were taken alive, with fifteen hundred Numidian horses, and seventy-two military
                    standards. The prince himself fled from the field with a few attendants during
                    the confusion. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The camp was then pitched near
                    Tunes in the same place as before, and thirty ambassadors came to Scipio from
                    Carthage. These behaved in a manner even more calculated to excite compassion
                    than the former, in proportion as their situation was more pressing; but from
                    the recollection of their recent perfidy, they were heard with considerably less
                    pity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the council, though all were
                    impelled by just resentment to demolish Carthage, yet, when they reflected upon
                    the magnitude of the undertaking, and the length of time which would be consumed
                    in the siege of so well fortified and strong a city, while Scipio himself was
                    uneasy in <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> consequence of the expectation of
                    a successor, who would come in for the glory of having terminated the war,
                    though it was accomplished already by the exertions and danger of another, the
                    minds of all were inclined to peace. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day the ambassadors being called in
                    again, and, with many rebukes for their perfidy, warned that, in- <pb n="1330"
                        xml:id="p.1330"/> structed by so many disasters, they would at length
                    believe in the existence of the gods, and the obligation of an oath, these
                    conditions of the peace were stated to them: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That they should enjoy their liberty and live under their own laws; that
                        they should possess such cities and territories as they had enjoyed before
                        the war, and with the same boundaries, and that the Romans should on that
                        day desist from devastation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That they
                        should restore to the Romans all deserters and fugitives, giving up all
                        their ships of war except ten triremes, with such tamed elephants as they
                        had, and that they should not tame any more. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> That they should not carry on war in or out of Africa without the
                        permission of the Roman people. That they should make restitution to
                        Masinissa, and form a league with him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        That they should furnish corn, and pay for the auxiliaries until the
                        ambassadors had returned from Rome. That they should pay ten thousand
                        talents of silver, in equal annual instalments distributed over fifty years.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That they should give a hundred
                        hostages, according to the pleasure of Scipio, not younger than fourteen nor
                        older than thirty. That he would grant them a truce on condition that the
                        transports, together with their cargoes, which had been seized during the
                        former truce, were restored. Otherwise they would have no truce, nor any
                        hope of a peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the ambassadors who were ordered to bear
                    these conditions home reported them in an assembly, and Gisgo had stood forth to
                    dissuade them from the terms, and was being listened to by the multitude, who
                    were at once indisposed for peace and unfit for war, Hannibal, indignant that
                    such language should <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> be held and listened to
                    at such a juncture, laid hold of Gisgo with his own hand, and dragged him from
                    his elevated position. This unusual sight in a free state having raised a murmur
                    among the people, the soldier, disconcerted at the liberties which the citizens
                    took, thus addressed them: <quote> Having left you when nine years old, I have
                        returned after a lapse of thirty-six years. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> I flatter myself I am well acquainted with the qualifications of a
                        soldier, having been instructed in them from my childhood, sometimes by my
                        own situation, and sometimes by that of my country. The privileges, the
                        laws, and customs of the city and the forum you ought to teach me. </quote>
                    Having thus apologized for his indiscretion, he discoursed largely concerning
                    the peace, showing how inoppressive the <pb n="1331" xml:id="p.1331"/> terms
                    were, and how necessary it was. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The greatest
                    difficulty was, that of the ships which had been seized during the truce nothing
                    was to be found except the ships themselves: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    nor was it easy to collect the property, because those who were charged with
                    having it were opposed to the peace. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It was
                    resolved that the ships should be restored, and that the men at least should be
                    looked up; and as to whatever else was missing, that it should be left to Scipio
                    to put a value upon it, and that the Carthaginians should make compensation
                    accordingly in money. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There are those who say
                    that Hannibal went from the field of battle to the sea-coast; whence he
                    immediately sailed in a ship, which he had ready for the purpose, to king
                    Antiochus; and that when Scipio demanded above every thing that Hannibal should
                    be given up to him, answer was made that Hannibal was not in Africa. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the ambassadors returned to Scipio, the
                    quaestors were ordered to give in an account, made out from the public
                    registers, of the public property which had been in the ships; and the owners to
                    make a return of the private property. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the
                    amount of the value twenty-five thousand pounds of silver were required to be
                    paid down; and a truce for three months was granted to the Carthaginians.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was added, that during the time of the
                    truce they should not send ambassadors any where else than to Rome; and that,
                    whatever ambassadors came to Carthage, they should not dismiss them before
                    informing the Roman general who they were, and what they sought. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> With the Carthaginian ambassadors, Lucius Veturius
                    Philo, Marcus Marcius Ralla, and Lucius Scipio, brother of the general, were
                    sent to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the time in which these
                    events took place, the supplies sent from Sicily and Sardinia produced such
                    cheapness of provisions, that the merchant gave up the corn to the mariners for
                    their freight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At Rome alarm was excited at
                    the first intelligence of the renewal of hostilities by the Carthaginians; and
                    Tiberius Claudius was directed to conduct the fleet with speed into Sicily, and
                    cross over from that place into Africa. The other consul, Marcus Servilius, was
                    directed to stay at the city until the state of affairs in Africa was
                    ascertained. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Tiberius Claudius, the consul,
                    proceeded slowly with every thing connected with the equipment and sailing of
                    the fleet, because the senate had decided that it should be left to Scipio,
                    rather than to the consul, to determine <pb n="1332" xml:id="p.1332"/> the
                    conditions on which the peace should be granted. The accounts also of prodigies
                    which arrived just at the time of the news of the revival of the war, had
                    occasioned great alarm. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At Cumae the orb of
                    the sun seemed diminished, and a shower of stones fell; and in the territory of
                    Veliternum the earth sank in great chasms, and trees were swallowed up in the
                    cavities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At Aricia the forum and the shops
                    around it, at Frusino a wall in several places, and a gate, were struck by
                    lightning; and in the Palatium a shower of stones fell. The latter prodigy,
                    according to the custom handed down by tradition, was expiated by a nine days'
                    sacred rite; the rest with victims of the larger sort. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Amid these events an unusually great rising of the waters
                    was converted into a prodigy; for the Tiber overflowed its banks to such a
                    degree, that as the circus was under water, the Apollinarian games were got up
                    near the temple of Venus Erycina, without the Colline gate. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> However, the weather suddenly clearing up on the very day
                    of the celebration, the procession, which had begun to move at the Colline gate,
                    was recalled and transferred to the circus, on its being known that the water
                    had retired thence. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The joy of the people and
                    the attraction of the games were increased by the restoration of this solemn
                    spectacle to its proper scene. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul Claudius, having set out at length
                    from the city, was placed in the most imminent danger by a violent tempest,
                    which overtook him between the ports of Cosa and Laurentum. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Having reached Populonii, where he waited till the
                    remainder of the tempest had spent itself, he crossed over to the island Ilva.
                    From Ilva he went to Corsica, and from Corsica to Sardinia. Here, while sailing
                    round the Montes Insani, a tempest much more violent in itself, and in a more
                    dangerous situation, dispersed his fleet. Many of his ships were shattered and
                    stripped of their rigging, and some were wrecked. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> His fleet thus weather beaten and shattered arrived at
                    Carales, where the winter came on while the ships were drawn on shore and
                    refitted. The year having elapsed, and no one proposing to continue him in
                    command, Tiberius Claudius brought back his fleet to Rome in a private capacity.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Marcus Servilius set out for his province,
                    having nominated Caius Servilius Geminus as dictator, that he might not be
                    recalled to the city to hold the elections. The dictator ap- <pb n="1333"
                        xml:id="p.1333"/> pointed Publius Aelius Paetus master of the horse.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It frequently happened, that the elections
                    could not be held on account of bad weather, though the days were fixed for
                    them; and, therefore, as the magistrates of the former year retired from their
                    offices on the day before the ides of March, and fresh ones were not appointed
                    to succeed them, the state was without curule magistrates. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Manlius Torquatus, a pontiff, died this year. Caius
                    Sulpicius Galba was elected in his room. The Roman games were thrice repeated by
                    the curule aediles, Lucius Licinius Lucullus and Quintus Fulvius. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Some scribes and runners belonging to the aediles
                    were found, on the testimony of an informer, to have privately conveyed money
                    out of the treasury, and were condemned, not without disgrace to the aedile
                    Lucullus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Publius Aelius Tubero and Lucius
                    Laetorius, plebeian aediles, on account of some informality in their creation,
                    abdicated their office, after having celebrated the games, and the banquet on
                    occasion of the games, in honour of Jupiter, and after having placed in the
                    Capitol three statues made out of silver paid as fines. The dictator and master
                    of the horse celebrated the games in honour of Ceres, in conformity with a
                    decree of the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman, together with the Carthaginian
                    ambassadors, having arrived at Rome from Africa, the senate was assembled at the
                    temple of Bellona; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> when Lucius Veturius Philo
                    stated, to the great joy of the senate, that a battle had been fought with
                    Hannibal, which was decisive of the fate of the Carthaginians, and that a period
                    was at length put to that calamitous war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                    added what formed a small accession to their successes, that Vermina, the son of
                    Syphax, had been vanquished. He was then ordered to go forth to the public
                    assembly, and impart the joyful tidings to the people. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then, a thanksgiving having been appointed, all the temples
                    in the city were thrown open, and supplications for three days were decreed. The
                    ambassadors of the Carthaginians, and those of king Philip, for they also had
                    arrived, requesting an audience of the senate, answer was made by the dictator,
                    by order of the fathers, that the new consuls would give them an audience. The
                    elections were then held. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls elected
                    were Cneius Cornelius Lentulus and Publius Aelius Paetus. The praetors elected
                    were Marcus Junius Pennus, to whose lot the city jurisdiction fell, Marcus
                    Valerius Falto, who re- <pb n="1334" xml:id="p.1334"/> ceived Bruttium, Marcus
                    Fabius Buteo, who received Sardinia, and Publius Aelius Tubero, who received
                    Sicily. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was the pleasure of the senate that
                    nothing should be done respecting the provinces of the consuls, till the
                    ambassadors of king Philip and the Carthaginians had been heard; for they
                    foresaw the termination of one war and the commencement of another. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Cneius Lentulus, the consul, was inflamed with a
                    strong desire to have the province of Africa, looking forward to an easy victory
                    if there was still war, or, if it was on the point of being concluded, to the
                    glory of having it terminated in his consulate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> He therefore refused to allow any business to be transacted before the
                    province of Africa was assigned him; his colleague, who was a moderate and
                    prudent man, giving up his claim to it, for he clearly saw that a contest with
                    Scipio for that honour would be not only unjust but unequal. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Minucius Thermus, and Manius Acilius Glabrio,
                    tribunes of the people, said that Cneius Cornelius was endeavouring to effect
                    the same object which had been attempted in vain by the consul Tiberius Claudius
                    the former year. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That, by the direction of
                    the senate, it had been proposed to the people to decide whom they wished to
                    have the command in Africa, and all the thirty-five tribes had concurred in
                    assigning that command to Publius Scipio. After many discussions, both in the
                    senate and popular assembly, it was at length determined to leave it to the
                    senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The fathers, therefore, on oath, for
                    so it had been agreed, voted, that as to the provinces, <milestone n="12??"
                        unit="section"/> the consuls should settle between them- selves, or
                    determine by lots, which of them should have Italy, and which a fleet of fifty
                    ships. That he to whose lot the fleet fell should sail to Sicily, and if peace
                    could not be concluded with the Carthaginians, that he should cross over into
                    Africa. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That the consul should act by sea,
                    and Scipio by land, with the same right of command as heretofore. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> If an agreement should be come to, as to the terms
                    of the peace, that then the plebeian tribunes should consult the commons as to
                    whether they ordered the consul or Publius Scipio to grant the peace; and if the
                    victorious army was to be brought home out of Africa, whom they ordered to bring
                    it. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> That if they ordered that the peace
                    should be granted by Publius Scipio, and that the army should be brought home
                    likewise by him, then the consul should not pass out of Sicily into <pb n="1335"
                        xml:id="p.1335"/> Africa. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> That the other
                    consul, to whose lot Italy fell, should receive two legions from Marcus Sextius
                    the praetor. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Publius Scipio was continued in command in the
                    province of Africa, with the armies which he then had. To the praetor Marcus
                    Valerius Falto the two legions in Bruttium, which Caius Livius had commanded the
                    preceding year, were assigned. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Publius Aelius,
                    the praetor, was to receive two legions in Sicily from Cneius Tremellius. To
                    Marcus Fabius was assigned one legion, which Publius Lentulus, propraetor, had
                    commanded, to be employed in Sardinia; Marcus Servilius, the consul of the
                    former year, was continued in command in Etruria, with his own two legions
                    likewise. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As to Spain, it appeared that Lucius
                    Cornelius Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus had been there for now several
                    years. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was resolved, therefore, that the
                    consuls should make application to the plebeian tribunes to take the opinion of
                    the people, if they thought proper, as to whom they ordered to have command in
                    Spain; that the person so ordered should form one legion of Roman soldiers out
                    of the two armies, and also fifteen cohorts of the allies of the Latin
                    confederacy, with which he should occupy the province. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> That Lucius Cornelius Lentulus and Lucius Manlius Acidinus
                    should convey the old soldiers into Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To
                    Cornelius, the consul, was assigned a fleet of fifty ships formed out of the two
                    fleets, one of which was under Cneius Octavius in Africa, the other employed in
                    protecting the coast of Sicily, under Publius Villius. He was to select such
                    ships as he pleased. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That Publius Scipio
                    should still have the forty ships of war which he before had, or if he wished
                    that Cneius Octavius should command it, as he had commanded a fleet there
                    before, that Octavius should be continued in command for a year as propraetor;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but if he appointed Laelius to the command
                    of it, Octavius should retire to Rome, and bring with him the ships which the
                    consul did not want. To Marcus Fabius also ten men of war were assigned for
                    Sardinia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consuls were directed to enlist
                    two city legions, so that the operations of the state might be carried on this
                    year with fourteen legions, and one hundred men of war. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the business relating to the ambassadors
                    of Philip and the Carthaginians was considered. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> It was resolved that the Macedonians should be brought before the senate
                    first. <pb n="1336" xml:id="p.1336"/> Their address comprehended a variety of
                    subjects, being employed partly in clearing themselves from the charges relative
                    to the depredations committed against the allies, which the deputies sent to the
                    king from Rome had brought against them; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and
                    partly in preferring accusations themselves against the allies of the Roman
                    people, but particularly against Marcus Aurelius, whom they inveighed against
                    with much greater acrimony; for they said that, being one of the three
                    ambassadors sent to them, he had staid behind, and levying soldiers, had
                    assailed them with hostilities contrary to the league, and frequently fought
                    pitched battles with their prefects; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and
                    partly in preferring a request that the Macedonians and their general, Sopater,
                    who had served in the army of Hannibal for hire, and having been made prisoners
                    were kept in bondage, should be restored to them. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> In opposition to these things, Marcus Furius, who had been
                    sent from Macedonia for the express purpose by Aurelius, thus argued: he said,
                        <quote> that Aurelius, having been left behind, lest the allies of the Roman
                        people, wearied by devastations and injuries, should revolt to the king, had
                        not gone beyond the boundaries of the allies; but had taken measures to
                        prevent plundering parties from crossing over into their lands with
                        impunity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That Sopater was one of those
                        who wore purple, and was related to the king; that he had been lately sent
                        into Africa with four thousand Macedonians and a sum of money to assist
                        Hannibal and the Carthaginians. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Macedonians, on being interrogated on
                    these points, proceeded to answer in a subtle and evasive manner; but without
                    waiting for the conclusion of their reply they were told, <quote> that the king
                        was seeking occasion for war, and that if he persisted he would soon obtain
                        his object. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That the treaty had been
                        doubly violated by him, both by offering insults to the allies of the Roman
                        people, by assaulting them with hostilities and arms, and also by aiding
                        their enemies with auxiliaries and money. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        That Publius Scipio was deemed to have acted properly and regularly in
                        keeping in chains, as enemies, those who had been made prisoners while
                        bearing arms against the Romans; and that Marcus Aurelius had consulted the
                        interest of the state, and the senate were thankful to him for it, in
                        protecting the allies <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> of the Roman
                        people by arms, since he could not do it by the obligation of the treaty.
                    </quote> The Macedonian ambassadors having been dismissed with this <pb n="1337"
                        xml:id="p.1337"/> unpleasant answer, the Carthaginian ambassadors were
                    called. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On observing their ages and dignified
                    appearance, for they were by far the first men of the state, all promptly
                    declared their conviction, that now they were sincere in their desire to effect
                    a peace. Hasdrubal, however, surnamed by his countrymen Haedus, who had
                    invariably recommended peace, and was opposed to the Barcine faction, was
                    regarded with greater interest than the rest. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    On these accounts the greater weight was attached to him when transferring the
                    blame of the war from the state at large to the cupidity of a few. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> After a speech of varied character, in which he
                    sometimes refuted the charges which had been brought, at other times admitted
                    some, lest by impudently denying what was manifestly true their forgiveness
                    might be the more difficult; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and then, even
                    admonishing the conscript fathers to be guided by the rules of decorum and
                    moderation in their prosperity, he said, that if the Carthaginians had listened
                    to himself and Hanno, and had been disposed to make a proper use of
                    circumstances, they would themselves have dictated terms of peace, instead of
                    begging it as they now did. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> That it rarely
                    happened that good fortune and a sound judgment were bestowed upon men at the
                    same time. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> That the Roman people were
                    therefore invincible, because when successful they forgot not the maxims of
                    wisdom and prudence; and indeed it would have been matter of astonishment did
                    they act otherwise. That those persons to whom success was a new and uncommon
                    thing, proceeded to a pitch of madness in their ungoverned transports in
                    consequence of their not being accustomed to it. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> That to the Roman people the joy arising from victory was a
                    matter of common occurrence, and was now almost become old-fashioned. That they
                    had extended their empire more by sparing the vanquished than by conquering. The
                    language employed by the others was of a nature more calculated to excite
                    compassion; they represented from what a height of power the Carthaginian
                    affairs had fallen. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> That nothing, besides the
                    walls of Carthage, remained to those who a little time ago held almost the whole
                    world in subjection by their arms; that, shut up within these, they could see
                    nothing any where on sea or land which owned their authority. <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/> That they would retain possession of their city itself and
                    their household gods only, in case the Roman people should refrain <pb n="1338"
                        xml:id="p.1338"/> from venting their indignation upon these, which is all
                    that remains for them to do. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> When it was
                    manifest that the fathers were moved by compassion, it is said that one of the
                    senators, violently incensed at the perfidy of the Carthaginians, immediately
                    asked with a loud voice, by what gods they would swear in striking the league,
                    since they had broken their faith with those by whom they swore in striking the
                    former one? <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> By those same, replied Hasdrubal,
                    who have shown such determined hostility to the violators of treaties. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The minds of all being disposed to peace,
                    Cneius Lentulus, whose province the fleet was, protested against the decree of
                    the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Upon this, Manius Acilius and
                    Quintus Minucius, tribunes of the people, put the question to the people,
                    whether they willed and ordered that the senate should decree that peace should
                    be made with the Carthaginians? whom they ordered to grant that peace, and whom
                    to conduct the army out of Africa? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All the
                    tribes ordered respecting the peace according as the question had been put. That
                    Publius Scipio should grant the peace, and that he also should conduct the army
                    home. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Agreeably to this order, the senate
                    decreed that Publius Scipio, acting according to the opinion of the ten
                    deputies, should make peace with the Carthaginian people on what terms he
                    pleased. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians then returned
                    thanks to the senate, and requested that they might be allowed to enter the city
                    and converse with their countrymen who had been made prisoners and were in
                    custody of the state; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> observing, that some of
                    them were their relations and friends, and men of rank, and some, persons to
                    whom they were charged with messages from their relations. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Having obtained these requests, they again asked permission
                    to ransom such of them as they pleased; when they were desired to give in their
                    names. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Having given in a list of about two
                    hundred, a decree of the senate was passed to the effect, that the Carthaginian
                    ambassadors should be allowed to take away into Africa to Publius Cornelius
                    Scipio two hundred of the Carthaginian prisoners, selecting whom they pleased;
                    and that they should convey to him a message, that if the peace were concluded,
                    he should restore them to the Carthaginians without ransom. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The heralds being ordered to go into Africa to strike the
                    league, at their own desire the senate passed a decree that they should take
                    with them flint stones of their <pb n="1339" xml:id="p.1339"/> own, and vervain
                    of their own; that the Roman praetor should command them to strike the league,
                    and that they should demand of him herbs. The description of herb usually given
                    to the heralds is taken from the Capitol. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Thus the Carthaginians, being allowed to depart from Rome, when they had gone
                    into Africa to Scipio concluded the peace on the terms before mentioned.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They delivered up their men-of-war, their
                    elephants, deserters, fugitives, and four thousand prisoners, among whom was
                    Quintus Terentius Culleo, a senator. The ships he ordered to be taken out into
                    the main and burnt. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some say there were five
                    hundred of every description of those which are worked with oars, and that the
                    sudden sight of these, when burning, occasioned as deep a sensation of grief to
                    the Carthaginians as if Carthage had been in flames. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The measures adopted respecting the deserters were more
                    severe than those respecting the fugitives. Those who were of the Latin
                    confederacy were decapitated; the Romans were crucified. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The last peace with the Carthaginians was made
                    forty years before this, in the consulate of Quintus Lutatius and Aulus Manlius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The war commenced twenty-three years
                    afterwards, in the consulate of Publius Cornelius and Tiberius Sempronius. It
                    was concluded in the seventeenth year, in the consulate of Cneius Cornelius and
                    Publius Aelius Paetus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is related that
                    Scipio frequently said afterwards, that first the ambition of Tiberius Claudius,
                    and afterwards of Cneius Cornelius, were the causes which prevented his
                    terminating the war by the destruction of Carthage. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Carthaginians, finding difficulty in raising the first
                    sum of money to be paid, as their finances were exhausted by a protracted war,
                    and in consequence great lamentation and grief arising in the senate-house, it
                    is said that Hannibal was observed laughing; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and when Hasdrubal Haedus rebuked him for laughing amid the public grief, when
                    he himself was the occasion of the tears which were shed, he said: <quote> If,
                        as the expression of the countenance is discerned by the sight, so the
                        inward feelings of the mind could be distinguished, it would clearly appear
                        to you that that laughter which you censure came from a heart not elated
                        with joy, but frantic with misfortunes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        And yet it is not so ill-timed as those absurd and inconsistent tears of
                        yours. Then you ought to have wept, when our arms were taken <pb n="1340"
                            xml:id="p.1340"/> from us, our ships burnt, and we were forbidden to
                        engage in foreign wars, for that was the wound by which we fell. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Nor is it just that you should suppose that the
                        measures which the Romans have adopted towards you have been dictated by
                        animosity. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> No great state can remain at
                        rest long together. If it has no enemy abroad it finds one at home, in the
                        same manner as over-robust bodies seem secure from external causes, but are
                        encumbered with their own strength. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So
                        far, forsooth, we are affected with the public calamities as they reach our
                        private affairs; nor is there any circumstance attending them which is felt
                        more acutely than the loss of money. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Accordingly, when the spoils were torn down from vanquished Carthage, when
                        you beheld her left unarmed and defenseless amid so many armed nations of
                        Africa, none heaved a sigh. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Now, because
                        a tribute is to be levied from private property, you lament with one accord,
                        as though at the funeral of the state. How much do I dread lest you should
                        soon be made sensible that you have shed tears this day for the lightest of
                        your misfortunes! </quote> Such were the sentiments which Hannibal delivered
                    to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Scipio, having summoned
                    an assembly, presented Masinissa, in addition to his paternal dominions, with
                    the town of Cirta, and the other cities and territories which had passed from
                    the kingdom of Syphax into the possession of the Romans. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> He ordered Cneius Octavius to conduct the fleet to Sicily
                    and deliver it to Cneius Cornelius the consul, and directed the Carthaginian
                    ambassadors to go to Rome, that the arrangements he had made, with the advice of
                    the ten deputies, might be ratified by the sanction of the fathers and the order
                    of the people. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Peace having been established by sea and land,
                    he embarked his troops and crossed over to Lilybaeum in Sicily; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> whence, having sent a great part of his soldiers by ships,
                    he himself proceeded through Italy, which was rejoicing, not less on account of
                    the peace than the victory; while not only the inhabitants of the cities poured
                    out to show him honour, but crowds of rustics thronged the roads. He arrived at
                    Rome and entered the city in a triumph of unparalleled splendour. He brought
                    into the treasury one hundred and twenty-three thousand pounds of silver.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He distributed to each of his soldiers
                    four hundred <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> out of the spoils. By the death of
                        <pb n="1341" xml:id="p.1341"/> Syphax, which took place but a short time
                    before at Tibur, whither he had been removed from Alba, a diminution was
                    occasioned in the interest of the pageant rather than in the glory of him who
                    triumphed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His death, however, was attended
                    with circumstances which produced a strong sensation, for he was buried at the
                    public expense. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Polybius, an author by no
                    means to be despised, asserts that this king was led in the triumph. Quintus
                    Terentius Culleo followed Scipio in his triumph with a cap of liberty on his
                    head, and during the remainder of his life treated him with the respect due to
                    him as the author of his freedom. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I have not
                    been able to ascertain whether the partiality of the soldiers or the favour of
                    the people fixed upon him the surname of Africanus, or whether in the same
                    manner as Felix was applied to Sulla, and Magnus to Pompey, in the memory of our
                    fathers, it originated in the flattery of his friends. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He was, doubtless, the first general who was distinguished
                    by a name derived from the nation which he had conquered. Afterwards, in
                    imitation of his example, some, by no means his equals in his victories, affixed
                    splendid inscriptions on their statues and gave honourable surnames to their
                    families. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
