<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 30</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="book">
                <head>Close of the Hannibalic War</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now the sixteenth year of the Punic
                        War. The new consuls, Cnaeus Servilius and Caius Servilius, laid before the
                        senate the questions of the general policy of the republic, the conduct of
                        the war and the assignment of the provinces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> It was resolved that the consuls should come to an arrangement, or
                        failing that decide by ballot, which of <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                        them should oppose Hannibal in Bruttium whilst the other should have Etruria
                        and the Ligurians as his province. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The one
                        to whom Bruttium fell was to take over the army from P. Sempronius, and
                        Sempronius, whose command was extended for a year as proconsul, was to
                        relieve P. Licinius; the latter was to return to Rome. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Licinius was not only a fine soldier but he was in
                        every respect one of the most accomplished citizens of the time; he combined
                        in himself all the advantages which nature or fortune could bestow; he was
                        an exceptionally handsome man and possessed remarkable physical strength;
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he was considered a most eloquent
                        speaker, whether he was pleading a cause or defending or attacking a measure
                        in the senate or before the Assembly, and he was thoroughly conversant with
                        pontifical law. And his recent consulship had established his reputation as
                        a military leader. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Arrangements similar to
                        those in Bruttium were also made in Etruria and Liguria; M. Cornelius was to
                        hand over his army to the new consul and hold the province of Gaul with
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the legions which L. Scribonius had
                        commanded the previous year. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then the
                        consuls balloted for their provinces; Bruttium fell to Caepio, Etruria to
                        Servilius Geminus. The balloting for the praetors' provinces followed;
                        Aelius Paetus obtained the City jurisdiction, P. Lentulus drew Sardinia, P.
                        Villius Sicily, and Quintilius Varus Ariminum with the two legions which had
                        formed Lucretius Spurius' command. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Lucretius had his command extended for a year to allow of his rebuilding
                        Genua, which had been destroyed by Mago. Scipio's command was extended until
                        the war in Africa was brought to a close. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        A decree was also made that, as he had entered upon his province of Africa,
                        solemn intercessions should be offered up that the expedition might be to
                        the advantage of the Roman people, of the general himself and of his army.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> 3000 men were raised for service in
                        Sicily, as all the troops in that province had been taken to Africa and it
                        had been decided that Sicily should be protected by forty ships until the
                        fleet returned from Africa. Villius took with him thirteen new ships, the
                        rest were the old ones in Sicily which were refitted. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> M. Pomponius, who had been praetor the year before, was
                        appointed to take charge of this fleet, and placed on board the new levies
                        he had brought from Italy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A fleet of
                        equal strength was assigned to Cnaeus Octavius, who also had been praetor
                        the previous year and was now invested with similar powers for the
                        protection of the Sardinian coast. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        praetor Lentulus was ordered to furnish 2000 men for service with the fleet.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In view of the uncertainty as to where
                        the Carthaginian fleet would land, though they would be sure to seek some
                        unguarded spot, M. Marcius was furnished with forty ships to watch the coast
                        of Italy. The consuls were authorised by the senate to raise 3000 men for
                        this fleet and also two legions to defend the City against all
                        contingencies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The province of Spain was
                        left in the hands of the former commanders, L. Lentulus and L. Manlius
                        Acidinus, who retained their old legions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Altogether there were 20 legions and 160 ships of war on active service this
                        year. The praetors were ordered to go to their respective provinces.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Before the consuls left the City they
                        received the commands of the senate to celebrate the Great Games which the
                        vow of the Dictator T. Manlius Torquatus required to be celebrated every
                        five years, if the condition of the republic remained unaltered. Numerous
                        stories of portents filled men's minds with superstitious terrors.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was said that crows picked with
                        their beaks some of the gold on the Capitol and actually ate it, and rats
                        gnawed a golden crown at Antium. The whole of the country round Capua was
                        covered by an immense flight of locusts, and no one knew whence they had
                        come. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At Reate a foal was born with five
                        feet; at Anagnia fiery meteors were seen in different parts of the sky and
                        these were followed by a huge blazing torch; <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> at Frusino a thin bow encircled the sun, which
                        afterwards grew to such a size that it extended beyond the bow; <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> at Arpinum there was a subsidence of the ground
                        and a vast chasm was formed. Whilst one of the consuls was sacrificing, the
                        liver of the first victim was found to be without a head. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> These portents were expiated by sacrifices of
                        full-grown animals, the college of pontiffs intimated the deities to whom
                        they were to be offered. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this business was completed the
                        consuls and praetors departed to their various provinces. They were all,
                        however, interested in Africa, as much so indeed as if the ballot had
                        assigned it to them, whether it was that they saw that the issue of the war
                        and their country's fate would be decided there, or that they wished to do a
                        service to Scipio as the man to whom all eyes were turned. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> So it was that not only from Sardinia, as above stated,
                        but from Sicily itself and from Spain, clothing, corn, even arms as well as
                        supplies of all kinds were forwarded to him from the Sicilian harbours.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Throughout the winter there had been
                        no pause in the numerous operations which Scipio was conducting on all
                        sides. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He maintained the investment of
                        Utica; his camp was in full view of Hasdrubal; the Carthaginians had
                        launched their ships, their fleet was fully equipped and ready to intercept
                        his supplies. Nevertheless he had not lost sight of his purpose to win
                        Syphax, in case his passion for his bride should have cooled through
                        unstinted enjoyment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Syphax was anxious
                        for peace and proposed as conditions that the Romans should evacuate Africa,
                        and the Carthaginians Italy, but he gave Scipio to understand that if the
                        war continued he should not desert his allies. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> I believe that the negotiations were conducted through
                        intermediaries-and most of the authorities take this view-rather than that
                        Syphax, as Antias Valerius asserts, came to the Roman camp to confer
                        personally with Scipio. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first the Roman
                        commander would hardly allow these terms to be mentioned; afterwards,
                        however, in order that his men might have a plausible reason for visiting
                        the enemies' camp he did not reject then so decidedly, and held out hopes
                        that after frequent discussions they might come to an agreement. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The winter quarters of the Carthaginians,
                        constructed as they were of materials collected haphazard from the country
                        round, were almost wholly built of wood. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        The Numidians in particular lived in huts made of wattled reeds and roofed
                        with grass matting; they were dispersed all over the camp in no order or
                        arrangement, and some even lay outside the lines. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> When this was reported to Scipio, he was hopeful of
                        burning the camp down if an opportunity presented itself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys who were sent to Syphax were
                        accompanied by some first-rank centurions, men of tried courage and
                        sagacity, who were disguised as camp-servants. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst the envoys were in conference these men strolled
                        about the camp noting all the adits and exits, the general arrangement of
                        the camp, the positions of the Carthaginians and Numidians, respectively,
                        and the distance between Hasdrubal's camp and that of Syphax. They also
                        watched the methods adopted in posting the watches and guards, to see
                        whether a surprise attack would be better made by night or by day.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The conferences were pretty frequent,
                        and different men were purposely sent each time in order that these details
                        might become known to a larger number. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As
                        the discussions went on with increasing frequency, Syphax, and through him
                        the Carthaginians, fully expected that peace would be attained with a few
                        days. Suddenly the Roman envoys announced that they had been forbidden to
                        return to headquarters unless a definite reply were given. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Syphax must either say what he had made up his mind to
                        do or, if it was necessary for him to consult Hasdrubal and the
                        Carthaginians, he should do so; the time had come for either a peace
                        settlement or an energetic resumption of hostilities. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst Syphax was consulting Hasdrubal and the
                        Carthaginians, the Roman spies had time to visit every part of the camp, and
                        Scipio was able to make all his arrangements. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The prospect of peace had, as usually happens, made
                        Syphax and the Carthaginians less on the alert to guard against any hostile
                        attempt which might be made in the meantime. At last a reply came, but as
                        the Romans were supposed to be anxious for peace, the opportunity was taken
                        of adding some unacceptable conditions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        This was just what Scipio wanted to justify him in breaking off the
                        armistice. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He told the king's messenger
                        that he would refer the matter to his council, and the next day he gave his
                        reply to the effect that not a single member of the council beside himself
                        was in favour of peace. The messenger was to take word that the only hope of
                        peace for Syphax lay in his abandoning the cause of the Carthaginians.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus Scipio put an end to the truce
                        in order that he might be free to carry out his plans without any breach of
                        faith. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He launched his ships-it was now
                        the commencement of spring-and placed his engines and artillery on board as
                        though he were going to attack Utica from the sea. He also sent 2000 men to
                        hold the hill commanding the city which he had previously occupied, partly
                        with a view of diverting <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> the enemy's
                        attention from his real design, and partly to prevent his camp from being
                        attacked from the city, as it would be left with only a weak guard while he
                        was marching against Syphax and Hasdrubal. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After making these arrangements he
                        summoned a council of war and ordered the spies to report what they had
                        discovered, and at the same time requested Masinissa who knew all about the
                        enemy to give the council any information he could. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He then laid before them his own plan of operations for
                        the coming night and directed the tribunes to lead the troops out of camp as
                        soon as the trumpets sounded on the break-up of the council. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> In obedience to his order the march out began at
                        sunset. About the first watch the column of march was deployed into line of
                        battle. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After advancing in this order at
                        an easy pace for seven miles they reached the hostile camp about midnight.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Scipio assigned a portion of his
                        force, including Masinissa and his Numidians, to Laelius with instructions
                        to attack Syphax and fire his camp. Then he took Laelius and Masinissa apart
                        and appealed to them each separately to <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        make up by extra care and diligence for the confusion inseparable from a
                        night attack. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He told them that he should
                        attack Hasdrubal and the Carthaginian camp, but would wait until he saw the
                        king's camp on fire. He had not to wait long, for when the fire was cast on
                        the nearest huts it very soon caught the next ones and then running along in
                        all directions spread over the whole camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Such an extensive fire breaking out at night naturally produced alarm and
                        confusion, but Syphax's men thinking it was due to accident and not to the
                        enemy rushed out without arms to try and extinguish it. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> They found themselves at once confronted by an armed
                        foe, mainly Numidians whom Masinissa, thoroughly acquainted with the
                        arrangement of the camp, had posted in places where they could block all the
                        avenues. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Some were caught by the flames,
                        whilst half asleep in their beds, numbers who had fled precipitately,
                        scrambling over one another were trampled to death in the camp gates. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the Carthaginian camp the first to see
                        the glowing flames were the watch, then others wakened by the tumult
                        observed them, and all fell into the same mistake of supposing that it was
                        an accidental outbreak. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They took the
                        cries proceeding from wounded combatants as due to the nocturnal alarm, and
                        so were unable to realise what had actually happened. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Not in the least suspecting the presence of an enemy,
                        they rushed out, each through the gate nearest to him, without any weapons
                        carrying out what might help to extinguish the flames, and so came right on
                        the Roman army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were all cut down,
                        for the enemy gave no quarter, that none might escape and give the alarm. In
                        the confusion the gates were left unguarded, and Scipio at once seized them
                        and fire was flung upon the nearest huts. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The flames broke out at first in different places but, creeping from hut to
                        hut, in a very few moments wrapped the whole camp in one vast conflagration.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Men and animals alike scorched with
                        the heat blocked the passages to the gates and fell crushed by each other.
                        Those whom the fire did not overtake perished by the sword and the two camps
                        were involved in one common destruction. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Both the generals, however, saved themselves, and out of all those thousands
                        only 2000 infantry and 500 cavalry made good their escape, the majority
                        being wounded or suffering from the fire. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Forty thousand men perished either from the fire or the enemy, over 5000
                        were taken alive, including many Carthaginian nobles of whom eleven were
                        senators; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> 174 standards were captured,
                        2700 horses and 6 elephants, 8 others having been killed or burnt to death.
                        An enormous quantity of arms was secured, these the general devoted to
                        Vulcan, and they were all burnt. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hasdrubal, who was accompanied in his
                        flight by a small body of horse, made for the nearest city, where he was
                        subsequently joined by all who survived, but fearing that it might be
                        surrendered to Scipio, he left it in the night. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Soon after his departure the gates were opened to admit
                        the Romans, and as the surrender was a voluntary one the place suffered no
                        hostile treatment. Two cities were taken and sacked soon afterwards, and the
                        loot found there with what had been rescued from the burning camp was all
                        given to the soldiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Syphax established
                        himself in a fortified position about eight miles distant; Hasdrubal
                        hastened to Carthage, fearing lest the recent disaster should frighten the
                        senate into a more yielding mood. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So great
                        in fact was the alarm that people expected Scipio to leave Utica alone and
                        instantly commence the siege of Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The sufetes-a magistrate corresponding to our consul-convened a meeting of
                        the senate. Here three proposals were made. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> One was to send envoys to Scipio to negotiate a peace; another, to recall
                        Hannibal to protect his country from the ruin which threatened it; the
                        third, which showed a firmness worthy of Romans in adversity, urged the
                        reinforcement of the army to its proper strength and an appeal to Syphax not
                        to abandon hostilities. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The last proposal,
                        which was supported by Hasdrubal and the whole of the Barcine party, was
                        adopted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Recruiting began at once in the
                        city and the country districts, and a deputation was sent to Syphax, who was
                        already doing his utmost to repair his losses and renew hostilities. He was
                        urged on by his wife, who did not now trust to the endearments and caresses
                        with which she had formerly swayed her lover, <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> but with prayers and piteous appeals and eyes bathed in
                        tears she conjured him not to betray her father and her country, or allow
                        Carthage to be devastated by the flames which had consumed his camp.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The deputation gave him encouragement
                        and hope by informing him that they had met near a city called Obba a body
                        of 4000 Celtiberian mercenaries who had been raised in Spain, a splendid
                        force, and that Hasdrubal would appear ere long with a formidable army.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He answered them in friendly terms,
                        and then took them to see a large number of Numidian peasants to whom he had
                        just given arms and horses, and assured them that he would call out all the
                        fighting men in his kingdom. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He was well
                        aware, he said, that he owed his defeat to fire, and not to the chances of
                        battle; it was only the man who was vanquished by arms that was inferior in
                        war. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Such was the tenor of his reply to
                        the deputation. A few days later, Hasdrubal and Syphax joined forces; their
                        united strength amounted to about 30,000 men. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just as though the war were at end, so far
                        as Syphax and the Carthaginians were concerned, Scipio pressed on the siege
                        of Utica and was already bringing his engines up to the walls when he
                        received intelligence of the enemy's activity. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Leaving a small force to keep up the appearance of an
                        investment by land and sea, he marched with the main body of his army to
                        meet his foes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His first position was on a
                        hill some four miles distant from the king's camp. The next day he marched
                        his cavalry down into what are called the Magni Campi, a stretch of level
                        country extending from the foot of the hill, and spent the day in riding up
                        to the enemies' outposts and harassing them with skirmishes. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> For the next two days both sides kept up this
                        desultory fighting without any result worth mentioning; on the fourth day
                        both sides came down to battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman
                        commander drew up his principes behind the leading maniples of the hastati,
                        and the triarii as reserves; the Italian cavalry were stationed on the right
                        wing, Masinissa and the Numidians on the left. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Syphax and Hasdrubal placed the Numidian cavalry
                        opposite the Italian, and the Carthaginian horse fronted Masinissa, whilst
                        the Celtiberians formed the centre to meet the charge of the legions. In
                        this formation they closed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Numidians
                        and Carthaginians on the two wings were routed at the first charge; the
                        former consisting mostly of peasants could not withstand the Roman horse,
                        nor could the Carthaginians, also raw levies, hold their own against
                        Masinissa, whose recent victory had made him more formidable than ever.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Though exposed on both flanks the
                        Celtiberians stood their ground, for as they did not know the country,
                        flight offered no chance of safety, nor could they hope for any quarter from
                        Scipio after carrying their mercenary arms into Africa to attack the man who
                        had done so much for them and their countrymen. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Completely enveloped by their foes they died fighting
                        to the last, and fell one after another on the ground where they stood.
                        Whilst the attention of all was turned to them, Syphax and Hasdrubal gained
                        time to make their escape. The victors, wearied with slaughter more than
                        with fighting, were at last overtaken by the night. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the morrow Scipio sent Laelius with the
                        whole of the Roman and Numidian cavalry and some light-armed infantry in
                        pursuit of Syphax and Hasdrubal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        cities in the neighbourhood, all of which were subject to Carthage, he
                        attacked successively with his main body; some he won by appealing to their
                        hopes and fears, some he took by storm. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Carthage was in a state of terrible panic, they felt quite sure that when he
                        had subjugated all their neighbours in the rapid progress of his arms, he
                        would make a sudden attack on Carthage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The walls were repaired and protected by outworks, and each man carried off
                        from the fields, on his own account, what would enable him to endure a long
                        siege. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Few ventured to mention the word
                        "peace" in the senate, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> many were in
                        favour of recalling Hannibal, the majority were of opinion that the fleet
                        which was intended to intercept supplies should be sent to destroy the ships
                        anchored off Utica, possibly the naval camp as well, which was
                        insufficiently guarded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This proposal
                        found most favour, at the same time they decided to send to Hannibal, "for
                        even," it was argued, "supposing that the naval operations were completely
                        successful, the siege of Utica would be only partly raised, <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> and then there was the defence of Carthage-they
                        had no general but Hannibal, no army but his that could undertake that
                        task." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The next day the ships were
                        launched, and at the same time a party of delegates set sail for Italy. The
                        critical state of affairs acted as strong stimulus, everything was done with
                        feverish energy, any one who showed hesitation or slackness was regarded as
                        a traitor to the safety of all. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As Scipio
                        was making slow progress, his army being encumbered with the spoils of many
                        cities, he sent the prisoners and the rest of the booty to his old camp at
                        Utica. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As Carthage was now his objective,
                        he seized Tyneta, from which the garrison had fled, a place about fifteen
                        miles from Carthage, protected by its natural situation as well as by
                        defensive works. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It is visible from
                        Carthage and its walls afford a view of the sea which surrounds that city.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Romans were busily engaged in
                        intrenching they saw the hostile fleet sailing from Carthage to Utica.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They at once ceased work, orders were
                        given to march, and the army made a rapid advance, fearing lest the ships
                        should be caught with their prows turned shorewards for siege operations, in
                        utter unreadiness for a naval battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        "How" they asked themselves, "can a mobile and fully armed fleet in perfect
                        sailing order be successfully resisted by ships loaded with artillery and
                        war machines, or converted into transports, or brought up so close to the
                        walls as to allow of scaling parties using them instead of an agger and
                        gangways?" <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Under the circumstances Scipio
                        abandoned the usual tactics. Bringing the warships which could have
                        protected the others into the rearmost position close inshore, he lined up
                        the transports in front of them four deep to serve as a wall against the
                        enemy's attack. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To prevent the lines from
                        being broken by violent charges he laid masts and yard-arms from ship to
                        ship and secured them by stout ropes which bound them together like one
                        continuous chain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then fastened planks
                        upon the top of these, so making a free passage along the whole line, and
                        under these bridges the despatch-boats had room to run out against the enemy
                        and retire into safety. After making these hurried arrangements as complete
                        as time would allow, he placed about 1000 picked men on board the transports
                        and an <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> immense quantity of missile
                        weapons, so that however long the fighting went on there might be enough.
                        Thus ready and eager, they waited for the enemy. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If the Carthaginians had moved more
                        rapidly they would have found hurry and confusion everywhere, and they might
                        have destroyed the fleet in the first onset. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> They were, however, disheartened by the defeat of their land forces, and
                        now they did not feel confidence even on the sea, the element where they
                        were strongest. After sailing slowly all through the day they brought up
                        towards sunset at a harbour called by the natives Rusocmon. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The following day, they put out to sea in line
                        of battle, expecting the Romans to come out and attack them. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> After they had been stationary for a long time
                        and no movement on the part of the enemy was visible, they at last commenced
                        an attack on the transports. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> There was
                        nothing in the least resembling a naval action, it looked almost exactly as
                        if ships were attacking walls. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        transports were considerably higher than their opponents, and consequently
                        the missiles from the Carthaginian vessels, which had to be hurled from
                        below, were mostly ineffective; those from the transports thrown from above
                        fell with more force, their weight adding to the blow. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The despatch-boats and light vessels which ran out
                        through the intervals under the plank gangways were many of them run down by
                        the momentum and bulk of the warships, and in <milestone n="15??"
                            unit="section"/> time they became a hindrance to those fighting on the
                        transports, who were often obliged to desist for fear of hitting them while
                        they were mixed up with the enemy's ships. <milestone n="16" unit="section"
                        /> At last the Carthaginans began to throw poles with grappling-hooks
                            <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> at the end-the soldiers call them
                        harpagones-on to the Roman ships, and it was impossible to cut away either
                        the poles or the chains by which they were suspended. <milestone n="18"
                            unit="section"/> When a warship had hooked one of the transports it was
                        rowed astern, and you would see the ropes which fastened the transports one
                        to another give way, and sometimes a whole line of transports would be
                        dragged off together. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> In this way all the
                        gangways connecting the first line of transports were broken up, and there
                        was hardly any place left where the defenders could spring back into the
                        second line. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Six transports were towed
                        off to Carthage. Here the rejoicing was greater than the circumstances of
                        the case warranted, but what made it all the more welcome was the fact that
                        the <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/> Roman fleet had narrowly escaped
                        destruction, an escape due to the Carthaginian commander's slackness and the
                        timely arrival of Scipio. Amid such continual disasters and mourning this
                        was an unhoped-for cause of congratulation. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meantime Laelius and Masinissa, after a
                        fifteen days' march, entered Numidia, and the Maesulians, delighted to see
                        their king whose absence they had so long regretted, placed him once more on
                        his ancestral throne. All the garrisons with which Syphax had held the
                        country were expelled and he was confined within the limits of his former
                        dominions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had no intention, however,
                        of remaining quiet; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> he was goaded on by
                        his wife, whom he passionately loved, and by her father, and he had such an
                        abundance of men and horses that the mere sight of the resources afforded by
                        a realm which had enjoyed many years of prosperity would have stimulated the
                        ambition of even a less barbarous and impulsive nature than Syphax
                        possessed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He assembled all who were fit
                        for war, and after distributing horses, armour and weapons amongst them he
                        formed the mounted men into squadrons and the infantry into cohorts, a plan
                        which he had learnt in the old days from the centurions. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> With this army, quite as numerous as the one he had had
                        before but consisting almost entirely of raw and untrained levies, he
                        marched off to meet his enemies, and fixed his camp in their vicinity.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At first he sent small bodies of
                        cavalry from the outposts to make a cautious reconnaissance; compelled to
                        retire by showers of darts they galloped back to their comrades. Sorties
                        were made on both sides alternately, and indignant at being repulsed, larger
                        bodies came up. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This acts as an incentive
                        in cavalry skirmishes when the winning side find their comrades flocking to
                        them in hopes of victory and rage at the prospect of defeat brings supports
                        to those who are losing. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> So it was then,
                        the fighting had been begun by a few, but the love of battle at last brought
                        the whole of the cavalry on both sides into the field. As long as the
                        cavalry only were engaged the Romans had great difficulty in withstanding
                        the immense numbers of Maesulians whom Syphax was sending forward.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Suddenly, however, the Roman light
                        infantry ran out between the cavalry who made way for them, and this gave
                        steadiness to the line and checked the rush of the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The latter slackened speed and then came to a halt, and
                        were soon thrown into confusion by this unaccustomed mode of fighting. At
                        last they gave ground not only before the infantry but before the cavalry
                        also, to whom the support of their infantry had given fresh courage.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> By this time the legions were coming
                        up, but the Maesulians did not wait for their attack, the mere sight of the
                        standards and arms was enough, such was the effect either of the
                        recollection of their past defeats or of the fear which the enemy now
                        inspired. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Syphax was riding up to the hostile
                        squadrons in the hope that either a sense of honour or his own personal
                        danger might check the flight of his men, when his horse was severely
                        wounded and he was thrown, overpowered and made prisoner, and carried off to
                        Laelius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Masinissa was especially delighted to see
                        him as a captive. Cirta was Syphax's capital, and a considerable number
                        escaped to that city. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The losses sustained
                        were insignificant compared with the importance of the victory, for the
                        fighting had been confined to the cavalry. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        There were not more than 5000 killed, and in the storming of the camp,
                        whither the mass of troops had fled after losing their king, less than half
                        that number were made prisoners. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Masinissa
                        told Laelius that nothing would delight him more for the moment than to
                        visit as conqueror his ancestral dominions which had after so many years
                        been recovered, but prompt action was as necessary in success as in defeat.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He suggested that he should be allowed
                        to go on with the cavalry and the vanquished Syphax to Cirta, which he would
                        be able to surprise amidst the general confusion and alarm; Laelius might
                        follow with the infantry by easy stages. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Laelius gave his consent and Masinissa advanced to Cirta and ordered the
                        leading citizens to be invited to a conference. They were ignorant of what
                        had happened to the king, and though Masinissa told them all that had
                        occurred he found threats and persuasion equally unavailing until the king
                        was brought before them in chains. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At this
                        painful and humiliating spectacle there was an outburst of grief, the
                        defences were abandoned, and there was a unanimous resolve to seek the
                        victor's favour by opening the gates to him. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> After placing guards round all the gates and at
                        suitable places in the fortifications he galloped up to the palace to take
                        possession of it. </p>
                    <p> As he was entering the vestibule, on the very threshold in fact, he was met
                        by Sophonisba, the wife of Syphax and daughter of the Carthaginian
                        Hasdrubal. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When she saw him surrounded by
                        an armed escort, and conspicuous by his arms and general appearance, she
                        rightly guessed that he was the king, and throwing herself at his feet,
                        exclaimed: "Your courage and good fortune aided by the gods have given you
                        absolute power over us. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But if a captive
                        may utter words of supplication before one who is master of her fate,
                            <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> if she may touch his victorious
                        right hand, then I pray and beseech you by the kingly greatness in which we
                        too not long ago were clothed, by the name of Numidian which you and Syphax
                        alike bear, by the tutelary deities of this royal abode who, I pray, may
                        receive you with fairer omens than those with which they sent him hence,
                        grant this favour at <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> least to your
                        suppliant that you yourself decide your captive's fate whatever it may be,
                        and do not leave me to fall under the cruel tyranny of a Roman. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Had I been simply the wife of Syphax I would
                        still choose to trust to the honour of a Numidian, born under the same
                        African sky as myself, rather than that of an alien and a foreigner.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But I am a Carthaginian, the daughter
                        of Hasdrubal, and you see what I have to fear. If no other way is possible
                        then I implore you to save me by death from falling into Roman hands."
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Sophonisba was in the bloom of youth
                        and in all the splendour of her beauty, and as she held Masinissa's hand and
                        begged him to give his word that she should not be surrendered to the
                        Romans, her tone became one of blandishment rather than entreaty. <milestone
                            n="18" unit="section"/> A slave to passion like all his countrymen, the
                        victor at once fell in love with his captive. He gave her his solemn
                        assurance that he would do what she wished him to do and then retired into
                        the palace. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Here he considered in what
                        way he could redeem his promise, and as he saw no practical way of doing so
                        he allowed his passion to dictate to him as a method equally reckless and
                        indecent. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> Without a moment's delay he
                        made preparations for celebrating his nuptials on that very day, so that
                        neither Laelius nor Scipio might be free to treat as a prisoner one who was
                        now Masinissa's wife. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> When the marriage
                        ceremony was over Laelius appeared on the scene, and, far from concealing
                        his disapproval of what had been done, he actually attempted to drag her
                        from her bridegroom's arms and send her with Syphax and the other prisoners
                        to Scipio. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> However, Masinissa's
                        remonstrances so far prevailed that it was left to Scipio to decide which of
                        the two kings should be the happy possessor of Sophonisba. After Laelius had
                        sent Syphax and the other prisoners away, he recovered, with Masinissa's
                        aid, the remaining cities in Numidia which were still held by the king's
                        garrisons. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news arrived that Syphax was
                        being brought into camp, the whole army turned out as though to watch a
                        triumphal procession. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king himself, in
                        chains, was the first to appear, he was followed by a crowd of Numidian
                        nobles. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As they passed the soldiers each
                        in turn sought to magnify their victory by exaggerating the greatness of
                        Syphax and the military reputation of his nation. "This is the king," they
                        said, "whose greatness has been so far acknowledged by the most powerful
                        States in the world-Rome and Carthage-that Scipio left his army in Spain and
                        sailed with <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> two triremes to Africa to secure his
                        alliance, whilst the Carthaginian Hasdrubal not only visited him in his
                        kingdom, but even gave him his daughter in marriage. He has had the Roman
                        and the Carthaginian commanders both in his power at the same time.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As each side has sought peace and
                        friendship from the immortal gods by sacrifices duly offered, so each side
                        alike has sought peace and friendships from him. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He was powerful enough to expel Masinissa from his
                        kingdom, and he reduced him to such a condition that he owed his life to the
                        report of his death and to his concealment in the forest, where he lived on
                        what he could catch there like a wild beast." <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Amidst these remarks of the bystanders, the king was
                        conducted to the headquarters tent. As Scipio compared the earlier fortunes
                        of the man with his present condition and recalled to mind his own
                        hospitable relations with him, the mutually pledged right hands, the
                        political and personal bonds between them, he was greatly moved. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Syphax, too, thought of these things, but they
                        gave him courage in addressing his conqueror. Scipio questioned him as to
                        his object in first denouncing his alliance with Rome and then starting an
                        unprovoked war against her. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He admitted
                        that he had done wrong and behaved like a madman but his taking up arms
                        against Rome was not the beginning of his madness, it was the last act.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He first exhibited his folly, his
                        utter disregard of all private ties and public obligations, when he admitted
                        a Carthaginian bride into his house. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        torches which illuminated these nuptials had set his palace in a blaze. That
                        fury of a woman, that scourge, had used every endearment to alienate and
                        warp his feelings, and would not rest till she had with her own impious
                        hands armed him against his host and friend. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> However, broken and ruined as he was, he had this to
                        console him in his misery-that pestilential fury had entered the household
                        of his bitterest foe. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Masinissa was not
                        wiser or more consistent than he had been, his youth made him even less
                        cautious; at all events that marriage proved him to be more foolish and
                        headstrong. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was the language of a man animated,
                        not only by hatred towards an enemy, but also by the sting of hopeless love,
                        knowing as he did that the woman he loved was in the house of his rival.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Scipio was deeply distressed at what
                        he heard. Proof of the charges was found in the hurrying on of the nuptials
                        almost amid the clash of arms without consulting or even waiting for
                        Laelius. Masinissa had acted with such precipitancy that the very first day
                        he saw his prisoner he married her, and the rites were actually performed
                        before the tutelary deities of his enemy's house. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> This conduct appeared all the more shocking to Scipio
                        because when he himself was in Spain, young as he was, no captive girl had
                        ever moved him by her beauty. Whilst he was thinking all this over, Laelius
                        and Masinissa appeared. He extended the same gracious and friendly welcome
                        to both, and in the presence of a large number of his officers addressed
                        them in most laudatory terms. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then he took
                        Masinissa quietly aside and spoke to him as follows: "I think, Masinissa,
                        that you must have seen some good qualities in me when you went to Spain to
                        establish friendly relations with me, and also when, afterwards, you trusted
                        yourself and all your fortunes to me in Africa. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Now, among all the virtues which attracted you there is
                        none upon which I pride myself so much as upon my continence and the control
                        of my passions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> I wish, Masinissa, that
                        you would add these to the other noble features of your own character. At
                        our time of life we are not, believe me, so much in danger from armed foes
                        as from the seductive pleasures which tempt us on every side. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The man who has curbed and subjugated these by
                        his self-control has won for himself greater glory and a greater victory
                        than we have won over Syphax. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The courage
                        and energy you have displayed in my absence I have gladly dwelt upon and
                        gratefully remember; the rest of your conduct I prefer that you should
                        reflect upon when alone, rather than that I should make you blush by
                        alluding to it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Syphax has been defeated
                        and made prisoner under the auspices of the people of Rome, and this being
                        so, his wife, his kingdom, his territory, his towns with all their
                        inhabitants, whatever in short Syphax possessed, belong now to Rome as the
                        spoils of war. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Even if his wife were not
                        a Carthaginian, if we did not know that her father is in command of the
                        enemy's forces, it would still be our duty to send her with her husband to
                        Rome, and leave it to the senate and people to decide the fate of one who is
                        alleged to have estranged our ally and precipitated him in arms against us.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Conquer your feelings and be on your
                        guard against letting one vice mar the many good qualities you possess and
                        sullying the grace of all your services by a fault which is out of all
                        proportion to its cause." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On hearing this Masinissa blushed
                        furiously and even shed tears. He said that he would comply with the
                        general's wishes, and begged him to take into consideration, as far as he
                        could, the pledge he had rashly given, for he had promised that he would not
                        let her pass into any one's power. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then he
                        left the headquarters tent and retired to his own in a state of distraction.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Dismissing all his attendants he
                        remained there some time, giving vent to continual sighs and groans which
                        were quite audible to those outside. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At
                        last with a deep groan he called one of his slaves in whom he placed
                        complete confidence and who had in his keeping the poison which kings
                        usually have in reserve against the vicissitudes of Fortune. After mixing it
                        in a cup he told him to take it to Sophonisba, and at the same time tell her
                        that Masinissa would have gladly fulfilled the first promise that he made to
                        his wife, but as those who have the power were depriving him of the right to
                            <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> do so, he was fulfilling the
                        second-that she should not fall into the hands of the Romans alive.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The thought of her father, her
                        country, and the two kings who had wedded her would decide her how to act.
                        When the servant came with the poison and the message to Sophonisba, she
                        said, "I accept this wedding gift, no unwelcome one if my husband can do
                        nothing more for his wife. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But tell him
                        that I should have died more happily had not my marriage bed stood so near
                        my grave." The high spirit of these words was sustained by the fearless way
                        in which, without the slightest sign of trepidation, she drank the potion.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the news reached Scipio he was
                        afraid that the young man, wild with grief, would <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> take some still more desperate step, so he at once sent
                        for him, and tried to console him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> at the
                        same time gently censuring him for having atoned for one act of madness by
                        committing another and making the affair more tragic than it need have been.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The next day, with the view of
                        diverting his thoughts, Scipio mounted the tribunal and ordered the assembly
                        to be sounded. Addressing Masinissa as king and eulogising him in the
                        highest possible terms, he presented him with a golden crown, curule chair,
                        an ivory sceptre and also with a purple-bordered toga and a tunic
                        embroidered with palms. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He enhanced the
                        value of these gifts by informing him that the Romans considered no honour
                        more splendid than that of a triumph, and that no more magnificent insignia
                        were borne by triumphing generals than those which the Roman people deemed
                        Masinissa, alone of all foreigners, worthy to possess. Laelius was the next
                        to be commended, he was presented with a golden crown. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Other soldiers received rewards according to their
                        services. The honours which had had been conferred on the king went far to
                        assuage his grief, and he was encouraged <milestone n="14??" unit="section"
                        /> to hope for the speedy possession of the whole of Numidia now that Syphax
                        was out of the way. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laelius was sent in charge of Syphax and
                        the other prisoners to Rome, and envoys from Masinissa accompanied him.
                        Scipio returned to his camp at Tyneta and completed the fortifications which
                        he had commenced. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The rejoicing of the
                        Carthaginians over the temporary success of their naval attack was
                        short-lived and evanescent, for when they heard of the capture of Syphax, on
                        whom they had rested their hopes almost more than on Hasdrubal and his army,
                        they completely lost heart. The war party could no longer gain a hearing and
                        the senate sent the "Thirty Seniors" to Scipio to sue for peace. This body
                        was the most august council in their state and controlled to a very large
                        extent even the senate itself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they
                        reached the headquarters tent in the Roman camp, they made a profound
                        obeisance and prostrated themselves-a practice, I believe, which they
                        brought with them from their original home. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> Their language corresponded to their abject posture. They made no excuse
                        for themselves, but threw the responsibility for the war on Hannibal and his
                        supporters. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They craved pardon for a city
                        which had been twice ruined by the recklessness of its citizens and could
                        only be preserved in safety by the good-will of its enemy. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> What Rome sought, they pleaded, was the homage and
                        submission of the vanquished, not their annihilation. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> They professed themselves ready to execute any commands
                        which he chose to give. Scipio replied that he had come to Africa in the
                        hope-a hope which his successes had confirmed-of taking back to Rome a
                        complete victory, and not merely proposals for peace. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Still, though victory was almost within his grasp, he
                        would not refuse to grant terms of peace, that all nations <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> might know that Rome was actuated by the spirit
                        of justice, whether she was undertaking a war or putting an end to one. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He stated the terms of peace, which were
                        the surrender of all prisoners, deserters and refugees; the withdrawal of
                        the armies from Italy and Gaul; the abandonment of all action in Spain; the
                        evacuation of all the islands lying between Italy and Africa and the
                        surrender of their entire navy with the exception of twenty vessels.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They were also to provide 500,000
                        pecks of wheat and 300,000 of barley, but the actual amount of the money
                        indemnity is doubtful. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In some authors I
                        find 5000 talents, in others 5000 pounds of silver mentioned; some only say
                        that double pay for the troops was demanded. "You will be allowed," he
                        added, "three days to consider whether you will agree to peace on these
                        terms. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> If you decide to do so, arrange an
                        armistice with me, and send envoys to the senate in Rome." The Carthaginians
                        were then dismissed. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> As their object was
                        to gain time to allow of Hannibal's sailing across to Africa they resolved
                        that no conditions of peace should be rejected, and accordingly they sent
                        delegates to <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> conclude an armistice with
                        Scipio, and a deputation was also sent to Rome to sue for peace, the latter
                        taking with them a few prisoners and deserters for the sake of appearance,
                        in order that peace might more be readily granted. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Several days previously Laelius arrived in
                        Rome with Syphax and the Numidian prisoners. He made a report to the senate
                        of all that had been done in Africa and there were great rejoicings at the
                        present position of affairs and sanguine hopes for the future. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> After discussing the matter the senate decided
                        that Syphax should be interned at Alba and that Laelius should stay in Rome
                        until the Carthaginian delegates arrived. A four days' thanksgiving was
                        ordered. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the adjournment of the House,
                        P. Aelius, the praetor, forthwith convened a meeting of the Assembly, and
                        mounted the rostrum, accompanied by C. Laelius. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When the people heard that the armies of Carthage had
                        been routed, a far-famed king defeated and made prisoner, and a victorious
                        progress made throughout Numidia, they could no longer restrain their
                        feelings and expressed their unbounded joy in shouts and other
                        demonstrations of delight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Seeing the
                        people in this mood the praetor at once gave orders for the sacristans to
                        throw open the <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> holy places throughout
                        the City in order that the people might have the whole day for going round
                        the shrines to offer up their adoration and thanksgivings to the gods. </p>
                    <p> The next day he introduced Masinissa's envoys to the senate. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> They first of all congratulated the senate upon
                        Scipio's successes in Africa and then expressed thanks on behalf of
                        Masinissa for Scipio's action in not only conferring upon him the title of
                        king, but also in <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> giving practical
                        effect to it by restoring to him his ancestral dominion where now that
                        Syphax was disposed of he would, if the senate so decided, reign free from
                        all fear of opposition. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He was grateful
                        for the way in which Scipio had spoken of him before his officers and for
                        the splendid insignia with which he had been honoured and which he had done
                        his best to prove himself worthy of and would continue to do so. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> They petitioned the senate to confirm by a
                        formal decree the royal title and the other favours and dignities which
                        Scipio had conferred upon him. And as an additional boon, Masinissa begged,
                        if he was not asking too much, that they would release the Numidian
                        prisoners who were under guard in Rome; that, he considered, would increase
                        his prestige with his subjects. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The reply
                        given to the envoys was to the effect that the senate congratulated the king
                        as much as themselves upon the successes in Africa; <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio had acted rightly and in perfect order in
                        recognising Masinissa as king, and the senators warmly approved of all he
                        had done to meet Masinissa's wishes. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They
                        passed a decree that the presents which the envoys were to take to the king
                        should comprise two purple cloaks with a golden clasp on each and two tunics
                        embroidered with the laticlave; two richly caparisoned horses and a set of
                        equestrian armour with cuirasses for each; two tents and military furniture
                        such as the consuls are usually provided with. The praetor received
                        instructions to see that these things were sent to the king. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> The envoys each received presents to the value
                        of 5000 ases, and each member of their suite to the value of 1000 ases.
                        Besides these, two suits of apparel were given to each of the envoys, and
                        one to each of their suite and also to each of the Numidian prisoners who
                        were to be restored to the king. During their stay in Rome a house was
                        placed at their disposal and they were treated as guests of the State. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this summer P. Quintilius Varus the
                        praetor and M. Cornelius the proconsul fought a regular engagement with
                        Mago. The praetor's legions formed the fighting line; Cornelius kept his in
                        reserve, but rode to the front and took command of one wing, the praetor
                        leading the other, and both of them exhorted the soldiers to make a furious
                        charge on the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they failed to
                        make any impression upon them, Quintilius said to Cornelius, "As you see,
                        the battle is progressing too slowly; the enemy finding themselves offering
                        an unhoped-for resistance have steeled themselves against fear, there is
                        danger of this fear passing into audacity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        We must let loose a hurricane of cavalry against them if we want to shake
                        them and make them give ground. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Either,
                        then, you must keep up the fighting at the front and I will bring the
                        cavalry into action, or I will remain here and direct the operations of the
                        first line while you launch the cavalry of the four legions against the
                        enemy." The proconsul left it to the praetor to decide what he would do.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Quintilius, accordingly, accompanied
                        by his son Marcus, an enterprising and energetic youth, rode off to the
                        cavalry, ordered them to mount and sent them at once against the enemy.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The effect of their charge was
                        heightened by the battle-shout of the legions, and the hostile lines would
                        not have stood their ground, had not Mago, at the first movement of the
                        cavalry, promptly brought his elephants into action. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The appearance of these animals, their trumpeting and
                        smell so terrified the horses as to render the assistance of the cavalry
                        futile. When engaged at close quarters and able to use sword and lance the
                        Roman cavalryman was the better fighter, but when carried away by a
                        frightened horse, he was a better target for the Numidian darts. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> As for the infantry, the twelfth legion had lost
                        a large proportion of their men and were holding their ground more to avoid
                        the disgrace of retreat than from any hope of offering effectual resistance.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor would they have held it any longer
                        if the thirteenth legion which was in reserve had not been brought up and
                        taken part in the doubtful conflict. To oppose this fresh legion Mago
                        brought up his reserves also. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These were
                        Gauls, and the hastati of the eleventh legion had not much trouble in
                        putting them to rout. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They then closed up
                        and attacked the elephants who were creating confusion in the Roman infantry
                        ranks. Showering their darts upon them as they crowded together, and hardly
                        ever failing to hit, they drove them all back upon the Carthaginian lines,
                        after four had fallen, severely wounded. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At last the enemy began to give ground,
                        and the whole of the Roman infantry, when they saw the elephants turning
                        against their own side, rushed forward to increase the confusion and panic.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As long as Mago kept his station in
                        front, his men retreated slowly and in good order, but when they saw him
                        fall, seriously wounded and carried almost fainting from the field, there
                        was a general flight. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The losses of the
                        enemy amounted to 5000 men, and 22 standards were taken. The victory was a
                        far from bloodless one for the Romans, they lost 2300 men in the praetor's
                        army, mostly from the twelfth legion, and amongst them two military
                        tribunes, M. Cosconius and M. Maevius. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        The thirteenth legion, the last to take part in the action, also had its
                        losses; C. Helvius, a military tribune, fell whilst restoring the battle,
                        and twenty-two members of the cavalry corps, belonging to distinguished
                        families, together with some of the centurions were trampled to death by the
                        elephants. The battle would have lasted longer had not Mago's wound given
                        the Romans the victory. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mago withdrew during the night and
                        marching as rapidly as his wound would allow reached that part of the
                        Ligurian coast which is inhabited by the Ingauni. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Here he was met by the deputation from Carthage which
                        had landed a few days previously at Genua. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        They informed him that he must sail for Africa at the earliest possible
                        moment; his brother Hannibal, to whom similar instructions had been given,
                        was on the point of doing so. Carthage was not in a position to retain her
                        hold upon Gaul and Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The commands of
                        the senate and the dangers threatening his country decided Mago's course,
                        and moreover there was the risk of an attack from the victorious enemy if he
                        delayed, and also of the desertion of the Ligurians who, seeing Italy
                        abandoned by the Carthaginians, would go over to those in whose power they
                        would ultimately be. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He hoped too that a
                        sea voyage would be less trying to his wound than the jolting of the march
                        had been, and that everything would contribute to his recovery. He embarked
                        his men and set sail, but he had not cleared Sardinia when he died of his
                        wound. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some of his ships which had parted
                        company with the rest when out at sea were captured by the Roman fleet which
                        was lying off Sardinia. Such was the course of events in the Alpine
                        districts of Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul C.
                        Servilius had done nothing worth recording in Etruria, nor after his
                        departure for Gaul. In the latter country he had rescued his father C.
                        Servilius and also C. Lutatius after sixteen years of servitude, the result
                        of their capture by the Boii at Tannetum. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        With his father on one side of him and Lutatius on the other he returned to
                        Rome honoured more on personal than public grounds. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> A measure was proposed to the people relieving him from
                        penalties for having illegally acted as tribune of the plebs and plebeian
                        aedile while his father who had filled a curule chair was, unknown to him,
                        still alive. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the bill of indemnity
                        was passed he returned to his province. The consul Cnaeus Servilius in
                        Bruttium received the surrender of several places, now that they saw that
                        the Punic War was drawing to a close. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Amongst these were Consentia, Aufugium, Bergae, Besidiae, Oriculum,
                        Lymphaeum, Argentanum, and Clampetia. He also fought a battle with Hannibal
                        in the neighbourhood of Croto, of which no clear account exists. According
                        to Valerius Antias, 5000 of the enemy were killed, but either this is an
                        unblushing fiction, or its omission in the annalists shows great
                        carelessness. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> At all events nothing
                        further was done by Hannibal in Italy, for the delegation summoning him to
                        Africa happened to arrive from Carthage about the same time as the one to
                        Mago. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It is said that he gnashed his teeth,
                        groaned, and almost shed tears when he heard what the delegates had to say.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After they had delivered their
                        instructions, he exclaimed, "The men who tried to drag me back by cutting
                        off my supplies of men and money are now recalling me not by crooked means
                        but plainly and openly. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So you see, it is
                        not the Roman people who have been so often routed and cut to pieces that
                        have vanquished Hannibal, but the Carthaginian senate by their detraction
                        and envy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is not Scipio who will pride
                        himself and exult over the disgrace of my return so much as Hanno who has
                        crushed my house, since he could do it in no other way, beneath the ruins
                        for Carthage." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He had divined what would
                        happen, and had got his ships ready in anticipation. The unserviceable
                        portion of his troops he got rid of by distributing them ostensibly as
                        garrisons amongst the few towns which, more out of fear than loyalty, still
                        adhered to him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The main strength of his
                        army he transported to Africa. Many who were natives of Italy refused to
                        follow him, and withdrew into the temple of Juno Lacinia, a shrine which up
                        to that day had remained inviolate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There,
                        actually within the sacred precinct, they were foully murdered. Seldom,
                        according to the accounts, has any one left his native country to go into
                        exile in such gloomy sorrow as Hannibal manifested when quitting the country
                        of his foes. It is stated that he often looked back to the shores of Italy,
                        accusing gods and men and even cursing himself for not having led his
                        soldiers reeking with blood from the victorious field of Cannae straight to
                        Rome. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio, he said, who whilst consul
                        had never seen a Carthaginian in Italy, had dared to <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> go to Africa, whereas he who had slain 100,000 men at
                        Thrasymenus and at Cannae had wasted his strength round Casilinum and Cumae
                        and Nola. Amid these accusations and regrets he was borne away from his long
                        occupation of Italy. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news of Mago's departure reached Rome
                        at the same time as that of Hannibal. The joy with which the intelligence of
                        this twofold relief was received was, however, chastened by the fact that
                        their generals had, through lack of either courage or strength, failed to
                        detain them, though they had received express instructions from the senate
                        to that effect. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was also a feeling
                        of anxiety as to what the issue would be now that the whole brunt of the war
                        fell upon one army and one commander. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Just
                        at this time, a commission arrived from Saguntum bringing some Carthaginians
                        who had landed in Spain for the purpose of hiring auxiliaries, and whom they
                        had captured together with the money they had brought. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> 250 pounds of silver and 800 pounds of gold were
                        deposited in the vestibule of the senate-house. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After the men had been handed over and thrown into
                        prison, the gold and silver was returned to the Saguntines. A vote of thanks
                        was accorded to them, they were presented with gifts and also provided with
                        ships in which to return to Spain. Following upon this incident some of the
                        senior senators reminded the House of a great omission. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> "Men," they said, "are much more alive to their
                        misfortunes than to the good things that come to them. We remember what
                        panic and terror we felt when Hannibal descended upon Italy. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> What defeats and mourning followed! The enemy's
                        camp was visible from the City-what prayers we one and all put up!
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> How often in our councils have we
                        heard the plaint of men lifting up their hands to heaven and asking whether
                        the day would ever come when they would see Italy freed from an enemy's
                        presence and flourishing in peace and prosperity! <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> At last, after sixteen years of war, the gods have
                        granted us this boon, and yet there are none who ask that thanks should be
                        offered to them. Men do not receive even a present blessing with grateful
                        hearts, much less are they are likely to remember past benefits." <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> A general shout arose from all parts of the
                        House calling upon the praetor P. Aelius to submit a motion. It was decreed
                        that a five days' thanksgiving should be offered at all the shrines and a
                        hundred and twenty full-grown victims sacrificed. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Laelius had by this time left Rome with Masinissa's
                        envoys. On tidings being received that the Carthaginian peace deputation had
                        been seen at Puteoli and would come on from there by land it was decided to
                        recall Laelius in order that he might be present at the interview. Q.
                        Fulvius Gillo, one of Scipio's staff-officers, conducted the Carthaginians
                        to Rome. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As they were forbidden to enter
                        the City they were domiciled in a country house belonging to the State, and
                        an audience of the senate was granted them in the temple of Bellona. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their speech to the senate was much the
                        same as the one they had made to Scipio; they disclaimed any responsibility
                        for the war on the part of the government and threw the entire blame on
                        Hannibal. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "He had no orders from their
                        senate to cross the Ebro, much less the Alps. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> It was on his own authority that he had made war not
                        only on Rome but even on Saguntum; any one who took a just view would
                        recognise that the treaty with Rome remained unbroken to that day.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their instructions accordingly were
                        simply that they should ask to be allowed to continue on the same terms of
                        peace as those which had been settled on the last occasion with C.
                        Lutatius." <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In accordance with the
                        traditional usage the praetor gave any one who wished permission to
                        interrogate the envoys, and the senior members who had taken part in
                        arranging the former treaties put various questions. The envoys, who were
                        almost all young men, said that they had no recollection of what happened.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then loud protests broke out from all
                        parts of the House; the senators declared that it was an instance of Punic
                        treachery, men were selected to ask for a renewal of the old treaty who did
                        not even remember its terms. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys were then ordered to withdraw
                        and the senators were asked for their opinions. M. Livius advised that as
                        the consul C. Servilius was the nearest he should be summoned to Rome in
                        order that he might be present during the debate. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> No more important subject could be discussed than the
                        one before them, and it did not seem to him compatible with the dignity of
                        the Roman people that the discussion should take place in the absence of
                        both the consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Q. Metellus, who had
                        been consul three years previously and had also been Dictator, gave it as
                        his opinion that as P. Scipio, after destroying their armies and devastating
                        their land, had driven the enemy to the necessity of suing for peace, there
                        was no one in the world <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> who could form a
                        truer judgment as to their real intention in opening negotiations than the
                        man who was at that moment carrying the war up to the gates of Carthage. In
                        his opinion they ought to take Scipio's advice and no other as to whether
                        the offer of peace ought to be accepted or rejected. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> M. Valerius Laevinus, who had filled two consulships,
                        declared that they had come as spies and not as envoys, and he urged that
                        they should be ordered to leave Italy and escorted by a guard to their
                        ships, and that written instructions should be sent to Scipio not to relax
                        hostilities. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Laelius and Fulvius supported
                        this proposal and stated that Scipio thought that the only hope of peace lay
                        in Mago and Hannibal not being recalled, but the Carthaginians would adopt
                        every subterfuge whilst waiting for their generals <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> and their armies, and would then continue the war,
                        ignoring treaties however recent, and in defiance of all the gods. These
                        statements led the senate to adopt Laevinus' proposal. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The envoys were dismissed with no prospect of peace and
                        the curtest of replies. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul Cnaeus Servilius, fully
                        persuaded that the credit of restoring peace in Italy was due to him, and
                        that it was he who had driven Hannibal out of the country, followed the
                        Carthaginian commander to Sicily, intending to sail from there to Africa.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When this became known in Rome the
                        senate decided that the praetor should write to him and inform him that the
                        senate thought it right that he should remain in Italy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The praetor said that Servilius would pay no attention
                        to a letter from him, and on this it was resolved to appoint P. Sulpicius
                        Dictator, and he by virtue of his superior authority recalled the consul to
                        Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Dictator spent the remainder of
                        the year in visiting, accompanied by M. Servilius, his Master of the Horse,
                        the different cities of Italy which had fallen away from Rome during the
                        war, and holding an enquiry in each case. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        During the armistice a hundred transports carrying supplies and escorted by
                        twenty warships were despatched from Sardinia by Lentulus the praetor and
                        reached Africa without any damage either from the enemy or from storms.
                        Cnaeus Octavius sailed from Sicily with two hundred transports and thirty
                        warships, but was not equally fortunate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        He had a favourable voyage until he was almost within sight of Africa, when
                        he was becalmed; then a south-westerly wind sprang up which scattered his
                        ships in all directions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thanks to the
                        extraordinary efforts of the rowers against the adverse waves, Octavius
                        succeeded in making the Promontory of Apollo. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The greater part of the transports were driven to
                        Aegimurus, an island which forms a breakwater to the bay on which Carthage
                        is situated and about thirty miles distant from the city. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Other were carried up to the city itself as far as the
                        Aquae Calidae ("hot-springs"). All this was visible from Carthage, and a
                        crowd gathered from all parts of the city in the forum. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The magistrates convened the senate; the people who
                        were in the vestibule of the senate-house protested against so much booty
                        being allowed to slip out of their hands and out of their sight. Some
                        objected that this would be a breach of faith whilst peace negotiations were
                        going on, others were for respecting the truce which had not yet expired.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The popular assembly was so mixed up
                        with the senate that they almost formed one body, and they unanimously
                        decided that Hasdrubal should proceed to Aegimurum with fifty ships of war
                        and pick up the Roman ships which were scattered along the coast or in the
                        harbours. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Those transports which had been
                        abandoned by their crews at Aegimurum were towed to Carthage, and
                        subsequently others were brought in from Aquae Calidae. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The envoys had not yet come back from
                        Rome, and it was not known whether the senate had decided for peace or for
                        war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> What did most to arouse Scipio's
                        indignation was the fact that all hopes of peace were destroyed and all
                        respect for the truce flouted by the very men who had asked for a truce and
                        were suing for peace. He at once sent L. Baebius, M. Servilius and L. Fabius
                        to Carthage to protest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As they were in
                        danger of ill-treatment from the mob and saw that they might be prevented
                        from returning, they requested the magistrates who had protected them from
                        violence to send ships to escort them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Two
                        triremes were supplied to them, and when they reached the mouth of the
                        Bagradas, from which the Roman camp was visible, the ships returned to
                        Carthage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Carthaginian fleet was lying
                        off Utica, and whether it was in consequence of a secret message from
                        Carthage, or whether Hanno, who was in command, acted on his own
                        responsibility without the connivance of his government, in any case, three
                        quadriremes from the fleet made a sudden attack upon the Roman quinquereme
                        as it was rounding the promontory. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They
                        were, however, unable to ram it owing to its superior speed, and its greater
                        height prevented any attempt to board it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        As long as the missiles lasted, the quinquereme made a brilliant defence,
                        but when these failed nothing could have saved it but the nearness of the
                        land and the numbers of men who had come down from the camp to the shore to
                        watch. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The rowers drove the ships on to
                        the beach with their utmost strength; the vessel was wrecked, but the
                        passengers escaped uninjured. Thus, by one misdeed after another, all doubt
                        was removed as to the truce having been broken when Laelius and the
                        Carthaginians arrived on their return from Rome. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio informed them that in spite of the fact that the
                        Carthaginians had broken not only the truce which they <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> had pledged themselves to observe, but even the law of
                        nations in their treatment of the envoys, he should himself take no action
                        in their case which would be inconsistent with the traditional maxims of
                        Rome or contrary to his own principles. He then dismissed them and prepared
                        to resume operations. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hannibal was now
                        nearing the land and he ordered a sailor to climb the mast and find out what
                        part of the country they were making for. The man reported that they were
                        heading for a ruined sepulchre. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Hannibal
                        regarding it as an evil omen ordered the pilot to sail past the place and
                        brought up the fleet at Leptis, where he disembarked his force. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The above-described events all happened
                        during this year, the subsequent ones belong to the year following when M.
                        Servilius the Master of the Horse and Tiberius Claudius Nero were the
                        consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Towards the close of the year a
                        deputation came from the Greek cities in alliance with us to complain that
                        their country had been devastated and the envoys who had been sent to demand
                        redress were not allowed to approach Philip. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> They also brought information that 4000 men under Sopater had sailed for
                        Africa to assist the Carthaginians, taking a considerable sum of money with
                        them. The senate decided to send to Philip and inform him that they regarded
                        these proceedings as a violation of the treaty. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> C. Terentius Varro, C. Mamilius and M. Aurelius were
                        entrusted with this mission, and they were furnished with three
                        quinqueremes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The year was rendered
                        memorable by an enormous fire, in which the houses on the Clivus Publicius
                        were burnt to the ground, and also by a great flood. Food, however, was
                        extremely cheap, for not only was the whole of Italy open, now that it was
                        left in peace, but a great <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> quantity of
                        corn had been sent from Spain, which the curule aediles, M. Valerius Falto
                        and M. Fabius Buteo, distributed to the people, ward by ward, at four ases
                        the peck. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The death occurred this year of
                        Quintus Fabius Maximus at a very advanced age, if it be true, as some
                        authorities assert, that he had been augur for sixty-two years. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> He was a man who deserved the great surname he
                        bore, even if he had been the first to bear it. He surpassed his father in
                        his distinctions, and equalled his grandfather Rullus. Rullus had won more
                        victories and fought greater battles, but his grandson had Hannibal for an
                        opponent and that made up for everything. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        He was held to be cautious rather than energetic, and though it may be a
                        question whether he was naturally slow in action or whether he adopted these
                        tactics as especially suitable to the character of the war, nothing is more
                        certain that that, as Ennius says, "one man by his slowness restored the
                        State." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He had been both augur and
                        pontifex; his son Q. Fabius Maximus succeeded him as augur, Ser. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Sulpicius Galba as pontifex. The Roman and the
                        Plebeian Games were celebrated by the aediles M. Sextius Sabinus and Cnaeus
                        Tremellius Flaccus, the former for one day, the latter were repeated for
                        three days. These two aediles were elected praetors together with C. Livius
                        Salinator and C. Aurelius Cotta. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        Authorities are divided as to who presided over the elections, whether the
                        consul C. Servilius did so or whether, owing to his being detained in
                        Etruria by the conspiracy trials which the senate had ordered him to
                        conduct, he named a Dictator to preside. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of the following year the
                        consuls M. Servilius and Tiberius Claudius convened the senate in the
                        Capitol to decide the allocation of the provinces. As they both wanted
                        Africa they were anxious to ballot for that province and for Italy.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Mainly, however, owing to the efforts
                        of Q. Metellus, nothing was decided about Africa; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> the consuls were instructed to arrange with the
                        tribunes of the plebs for a vote of the people to be taken as to whom they
                        wished to conduct the war in Africa. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        tribes were unanimously in favour of P. Scipio. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> In spite of this the senate decreed that the two
                        consuls should ballot, and Africa was drawn by Ti. Claudius, who was to take
                        across a fleet of fifty vessels-all quinqueremes-and exercise the same
                        powers as Scipio. Etruria fell to M. Servilius. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> C. Servilius who had held that province had his command
                        extended in case the senate should require his presence in Rome. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The praetors were distributed as follows: M.
                        Sextius received Gaul and P. Quintilius Varus was to hand over two legions
                        which he had there; C. Livius was to hold Bruttium with the two legions
                        which P. Sempronius had commanded there the year before; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Cnaeus Tremellius was sent to Sicily and took over the
                        two legions from P. Villius Tappulus, the praetor of the previous year;
                        Villius in the capacity of propraetor was furnished with twenty warships and
                        1000 men for the protection of the Sicilian coast; M. Pomponius was to send
                        1500 men to Rome in the twenty remaining ships. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The City jurisdiction passed into the hands of C.
                        Aurelius Cotta. The other commands were unchanged. Sixteen legions were
                        considered sufficient this year for the defence of the dominion of Rome.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In order that all things might be
                        undertaken and <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> carried out with the
                        favour of the gods, it was decided that before the consuls took the field
                        they should celebrate the Games and offer the sacrifices which T. Manlius
                        the Dictator had vowed during the consulship of M. Claudius Marcellus and T.
                        Quinctius, if the republic should maintain its position unimpaired for five
                        years. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Games were celebrated in the
                        Circus, the celebration lasting four days, and the victims vowed to the
                        several deities were duly sacrificed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> All through this time there was a growing
                        tension of feeling, hopes and fears alike were becoming stronger. Men could
                        not make up their minds whether they had more to rejoice over in the fact
                        that at the end of sixteen years Hannibal had finally evacuated Italy and
                        left the unchallenged possession of it to Rome, or more to fear from his
                        having landed in Africa with his military strength unimpaired. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> "The seat of danger," they said, "is changed, but
                        not the danger itself. Quintus Fabius, who has just died, foretold how great
                        the struggle would be when he declared in oracular tones that Hannibal would
                        be a more formidable foe in his own country than he had been on alien soil.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Scipio has not to do with Syphax,
                        whose subjects are undisciplined barbarians and whose army was generally led
                        by Statorius, who was little more than a camp menial, nor with Syphax's
                        elusive father-in-law, Hasdrubal nor with a half-armed mob of peasants
                        hastily collected from the fields. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It is
                        Hannibal whom he has to meet, who was all but born in the headquarters of
                        his father, that bravest of generals; reared and brought up in the midst of
                        arms, a soldier whilst still a boy, and when hardly out of his teens in high
                        command. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He has passed the prime of his
                        manhood in victory after victory and has filled Spain and Gaul and Italy
                        from the Alps to the southern sea with memorials of mighty deeds. The men he
                        is leading are his contemporaries in arms, steeled by innumerable hardships
                        such as it is hardly credible that men can have gone through, bespattered,
                        times without number, with Roman blood, laden with spoils stripped from the
                        bodies, not of common soldiers only, but even of commanders-in-chief.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Scipio will meet many on the field of
                        battle who with their own hands have slain the praetors, the commanders, the
                        consuls of Rome, and who are now decorated with mural and vallarian wreaths
                        after roaming at will through the camps and cities of Rome which they
                        captured. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All the fasces borne before
                        Roman magistrates today are not so many in number as those which Hannibal
                        might have had borne before him, taken on the field of battle when the
                        commander-in-chief was slain." <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By dwelling
                        on such gloomy prognostications they increased their fears and anxieties.
                        And there was another ground for apprehension. They had been accustomed to
                        seeing war going on first in one part of Italy and then in another without
                        much hope of its being soon brought to a close. Now, however, all thoughts
                        were turned on Scipio and Hannibal, they seemed as though purposely pitted
                        against each other for a final and decisive struggle. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Even those who felt the greatest confidence in Scipio
                        and entertained the strongest hopes that he would be victorious became more
                        nervous and anxious as they realised that the fateful hour was approaching.
                        The Carthaginians were in a very similar mood. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> When they thought of Hannibal and the greatness of the
                        deeds he had done they regretted that they had sued for peace, but when they
                        reflected that they had been twice worsted in the open <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> field, that Syphax was a prisoner, that they had been
                        driven out of Spain and then out of Italy, and that all this was the result
                        of one man's resolute courage, and that man Scipio, they dreaded him as
                        though he had been destined from his birth to be their ruin. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .Hannibal had reached Hadrumetum where he
                        remained a few days for his men to recover from the effects of the voyage,
                        when breathless couriers announced that all the country round Carthage was
                        occupied by Roman arms. He at once hurried by forced marches to Zama. Zama
                        is a five days' march from Carthage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        scouts whom he had sent forward to reconnoitre were captured by the Roman
                        outposts and conducted to Scipio. Scipio placed them in charge of the
                        military tribunes and gave orders for them to be taken round the camp where
                        they were to look at everything they wished to see without fear. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> After asking them whether they had examined all
                        to their satisfaction, he sent them back with an escort to Hannibal.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The report they gave was anything but
                        pleasant hearing for him, for as it happened Masinissa had on that very day
                        come in with a force of 6000 infantry and 4000 cavalry. What gave him most
                        uneasiness was the confidence of the enemy which he saw too clearly was not
                        without good grounds. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So, although he had
                        been the cause of the war, though his arrival had upset the truce and
                        diminished the hope of any peace being arranged, he still thought that he
                        would be in a better position to obtain terms if he were to ask for peace
                        while his strength was still unbroken than after a defeat. Accordingly he
                        sent a request to Scipio to grant him an interview. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Whether he did this on his own initiative or in
                        obedience to the orders of his government I am unable to say definitely.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius Antius says that he was
                        defeated by Scipio in the first battle with a loss of 12,000 killed and 1700
                        taken prisoners, and that after this he went in company with ten delegates
                        to Scipio's camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> However this may be,
                        Scipio did not refuse the proposed interview, and by common agreement the
                        two commanders advanced their camps towards each other that they might meet
                        more easily. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Scipio took up his position
                        not far from the city of Naragarra on ground which, in addition to other
                        advantages, afforded a supply of water within range of missiles from the
                        Roman lines. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hannibal selected some
                        rising ground about four miles away, a safe and advantageous position,
                        except that water had to be obtained from a distance. A spot was selected
                        midway between the camps, which, to prevent any possibility of treachery,
                        afforded a view on all sides. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .When their respective escorts had
                        withdrawn to an equal distance, the two leaders advanced to meet each other,
                        each accompanied by an interpreter-the greatest commanders not only of their
                        own age but of all who are recorded in history before their day, <milestone
                            n="2??" unit="section"/> the peers of the most famous kings and
                        commanders that the world had seen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For a
                        few moments they gazed upon one another in silent admiration. Hannibal was
                        the first to speak. "If," he said, "Destiny has so willed it that I, who was
                        the first to make war on Rome and who have so often had the final victory
                        almost within my grasp, should now be the first to come to ask for peace, I
                        congratulate myself that Fate has appointed you, above all others, as the
                        one from whom I am to ask it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Amongst your
                        many brilliant distinctions this will not be your smallest title to fame,
                        that Hannibal, to whom the gods have given the victory over so many Roman
                        generals, has yielded to you, that it has fallen to your lot to put an end
                        to a war which has been more memorable for your defeats than for ours.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This is indeed the irony of fortune,
                        that after taking up arms when your father was consul, and having him for my
                        opponent in my first battle, it should be his son to whom I come unarmed to
                        ask for peace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It would have been far
                        better had the gods endowed our fathers with such a disposition that you
                        would have been contented with the sovereignty of Italy, whilst we were
                        contented with Africa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As it is, even for
                        you, Sicily and Sardinia are no adequate compensation for the loss of so
                        many fleets, so many armies, and so many splendid generals. But it is easier
                        to regret the past than to repair it. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> We
                        coveted what belonged to others, consequently we had to fight for our own
                        possessions; not only has war assailed you in Italy and us in Africa, but
                        you have seen the arms and standards of an enemy almost within your gates
                        and on your walls while we hear in Carthage the murmur of the Roman camp.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So the thing which we detest most of
                        all, which you would have wished for before everything, has actually come
                        about, the question of peace is raised when your fortunes are in the
                        ascendant. We who are most concerned in securing peace are the ones to
                        propose it, and we have full powers to treat, whatever we do here our
                        governments will ratify. All we need is a temper to discuss things calmly.
                        As far as I am concerned, coming back to a country which I left as a boy,
                        years and a chequered experience of good and evil fortune have so
                        disillusioned me that I prefer to take reason rather than Fortune as my
                        guide. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As for you, your youth and
                        unbroken success will make you, I fear, impatient of peaceful counsels.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It is not easy for the man whom
                        Fortune never deceives to reflect on the uncertainties and accidents of
                        life. What I was at Thrasymenus and at Cannae, that you are today. You were
                        hardly old enough to bear arms when you were placed in high command, and in
                        all your enterprises, even the most daring, Fortune has never played you
                        false. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> You avenged the deaths of your
                        father and your uncle, and that disaster to your house became the occasion
                        of your winning a glorious reputation for courage and filial piety.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You recovered the lost provinces of
                        Spain after driving four Carthaginian armies out of the country. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Then you were elected consul, and whilst your
                        predecessors had hardly spirit enough to protect Italy, you crossed over to
                        Africa, and after destroying two armies and capturing and burning two camps
                        within an hour, taking the powerful monarch Syphax prisoner, and robbing his
                        dominions and ours of numerous cities you have at last dragged me away from
                        Italy after I had kept my hold upon it for sixteen years. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> It is quite possible that in your present mood you
                        should prefer victory to an equitable peace; I, too, know the ambition which
                        aims at what is great rather than at what is expedient; on me, too, a
                        fortune such as yours once shone. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But if
                        in the midst of success the gods should also give us wisdom, we ought to
                        reflect not only on what has happened in the past but also upon what may
                        happen in the future. To take only one instance, I myself am a sufficient
                        example of the fickleness of fortune. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        Only the other day I had placed my camp between your city and the Anio and
                        was advancing my standards against the walls of Rome-here you see me,
                        bereaved of my two brothers, brave soldiers and brilliant generals as they
                        were, in front of the walls of my native place which is all but invested,
                        and begging on behalf of my city that it may be spared the fate with which I
                        have threatened yours. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The greater a
                        man's good fortune the less ought he to count upon it. Success attends you
                        and has deserted us, and this will make peace all the more splendid to you
                        who grant it; to us who ask for it it is a stern necessity rather than an
                        honourable surrender. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Peace once
                        established is a better and safer thing than hoping for victory; that is in
                        your hands, this in the hands of the gods. Do not expose so many years' good
                        fortune to the hazard of a single hour. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                        You think of your own strength, but think too of the part which fortune
                        plays and the even chances of battle. On both sides there will be swords and
                        men to use them, nowhere does the event less answer expectation than in war.
                            <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> Victory will not add so much to the
                        glory which you can now win by granting peace, as defeat will take away from
                        it. The chances of a single hour can annihilate all the honours you have
                        gained and all you can hope for. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> If you
                        cement a peace, P. Cornelius, you are master of all, otherwise you will have
                        to accept whatever fortune the gods send you. <milestone n="23"
                            unit="section"/> M. Atilius Regulus on this very soil would have
                        afforded an almost unique instance of the success which waits on merit, had
                        he in the hour of victory granted peace to our fathers when they asked for
                        it. But as he would set no bounds to his prosperity, nor curb his elation at
                        his good fortune, the height to which he aspired only made his fall the more
                        terrible. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> "It is for him who grants peace, not for
                        him who seeks it, to name the terms, but perhaps it may not be presumptuous
                        in us to assess our own penalty. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/> We
                        consent to everything remaining yours for which we went to war-Sicily,
                        Sardinia, Spain and all the islands that lie between Africa and Italy. We
                        Carthaginians, confined within the shores of Africa, are content, since such
                        is the will of the gods, to see you ruling all outside our frontiers by sea
                        and land as your dominions. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/> I am bound to
                        admit that the lack of sincerity lately shown in the request for peace and
                        in the non-observance of the truce justified your suspicions as to the good
                        faith of Carthage. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> But, Scipio, the loyal
                        observance of peace depends largely upon the character of those through whom
                        it is sought. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/> I hear that your senate
                        have sometimes even refused to grant it because the ambassadors were not of
                        sufficient rank. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/> Now it is Hannibal who
                        seeks it, and I should not ask for it if I did not believe it to be
                        advantageous to us, and because I believe it to be so I shall keep it
                        inviolate. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/> As I was responsible for
                        beginning the war and as I conducted it in a way which no one found fault
                        with until the gods were jealous of my success, so I shall do my utmost to
                        prevent any one from being discontented with the peace which I shall have
                        been the means of procuring." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To these arguments the Roman commander
                        made the following reply: "I was quite aware, Hannibal, that it was the hope
                        of your arrival that led the Carthaginians to break the truce and cloud all
                        prospect of peace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In fact, you yourself
                        admit as much, since you are eliminating from the terms formerly proposed
                        all that has not already been long in our power. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> However, as you are anxious that your countrymen should
                        realise what a great relief you are bringing them, I must make it my care
                        that they shall not have the conditions they formerly agreed to struck out
                        today as a reward for their perfidy. You do not deserve to have the old
                        proposals still open and yet you are seeking to profit by dishonesty!
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Our fathers were not the aggressors in
                        the war for Sicily, nor were we the aggressors in Spain, but the dangers
                        which threatened our Mamertine allies in the one case and the destruction of
                        Saguntum in the other made our case a righteous one and justified our arms.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That you provoked the war in each case
                        you yourself admit, and the gods bear witness to the fact; they guided the
                        former war to a just and righteous issue, and they are doing and will do the
                        same with this one. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As for myself, I do
                        not forget what weak creatures we men are; I do not ignore the influence
                        which Fortune exercises and the countless accidents to which all our doings
                        are liable. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Had you of your own free will
                        evacuated Italy and embarked your army before I sailed for Africa and then
                        come with proposals for peace, I admit that I should have acted in a
                        high-handed and arbitrary spirit if I had rejected them. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But now that I have dragged you to Africa like a
                        reluctant and tricky defendant I am not bound to show you the slightest
                        consideration. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So then, if in addition to
                        the terms on which peace might have been concluded previously, there is the
                        further condition of an indemnity for the attack on our transports and the
                        ill-treatment of our envoys during the armistice, I shall have something to
                        lay before the councils. If you consider this unacceptable. then prepare for
                        war as you have been unable to endure peace." Thus, no understanding was
                        arrived at and the commanders rejoined their armies. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> They reported that the discussion had been fruitless,
                        that the matter must be decided by arms, and the result left to the gods.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On their return to their camps, the
                        commanders-in-chief each issued an order of the day to their troops. "They
                        were to get their arms ready and brace up their courage for a final and
                        decisive struggle; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> if success attended
                        them they would be victors not for a day only but for all time; they would
                        know before the next day closed whether Rome or Carthage was to give laws to
                        the nations. For not Africa and Italy only-the whole world will be the prize
                        of victory. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Great as is the prize, the
                        peril in case of defeat will be as great. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        "For no escape lay open to the Romans in a strange and unknown land; and
                        Carthage was making her last effort, if that failed, her destruction was
                        imminent. On the morrow they went out to battle-the two most brilliant
                        generals and the two strongest armies that the two most powerful nations
                        possessed-to crown on that day the many honours they had won, or for ever
                        lose them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The soldiers were filled with
                        alternate hopes and fears as they gazed at their own and then at the
                        opposing lines and measured their comparative strength with the eye rather
                        than the mind, cheerful and despondent in turn. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The encouragement which they could not give to
                        themselves their generals gave them in their exhortations. The Carthaginian
                        reminded his men of their sixteen years' successes on Italian soil, of all
                        the Roman generals who had fallen and all the armies that had been
                        destroyed, and as he came to each soldier who had distinguished himself in
                        any battle, he recounted his gallant deeds. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> Scipio recalled the conquest of Spain and the recent battles in Africa
                        and showed up the enemies' confession of weakness, since their fears
                        compelled them to sue for <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> peace and
                        their innate faithlessness prevented them from abiding by it. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> He turned to his own purpose the conference with
                        Hannibal, which being private allowed free scope for invention. He drew an
                        omen and declared that the gods had vouchsafed the same auspices to them as
                        those under which their fathers fought at the Aegates. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The end of the war and of their labours, he assured
                        them, had come; the spoils of Carthage were in their hands, and the return
                        home to their wives and children and household gods. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He spoke with uplifted head and a face so radiant that
                        you might suppose he had already won the victory. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then he drew up his men, the hastati in
                        front, behind them the principes, the triarii closing the rear. He did not
                        form the cohorts in line before their respective standards, but placed a
                        considerable interval between the maniples in order that there might be
                        space for the enemy elephants to be driven through without breaking the
                        ranks. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Laelius, who had been one of his
                        staff-officers and was now by special appointment of the senate acting as
                        quaestor, was in command of the Italian cavalry on the left wing, Masinissa
                        and his Numidians being posted on the right. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> The velites, the light infantry of those days, were stationed at the head
                        of the lanes between the columns of maniples with instructions to retire
                        when the elephants charged and shelter themselves behind the lines of
                        maniples, or else run to the right and left behind the standards and so
                        allow the monsters to rush on to meet the darts from both sides. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> To make his line look more menacing Hannibal
                        posted his elephants in front. He had eighty altogether, a larger number,
                        than he had ever brought into action before. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Behind them were the auxiliaries, Ligurians and Gauls, with an admixture
                        of Balearics and Moors. The second line was made up of Carthaginians and
                        Africans together with a legion of Macedonians. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> A short distance behind these were posted his Italian
                        troops in reserve. These were mainly Bruttians who had followed him from
                        Italy more from the compulsion of necessity than of their own free will.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Like Scipio, Hannibal covered his
                        flanks with his cavalry, the Carthaginians on the right, the Numidians on
                        the left. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Different words of encouragement were
                        required in an army composed of such diverse elements, where the soldiers
                        had nothing in common, neither language nor custom nor laws nor arms nor
                        dress, nor even the motive which brought them into the ranks. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> To the auxiliaries he held out the attraction of
                        the pay which they would receive, and the far greater inducement of the
                        booty they would secure. In the case of the Gauls he appealed to their
                        instinctive and peculiar hatred of the Romans. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The Ligurians, drawn from wild mountain fastnesses,
                        were told to look upon the fruitful plains of Italy as the rewards of
                        victory. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Moors and Numidians were
                        threatened by the prospect of being under the unbridled tyranny of
                        Masinissa. Each nationality was swayed by its hopes or fears. The
                        Carthaginians had placed before their eyes, their city walls, their homes,
                        their fathers' sepulchres, their wives and children, the alternative of
                        either slavery and destruction or the empire of the world. There was no
                        middle course, they had either everything to hope for or everything to fear.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Whilst the commander-in-chief was
                        thus addressing the Carthaginians, and the officers of the various
                        nationalities were conveying his words to their own people and to the aliens
                        mingled with them mostly through interpreters, the <milestone n="13??"
                            unit="section"/> trumpets and horns of the Romans were sounded and such
                        a clangor arose that the elephants, mostly those in front of the left wing,
                        turned upon the Moors and Numidians behind them. Masinissa had no difficulty
                        in turning this disorder into flight and so clearing the Carthaginian left
                        of its cavalry. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> A few of the animals,
                        however, showed no fear and were urged forward upon the ranks of velites,
                        amongst whom, in spite of the many wounds they received, they did
                        considerable execution. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The velites, to
                        avoid being trampled to death, sprang back to the maniples and thus allowed
                        a path for the elephants, from both sides of which they rained their darts
                        on the beasts. The leading maniples also kept up a fusillade of missiles
                        until these animals too were driven out of the Roman lines on to their own
                        side and put the Carthaginian cavalry, who were covering the right flank, to
                        flight. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> When Laelius saw the enemy's
                        horse in confusion he at once took advantage of it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the infantry lines closed, the
                        Carthaginians were exposed on both flanks, owing to the flight of the
                        cavalry, and were losing both confidence and strength. Other circumstances,
                        too, seemingly trivial in themselves but of considerable importance in
                        battle, gave the Romans an advantage. Their cheers formed one united shout
                        and were therefore fuller and more intimidating; those of the enemy, uttered
                        in many languages, were only dissonant cries. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans kept their foothold as they fought and
                        pressed the enemy by the sheer weight of their arms and bodies; on the other
                        side there was much more agility and nimbleness of foot than actual fighting
                        strength. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As a consequence, the Romans
                        made the enemy give ground in their very first charge, then pushing them
                        back with their shields and elbows and moving forward on to the ground from
                        which they had dislodged them, they made a considerable advance as though
                        meeting with no resistance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When those in
                        the rear became aware of the forward movement they too pressed on those in
                        front thereby considerably increasing the weight of the thrust. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> This retirement on the part of the enemy's
                        auxiliaries was not checked by the Africans and Carthaginians who formed the
                        second line. In fact, so far were they from supporting them that they too
                        fell back, fearing lest the enemy, after overcoming the obstinate resistance
                        of the first line. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> should reach them. On
                        this the auxiliaries suddenly broke and turned tail; some took refuge within
                        the second line, others, not allowed to do so, began to cut down those who
                        refused to admit them after refusing to support them. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> There were now two battles going on, the Carthaginians
                        had to fight with the enemy, and at the same time with their own troops.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Still, they would not admit these
                        maddened fugitives within their ranks, they closed up and drove them to the
                        wings and out beyond the fighting ground, fearing lest their fresh and
                        unweakened lines should be demoralised by the intrusion of panic-struck and
                        wounded men. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The ground where the auxiliaries had been
                        stationed had become blocked with such heaps of bodies and arms that it was
                        almost more difficult to cross it than it had been to make way through the
                        masses of the enemy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The hastati who
                        formed the first line followed up the enemy, each man advancing as best he
                        could over the heaps of bodies and arms and the slippery bloodstained ground
                        until the standards and maniples were all in confusion. Even the standards
                        of the principes began to sway to and fro when they saw how irregular the
                        line in front had become. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As soon as
                        Scipio observed this he ordered the call to be sounded for the hastati to
                        retire, and after withdrawing the wounded to the rear he brought up the
                        principes and triarii to the wings, in order that the hastati in the centre
                        might be supported and protected on both flanks. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Thus the battle began entirely afresh, as the Romans
                        had at last got to their real enemies, who were a match for them in their
                        arms, their experience and their military reputation, and who had as much to
                        hope for and to fear as themselves. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        Romans, however, had the superiority in numbers and in confidence, since
                        their cavalry had already routed the elephants and they were fighting with
                        the enemy's second line after defeating his first. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Laelius and Masinissa, who had followed up
                        the defeated cavalry a considerable distance, now returned from the pursuit
                        at the right moment and attacked the enemy in the rear. This at last decided
                        the action. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The enemy were routed, many
                        were surrounded and killed in action, those who dispersed in flight over the
                        open country were killed by the cavalry who were in possession of every
                        part. Above 20,000 of the Carthaginians and their allies perished on that
                        day and almost as many were made prisoners. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> 132 standards were secured and 11 elephants. The victors lost 1500 men.
                        Hannibal escaped in the melee with a few horsemen and fled to Hadrumetum.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before quitting the field he had done
                        everything possible in the battle itself and in the preparation for it.
                        Scipio himself acknowledged and all experienced soldiers agreed that
                        Hannibal had shown singular skill in the disposition of his troops.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He placed his elephants in front so
                        that their irregular charge and irresistible force might make it <milestone
                            n="6??" unit="section"/> impossible for the Romans to keep their ranks
                        and maintain the order of their formation, in which their strength and
                        confidence mainly lay. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then he posted the
                        mercenaries in front of his Carthaginians, in order that this motley force
                        drawn from all nations, held together not by a spirit of loyalty but by
                        their pay, might not find it easy to run away. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Having to sustain the first onset they might wear down
                        the impetuosity of the enemy, and if they did nothing else they might blunt
                        his sword by their wounds. Then came the Carthaginian and African troops,
                        the mainstay of his hopes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were equal
                        in all respects to their adversaries and even had the advantage inasmuch as
                        they would come fresh into action against a foe weakened by wounds and
                        fatigue. As to the Italian troops, he had his doubts as to whether they
                        would turn out friends or foes and withdrew them consequently into the
                        rearmost line. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After giving this final
                        proof of his great abilities, Hannibal fled, as has been stated, to
                        Hadrumetum. From here he was summoned to Carthage, to which city he returned
                        thirty-six years after he had left it as a boy. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He told the senate frankly that he had lost not a
                        battle merely but the whole war, and that their only chance of safety lay in
                        obtaining peace. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> From the battlefield Scipio proceeded at
                        once to storm the enemies' camp, where an immense quantity of plunder was
                        secured. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He then returned to his ships,
                        having received intelligence that P. Lentulus had arrived off Utica with 50
                        warships and 100 transports loaded with supplies of every kind. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Laelius was sent to carry the news of the victory
                        to Scipio, who, thinking that the panic in Carthage ought to be increased by
                        threatening the city on all sides, ordered Octavius to march the legions
                        thither overland while he himself sailed from Utica with his old fleet
                        strengthened by the division which Lentulus had brought, and steered for the
                        harbour of Carthage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As he was approaching
                        it he was met by a vessel hung with bands of white wool and branches of
                        olive. In it there were the ten foremost men of the State, who, on
                        Hannibal's advice, had been sent as an embassy to sue for peace. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> As soon as they were near the stern of the
                        general's vessel they held up the suppliant emblems, and made imploring
                        appeals to Scipio for his pity and protection. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The only answer vouchsafed them was that they were to
                        go to Tunis, as Scipio was about to move his army to that place. Keeping on
                        his course he entered the harbour of Carthage in order to survey the
                        situation of the city, not so much for the purpose of acquiring information
                        as of discouraging the enemy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then
                        sailed back to Utica and recalled Octavius thither also. As the latter was
                        on his way to Tunis he was informed that Vermina, the son of Syphax, was
                        coming to the aid of the Carthaginians with a force consisting mainly of
                        cavalry. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Octavius attacked the Numidians
                        whilst on the march with a portion of his infantry and the whole of his
                        cavalry. The action took place on December I7, and soon ended in the utter
                        rout of the Numidians. As they were completely surrounded by the Roman
                        cavalry all avenues of escape were closed; 15,000 were killed and 1200 taken
                        prisoners, 1500 horses were also secured and 72 standards. The prince
                        himself escaped with a few horsemen. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        Romans then reoccupied their old position at Tunis, and here an embassy
                        consisting of thirty delegates had an interview with Scipio. Though they
                        adopted a much humbler tone than on the previous occasion, as indeed their
                        desperate condition demanded, they were listened to with much less sympathy
                        on account of their recent breach of faith. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> At first the council of war, moved by a righteous indignation, were in
                        favour of the complete destruction of Carthage. When, however, they
                        reflected on the greatness of the task and the length of time which the
                        investment of so strong and well-fortified a city would occupy, they felt
                        considerable hesitation. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Scipio himself
                        too was afraid that his successor might come and claim the glory of
                        terminating the war, after the way had been prepared for it by another man's
                        toils and dangers. So there was a unanimous verdict in favour of peace being
                        made. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day the envoys were again
                        summoned before the council and severely taken to task for their want of
                        truth and honesty, and they were admonished to lay to heart the lesson
                        taught by their numerous defeats and to believe in the power of the gods and
                        the sanctity of oaths. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The conditions of
                        peace were then stated to them. They were to be a free State, living under
                        their own laws; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> all the cities, all the
                        territory and all the frontiers that they had held before the war they were
                        to continue to hold, and the Romans would on that day cease from all further
                        depredations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were to restore to the
                        Romans all the deserters, refugees and prisoners, to deliver up their
                        warships, retaining only ten triremes and all their trained elephants, at
                        the same time undertaking not to train any more. They were not to make war
                        either within or beyond the frontiers of Africa without the permission of
                        Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They were to restore all his
                        possessions to Masinissa and make a treaty with him. Pending the return of
                        the envoys from Rome they were to supply corn and pay to the auxiliaries in
                        the Roman army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were also to pay a
                        war indemnity of 10,000 talents of silver, the payment to be in equal annual
                        instalments, extending over fifty years. One hundred hostages were to be
                        handed over, to be selected by Scipio between the ages of fourteen and
                        thirty years. Finally, he undertook to grant them an armistice if the
                        transports which had been seized during the previous truce were restored
                        with all that they contained. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Otherwise
                        there would be no armistice, nor any hopes of peace. </p>
                    <p> When the envoys brought these terms back and laid them before the Assembly,
                        Gisgo came forward and protested against any proposals for peace. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The populace, alike opposed to peace and
                        incapable of war, were giving him a favourable hearing when Hannibal,
                        indignant at such arguments being urged at such a crisis, seized him and
                        dragged him by main force off the platform. This was an unusual sight in a
                        free community, and the people were loud in their disapproval. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The soldier, taken aback by the free expression
                        of opinion on the part of his fellow-citizens, said, "I left you when I was
                        nine years old, and now after thirty-six years' absence I have returned. The
                        art of war which I have been taught from my boyhood, first as a private
                        soldier and then in high command, I think I am fairly well acquainted with.
                        The rules and laws and customs of civic life and of the forum I must learn
                        from you." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After this apology for his
                        inexperience, he discussed the terms of peace and showed that they were not
                        unreasonable and that their acceptance was a necessity. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The greatest difficulty of all concerned the transports
                        seized during the armistice, for nothing was to be found but the ships
                        themselves, and any investigation would be difficult, as those who would be
                        charged were the opponents of peace. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It
                        was decided that the ships should be restored and that in any case search
                        should be made for the crews. It was left to Scipio to put a value on
                        whatever else was missing and the Carthaginians were to pay the amount in
                        cash. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> According to some writers, Hannibal
                        went down to the coast straight from the battlefield, and going on board a
                        ship which was in readiness, set sail immediately for the court of King
                        Antiochus, and when Scipio insisted before all else upon his surrender, he
                        was told that Hannibal was not in Africa. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the return of the envoys to Scipio
                        the quaestors received instructions to make an inventory from the public
                        registers of all the government property in the transports, and all the
                        private property was to be notified by the owners. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Twenty-five thousand pounds of silver were required to
                        be paid down as an equivalent for the pecuniary value, and a three months'
                        armistice granted to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A
                        further stipulation was made that as long as the armistice was in force,
                        they should not send envoys to any place but Rome, and if any envoys came to
                        Carthage they were not to allow them to leave until the Roman commander had
                        been informed of the object of their visit. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> The Carthaginians envoys were accompanied to Rome by L. Veturius Philo,
                        M. Marcius Ralla and L. Scipio the commander-in-chief's brother. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> During this time the supplies which arrived from
                        Sicily and Sardinia made provisions so cheap that the traders left the corn
                        for the sailors in return for its freight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The first news of the resumption of hostilities by Carthage created
                        considerable uneasiness in Rome. Tiberius Claudius was ordered to take a
                        fleet without loss of time to Sicily and from there to Africa; the other
                        consul was ordered to remain in the City until the position of affairs in
                        Africa was definitely known. Tib. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Claudius
                        was extremely slow in getting his fleet ready and putting out to sea, for
                        the senate had decided that Scipio rather than he, though consul, should be
                        empowered to fix the terms on which peace should be granted. The general
                        alarm at the tidings from Africa was increased by rumours of various
                        portents. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At Cumae the sun's disk was seen
                        to diminish in size and there was a shower of stones; in the district of
                        Veliternum the ground subsided and immense caverns were formed in which
                        trees were swallowed up; at Aricia the forum and the shops round it were
                        struck by lightning, as were also portions of the walls of Frusino and one
                        of the gates; there was also a shower of stones on the Palatine. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The latter portent was expiated, according to the
                        traditional usage, by continuous prayer and sacrifice for nine days, the
                        others by sacrifice of full-grown victims. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> In the middle of all these troubles there was an extraordinarily heavy
                        rainfall which was also regarded as supernatural. The Tiber rose so high
                        that the Circus was flooded and arrangements were made to celebrate the
                        Games of Apollo outside the Colline Gate at the temple of Venus Erucina.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the actual day, however, the sky
                        suddenly cleared and the procession which had started for the Colline Gate
                        was recalled and conducted to the Circus as it was announced that the water
                        had subsided. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The return of the solemn
                        spectacle to its proper place added to the public joy and also to the number
                        of spectators. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At last the consul took his departure from
                        the City. He was, however, caught in a violent storm between the ports of
                        Cosa and Loretum, and was in the greatest danger, but he succeeded in making
                        the harbour of Populonia, where he remained at anchor till the tempest wore
                        itself out. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From there he sailed to Elba,
                        then on to Corsica and from there to Sardinia. Here, whilst rounding the
                        Montes Insani, he was caught in a much more violent storm and off a much
                        more dangerous coast. His fleet was scattered, many of his vessels were
                        dismantled and sprang leaks, some were totally wrecked. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> With his fleet thus tempest-tossed and shattered he
                        found shelter at Caralis. Whilst he was repairing his ships here winter
                        overtook him. His year of office expired, and as he received no extension of
                        command he brought his fleet back to Rome in a private capacity. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Before leaving for his province M. Servilius
                        named C. Servilius Dictator in order to avoid being recalled to conduct the
                        elections. The Dictator appointed P. Aelius Paetus Master of the Horse.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In spite of various dates being fixed
                        for the elections the weather prevented them from being held. Consequently,
                        when the magistrates went out of office on March 14 no new ones had been
                        appointed and the republic was without any curule magistrates. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The pontifex T. Manlius Torquatus died this year
                        and his place was filled by C. Sulpicius Galba. The Roman Games were
                        celebrated three times by the curule aediles L. Licinius Lucullus and Q.
                        Fulvius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some of the secretaries and
                        messengers of the aediles were found guilty on the evidence of witnesses of
                        abstracting money from the aediles' chest and Lucullus was seriously
                        compromised in the matter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The plebeian
                        aediles, P. Aelius Tubero and L. Laetorius, were found to have been
                        irregularly appointed and resigned office. Before this happened, however,
                        they had celebrated the Plebeian Games and the festival of Jupiter and had
                        also placed in the Capitol three statues made out of the silver paid in
                        fines. The Dictator and the Master of the Horse were authorised by the
                        senate to celebrate the Games in honour of Ceres. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the arrival of the Roman commissioners
                        from Africa, simultaneously with that of the Carthaginians, the senate met
                        at the temple of Bellona. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> L. Veturius
                        Philo reported that Carthage had made her last effort, a battle had been
                        fought with Hannibal and an end had at last been put to this disastrous war.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This announcement was received by the
                        senators with huge delight, and Veturius reported a further success though
                        comparatively an unimportant one, namely the defeat of Vermina, the son of
                        Syphax. He was ordered to go to the Assembly and make the people sharers in
                        the good news. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Amidst universal
                        congratulations all the temples in the City were thrown open and public
                        thanksgivings were ordered for three days. The envoys from Carthage and
                        those from Philip who had also arrived, requested an audience of the senate.
                        The Dictator, at the instance of the senate, informed them that the new
                        consuls would grant them one. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        elections were then held and Cnaeus Cornelius Lentulus and P. Aelius Paetus
                        were made consuls. The praetors elected were M. Junius Pennus, to whom the
                        City jurisdiction was allotted; M. Valerius Falto, to whom Bruttium fell; M.
                        Fabius Buteo, who received Sardinia, and P. Aelius Tubero, to whom the
                        ballot gave Sicily. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As to the consuls'
                        provinces it was agreed that nothing should be done until Philip's envoys
                        and those from Carthage had obtained an audience. No sooner was one war at
                        an end than there was the prospect of another commencing. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The consul Cnaeus Lentulus was keenly desirous of
                        obtaining Africa as his province; if the war should continue, he looked
                        forward to an easy victory; if it were coming to an end he was anxious to
                        have the glory of terminating so great a struggle. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> He gave out that he would not allow any business to be
                        transacted until Africa had been decreed to him as his province. His
                        colleague being a moderate and sensible man gave way, he saw that to attempt
                        to wrest Scipio's glory from him would be not only unjust but hopeless.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Two of the tribunes of the plebs-Q.
                        Minucius Thermus and Manlius Acilius Glabrio-declared that Cnaeus Cornelius
                        was attempting to do what Tiberius Claudius had failed to do, and that after
                        the senate had authorised the question of the supreme command in Africa to
                        be referred to the Assembly, the thirty-five tribes had unanimously decreed
                        it to Scipio. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After numerous debates both
                        in the senate and in the assembly it was finally settled to leave the matter
                        to the senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was arranged that the
                        senators should vote on oath, and their decision was that the consuls should
                        come to a mutual understanding, or failing that, should resort to <milestone
                            n="12??" unit="section"/> the ballot, as to which of them should have
                        Italy and which should take command of the fleet of fifty vessels. The one
                        to whom the fleet was assigned was to sail to Sicily, and if it proved
                        impossible to make peace with Carthage, he was to proceed to Africa.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The consul was to act by sea; Scipio,
                        retaining his full powers, was to conduct the campaign on land. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> If the terms of peace were agreed upon the
                        tribunes of the plebs were to ask the people whether it was their will that
                        peace should be granted by the consul or by Scipio. And also if the
                        victorious army was to be brought away from Africa, they were to decide who
                        should bring it. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Should the people
                        resolve that peace was to be concluded through Scipio and that he was also
                        to bring the army back, then the consul was not to sail for Africa.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The other consul, who had Italy for
                        his province, was to take over two legions from the praetor M. Sextius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Scipio received an extension of his
                        command and retained the armies he had in Africa. The two legions in
                        Bruttium which had been under C. Livius were transferred to the praetor M.
                        Valerius Falto <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> and the two legions in
                        Sicily under Cnaeus Tremellius were to be taken over by the praetor P.
                        Aelius. The legion in Sardinia, commanded by the propraetor P. Lentulus, was
                        assigned to M. Fabius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> M. Servilius, the
                        consul of the previous year, was continued in command of his two legions in
                        Etruria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With regard to Spain, L.
                        Cornelius Lentulus and L. Manlius Acidinus had been there for some years and
                        the consuls were to arrange with the tribunes to ask the Assembly to decide
                        who should command in Spain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The general
                        appointed was to form one legion of Romans out of the two armies and fifteen
                        cohorts of Latin allies, with which to hold the province, and L. Cornelius
                        and L. Manlius were to bring the old soldiers home. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Whichever consul received Africa as his province was to
                        select fifty ships out of the two fleets, i.e., the one which Cnaeus
                        Octavius was commanding in African waters and the one with which P. Villius
                        was guarding the Sicilian seaboard. P. Scipio was to keep the forty warships
                        which he had. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Should the consul wish Cn.
                        Octavius to continue in command of his fleet, he would take rank as
                        propraetor; if he gave the command to Laelius, then Octavius was to leave
                        for Rome and bring back the ships which the consul did not want. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Ten warships were also assigned to M. Fabius for
                        Sardinia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In addition to the
                        above-mentioned troops the consuls were ordered to raise two City legions so
                        that there might be fourteen legions and one hundred ships of war at the
                        disposal of the republic for the year. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the admission of the embassies from
                        Philip and the Carthaginians was discussed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> It was decided that the Macedonians should be introduced first. Their
                        address dealt with various points. They began by disclaiming all
                        responsibility for the depredations on the friendly countries of which the
                        Roman envoys had complained to the king. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Then they themselves brought charges against the allies of Rome and a much
                        more serious one against M. Aurelius, one of the three envoys, who they said
                        had stayed behind and after raising a body of troops commenced hostilities
                        against them in violation of treaty rights, and fought several engagements
                        with their commanders. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They ended with a
                        demand that the Macedonians with their general Sopater who had served as
                        mercenaries under Hannibal and were then prisoners in chains should be
                        restored to them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In reply, M. Furius, who
                        had been sent from Macedonia by Aurelius to represent him, pointed out that
                        Aurelius had certainly been left behind, but it was for the purpose of
                        preventing the allies of Rome from being driven to secede to the king in
                        consequence of the injuries and depredations from which they were suffering.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He had not overstepped their
                        frontiers; he had made it his business to see that no hordes of plunderers
                        crossed those frontiers with impunity. Sopater, who was one of the
                        purple-clad nobles who stood near the throne and was related to the monarch,
                        had recently been sent to Africa to assist Hannibal and Carthage with money
                        and also with a force of 4000 Macedonians. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On being questioned as to these matters
                        the Macedonians gave unsatisfactory and evasive replies, and consequently
                        the answer they received from the senate was anything but favourable.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were told that their king was
                        looking for war, and if he went on as he was doing, he would very soon find
                        it. He had been guilty of a twofold breach of treaty, for he had committed
                        wanton aggression on the allies of Rome by hostile arms and he had also
                        aided the enemies of Rome with men and money. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio was acting rightly and legitimately in treating
                        those taken in arms against Rome as enemies and keeping them in chains.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> M. Aurelius also was acting in the
                        interests of the State-and the senate thanked him for it-when he afforded
                        armed protection to the allies of Rome since treaty rights were powerless
                        for their defence. With this stern reply the Macedonian envoys were
                        dismissed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then the Carthaginians were
                        called in. As soon as their age and rank were recognised, for they were
                        quite the foremost men in the State, the senators remarked that now it was
                        really a question of peace. Conspicuous amongst them all was Hasdrubal, on
                        whom his countrymen had bestowed the sobriquet of "Haedus." <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> He had always been an advocate of peace and an
                        opponent of the Barcine party. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This gave
                        his words additional weight when he disavowed all responsibility for the war
                        on behalf of his government and fastened it on a few ambitious and grasping
                        individuals. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> His speech was discursive and eloquent.
                        He repudiated some of the charges, others he admitted lest unabashed denials
                        of established facts might lead to less consideration being shown. He warned
                        the senators to use their good fortune in a spirit of moderation and
                        self-restraint. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> "If," he continued, "the
                        Carthaginians had listened to Hanno and myself and had been willing to take
                        advantage of their opportunity, they would have dictated the terms of peace
                        which now they are seeking from you. Seldom are good fortune and good sense
                        granted to men at the same time. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> What
                        makes Rome invincible is the fact that her people do not lose their sound
                        judgment in the hour of prosperity. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> And
                        indeed it would be a matter for surprise were it otherwise, for those to
                        whom good fortune is a novelty go mad with unrestrained delight because they
                        are unused to it, but to you Romans the joy of victory is a usual, I might
                        almost say a commonplace experience. It is by clemency towards the conquered
                        more than by conquest itself that you have extended your dominion."
                            <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The others spoke in language more
                        calculated to evoke compassion. They reminded their audience of the powerful
                        and influential position from which Carthage had fallen. Those, they said,
                        who lately held almost the whole world subject to their arms had nothing now
                        left to them but their city walls. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                        Confined within these they saw nothing on land or sea which owned their
                        sway. Even their city and their hearths and homes they would only keep if
                        the Roman people were willing to spare them; if not, they lost everything.
                            <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> As it became evident that the
                        senators were moved with compassion, one of them, exasperated by the perfidy
                        of the Carthaginians, is said to have called out, "By what gods will you
                        swear to observe the treaty, since you have been false to those by whom you
                        swore before?" <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> "By the same as before,"
                        Hasdrubal replied, "since they visit their wrath on those who violate
                        treaties." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst all were in favour of peace the
                        consul Cnaeus Lentulus, who was in command of the fleet, prevented the House
                        from passing any resolution. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thereupon,
                        two tribunes of the plebs, Manius Acilius and Q. Minucius, at once brought
                        the questions before the people: Was it their will and pleasure that the
                        senate should pass a decree for the conclusion of peace with Carthage? Who
                        was to grant the peace? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and Who was to
                        bring away the army from Africa? On the question of peace all the tribes
                        voted in the affirmative; they also made an order that Scipio should grant
                        the peace and bring the army home. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                        pursuance of this decision the senate decreed that P. Scipio should, in
                        agreement with the ten commissioners, make peace with the people or Carthage
                        on such terms as he thought right. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On this
                        the Carthaginians expressed their thanks to the senators, and begged that
                        they might be allowed to enter the City and converse with their
                        fellow-countrymen who were detained as State-prisoners. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> These were members of the nobility, some of them their
                        own friends and relations, and others there were for whom they had messages
                        from their friends at home. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this was
                        arranged they made a further request that they might be allowed to ransom
                        any of the prisoners whom they wished. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        They were told to furnish the names, and they gave in about two hundred. The
                        senate then passed a resolution that a commission should be appointed to
                        take back to P. Scipio in Africa two hundred of the prisoners whom the
                        Carthaginians had selected and to inform him that if peace were established
                        he was to restore them to the Carthaginians without ransom. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> When the fetials received orders to proceed to Africa
                        for the purpose of striking the treaty they requested the senate to define
                        the procedure. The senate accordingly decided upon this formula: "The
                        fetials shall take with them their own flints and their own herbs; when a
                        Roman praetor orders them to strike the treaty they shall demand the sacred
                        herbs from him." <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The herbs given to the
                        fetials are usually taken from the Citadel. The Carthaginian envoys were at
                        length dismissed and returned to Scipio. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        They concluded peace with him on the terms mentioned above, and delivered up
                        their warships, their elephants, the deserters and refugees and 4000
                        prisoners including Q. Terentius Calleo, a senator. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Scipio ordered the ships to be taken out to sea and
                        burnt. Some authorities state that there were 500 vessels, comprising every
                        class propelled by oars. The sight of all those vessels suddenly bursting
                        into flames caused as much grief to the people as if Carthage itself were
                        burning. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The deserters were dealt with
                        much more severely than the fugitives; those belonging to the Latin
                        contingents were beheaded, the Romans were crucified. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The last time peace was concluded with
                        Carthage was in the consulship of Q. Lutatius and A. Manlius, forty years
                        previously. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Twenty-three years afterwards
                        the war began in the consulship of P. Cornelius and Tiberius Sempronius. It
                        ended in the consulship of Cnaeus Cornelius and P. Aelius Paetus, seventeen
                        years later. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Tradition tells of a remark
                        which Scipio is said to have frequently made to the effect that it was owing
                        to the jealous ambition of Tiberius Claudius and afterwards to that of
                        Cnaeus Cornelius that the war did not end with the destruction of Carthage.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Carthage found a difficulty in meeting
                        the first instalment of the war indemnity as her treasury was exhausted.
                        There was lamentation and weeping in the senate and in the middle of it all
                        Hannibal is said to have been seen smiling. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> Hasdrubal Haedus rebuked him for his mirth amid the nation's tears. "If,"
                        Hannibal replied, "you could discern my inmost thoughts as plainly as you
                        can tell the expression of my countenance you would easily discover that
                        this laughter which you find fault with does not proceed from a merry heart
                        but from one almost demented with misery. All the same, it is very far from
                        being so ill-timed as those foolish and misplaced tears of yours. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The proper time to weep was when we were deprived
                        of our arms, when our ships were burnt, when we were interdicted from all
                        war beyond our frontiers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That is the
                        wound that will prove fatal. There is not the slightest reason for supposing
                        that the Romans are consulting your peace and quietness. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> No great State can remain quiet; if it has no enemy
                        abroad it finds one at home, just as excessively strong men, whilst
                        seemingly safe from outside mischief, fall victims to the burden of their
                        own strength. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Of course we only feel
                        public calamities so far as they affect us personally, and nothing in them
                        gives us a sharper pang than the loss of money. When the spoils of victory
                        were being dragged away from Carthage when you saw yourselves left naked and
                        defenceless amidst an Africa in arms, nobody uttered a groan; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> now because you have to contribute to the
                        indemnity from your private fortunes you lament as loudly as though you were
                        present at your country's funeral. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I
                        greatly fear that you will very soon find that it is the least of your
                        misfortunes which you are shedding tears over today." Such was the way in
                        which Hannibal spoke to the Carthaginians. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> Scipio summoned his troops to assembly, and in the presence of the whole
                        army rewarded Masinissa by adding to his ancestral realm the town of Cirta
                        and the other cities and districts which had belonged to the dominion of
                        Syphax and had passed under the rule of Rome. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Cnaeus Octavius received instructions to take the fleet
                        to Sicily and hand it over to the consul Cnaeus Cornelius. Scipio told the
                        Carthaginian envoys to start for Rome in order that the arrangements he had
                        made in consultation with the ten commissioners might receive the sanction
                        of the senate and the formal order of the people. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As peace was now established on land and
                        sea Scipio embarked his army and sailed to Lilybaeum. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> From there he sent the greater part of his army on in
                        the ships, whilst he himself travelled through Italy. The country was
                        rejoicing quite as much over the restoration of peace as over the victory he
                        had won, and he made his way to Rome through multitudes who poured out from
                        the cities to do him honour, and crowds of peasants who blocked the roads in
                        the country districts. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The triumphal
                        procession in which he rode into the City was the most brilliant that had
                        ever been seen. The weight of silver which he brought into the treasury
                        amounted to 123,000 pounds. Out of the booty he distributed forty ases to
                        each soldier. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Syphax had died shortly
                        before at Tibur whither he had been transferred from Alba, but his removal,
                        if it detracted from the interest of the spectacle, in no way dimmed the
                        glory of the triumphing general. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His
                        death, however, provided another spectacle, for he received a public
                        funeral. Polybius, an authority of considerable weight, says that this king
                        was led in the procession. Q. Terentius Culleo marched behind Scipio wearing
                        the cap of liberty, and in all his after-life honoured as was meet the
                        author of his freedom. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As to the sobriquet
                        of Africanus, whether it was conferred upon him by the devotion of his
                        soldiers or by the popular breath, or whether as in the recent instances of
                        Sylla the Fortunate and Pompey the Great it originated in the flattery of
                        his friends, I cannot say for certain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At
                        all events, he was the first commander-in-chief who was ennobled by the name
                        of the people he had conquered. Since his time men who have won far smaller
                        victories have in imitation of him left splendid inscriptions on their busts
                        and illustrious names to their families. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
