<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd">
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Life of Cnaeus Julius Agricola</title>
<author>Cornelius Tacitus</author>
<editor role="translator">Alfred John Church</editor>
<editor role="translator">William Jackson Brodribb</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
        <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
        <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
        <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>about 1204 lines</extent>
    <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2001-03-12</date>
    </publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>The Agricola and Germany of Tacitus</title>
<author>Tacitus</author>
<respStmt>
<name>Sara Bryant</name>
<resp>edited for Perseus</resp>
</respStmt>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>MacMillan and Co.</publisher>
<date>1868</date>
</imprint>
    <imprint>
        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
        <date>1942 reprint</date>
    </imprint>
</monogr>
    <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uva.x000756690">HathiTrust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>

<body>

<div1 type="book">
<head>THE LIFE OF CN&AElig;US JULIUS 
AGRICOLA</head>
<div2 type="chapter" n="1"><p>To bequeath to posterity a 
record of the deeds and characters of distinguished men is an ancient 
practice which even the present age, careless as it is of its own sons, has 
not abandoned whenever some great and conspicuous excellence has conquered 
and risen superior to that failing, common to petty and to great states, 
blindness and hostility to goodness. But in days gone by, as there was a 
greater inclination and a more open path to the achievement of memorable 
actions, so the man of highest genius was led by the simple reward of a good 
conscience to hand on without partiality or self-seeking the remembrance of 
greatness. Many too thought that to write their own lives showed the 
confidence of integrity rather than presumption. Of Rutilius and Scaurus no 
one doubted the honesty or questioned the motives. So true is it that merit 
is best appreciated by the age in which it thrives most easily. But in these 
days, I, who have to record the life of one who has passed away, must crave 
an indulgence, which I should not have had to ask had I only to inveigh 
against an age so cruel, so hostile to all virtue.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="2"><p>We have read that the panegyrics pronounced by 
Arulenus Rusticus on P&aelig;tus Thrasea, and by Herennius Senecio on 
Priscus Helvidius, were made capital crimes, that not only their persons but 
their very books were objects of rage, and that the triumvirs were 
commissioned to burn in the forum those works of splendid genius. They 
fancied, forsooth, that in that fire the voice of the Roman people, the 
freedom of the Senate, and the conscience of the human race were perishing, 
while at the same time they banished the teachers of philosophy, and exiled 
every noble pursuit, that nothing good might anywhere confront them. 
Certainly we

showed a magnificent example of patience; as a 
former age had witnessed the extreme of liberty, so we witnessed the extreme 
of servitude, when the informer robbed us of the interchange of speech and 
hearing. We should have lost memory as well as voice, had it been as easy to 
forget as to keep silence.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="3"><p>Now at last 
our spirit is returning. And yet, though at the dawn of a most happy age 
Nerva C&aelig;sar blended things once irreconcilable, sovereignty and 
freedom, though Nerva Trajan is now daily augmenting the prosperity of the 
time, and though the public safety has not only our hopes and good wishes, 
but has also the certain pledge of their fulfillment, still, from the 
necessary condition of human frailty, the remedy works less quickly than the 
disease. As our bodies grow but slowly, perish in a moment, so it is easier 
to crush than to revive genius and its pursuits. Besides, the charm of 
indolence steals over us, and the idleness which at first we loathed we 
afterwards love. What if during those fifteen years, a large portion of 
human life, many were cut off by ordinary casualties, and the ablest fell 
victims to the Emperor's rage, if a few of us survive, I may almost say, not 
only others but our ownselves, survive, though there have been taken from 
the midst of life those many years which brought the young in dumb silence 
to old age, and the old almost to the very verge and end of existence! Yet 
we shall not regret that we have told, though in language unskilful and 
unadorned, the story of past servitude, and borne our testimony to present 
happiness. Meanwhile this book, intended to do honour to <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, my 
father-in-law, will, as an expression of filial regard, be commended, or at 
least excused.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="4"><p>Cn&aelig;us Julius 
Agricola was born at the ancient and famous colony of <rs type="placename">Forum Julii</rs>. Each of his grandfathers was an Imperial 
procurator, that is, of the highest equestrian rank. His father, Julius 
Gr&aelig;cinus, a member of the Senatorian order, and distinguished for his 
pursuit of eloquence and philosophy, earned for himself by these very merits 
the displeasure of Caius C&aelig;sar. He was ordered to impeach Marcus 
Silanus, and because he refused was put to death. His mother was Julia 
Procilla, a lady of singular virtue.

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">BIRTH, 
EDUCATION, APPRENTICESHIP</note>
Brought up by her side with fond affection, 
he passed his boyhood and youth in the cultivation of every worthy 
attainment. He was guarded from the enticements of the profligate not only 
by his own good and straightforward character, but also by having, when 
quite a child, for the scene and guide of his studies, <rs type="placename">Massilia</rs>, a place where refinement and provincial 
frugality were blended and happily combined. I remember that he used to tell 
us how in his early youth he would have imbibed a keener love of philosophy 
than became a Roman and a senator, had not his mother's good sense checked 
his excited and ardent spirit. It was the case of a lofty and aspiring soul 
craving with more eagerness than caution the beauty and splendour of great 
and glorious renown. But it was soon mellowed by reason and experience, and 
he retained from his learning that most difficult of 
lessons&mdash;moderation.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="5"><p>He served his 
military apprenticeship in <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> to the 
satisfaction of Suetonius Paullinus, a painstaking and judicious officer, 
who, to test his merits, selected him to share his tent. Without the 
recklessness with which young men often make the profession of arms a mere 
pastime, and without indolence, he never availed himself of his tribune's 
rank or his inexperience to procure enjoyment or to escape from duty. He 
sought to make himself acquainted with the province and known to the army; 
he would learn from the skilful, and keep pace with the bravest, would 
attempt nothing for display, would avoid nothing from fear, and would be at 
once careful and vigilant. </p>
<p>Never indeed had <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> been more excited, or in a more critical 
condition. Veteran soldiers had been massacred, colonies burnt, armies cut 
off. The struggle was then for safety; it was soon to be for victory. And 
though all this was conducted under the leadership and direction of another, 
though the final issue and the glory of having won back the province 
belonged to the general, yet skill, experience, and ambition were acquired 
by the young officer. His soul too was penetrated with the desire of warlike 
renown, a sentiment unwelcome to an age which put a sinister construction on 
eminent merit, and made glory as perilous as infamy.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="6"><p>From <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> he went to <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>, to go through the regu-

lar course of 
office, and there allied himself with Domitia Decidiana, a lady of 
illustrious birth. The marriage was one which gave a man ambitious of 
advancement distinction and support. They lived in singular harmony, through 
their mutual affection and preference of each other to self. However, the 
good wife deserves the greater praise, just as the bad incurs a heavier 
censure.</p>
<p>Appointed Qu&aelig;stor, the ballot gave him <rs type="placename">Asia</rs> for his province, Salvius Titianus for his 
proconsul. Neither the one nor the other corrupted him, though the province 
was rich and an easy prey to the wrongdoer, while the proconsul, a man 
inclined to every species of greed, was ready by all manner of indulgence to 
purchase a mutual concealment of guilt. </p>
<p>A daughter was there added to 
his family to be his stay and comfort, for shortly after he lost the son 
that had before been born to him. The year between his qu&aelig;storship and 
tribunate, as well as the year of the tribunate itself, he passed in 
retirement and inaction, for he knew those times of <placeName key="tgn,2538429">Nero</placeName> when indolence 
stood for wisdom. His pr&aelig;torship was passed in the same consistent 
quietude, for the usual judicial functions did not fall to his lot. The 
games and the pageantry of his office he ordered according to the mean 
between strictness and profusion, avoiding extravagance, but not missing 
distinction. He was afterwards appointed by Galba to draw up an account of 
the temple offerings, and his searching scrutiny relieved the conscience of 
the state from the burden of all sacrileges but those committed by 
Nero.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="7"><p>The following year inflicted a 
terrible blow on his affections and his fortunes. Otho's fleet, while 
cruising idly about, cruelly ravaged <rs type="placename">Intemelii</rs>, a 
district of <rs type="placename">Liguria</rs>; his mother, who was living here 
on her own estate, was murdered. The estate itself and a large part of her 
patrimony were plundered. This was indeed the occasion of the crime. 
<placeName key="tgn,2018415">Agricola</placeName>, who instantly set out to discharge the duties of affection, was 
overtaken by the tidings that Vespasian was aiming at the throne. He at once 
joined his party. Vespasian's early policy, and the government of <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> were directed by Mucianus, for Domitian was a mere 
youth, and from his father's elevation sought only the opportunities of 
indulgence.

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">MARRIAGE, OFFICES, 
ADVANCEMENT</note></p>
<p><placeName key="tgn,2055831">Agricola</placeName>, having been sent by Mucianus to conduct a 
levy of troops, and having done his work with integrity and energy, was 
appointed to command the 20th Legion, which had been slow to take the new 
oath of allegiance, and the retiring officer of which was reported to be 
acting disloyally. It was a trying and formidable charge for even officers 
of consular rank, and the late pr&aelig;torian officer, perhaps from his own 
disposition, perhaps from that of the soldiers, was powerless to restrain 
them. Chosen thus at once to supersede and to punish, <placeName key="tgn,2055831">Agricola</placeName>, with a 
singular moderation, wished it to be thought that he had found rather than 
made an obedient soldiery.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="8"><p><rs type="placename">Britain</rs> was then under Vettius Bolanus, who governed 
more mildly than suited so turbulent a province. <placeName key="tgn,2055831">Agricola</placeName> moderated his 
energy and restrained his ardour, that he might not grow too important, for 
he had learnt to obey, and understood well how to combine expediency with 
honour. Soon afterwards <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> received for its 
governor a man of consular rank, Petilius Cerialis. Agricola's merits had 
now room for display. Cerialis let him share at first indeed only the toils 
and dangers, but before long the glory of war, often by way of trial putting 
him in command of part of the army, and sometimes, on the strength of the 
result, of larger forces. Never to enhance his own renown did Agricola boast 
of his exploits; he always referred his success, as though he were but an 
instrument, to his general and director. Thus by his valour in obeying 
orders and by his modesty of speech he escaped jealousy without losing 
distinction.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="9"><p>As he was returning from 
the command of the legion, Vespasian admitted him into the patrician order, 
and then gave him the province of <rs type="placename">Aquitania</rs>, a 
preeminently splendid appointment both from the importance of its duties and 
the prospect of the consulate to which the Emperor destined him. Many think 
the genius of the soldier wants subtlety, because military law, which is 
summary and blunt, and apt to appeal to the sword, finds no exercise for the 
refinements of the forum. Yet Agricola, from his natural good sense, though 
called to act among civilians, did his work with ease and correctness. And, 
besides, the times of business and relaxation were kept distinct. When his 
public and judicial

duties required it, he was dignified, 
thoughtful, austere, and yet often merciful; when business was done with, he 
wore no longer the official character. He was altogether without harshness, 
pride, or the greed of gain. With a most rare felicity, his good nature did 
not weaken his authority, nor his strictness the attachment of his friends. 
To speak of uprightness and purity in such a man would be an insult to his 
virtues. Fame itself, of which even good men are often weakly fond, he did 
not seek by an ostentation of virtue or by artifice. He avoided rivalry with 
his colleagues, contention with his procurator, thinking such victories no 
honour and defeat disgrace. For somewhat less than three years he was kept 
in his governorship, and was then recalled with an immediate prospect of the 
consulate. A general belief went with him that the province of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> was to be his, not because he had himself hinted 
it, but because he seemed worthy of it. Public opinion is not always 
mistaken; sometimes even it chooses the right man. He was consul, and I but 
a youth, when he betrothed to me his daughter, a maiden even then of noble 
promise. After his consulate he gave her to me in marriage, and was then at 
once appointed to the government of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, with 
the addition of the sacred office of the pontificate.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="10"><p>The geography and inhabitants of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, already described by many writers, I will speak 
of, not that my research and ability may be compared with theirs, but 
because the country was then for the first time thoroughly subdued. And so 
matters, which as being still not accurately known my predecessors 
embellished with their eloquence, shall now be related on the evidence of 
facts. </p>
<p><rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, the largest of the islands which 
Roman geography includes, is so situated that it faces <rs type="placename">Germany</rs> on the east, <rs type="placename">Spain</rs> on 
the west; on the south it is even within sight of <rs type="placename">Gaul</rs>; its northern extremities, which have no shores 
opposite to them, are beaten by the waves of a vast open sea. The form of 
the entire country has been compared by Livy and Fabius Rusticus, the most 
graphic among ancient and modern historians, to an oblong shield or 
battle-axe. And this no doubt is its shape without <rs type="placename">Caledonia</rs>, so that it has become the popular description 
of the whole island. There

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">GEOGRAPHY AND 
ETHNOLOGY OF <rs type="placename">BRITAIN</rs></note>
is, however, a large and 
irregular tract of land which juts out from its furthest shores, tapering 
off in a wedge-like form. Round these coasts of remotest ocean the Roman 
fleet then for the first time sailed, ascertained that <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> is an island, and simultaneously discovered and 
conquered what are called the <rs type="placename">Orcades</rs>, islands 
hitherto unknown. <rs type="placename">Thule</rs> too was descried in the 
distance, which as yet had been hidden by the snows of winter. Those waters, 
they say, are sluggish, and yield with difficulty to the oar, and are not 
even raised by the wind as other seas. The reason, I suppose, is that lands 
and mountains, which are the cause and origin of storms, are here 
comparatively rare, and also that the vast depths of that unbroken expanse 
are more slowly set in motion. But to investigate the nature of the ocean 
and the tides is no part of the present work, and many writers have 
discussed the subject. I would simply add, that nowhere has the sea a wider 
dominion, that it has many currents running in every direction, that it does 
not merely flow and ebb within the limits of the shore, but penetrates and 
winds far inland, and finds a home among hills and mountains as though in 
its own domain.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="11"><p>Who were the original 
inhabitants of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, whether they were indigenous 
or foreign, is, as usual among barbarians, little known. Their physical 
characteristics are various and from these conclusions may be drawn. The red 
hair and large limbs of the inhabitants of <rs type="placename">Caledonia</rs> 
point clearly to a German origin. The dark complexion of the Silures, their 
usually curly hair, and the fact that <rs type="placename">Spain</rs> is the 
opposite shore to them, are an evidence that Iberians of a former date 
crossed over and occupied these parts. Those who are nearest to the Gauls 
are also like them, either from the permanent influence of original descent, 
or, because in countries which run out so far to meet each other, climate 
has produced similar physical qualities. But a general survey inclines me to 
believe that the Gauls established themselves in an island so near to them. 
Their religious belief may be traced in the strongly-marked British 
superstition. The language differs but little; there is the same boldness in 
challenging danger, and, when it is near, the same timidity in shrinking 
from it. The Britons, however, exhibit more spirit, as being a people

whom a long peace has not yet enervated. Indeed we have understood 
that even the Gauls were once renowned in war; but, after a while, sloth 
following on ease crept over them, and they lost their courage along with 
their freedom. This too has happened to the long-conquered tribes of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>; the rest are still what the Gauls once 
were.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="12"><p>Their strength is in infantry. 
Some tribes fight also with the chariot. The higher in rank is the 
charioteer; the dependants fight. They were once ruled by kings, but are now 
divided under chieftains into factions and parties. Our greatest advantage 
in coping with tribes so powerful is that they do not act in concert. Seldom 
is it that two or three states meet together to ward off a common danger. 
Thus, while they fight singly, all are conquered. </p>
<p>Their sky is obscured 
by continual rain and cloud. Severity of cold is unknown. The days exceed in 
length those of our part of the world; the nights are bright, and in the 
extreme north so short that between sunlight and dawn you can perceive but a 
slight distinction. It is said that, if there are no clouds in the way, the 
splendour of the sun can be seen throughout the night, and that he does not 
rise and set, but only crosses the heavens. The truth is, that the low 
shadow thrown from the flat extremities of the earth's surface does not 
raise the darkness to any height, and the night thus fails to reach the sky 
and stars. </p>
<p>With the exception of the olive and vine, and plants which 
usually grow in warmer climates, the soil will yield, and even abundantly, 
all ordinary produce. It ripens indeed slowly, but is of rapid growth, the 
cause in each case being the same, namely, the excessive moisture of the 
soil and of the atmosphere. <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> contains gold 
and silver and other metals, as the prize of conquest. The ocean, too, 
produces pearls, but of a dusky and bluish hue. Some think that those who 
collect them have not the requisite skill, as in the <rs type="placename">Red 
Sea</rs> the living and breathing pearl is torn from the rocks, while in <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> they are gathered just as they are thrown up. I 
could myself more readily believe that the natural properties of the pearls 
are in fault than our keenness for gain.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="13"><p>The Britons themselves bear cheerfully the conscrip-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">AGRICULTURE, ORGANIZATION</note>
tion, the taxes, and 
the other burdens imposed on them by the Empire, if there be no oppression. 
Of this they are impatient; they are reduced to subjection, not as yet to 
slavery The deified <placeName key="tgn,2008628">Julius</placeName>, the very first Roman who entered <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> with an army, though by a successful engagement 
he struck terror into the inhabitants and gained possession of the coast, 
must be regarded as having indicated rather than transmitted the acquisition 
to future generations. Then came the civil wars, and the arms of our leaders 
were turned against their country, and even when there was peace, there was 
a long neglect of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>. This Augustus spoke of as 
policy, <placeName key="tgn,2720789">Tiberius</placeName> as an inherited maxim. That Caius C&aelig;sar meditated an 
invasion of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> is perfectly clear, but his 
purposes, rapidly formed, were easily changed, and his vast attempts on <rs type="placename">Germany</rs> had failed. Claudius was the first to renew the 
attempt, and conveyed over into the island some legions and auxiliaries, 
choosing Vespasian to share with him the campaign, whose approaching 
elevation had this beginning. Several tribes were subdued and kings made 
prisoners, and destiny learnt to know its favourite.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="14"><p>Aulus Plautius was the first governor of consular 
rank, and Ostorius Scapula the next. Both were famous soldiers, and by 
degrees the nearest portions of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> were brought 
into the condition of a province, and a colony of veterans was also 
introduced. Some of the states were given to king Cogidumnus, who lived down 
to our day a most faithful ally. So was maintained the ancient and 
long-recognised practice of the Roman people, which seeks to secure among 
the instruments of dominion even kings themselves. Soon after, Didius Gallus 
consolidated the conquests of his predecessors, and advanced a very few 
positions into parts more remote, to gain the credit of having enlarged the 
sphere of government. Didius was succeeded by Veranius, who died within the 
year. Then Suetonius Paullinus enjoyed success for two years; he subdued 
several tribes and strengthened our military posts. Thus encouraged, he made 
an attempt on the island of <rs type="placename">Mona</rs>, as a place from 
which the rebels drew reinforcements; but in doing this he left his rear 
open to attack.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="15"><p>Relieved from 
apprehension by the legate's absence, the Britons dwelt much among 
themselves on the miseries of

subjection, compared their wrongs, 
and exaggerated them in the discussion. "All we get by patience," they said, 
"is that heavier demands are exacted from us, as from men who will readily 
submit. A single king once ruled us; now two are set over us; a legate to 
tyrannise over our lives, a procurator to tyrannise over our property. Their 
quarrels and their harmony are alike ruinous to their subjects. The 
centurions of the one, the slaves of the other, combine violence with 
insult. Nothing is now safe from their avarice, nothing from their lust. In 
war it is the strong who plunders; now, it is for the most part by cowards 
and poltroons that our homes are rifled, our children torn from us, the 
conscription enforced, as though it were for our country alone that we could 
not die. For, after all, what a mere handful of soldiers has crossed over, 
if we Britons look at our own numbers. <rs type="placename">Germany</rs> did 
thus actually shake off the yoke, and yet its defence was a river, not the 
ocean. With us, fatherland, wives, parents, are the motives to war; with 
them, only greed and profligacy. They will surely fly, as did the now 
deified <placeName key="tgn,2008628">Julius</placeName>, if once we emulate the valour of our sires. Let us not be 
panicstricken at the result of one or two engagements. The miserable have 
more fury and greater resolution. Now even the gods are beginning to pity 
us, for they are keeping away the Roman general, and detaining his army far 
from us in another island. We have already taken the hardest step; we are 
deliberating. And indeed, in all such designs, to dare is less perilous than 
to be detected."</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="16"><p>Rousing each other 
by this and like language, under the leadership of Boudicea, a woman of 
kingly descent (for they admit no distinction of sex in their royal 
successions), they all rose in arms. They fell upon our troops, which were 
scattered on garrison duty, stormed the forts, and burst into the colony 
itself, the head-quarters, as they thought, of tyranny. In their rage and 
their triumph, they spared no variety of a barbarian's cruelty. Had not 
Paullinus on hearing of the outbreak in the province rendered prompt 
succour, <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> would have been lost. By one 
successful engagement, he brought it back to its former obedience, though 
many, troubled by the conscious guilt of rebellion and by particular dread 
of the legate, still clung to their arms. Excellent as he

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">BOUDICEA'S REVOLT CRUSHED</note>
was in other respects, his policy 
to the conquered was arrogant, and exhibited the cruelty of one who was 
avenging private wrongs. Accordingly Petronius Turpilianus was sent out to 
initiate a milder rule. A stranger to the enemy's misdeeds and so more 
accessible to their penitence, he put an end to old troubles, and, 
attempting nothing more, handed the province over to Trebellius Maximus. 
Trebellius, who was somewhat indolent, and never ventured on a campaign, 
controlled the province by a certain courtesy in his administration. Even 
the barbarians now learnt to excuse many attractive vices, and the 
occurrence of the civil war gave a good pretext for inaction. But we were 
sorely troubled with mutiny, as troops habituated to service grew 
demoralised by idleness. Trebellius, who had escaped the soldiers' fury by 
flying and hiding himself, governed henceforth on sufferance, a disgraced 
and humbled man. It was a kind of bargain; the soldiers had their licence, 
the general had his life; and so the mutiny cost no bloodshed. Nor did 
Vettius Bolanus, during the continuance of the civil wars, trouble <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> with discipline. There was the same inaction 
with respect to the enemy, and similar unruliness in the camp, only Bolanus, 
an upright man, whom no misdeeds made odious, had secured affection in 
default of the power of control.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="17"><p>When 
however Vespasian had restored to unity <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> as 
well as the rest of the world, in the presence of great generals and 
renowned armies the enemy's hopes were crushed. They were at once 
panic-stricken by the attack of Petilius Cerialis on the state of the 
Brigantes, said to be the most prosperous in the entire province. There were 
many battles, some by no means bloodless, and his conquests, or at least his 
wars, embraced a large part of the territory of the Brigantes. Indeed he 
would have altogether thrown into the shade the activity and renown of any 
other successor; but Julius Frontinus was equal to the burden, a great man 
as far as greatness was then possible, who subdued by his arms the powerful 
and warlike tribe of the Silures, surmounting the difficulties of the 
country as well as the valour of the enemy.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="18"><p>Such was the state of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, and such 
were the vicissitudes of the war, which <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName> found on his crossing over 
about midsummer. Our soldiers made it a pretext for care-

lessness, as if all fighting was over, and the enemy were biding 
their time. The Ordovices, shortly before <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName>'s arrival, had destroyed 
nearly the whole of a squadron of allied cavalry quartered in their 
territory. Such a beginning raised the hopes of the country, and all who 
wished for war approved the precedent, and anxiously watched the temper of 
the new governor. Meanwhile <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName>, though summer was past and the 
detachments were scattered throughout the province, though the soldiers' 
confident anticipation of inaction for that year would be a source of delay 
and difficulty in beginning a campaign, and most advisers thought it best 
simply to watch all weak points, resolved to face the peril. He collected a 
force of veterans and a small body of auxiliaries; then as the Ordovices 
would not venture to descend into the plain, he put himself in front of the 
ranks to inspire all with the same courage against a common danger, and led 
his troops up a hill. The tribe was all but exterminated. </p>
<p>Well aware 
that he must follow up the prestige of his arms, and that in proportion to 
his first success would be the terror of the other tribes, he formed the 
design of subjugating the island of <rs type="placename">Mona</rs>, from the 
occupation of which Paullinus had been recalled, as I have already related, 
by the rebellion of the entire province. But, as his plans were not matured, 
he had no fleet. The skill and resolution of the general accomplished the 
passage. With some picked men of the auxiliaries, disencumbered of all 
baggage, who knew the shallows and had that national experience in swimming 
which enables the Britons to take care not only of themselves but of their 
arms and horses, he delivered so unexpected an attack that the astonished 
enemy who were looking for a fleet, a naval armament, and an assault by sea, 
thought that to such assailants nothing could be formidable or invincible. 
And so, peace having been sued for and the island given up, <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName> became 
great and famous as one who, when entering on his province, a time which 
others spend in vain display and a round of ceremonies, chose rather toil 
and danger. Nor did he use his success for self-glorification, or apply the 
name of campaigns and victories to the repression of a conquered people. He 
did not even describe his achievements in a laurelled letter. Yet by 
thus

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">MILITARY AND CIVIL SUCCESS</note>
disguising 
his renown he really increased it, for men inferred the grandeur of his 
aspirations from his silence about services so great.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="19"><p>Next, with thorough insight into the feelings of 
his province, and taught also, by the experience of others, that little is 
gained by conquest if followed by oppression, he determined to root out the 
causes of war. Beginning first with himself and his dependants, he kept his 
household under restraint, a thing as hard to many as ruling a province. He 
transacted no public business through freedmen or slaves; no private 
leanings, no recommendations or entreaties of friends, moved him in the 
selection of centurions and soldiers, but it was ever the best man whom he 
thought most trustworthy. He knew everything, but did not always act on his 
knowledge. Trifling errors he treated with leniency, serious offences with 
severity. Nor was it always punishment, but far oftener penitence, which 
satisfied him. He preferred to give office and power to men who would not 
transgress, rather than have to condemn a transgressor. He lightened the 
exaction of corn and tribute by an equal distribution of the burden, while 
he got rid of those contrivances for gain which were more intolerable than 
the tribute itself. Hitherto the people had been compelled to endure the 
farce of waiting by the closed granary and of purchasing corn unnecessarily 
and raising it to a fictitious price. Difficult byroads and distant places 
were fixed for them, so that states with a winter-camp close to them had to 
carry corn to remote and inaccessible parts of the country, until what was 
within the reach of all became a source of profit to the few.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="20"><p><placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName>, by the repression of these abuses in his 
very first year of office, restored to peace its good name, when, from 
either the indifference or the harshness of his predecessors, it had come to 
be as much dreaded as war. When, however, summer came, assembling his 
forces, he continually showed himself in the ranks, praised good discipline, 
and kept the stragglers in order. He would himself choose the position of 
the camp, himself explore the estuaries and forests. Meanwhile he would 
allow the enemy no rest, laying waste his territory with sudden incursions, 
and, having sufficiently alarmed him, would then by forbearance display

the allurements of peace. In consequence, many states, which up to 
that time had been independent, gave hostages, and laid aside their 
animosities; garrisons and forts were established among them with a skill 
and diligence with which no newly-acquired part of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> had before been treated.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="21"><p>The following winter passed without disturbance, 
and was employed in salutary measures. For, to accustom to rest and repose 
through the charms of luxury a population scattered and barbarous and 
therefore inclined to war, <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName> gave private encouragement and public 
aid to the building of temples, courts of justice and dwelling-houses, 
praising the energetic, and reproving the indolent. Thus an honourable 
rivalry took the place of compulsion. He likewise provided a liberal 
education for the sons of the chiefs, and showed such a preference for the 
natural powers of the Britons over the industry of the Gauls that they who 
lately disdained the tongue of <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> now coveted its 
eloquence. Hence, too, a liking sprang up for our style of dress, and the 
"toga" became fashionable. Step by step they were led to things which 
dispose to vice, the lounge, the bath, the elegant banquet. All this in 
their ignorance, they called civilization, when it was but a part of their 
servitude.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="22"><p>The third year of his 
campaigns opened up new tribes, our ravages on the native population being 
carried as far as the <rs type="placename">Taus</rs>, an estuary so called. 
This struck such terror into the enemy that he did not dare to attack our 
army, harassed though it was by violent storms; and there was even time for 
the erection of forts. It was noted by experienced officers that no general 
had ever shown more judgment in choosing suitable positions, and that not a 
single fort established by <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName> was either stormed by the enemy or 
abandoned by capitulation or flight. Sorties were continually made; for 
these positions were secured from protracted siege by a year's supply. So 
winter brought with it no alarms, and each garrison could hold its own, as 
the baffled and despairing enemy, who had been accustomed often to repair 
his summer losses by winter successes, found himself repelled alike both in 
summer and winter. </p>
<p>Never did <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName> in a greedy spirit appropriate the 
achievements of others; the centurion and the prefect both

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">CONQUESTS IN NORTH</note>
found in him an impartial witness of 
their every action. Some persons used to say that he was too harsh in his 
reproofs, and that he was as severe to the bad as he was gentle to the good. 
But his displeasure left nothing behind it; reserve and silence in him were 
not to be dreaded. He thought it better to show anger than to cherish 
hatred.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="23"><p>The fourth summer he employed 
in securing what he had overrun. Had the valour of our armies and the renown 
of the Roman name permitted it, a limit to our conquests might have been 
found in <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> itself. <rs type="placename">Clota</rs> and <rs type="placename">Bodotria</rs>, estuaries 
which the tides of two opposite seas carry far back into the country, are 
separated by but a narrow strip of land This <placeName key="tgn,2035963">Agricola</placeName> then began to defend 
with a line of forts, and, as all the country to the south was now occupied, 
the enemy were pushed into what might be called another island.</p></div2> 

<div2 type="chapter" n="24"><p>In the fifth year of the war Agricola, 
himself in the leading ship, crossed the <rs type="placename">Clota</rs>, and 
subdued in a series of victories tribes hitherto unknown. In that part of 
<rs type="placename">Britain</rs> which looks towards <placeName key="tgn,1000078">Ireland</placeName>, he posted some 
troops, hoping for fresh conquests rather than fearing attack, inasmuch as 
<placeName key="tgn,1000078">Ireland</placeName>, being between <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> and <rs type="placename">Spain</rs> and conveniently situated for the seas round <rs type="placename">Gaul</rs>, might have been the means of connecting with great 
mutual benefit the most powerful parts of the empire. Its extent is small 
when compared with <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, but exceeds the islands 
of our seas. In soil and climate, in the disposition, temper, and habits of 
its population, it differs but little from <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>. 
We know most of its harbours and approaches, and that through the 
intercourse of commerce. One of the petty kings of the nation, driven out by 
internal faction, had been received by <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, who detained him under the 
semblance of friendship till he could make use of him. I have often heard 
him say that a single legion with a few auxiliaries could conquer and occupy 
<rs type="placename">Ireland</rs>, and that it would have a salutary effect on 
<rs type="placename">Britain</rs> for the Roman arms to be seen everywhere, 
and for freedom, so to speak, to be banished from its sight.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="25"><p>In the summer in which he entered on the sixth year 
of his office, his operations embraced the states beyond <rs type="placename">Bodotria</rs>, and, as he dreaded a general movement among 
the remoter tribes, as well as the perils which would beset an

invading army, he explored the harbours with a fleet, which, at first 
employed by him as an integral part of his force, continued to accompany 
him. The spectacle of war thus pushed on at once by sea and land was 
imposing; while often infantry, cavalry, and marines, mingled in the same 
encampment and joyously sharing the same meals, would dwell on their own 
achievements and adventures, comparing, with a soldier's boastfulness, at 
one time the deep recesses of the forest and the mountain with the dangers 
of waves and storms, or, at another, battles by land with victories over the 
ocean. The Britons too, as we learnt from the prisoners, were confounded by 
the sight of a fleet, as if, now that their inmost seas were penetrated, the 
conquered had their last refuge closed against them. The tribes inhabiting 
<rs type="placename">Caledonia</rs> flew to arms, and with great preparations, 
made greater by the rumours which always exaggerate the unknown, themselves 
advanced to attack our fortresses, and thus challenging a conflict, inspired 
us with alarm. To retreat south of the <rs type="placename">Bodotria</rs>, and 
to retire rather than to be driven out, was the advice of timid pretenders 
to prudence, when <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> learnt that the enemy's attack would be made with 
more than one army. Fearing that their superior numbers and their knowledge 
of the country might enable them to hem him in, he too distributed his 
forces into three divisions, and so advanced.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="26"><p>This becoming known to the enemy, they suddenly changed their 
plan, and with their whole force attacked by night the ninth Legion, as 
being the weakest, and cutting down the sentries, who were asleep or 
panic-stricken, they broke into the camp. And now the battle was raging 
within the camp itself, when Agricola, who had learnt from his scouts the 
enemy's line of march and had kept close on his track, ordered the most 
active soldiers of his cavalry and infantry to attack the rear of the 
assailants, while the entire army were shortly to raise a shout. Soon his 
standards glittered in the light of daybreak. A double peril thus alarmed 
the Britons, while the courage of the Romans revived; and feeling sure of 
safety, they now fought for glory. In their turn they rushed to the attack, 
and there was a furious conflict within the narrow passages of the gates 
till the enemy

<note anchored="yes" place="marg"><rs type="placename">CALEDONIA</rs> 
PENETRATED</note>
were routed. Both armies did their utmost, the one for the 
honour of having given aid, the other for that of not having needed support. 
Had not the flying enemy been sheltered by morasses and forests, this 
victory would have ended the war.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="27"><p>Knowing this, and elated by their glory, our army exclaimed that nothing 
could resist their valour&mdash;that they must penetrate the recesses of <rs type="placename">Caledonia</rs>, and at length after an unbroken succession of 
battles, discover the furthest limits of <rs type="placename"><placeName key="tgn,7008653">Britain</placeName></rs>. 
Those who but now were cautious and prudent, became after the event eager 
and boastful. It is the singularly unfair peculiarity of war that the credit 
of success is claimed by all, while a disaster is attributed to one alone. 
But the Britons thinking themselves baffled, not so much by our valour as by 
our general's skilful use of an opportunity, abated nothing of their 
arrogant demeanour, arming their youth, removing their wives and children to 
a place of safety, and assembling together to ratify, with sacred rites, a 
confederacy of all their states. Thus, with angry feelings on both sides, 
the combatants parted.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="28"><p>The same summer 
a Usipian cohort, which had been levied in <rs type="placename">Germany</rs> 
and transported into <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, ventured on a great 
and memorable exploit. Having killed a centurion and some soldiers, who, to 
impart military discipline, had been incorporated with their ranks and were 
employed at once to instruct and command them, they embarked on board three 
swift galleys with pilots pressed into their service. Under the direction of 
one of them&mdash;for two of the three they suspected and consequently put 
to death&mdash;they sailed past the coast in the strangest way before any 
rumour about them was in circulation. After a while, dispersing in search of 
water and provisions, they encountered many of the Britons, who sought to 
defend their property. Often victorious though now and then beaten, they 
were at last reduced to such an extremity of want as to be compelled to eat, 
at first, the feeblest of their number, and then victims selected by lot. 
Having sailed round <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> and lost their vessels 
from not knowing how to manage them, they were looked upon as pirates and 
were intercepted, first by the Suevi and then by the Frisii. Some who were 
sold as slaves in the way of trade, and were brought through the process of 
barter as far as our

side of the <rs type="placename">Rhine</rs>, 
gained notoriety by the disclosure of this extraordinary adventure.</p></div2> 

<div2 type="chapter" n="29"><p>Early in the summer Agricola sustained a 
domestic affliction in the loss of a son born a year before, a calamity 
which he endured, neither with the ostentatious fortitude displayed by many 
brave men, nor, on the other hand, with womanish tears and grief. In his 
sorrow he found one source of relief in war. Having sent on a fleet, which 
by its ravages at various points might cause a vague and wide-spread alarm, 
he advanced with a lightly equipped force, including in its ranks some 
Britons of remarkable bravery, whose fidelity had been tried through years 
of peace, as far as the <rs type="placename">Grampian mountains</rs>, which 
the enemy had already occupied. For the Britons, indeed, in no way cowed by 
the result of the late engagement, had made up their minds to be either 
avenged or enslaved, and convinced at length that a common danger must be 
averted by union, had, by embassies and treaties, summoned forth the whole 
strength of all their states. More than 30,000 armed men were now to be 
seen, and still there were pressing in all the youth of the country, with 
all whose old age was yet hale and vigorous, men renowned in war and bearing 
each decorations of his own. Meanwhile, among the many leaders, one superior 
to the rest in valour and in birth, Galgacus by name, is said to have thus 
harangued the multitude gathered around him and clamouring for 
battle:&mdash;</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="30"><p>"Whenever I consider 
the origin of this war and the necessities of our position, I have a sure 
confidence that this day, and this union of yours, will be the beginning of 
freedom to the whole of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>. To all of us 
slavery is a thing unknown; there are no lands beyond us, and even the sea 
is not safe, menaced as we are by a Roman fleet. And thus in war and battle, 
in which the brave find glory, even the coward will find safety. Former 
contests, in which, with varying fortune, the Romans were resisted, still 
left in us a last hope of succour, inasmuch as being the most renowned 
nation of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, dwelling in the very heart of the 
country, and out of sight of the shores of the conquered, we could keep even 
our eyes unpolluted by the contagion of slavery. To us who dwell on the 
uttermost confines of the earth and

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">GALGACUS' 
SPEECH</note>
of freedom, this remote sanctuary of Britain's glory has up to 
this time been a defence. Now, however, the furthest limits of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> are thrown open, and the unknown always passes 
for the marvellous. But there are no tribes beyond us, nothing indeed but 
waves and rocks, and the yet more terrible Romans, from whose oppression 
escape is vainly sought by obedience and submission. Robbers of the world, 
having by their universal plunder exhausted the land, they rifle the deep. 
If the enemy be rich, they are rapacious; if he be poor, they lust for 
dominion; neither the east nor the west has been able to satisfy them. Alone 
among men they covet with equal eagerness poverty and riches. To robbery, 
slaughter, plunder, they give the lying name of empire; they make a solitude 
and call it peace.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="31"><p>"Nature has willed 
that every man's children and kindred should be his dearest objects. Yet 
these are torn from us by conscriptions to be slaves elsewhere. Our wives 
and our sisters, even though they may escape violation from the enemy, are 
dishonoured under the names of friendship and hospitality. Our goods and 
fortunes they collect for their tribute, our harvests for their granaries. 
Our very hands and bodies, under the lash and in the midst of insult, are 
worn down by the toil of clearing forests and morasses. Creatures born to 
slavery are sold once for all, and are, moreover, fed by their masters; but 
<rs type="placename">Britain</rs> is daily purchasing, is daily feeding, her 
own enslaved people. And as in a household the last comer among the slaves 
is always the butt of his companions, so we in a world long used to slavery, 
as the newest and the most contemptible, are marked out for destruction. We 
have neither fruitful plains, nor mines, nor harbours, for the working of 
which we may be spared. Valour, too, and high spirit in subjects, are 
offensive to rulers; besides, remoteness and seclusion, while they give 
safety, provoke suspicion. Since then you cannot hope for quarter, take 
courage, I beseech you, whether it be safety or renown that you hold most 
precious. Under a woman's leadership the Brigantes were able to burn a 
colony, to storm a camp, and had not success ended in supineness, might have 
thrown off the yoke. Let us, then, a fresh and unconquered people, never 
likely to abuse our freedom, show forthwith

at the very first 
onset what heroes <rs type="placename">Caledonia</rs> has in 
reserve.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="32"><p>"Do you suppose that the 
Romans will be as brave in war as they are licentious in peace? To our 
strifes and discords they owe their fame, and they turn the errors of an 
enemy to the renown of their own army, an army which, composed as it is of 
every variety of nations, is held together by success and will be broken up 
by disaster. These Gauls and <placeName key="tgn,2088713">Germans</placeName>, and, I blush to say, these numerous 
Britons, who, though they lend their lives to support a stranger's rule, 
have been its enemies longer than its subjects, you cannot imagine to be 
bound by fidelity and affection. Fear and terror there certainly are, feeble 
bonds of attachment; remove them, and those who have ceased to fear will 
begin to hate. All the incentives to victory are on our side. The Romans 
have no wives to kindle their courage; no parents to taunt them with flight; 
many have either no country or one far away. Few in number, dismayed by 
their ignorance, looking around upon a sky, a sea, and forests which are all 
unfamiliar to them; hemmed in, as it were, and enmeshed, the Gods have 
delivered them into our hands. Be not frightened by idle display, by the 
glitter of gold and of silver, which can neither protect nor wound. In the 
very ranks of the enemy we shall find our own forces. Britons will 
acknowledge their own cause; Gauls will remember past freedom; the other 
<placeName key="tgn,2088713">Germans</placeName> will abandon them, as but lately did the Usipii. Behind them there 
is nothing to dread. The forts are ungarrisoned; the colonies in the hands 
of aged men; what with disloyal subjects and oppressive rulers, the towns 
are ill-affected and rife with discord. On the one side you have a general 
and an army; on the other, tribute, the mines, and all the other penalties 
of an enslaved people. Whether you endure these for ever, or instantly 
avenge them, this field is to decide. Think, therefore, as you advance to 
battle, at once of your ancestors and of your posterity."</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="33"><p>They received his speech with enthusiasm, and as is 
usual among barbarians, with songs, shouts and discordant cries. And now was 
seen the assembling of troops and the gleam of arms, as the boldest warriors 
stepped to the front. As the line was forming, <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, who, though his 
troops

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">AGRICOLA'S SPEECH</note>
were in high 
spirits and could scarcely be kept within the entrenchments, still thought 
it right to encourage them, spoke as follows&mdash; </p>
<p>"Comrades, this is 
the eighth year since, thanks to the greatness and good fortune of <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> and to your own loyalty and energy, you conquered 
<rs type="placename">Britain</rs>. In our many campaigns and battles, whether 
courage in meeting the foe, or toil and endurance in struggling, I may say, 
against nature herself, have been needed, I have ever been well satisfied 
with my soldiers, and you with your commander. And so you and I have passed 
beyond the limits reached by former armies or by former governors, and we 
now occupy the last confines of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>, not merely 
in rumour and report, but with an actual encampment and armed force. <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> has been both discovered and subdued. Often on 
the march, when morasses, mountains, and rivers were wearing out your 
strength, did I hear our bravest men exclaim, 'When shall we have the enemy 
before us?&mdash;when shall we fight?' He is now here, driven from his lair, 
and your wishes and your valour have free scope, and everything favours the 
conqueror, everything is adverse to the vanquished. For as it is a great and 
glorious achievement, if we press on, to have accomplished so great a march, 
to have traversed forests and to have crossed estuaries, so, if we retire, 
our present most complete success will prove our greatest danger. We have 
not the same knowledge of the country or the same abundance of supplies, but 
we have arms in our hands, and in them we have everything. For myself I have 
long been convinced that neither for an army nor for a general is retreat 
safe. Better, too, is an honourable death than a life of shame, and safety 
and renown are for us to be found together. And it would be no inglorious 
end to perish on the extreme confines of earth and of nature.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="34"><p>"If unknown nations and an untried enemy confronted 
you, I should urge you on by the example of other armies. As it is, look 
back upon your former honours, question your own eyes. These are the men who 
last year under cover of darkness attacked a single legion, whom you routed 
by a shout. Of all the Britons these are the most confirmed runaways, and 
this is why they have survived so long. Just as

when the huntsman 
penetrates the forest and the thicket, all the most courageous animals rush 
out upon him, while the timid and feeble are scared away by the very sound 
of his approach, so the bravest of the Britons have long since fallen; and 
the rest are a mere crowd of spiritless cowards. You have at last found 
them, not because they have stood their ground, but because they have been 
overtaken. Their desperate plight, and the extreme terror that paralyses 
them, have rivetted their line to this spot, that you might achieve in it a 
splendid and memorable victory. Put an end to campaigns; crown your fifty 
years' service with a glorious day; prove to your country that her armies 
could never have been fairly charged with protracting a war or with causing 
a rebellion."</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="35"><p>While <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> was yet 
speaking, the ardour of the soldiers was rising to its height, and the close 
of his speech was followed by a great outburst of enthusiasm. In a moment 
they flew to arms. He arrayed his eager and impetuous troops in such a 
manner that the auxiliary infantry, 8,000 in number, strengthened his 
centre, while 3,000 cavalry were posted on his wings. The legions were drawn 
up in front of the intrenched camp; his victory would be vastly more 
glorious if won without the loss of Roman blood, and he would have a reserve 
in case of repulse. The enemy, to make a formidable display, had posted 
himself on high ground; his van was on the plain, while the rest of his army 
rose in an arch-like form up the slope of a hill. The plain between 
resounded with the noise and with the rapid movements of chariots and 
cavalry. <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, fearing that from the enemy's superiority of force he 
would be simultaneously attacked in front and on the flanks, widened his 
ranks, and though his line was likely to be too extended, and several 
officers advised him to bring up the legions, yet, so sanguine was he, so 
resolute in meeting danger, he sent away his horse and took his stand on 
foot before the colours.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="36"><p>The action 
began with distant fighting. The Britons with equal steadiness and skill 
used their huge swords and small shields to avoid or to parry the missiles 
of our soldiers, while they themselves poured on us a dense shower of darts, 
till <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> encouraged three Batavian and two Tun-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">BATTLE OF <rs type="placename">GRAMPIAN MOUNTAIN</rs></note>
grian 
cohorts to bring matters to the decision of close fighting with swords. Such 
tactics were familiar to these veteran soldiers, but were embarrassing to an 
enemy armed with small bucklers and unwieldy weapons. The swords of the 
Britons are not pointed, and do not allow them to close with the foe, or to 
fight in the open field. No sooner did the Batavians begin to close with the 
enemy, to strike them with their shields, to disfigure their faces, and 
overthrowing the force on the plain to advance their line up the hill, than 
the other auxiliary cohorts joined with eager rivalry in cutting down all 
the nearest of the foe. Many were left behind half dead, some even 
unwounded, in the hurry of victory. Meantime the enemy's cavalry had fled, 
and the charioteers had mingled in the engagement of the infantry. But 
although these at first spread panic, they were soon impeded by the close 
array of our ranks and by the inequalities of the ground. The battle had 
anything but the appearance of a cavalry action, for men and horses were 
carried along in confusion together, while chariots, destitute of guidance, 
and terrified horses without drivers, dashed as panic urged them, sideways, 
or in direct collision against the ranks.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="37"><p>Those of the Britons who, having as yet taken no part in the 
engagement, occupied the hill-tops, and who without fear for themselves sat 
idly disdaining the smallness of our numbers, had begun gradually to descend 
and to hem in the rear of the victorious army, when <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, who feared 
this very movement, opposed their advance with four squadrons of cavalry 
held in reserve by him for any sudden emergencies of battle. Their repulse 
and rout was as severe as their onset had been furious. Thus the enemy's 
design recoiled on himself, and the cavalry which by the general's order had 
wheeled round from the van of the contending armies, attacked his rear. 
Then, indeed, the open plain presented an awful and hideous spectacle. Our 
men pursued, wounded, made prisoners of the fugitives only to slaughter them 
when others fell in their way. And now the enemy, as prompted by their 
various dispositions, fled in whole battalions with arms in their hands 
before a few pursuers, while some, who were unarmed, actually rushed to the 
front and gave themselves up to death. Everywhere there lay scattered

arms, corpses, and mangled limbs, and the earth reeked with blood. 
Even the conquered now and then felt a touch of fury and of courage. On 
approaching the woods, they rallied, and as they knew the ground, they were 
able to pounce on the foremost and least cautious of the pursuers. Had not 
<placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, who was present everywhere, ordered a force of strong and 
lightly-equipped cohorts, with some dismounted troopers for the denser parts 
of the forest, and a detachment of cavalry where it was not so thick, to 
scour the woods like a party of huntsmen, serious loss would have been 
sustained through the excessive confidence of our troops. When, however, the 
enemy saw that we again pursued them in firm and compact array, they fled no 
longer in masses as before, each looking for his comrade; but dispersing and 
avoiding one another, they sought the shelter of distant and pathless wilds. 
Night and weariness of bloodshed put an end to the pursuit. About 10,000 of 
the enemy were slain; on our side there fell 360 men, and among them Aulus 
Atticus, the commander of the cohort, whose youthful impetuosity and 
mettlesome steed had borne him into the midst of the enemy.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="38"><p>Elated by their victory and their booty, the 
conquerors passed a night of merriment. Meanwhile the Britons, wandering 
amidst the mingled wailings of men and women, were dragging off their 
wounded, calling to the unhurt, deserting their homes, and in their rage 
actually firing them, choosing places of concealment only instantly to 
abandon them. One moment they would take counsel together, the next, part 
company, while the sight of those who were dearest to them sometimes melted 
their hearts, but oftener roused their fury. It was an undoubted fact that 
some of them vented their rage on their wives and children, as if in pity 
for their lot. The following day showed more fully the extent of the 
calamity, for the silence of desolation reigned everywhere: the hills were 
forsaken, houses were smoking in the distance, and no one was seen by the 
scouts. These were despatched in all directions; and it having been 
ascertained that the track of the flying enemy was uncertain, and that there 
was no attempt at rallying, it being also impossible, as summer was now 
over, to extend the war, <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> led back his army into the territory of 
the Boresti. He received hos-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">EXTENT OF ROMAN 
VICTORY</note>
tages from them, and then ordered the commander of the fleet 
to sail round <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>. A force for this purpose was 
given him, which great panic everywhere preceded. <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> himself, leading 
his infantry and cavalry by slow marches, so as to overawe the 
newly-conquered tribes by the very tardiness of his progress, brought them 
into winter-quarters, while the fleet with propitious breezes and great 
renown entered the harbour of <rs type="placename">Trutulium</rs>, to which it 
had returned after having coasted along the entire southern shore of the 
island.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="39"><p>Of this series of events, 
though not exaggerated in the despatches of <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> by any boastfulness of 
language, Domitian heard, as was his wont, with joy in his face but anxiety 
in his heart. He felt conscious that all men laughed at his late mock 
triumph over <rs type="placename">Germany</rs>, for which there had been 
purchased from traders people whose dress and hair might be made to resemble 
those of captives, whereas now a real and splendid victory, with the 
destruction of thousands of the enemy, was being celebrated with just 
applause. It was, he thought, a very alarming thing for him that the name of 
a subject should be raised above that of the Emperor; it was to no purpose 
that he had driven into obscurity the pursuit of forensic eloquence and the 
graceful accomplishments of civil life, if another were to forestall the 
distinctions of war. To other glories he could more easily shut his eyes, 
but the greatness of a good general was a truly imperial quality. Harassed 
by these anxieties, and absorbed in an incommunicable trouble, a sure 
prognostic of some cruel purpose, he decided that it was best for the 
present to suspend his hatred until the freshness of <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>'s renown and 
his popularity with the army should begin to pass away.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="40"><p>For <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> was still the governor of <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>. Accordingly the Emperor ordered that the usual 
triumphal decorations, the honour of a laurelled statue, and all that is 
commonly given in place of the triumphal procession, with the addition of 
many laudatory expressions, should be decreed in the senate, together with a 
hint to the effect that <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> was to have the province of <rs type="placename">Syria</rs>, then vacant by the death of Atilius Rufus, a man 
of consular rank, and generally reserved for men of distinction. It was 
believed by many persons that one of the freedmen employed on confidential 
serv-

ices was sent to <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, bearing a despatch in which <rs type="placename">Syria</rs> was offered him, and with instructions to deliver 
it should he be in <rs type="placename">Britain</rs>; that this freedman in 
crossing the straits met <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, and without even saluting him made his 
way back to Domitian; though I cannot say whether the story is true, or is 
only a fiction invented to suit the Emperor's character. </p>
<p>Meanwhile 
<placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> had handed over his province in peace and safety to his successor. 
And not to make his entrance into <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> conspicuous 
by the concourse of welcoming throngs, he avoided the attentions of his 
friends by entering the city at night, and at night too, according to 
orders, proceded to the palace, where, having been received with a hurried 
embrace and without a word being spoken, he mingled in the crowd of 
courtiers. Anxious henceforth to temper the military renown, which annoys 
men of peace, with other merits, he studiously cultivated retirement and 
leisure, simple in dress, courteous in conversation, and never accompanied 
but by one or two friends, so that the many who commonly judge of great men 
by their external grandeur, after having seen and attentively surveyed him, 
asked the secret of a greatness which but few could explain.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="41"><p>During this time he was frequently accused before 
Domitian in his absence, and in his absence acquitted. The cause of his 
danger lay not in any crime, nor in any complaint of injury, but in a ruler 
who was the foe of virtue, in his own renown, and in that worst class of 
enemies&mdash;the men who praise. And then followed such days for the 
commonwealth as would not suffer <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> to be forgotten; days when so many 
of our armies were lost in <rs type="placename">M&oelig;sia</rs>, <rs type="placename">Dacia</rs>, <rs type="placename">Germany</rs>, and <rs type="placename">Pannonia</rs>, through the rashness or cowardice of our 
generals, when so many of our officers were besieged and captured with so 
many of our auxiliaries, when it was no longer the boundaries of empire and 
the banks of rivers which were imperilled, but the winter-quarters of our 
legions and the possession of our territories. And so when disaster followed 
upon disaster, and the entire year was marked by destruction and slaughter, 
the voice of the people called <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> to the command; for they all 
contrasted his vigour, firmness, and experience in war, with the inertness 
and ti-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">AGRICOLA'S MODESTY AND 
DISCRETION</note>
midity of other generals. This talk, it is quite certain, 
assailed the ears of the Emperor himself, while affection and loyalty in the 
best of his freedmen, malice and envy in the worst, kindled the anger of a 
prince ever inclined to evil. And so at once, by his own excellences and by 
the faults of others, <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> was hurried headlong to a perilous 
elevation.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="42"><p>The year had now arrived 
in which the pro-consulate of <rs type="placename">Asia</rs> or <rs type="placename">Africa</rs> was to fall to him by lot, and, as Civica had 
been lately murdered, <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName> did not want a warning, or Domitian a 
precedent. Persons well acquainted with the Emperor's feelings came to ask 
<placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, as if on their own account, whether he would go. First they hinted 
their purpose by praises of tranquillity and leisure; then offered their 
services in procuring acceptance for his excuses; and at last, throwing off 
all disguise, brought him by entreaties and threats to Domitian. The 
Emperor, armed beforehand with hypocrisy, and assuming a haughty demeanour, 
listened to his prayer that he might be excused, and having granted his 
request allowed himself to be formally thanked, nor blushed to grant so 
sinister a favour. But the salary usually granted to a pro-consul, and which 
he had himself given to some governors, he did not bestow on <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, 
either because he was offended at its not having been asked, or was warned 
by his conscience that he might be thought to have purchased the refusal 
which he had commanded. It is, indeed, human nature to hate the man whom you 
have injured; yet the Emperor, notwithstanding his irascible temper and an 
implacability proportioned to his reserve, was softened by the moderation 
and prudence of <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, who neither by a perverse obstinacy nor an idle 
parade of freedom challenged fame or provoked his fate. Let it be known to 
those whose habit it is to admire the disregard of authority, that there may 
be great men even under bad emperors, and that obedience and submission, 
when joined to activity and vigour, may attain a glory which most men reach 
only by a perilous career, utterly useless to the state, and closed by an 
ostentatious death.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="43"><p>The end of his 
life, a deplorable calamity to us and a grief to his friends, was regarded 
with concern even by strangers and those who knew him not. The common 
people

and this busy population continually inquired at his 
house, and talked of him in public places and in private gatherings. No man 
when he heard of Agricola's death could either be glad or at once forget it. 
Men's sympathy was increased by a prevalent rumour that he was destroyed by 
poison. For myself, I have nothing which I should venture to state for fact. 
Certainly during the whole of his illness the Emperor's chief freedmen and 
confidential physicians came more frequently than is usual with a court 
which pays its visits by means of messengers. This was, perhaps, solicitude, 
perhaps espionage. Certain it is, that on the last day the very agonies of 
his dying moments were reported by a succession of couriers, and no one 
believed that there would be such haste about tidings which would be heard 
with regret. Yet in his manner and countenance the Emperor displayed some 
signs of sorrow, for he could now forget his enmity, and it was easier to 
conceal his joy than his fear. It was well known that on reading the will, 
in which he was named co-heir with Agricola's excellent wife and most 
dutiful daughter, he expressed delight, as if it had been a complimentary 
choice. So blinded and perverted was his mind by incessant flattery, that he 
did not know that it was only a bad Emperor whom a good father would make 
his heir.</p></div2>
<div2 type="chapter" n="44"><p>Agricola was born on the 
13th of June, in the third consulate of Caius C&aelig;sar; he died on the 
23rd of August, during the consulate of Collega and Priscus, being in the 
fifty-sixth year of his age. Should posterity wish to know something of his 
appearance, it was graceful rather than commanding. There was nothing 
formidable in his appearance; a gracious look predominated. One would easily 
believe him a good man, and willingly believe him to be great. As for 
himself, though taken from us in the prime of a vigorous manhood, yet, as 
far as glory is concerned, his life was of the longest. Those true 
blessings, indeed, which consist in virtue, he had fully attained; and on 
one who had reached the honours of a consulate and a triumph, what more had 
fortune to bestow? Immense wealth had no attractions for him, and wealth he 
had, even to splendour. As his daughter and his wife survived him, it may be 
thought that he was even fortunate&mdash;fortunate, in that while his 
honours

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">DOMITIAN GLOATS OVER HIS DEATH</note>
had 
suffered no eclipse, while his fame was at its height, while his kindred and 
his friends still prospered, he escaped from the evil to come. For, though 
to survive until the dawn of this most happy age and to see a Trajan on the 
throne was what he would speculate upon in previsions and wishes confided to 
my ears, yet he had this mighty compensation for his premature death, that 
he was spared those later years during which Domitian, leaving now no 
interval or breathing space of time, but, as it were, with one continuous 
blow, drained the life-blood of the Commonwealth.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="45"><p>Agricola did not see the senate-house besieged, or the senate 
hemmed in by armed men, or so many of our consulars falling at one single 
massacre, or so many of <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>'s noblest ladies exiles and fugitives. Carus 
Metius had as yet the distinction of but one victory, and the noisy counsels 
of Messalinus were not heard beyond the walls of <rs type="placename">Alba</rs>, and Massa B&aelig;bius was then answering for his 
life. It was not long before our hands dragged Helvidius to prison, before 
we gazed on the dying looks of Manricus and Rusticus, before we were steeped 
in Senecio's innocent blood. Even <placeName key="tgn,2538429">Nero</placeName> turned his eyes away, and did not 
gaze upon the atrocities which he ordered; with Domitian it was the chief 
part of our miseries to see and to be seen, to know that our sighs were 
being recorded, to have, ever ready to note the pallid looks of so many 
faces, that savage countenance reddened with the hue with which he defied 
shame. </p>
<p>Thou wast indeed fortunate, <placeName key="tgn,2110243">Agricola</placeName>, not only in the splendour 
of thy life, but in the opportune moment of thy death. Thou submittedst to 
thy fate, so they tell us who were present to hear thy last words, with 
courage and cheerfulness, seeming to be doing all thou couldst to give thine 
Emperor full acquittal. As for me and thy daughter, besides all the 
bitterness of a father's loss, it increases our sorrow that it was not 
permitted us to watch over thy failing health, to comfort thy weakness, to 
satisfy ourselves with those looks, those embraces. Assuredly we should have 
received some precepts, some utterances to fix in our inmost hearts. This is 
the bitterness of our sorrow, this the smart of our wound, that from the 
circumstance of so long an absence thou wast lost to us four years before. 
Doubtless, best of

fathers, with that most loving wife at thy 
side, all the dues of affection were abundantly paid thee, yet with too few 
tears thou wast laid to thy rest, and in the light of thy last day there was 
something for which thine eyes longed in vain.</p></div2> 
<div2 type="chapter" n="46"><p>If there is any dwelling-place for the spirits of the just; if, 
as the wise believe, noble souls do not perish with the body, rest thou in 
peace; and call us, thy family, from weak regrets and womanish laments to 
the contemplation of thy virtues, for which we must not weep nor beat the 
breast. Let us honour thee not so much with transitory praises as with our 
reverence, and, if our powers permit us, with our emulation. That will be 
true respect, that the true affection of thy nearest kin. This, too, is what 
I would enjoin on daughter and wife, to honour the memory of that father, 
that husband, by pondering in their hearts all his words and acts, by 
cherishing the features and lineaments of his character rather than those of 
his person. It is not that I would forbid the likenesses which are wrought 
in marble or in bronze; but as the faces of men, so all similitudes of the 
face are weak and perishable things, while the fashion of the soul is 
everlasting, such as may be expressed not in some foreign substance, or by 
the help of art, but in our own lives. Whatever we loved, whatever we 
admired in <placeName key="tgn,2018415">Agricola</placeName>, survives, and will survive in the hearts of men, in the 
succession of the ages, in the fame that waits on noble deeds. Over many 
indeed, of those who have gone before, as over the inglorious and ignoble, 
the waves of oblivion will roll; Agricola, made known to posterity by 
history and tradition, will live for ever.</p></div2></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
