<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>For Aulus Licinius Archias</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--<encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>-->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-05-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Minor changes merging new work. EpiDoc and CTS check.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-16" who="Zach Himes">Changed section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change></revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi016.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
   <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO FOR AULUS LICINIUS ARCHIAS, THE POET</head>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>Archias was a Greek poet, a native of Antioch, who came to Rome in the train of Lucullus,
    when Cicero was a child. He assumed the names of Aulus and Licinius, the last out of compliment
    to the Luculli, and Cicero had been for some time a pupil of his, and had retained a great
    regard for him. A man of the name of Gracchus now prosecuted him as a false pretender to the
    rights of a Roman citizen, according to the provisions of the <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex
     Papiria</foreign>. But Cicero contends that he is justified by that very law, for Archias
    before coming to Rome had stayed at Heraclea, a confederate city, and had been enrolled as a
    Heraclean citizen; and in the <foreign xml:lang="lat">lex Papiria</foreign> it was expressly
    provided that those who were on the register of any confederate city as its citizens, if they
    were residing in Italy at the time the law was passed, and if they made a return of themselves
    to the praetor within sixty days, were to be exempt from its operation. However, the greatest
    part of this oration is occupied, not in legal arguments, but in a panegyric on Archias, who is
    believed to have died soon afterwards; and he must have been a very old man at the time that it
    was spoken, as it was neatly forty years previously that he had first come to Rome.</p></div>
   

   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>If there is any natural ability in me, O judges,—and I know how slight that is; or if I have
    any practice as a speaker,—and in that line I do not deny that I have some experience; or if I
    have any method in my oratory, drawn from my study of the liberal sciences, and from that
    careful training to which I admit that at no part of my life have I ever been disinclined;
    certainly, of all those qualities, this Aulus Licinius is entitled to be among the first to
    claim the benefit from me as his peculiar right. For as far as ever my mind can look back upon
    the space of time that is past, and recall the memory of its earliest youth, tracing my life
    from that starting-point, I see that Archias was the principal cause of my undertaking, and the
    principal means of my mastering, those studies. And if this voice of mine, formed by his
    encouragement and his precepts, has at times been the instrument of safety to others,
    undoubtedly we ought, as far as lies in our power, to help and save the very man from whom we
    have received that gift which has enabled us to bring help to many and salvation to some.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p> And lest any one should, perchance, marvel at this being said
    by me, as the chief of his ability consists in something else, and not in this system and
    practice of eloquence, he must be told that even we ourselves have never been wholly devoted to
    this study. In truth, all the arts which concern the civilising and humanising of men, have some
    link which binds them together, and are, as it were, connected by some relationship to one
    another. </p></div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And, that it may not appear marvellous to any one of you, that I, in a formal proceeding like
    this, and in a regular court of justice, when an action is being tried before a praetor of the
    Roman people, a most eminent man, and before most impartial judges, before such an assembly and
    multitude of people as I see around me, employ this style of speaking, which is at variance, not
    only with the ordinary usages of courts of justice, but with the general style of forensic
    pleading; I entreat you in this cause to grant me this indulgence, suitable to this defendant,
    and as I trust not disagreeable to you,—the indulgence, namely, of allowing me, when speaking in
    defence of a most sublime poet and most learned man, before this concourse of highly-educated
    citizens, before this most polite and accomplished assembly, and before such a praetor as him
    who is presiding at this trial, to enlarge with a little more freedom than usual on the study of
    polite literature and refined arts, and, speaking in the character of such a man as that, who,
    owing to the tranquillity of his life and the studies to which he has devoted himself, has but
    little experience of the dangers of a court of justice, to employ a new and unusual style of
    oratory. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p> And if I feel that that indulgence is given and
    allowed me by you, I will soon cause you to think that this Aulus Licinius is a man who not
    only, now that he is a citizen, does not deserve to be expunged from the list of citizens, but
    that he is worthy, even if he were not one, of being now made a citizen. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For when first Archias grew out of childhood, and out of the studies of those arts by which
    young boys are gradually trained and refined, he devoted himself to the study of writing. First
    of all at Antioch, (for he was born there, and was of high rank there,) formerly an illustrious
    and wealthy city, and the seat of learned men and of liberal sciences; and there it was his lot
    speedily to show himself superior to all in ability and credit. Afterwards, in the other parts
    of Asia, and over all Greece, his arrival was so talked of wherever he came, that the anxiety
    with which he was expected was even greater than the fame of his genius;—but the admiration
    which he excited when he had arrived, exceeded even the anxiety with which he was expected.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> Italy was at that time full of Greek science and of Greek
    systems, and these studies were at that time cultivated in Latium with greater zeal than they
    now are in the same towns; and here too at Rome, on account of the tranquil state of the
    republic at that time, they were far from neglected. Therefore, the people of Tarentum, and
    Rhegium, and Neapolis, presented him with the freedom of the city and with other gifts; and all
    men who were capable of judging of genius thought him deserving of their acquaintance and
    hospitality. When, from this great celebrity of his, he had become known to us though absent, he
    came to Rome, in the consulship of Marius and Catulus. It was his lot to have those men as his
    first consuls, the one of whom could supply him with the most illustrious achievements to write
    about, the other could give him, not only exploits to celebrate, but his ears and judicious
    attention. Immediately the Luculli, though Archias was as yet but a youth,<note anchored="true">The Latin is <foreign xml:lang="lat">praetextus</foreign>. Before he had exchanged the <foreign xml:lang="lat">praetexta</foreign> for the <foreign xml:lang="lat">toga virilis</foreign>. It
     has generally been thought that the age at which this exchange was made was seventeen, but
     Professor Long, the highest possible authority on all subjects of Latin literature, and
     especially on Roman law, says, (Smith, Dict. Ant V. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Impubes</foreign>,)
     “The <foreign xml:lang="lat">toga virilis</foreign> was assumed at the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Liberalia</foreign> in the month of March; and though no age appears to have been positively
     fixed for the ceremony, it probably took place, as a general rule, on the feast which next
     followed the completion of the fourteenth year, though it is certain that the completion of the
     fourteenth year was not always the time observed.” Even supposing Archias to have been
     seventeen, it appears rather an early age for him to have established such a reputation as
     Cicero speaks of, and perhaps, as not being at that time a Roman citizen, he probably did not
     wear the <foreign xml:lang="lat">praetexta</foreign> at all; the expression is not to be taken
     literally, but we are merely to understand generally that he was quite a young man.</note>
    received him in their house. But it was not <pb n="414"/> only to his genius and his learning,
    but also to his natural disposition and virtue, that it must be attributed that the house which
    was the first to be opened to him in his youth, is also the one in which he lives most
    familiarly in his old age. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> He at that time gained the
    affection of Quintus Metellus, that great man who was the conqueror of Numidia, and his son
    Pius. He was eagerly listened to by Marcus Aemilius; he associated with Quintus Catulus,—both
    with the father and the sons. He was highly respected by Lucius Crassus; and as for the Luculli,
    and Drusus, and the Octavii, and Cato, and the whole family of the Hortensii, he was on terms of
    the greatest possible intimacy with all of them, and was held by them in the greatest honour.
    For, not only did every one cultivate his acquaintance who wished to learn or to hear anything,
    but even every one pretended to have such a desire. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>In the meantime, after a sufficiently long interval, having gone with Lucius Lucullus into
    Sicily, and having afterwards departed from that province in the company of the same Lucullus,
    he came to Heraclea. And as that city was one which enjoyed all the rights of a confederate city
    to their full extent, he became desirous of being enrolled as a citizen of it. And, being
    thought deserving of such a favour for his own sake, when aided by the influence and authority
    of Lucullus, he easily obtained it from the Heracleans. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> The
    freedom of the city was given him in accordance with the provisions of the law of Silvanus and
    Carbo: “If any men had been enrolled as citizens of the confederate cities, and if, at the time
    that the law was passed, they had a residence in Italy, and if within sixty days they had made a
    return or themselves to the praetor.” As he had now had a residence at Rome for many years, he
    returned himself as a citizen to the praetor, Quintus Metellus, his most intimate friend.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> If we have nothing else to speak about except the rights of
    citizenship and the law, I need say no more. The cause is over. For which of all these
    statements, O Gratius, can be invalidated? Will you deny that he was enrolled, at the time I
    speak of, as a citizen of Heraclea? There is a man present of the very highest authority, a most
    scrupulous and truthful man, Lucius Lucullus, who will tell you not that he thinks it, but that
    he knows it; not that he has heard of it, but that he saw it; not even that he was present when
    it was done, but that he actually did it himself. Deputies from Heraclea are present, men of the
    highest rank; they have come expressly on account of this trial, with a commission from their
    city, and to give evidence on the part of their city; and they say that he was enrolled as a
    Heraclean. On this you ask for the public registers of the Heracleans, which we all know were
    destroyed in the Italian war, when the register office was burnt. It is ridiculous to say
    nothing to the proofs which we have, but to ask for proofs which it is impossible for us to
    have; to disregard the recollection of men, and to appeal to the memory of documents; and when
    you have the conscientious evidence of a most honourable man, the oath and good faith of a most
    respectable municipality, to reject those things which cannot by any possibility be tampered
    with, and to demand documentary evidence, though you say at the same moment that that is
    constantly played tricks with. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p> “But he had no residence at
    Rome.” What, not he who for so many years before the freedom of the city was given to him, had
    established the abode of all his property and fortunes at Rome? “But he did not return himself.”
    Indeed he did, and in that return which alone obtains with the college of praetors the authority
    of a public document. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For as the returns of Appius were said to have been kept carelessly, and as the trifling
    conduct of Gabinius, before he was convicted, and his misfortune after his condemnation, had
    taken away all credit from the public registers, Metellus, the most scrupulous and moderate of
    all men, was so careful, that he came to Lucius Lentulus, the praetor, and to the judges, and
    said that he was greatly vexed at an erasure which appeared in one name. In these documents,
    therefore, you will see no erasure affecting the name of Aulus Licinius. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> And as this is the case, what reason have you for doubting about his
    citizenship, especially as he was enrolled as a citizen of other cities also? In truth, as men
    in Greece were in the habit of giving rights of citizenship to many men of very ordinary
    qualifications, and endowed with no talents at all, or with very moderate ones, without any
    payment, it is likely, I suppose, that the Rhegians, and Locrians, and Neapolitans, and
    Tarentines should have been unwilling to give to this man, enjoying the highest possible
    reputation for genius, what they were in the habit of giving even to theatrical artists. What,
    when other men, who not only after the freedom of the city had been given, but even after the
    passing of the Papian law, crept somehow or other into the registers of those municipalities,
    shall he be rejected who does not avail himself of those other lists in which he is enrolled,
    because he always wished to be considered a Heraclean? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> You
    demand to see our own censor's returns. I suppose no one knows that at the time of the last
    census he was with that most illustrious general, Lucius Lucullus, with the army; that at the
    time of the preceding one he was with the same man when he was in Asia as quaestor; and that in
    the census before that, when Julius and Crassus were censors, no regular account of the people
    was taken. But, since the census does not confirm the right of citizenship, but only indicates
    that he, who is returned in the census, did at that time claim to be considered as a citizen, I
    say that, at that time, when you say, in your speech for the prosecution, that he did not even
    himself consider that he had any claim to the privileges of a Roman citizen, he more than once
    made a will according to our laws, and he entered upon inheritances left him by Roman citizens;
    and he was made honourable mention of by Lucius Lucullus, both as praetor and as consul, in the
    archives kept in the treasury. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You must rely wholly on what arguments you can find. For he will never be convicted either by
    his own opinion or his case, or by that which is formed of it by his friends. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>You ask us, O Gratius, why we are so exceedingly attached to this man. Because he supplies us
    with food whereby our mind is refreshed after this noise in the forum, and with rest for our
    ears after they have been wearied with bad language. Do you think it possible that we could find
    a supply for our daily speeches, when discussing such a variety of matters, unless we were to
    cultivate our minds by the study of literature; or that our minds could bear being kept so
    constantly on the stretch if we did not relax them by that same study? But I confess that I am
    devoted to those studies, let others be ashamed of them if they have buried themselves in books
    without being able to produce anything out of them for the common advantage or anything which
    may bear the eyes of men and the light. But why need I be ashamed, who for many years have lived
    in such a manner as never to allow my own love of tranquillity to deny me to the necessity or
    advantage of another or my fondness for pleasure to distract, or even sleep to delay my
    attention to such claims? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> Who then can reproach me or who has
    any right to be angry with me, if I allow myself as much time for the cultivation of these
    studies as some take for the performance of their own business, or for celebrating days of
    festival and games, or for other pleasures, or even for the rest and refreshment of mind and
    body, or as others devote to early banquets, to playing at dice, or at ball? And this ought to
    be permitted to me, because by these studies my power of speaking and those faculties are
    improved, which, as far as they do exist in me, have never been denied to my friends when they
    have been in peril. And if that ability appears to any one to be but moderate, at all events I
    know whence I derive those principles which are of the greatest value. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> For if I had not persuaded myself from my youth upwards, both by the precepts
    of many masters and by much reading, that there is nothing in life greatly to be desired, except
    praise and honour, and that while pursuing those things all tortures of the body, all dangers of
    death and banishment are to be considered but of small importance, I should never have exposed
    myself, in defence of your safety, to such numerous and arduous contests, and to these daily
    attacks of profligate men. But all books are full of such precepts, and all the sayings of
    philosophers, and all antiquity is full of precedents teaching the same lesson; but all these
    things would lie buried in darkness, if the light of literature and learning were not applied to
    them. How many images of the bravest men, carefully elaborated, have both the Greek and Latin
    writers bequeathed to us, not merely for us to look at and gaze upon, but also for our
    imitation! And I, always keeping them before my eyes as examples for my own public conduct, have
    endeavoured to model my mind and views by continually thinking of those excellent men.
     </p></div><milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Some one will ask, “What? were those identical <pb n="418"/> great men, whose virtues have
    been recorded in books, accomplished in all that learning which you are extolling so highly?” It
    is difficult to assert this of all of them; but still I know what answer I can make to that
    question: I admit that many men have existed of admirable disposition and virtue, who, without
    learning, by the almost divine instinct of their own mere nature, have been, of their own
    accord, as it were, moderate and wise men. I even add this, that very often nature without
    learning has had more to do with leading men to credit and to virtue, than learning when not
    assisted by a good natural disposition. And I also contend, that when to an excellent and
    admirable natural disposition there is added a certain system and training of education, then
    from that combination arises an extraordinary perfection of character; </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> such as is seen in that god-like man, whom our fathers saw in their time,
    Africanus; and in Caius Laelius and Lucius Furius, most virtuous and moderate men; and in that
    most excellent man, the most learned man of his time, Marcus Cato the elder; and all these men,
    if they had been to derive no assistance from literature in the cultivation and practice of
    virtue, would never have applied themselves to the study of it. Though, even if there were no
    such great advantage to be reaped from it, and if it were only pleasure that is sought from
    these studies, still I imagine you would consider it a most reasonable and liberal employment of
    the mind: for other occupations are not suited to every time, nor to every age or place; but
    these studies are the food of youth, the delight of old age; the ornament of prosperity, the
    refuge and comfort of adversity; a delight at home, and no hindrance abroad; they are companions
    by night, and in travel, and in the country. </p></div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And if we ourselves were not able to arrive at these advantages, nor even taste them with our
    senses, still we ought to admire them, even when we saw them in others. Who of us was of so
    ignorant and brutal a disposition as not lately to be grieved at the death of Roscius? who,
    though he was an old man when he died, yet on account of the excellence and beauty of his art,
    appeared to be one who on every account ought not to have died. Therefore, had he by the
    gestures of his body gained so much of our affections, and shall we disregard the incredible
    movements of the mind, and the rapid operations of genius?</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> How often have I seen this man.
    Archias, O judges,—(for I will take advantage of your kindness, since you listen to me so
    attentively while speaking in this unusual manner,)—how often have I seen him, when he had not
    written a single word, repeat extempore a great number of admirable verses on the very events
    which were passing at the moment! How often have I seen him
    go back, and describe the same thing over again with an entire change of language and ideas! And
    what he wrote with care and with much thought that I have seen admired to such a degree, as to
    equal the credit of even the writings of the ancients. Should not I, then, love this man? should
    I not admire him? should not I think it my duty to defend him in every possible way? And,
    indeed, we have constantly heard from men of the greatest eminence and learning, that the study
    of other sciences was made up of learning, and rules, and regular method; but that a poet was
    such by the unassisted work of nature, and was moved by the vigour of his own mind, and was
    inspired, as it were, by some divine wrath. Wherefore rightly does our own great Ennius call
    poets holy; because they seem to be recommended to us by some especial gift, as it were, and
    liberality of the gods. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> Let then, judges, this name of poet,
    this name which no barbarians even have ever disregarded, be holy in your eyes, men of
    cultivated minds as you all are. Rocks and deserts reply to the poet's voice; savage beasts are
    often moved and arrested by song; and shall we, who have been trained in the pursuit of the most
    virtuous acts, refuse to be swayed by the voice of poets? The Colophonians say that Homer was
    their citizen; the Chians claim him as theirs; the Salaminians assert their right to him; but
    the men of Smyrna loudly assert him to be a citizen of Smyrna, and they have even raised a
    temple to him in their city. Many other places also fight with one another for the honour of
    being his birth-place. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>They, then, claim a stranger, even after his death, because he was a poet; shall we reject
    this man while he is alive, a man who by his own inclination and by our laws does actually
    belong to us? especially when Archias has employed all his genius with the utmost zeal in
    celebrating the glory and renown of the Roman people? For when a young man, he touched on our
    wars against the Cimbri, and gained the favour even of Caius Marius himself, a man who was
    tolerably proof against this sort of study. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p> For there was no
    one so <pb n="420"/> disinclined to the Muses as not willingly to endure that the praise of his
    labours should be made immortal by means of verse. They say that the great Themistocles, the
    greatest man that Athens produced, said, when some one asked him what sound or whose voice he
    took the greatest delight in hearing, “The voice of that by whom his own exploits were best
    celebrated.” Therefore, the great Marius was also exceedingly attached to Lucius Plotius,
    because he thought that the achievement which he had performed could be celebrated by his
    genius. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p> And the whole Mithridatic war, great and difficult as
    it was, and carried on with so much diversity of fortune by land and sea, has been related at
    length by him; and the books in which that is sung of, not only make illustrious Lucius
    Lucullus, that most gallant and celebrated man, but they do honour also to the Roman people.
    For, while Lucullus was general, the Roman people opened Pontus, though it was defended both by
    the resources of the king and by the character of the country itself. Under the same general the
    army of the Roman people, with no very great numbers, routed the countless hosts of the
    Armenians. It is the glory of the Roman people that, by the wisdom of that same general, the
    city of the Cyzicenes, most friendly to us, was delivered and preserved from all the attacks of
    the kind, and from the very jaws as it were of the whole war. Ours is the glory which will be
    for ever celebrated, which is derived from the fleet of the enemy which was sunk after its
    admirals had been slain, and from the marvellous naval battle off Tenedos: those trophies belong
    to us, those monuments are ours, those triumphs are ours. Therefore, I say that the men by whose
    genius these exploits are celebrated, make illustrious at the same time the glory of the Roman
    people. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p> Our countryman, Ennius, was dear to the elder
    Africanus; and even on the tomb of the Scipios his effigy is believed to be visible, carved in
    the marble. But undoubtedly it is not only the men who are themselves praised who are done
    honour to by those praises, but the name of the Roman people also is adorned by them. Cato, the
    ancestor of this Cato, is extolled to the skies. Great honour is paid to the exploits of the
    Roman people. Lastly, all those great men, the Maximi, the Marcelli, and the Fulvii, are done
    honour to, not without all of us having also a share in the panegyric. <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore our ancestors received the man who was the cause of all this, a man of Rudiae, into
    their city as a citizen; and shall we reject from our city a man of Heraclea, a man sought by
    many cities, and made a citizen of ours by these very laws?</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> For if any one thinks that there is a smaller gain of glory
    derived from Greek verses than from Latin ones, he is greatly mistaken, because Greek poetry is
    read among all nations, Latin is confined to its own natural limits, which are narrow enough.
    Wherefore, if those achievements which we have performed are limited only by the bounds of the
    whole world, we ought to desire that, wherever our vigour and our arms have penetrated, our
    glory and our fame should likewise extend. Because, as this is always an ample reward for those
    people whose achievements are the subject of writings, so especially is it the greatest
    inducement to encounter labours and dangers to all men who fight for themselves for the sake of
    glory. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p> How many historians of his exploits is Alexander the
    Great said to have had with him; and he, when standing on Cape Sigeum at the grave of Achilles,
    said—“O happy youth, to find Homer as the panegyrist of your glory!” And he said the truth; for,
    if the <title>Iliad</title> had not existed, the same tomb which covered his body would have
    also buried his renown. What, did not our own Magnus, whose valour has been equal to his
    fortune, present Theophanes the Mitylenaean, a relater of his actions, with the freedom of the
    city in an assembly of the soldiers? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> And those brave men, our
    countrymen, soldiers and country bred men as they were, still being moved by the sweetness of
    glory, as if they were to some extent partakers of the same renown, showed their approbation of
    that action with a great shout. Therefore, I suppose, if Archias were not a Roman citizen
    according to the laws, he could not have contrived to get presented with the freedom of the city
    by some general! Sulla, when he was giving it to the Spaniards and Gauls, would, I suppose, have
    refused him if he had asked for it! a man whom we ourselves saw in the public assembly, when a
    bad poet of the common people had put a book in his hand, because he had made an epigram on him
    with every other verse too long, immediately ordered some of the things which he was selling at
    the moment to be given him as a reward, on condition of not writing anything more about him for
    the future. Would not he who <pb n="422"/> thought the industry of a bad poet still worthy of
    some reward, have sought out the genius, and excellence, and copiousness in writing of this man?
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p> What more need I say? Could he not have obtained the freedom
    of the city from Quintus Metellus Pius, his own most intimate friend, who gave it to many men,
    either by his own request, or by the intervention of the Luculli? especially when Metellus was
    so anxious to have his own deeds celebrated in writing, that he gave his attention willingly to
    poets born even at Cordova, whose poetry had a very heavy and foreign flavour. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For this should not be concerned, which cannot possibly be kept in the dark, but it might be
    avowed openly: we are all influenced by a desire of praise, and the best men are the most
    especially attracted by glory. Those very philosophers even in the books which they write about
    despising glory, put their own names on the title-page. In the very act of recording their
    contempt for renown and notoriety, they desire to have their own names known and talked of.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> Decimus Brutus, that most excellent citizen and consummate
    general, adorned the approaches to his temples and monuments with the verses of Attius. And
    lately that great man Fulvius, who fought with the Aetolians, having Ennius for his companion,
    did not hesitate to devote the spoils of Mars to the Muses. Wherefore, in a city in which
    generals, almost in arms, have paid respect to the name of poets and to the temples of the
    Muses, these judges in the garb of peace ought not to act in a manner inconsistent with the
    honour of the Muses and the safety of poets. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>And that you may do that the more willingly, I will now reveal my own feelings to you, O
    judges, and I will make a confession to you of my own love of glory,—too eager perhaps, but
    still honourable. For this man has in his verses touched upon and begun the celebration of the
    deeds which we in our consulship did in union with you, for the safety of this city and empire,
    and in defence of the life of the citizens and of the whole republic. And when I had heard his
    commencement because it appeared to me to be a great subject and at the same time an agreeable
    one, I encouraged him to complete his work. For virtue seeks no other reward for its labours and
    its dangers beyond that of praise and renown; and if that be denied to it, what reason is there,
    O judges, why in so small and brief a course of life as is allotted to us, we should impose such
    labours on ourselves? </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p> Certainly, if the mind had no
    anticipations of posterity, and if it were to confine all its thoughts within the same limits as
    those by which the space of our lives is bounded, it would neither break itself with such severe
    labours, nor would it be tormented with such cares and sleepless anxiety, nor would it so often
    have to fight for its very life. At present there is a certain virtue in every good man, which
    night and day stirs up the mind with the stimulus of glory, and reminds it that all mention of
    our name will not cease at the same time with our lives, but that our fame will endure to all
    posterity. </p></div><milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Do we all who are occupied in the affairs of the state, and who are surrounded by such perils
    and dangers in life, appear to be so narrow-minded, as, though to the last moment of our lives
    we have never passed one tranquil or easy moment, to think that everything will perish at the
    same time as ourselves? Ought we not, when many most illustrious men have with great care
    collected and left behind them statues and images, representations not of their minds but of
    their bodies, much more to desire to leave behind us a copy of our counsels and of our virtues,
    wrought and elaborated by the greatest genius? I thought, at the very moment of performing them,
    that I was scattering and disseminating all the deeds which I was performing, all over the world
    for the eternal recollection of nations. And whether that delight is to be denied to my soul
    after death, or whether, as the wisest men have thought, it will affect some portion of my
    spirit, at all events, I am at present delighted with some such idea and hope. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Preserve then, O judges, a man of such virtue as that of Archias, which you see testified to
    you not only by the worth of his friends, but by the length of time during which they have been
    such to him, and of such genius as you ought to think is his, when you see that it as been
    sought by most illustrious men. And his cause is one which is approved of by the benevolence of
    the law by the authority of his municipality, by the testimony of Lucullus, and by the
    documentary evidence of Metellus. And as this is the case, we do entreat you, O judges, if there
    may be any weight attached, I will not say to human, but even to divine recommendation in such
    important matters, to receive under your protection that man who has at all times done honour to
    your generals and to the exploits of the Roman people,—who even in these recent <pb n="424"/>
    perils of our own, and in your domestic dangers, promises to give an eternal testimony of praise
    in our favour, and who forms one of that band of poets who have at all times and in all nations
    been considered and called holy, so that he may seem relieved by your humanity, rather than
    overwhelmed by your severity. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The things which, according to my custom, I have said briefly and simply, O judges, I trust
    have been approved by all of you. Those things which I have spoken, without regarding the habits
    of the forum or judicial usage, both concerning the genius of the man and my own zeal in his
    behalf, I trust have been received by you in good part. That they have been so by him who
    presides at this trial, I am quite certain.</p></div>
  </div>
 </body></text>

</TEI>
