<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 10-12 - 12</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <biblStruct default="NO">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With An English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="NO">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb id="p.353"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="book">
                <head>Book XII</head>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="pr" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    I now come to what is by far the most arduous
portion of the task which I have set myself to perform. Indeed had I fully realised the difficulties
when I first designed this work, I should have considered betimes whether my strength was sufficient to
support the load that now weighs upon me so heavily.
But to begin with, I felt how shameful it would be
to fail to perform what I had promised, and later,
despite the fact that my labour became more and
more arduous at almost every stage, the fear of
stultifying what I had already written sustained my
courage through every difficulty.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently
even now, though the burden that oppresses me is
greater than ever, the end is in sight and I am
resolved to faint by the wayside rather than despair.
But the fact that I began with comparatively trivial
details deceived me. Subsequently I was lured still
further on my voyage by the temptations of the
favouring breeze that filled my sails; but the rules
which I was then concerned to give were still of a
familiar kind and had been already treated by most
writers of rhetorical textbooks: thus far I seemed to
myself to be still in sight of shore and I had the
company of many who had ventured to entrust themselves to the self-same winds.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But presently when
I entered on the task of setting forth a theory of
                    <pb id="p.355"/>
                    eloquence which had been but newly discovered and
rarely essayed, I found but few that had ventured so
far from harbour. And finally now that the ideal
orator, whom it was my design to mould, has been
dismissed by his masters and is either proceeding
on his way borne onward by his own impetus, or
seeking still mightier assistance from the innermost
shrine of wisdom, I begin to feel how far I have
been swept into the great deep.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Now there is
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Nothing before and nothing behind but the sky and the Ocean.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="NO">
                                <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                                iii. 193.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    One only can I discern in all the boundless waste of
waters, Marcus Tullius Cicero, and even he, though
the ship in which he entered these seas is of such
size and so well found, begins to lessen sail and to
row a slower stroke, and is content to speak merely
of the kind of speech to be employed by the perfect
orator. But my temerity is such that I shall essay to
form my orator's character and to teach him his duties.
Thus I have no predecessor to guide my steps and
must press far, far on, as my theme may demand.
Still an honourable ambition is always deserving of
approval, and it is all the less hazardous to dare
greatly, when forgiveness is assured us if we fail.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The orator then, whom I am concerned to form,
shall be the orator as defined by Marcus Cato,
                    <quote>a good man, skilled in speaking.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp. I. Pr.</hi>
                        9.
                    </note>
                    But above all he must
possess the quality which Cato places first and which
is in the very nature of things the greatest and most
important, that is, he must be a good man. This is
essential not merely on account of the fact that, if
the powers of eloquence serve only to lend arms to
crime, there can be nothing more pernicious than
                    <pb id="p.357"/>
                    eloquence to public and private welfare alike, while
I myself, who have laboured to the best of my ability
to contribute something of value to oratory, shall have
rendered the worst of services to mankind, if I forge
these weapons not for a soldier, but for a robber.
But why speak of myself?
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Nature herself will have
proved not a mother, but a stepmother with regard
to what we deem her greatest gift to man, the gift
that distinguishes us from other living things, if she
devised the power of speech to be the accomplice of
crime, the foe to innocency and the enemy of truth.
For it had been better for men to be born dumb and
devoid of reason than to turn the gifts of providence
to their mutual destruction.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But this conviction of
mine goes further. For I do not merely assert that
the ideal orator should be a good man, but I affirm
that no man can be an orator unless he is a good man.
For it is impossible to regard those men as gifted
with intelligence who on being offered the choice
between the two paths of virtue and of vice choose
the latter, nor can we allow them prudence, when
by the unforeseen issue of their own actions they
render themselves liable not merely to the heaviest
penalties of the laws, but to the inevitable torment
of an evil conscience.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But if the view that a bad
man is necessarily a fool is not merely held by philosolphers, but is the universal belief of ordinary men,
the fool will most assuredly never become an orator.
To this must be added the fact that the mind will
not find leisure even for the study of the noblest of
tasks, unless it first be free from vice. The reasons for
this are, first, that vileness and virtue cannot jointly
inhabit in the selfsame heart and that it is as impossible for one and the same mind to harbour good
                    <pb id="p.359"/>
                    and evil thoughts as it is for one man to be at once
both good and evil:
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and secondly, that if the intelligence is to be concentrated on such a vast subject as
eloquence it must be free from all other distractions,
among which must be included even those preoccupations which are free from blame. For it is only
when it is free and self-possessed, with nothing to
divert it or lure it elsewhere, that it will fix its
attention solely on that goal, the attainment of which
is the object of its preparations.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    If on the other
hand inordinate care for the development of our
estates, excess of anxiety over household affairs,
passionate devotion to hunting or the sacrifice of
whole days to the shows of the theatre, rob our
studies of much of the time that is their due (for
every moment that is given to other things involves
a loss of time for study), what, think you, will be the
results of desire, avarice, and envy, which waken such
violent thoughts within our souls that they disturb
our very slumbers and our dreams?
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    There is nothing
so preoccupied, so distracted, so rent and torn by so
many and such varied passions as an evil mind. For
when it cherishes some dark design, it is tormented
with hope, care and anguish of spirit, and even when
it has accomplished its criminal purpose, it is racked
by anxiety, remorse and the fear of all manner of
punishments. Amid such passions as these what
room is there for literature or any virtuous pursuit?
You might as well look for fruit in land that is choked
with thorns and brambles.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Well then, I ask you, is
not simplicity of life essential if we are to be able to
endure the toil entailed by study? What can we
hope to get from lust or luxury? Is not the desire
to win praise one of the strongest stimulants to a
                    <pb id="p.361"/>
                    passion for literature? But does that mean that we
are to suppose that praise is an object of concern to
bad men? Surely every one of my readers must by
now have realised that oratory is in the main concerned with the treatment of what is just and
honourable? Can a bad and unjust man speak on
such themes as the dignity of the subject demands?
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Nay, even if we exclude the most important aspects
of the question now before us, and make the impossible concession that the best and worst of men
may have the same talent, industry and learning, we
are still confronted by the question as to which of
the two is entitled to be called the better orator. The
answer is surely clear enough: it will be he who is
the better man. Consequently, the bad man and the
perfect orator can never be identical.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For nothing
is perfect, if there exists something else that is
better. However, as I do not wish to appear to
adopt the practice dear to the Socratics of framing
answers to my own questions, let me assume the
existence of a man so obstinately blind to the truth
as to venture to maintain that a bad man equipped
with the same talents, industry and learning will
be not a whit inferior to the good man as an
orator; and let me show that he too is mad.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There is one point at any rate which no one will
question, namely, that the aim of every speech is to
convince the judge that the case which it puts forward is true and honourable. Well then, which will
do this best, the good man or the bad? The good
man will without doubt more often say what is true
and honourable.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    But even supposing that his duty
should, as I shall show may sometimes happen, lead
him to make statements which are false, his words
                    <pb id="p.363"/>
                    are still certain to carry greater weight with his
audience. On the other hand bad men, in their
contempt for public opinion and their ignorance of
what is right, sometimes drop their mask unawares,
and are impudent in the statement of their case and
shameless in their assertions.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Further, in their
attempt to achieve the impossible they display an
unseemly persistency and unavailing energy. For
in lawsuits no less than in the ordinary paths of
life, they cherish depraved expectations. But it
often happens that even when they tell the truth
they fail to win belief, and the mere fact that such
a man is its advocate is regarded as an indication of
the badness of the case.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    I must now proceed to deal with the objections
which common opinion is practically unanimous in
bringing against this view. Was not Demosthenes
an orator? And yet we are told that he was a bad
man. Was not Cicero an orator? And yet there
are many who have found fault with his character as
well. What am I to answer? My reply will be
highly unpopular and I must first attempt to conciliate my audience.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    I do not consider that
Demosthenes deserves the serious reflexions that
have been made upon his character to such an
extent that I am bound to believe all the charges
amassed against him by his enemies; for my reading
tells me that his public policy was of the noblest and
his end most glorious.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Again, I cannot see that the
aims of Cicero were in any portion of his career other
than such as may become an excellent citizen. As
evidence I would cite the fact that his behaviour as
consul was magnificent and his administration of his
province a model of integrity, while he refused to
                    <pb id="p.365"/>
                    become one of the twenty commissioners,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For the distribution of the Campanian lands.</note>
                    and in the
grievous civil wars which afflicted his generation
beyond all others, neither hope nor fear ever deterred
him from giving his support to the better party, that
is to say, to the interests of the common weal.
Some, it is true, regard him as lacking in courage.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The best answer to these critics is to be found in his
own words, to the effect that he was timid not in
confronting peril, but in anticipating it. And this
he proved also by the manner of his death, in meeting
which he displayed a singular fortitude.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    But even
if these two men lacked the perfection of virtue, I
will reply to those who ask if they were orators, in
the manner in which the Stoics would reply, if asked
whether Zeno, Cleanthes or Chrysippus himself were
wise men. I shall say that they were great men
deserving our veneration, but that they did not
attain to that which is the highest perfection
of man's nature.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    For did not Pythagoras desire
that he should not be called a wise man, like the
sages who preceded him, but rather a student of
wisdom?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">filo/sofos,</foreign>
                        a term of which he was reputed the
inventor.
                    </note>
                    But for my own part, conforming to the
language of every day, I have said time and again,
and shall continue to say, that Cicero was a perfect
orator, just as in ordinary speech we call our friends
good and sensible men, although neither of these
titles can really be given to any save to him that
has attained to perfect wisdom. But if I am called
upon to speak strictly and in accordance with the
most rigid laws of truth, I shall proclaim that I seek
to find that same perfect orator whom Cicero also
sought to discover.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    For while I admit that he stood
on the loftiest pinnacle of eloquence, and can discover scarcely a single deficiency in him, although I
                    <pb id="p.367"/>
                    might perhaps discover certain superfluities which I
think he would have pruned away (for the general
view of the learned is that he possessed many virtues
and a few faults, and he himself
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Brut.</hi>
                        xci. 316.
                        <hi rend="italics">Orat.</hi>
                        xxx. 107.
                    </note>
                    states that he has
succeeded in suppressing much of his youthful
exuberance), none the less, in view of the fact that,
although he had by no means a low opinion of himself, he never claimed to be the perfect sage, and,
had he been granted longer life and less troubled conditions for the composition of his works, would doubtless have spoken better still, I shall not lay myself
open to the charge of ungenerous criticism, if I say
that I believe that he failed actually to achieve that
perfection to the attainment of which none have
approached more nearly,
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    and indeed had I felt otherwise in this connexion, I might have defended my
point with greater boldness and freedom.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Quintilian's reverence for Cicero is such that he feels
hampered in maintaining his thesis.
                    </note>
                    Marcus
Antonius declared that he had seen no man who was
genuinely eloquent (and to be eloquent is a far less
achievement than to be an orator), while Cicero himself has failed to find his orator in actual life and
merely imagines and strives to depict the ideal. Shall
I then be afraid to say that in the eternity of time
that is yet to be, something more perfect may be found
than has yet existed?
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    I say nothing of those critics
who will not allow sufficient credit even for eloquence
to Cicero and Demosthenes, although Cicero himself
does not regard Demosthenes as flawless, but asserts
that he sometimes nods,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See x. i. 24.</note>
                    while even Cicero fails to
satisfy Brutus and Calvus (at any rate they criticised
his style to his face), or to win the complete approval
of either of the Asinii, who in various passages attack
the faults of his oratory in language which is positively
hosthe.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.369"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    However, let us fly in the face of nature and
assume that a bad man has been discovered who is
endowed with the highest eloquence. I shall none
the less deny that he is an orator. For I should not
allow that every man who has shown himself ready
with his hands was necessarily a brave man, because
true courage cannot be conceived of without the
accompaniment of virtue.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Surely the advocate who
is called to defend the accused requires to be a man
of honour, honour which greed cannot corrupt, influence seduce, or fear dismay. Shall we then dignify the traitor, the deserter, the turncoat with the
sacred name of orator? But if the quality which is
usually termed goodness is to be found even in quite
ordinary advocates, why should not the orator, who
has not yet existed, but may still be born, be no less
perfect in character than in excellence of speech?
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    It is no hack-advocate, no hireling pleader, nor yet,
to use no harser term, a serviceable attorney of the
class generally known as
                    <hi rend="italics">causidici,</hi>
                    that I am seeking to
form, but rather a man who to extraordinary natural
gifts has added a thorough mastery of all the fairest
branches of knowledge, a man sent by heaven to be
the blessing of mankind, one to whom all history
can find no parallel, uniquely perfect in every detail
and utterly noble alike in thought and speech.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    How
small a portion of all these abilities will be required
for the defence of the innocent, the repression of
crime or the support of truth against falsehood in
suits involving questions of money? It is true that
our supreme orator will bear his part in such tasks,
but his powers will be displayed with brighter splendour in greater matters than these, when he is
called upon to direct the counsels of the senate and
                    <pb id="p.371"/>
                    guide the people from the paths of error to better
things.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Was not this the man conceived by Virgil
and described as quelling a riot when torches and
stones have begun to fly:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                        i. 151
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Then, if before their eyes some statesman grave</l>
                            <l part="N">Stand forth, with virtue and high service crowned,</l>
                            <l part="N">Straight are they dumb and stand intent to hear.</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    Here then we have one who is before all else a
good man, and it is only after this that the poet adds
that he is skilled in speaking:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>His words their minds control, their passions soothe.</quote>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    Again,
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    will not this same man, whom we are striving
to form, if in time of war he be called upon to inspire
his soldiers with courage for the fray, draw for his
eloquence on the innermost precepts of philosophy?
For how can men who stand upon the verge of battle
banish all the crowding fears of hardship, pain and
death from their minds, unless those fears be replaced by the sense of the duty that they owe
their country, by courage and the lively image of a
soldier's honour?
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    And assuredly the man who will
best inspire such feelings in others is he who has
first inspired them in himself. For however we strive
to conceal it, insincerity will always betray itself, and
there was never in any man so great eloquence as
would not begin to stumble and hesitate so soon as
his words ran counter to his inmost thoughts.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Now:
a bad man cannot help speaking things other than
he feels. On the other land, the good will never be
at a loss for honourable words or fail to find matter
full of virtue for utterance, since among his virtues
practical wisdom will be one. And even though his
                    <pb id="p.373"/>
                    imagination lacks artifice to lend it charm, its own
nature will be ornament enough, for if honour dictate
the words, we shall find eloquence there as well.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, let those that are young, or rather let all
of us, whatever our age, since it is never too late to
resolve to follow what is right, strive with all our
hearts and devote all our efforts to the pursuit of virtue
and eloquence; and perchance it may be granted to us
to attain to the perfection that we seek. For since
nature does not forbid the attainment of either, why
should not someone succeed in attaining both together? And why should not each of us hope to be
that happy man?
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    But if our powers are inadequate
to such achievement, we shall still be the better for
the double effort in proportion to the distance which
we have advanced toward either goal. At any rate
let us banish from our hearts the delusion that
eloquence, the fairest of all things, can be combined
with vice. The power of speaking is even to be
accounted an evil when it is found in evil men; for it
makes its possessors yet worse than they were before.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    I think I hear certain persons (for there will
always be some who had rather be eloquent than
good) asking,
                    <quote>
                        Why then is there so much art in connexion with eloquence? Why have you talked so
much of 'glosses,'
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">color</hi>
                            is a technical term for
                            <quote>
                                the particular aspect given
to a case by skilful manipulation of the facts—the 'gloss'
or 'varnish' put on them by the accused or accuser.
                            </quote>
                            —Peterson
                            <hi rend="italics">on Quint.</hi>
                            X. i. 116.
                        </note>
                        the methods of defence to be
employed in difficult cases, and sometimes even of
actual confession of guilt, unless it is the case that
the power and force of speech at times triumphs over
truth itself? For a good man will only plead good
cases, and those might safely be left to truth to
support without the aid of learning.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    Now, though
my reply to these critics will in the first place be
a defence of my own work, it will also explain what
                    <pb id="p.375"/>
                    I consider to be the duty of a good man on occasions
when circumstances have caused him to undertake the defence of the guilty. For it is by no
means useless to consider how at times we should
speak in defence of falsehood or even of injustice, if
only for this reason, that such an investigation will
enable us to detect and defeat them with the greater
ease, just as the physician who has a thorough
knowledge of all that can injure the health will be
all the more skilful in the prescription of remedies.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    For the Academicians, although they will argue on
either side of a question, do not thereby commit
themselves to taking one of these two views as their
guide in life to the exclusion of the other, while the
famous Carneades, who is said to have spoken at
Rome in the presence of Cato the Censor, and to
have argued against justice with no less vigour than
he had argued for justice on the preceding day, was
not himself an unjust man. But the nature of virtue
is revealed by vice, its opposite, justice becomes yet
more manifest from the contemplation of injustice,
and there are many other things that are proved by
their contraries. Consequently the schemes of his
adversaries should be no less well known to the
orator than those of the enemy to a commander in
the field.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    But it is even true, although at first sight
it seems hard to believe, that there may be sound
reason why at times a good man who is appearing
for the defence should attempt to conceal the truth
from the judge. If any of my readers is surprised
at my making such a statement (although this
opinion is not of my own invention, but is derived
from those whom antiquity regarded as the greatest
teachers of wisdom), I would have him reflect that
                    <pb id="p.377"/>
                    there are many things which are made honourable
or the reverse not by the nature of the facts, but by
the causes from which they spring.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    For if to slay
a man is often a virtue and to put one's own children
to death is at times the noblest of deeds, and if it
is permissible in the public interest to do deeds
yet more horrible to relate than these, we should
assuredly take into consideration not solely and
simply what is the nature of the case which the
good man undertakes to defend, but what is his
reason and what his purpose in so doing.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    And first
of all everyone must allow, what even the sternest
of the Stoics admit, that the good man will sometimes tell a lie, and further that he will sometimes do
so for comparatively trivial reasons; for example we
tell countless lies to sick children for their good and
make many promises to them which we do not intend
to perform.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    And there is clearly far more justification for lying when it is a question of diverting
an assassin from his victim or deceiving an enemy
to save our country. Consequently a practice which
is at times reprehensible even in slaves, may on
other occasions be praiseworthy even in a wise man.
If this be granted, I can see that there will be many
possible emergencies such as to justify an orator in
undertaking cases of a kind which, in the absence of
any honourable reason, he would have refused to
touch.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    In saying this I do not mean that we should
be ready under any circumstances to defend our
father, brother or friend when in peril (since I
hold that we should be guided by stricter rules in
such matters), although such contingencies may
well cause us no little perplexity, when we have to
decide between the rival claims of justice and natural
                    <pb id="p.379"/>
                    affection. But let us put the problem beyond all
question of doubt. Suppose a man to have plotted
against a tyrant and to be accused of having done so.
Which of the two will the orator, as defined by us,
desire to save? And if he undertakes the defence
of the accused, will he not employ falsehood with
no less readiness than the advocate who is defending
a bad case before a jury?
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Again, suppose that the
judge is likely to condemn acts which were rightly
done, unless we can convince him that they were
never done. Is not this another case where the
orator will not shrink even from lies, if so he may
save one who is not merely innocent, but a praiseworthy citizen? Again, suppose that we realise that
certain acts are just in themselves, though prejudicial
to the state under existing circumstances. Shall we
not then employ methods of speaking which, despite
the excellence of their intention, bear a close resemblance to fraud.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    Further, no one will hesitate
for a moment to hold the view that it is in the
interests of the commonwealth that guilty persons
should be acquitted rather than punished, if it be
possible thereby to convert them to a better state of
mind, a possibility which is generally conceded. If
then it is clear to an orator that a man who is guilty
of the offences laid to his charge will become a good
man, will he not strive to secure his acquittal?
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    Imagine for example that a skilful commander, without whose aid the state cannot hope to crush its
enemies, is labouring under a charge which is obviously true: will not the common interest irresistibly
summon our orator to defend him? We know at
any rate that Fabricius publicly voted for and secured
the election to the consulate of Cornelius Rufinus,
                    <pb id="p.381"/>
                    despite the tact that he was a bad citizen and his
personal enemy, merely because he knew that he
was a capable general and the state was threatened
with war.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The late is uncertain, but the reference must be either to
the Samnite war of 290 or the war with Pyrrhus.
                    </note>
                    And when certain persons expressed
their surprise at his conduct, he replied that he had
rather be robbed by a fellow-citizen than be sold as
a slave by the enemy. Well then, had Fabricius
been an orator, would he not have defended Rufinus
against a charge of peculation, even though his
guilt were as clear as day?
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    I might produce many
other similar examples, but one of them taken at
random is enough. For my purpose is not to
assert that such tasks will often be incumbent
on the orator whom I desire to form, but merely to
show that, in the event of his being compelled to
take such action, it will not invalidate our definition
of an orator as a
                    <quote>good man, skilled in speaking.</quote>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    And it is necessary also both to teach and learn how
to establish difficult cases by proof. For often even
the best cases have a resemblance to bad and, the
charges which tell heavily against an innocent person frequently have a strong resemblance to the
truth. Consequently, the same methods of defence
have to be employed that would be used if he were
guilty. Further, there are countless elements which
are common to both good cases and bad, such as oral
and documentary evidence, suspicions and opinions,
all of which have to be established or disposed of in
the same way, whether they be true or merely resemble the truth. Therefore, while maintaining his
integrity of purpose, the orator will modify his pleading to suit the circumstances.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Since then the orator is a good man, and such
goodness cannot be conceived as existing apart from
                    <pb id="p.383"/>
                    virtue, virtue, despite the fact that it is in part
derived from certain natural impulses, will require to
be perfected by instruction. The orator must above
all things devote his attention to the formation of
moral character and must acquire a complete knowledge of all that is just and honourable. For without
this knowledge no one can be either a good man or
skilled in speaking,
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    unless indeed we agree with
those who regard morality as intuitive and as owing
nothing to instruction: indeed they go so far as to
acknowledge that handicrafts, not excluding even
those which are most despised among them, can
only be acquired by the result of teaching, whereas
virtue, which of all gifts to man is that which makes
him most near akin to the immortal gods, comes to
him without search or effort, as a natural concomitant
of birth. But can the man who does not know what
abstinence is, claim to be truly abstinent?
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    or brave, if
he has never purged his soul of the fears of pain, death
and superstition? or just, it he has never, in language
approaching that of philosophy, discussed the nature
of virtue and justice, or of the laws that have been
given to mankind by nature or established among
individual peoples and nations? What a contempt
it argues for such themes to regard them as being
so easy of comprehension!
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    However, I pass this by;
for I am sure that no one with the least smattering
of literary culture will have the slightest hesitation
in agreeing with me. I will proceed to my next
point, that no one will achieve sufficient skill even in
speaking, unless he makes a thorough study of all
the workings of nature and forms his character on
the precepts of philosophy and the dictates of reason.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For it is with good cause that Lucius Crassus, in the
                    <pb id="p.385"/>
                    third book of the
                    <hi rend="italics">de Oratore,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chs. xx. xxvii. and xxxi.</note>
                    affirms that all that is
said concerning equity, justice, truth and the good,
and their opposites, forms part of the studies of an
orator, and that the philosophers, when they exert
their powers of speaking to defend these virtues, are
using the weapons of rhetoric, not their own. But
he also confesses that the knowledge of these subjects must be sought from the philosophers for the
reason that, in his opinion, philosophy has more
effective possession of them.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And it is for the same
reason that Cicero in several of his books and letters
proclaims that eloquence has its fountain-head in the
most secret springs of wisdom, and that consequently
for a considerable time the instructors of morals and
of eloquence were identical. Accordingly this exhortation of mine must not be taken to mean that I
wish the orator to be a philosopher, since there is no
other way of life that is further removed from the
duties of a statesman and the tasks of an orator.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For what philosopher has ever been a frequent
speaker in the courts or won renown in public
assemblies? Nay, what philosopher has ever taken a
prominent part in the government of the state, which
forms the most frequent theme of their instructions?
None the less I desire that he, whose character I am
seeking to mould, should be a
                    <quote>wise man</quote>
                    in the
Roman sense, that is, one who reveals himself as a true
statesman, not in the discussions of the study, but
in the actual practice and experience of life.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But
inasmuch as the study of philosophy has been
deserted by those who have turned to the pursuit of
eloquence, and since philosophy no longer moves in
its true sphere of action and in the broad daylight of
the forum, but has retired first to porches and
                    <pb id="p.387"/>
                    gymnasia and finally to the gatherings of the schools, all
that is essential for an orator, and yet is not taught
by the professors of eloquence, must undoubtedly be
sought from those persons in whose possession it
has remained. The authors who have discoursed on
the nature of virtue must be read through and
through, that the life of the orator may be wedded
to the knowledge of things human and divine.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But
how much greater and fairer would such subjects
appear if those who taught them were also those
who could give them most eloquent expression! O
that the day may dawn when the perfect orator of
our heart's desire shall claim for his own possession
that science that has lost the affection of mankind
through the arrogance of its claims and the vices of
some that have brought disgrace upon its virtues,
and shall restore it to its place in the domain of
eloquence, as though he had been victorious in a
trial for the restoration of stolen goods!
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And since
philosophy falls into three divisions, physics, ethics
and dialectic, which, I ask you, of these departments is not closely connected with the task of the
orator?
                </p>
                <p>
                    Let us reverse the order just given and deal first
with the third department which is entirely concerned with words. If it be true that to know the
properties of each word, to clear away ambiguities,
to unravel perplexities, to distinguish between truth
and falsehood, to prove or to refute as may be
desired, all form part of the functions of an orator,
who is there that can doubt the truth of my contention?
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    I grant that we shall not have to employ
dialectic with such minute attention to detail when
we are pleading in the courts as when we are
                    <pb id="p.389"/>
                    engaged in philosophical debate, since the orator's
duty is not merely to instruct, but also to move and
delight his audience; and to succeed in doing this
he needs a strength, impetuosity and grace as well.
For oratory is like a river: the current is stronger
when it flows within deep banks and with a mighty
flood, than when the waters are shallow and broken
by the pebbles that bar their way.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    And just as
the trainers of the wrestling school do not impart
the various
                    <hi rend="italics">throws</hi>
                    to their pupils that those who
have learnt them may make use of all of them in
actual wrestling matches (for weight and strength
and wind count for more than these), but that they
may have a store from which to draw one or two
of such tricks, as occasion may offer;
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    even so the
science of dialectic, or if you prefer it of disputation, while it is often useful in definition, inference,
differentiation, resolution of ambiguity, distinction
and classification, as also in luring on or entangling
our opponents, yet if it claim to assume the entire
direction of the struggles of the forum, will merely
stand in the way of arts superior to itself and by its
very subtlety will exhaust the strength that has
been pared down to suit its limitations.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    As a
result you will find that certain persons who show
astonishing skill in philosophical debate, as soon as
they quit the sphere of their quibbles, are as helpless in any case that demands more serious pleading
as those small animals which, though nimble enough
in a confined space, are easily captured in an open
field.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Proceeding to moral philosophy or ethics, we may
note that it at any rate is entirely suited to the
orator. For vast as is the variety of cases (since in
                    <pb id="p.391"/>
                    them, as I have pointed out in previous books, we seek
to discover certain points by conjecture,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        vi. 45.
                    </note>
                    reach our
conclusions in others by means of definition,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. vi. 45.</note>
                    dispose
of others on legal grounds' or by raising the question of competence,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See ill. vi. 23.</note>
                    while other points are established by syllogism
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. vi. 15.</note>
                    and others involve contradictions
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably an allusion to contradictory laws. See VIII. vii.
                    </note>
                    or are diversely interpreted owing to some
ambiguity of language
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See VII. ix.</note>
                    ), there is scarcely a single
one which does not at some point or another involve
the discussion of equity and virtue, while there are
also, as everyone knows, not a few which turn
entirely on questions of quality.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Again in deliberative assemblies how can we advise a policy without
raising the question of what is honourable? Nay,
even the third department of oratory, which is
concerned with the tasks of praise and denunciation,
must without a doubt deal with questions of right
and wrong.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    For the orator will assuredly have
much to say on such topics as justice, fortitude,
abstinence, self-control and piety. But the good
man, who has come to the knowledge of these things
not by mere hearsay, as though they were just words
and names for his tongue to employ, but has grasped
the meaning of virtue and acquired a true feeling for
it, will never be perplexed when he has to think out
a problem, but will speak out truly what he
knows.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Since, however,
                    <hi rend="italics">general</hi>
                    questions are always
more important than special (for the particular is
contained in the universal, while the universal is
never to be regarded as something superimposed on
the particular), everyone will readily admit that the
studies of which we are speaking are pre-eminently
concerned with general questions.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Further, since
there are numerous points which require to be
                    <pb id="p.393"/>
                    determined by appropriate and concise definitions
(hence the
                    <hi rend="italics">definitive basis</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III vi. 31.</note>
                    of cases), it is surely
desirable that the orator should be instructed in
such things by those who have devoted special
attention to the subject. Again, does not every
question of law turn either on the precise meaning
of words, the discussion of equity, or conjecture as
to the intention—subjects which in part encroach on
the domain of dialectic and in part on that of ethics?
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently all oratory involves a natural admixture
of all these philosophic elements—at least, that is to
say, all oratory that is worthy of the name. For
mere garrulity that is ignorant of all such learning
must needs go astray, since its guides are either
non-existent or false.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Physics
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        natural phlilosophy in the widest sense.
                    </note>
                    on the other hand is far richer than the
other branches of philosophy, if viewed from the
standpoint of providing exercise in speaking, in
proportion as a loftier inspiration is required to
speak of things divine than of things human; and
further it includes within its scope the whole of
ethics, which as we have shown
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 15.</note>
                    are essential to the
very existence of oratory.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    For, if the world is
governed by providence, it will certainly be the
duty of all good men to bear their part in the
administration of the state. If the origin of our
souls be divine, we must win our way towards virtue
and abjure the service of the lusts of our earthly
body. Are not these themes which the orator will
frequently be called upon to handle? Again there
are questions concerned with auguries and oracles
or any other religious topic (all of them subjects
that have often given rise to the most important debates in the senate) on which the orator will have to
                    <pb id="p.395"/>
                    discourse, if he is also to be the statesman we
would have him be. And finally, how can we conceive of any real eloquence at all proceeding from
a man who is ignorant of all that is best in the
world?
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    If our reason did not make these facts
obvious, we should still be led by historical examples
to believe their truth. For Pericles, whose eloquence, despite the fact that it has left no visible
record for posterity, was none the less, if we may
believe the historians and that free-speaking tribe,
the old comic poets, endowed with almost incredible
force, is known to have been a pupil of the physicist
Anaxagoras, while Demosthenes, greatest of all the
orators of Greece, sat at the feet of Plato.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    As for
Cicero, he has often proclaimed
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Or. iii 12</hi>
                    </note>
                    the fact that he
owed less to the schools of rhetoric than to the
walks of Academe: nor would he ever have developed
such amazing fertility of talent, had he bounded his
genius by the limits of the forum and not by the
frontiers of nature herself.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But this leads me to another question as to which
school of philosophy is like to prove of most service
to oratory, although there are only a few that can be
said to contend for this honour.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    For in the first
place Epicurus banishes us from his presence without
more ado, since he bids all his followers to fly from
learning in the swiftest ship that they can find.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">paidei/an pa=san a)ka/tion a)ra/menos feu=ge.</foreign>
                    </note>
                    Nor would Aristippus, who regards the highest good
as consisting in physical pleasure, be likely to exhort
us to the toils entailed by our study. And what
part can Pyrrho have in the work that is before us?
For he will have doubts as to whether there exist
judges to address, accused to defend, or a senate
where he can be called upon to speak his opinion.
                    <pb id="p.397"/>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Some authorities hold that the Academy will be the
most useful school, on the ground that its habit of
disputing on both sides of a question approaches
most nearly to the actual practice of the courts.
And by way of proof they add the fact that this
school has produced speakers highly renowned for
their eloquence. The Peripatetics also make it their
boast that they have a form of study which is near
akin to oratory. For it was with them in the main
that originated the practice of declaiming on general
questions
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See II. i. 9. III. v. 5. and 10.</note>
                    by way of exercise. The Stoics, though
driven to admit that, generally speaking, their teachers
have been deficient both in fullness and charm of
eloquence, still contend that no men can prove more
acutely or draw conclusions with greater subtlety
than themselves.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    But all these arguments take
place within their own circle, for, as though they
were tied by some solemn oath or held fast in the
bonds of some superstitious belief, they consider that
it is a crime to abandon a conviction once formed.
On the other hand, there is no need for an orator to
swear allegiance to any one philosophic code.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    For
lie has a greater and nobler aim, to which he directs
all his efforts with as much zeal as if he were a
candidate for office, since he is to be made perfect
not only in the glory of a virtuous life, but in that of
eloquence as well. He will consequently select as
his models of eloquence all the greatest masters of
oratory, and will choose the noblest precepts and
the most direct road to virtue as the means for
the formation of an upright character. He will
neglect no form of exercise, but will devote special
attention to those which are of the highest and
fairest nature.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    For what subject can be found more
                    <pb id="p.399"/>
                    fully adapted to a rich and weighty eloquence than
the topics of virtue, politics, providence, the origin
of the soul and friendship? The themes which tend
to elevate mind and language alike are questions
such as what things are truly good, what means there
are of assuaging fear, restraining the passions and
lifting us and the soul that came from heaven clear
of the delusions of the common herd.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    But it is desirable that we should not restrict our
study to the precepts of philosophy alone. It is still
more important that we should know and ponder
continually all the noblest sayings and deeds that have
been handed down to us from ancient times. And
assuredly we shall nowhere find a larger or more
remarkable store of these than in the records of our
own country.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Who will teach courage, justice,
loyalty, self-control, simplicity, and contempt of
grief and pain better than men like Fabricius, Curius,
Regulus, Decius, Mucius and countless others? For
if the Greeks bear away the palm for moral precepts,
Rome can produce more striking examples of moral
performance, which is a far greater thing.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    But the
man who does not believe that it is enough to fix
his eyes merely on his own age and his own transitory
life, but regards the space allotted for an honourable
life and the course in which glory's race is run as
conditioned solely by the memory of posterity, will
not rest content with a mere knowledge of the
events of history. No, it is from the thought of
posterity that he must inspire his soul with justice
and derive that freedom of spirit which it is his duty
to display when he pleads in the courts or gives
counsel in the senate. No man will ever be the
consummate orator of whom we are in quest unless
                    <pb id="p.401"/>
                    he has both the knowledge and the courage to speak
in accordance with the promptings of honour.
                </p>
                <p>
                    III. Our orator will also require a knowledge of
civil law and of the custom and religion of the state
in whose life he is to bear his part. For how will he
be able to advise either in public or in private, if he
is ignorant of all the main elements that go to make
the state? How can he truthfully call himself an
advocate if he has to go to others to acquire that
knowledge which is all-important in the courts?
He will be little better than if he were a reciter of
the poets.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For he will be a mere transmitter of the
instructions that others have given him, it will be on
the authority of others that he propounds what he
asks the judge to believe, and he whose duty it is to
succour the litigant will himself be in need of succour.
It is true that at times this may be effected with but
little inconvenience, if what he advances for the
edification of the judge has been taught him and
composed in the seclusion of his study and learnt by
heart there like other elements of the case. But
what will he do, when he is confronted by unexpected
problems such as frequently arise in the actual
course of pleading? Will he not disgrace himself by looking round and asking the junior counsel
who sit on the benches behind him for advice?
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Can
lie hope to get a thorough grasp of such information
at the very moment when he is required to produce
it in his speech? Can he make his assertions with
confidence or speak with native simplicity as though
his arguments were his own? Grant that he may do
so in his actual speech. But what will he do in a
debate, when he has continually to meet fresh points
raised by his opponent and is given no time to learn
                    <pb id="p.403"/>
                    up his case? What will do, if he has no legal
expert to advise him or if his prompter through
insufficient knowledge of the subject provides him
with information that is false? It is the most serious
drawback of such ignorance, that he will always
believe that his adviser knows what he is talking
about.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    I am not ignorant of the generally prevailing custom, nor have I forgotten those who sit by
our store-chests and provide weapons for the pleader:
I know too that the Greeks did likewise: hence
the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">pragmaticus</hi>
                    which was bestowed on
such persons. But I am speaking of an orator, who
owes it as a duty to his case to serve it not merely
by the loudness of his voice, but by all other means
that may be of assistance to it.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently I do
not wish my orator to be helpless, if it so chance
that he puts in an appearance for the preliminary
proceedings to which the hour before the commencement of the trial
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Ad horam constare</hi>
                        appears to be a technical
                        <hi rend="italics">term</hi>
                        for
                        <quote>apperance at the preliminary hour.</quote>
                        the purpose of which
is indicated in the paraphrase given above.
                    </note>
                    is allotted, or to be unskilful in
the preparation and production of evidence. For
who, sooner than himself, should prepare the points
which he wishes to be brought out when he is
pleading? You might as well suppose that the
qualifications of a successful general consist merely
in courage and energy in the field of battle and skill
in meeting all the demands of actual conflict, while
suffering him to be ignorant of the methods of levying troops, mustering and equipping his forces,
arranging for supplies or selecting a suitable position
for his camp, despite the fact that preparation for
war is an essential preliminary for its successful
conduct.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And yet such a general would bear a
very close resemblance to the advocate who leaves
much of the detail that is necessary for success to
                    <pb id="p.405"/>
                    the care of others, more especially in view of the
fact that this, the most necessary element in the
management of a case, is not as difficult as it may
perhaps seem to outside observers. For every point
of law, which is certain, is based either on written
law or accepted custom: if, on the other hand, the
point is doubtful, it must be examined in the light
of equity.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Laws which are either written or founded
on accepted custom present no difficulty, since they
call merely for knowledge and make no demand on
the imagination. On the other hand, the points explained in the rulings of the legal experts turn either
on the interpretation of words or on the distinction
between right and wrong. To understand the meaning of each word is either common to all sensible
men or the special possession of the orator, while
the demands of equity are known to every good
man.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Now I regard the orator above all as being
a man of virtue and good sense, who will not be
seriously troubled, after having devoted himself to
the study of that which is excellent by nature, if
some legal expert disagrees with him; for even they
are allowed to disagree among themselves. But if
he further wishes to know the views of everyone,
he will require to read, and reading is the least
laborious of' all the tasks that fall to the student's
lot.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover, if the class of legal experts is as a rule
drawn from those who, in despair of making successful pleaders, have taken refuge with the law,
how easy it must be for an orator to know what
those succeed in learning, who by their own confession are incapable of becoming orators! But
Marcus Cato was at once a great orator and an
expert lawyer, while Scaevola and Servius Sulpicius
                    <pb id="p.407"/>
                    were universally allowed to be eloquent as well.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi>
                        as well as experts on the law.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And Cicero not merely possessed a sufficient supply of
legal knowledge to serve his needs when pleading,
but actually began to write on the subject, so that
it is clear that an orator has not merely time to
learn, but even to teach the law.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Let no one, however, regard the advice I have
given as to the attention due to the development
of character and the study of the law as being
impugned by the fact that we are familiar with
many who, because they were weary of the toil
entailed on those who seek to scale the heights
of eloquence, have betaken themselves to the study
of law as a refuge for their indolence. Some of
these transfer their attention to the praetor's edicts
or the civil law,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The piraetor's edicts were displayed on a whitened board
(
                        <hi rend="italics">in albo</hi>
                        ), while the headings of the civil law were written in
red.
                    </note>
                    and have preferred to become
specialists in
                    <hi rend="italics">formulae,</hi>
                    or legalists, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Or.</hi>
                        I. iv. 231.
                    </note>
                    calls
them, on the pretext of choosing a more useful
branch of study, whereas their real motive was its
comparative easiness.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Others are the victims of a
more arrogant form of sloth; they assume a stern
air and let their beards grow, and, as though despising the precepts of oratory, sit for a while in
the schools of the philosophers, that, by an assumption of a severe mien before the public gaze and by
an affected contempt of others they may assert their
moral superiority, while leading a life of debauchery
at home. For philosophy may be counterfeited, but
eloquence never.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Above all, our orator should be equipped
with a rich store of examples both old and new:
and he ought not merely to know those which are
recorded in history or transmitted by oral tradition
or occur from day to day, but should not neglect
                    <pb id="p.409"/>
                    even those fictitious examples invented by the great
poets.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For while the former have the authority of
evidence or even of legal decisions, the latter also
either have the warrant of antiquity or are regarded
as having been invented by great men to serve as
lessons to the world. He should therefore be acquainted with as many examples as possible. It is
this which gives old age so much authority, since
the old are believed to have a larger store of knowledge and experience, as Homer so frequently bears
witness. But we must not wait till the evening of
our days, since study has this advantage that, as far
as knowledge of facts is concerned, it is capable of
giving the impression that we have lived in ages
long gone by.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Such are the instruments of which I promised
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Pr.</hi>
                        22 and xii.
                        <hi rend="italics">Pr.</hi>
                        4.
                    </note>
                    to give account, the instruments, that is, not merely
of the art, as some have held, but of the orator himself. These are the weapons that he should have
ready to his hand, this the knowledge with which he
must be equipped, while it must be supplemented by
a ready store of words and figures, power of imagination, skill in arrangement, retentiveness of memory
and grace of delivery. But of all these qualities the
highest is that loftiness of soul which fear cannot
dismay nor uproar terrify nor the authority of the
audience fetter further than the respect which is
their due.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For although the vices which are its
opposites, such as arrogance, temerity, impudence
and presumption, are all positively obnoxious, still
without constancy, confidence and courage, art, study
and proficiency will be of no avail. You might as
well put weapons into the hands of the unwarlike
and the coward. It is indeed with some reluctance,
                    <pb id="p.411"/>
                    as it may give rise to misunderstanding, that I say
that even modesty (which, though a fault in itself, is
an amiable failing which may easily be the mother of
virtues) is on occasion an impediment and has
frequently caused the fruits of genius and study to
consume away in the mildew of obscurity merely
because they have never been displayed to the public
day.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But in case any of my readers should still lack
skill to distinguish the precise meaning of each
word, I would have him know that it is not honest
shame that is the object of my criticism, but that
excess of modesty which is really a form of fear
deterring the soul from doing what is its duty to do,
and resulting in confusion of mind, regret that our
task was ever begun, and sudden silence. For who
can hesitate to give the name of fault to a feeling
that makes a man ashamed to do what is right?
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    On
the other hand, I am not unwilling that the man who
has got to make a speech should show signs of
nervousness when he rises to his feet, should change
colour and make it clear that he feels the risks of his
position: indeed, if these symptoms do not occur
naturally, it will be necessary to simulate them.
But the feeling that stirs us should be due to the
realisation of the magnitude of our task and not to
fear: we should be moved, but not to the extent of
collapsing. But the best remedy for such excess
of modesty is confidence: however great our natural
timidity of mien, we shall find strength and support
in the consciousness of the nobility of our task.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    There are also those natural instruments which, as
I mentioned above,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        I
                        <hi rend="italics">Pr.</hi>
                        27.
                    </note>
                    may be further improved by
care, such as voice, lungs and grace of carriage
and movement, all of which are of such importance
                    <pb id="p.413"/>
                    as frequently to give a speaker the reputation for
talent. Our own age has had orators of greater
resource and power, but Trachalus appeared to stand
out above all his contemporaries, when he was speaking. Such was the elect produced by his lofty
stature, the fire of his eye, the dignity of his brow,
the excellence of his gesture, coupled with a voice
which was not almost a tragedian's, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de Or.</hi>
                        I. xxviii. 128.
                    </note>
                    demands that it should be, but surpassed the voice
of all tragedians that I have ever heard.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    At any
rate I remember that, when he was speaking in the
Basilica Julia before the first tribunal, and the four
panels of judges
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Of the Cenutumviral Court. Four different cases were
being tried simultaneously.
                    </note>
                    were assembled as usual and the
whole building was full of noise, he could still be
heard and understood and applauded from all four
tribunals at once, a fact which was not complimentary
to the other pleaders. But gifts like these are such
as all may pray for and few are happy enough to
attain. And if we cannot achieve such fortune, we
must even be content to be heard by the court which
we are addressing. Such then should the orator be,
and such are the things which he should know.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The age at which the orator should begin to
plead will of course depend on the development of
his strength. I shall not specify it further, since it
is clear that Demosthenes pleaded against his
guardians while he was still a mere boy, Calvus,
Caesar and Pollio
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Demosthenes was 18, Crassus 19, Caesar 21, Asinius Pollio
and Calvus not much older. See Tac.
                        <hi rend="italics">Dial.</hi>
                        34.
                    </note>
                    all undertook cases of the first
importance before they were old enough to be
qualified for the quaestorship, others are said to have
pleaded while still wearing the garb of boyhood,
and Augustus Caesar delivered a funeral oration over
his grandmother from the public rostra when he was
only twelve years old.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In my opinion we should aim
                    <pb id="p.415"/>
                    at a happy mean. The unripe brow of boyhood
should not be prematurely robbed of its ingenuous
air nor should the young speaker's powers be brought
before the public while yet unformed, since such a
practice leads to a contempt for study, lays the
foundations of impudence and induces a fault which
is pernicious in all departments of life, namely, a self-confidence that is not justified by the speaker's
resources.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, it is undesirable to
postpone the apprenticeship of the bar till old age:
for the fear of appearing in public grows daily and
the magnitude of the task on which we must venture
continually increases and we waste time deliberating
when we should begin, till we find it is too late to
begin at all. Consequently it is desirable that the
fruit of our studies should be brought before the
public eye while it is still fresh and sweet, while it
may hope for indulgence and be secure of a kindly
disposition in the audience, while boldness is not
unbecoming and youth compensates for all defects
and boyish extravagance is regarded as a sign of
natural vigour.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Take for example the whole of the
well-known passage from Cicero's defence of Sextus
Roscius:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">pro Rose. Amer.</hi>
                        xxvi. 72.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        For what is more common than the air
to the living, than the earth to the dead, than the
sea to mariners or the shore to shipwrecked men?
                    </quote>
                    etc. This passage was delivered at the age of
twenty-six amid loud applause from the audience,
but in later years
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Orat.</hi>
                        xxx. 107.
                    </note>
                    he acknowledges that the ferment
of youth has died down and his style been clarified
with age. And, indeed, however much private study
may contribute to success, there is still a peculiar
proficiency that the courts alone can give: for there
the atmosphere is changed and the reality of the
                    <pb id="p.417"/>
                    peril puts a different complexion on things, while, if
it is impossible to combine the two, practice without
theory is more useful than theory without practice.
Consequently,
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    some who have grown old in the
schools lose their heads when confronted by the
novelty of the law courts and wish that it were
possible to reproduce all the conditions under which
they delivered their exercises. But there sits the
judge in silence, their opponent bellows at them, no
rash utterance passes unnoticed and all assumptions
must be proved, the clock cuts short the speech that
has been laboriously pieced together at the cost of
hours of study both by day and night, and there are
certain cases which require simplicity of language and
the abandonment of the perpetual bombast of the
schools, a fact which these fluent fellows completely
fail to realise.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And so you will find some persons
who regard themselves as too eloquent to speak in
the courts. On the other hand, the man, whom we
conducted to the forum while still young and in the
charm of immaturity, should begin with as easy and
favourable a case as may be (just as the cubs of wild
beasts are brought up to start with on softer
forms of prey), and should not proceed straight
from this commencement to plead case after case
without a break, or cause his talents to set and
harden while they still require nourishment; on the
contrary, as soon as he has come to realise the nature
of the conflicts in which he will have to engage and
the object to which his studies should be directed, he
should take an interval of rest and refreshment.
Thus,
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    at an age to which boldness is still natural, he
will find it easy to get over the timidity which invariably accompanies the period of apprenticeship, and
                    <pb id="p.419"/>
                    will not, on the other hand, carry his boldness so far
as to lead him to despise the difficulties of his task.
This was the method employed by Cicero: for when
he had already won a distinguished position at the
bar of his day, he took ship to Asia and there studied
under a number of professors of philosophy and
rhetoric, but above all under Apollonius Molon,
whose lectures he had attended at Rome and to
whom he now at Rhodes entrusted the refashioning
and recasting of his style. It is only when theory
and practice are brought into a perfect harmony
that the orator reaps the reward of all his study.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    When our orator has developed his strength
to such a pitch that it is equal to every kind of confact in which he may be called upon to bear his part,
his first consideration should be to exercise care in
the choice of the cases which he proposes to undertake. A good man will undoubtedly prefer defence
to prosecution, but he will not have such a rooted
objection to the task of accuser as to disregard his
duty towards the state or towards individuals and
refuse to call any man to render an account of his
way of life. For the laws themselves would be
powerless without the assistance of advocates equal
to the task of supporting them; and to regard it as a
sin to demand the punishment of crime is almost equivalent to the sanctioning of crime, while it is certainly
contrary to the interest of the good to give the
wicked free leave to work their will.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, our
orator will not suffer the complaints of our allies, the
death of friends or kinsmen, or conspiracies that
threaten the common weal to go unavenged, while
his conduct will be governed not by a passion to
secure the punishment of the guilty, but by the
                    <pb id="p.421"/>
                    desire to correct vice and reform morals. For fear
is the only means of restraining those who cannot
be led to better ways by the voice of reason.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, while to devote one's life to the task of
accusation, and to be tempted by the hope of reward
to bring the guilty to trial is little better than making
one's living by highway robbery, none the less to rid
one's country of the pests that gnaw its vitals is
conduct worthy of comparison with that of heroes,
who champion their country's cause in the field of
battle. For this reason men who were leaders of the
state have not refused to undertake this portion of
an orator's duty, and even young men of high rank
have been regarded as giving their country a pledge
of their devotion by accusing bad citizens, since it
was thought that their hatred of evil and their
readiness to incur enmity were proofs of their confidence in their own rectitude.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Such action was
taken by Hortensius, the Luculli, Sulpicius, Cicero,
Caesar and many others, among them both the Catos,
of whom one was actually called the Wise,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        Cato the Elder.
                    </note>
                    while if
the other is not regarded as wise, I do not know of
any that can claim the title after him. On the other
hand, this same orator of ours will not defend all and
sundry: that haven of safety which his eloquence
provides will never be opened to pirates as it is to
others, and he will be led to undertake cases mainly
by consideration of their nature.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    However, since
one man cannot undertake the cases of all litigants
who are not, as many undoubtedly are, dishonest, he
will be influenced to some extent by the character
of the persons who recommend clients to his protection and also by the character of the litigants
themselves, and will allow himself to be moved by
                    <pb id="p.423"/>
                    the wishes of all virtuous men; for a good man will
naturally have such for his most intimate friends.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But he must put away from him two kinds of
pretentious display, the one consisting in the
officious proffering of his services to the powerful
against those of meaner position, and the other,
which is even more obtrusive, in deliberately supporting inferiors against those of high degree. For a
case is not rendered either just or the reverse by the
social position of the parties engaged. Nor, again,
will a sense of shame deter him from throwing over
a case which he has undertaken in the belief that it
had justice on its side, but which his study of the
facts has shown to be unjust, although before doing
so he should give his client his true opinion on the
case.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For, if we judge aright, there is no greater
benefit that we can confer on our clients than this,
that we should not cheat them by giving them empty
hopes of success. On the other hand, no client that
does not take his advocate into his counsel deserves
that advocate's assistance, and it is certainly unworthy
of our ideal orator that he should wittingly defend
injustice. For if he is led to defend what is false
by any of the motives which I mentioned above,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">XII. i. 36.</note>
                    his
own action will still be honourable.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It is an open question whether he should never
demand a fee for his services. To decide the
question at first sight would be the act of a fool.
For we all know that by far the most honourable
course, and the one which is most in keeping with a
liberal education and that temper of mind which we
desiderate, is not to sell our services nor to debase
the value of such a boon as eloquence, since there
are not a few things which come to be regarded as
                    <pb id="p.425"/>
                    cheap, merely because they have a price set upon
them.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    This much even the blind can see, as the
saying is, and no one who is the possessor of sufficient
wealth to satisfy his needs (and that does not imply
any great opulence) will seek to secure an income
by such methods without laying himself open to the
charge of meanness. On the other hand, if his
domestic circumstances are such as to require some
addition to his income to enable him to meet the
necessary demands upon his purse, there is not a
philosopher who would forbid him to accept this form
of recompense for his services, since collections were
made even on behalf of Socrates, and Zeno, Cleanthes
and Chrysippus took fees from their pupils.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Nor
can I see how we can turn a more honest penny than
by performance of the most honourable of tasks and
by accepting money from those to whom we have
rendered the most signal services and who, if they
made no return for what we have done for them,
would show themselves undeserving to have been
defended by us. Nay, it is not only just, but
necessary that this should be so, since the duties of
advocacy and the bestowal of every minute of our
time on the affairs of others deprive us of all other
means of making money.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But we must none the
less observe the happy mean, and it makes no small
difference from whom we take payment, what payment we demand, and how long we continue to do
so. As for the piratical practice of bargaining and
the scandalous traffic of those who proportion their
fees to the peril in which their would-be client
stands, such a procedure will be eschewed even by
those who are more than half scoundrels, more
especially since the advocate who devotes himself
                    <pb id="p.427"/>
                    to the defence of good men and worthy causes will
have nothing to fear from ingratitude. And even if
a client should prove ungrateful, it is better that he
should be the sinner and not our orator.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    To conelude, then, the orator will not seek to make more
money than is sufficient for his needs, and even if he
is poor, he will not regard his payment as a fee, but
rather as the expression of the principle that one
good turn deserves another, since he will be well
aware that he has conferred far more than he receives.
For it does not follow that because his services
ought not to be sold, they should therefore be
unremunerated. Finally, gratitude is primarily the
business of the debtor.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    We have next to consider how a case should
be studied, since such study is the foundation of
oratory. There is no one so destitute of all talent
as, after making himself thoroughly familiar with all
the facts of his case, to be unable at least to communicate those facts to the judge.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But those who
devote any serious attention to such study are very
few indeed. For, to say nothing of those careless
advocates who are quite indifferent as to what the
pivot of the whole case may be, provided only there
are points which, though irrelevant to the case, will
give them the opportunity of declaiming in thunderous tones on the character of persons involved or
developing some commonplace, there are some who
are so perverted by vanity that, on the oft-repeated
pretext that they are occupied by other business,
they bid their client come to them on the day preceding the trial or early on the morning of the day
itself, and sometimes even boast that they learnt up
their case while sitting in court;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    while others by
                    <pb id="p.429"/>
                    way of creating an impression of extraordinary talent,
and to make it seem that they arc quick in the uptake, pretend that they have grasped the facts of
the case and understand the situation almost before
they have heard what it is, and then after chanting
out some long and fluent discourse which has nought
to do either with the judge or their client, but
awakens the clamorous applause of the audience,
they are escorted home through the forum, perspiring
at every pore and attended by flocks of enthusiastic
friends.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Further, I would not even tolerate the
affectation of those who insist that their friends, and
not themselves, should be instructed in the facts
of the case, though this is a less serious evil, if the
friends can be relied upon to learn and supply the
facts correctly. But who can give such effective
study to the case as the advocate himself? How
can the intermediary, the go-between or interpreter,
devote himself whole-heartedly to the study of other
men's cases, when those who have got to do the
actual pleading do not think it worth while to get
up their own?
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, it is a most
pernicious practice to rest content with a written
statement of the case composed either by the litigant
who betakes himself to an advocate because he finds
that his own powers are not equal to the conduct of
his case, or by some member of that class of legal
advisers
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Advocatus</hi>
                        is here used in its original sense. By Quintilian's time it had come also to mean
                        <quote>advocate,</quote>
                        and is
often so used by him elsewhere.
                    </note>
                    who admit that they are incapable of pleading, and then proceed to take upon themselves the
most difficult of all the tasks that confront the pleader.
For if a man is capable of judging what should be
said, what concealed, what avoided, altered or even
invented, why should he not appear as orator himself,
since he performs the far more difficult feat of making
                    <pb id="p.431"/>
                    an orator?
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Such persons would not, however, do so
much harm if they would only put down all the
facts as they occurred. But as it is, they add suggestions of their own, put their own construction on
the facts and insert inventions which are far more
damaging than the unvarnished truth. And then
the advocate as a rule, on receiving the document,
regards it as a crime to make any alteration, and
keeps to it as faithfully as if it were a theme set for
declamation in the schools. The sequel is that they
are tripped up and have to learn from their opponents the case which they refused to learn from their
own clients.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    We should therefore above all allow
the parties concerned ample time for an interview in
a place free from interruption, and should even
exhort them to set forth on the spot all the facts in
as many words as they may choose to use and allowing them to go as far back as they please. For it is
less of a drawback to listen to a number of irrelevant
facts than to be left in ignorance of essentials.
Moreover,
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    the orator will often detect both the evil
and its remedy in facts which the litigant regarded
as devoid of all importance, one way or the other.
Further, the advocate who has got to plead the case
should not put such excessive confidence in his
powers of memory as to disdain to jot down what he
has heard.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Nor should one hearing be regarded as sufficient.
The litigant should be made to repeat his statements
at least once, not merely because certain points may
have escaped him on the occasion of his first statement, as is extremely likely to happen if, as is often
the case, he is a man of no education, but also that
we may note whether he sticks to what he originally
                    <pb id="p.433"/>
                    said.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For a large number of clients lie, and hold
forth, not as if they were instructing their advocate
in the facts of the case, but as if they were pleading
with a judge. Consequently we must never be too
ready to believe them, but must test them in every
way, try to confuse them and draw them out.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For
just as doctors have to do more than treat the
ailments which meet the eye, and need also to
discover those which he hid, since their patients
often conceal the truth, so the advocate must look
out for more points than his client discloses to him.
After he considers that he has given a sufficiently
patient hearing to the latter's statements, he must
assume another character and adopt the rôle of his
opponent, urging every conceivable objection that a
discussion of the kind which we are considering may
permit.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The client must be subjected to a hosthe
cross-examination and given no peace: for by enquiring into everything, we shall sometimes come
upon the truth where we least expect it.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In fact, the advocate who is most successful in
getting up his case is he who is incredulous. For
the client promises everything: the people, he says,
will bear witness to the truth of what he says, he can
produce documentary evidence at a moment's notice
and there are some points which he says his opponent
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    will not deny. It is therefore necessary to look into
every document connected with the case, and where
the mere sight of them is not sufficient, they must
be read through. For very frequently they are
either not at all what the client alleged them to be,
or contain less, or are mixed up with elements that
may damage our case, or prove more than is required
and are likely to detract from their credibility just
                    <pb id="p.435"/>
                    because they are so extravagant.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Further, it will
often be found that the thread is broken or the seal
tampered with or the signatures unsupported by
witnesses. And unless you discover such facts at
home, they will take you by surprise in court and
trip you up, doing you more harm by forcing you to
abandon them than they would have done had they
never been promised you. There are also a number
of points which the client regards as irrelevant to
his case, which the advocate will be able to elicit,
provided he go carefully through all the
                    <quote>dwelling places</quote>
                    of argument which I have already described.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        V. x. 20
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq. i. e.</hi>
                        sources from which arguments may be
drawn.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Now though, for reasons already mentioned, it is
most undesirable that he should hunt for and try
every single one of those, while actually engaged in
pleading his case, it is most necessary in the preliminary study of the case to leave no stone unturned to
discover the character of the persons involved, the
circumstances of time and place, the customs and
documents concerned, and the rest, from which we
may not merely deduce the proofs known as artificial,
but may also discover which witnesses are most to be
feared and the best method of refuting them. For
it makes a great difference whether it be envy,
hatred or contempt that forms the chief obstacle to
the success of the defence, since of these obstacles
the first tells most against superiors, the second
against equals, and the third against those of low
degree.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Having thus given a thorough examination
to the case and clearly envisaged all those points
which will tell for or against his client, the orator
must then place himself in the position of a third
person, namely, the judge, and imagine that the
                    <pb id="p.437"/>
                    case is being pleaded before himself, and assume
that the point which would have carried most weight
with himself, had he been trying the case, is likely
to have the greatest influence with the actual judge.
Thus he will rarely be deceived as to the result of
the trial, or, if he is, it will be the fault of the judge.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the points to be observed in the
actual pleading, I have dealt with these in every
portion of this work, but there still remain a few on
which I must touch as being specially appropriate to
the present place, since they are concerned not so
much with the art of speaking as with the duties
of the advocate. Above all it is important that he
should never, like so many, be led by a desire to win
applause to neglect the interest of the actual case.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    It is not always the duty of generals in the field to
lead their armies through flat and smiling country:
it will often be necessary to cross rugged mountain
ranges, to storm cities placed on inaccessible cliffs or
rendered difficult of access by elaborate fortifications.
Similarly oratory will always be glad of the opportunity of manœuvring in all its freedom and delighting the spectator by the deployment of its full
strength for conflict in the open field;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    but if it is
forced to enter the tortuous defiles of the law, or
dark places whence the truth has to be dragged
forth, it will not go prancing in front of the enemy's
lines nor launch its shafts of quivering and passionate
epigram of the fashion that is now so popular, but
will wage war by means of sap and mine and ambush
and all the tactics of secrecy.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    None of these
methods win applause during their actual execution:
the reward comes after they have been carried to a
successful termination, when even the most ambitious
                    <pb id="p.439"/>
                    will reap a richer recompense than they could ever
have secured by other means. For so soon as the
thunders of applause awakened among their admirers
by these affected declamatory displays have died
away, the glory of true virtue rises again with
renewed splendour, the judges do not conceal who
it is has moved them, the well-trained orator wins
their belief and oratory receives its only genuine
tribute, the praise accorded it when its task is done.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The old orators indeed used to conceal their eloquence, a method which is recommended by Marcus
Antonius, as a means of securing that the speaker's
words should carry conviction and of masking the
advocate's real designs. But the truth is that the
eloquence of those days was capable of concealment,
for it had not yet attained that splendour of diction
which makes it impossible to hide its light under a
bushel. Therefore artifice and stratagem should be
masked, since detection in such cases spells failure.
Thus far, and thus only, may eloquence hope to enjoy
the advantages of secrecy.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But when we come to
consider the choice of words, the weight essential
to general reflexions and the elegance demanded by
figures, we are confronted by elements which must
either strike the attention or be condemned to nonexistence. But the very fact that they strike the
attention is a reason why they should not flaunt
themselves obtrusively. And, if we have to make
the choice, I should prefer that it should be the
cause, and not the orator, to which we award our
praise. Nevertheless, the true orator will achieve
the distinction of seeming to speak with all the
excellence that an excellent case deserves. One
thing may be regarded as certain, that no one can
                    <pb id="p.441"/>
                    plead worse than he who wins applause despite the
disapproval meted out to his case. For the inevitable
conclusion is that the applause must have been
evoked by something having no connexion with the
case.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Further, the true orator will not turn up his
nose at cases of minor importance on the ground of
their being beneath his dignity or as being likely
to detract from his reputation because the subject
matter does not allow his genius full scope. For the
strongest reason for undertaking a case is to be fund
in our duty towards our clients: nay, we should even
desire the suits in which our friends are involved to
he as unimportant as possible, and remember that the
advocate who gives an adequate presentment to his
case, has spoken exceeding well.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But there are so he who, even although the cases
which they have undertaken give but small scope for
eloquence, none the less trick it out with matter
drawn from without and, if all else fails, fill up the
gaps in their case with abuse of their opponents,
true if possible, but false if necessary, the sole consideration that weighs with them being that it affords
exercise for their talents and is likely to win applause
during its delivery. Such conduct seems to me so
unworthy of our perfect orator that, in my opinion,
he will not even bring true charges against his
opponents unless the case demand.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For it is a
dog's eloquence, as Appius says, to undertake the
task of abusing one's opponent,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">A cognitor</hi>
                        is one who represents another. The litigant
may abuse his opponent, but that does not justify his
advocate in doing so.
                    </note>
                    and they who do so
should steel themselves in advance to the prospect
of being targets for like abuse themselves, since
those who adopt this style of pleading are frequently
attacked themselves, and there can at any rate be
no doubt that the litigant pays dearly for the violence
                    <pb id="p.443"/>
                    of his advocate. But such faults are less serious than
that which lies deep in the soul itself, making the
evil speaker to differ from the evil doer only in
respect of opportunity.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It is not uncommon for
the litigant to demand a base and inhuman gratification of his rancour, such as not a single man among
the audience will approve, for it is on revenge rather
than on protection that his heart is set. But in this,
as in a number of other points, it is the duty of the
orator to refuse to comply with his clients' desires.
For how can a man with the least degree of gentlemanly feeling consent to make a brutal attack merely
because another desires it?
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    And yet there are some
who take pleasure in directing their onslaughts
against their opponents' counsel as well, a practice
which, unless they have deserved such attacks, shows
an inhuman disregard of the duties incumbent on the
profession, and is not merely useless to the speaker
(since he thereby gives his opponent the right to
reply in the same strain), but contrary to the
interests of his case, since it creates a hosthe and
antagonistic disposition in the advocates attacked,
whose eloquence, however feeble it may be, will be
redoubled by resentment at the insults to which
they have been subjected.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Above all, it involves a
complete waste of one of the most valuable of an
orator's assets, namely that self-restraint which gives
weight and credit to his words, if he debases himself from an honest man into a snarling wrangler,
directing all his efforts not to win the goodwill of the
judge, but to gratify his client's spite.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Often too
the attractions of freedom of speech will lure him
into a rashness of language perilous not merely to
the interests of the case, but to those of the speaker
                    <pb id="p.445"/>
                    himself. It was not without good reason that Pericles used to pray that no word might occur to his
mind that could give offence to the people. But
what he felt with regard to the people, I feel with
regard to every audience, since they can cause just
as much harm to the orator as the people could
ever do to Pericles. For utterances which seemed
courageous at the moment of speaking, are called
foolish when it is found that they have given offence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    In view of the tact that there is commonly a great
variety in the aims which pleaders set before themselves and that the diligence shown by some is
branded as tedious caution, while the readiness of
others is criticised as rashness, I think that this will
be an appropriate place to set forth my views as to
how the orator may strike the happy mean.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    He will
show all the diligence of which he is capable in his
pleading. For to plead worse than he might have
done, is not merely an indication of negligence, but
stamps him as a had man and a traitor, disloyal to the
cause which he has undertaken. Consequently he
must refuse to undertake more cases than he feels
he can manage.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    As far as possible he will deliver
only what he has written, and, if circumstances
permit, only what he has, as Demosthenes says,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">This passage is our sole authority for the saying.</note>
                    carved into shape. Such a practice is possible in
first hearings and also in subsequent hearings such as
are granted in the public courts after an interval of
several days. On the other hand, when we have to
reply on the spot, it is impossible to prepare everything: in fact for the less ready type of speaker, it
may, in the event of his opponents putting forward
arguments quite other than those which they were
expected to advance, be a positive drawback to have
                    <pb id="p.447"/>
                    written anything.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    For it is only with reluctance
that such speakers will under such circumstances
consent to abandon what they have written, and
throughout their pleading keep looking back and
trying to discover whether any portion of their
manuscript can be saved from the wreck and interpolated into what they have to improvise. And if
they do make such interpolations, the result is a lack
of' cohesion which is betrayed not merely by the
gaping of the seams where the patch has been unskilfully inserted, but by the differences of style.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, the vigour of their eloquence will be
hampered and their thought will lack connexion, each
of which circumstances reacts unfavourably upon the
other, since what is written trammels the mind
instead of following its lead. Therefore, in such
pleadings we must, as the rustic adage says,
                    <quote>stand on all our feet.</quote>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    For since the case turns on the
propounding and refutation of arguments, it is
always possible to write out what we propose to
advance on our own behalf, and similar preparation
is also possible with regard to the refutation of such
replies as are absolutely certain to be made by our
adversary: for there are times when we have this
certainty. But with regard to all other portions of
our speech, the only preparation that is possible in
advance consists in a thorough knowledge of our
case, while there is a second precaution which may
be taken in court, consisting in giving our best
attention to our opponent's speech.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    On the other
hand, there is much that may be thought out in
advance and we may forearm our mind against all
possible emergencies, a course which is far safer
than writing, since a train of thought can easily be
                    <pb id="p.449"/>
                    abandoned or diverted in a new direction. But
whether we have to improvise a reply, or are obliged
to speak extempore by some other reason, the orator
on whom training, study and practice have conferred
the gift of facility, will never regard himself as lost
or taken at hopeless disadvantage.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    He stands
armed for battle, ever ready for the fray, and his
eloquence will no more fail him in the courts than
speech will fail him in domestic affairs and the daily
concerns of life: and he will never shirk his burden
for fear of failing to find words, provided he has time
to study his case: for all other knowledge will always
be his at command.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The question of the
                    <quote>kind of style</quote>
                    to be
adopted remains to be discussed. This was described
in my original division
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">II. xiv. 5.</note>
                    of my subject as forming its
third portion: for I promised that I would speak of
the art, the artist and the work. But since oratory
is the work both of rhetoric and of the orator, and
since it has many forms, as I shall show, the art and
the artist are involved in the consideration of all
these forms. But they differ greatly from one
another, and not merely in
                    <hi rend="italics">species,</hi>
                    as statue differs
from statue, picture from picture and speech from
speech, but in
                    <hi rend="italics">genus</hi>
                    as well, as, for example,
Etruscan statues differ from Greek and Asiatic
orators from Attic.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But these different kinds of
work, of which I speak, are not merely the product
of different authors, but have each their own following of admirers, with the result that the perfect
orator has not yet been found, a statement which
perhaps may be extended to all arts, not merely
because some qualities are more evident in some
artists than in others, but because one single form
                    <pb id="p.451"/>
                    will not satisfy all critics, a fact which is due in
part to conditions of time or place, in part to the
taste and ideals of individuals.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The first great painters, whose works deserve
inspection for something more than their mere
antiquity, are said to have been Polygnotus and
Aglaopllon,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Of the painters mentioned in this and the following
sections Polyglotus of Thasos, son of Aglaophon, painted at
Athens in the middle of the 5th century B.C.. Zunis of
Heracelea Parrhasius of Ephesus flourished 420–390, while
the remainder are painters of the 4th century. Of these
Palmphilus of Sicyon was the teacher of Melanthius and
Apelles, the latter being the most famous painter of antiquity.
                    </note>
                    whose simple colouring has still such
enthusiastic admirers that they prefer these almost
primitive works, which may be regarded as the first
foundations of the art that was to be, over the works
of the greatest of their successors, their motive
being, in my opinion, an ostentatious desire to seem
persons of superior taste.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Later Zeuxis and Parrhasius contributed much to the progress of painting.
These artists were separated by no great distance of
time, since both flourished about the period of the
Peloponnesian war: for example, Xenophon
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Memoir.</hi>
                        III. x. 1.
                    </note>
                    has
preserved a conversation between Socrates and
Parrhasius. The first-mentioned seems to have
discovered the method of representing light and
shade, while the latter is said to have devoted
special attention to the treatment of line.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For
Zeuxis emphasised the limbs of the human body,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi>
                        by giving them roundness and solidity by his treatment of light and shade.
                    </note>
                    thinking thereby to add dignity and grandeur to
his style: it is generally supposed that in this he
followed the example of Homer, who likes to
represent even his female characters as being of
heroic mould. Parrhasius, on the other hand, was
so fine a draughtsman that he has been styled the
law-giver of his art, on the ground that all other
artists take his representations of gods and heroes as
models, as though no other course were possible.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It was, however, from about the period of the reign
of Philip down to that of the successors of Alexander
                    <pb id="p.453"/>
                    that painting flourished more especially, although
the different artists are distinguished for different
excellences. Protogenes, for example, was renowned
for accuracy, Pamphilus and Melanthius for soundness of taste, Antiphilus for facility, Theon of Samos
for his depiction of imaginary scenes, known as
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">fantasi/ai,</foreign>
                    and Apelles for genius and grace, in the
latter of which qualities he took especial pride.
Euphranor, on the other hand, was admired on the
ground that, while he ranked with the most eminent
masters of other arts, he at the same time achieved
marvellous skill in the arts of sculpture and painting.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The same differences exist between sculptors. The
art of Callon and Hegesias
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Callon of Aegina and Hegesias flourished in the latter
years of the 6th century. Calamis of Athens and Myron of
Eleutheae, first half of 5th centuryy. Phidlias of Athens and
Polyelitus of Argos, the two most famous sculptors of the
second half of 5th century. Praxiteles, middle of 4th
century. Lysippus and Demetrius, last half of 4th century.
                    </note>
                    is somewhat rude and
recalls the Etruscans, but the work of Calamis has
already begun to be less stiff, while Myron's statues
show a greater softness of form than had been
achieved by the artists just mentioned. Polyclitus
surpassed all others for care and grace, but although
the majority of critics account him as the greatest
of sculptors, to avoid making him faultless they
express the opinion that his work is lacking in
grandeur.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For while he gave the human form an
ideal grace, he is thought to have been less successful in representing the dignity of the gods. he is
further alleged to have shrunk from representing
persons of maturer years, and to have ventured on
nothing more difficult than a smooth and beardless
face. But the qualities lacking in Polyclitus are
allowed to have been possessed by Phidias and
Alcamenes.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, Phidias is regarded
as more gifted in his representation of gods than of
men, and indeed for chryselephantine statues he is
without a peer, as he would in truth be, even if he
                    <pb id="p.455"/>
                    had produced nothing in this material beyond his
Minerva at Athens and his Jupiter at Olympia in
Elis, whose beauty is such that it is said to have
added something even to the awe with which the
god was already regarded: so perfectly did the
majesty of the work give the impression of godhead.
Lysippus and Praxiteles are asserted to be supreme
as regards faithfulness to nature. For Demetrius is
blamed for carrying realism too far, and is less
concerned about the beauty than the truth of his
work.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Now, if we turn our attention to the various styles
of oratory, we shall find almost as great variety of
talents as there are of personal appearance. There
were certain kinds of oratory which, owing to the
circumstances of the age, suffered from lack of polish,
although in other respects they displayed remarkable
genius. In this class we may place orators such as
Laelius, Africanus, Cato, and even the Gracchi,
whom we may call the
                    <quote>Polygnoti</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>Callones</quote>
                    of oratory.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Among orators of the intermediate
type we may rank Lucius Crassus and Quintus
Hortensius. Then let us turn to a vast harvest of
orators who flourished much about the same period.
It is here that we find the vigour of Caesar, the
natural talent of Caelius, the subtlety of Calidius,
the accuracy of Pollio, the dignity of Messala, the
austerity of Calvus, the gravity of Brutus, the acumen
of Sulpicius and the bitterness of Cassius, while
among those whom we have seen ourselves we
admire the fluency of Seneca, the strength of Africanus, the mellowness of Afer, the charm of Crispus,
the sonority of Trachalus and the elegance of Secundus.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    But in Cicero we have one who is not,
                    <pb id="p.457"/>
                    like Euphranor, merely distinguished in a number
of different forms of art, but is supreme in all the
different qualities which are praised in each individual
orator.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Cp.</hi>
                        x. i. 105
                        <hi rend="italics">sq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    And yet even his own contemporaries
ventured to attack him on the ground that he was
bombastic, Asiatic, redundant, given to excessive
repetition, liable at times to be pointless in his
witticisms, sensuous, extravagant and (an outrageous
accusation!) almost effeminate in his rhythm.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    And
later, after he had fallen a victim to the proscription of the second triumvirate, those who hated
and envied him and regarded him as their rival, nay,
even those who had flattered him in the days of his
power, attacked him now that he could no longer
reply. But that very man, who is now regarded
by some as being too jejune and dry, was attacked
by his personal enemies on no other ground than
that his style was too florid and his talents too little
under control. Both charges are false, but there is
more colour for the he in the latter case than in
the former.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Those, however, who criticised him
most severely were the speakers who desired to be
regarded as the imitators of Attic oratory. This
coterie, regarding themselves as the sole initiates in
the mysteries of their art, assailed him as an alien,
indifferent to their superstitions and refusing to be
bound by their laws. Their descendants are among
us to-day, a withered, sapless and anemic band.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For it is they that flaunt their weakness under the
name of health, in defiance of the actual truth, and
because they cannot endure the dazzling rays of the
sun of eloquence, hide themselves beneath the
shadow of a mighty name.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi>
                        Attic.
                    </note>
                    However, as Cicero himself answered them at length and in a number of
                    <pb id="p.459"/>
                    passages, it will be safer for me to be brief in my
treatment of this topic.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The distinction between the Attic and the Asiatic
schools takes us back to antiquity. The former were
regarded as concise and healthy, the latter as empty
and inflated: the former were remarkable for the
absence of all superfluity, while the latter were
deficient alike in taste and restraint. The reason
for this division, according to some authorities,
among them Santra, is to be found in the fact that,
as Greek gradually extended its range into the
neighbouring cities of Asia, there arose a class of
men who desired to distinguish themselves as orators
before they had acquired sufficient command of the
language, and who consequently began to express
by periphrases what could have been expressed
directly, until finally this practice became an ingrained habit.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    My own view, however, is that the
difference between the two styles is attributable to
the character both of the orators and the audiences
whom they addressed: the Athenians, with their
polish and refinement, refused to tolerate emptiness
and redundance, while the Asiatics, being naturally
given to bombast and ostentation, were puffed up
with a passion for a more vainglorious style of
eloquence.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    At a later period, the critics, to whom
we owe this classification, added a third style, the
Rhodian, which they asserted to he midway between
the two and to be a blend of both, since the orators
of this school are neither so concise as the Attic nor
redundant like the Asiatic school, but appear to
derive their style in part from their national characteristics, in part from those of their founder.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    For
it was Aeschines who introduced the culture of
                    <pb id="p.461"/>
                    Athens at Rhodes, which he had chosen as his place
of exile: and just as certain plants degenerate as a
result of change of soil and climate, so the fine Attic
flavour was marred by the admixture of foreign
ingredients. Consequently certain of the orators of
this school are regarded as somewhat slow and
lacking in energy, though not devoid of a certain
weight, and as resembling placid pools rather than
the limpid springs of Athens or the turbid torrents
of Asia.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    No one therefore should have any hesitation in
pronouncing Attic oratory to be by far the best. But
although all Attic writers have something in comion, namely a keen and exact judgement, their
talents manitest themselves in a number of different
forms.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently I regard those critics as committing a serious error who regard only those
authors as Attic who, while they are simple, lucid
and expressive, are none the less content with a
certain frugality of eloquence, and keep their hands
modestly within the folds of their cloaks. For what
author is there who answers to this conception? I
am prepared to grant that there is Lysias, since he
is the favourite model of the admirers of this school,
and such an admission will save us from being
referred to Coccus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The only Coccus known to us is stated by Suidas to
have been a pupil of Isocrates, whereas we should here
have expected Quintilian to refer to some orator of the
5th century contemporary with Andocides (closing decades
of 4th century).
                    </note>
                    and Andocides.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    But I should like
to ask whether Isocrates spoke in the Attic style.
For there is no author less like Lysias. They will
answer in the negative. And yet it is to the school
of Isocrates that we owe the greatest orators. Let
us look for something closer. Is Hyperides
Attic? Yes, they reply, but of an over-sensuous
character. I pass by a number of orators, such as
Lyucrgus and Aristogeiton and their predecessors
                    <pb id="p.463"/>
                    Isaeus and Antiphon; for though they have a certain
                    <hi rend="italics">generic</hi>
                    resemblance, they may be said to differ in
                    <hi rend="italics">species.</hi>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    But what of Aesehines, whom I mentioned
just now? Is not his style ampler and holder and
more lofty than theirs? And what of Demosthenes
himself? Did not he surpass all those simple and
circumspect orators in force, loftiness, energy, polish
and rhythm? Does he not rise to great heights in
his
                    <hi rend="italics">commonplaces</hi>
                    Does he not rejoice in the employment of figures? Does he not make brilliant use of
metaphor? Does he not lend a voice, a fictitious
utterance to speechless things?
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Does not his famous
oath by the warriors who fell fighting for their country
at Salamis and Marathon show that Plato was his
master? And shall we call Plato an Asiatic, Plato
who as a rule deserves comparison with poets instinct
with the divine fire of inspiration? What of Pericles?
Can we believe that his style was like the slender
stream of Lysias' eloquence, when the comedians,
even while they revile him, compare his oratory to
the bolts and thunder of the skies?
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    What is the
reason, then, why these critics regard that style
which flows in a slender trickle and babbles among
the pebbles as having the true Attic flavour and
the true scent of Attic thyme? I really think that,
if they were to discover a soil of exceptional richness
and a crop of unusual abundance within the boundaries
of Attica, they would deny it to be Attic, on the
ground that it has produced more seed than it
received: for you will remember the mocking comments passed by Menander
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Georg. 35 sqq.</hi>
                        (Koerte);
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">
                            a)pe/dwken o)rqw=s kai\ dikai/ws, ou) ple/on, | a)ll' au)to\ to\ me/tron.
                        </foreign>
                    </note>
                    on the exact fidelity
with which the soil of Attica repays its deposits.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Well, then, if any man should, in addition to the
actual virtues which the great orator Demosthenes
                    <pb id="p.465"/>
                    possessed, show himself to be the possessor of others,
that either owing to his own temperament or the
laws of Athens
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See II. xvi. 4. Quintilian alludes to an alleged law forbidding Athenian oratos, to appeal to the emotions in the
law courts.
                    </note>
                    Demosthenes is thought to have
lacked, and should reveal in himself the power of
strongly stirring the emotions, shall I hear one of
these critics protesting that Demosthenes never did
this? And if he produces something rhythmically
superior (an impossible feat, perhaps, but let us
assume it to be so), are we to be told that it is not
Attic? These critics would show finer feeling and
better judgement, if they took the view that Attic
eloquence meant perfect eloquence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Still I should find this attitude less intolerable if
it were only the Greeks that insisted on it. For Latin
eloquence, although in my opinion it closely resembles
the Greek as far as invention, arrangement, judgement and the like are concerned, and may indeed be
regarded as its disciple, cannot aspire to imitate it
in point of elocution. For, in the first place, it is
harsher in sound, since our alphabet does not contain
the most euphonious of the Greek letters, one a
vowel and the other a consonant,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">f</foreign>
                        alio
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">g</foreign>
                        .
                    </note>
                    than which there
are none that fall more sweetly on the ear, and
which we are forced to borrow whenever we use
Greek words.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    The result of such borrowing is, for
some reason or other, the immediate accession to
our language of a certain liveliness and charm.
Take, for example, words such as
                    <hi rend="italics">sephyri</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">zophori:</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Friezes.</note>
                    if they were spelt according to the Latin alphabet,
they would produce a heavy and barbarous sound.
For we replace these letters by others of a harsh
and unpleasant character,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        F and U;
                        <hi rend="italics">zefuri and zofori.</hi>
                    </note>
                    from which Greece is
happily immune.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    For the sixth letter in our alphabet
is represented by a sound which can scarcely be
                    <pb id="p.467"/>
                    called human or even articulate, being produced by
forcing the air through the interstices of the teeth.
Such a sound, even when followed by a vowel, is
harsh enough and, as often as it clashes (
                    <hi rend="italics">frangit</hi>
                    )
with a consonant,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        I. iv. 11.
                    </note>
                    as it does in this very word
                    <hi rend="italics">frangit,</hi>
                    becomes harsher still. Then there is the
Aeolic digamma whose sound occurs in words such
as our
                    <hi rend="italics">servus</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">cervus;</hi>
                    for even though we have
rejected the actual form of the letter, we cannot
get rid of that which it represents.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A sound approximating to our W.</note>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Similarly the
letter Q, which is superfluous and useless save for
the purpose of attaching to itself the vowels by
which it is followed, results in the formation of
harsh syllables, as, for example, when we write
                    <hi rend="italics">equos</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">aequum,</hi>
                    more especially since these two vowels
together produce a sound for which Greek has no
equivalent and which cannot therefore be expressed
in Greek letters.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The sound of Q in itself does not differ from C. It
would therefore be useless, save as an indication that U and
another vowel are to follow. The U in this combination
following Q was, as Donatus later pointed out,
                        <quote>neither a vowel nor a consonant,</quote>
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                        it was something between U
and V.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Again, we have a number of
words which end with M, a letter which suggests
the mooing of a cow, and is never the final letter
in any Greek word: for in its place they use the
letters
                    <hi rend="italics">nu,</hi>
                    the sound of which is naturally pleasant
and produces a ringing tone when it occurs at the
end of' a word, whereas in Latin this termination is
scarcely ever found.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Again, we have syllables which
produce such a harsh effect by ending in B and
D, that
                    <hi rend="italics">many,</hi>
                    not, it is true, of our most ancient
writers, but still writers of considerable antiquity,
have attempted to mitigate the harshness not merely
by saying
                    <hi rend="italics">aversa</hi>
                    for
                    <hi rend="italics">abversa,</hi>
                    but by adding an S
to the preposition
                    <hi rend="italics">ab,</hi>
                    although S is an ugly letter
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    in itself Our accents also are less agreeable than
those of the Greeks. This is due to a certain rigidity
and monotony of pronunciation, since the final
                    <pb id="p.469"/>
                    syllable is never marked by the rise of the acute
accent nor by the rise and fill of the circumflex, but
one or even two grave accents
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi>
                        the last syllable and often the last
                        <hi rend="italics">two</hi>
                        syllables
have the grave accent. See I. v.
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    are regularly to be
found at the end. Consequently the Greek language
is so much more agreeable in sound than the Latin,
that our poets, whenever they wish their verse to
be especially harmonious, adorn it with Greek words.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    A still stronger indication of the inferiority of Latin
is to be found in the fact that there are many things
which have no Latin names, so that it is necessary
to express them by metaphor or periphrasis, while
even in the case of things which have names, the
extreme poverty of the language leads us to resort
to the same practice.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.</hi>
                        because the names are not holly adequate and
there are no satisfactory synonyms.
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, the
Greeks have not merely abundance of words, but
they have also a number of different dialects.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently he who demands from Latin the
grace of Attic Greek, must first provide a like
charm of tone and equal richness of vocabulary. If
this advantage is denied us, we must adapt our
thoughts to suit the words we have and, where our
matter is unusually slight and delicate, must avoid
expressing it in words which are, I will not say too
gross, but at any rate too strong for it, for fear that
the combination should result in the destruction
both of delicacy and force.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    For the less help we
get from the language, the more must we rely on
inventiveness of thought to bring us through the
conflict. We must discover sentiments full of loftiness and variety, must stir all the emotions and
illumine our style by brilliance of metaphor. Since
we cannot be so delicate, let us be stronger. If
they beat us for subtlety, let us prevail by weight,
and if they have greater precision, let us outdo
                    <pb id="p.471"/>
                    them in fullness of expression.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    Even the lesser
orators of Greece have their own havens where they
may ride in safety,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Owing to the subtlety and delicacy of the Greek
language even second-rate talent will he able to win distinction in dealing with minor things. But the coarser and
more full-blooded nature of Latin makes this difficult.
                    </note>
                    while we as a rule carry more
sail. Let stronger gales fill our canvas, and yet let
us not always keep the high seas; for at times we
must cling to shore. The Greeks can easily traverse
any shallows; I must find a deeper, though not
much deeper, channel, that my bark may not run
aground.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    For even though the Greeks surpass us
where circumstances call for delicacy and restraint,
though we acknowledge their superiority in this
respect alone, and therefore do not claim to rival
them in comedy, that is no justification for our
abandonment of this department of oratory, but
rather a reason why we should handle it as best we
can. Now we can at any rate resemble the Greeks
in the method and judgement with which we treat
our matter, although that grace of language, which
our words cannot provide, must be secured by the
admixture of foreign condiments.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    For example, is
not Cicero shrewd, simple and not unduly exalted
in tone, when he deals with private eases? Is not
Calidius also distinguished for the same virtue?
Were not Scipio, Laelius and Cato the Attic orators
of Rome? Surely we ought to be satisfied with
them, since nothing can be better.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    There are still some critics who deny that any
form of eloquence is purely natural, except that
which closely resembles the ordinary speech of everyday life, which we use to our friends, our wives, our
children and our slaves, a language, that is to say,
which contents itself with expressing the purpose
of the mind without seeking to discover anything
in the way of elaborate and far-fetched phraseology.
                    <pb id="p.473"/>
                    And they hold that whatever is added to this
simplicity lays the speaker open to the charge of
affectation and pretentious ostentation of speech,
void of all sincerity and elaborated merely for the
sake of the words, although the sole duty assigned
to words by nature is to be the servants of thought.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Such language may be compared to the bodies of
athletes, which although they develop their strength
by exercise and diet, are of unnatural growth and
abnormal in appearance. For what, say these critics,
is the good of expressing a thing by periphrasis or
metaphor (that is, either by a number of words or
by words which have no connexion with the thing),
when everything has been allotted a name of its
own?
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    Finally, they urge that all the earliest orators
spoke according to the dictates of nature, but that
subsequently there arose a class of speakers resembling poets rather than orators, who regarded
false and artificial methods of expression as positive
merits; they were, it is true, more sparing than
the poets in their use of such expressions, but none
the less worked on similar lines. There is some
truth in this contention, and we should therefore
be careful not to depart from the more exact usage
of ordinary speech to the extent that is done by
certain orators.
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, that is no
reason for thus calumniating the man who, as I said
in dealing with the subject of artistic structure,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">x. ch. 4.</note>
                    succeeds in improving upon the bare necessaries of
style. For the common language of every day seems
to me to be of a different character from the style
of an eloquent speaker. If all that was required of
the latter was merely to indicate the facts, he might
rest content with literalness of language, without
                    <pb id="p.475"/>
                    further elaboration. But since it is his duty to
delight and move his audience and to play upon
the various feelings, it becomes necessary for him
to employ those additional aids which are granted
to us by that same nature which gave us speech.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    It is, in fact, as natural to do this as to harden the
muscles, increase our strength and improve our complexion by means of exercise. It is for this reason
that among all nations one man is regarded as more
eloquent and more attractive in his style than
another (since if this were not the case, all speakers
would be equal); but the same men speak differently on different subjects and observe distinctions
of character. Consequently the more effective a
man's speaking, the more in accordance with the
nature of eloquence will it be.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    I have, therefore, no strong objection even to the
views expressed by those who think that some concession should be made to the circumstances under which
we speak and to the ears of the audience which
require something more polished and emotional than
ordinary speech. For this reason I consider that it
would be absurd to restrict an orator to the style of
the predecessors of Cato and the Gracchi, or even
of those orators themselves. And I note that it was
the practice of Cicero, while devoting himself in the
main to the interests of his case, to take into account
the delectation of his audience as well, since, as he
pointed out, his own interests were concerned as
well as those of his client, although of course the
latter were of paramount importance. For his very
charm was a valuable asset.
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    I do not know what
can be added by way of improvement to the charms
of his style, except perhaps the introduction of
                    <pb id="p.477"/>
                    something more in the way of brilliant reflexions to
suit the taste of our own times. For this can be done
without injury to the treatment of our case or inpairing the authority of our language, provided that
such embellishments are not too frequent or continuous, and do not mutually destroy the effects
which they were designed to produce.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    I am ready
to go so far along the path of concession, but let no
man press me further. I concur in the fashion of
the day to the extent of agreeing that the toga
should not be long in the nap, but not to the extent
of insisting that it should be of silk: I agree that
the hair should be cut, but not that it should be
dressed in tiers and ringlets, since we must always
remember that ornaments, unless they be judged
from the standpoint of the fop and the debauchee,
are always effective in proportion to their seemliness.
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    But with regard to those passages to which we give
the name of
                    <hi rend="italics">reflexions,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        For this ever-recurring technical term there is no
adequate translation. It means a
                        <quote>reflexion coached in aphoristic or epigrammatic form.</quote>
                    </note>
                    a form of ornament which
was not employed by the ancients and, above all,
not by the Greeks, although I do find it in Cicero,
who can deny their usefulness, provided they are
relevant to the case, are not too diffuse and contribute to our success? For they strike the mind
and often produce a decisive effect by one single
blow, while their very brevity makes them cling to
the memory, and the pleasure which they produce
has the force of persuasion.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    There are, however, some who, while allowing
the actual delivery of such specially brilliant forms
of ornament, think that they should be excluded
from the written speech. Consequently I must not
dismiss even this topic without a word of discussion. For a number of learned authorities
                    <pb id="p.479"/>
                    have held that the written and the spoken speech
stand on different footings, and that consequently
some of the most eloquent of speakers have left
nothing for posterity to read in durable literary form,
as, for example, is the case with Pericles and Decades
Again, they urge that there have been authors, like
Isocrates, who, while admirable writers, were not
well-fitted for actual speaking;
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    and, further, that
actual pleading is characterised by a greater energy
and by the employment, almost verging on license,
of every artifice designed to please, since the minds
of an uneducated audience require to be moved and
led. On the other hand, the written speech with
is published as a model of style must be polished
and filed and brought into conformity with the
accepted rules and standards of artistic construction,
since it will come into the hands of learned men
and its art will be judged by artists.
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    These subtle
teachers (for such they have persuaded themselves
and others that they are) have laid it down that
the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">para/deigma</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Sec v. xi. 1. Parallels and especially historical ones.</note>
                    is best suited for actual speech and
the
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)nqu/mhma</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See v. xiv. 1
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                        A form of syllogism.
                    </note>
                    for writing. My own view is that
there is absolutely no difference between writing
well and speaking well, and that a written speech
is merely a record of one that has actually been
delivered. Consequently it must in my opinion
possess every kind of merit, and note that I say
merit, not fault. For I know that faults do sometimes meet with the approval of the uneducated.
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    What, then, will be the difference between what is
written and what is spoken? If I were given a jury
of wise men, I should cut down a large number of
passages from the speeches not only of Cicero, but
even of Demosthenes, who is much more concise.
                    <pb id="p.481"/>
                    For with such a jury there would be no need to
appeal to the emotions nor to charm and soothe the
ears, since according to Aristotle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Rhet.</hi>
                        iii. 13.
                    </note>
                    even exordia are
superfluous, if addressed to such persons, as they
will have no influence upon judges who are truly
wise: it will be sufficient to state the facts with
precision and significance and to marshal our array
of proofs.
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    Since, however, our judges are the
people, or drawn from the people, and since those
who are appointed to give sentence are frequently
ill-educated and sometimes mere rustics, it becomes
necessary to employ every method that we think
likely to assist our case, and these artifices must
not merely be produced in speech, but exhibited in
the written version as well, at least if in writing it
our design is to show how it should be spoken.
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    If
Demosthenes or Cicero had spoken the words as
they wrote them, would either have spoken ill
And is our acquaintance with either of those two
great orators based on anything save their writings?
Did they speak better, then, or worse than they
wrote? If they spoke worse, all that can be said
is that they should have spoken as they wrote,
while, if they spoke better, they should have
written as they spoke.
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    Well, you ask, is an orator
then always to speak as he writes? If possible,
always. If, however, the time allowed by the
judge is too short for this to be possible, he will
have to cut out much that he should have said,
but the published speech will contain the omitted
passages. On the other hand, such passages as
were uttered merely to suit the character of the
judges will not be published for the benefit of
posterity, for fear that they should seem to indicate
                    <pb id="p.483"/>
                    the author's deliberate judgement instead of being
a mere concession to the needs of the moment.
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    For it is most important that we should know how
the judge is disposed to listen, and his face will
often (as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Not in any extant work.</note>
                    reminds us) serve as a guide to
the speaker. Consequently we must press the points
that we see commend themselves to him, and draw
back from those which are ill-received, while our
actual language must be so modified that he will
find our arguments as intelligible as possible. That
this should be necessary is scarcely surprising, when
we consider the alterations that are frequently
necessary to suit the characters of the different
witnesses.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    He was a shrewd man who, when he
asked a rustic witness whether he knew Amphion,
and the witness replied that he did not, dropped
the aspirate and shortened the second syllable,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The witness did not recognise the name correctly
pronounced
                        <hi rend="italics">Amphion,</hi>
                        but recognised it when pronounced
Amphion.
                    </note>
                    whereupon the witness recognised him at once.
Such situations, when it is impossible to speak as
we write, will sometimes make it necessary to speak
in language other than that which we use in
writing.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    There is another threefold division, whereby,
it is held, we may differentiate three styles of
speaking, all of them correct. The first is termed
the plain
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">subtilis</hi>
                        (
                        <hi rend="italics">lit.</hi>
                        = finely woven) applied to style has three
meanings: (a) refined, (b) precise, (c) plain. See Sandys on
Cic.
                        <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi>
                        vi. 20.
                    </note>
                    (or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">i)sxno/n</foreign>
                    ), the second grand and
forcible (or
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a(dro/n</foreign>
                    ), and the third either intermediate or florid, the latter being a translation
of
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)nqhro/n.</foreign>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    The nature of these three styles is,
broadly speaking, as follows. The first would seem
best adapted for instructing, the second for moving,
and the third (by whichever name we call it) for
charming or, as others would have it, conciliating
the audience; for instruction the quality most
                    <pb id="p.485"/>
                    needed is acumen, for conciliation gentleness, and
for stirring the emotions force. Consequently it is
mainly in the plain style that we shall state our
facts and advance our proofs, though it should be
borne in mind that this style will often be sufficiently
full in itself without any assistance whatever from
the other two.
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    The intermediate style will have
more frequent recourse to metaphor and will make
a more attractive use of figures, while it will introduce alluring digressions, will be neat in rhythm
and pleasing in its reflexions: its flow, however, will
be gentle, like that of a river whose waters are clear,
but overshadowed by the green banks on either side.
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    But he whose eloquence is like to some great torrent
that rolls down rocks and
                    <quote>disdains a bridge</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Verg.
                        <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi>
                        viii. 728.
                    </note>
                    and
carves out its own banks for itself, will sweep the
judge from his feet, struggle as he may, and force
him to go whither he bears him. This is the orator
that will call the dead to life (as, for example, Cicero
calls upon Appius Caecus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See III. viii. 54.
                        <quote>
                            Cicero in the
                            <hi rend="italics">pro Caclio</hi>
                            makes both
Appius Caecus and her brother Clodius address Clodia the
former rebuking her for her immorality, the latter exhorting
her thereto.
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    ); it is in his pages
that his native land itself will cry aloud and at
times address the orator himself, as it addresses
Cicero in the speech delivered against Catiline in
the senate.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    Such an orator will also exalt his style
by amplification and rise even to
                    <hi rend="italics">hyperbole,</hi>
                    as when
Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Phil.</hi>
                        II. xxvii. 67. The passage continues:
                        <quote>
                            could
scarce, methinks, have swallowed with such speed so many
things, scattered in so many places.
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    cries,
                    <quote>What Charybdis was ever so voracious!</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>By the god of truth, even Ocean's self,</quote>
                    etc. (I choose these fine passages as being
familiar to the student). It is such an one that
will bring down the Gods to form part of his
audience or even to speak with him, as in the
following,
                    <quote>
                        For on you I call, ye hills and groves
of Alba, on you, I say, ye fallen altars of the
Albans, altars that were once the peers and equals
                        <pb id="p.487"/>
                        of the holy places of Rome.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">pro, Mil.</hi>
                        xxxi. 85.
                    </note>
                    This is he that will
inspire anger or pity, and while he speaks the judge
will call upon the gods and weep, following him
wherever he sweeps him from one emotion to
another, and no longer asking merely for instruction.
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore if one of these three styles has to be
selected to the exclusion of the others, who will
hesitate to prefer this style to all others, since it
is by far the strongest and the best adapted to the
most important cases?
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    For Homer himself assigns
to Menelaus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Mil.</hi>
                        iii. 214. The words which Quintilian translates by
                        <hi rend="italics">non deerrare verbhis</hi>
                        are
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)d' a)famartoeph/s,</foreign>
                        <quote>no stumbler in speech,</quote>
                        rather than
                        <quote>correct in speech.</quote>
                    </note>
                    an eloquence, terse and pleasing, exact
(for that is what is meant by
                    <quote>making no errors in words</quote>
                    ) and devoid of all redundance, which qualities
are virtues of the first type: and he says that from
the lips of Nestor
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>
                        i. 249.
                    </note>
                    flowed speech sweeter than honey,
than which assuredly we can conceive no greater
delight: but when he seeks to express the supreme
gift of eloquence possessed by Ulysses
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>
                        iii. 221.
                    </note>
                    he gives a
mighty voice and a vehemence of oratory equal to
the snows of winter in the abundance and the vigour
of its words.
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>With him then,</quote>
                    he says,
                    <quote>no mortal will contend, and men shall look upon him as on a god.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A blend of
                        <hi rend="italics">Il.</hi>
                        iii. 223 and
                        <hi rend="italics">Od.</hi>
                        viii. 173.
                    </note>
                    It is this force and impetuosity that Eupolis
admires in Pericles, this that Aristophanes
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Aeh.</hi>
                        530.
                        <quote>
                            Then in his wrath Pericles the Olympian
lightened and thundered and threw all Greece into confusion.
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    compares
to the thunderbolt, this that is the power of true
eloquence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    But eloquence cannot be confined even to these
three forms of style. For just as the third style is
intermediate between the grand and the plain style,
so each of these three are separated by interspaces
                    <pb id="p.489"/>
                    which are occupied by intermediate styles compounded of the two which he on either side.
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    For
there are styles fuller or plainer than the plain, and
gentler or more vehement than the vehement, while
the gentler style itself may either rise to greater
force or sink to milder tones. Thus we may discover
almost countless species of styles, each differing from
the other by some fine shade of difference. We may
draw a parallel from the winds. It is generally accepted that there are four blowing from the four
quarters of the globe, but we find there are also
a large number of winds which he between these,
called by a variety of names, and in certain cases
confined to certain districts and river valleys.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    The
same thing may be noted in music. For after assigning five notes to the lyre, musicians fill up the
intervals between the strings by a variety of notes,
and between these again they interpose yet others,
so that the original divisions admit of a number of
gradations.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    Eloquence has, therefore, a quantity of different
aspects, but it is sheer folly to inquire which of these
the orator should take as his model, since every
species that is in itself correct has its use, and what
is commonly called
                    <hi rend="italics">style of speaking</hi>
                    does not depend
on the orator. For he will use all styles, as circumstances may demand, and the choice will be
determined not only by the case as a whole, but by
the demands of the different portions of the case.
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    For just as he will not speak in the same way when
he is defending a client on a capital charge and
when he is speaking in a lawsuit concerned with an
inheritance, or discussing interdicts and suits taking
the form of a wager,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cp.</hi>
                        I. x. 5 and IV. ii. 61.
                        <hi rend="italics">Sponsio</hi>
                        (= wager) was a form
of lawsuit in which the litigant promised to pay a certain
sum of money if he lost his case. The
                        <hi rend="italics">intrdiet</hi>
                        was an order
issued by the praetor commanding or prohibiting certain
action.
                    </note>
                    or claims in connexion with
                    <pb id="p.491"/>
                    loans, so too he will preserve a due distinction
between the speeches which he makes in the senate,
before the people and in private consultations, while
he will also introduce numerous modifications to
suit the different persons and circumstances of time
and place. Thus in one and the same speech he
will use one style for stirring the emotions, and
another to conciliate his hearers; it is from different
sources that he will derive anger or pity, and the
art which he employs in instructing the judge will
be other than that which he employs to move him.
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    He will not maintain the same tone throughout his
                    <hi rend="italics">exordium, statement of fact, arguments, digression</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italics">peroration.</hi>
                    He will speak gravely, severely, sharply,
with vehemence, energy, fullness, bitterness, or
geniality, quietly, simply, Hatteringly, gently, sweetly,
briefy or wittily; he will not always be like himself, but he will never be unworthy of himself.
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    Thus the purpose for which oratory was above all
designed will be secured, that is to say, he will
speak with profit and with power to effect his aim,
while he will also win the praise not merely of the
learned, but of the multitude as well.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    They make the gravest mistake who consider that
the style which is best adapted to win popularity
and applause is a faulty and corrupt style of speaking
which revels in license of diction or wantons in
childish epigram or swells with stilted bombast or
riots in empty commonplace or adorns itself with
blossoms of eloquence which will fall to earth if
but lightly shaken, or regards extravagance as
sublime or raves wildly under the pretext of free
speech.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    I am ready to admit that such qualities
please many, and I feel no surprise that this should
                    <pb id="p.493"/>
                    be the case. For any kind of eloquence is pleasing
and attractive to the car, and every effort of the
voice inspires a natural pleasure in the soul of man;
indeed this is the sole cause of those familiar gatherings in the Forum or on the Old Wall,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italics">agger</hi>
                        of Servius Tullius, which served as a promenadec.
The nearest modern parallel may be found in the
                        <quote>Hyde Park orator.</quote>
                    </note>
                    so that there
is small reason for wonder if any pleader is safe to
draw a ring of listeners from the crowd.
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    And when
any unusually precious phrase strikes the ears of an
uneducated audience, whatever its true merits, it
wakens their admiration just for the very reason
that they feel they could never have produced it
themselves. And it deserves their admiration, since
even such success is hard to attain. On the other
hand, when such displays are compared with their
betters, they sink into insignificance and fade out
of sight, for they are like wool dyed red that
pleases in the absence of purple, but, as Ovid
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Halm. Am.</hi>
                        707
                        <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    says,
if compared with a cloak of Tyrian dye, pales in the
presence of the fairer hue.
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    If, however, we test
such corrupt eloquence by the touchstone of a critical
taste, as, for example, we test inferior dyes with
sulphur, it will lay aside the false brilliance that
deceived the eye and fade to a pallor almost too
repulsive to describe. Such passages shine only in
the absence of the sunlight, just as certain tiny
insects seem transformed in the darkness to little
flames of fire. Finally, while many approve of things
that are bad, no one disapproves of that which is
good.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>
                    But the true orator will not merely be able to
achieve all the feats of which I have spoken with
supreme excellence, but with the utmost ease as
well. For the sovereign power of eloquence and
the voice that awakens well-deserved applause will
                    <pb id="p.495"/>
                    be free from the perpetual distress of harassing
anxiety which wastes and fevers the orator who
painfully corrects himself and pines away over the
laborious weighing and piecing together of his
words.
                    <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
                    No, our orator, brilliant, sublime and
opulent of speech, is lord and master of all the
resources of eloquence, whose affluence surrounds
him. For he that has reached the summit has no
more weary hills to scale. At first the climber's toil
is hard, but the higher he mounts the easier becomes the gradient and the richer the soil.
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                    And
if by perseverance of study he pass even beyond
these gentler slopes, fruits for which none have
toiled thrust themselves upon him, and all things
spring forth unbidden; and yet if they be not
gathered daily, they will wither away. But even
such wealth must observe the mean, without which
nothing is either praiseworthy or beneficial, while
brilliance must be attended by manliness, and imagination by soundness of taste.
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
                    Thus the works
of the orator will be great not extravagant, sublime
not bombastic, bold not rash, severe but not gloomy,
grave but not slow, rich but not luxuriant, pleasing
but not effeminate, grand but not grandiose. It is
the same with other qualities: the mean is safest,
for the worst of all faults is to fly to extremes.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    After employing these gifts of eloquence in
the courts, in councils, in public assemblies and the
debates of the senate, and, in a word, in the performance of all the duties of a good citizen, the
orator will bring his activities to a close in a manner
worthy of a blameless life spent in the pursuit of
the noblest of professions. And he will do this,
not because he can ever have enough of doing good,
                    <pb id="p.497"/>
                    or because one endowed with intellect and talents
such as his would not be justified in praying that
such glorious labours may be prolonged to their
utmost span, but for this reason, that it is his duty
to look to the future, for fear that his work may be
less effective than it has been in the past.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For the
orator depends not merely on his knowledge, which
increases with the years, but on his voice, lungs and
powers of endurance. And if these be broken or
impaired by age or health, he must beware that he
does not fall short in something of his high reputation as a master of oratory, that fatigue does not
interrupt his eloquence, that he is not brought to
realise that some of his words are inaudible, or to
mourn that he is not what once he was.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Domitius
Afer was by far the greatest of all the orators whom
it has been my good fortune to know, and I saw
him, when far advanced in years, daily losing something of that authority which his merits had won
for him; he whose supremacy in the courts had once
been universally acknowledged, now pleaded amid
the unworthy laughter of some, and the silent
blushes of others, giving occasion to the malicious
saying that he had rather
                    <quote>faint than finish.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        By
                        <quote>finish</quote>
                        is meant
                        <quote>retire from pleading.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And
yet even then, whatever his deficiencies, he spoke
not badly, but merely less well.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Therefore before ever he fall a prey to the ambush
where time lies in wait for him, the orator should
sound the retreat and seek harbour while his ship
is yet intact. For the fruits of his studies will
not be lessened by retirement. Either he will bequeath the history of his own times for the delight
of after ages, or will interpret the law to those
who seek his counsels, as Lucius Crassus proposes
                    <pb id="p.499"/>
                    to do in the
                    <hi rend="italics">de Oratore</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">de</hi>
                        (
                        <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi>
                        I. xlii. 190.
                    </note>
                    of Cicero, or compose some
treatise on the art of oratory, or give worthy utterance
to the sublimest ideals of conduct.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    His house
will, as in the days of old, be thronged by all
the best of the rising generation, who will seek to
learn from him as from an oracle how they may find
the path to true eloquence. And he as their father
in the art will mould them to all excellence, and
like some old pilot will teach them of the shores
whereby their ships must sail, of the harbours where
they may shelter, and the signs of the weather, and
will expound to them what they shall do when the
breeze is fair or the tempest blows. Whereto he
will be inclined not only by the common duty of
humanity, but by a certain passion for the task that
once was his, since no man desires that the art
wherein he was once supreme should suffer decay
or diminution.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And what can be more honourable
than to teach that which you know surpassing well?
It was for this that the elder Caelius brought his son
to Cicero, as the latter
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">pro Cael.</hi>
                        iv. 10.
                    </note>
                    tells us, and it was with this
intent that the same great orator took upon himself
the duties of instructor, and trained Pansa, Hirtius
and Dolabella by declaiming daily before them or
hearing them declaim.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    And I know not whether
we should not deem it the happiest moment in an
orator's life, when he has retired from the public
gaze, the consecrated priest of eloquence, free from
envy and far from strife, when he has set his glory
on a pinnacle beyond the reach of detraction, enjoys,
while still living, that veneration which most men
win but after death, and sees how great shall be his
renown amid generations yet unborn.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    I can say with a good conscience that, as far as
                    <pb id="p.501"/>
                    my poor powers have permitted, I have published
frankly and disinterestedly, for the benefit of such
as might wish to learn, all that my previous knowledge and the researches made for the purpose of
this work might supply. And to have taught what
lie knows is satisfaction enough for any good man.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    I fear, however, that I may be regarded as setting
too lofty an ideal for the orator by insisting that he
should be a good man skilled in speaking, or as
imposing too many subjects of study on the learner.
For in addition to the many branches of knowledge
which have to be studied in boyhood and the traditional rules of eloquence, I have enjoined the study
of morals and of civil law, so that I am afraid that
even those who have regarded these things as
essential to my theme, may he appalled at the delay
which they impose and abandon all hope of achievement before they have put my precepts to the test.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    I would ask them to consider how great are the
powers of the mind of man and how astonishing its
capacity for carrying its desires into execution: for
has not man succeeded in crossing the high seas, in
learning the number and the courses of the stars,
and almost measuring the universe itself, all of them
accomplishments of less importance than oratory, but
of far greater difficulty? And then let them reflect
on the greatness of' their aims and on the fact that
no labour should be too huge for those that are
beckoned by the hope of such reward.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    If they can
only rise to the height of this conception, they will
find it easier to enter on this portion of their task,
and will cease to regard the road as impassable or
even hard. For the first and greatest of' the aims
we set before us, namely that we shall be good
                    <pb id="p.503"/>
                    men, depends for its achievement mainly on the
will to succeed: and he that truly and sincerely
forms such resolve, will easily acquire those forms
of knowledge that teach the way to virtue.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    For
the precepts that are enjoined upon us are not
so complex or so numerous that they may be
acquired by little more than a few years' study. It
is repugnance to learn that makes such labour long.
For if you will only believe it, you will quickly learn
the principles that shall lead you to a life of virtue
and happiness. For nature brought us into the world
that we might attain to all excellence of mind, and
so easy is it for those to learn who seek for better
things, that he who directs his gaze aright will
rather marvel that the bad should be so many.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For
as water is the natural element of fish, dry land
for creatures of the earth and the circumambient
atmosphere for winged things, even so it should
be easier to live according to nature than counter
to her will. As regards other accomplishments,
there are plenty of years available for their acquisition, even though we measure the life of man not
by the span of age, but by the period of youth. For
in every case order and method and a sense of proportion will shorten our labour.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    But the chief fault
lies with our teachers, in that they love to keep back
the pupils they have managed to lay their hands on,
partly from the desire to draw their miserable fees
for as long as possible, partly out of ostentation, to
enhance the difficulty of acquiring the knowledge
which they promise to impart, and to some extent
owing to their ignorance or carelessness in teaching.
The next most serious fault lies in ourselves, who
think it better to linger over what we have learned
                    <pb id="p.505"/>
                    than to learn what we do not yet know.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For example, to restrict my remarks mainly to the study
of rhetoric, what is the use of spending so many
years, after the fashion now so prevalent (for I will
say nothing of those who spend almost their whole
lives), in declaiming in the schools and devoting so
much labour to the treatment of fictitious themes,
when it would be possible with but slight expenditure
of time to form some idea of what the true conflicts
are in which the orator must engage, and of the
laws of speaking which he ought to follow?
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    In
saying this, I do not for a moment mean to suggest
that we should ever omit to exercise ourselves in
speaking. I merely urge that we should not grow old
over one special form of exercise. We have been in a
position to acquire varied knowledge, to familiarise
ourselves with the principles that should guide our
life, and to try our strength in the courts, while we
were still attending the schools. The theory of speaking is of such a nature that it does not demand
many years for its acquisition. For any one of the
various branches of knowledge which I have mentioned will, as a rule, be found to be comprised in
a few volumes, a fact which shows that instruction
does not require an indefinite amount of time to be
devoted to it. The rest depends entirely on practice,
which at once develops our powers and maintains
them, once developed.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Knowledge increases day
by day, and yet how many books is it absolutely
necessary to read in our search for its attainment, for
examples of facts from the historians or of eloquence
from the orators, or, again, for the opinions of the
philosophers and the lawyers, that is to say, if we
are content to read merely what is useful without
                    <pb id="p.507"/>
                    attempting the impossible task of reading everything?
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    But it is ourselves that make the time for
study short: for how little time we allot to it!
Some hours are passed in the futile labour of ceremonial calls, others in idle chatter, others in staring
at the shows of the theatre, and others again in
feasting. To this add all the various forms of amusement, the insane attention devoted to the cultivation
of the body, journeys abroad, visits to the country,
anxious calculation of loss and gain, the allurements
of lust, wine-bibbing and those remaining hours
which are all too few to gratify our souls on fire
with passion for every kind of pleasure.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    If all this
time were spent on study, life would seem long
enough and there would be plenty of time for learning, even though we should take the hours of daylight only into our account, without asking any
assistance from the night, of which no little space
is superfluous even for the heaviest sleeper. As it
is, we count not the years which we have given to
study, but the years we have lived.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    And indeed
even although geometricians, musicians and grammarians, together with the professors of every other
branch of knowledge, spend all their lives, however
long, in the study of one single science, it does not
therefore follow that we require several lives more
if we are to learn more. For they do not spend all
their days even to old age in learning these things,
but being content to have learned these things and
nothing more, exhaust their length of years not in
acquiring, but in imparting knowledge.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    However, to say nothing of Homer, in whom we
may find either the perfect achievements, or at
any rate clear signs of the knowledge of every art,
                    <pb id="p.509"/>
                    and to pass by Hippias of Elis, who not merely
boasted his knowledge of the liberal arts, but wore
a robe, a ring and shoes, all of which he had made
with his own hands, and had trained himself to be
independent of external assistance, we accept the
universal tradition of Greece to the effect that
Gorgias, triumphant over all the countless ills incident to extreme old age, would bid his hearers
propound any questions they pleased for him to
answer.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Again in what branch of knowledge
worthy of literary expression was Plato deficient?
How many generations' study did Aristotle require to embrace not merely the whole range of
philosophical and rhetorical knowledge, but to
investigate the nature of every beast and plant.
And yet they had to discover all these things which
we only have to learn. Antiquity has given us all
these teachers and all these patterns for our imitation,
that there might be no greater happiness conceivable
than to be born in this age above all others, since
all previous ages have toiled that we might reap the
fruit of their wisdom.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Marcus Cato was at once a
great general, a philosopher, orator, historian, and
an expert both in law and agriculture, and despite
his military labours abroad and the distractions of
political struggles at home, and despite the rudeness
of the age in which he lived, he none the less
learned Greek, when far advanced in years, that he
might prove to mankind that even old men are
capable of learning that on which they have set
their hearts.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    How wide, almost universal, was the
knowledge that Varro communicated to the world!
What of all that goes to make up the equipment of
an orator was lacking to Cicero? Why should I say
                    <pb id="p.511"/>
                    more, since even Cornelius Celsus, a man of very
ordinary ability, not merely wrote about rhetoric in
all its departments, but left treatises on the art of
war, agriculture and medicine as well. Indeed the
high ambition revealed by his design gives him the
right to ask us to believe that he was acquainted
with all these subjects.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    But, it will be urged, to carry out such a task is
difficult and has never been accomplished. To
which I reply that sufficient encouragement for
study may be found in the fact, firstly, that nature
does not forbid such achievement and it does not
follow that, because a thing never has been done, it
therefore never can be done, and secondly, that all
great achievements have required time for their first
accomplishment.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Poetry has risen to the heights
of glory, thanks to the efforts of poets so far apart
as Homer and Virgil, and oratory owes its position
to the genius of Demosthenes and Cicero. Finally,
whatever is best in its own sphere must at some
previous time have been non-existent. But even if
a man despair of reaching supreme excellence (and
why should he despair, if he have talents, health,
capacity and teachers to aid him?), it is none the
less a fine achievement, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Or.</hi>
                        i. 4.
                    </note>
                    says, to win the
rank of second or even third.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    For even if a soldier
cannot achieve the glory of Achilles in war, he will
not despise fame such as fell to the lot of Ajax and
Diomede, while those who cannot be Homers may
be content to reach the level of Tyrtaeus. Nay, if
men had been obsessed by the conviction that it was
impossible to surpass the man who had so far shown
himself best, those whom we now regard as best
would never have reached such distinction, Lucretius
                    <pb id="p.513"/>
                    and Macer would never have been succeeded by
Virgil, nor Crassus and Hortensius by Cicero, nor
they in their turn by those who flourished after
them.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    But even though we cannot hope to surpass
the great, it is still a high honour to follow in their
footsteps. Did Pollio and Messala, who began to
plead when Cicero held the citadel of eloquence,
fail to obtain sufficient honour in their lifetime or
to hand down a fair name to posterity? The arts
which have been developed to the highest pitch
of excellence would deserve but ill of mankind if
that which was best had also been the last of its
line.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    Add to this the further consideration that
even moderate eloquence is often productive of
great results and, if such studies are to be measured
solely by their utility, is almost equal to the perfect
eloquence for which we seek. Nor would it be difficult
to produce either ancient or recent examples to show
that there is no other source from which men have
reaped such a harvest of wealth, honour, friendship
and glory, both present and to come. But it would
be a disgrace to learning to follow the fashion of those
who say that they pursue not virtue, but only the
pleasure derived from virtue, and to demand this
meaner recompense from the noblest of all arts, whose
practice and even whose possession is ample reward
for all our labours.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Wherefore let us seek with all
our hearts that true majesty of oratory, the fairest
gift of god to man, without which all things are
stricken dumb and robbed alike of present glory and
the immortal record of posterity; and let us press
forward to whatsoever is best, since, if we do this,
we shall either reach the summit or at least see
many others far beneath us.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.515"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Such, Marcellus Victorius, were the views by
the expression of which it seemed to me that I
might, as far as in me lay, help to advance the
teaching of oratory. If the knowledge of these
principles proves to be of small practical utility to
the young student, it should at least produce what
[value more,—the will to do well.
                </p>
                <pb id="p.517"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
