<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 10-12 - 11</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <!--<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>-->
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With An English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="Section"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']/tei:div[@n='$3'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter and Section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Book"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change who="GRC" when="2006">tagging</change><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
           <change who="Zach Himes" when="2015-11-16">Edited teiHeader, converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb xml:id="p.155"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" subtype="book" type="translation">
                <head>Book XI</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    After acquiring the power of writing and thinking, as described in the preceding book, and also of
pleading extempore, if occasion demand, our next
task will be to ensure that appropriateness of speech,
which Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        III. x. 37.
                    </note>
                    shows to be the fourth department of
style, and which is, in my opinion, highly necessary.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For since the ornaments of style are varied and
manifold and suited for different purposes, they will,
unless adapted to the matter and the persons concerned, not merely fail to give our style distinction,
but will even destroy its effect and produce a result
quite the reverse of that which our matter should
produce. For what profit is it that our words should
be Latin, significant and graceful, and be further
embellished with elaborate figures and rhythms,
unless all these qualities are in harmony with the
views to which we seek to lead the judge and mould
his opinions?
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    What use is it if we employ a lofty
tone in cases of trivial import, a slight and refined
style in cases of great moment, a cheerful tone when
our matter calls for sadness, a gentle tone when it
demands vehemence, threatening language when
supplication, and submissive when energy is required, or fierceness and violence when our theme is
one that asks for charm? Such incongruities are as
unbecoming as it is for men to wear necklaces and
pearls and flowing raiment which are the natural
adornments of women, or for women to robe
                    <pb xml:id="p.157"/>
                    themselves in the garb of triumph, than which there can
be conceived no more majestic raiment.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This topic
is discussed by Cicero in the third book of the
                    <hi rend="italic">de Oratore,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">III. lv. 210.</note>
                    and, although he touches on it but lightly,
he really covers the whole subject when he says,
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        One single style of oratory is not suited to every case, nor
to every audience, nor every speaker, nor every occasion.
                    </hi>
                    And he says the same at scarcely greater length in
the
                    <hi rend="italic">Orator.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ch. xxi.
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    But in the first of these works Lucius
Crassus, since he is speaking in the presence of men
distinguished alike for their learning and their eloquence, thinks it sufficient merely to indicate this topic
to his audience for their recognition;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    while in the
latter work Cicero asserts that, as these facts are
familiar to Brutus, to whom that treatise is addressed,
they will be given briefer treatment, despite the fact
that the subject is a wide one and is discussed at
greater length by the philosophers. 1, on the other
hand, have undertaken the education of an orator,
and, consequently, am speaking not merely to those
that know, but also to learners; I shall, therefore,
have some claim to forgiveness if I discuss the topic
in greater detail.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    For this reason, it is of the first importance that
we should know what style is most suitable for conciliating, instructing or moving the judge, and what
effects we should aim at in different parts of our
speech. Thus we shall eschew antique, metaphorical and newly-coined words in our
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium, statement of facts</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">arguments,</hi>
                    as we shall avoid flowing
periods woven with elaborate grace, when the case
has to be divided and distinguished under its various
heads, while, on the other hand, we shall not employ
mean or colloquial language, devoid of all artistic
                    <pb xml:id="p.159"/>
                    structure, in the
                    <hi rend="italic">peroration,</hi>
                    nor, when the theme calls
for compassion, attempt to dry the tears of our audience with jests.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For all ornament derives its effect
not from its own qualities so much as from the
circumstances in which it is applied, and the occasion
chosen for saying anything is at least as important a
consideration as what is actually said. But the whole
of this question of appropriate language turns on
something more than our choice of style, for it has
much in common with invention. For if words can
produce such an impression, how much greater must
that be which is created by the facts themselves.
But I have already laid down rules for the treatment
of the latter in various portions of this work.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Too much insistence cannot be laid upon the point
that no one can be said to speak appropriately who
has not considered not merely what it is expedient,
but also what it is becoming to say. I am well
aware that these two considerations generally go
hand in hand. For whatever is becoming is, as a
rule, useful, and there is nothing that does more to
conciliate the good-will of the judge than the
observance or to alienate it than the disregard of
these considerations.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes, however, the two
are at variance. Now, whenever this occurs, expediency must yield to the demands of what is
becoming. Who is there who does not realise that
nothing would have contributed more to secure the
acquittal of Socrates than if he had employed the
ordinary forensic methods of defence and had
conciliated the minds of his judges by adopting a
submissive tone and had devoted his attention to
refuting the actual charge against him?
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    But such
a course would have been unworthy of his character,
                    <pb xml:id="p.161"/>
                    and, therefore, he pleaded as one who would account
the penalty to which he might be sentenced as the
highest of honours. The wisest of men preferred to
sacrifice the remnant of his days rather than to cancel
all his past life. And since he was but ill understood by the men of his own day, he reserved his
case for the approval of posterity and at the cost of
a few last declining years achieved through all the
ages life everlasting.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    And so although Lysias, who
was accounted the first orator of that time, offered
him a written defence, he refused to make use of
it, since, though he recognised its excellence, he
regarded it as unbecoming to himself. This instance alone shows that the end which the orator
must keep in view is not persuasion, but speaking
well, since there are occasions when to persuade
would be a blot upon his honour. The line adopted
by Socrates was useless to secure his acquittal, but
was of real service to him as a man; and that is by
far the greater consideration.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    In drawing this distinction between what is expedient and what is
becoming, I have followed rather the usage of common speech than the strict law of truth; unless,
indeed, the elder Africanus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Falsely accused of having taken a bribe from King
Antiochus. See
                        <hi rend="italic">Livy,</hi>
                        XXXVIII. li. 16.
                    </note>
                    is to be regarded as
having failed to consult his true interests, when he
retired into exile sooner than wrangle over his own
innocence with a contemptible tribune of the people,
or unless it be alleged that Publius Rutilius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. liii. 227
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    was
ignorant of his true advantage both on the occasion
when he adopted a defence which may almost be
compared with that of Socrates, and when he preferred to remain in exile rather than return at Sulla's
bidding.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    No, these great men regarded all those
trifles that the most abject natures regard as
                    <pb xml:id="p.163"/>
                    advantageous, as being contemptible if weighed in the
balance with virtue, and for this reason they have
their reward in the deathless praise of all generations. Let not us, then, be so poor spirited as to
regard the acts, which we extol, as being inexpedient.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    However, it is but rarely that this distinction, such
as it is, is called into play. As I have said, the
expedient and the becoming will, as a rule, be
identical in every kind of case. Still, there are two
things which will be becoming to all men at all times
and in all places, namely, to act and speak as befits a
man of honour, and it will never at any time beseem
any man to speak or act dishonourably. On the
other hand, things of minor importance and occupying something like a middle position between the
two are generally of such a nature that they may be
conceded to some, but not to others, while it will
depend on the character of the speaker and the
circumstances of time, place and motive whether we
regard them as more or less excusable or reprehensible.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    When, however, we are speaking of our
own affairs or those of others, we must distinguish
between the expedient and the becoming, while
recognising that the majority of the points which
we have to consider will fall under neither head.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In the first place, then, all kinds of boasting are a
mistake, above all, it is an error for an orator to praise
his own eloquence, and, further, not merely wearies,
but in the majority of cases disgusts the audience.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    For there is ever in the mind of man a certain
element of lofty and unbending pride that will not
brook superiority: and for this reason we take delight in raising the humble and submissive to their
feet, since such an act gives us a consciousness of our
                    <pb xml:id="p.165"/>
                    superiority, and as soon as all sense of rivalry disappears, its place is taken by a feeling of humanity.
But the man who exalts himself beyond reason is
looked upon as depreciating and showing a contempt
for others and as making them seem small rather
than himself seem great.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    As a result, those who are
beneath him feel a grudge against him (for those who
are unwilling to yield and yet have not the strength
to hold their own are always liable to this failing),
while his superiors laugh at him and the good
disapprove. Indeed, as a rule, you will find that
arrogance implies a false self-esteem, whereas those
who possess true merit find satisfaction enough in
the consciousness of possession.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Cicero has been severely censured in this connexion, although he was far more given to boasting
of his political achievements than of his eloquence,
at any rate, in his speeches.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    And as a rule he had
some sound reason for his self-praise. For he was
either defending those who had assisted him to crush
the conspiracy of Catiline, or was replying to attacks
made upon him by those who envied his position;
attacks which he was so far unable to withstand
that he suffered exile as the penalty for having
saved his country. Consequently, we may regard
his frequent reference to the deeds accomplished
in his consulship as being due quite as much to the
necessities of defence as to the promptings of vainglory.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    As regards his own eloquence, he never
made immoderate claims for it in his pleading, while
he always paid a handsome tribute to the eloquence
of the advocate, who opposed him. For example,
there are passages such as the following:
                    <quote>
                        If there
be aught of talent in me, and I am only too conscious
                        <pb xml:id="p.167"/>
                        how little it is,
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Arch.</hi>
                        i. I.
                    </note>
                    and,
                    <quote>In default of talent, I turned to industry for aid.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Quint.</hi>
                        i. 4.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Again, in his speech against
Caecilius on the selection of an accuser for Verres,
despite the fact that the question as to which was
the most capable pleader, was a factor of great
importance, he rather depreciated his opponent's
eloquence than exalted his own, and asserted that
he had done all in his power to make himself an
orator,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Div. in Caec.</hi>
                        xii. 40.
                    </note>
                    though he knew he had not succeeded.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    In
his letters to intimate friends, it is true, and occasionally in his dialogues, he tells the truth of his own
eloquence, though in the latter case he is careful
always to place the remarks in question in the
mouth of some other character. And yet I am not
sure that open boasting is not more tolerable, owing
to its sheer straightforwardness, than that perverted
form of self-praise, which makes the millionaire say
that he is not a poor man, the man of mark describe
himself as obscure, the powerful pose as weak,
and the eloquent as unskilled and even inarticulate.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    But the most ostentatious kind of boasting takes
the form of actual self-derision. Let us therefore
leave it to others to praise us. For it beseems us,
as Demosthenes says, to blush even when we are
praised by others. I do not mean to deny that
there are occasions when an orator may speak of
his own achievements, as Demosthenes himself does
in his defence of Ctesiphon.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Cor.</hi>
                        128.
                    </note>
                    But on that occasion
he qualified his statements in such a way as to show
that he was compelled by necessity to do so, and to
throw the odium attaching to such a proceeding on
the man who had forced him to it.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Again, Cicero
often speaks of his suppression of the Catilinarian
conspiracy, but either attributes his success to the
                    <pb xml:id="p.169"/>
                    courage shown by the senate or to the providence of
the immortal gods. If he puts forward stronger claims
to merit, it is generally when speaking against his
enemies and detractors; for he was bound to defend
his actions when they were denounced as discreditable.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    One could only wish that he had shown
greater restraint in his poems, which those who love
him not are never weary of criticising. I refer to
passages such as:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">From the poem on his consulship.</note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">Let arms before the peaceful toga yield,</l>
                            <l part="N">Laurels to eloquence resign the field,</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    or
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>O happy Rome, born in my consulship!</quote>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    together with that
                    <quote>Jupiter, by whom he is summoned to the assembly of the gods,</quote>
                    and the
                    <quote>Minerva that taught him her accomplishments</quote>
                    ;
extravagances which he permitted himself in imitation of certain precedents in Greek literature.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    But while it is unseemly to make a boast of one's
eloquence, it is, however, at times permissible to
express confidence in it. Who, for instance, can
blame the following?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        i. 2.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        What, then, am I to think?
That I am held in contempt? I see nothing either
in my past life, or my position, or such poor talents
as I may possess, that Antony can afford to despise.
                    </quote>
                    And a little later he speaks yet more openly:
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        Or did he wish to challenge me to a contest of
eloquence? I could wish for nothing better. For
what ampler or richer theme could I hope to find
than to speak at once for myself and against
Antony?
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Another form of arrogance is displayed by those who
declare that they have come to a clear conviction of
                    <pb xml:id="p.171"/>
                    the justice of their cause, which they would not
otherwise have undertaken. For the judges give
but a reluctant hearing to such as presume to
anticipate their verdict, and the orator cannot hope
that his opponents will regard his
                    <hi rend="italic">ipse dixit</hi>
                    with the
veneration accorded by the Pythagoreans to that of
their master. But this fault will vary in seriousness
according to the character of the orator who uses
such language.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    For such assertions may to some
extent be justified by the age, rank, and authority
of the speaker. But scarcely any orator is possessed
of these advantages to such an extent as to exempt
him from the duty of tempering such assertions by
a certain show of modesty, a remark which also
applies to all passages in which the advocate draws
any of his arguments from his own person. What
could have been more presumptuous than if Cicero
had asserted that the fact that a man was the son
of a Roman knight should never be regarded as a
serious charge, in a case in which
                    <hi rend="italic">he</hi>
                    was appearing
for the defence? But he succeeded in giving this
very argument a favourable turn by associating his
own rank with that of the judges, and saying,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Cael. ii.</hi>
                        4.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        The fact of a man being the son of a Roman knight
should never have been put forward as a charge by
the prosecution when these gentlemen were in the
jury-box and I was appearing for the defendant.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    An impudent, disorderly, or angry tone is always
unseemly, no matter who it be that assumes it; and
it becomes all the more reprehensible in proportion
to the age, rank, and experience of the speaker.
But we are familiar with the sight of certain brawling advocates who are restrained neither by respect
for the court nor by the recognised methods and
                    <pb xml:id="p.173"/>
                    manners of pleading. The obvious inference from
this attitude of mind is that they are utterly reckless
both in undertaking cases and in pleading them.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    For a man's character is generally revealed and the
secrets of his heart are laid bare by his manner of speaking, and there is good ground for the Greek aphorism
that,
                    <quote>as a man lives, so will he speak.</quote>
                    The following vices are of a meaner type: grovelling flattery,
affected buffoonery, immodesty in dealing with things
or words which are unseemly or obscene, and disregard of authority on all and every occasion. They
are faults which, as a rule, are found in those who
are over-anxious either to please or amuse.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    Again, different kinds of eloquence suit different
speakers. For example, a full, haughty, bold and
florid style would be less becoming to an old man
than that restrained, mild and precise style to which
Cicero refers, when he says that his style is beginning
to grow grey-haired.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        ii. 8.
                    </note>
                    It is the same with their style
as their clothes; purple and scarlet raiment goes ill
with grey hairs.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    In the young, however, we can
endure a rich and even, perhaps, a risky style. On
the other hand, a dry, careful and compressed style
is unpleasing in the young as suggesting the affectation of severity, since even the authority of character
that goes with age is considered as premature in
young men. Soldiers are best suited by a simple
style.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Those, again, who make ostentatious profession, as some do, of being philosophers, would do
well to avoid most of the ornaments of oratory, more
especially those which consist in appeals to the
passions, which they regard as moral blemishes. So,
too, the employment of rare words and of rhythmical
structure are incongruous with their profession.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    For
                    <pb xml:id="p.175"/>
                    their beards and gloomy brows are ill-suited not
merely to luxuriance of style, such as we find in
Cicero's
                    <quote>Rocks and solitudes answer to the voice,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Arch.</hi>
                        viii. 19.
                    </note>
                    but even to full-blooded passages as,
                    <quote>
                        For on you I
call, ye hills and groves of Alba; I call you to bear
me witness, and ye, too, fallen altars of the Albans,
that were once the peers and equals of the holy
places of Rome.
                    </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Mil.</hi>
                        xxxi. 85.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    But the public man, who is truly
wise and devotes himself not to idle disputations,
but to the administration of the state, from which
those who call themselves philosophers have withdrawn themselves afar, will gladly employ every
method that may contribute to the end which he
seeks to gain by his eloquence, although he will first
form a clear conception in his mind as to what aims
are honourable and what are not.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    There is a form
of eloquence which is becoming in the greatest
men, but inadmissible in others. For example, the
methods of eloquence employed by commanders and
conquerors in their hour of triumph are to a great
extent to be regarded as in a class apart. The
comparison of the eloquence of Plompey and Cato
the younger, who slew himself in the civil war, will
illustrate my meaning. The former was extraordinarily eloquent in the description of his own
exploits, while the latter's powers were displayed
in debates in the senate.
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the same remark
will seem freedom of speech in one's mouth, madness
in another's, and arrogance in a third. We laugh at
the words used by Thersites
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        ii. 225.
                    </note>
                    to Agamemnon; but
put them in the mouth of Diomede or some other
of his peers, and they will seem the expression of a
great spirit.
                    <quote>Shall I regard you as consul,</quote>
                    said
Lucius Crassus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        iii. 1.
                    </note>
                    to Phililppus,
                    <quote>
                        when you refuse to
                        <pb xml:id="p.177"/>
                        regard me as a senator?
                    </quote>
                    That was honourable
freedom of speech, and yet we should not tolerate
such words from everybody's lips.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    One of the poets
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cat. 93.</note>
                    says that he does not care whether Caesar be white
or black. That is madness. But reverse the case.
Suppose that Caesar said it of the poet? That
would be arrogance. The tragic and comic poets
pay special attention to character, since they introduce a great number and variety of persons. Those
who wrote speeches
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp. II.</hi>
                        xv. 30;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        viii. 51.
                    </note>
                    for others paid a like attention
to these points, and so do the declaimers; for we do
not always speak as advocates, but frequently as
actual parties to the suit.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    But even in these cases in which we appear as
advocates, differences of character require careful
observation. For we introduce fictitious personages
and speak through other's lips, and we must therefore
allot the appropriate character to those to whom
we lend a voice. For example, Publius Clodius will
be represented in one way, Appius Caecus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Clodius, the unscrupulous enemy of Cicero. Appins
Caccus, his ancestor, the great senator, who secured the
rejection of the terms of Pyrrhus.
                    </note>
                    in
another, while Caecilius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">See</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Cael.</hi>
                        xvi.
                    </note>
                    makes the father in his
comedy speak in quite a different manner from the
father in the comedy of Terence.
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    What can be
more brutal than the words of Verres' lictor,
                    <quote>To see him you will pay so much</quote>
                    ?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>
                        to visit a relative in prison,
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        v. xlv. 118;
                        <hi rend="italic">cp. Quint.</hi>
                        IX. iv. 71.
                    </note>
                    or braver than
those of the man from whom the scourge could
wring but one cry,
                    <quote>I am a Roman citizen!</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        V. lxii. 162.
                    </note>
                    Again, read the words which Cicero places in the
mouth of Milo in his peroration: are they not
worthy of the man who to save the state had so
oft repressed a seditious citizen, and had triumphed
by his valour over the ambush that was laid for
him?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        ii. 25; VI. v. 10.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Further, it is not merely true that the
variety required in impersonation will be in
                    <pb xml:id="p.179"/>
                    proportion to the variety presented by the case, for
impersonation demands even greater variety, since
it involves the portrayal of the emotions of children,
women, nations, and even of voiceless things, all
of which require to be represented in character.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    The same points have to be observed with respect
to those for whom we plead: for our tone will vary
with the character of our client, according as he is
distinguished, or of humble position, popular or the
reverse, while we must also take into account the
differences in their principles and their past life.
As regards the orator himself, the qualities which
will most commend him are courtesy, kindliness,
moderation and benevolence. But, on the other
hand, the opposite of these qualities will sometimes
be becoming to a good man. He may hate the bad,
be moved to passion in the public interest, seek to
avenge crime and wrong, and, in fine, as I said at
the beginning,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See ยง 14.</note>
                    may follow the promptings of every
honourable emotion.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    The character of the speaker and of the person on
whose behalf he speaks are, however, not the only
points which it is important to take into account:
the character of those before whom we have to
speak calls for serious consideration. Their power
and rank will make no small difference; we shall
employ different methods according as we are speaking before the emperor, a magistrate, a senator, a
private citizen, or merely a free man, while a
different tone is demanded by trials in the public
courts, and in cases submitted to arbitration.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    For
while a display of care and anxiety, and the employment of every device available for the amplification of our style are becoming when we are
                    <pb xml:id="p.181"/>
                    pleading for a client accused on a capital charge,
it would be useless to employ the same methods in
cases and trials of minor importance, and the speaker
who, when speaking from his chair before an arbitrator
on some trivial question, should make an admission
like that made by Cicero, to the effect that it was
not merely his soul that was in a state of commotion, but that his whole body was convulsed with
shuddering,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Div. in Caec.</hi>
                        xiii. 41
                    </note>
                    would meet with well-deserved ridicule.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    Again, who does not know what different styles of
eloquence are required when speaking before the
grave assembly of the senate and before the fickle
populace, since even when we are pleading before
single judges the same style will not be suitable
for use before one of weighty character and another
of a more frivolous disposition, while a learned judge
must not be addressed in the same tone that we
should employ before a soldier or a rustic, and our
style must at times be lowered and simplified, for
fear that he may be unable to take it in or to
understand it.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    Again, circumstances of time and place demand
special consideration. The occasion may be one
for sorrow or for rejoicing, the time at our disposal
may be ample or restricted, and the orator must
adapt himself to all these circumstances.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    It, likewise, makes no small difference whether we are
speaking in public or in private, before a crowded
audience or in comparative seclusion, in another
city or our own, in the camp or in the forum: each
of these places will require its own style and peculiar
form of oratory, since even in other spheres of life
the same actions are not equally suited to the forum,
the senate-house, the Campus Martius, the theatre
                    <pb xml:id="p.183"/>
                    or one's own house, and there is much that is not
in itself reprehensible, and may at times be absolutely necessary, which will be regarded as unseemly
if done in some place where it is not sanctioned by
custom.
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    I have already pointed out
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        VIII. iii. 11
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    how much
more elegance and ornament is allowed by the
topics of demonstrative oratory, whose main object
is the delectation of the audience, than is permitted
by deliberative or forensic themes which are concerned with action and argument.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To this must be added the fact that certain
qualities, which are in themselves merits of a high
order, may be rendered unbecoming by the special
circumstances of the case.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    For example, when a
man is accused on a capital charge, and, above all,
if he is defending himself before his conqueror or
his sovereign, it would be quite intolerable for him
to indulge in frequent metaphors, antique or newlycoined words, rhythms as far removed as possible
from the practice of every-day speech, rounded
periods, florid commonplaces and ornate reflexions.
Would not all these devices destroy the impression
of anxiety which should be created by a man in
such peril, and rob him of the succour of pity, on
which even the innocent are forced to rely?
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    Would
any man be moved by the sad plight of one who
revealed himself as a vainglorious boaster, and
ostentatiously flaunted the airs and graces of his
eloquence at a moment when his fate hung in
suspense? Would he not rather hate the man who,
despite his position as accused, hunted for fine
words, showed himself concerned for his reputation
as a clever speaker, and found time at such a
moment to display his eloquence?
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    I consider that
                    <pb xml:id="p.185"/>
                    Marcus Caelius, in the speech in which he defended
himself against a charge of breach of the peace, showed
a wonderful grasp of these facts, when he said:
                    <quote>
                        I
trust that none of you gentlemen, or of all those
who have come to plead against me, will find offence
in my mien or insolence in my voice, or, though that
is a comparative trifle, any trace of arrogance in
my gesture.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    But there are some cases where the
success of the pleader depends on apology, entreaties
for mercy, or confession of error. Can sorrow be
expressed in epigram? Or will
                    <hi rend="italic">enthymemes</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A form of syllogism. See V xiv. 1.</note>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">epiphonemata</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See VIII. v. 11.
                        <quote>An exclamation attached to the close of a statement or a proof by way of climax.</quote>
                    </note>
                    avail to win the judge's mercy? Will
not all embellishment of pure emotion merely impair its force and dispel compassion by such a display
of apparent unconcern?
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    Or, suppose that a father
has to speak of his son's death, or of some wrong
that is worse than death, will he, in making his statement of facts, seek to achieve that grace in exposition which is secured by purity and lucidity of
language, and content himself with setting forth
his case in due order with brevity and meaning?
Or will he count over the heads of his argument
upon his fingers, aim at niceties of division and
proposition, and speak without the least energy of
feeling as is usual in such portions of a speech?
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    Whither will his grief have fled while he is thus
engaged? Where has the fountain of his tears been
stayed? How came this callous attention to the
rules of text-books to obtrude itself? Will he not
rather, from his opening words to the very last he
utters, maintain a continuous voice of lamentation
and a mien of unvaried woe, if he desires to transplant his grief to the hearts of his audience? For
if he once remits aught of his passion of grief, he
                    <pb xml:id="p.187"/>
                    will never be able to recall it to the hearts of them
that hear him.
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    This is a point which declaimers,
above all, must be careful to bear in mind: I
mention this because I have no compunction in
referring to a branch of the art which was once also
my own, or in reverting to the consideration of the
youthful students such as once were in my charge:
the declaimer, I repeat, must bear this in mind,
since in the schools we often feign emotions that
affect us not as advocates, but as the actual sufferers.
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    For example, we even imagine cases where persons,
either because of some overwhelming misfortune or
repentance for some sin, demand from the senate the
right to make an end of their lives;
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        VII. iv. 39. It is said that poison was provided by the
state of Massilia to serve the turn of such unhappy persons,
so soon as they could convince the local senate that their
proposed suicide was justifiable.
                    </note>
                    and in these
cases it is obviously unbecoming not merely to adopt
a chanting intonation,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        I. viii. 2.
                    </note>
                    a fault which has also become
almost universal, or to use extravagant language,
but even to argue without an admixture of emotional
appeal, so managed as to be even more prominent
than the proof which is advanced. For the man
who can lay aside his grief for a moment while he
is pleading, seems capable even of laying it aside
altogether
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    I am not sure, however, that it is not in our
attitude towards our opponents that this care for
decorum, which we are now discussing, should be
most rigorously maintained. For there can be no
doubt, that in all accusations our first aim should
be to give the impression that it is only with the
greatest reluctance that we have consented to undertake the role of accuser. Consequently, I strongly
disapprove of such remarks as the following which
was made by Cassius Severus:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        x. i. 22. In 9 B.C. he accused Nonius Asprenas, a
friend of Augustus, of the crime of poisoning. Asprenas
was defended by Pollio, and supported by Augustus during
his trial.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        Thank Heaven, I
am still alive; and that I may find some savour in
                        <pb xml:id="p.189"/>
                        life, I see Asprenas arraigned for his crimes.
                    </quote>
                    For,
after this, it is impossible to suppose that he had
just or necessary reasons for accusing Asprenas, and
we cannot help suspecting that his motive was sheer
delight in accusation.
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    But, beside this consideration, which applies to all cases, there is the further
point that certain cases demand special moderation.
Therefore, a man who demands the appointment of
a curator for his father's property, should express his
grief at his father's affliction; and, however grave be
the charges that a father may be going to bring
against his son, he should emphasize the painful
nature of the necessity that is imposed upon him.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The imagined case would be as follows. The father disinherits the son for an alleged offence. The son accuses the
father of madness and demands a curator, etc.
                    </note>
                    And this he should do not merely in a few brief
words, but his emotion should colour his whole
speech, so that it may be felt not merely that he
is speaking, but that he is speaking the truth.
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    Again, if a ward make allegations against his
guardian, the latter must never give way to such
anger that no trace is left of his former love or
of a certain reverent regard for the memory of his
opponent's father. I have already spoken, in the
seventh book, I think,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">VII. iv. 24.</note>
                    of the way in which a case
should be pleaded against a father who disinherits
his son, or a wife who brings a charge of illtreatment against her husband, while the fourth book,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IV. i. 46.</note>
                    in which I prescribed certain rules for the exordium,
contains my instructions as to when it is becoming
that the parties should speak themselves, and when
they should employ an advocate to speak for them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    It will be readily admitted by everyone that
words may be becoming or offensive in themselves.
There is therefore a further point, which presents
the most serious difficulty, that requires notice in
                    <pb xml:id="p.191"/>
                    this connexion: we must consider by what means
things which are naturally unseemly and which, had
we been given the choice, we should have preferred
not to say, may be uttered without indecorum.
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    What at first sight can be more unpleasing and what
more revolting to the ears of men than a case in
which a son or his advocate has to speak against his
mother? And yet sometimes it is absolutely necessary, as, for example, in the case of Cluentius Habitus.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Clu.</hi>
                        lxi. 169
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                        Sasia was Cluentius' mother
                    </note>
                    But it is not always desirable to employ the method
adopted by Cicero against Sasia, not because he did not
make most admirable use of it, but because in such
cases it makes the greatest difference what the point
may be and what the manner in which the mother
seeks to injure her son.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    In the case of Sasia she hat
openly sought to procure the destruction of her son,
and consequently vigorous methods were justified
against her. But there were two points, the only
points which remained to be dealt with, that were
handled by Cicero with consummate skill: in the
first place, he does not forget the reverence that is
due to parents, and in the second, after a thorough
investigation of the history of the crime, he makes
it clear that it was not merely right, but a positive
necessity that he should say what he proposed to
say against the mother.
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    And he placed this explantation in the forefront of his case,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Clu.</hi>
                        vi. 17.
                    </note>
                    although it
had really nothing to do with the actual question at
issue; a fact which shows that his first consideration
in that difficult and complicated case was the consideration of what was becoming for him to say. He
therefore made the name of mother cast odium not
on the son, but on her who was the object of his
denunciations.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    It is, however, always possible that a
                    <pb xml:id="p.193"/>
                    mother may be her son's opponent in a case of less
serious import, or at any rate in a way which involves
less deadly hostility. Under such circumstances the
orator must adopt a gentler and more restrained
tone. For example, we may offer apology for the
line which we take, and thus lessen the odium
which we incur or even transfer it to a different
quarter, while if it be obvious that the son is deeply
grieved by the situation, it will be believed that he
is blameless in the matter and he will even become
an object of pity.
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    It will also be desirable to throw
the blame on others, so that it may be believed that
the mother's action was instigated by their malice,
and to assert that we will put up with every form of
provocation, and will say nothing harsh in reply, so
that, even although strong language may be absolutely necessary on our part, we may seem to be
driven to use it against our will. Nay, if some
charge has to be made against the mother, it will be
the advocate's task to make it seem that he does so
against the desire of the son and from a sense of
duty to his client. Thus both son and advocate will
win legitimate praise.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    What I have said about
mothers will apply to either parent; for I have
known of litigation taking place between fathers
and sons as well, after the
                    <hi rend="italic">emancipation</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>
                        from the
                        <hi rend="italic">patria potestas</hi>
                        by a fictitious form of sale.
                    </note>
                    of the son.
And when other relationships are concerned, we
must take care to create the impression that we
have spoken with reluctance and under stress of
necessity and that we have been forbearing in our
language; but the importance of so doing will vary
according to the respect due to the persons concerned. The same courtesy should be observed in
speaking on behalf of freedmen against their patrons.
                    <pb xml:id="p.195"/>
                    In fact, to sum up, it will never become us to plead
against such persons in a tone which we ourselves
should have resented in the mouth of men of like
condition.
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    The same respect is on occasion due to
persons of high rank, and it may be necessary to
offer justification for our freedom of speech to avoid
giving the impression that we have shown ourselves
insolent or ostentatious in our attack upon such
persons. Consequently Cicero, although he intended
to speak against Cotta
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        v. xiii. 20. P. Oppius, quaestor to M. Aurelius
Cotta in Bithynia, was charged by Cotta in a letter to the
Senate with misappropriation of supplies for his troops and
with an attempt on his life. The speech in which Cicero
defended Oppius (69 B.C.) is lost.
                    </note>
                    with the utmost vehemence,
and indeed the case of Publius Oppius was such that
he could not do otherwise, prefaced his attack by
pleading at some length the necessity imposed upon
him by his duty to his client.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes, again, it
will beseem us to spare or seem to spare our inferiors,
more especially if they be young. Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See opening sections of
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Caclio.</hi>
                    </note>
                    gives an
example of such moderation in the way in which he
deals with Atratinus in his defence of Caelius: he
does not lash him like an enemy, but admonishes
him almost like a father. For Atratinus was of
noble birth and young, and the grievance which led
him to bring the accusation was not unreasonable.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But the task is comparatively easy in those cases
in which it is to the judge, or even, it may be, to our
audience that we have to indicate the reason for our
moderation. The real difficulty arises when we are
afraid of offending those against whom we are
speaking.
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    The difficulties of Cicero when defending
Murena were increased by the fact that he was
opposed by two persons of this character, namely
Marcus Cato and Servius Sulpicius. And yet in
what courteous language, after allowing Sulpicius all
the virtues, he refuses to admit that he has any idea
of the way to conduct a candidature for the
                    <pb xml:id="p.197"/>
                    consulship.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Muren.</hi>
                        vii. 15.
                    </note>
                    What else was there in which a man of high
birth and a distinguished lawyer would sooner
admit his inferiority? With what skill he sets forth
his reasons for undertaking the defence of Murena,
when he says that he supported Sulpicius' candidature as opposed to that of Murena, but did not
regard that preference as reason why he should
support him in bringing a capital charge against his
rival!
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    And with what a light touch he deals with
Cato!
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Muren.</hi>
                        xxix. 60.
                    </note>
                    He has the highest admiration for his
character and desires to show that the fact that in
certain respects it has become severe and callous is due
not to any personal fault, but to the influence of the
Stoic school of philosophy; in fact you would imagine
that they were engaged not in a forensic dispute,
but merely in some philosophical discussion.
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    This
is undoubtedly the right method, and the safest rule
in such cases will be to follow the practice of Cicero,
namely, that, when we desire to disparage a man
without giving offence, we should allow him to be
the possessor of all other virtues and point out that
it is only in this one respect that he falls short of
his high standard, while we should, if possible, add
some reason why this should be so, such, for example,
as his being too obstinate or credulous or quick to
anger, or acting under the influence of others.
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    (For we may generally find a way out of such embarrassments by making it clear throughout our
whole speech that we not merely honour the object
of our criticism, but even regard him with affection.)
Further, we should have good cause for speaking thus
and must do so not merely with moderation, but also
give the impression that our action is due to the
necessities of the case.
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    A different situation arises,
                    <pb xml:id="p.199"/>
                    but an easier one, when we have to praise the actions
of men who are otherwise disreputable or hateful to
ourselves: for it is only right that we should award
praise where it is deserved, whatever the character
of the person praised may be. Cicero spoke in
defence of Gabinius and Publius Vatinius, both of
them his deadly enemies and men against whom
he had previously spoken and even published his
speeches: but he justifies himself by declaring that
he does so not because he is anxious for his reputation as an accomplished speaker, but because he is
concerned for his honour.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    He had a more difficult
task in his defence of Cluentius,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ch. 17
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    as it was necessary
for him to denounce Scamander's guilt, although he
had previously appeared for him. But he excuses
his action with the utmost grace, alleging the
importunity of those persons who had brought
Scamander to him, and his own youth at the time,
whereas it would have been a serious blot on his
reputation, especially in connexion with a case of the
most dubious character, if he had admitted that he
was one who was ready to undertake the defence of
guilty persons without asking awkward questions.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, when we are pleading before
a judge, who has special reasons for being hostile to
us or is for some personal motive ill-disposed to the
cause which we have undertaken, although it may
be difficult to persuade him, the method which we
should adopt in speaking is simple enough: we shall
pretend that our confidence in his integrity and in
the justice of our cause is such that we have no
fears. We must play upon his vanity by pointing out
that the less he indulges his own personal enmity
or interest, the greater will be the reputation for
                    <pb xml:id="p.201"/>
                    conscientious rectitude that will accrue to him from
his verdict.
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    The same method may be adopted if
our case should chance to be sent back to the same
judges from whom we have appealed: but we may
further, if the case should permit, plead that we
were forced to take the action which we did or were
led to it by error or suspicion.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>
                        apologise for refusing to accept his original judgement.
                    </note>
                    The safest course
will therefore be to express our regret, apologise for
our fault and employ every means to induce the
judge to feel compunction for his anger.
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>
                    It will
also sometimes happen that a judge may have to try
the same case on which he has previously given
judgment. In such circumstances the method
commonly adopted is to say that we should not
have ventured to dispute his sentence before any
other judge, since he alone would be justified in
revising it: but (and in this we must be guided by
the circumstances of the case) we may allege that
certain facts were not known on the previous
occasion or certain witnesses were unavailable, or,
though this must be advanced with the utmost
caution and only in the last resort, that our clients'
advocates were unequal to their task.
                    <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
                    And even if
we have to plead a case afresh before different
judges, as may occur in a second trial of a claim to
freedom or in cases in the centumviral courts, which
are divided between two different panels, it will be
most seemly, if we have lost our case before the first
panel, to say nothing against the judges who tried
the case on that occasion. But this is a subject
with which I dealt at some length in the passage
where I discussed
                    <hi rend="italic">proofs.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        ii. 1, where, as here, it is indicated that different
portions of a case might be tried by two panels of
                        <hi rend="italic">centumviri</hi>
                        sitting separately. The centumviral court dealt mainly with
cases of inheritance.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    It may happen that we have to censure actions in
others, of which we have been guilty ourselves,
                    <pb xml:id="p.203"/>
                    as, for example, when Tubero charges Ligarius
with having been in Africa.
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                    Again, there have
been cases where persons condemned for bribery
have indicted others for the same offence with a
view to recovering their lost position:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See v. x. 108 note and with reference to
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Clu.</hi>
                        xxxvi.
98.
                    </note>
                    for this
the schools provide a parallel in the theme where
a luxurious youth accuses his father of the same
offence. I do not see how this can be done with
decorum unless we succeed in discovering some
difference between the two cases, such as character,
age, motives, circumstances of time and place or
intention.
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
                    Tubero, for example, alleges that he
was a young man at the time and went thither
in the company of his father, who had been sent by
the senate not to take part in the war, but to purchase corn, and further that he left the party as
soon as he could, whereas Ligarius clung to the
party and gave his support, not to Gnaeus Pompeius, who was engaged with Caesar in a struggle
for the supreme power, though both wished to
preserve the state, but to Juba and the Africans
who were the sworn enemies of Rome.
                    <milestone n="81" unit="section"/>
                    The easiest
course, however, is to denounce another's guilt, while
admitting our own in the same connexion. However, that is the part of an informer, not of a
pleader. But if there is no excuse available, penitence is our only hope. For the man who is
converted to the hatred of his own errors, may
perhaps be regarded as sufficiently reformed.
                    <milestone n="82" unit="section"/>
                    For
there are occasionally circumstances which from
the very nature of the case may make such an
attitude not unbecoming, as, for example, in the
case where the father disinherits a son born of a
harlot because that son has married a harlot, a case
                    <pb xml:id="p.205"/>
                    which, although it forms a scholastic theme, might
actually arise in a court of law. There are a number
of pleas which the father may put forward with
becoming effect.
                    <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>
                    He will say that it is the prayer
of all parents that their sons should be better men
than themselves (for example, if a daughter also
had been born to him, the harlot, her mother,
would have wished her to be chaste), or that he
himself was in a humbler position (for a man in
such a position is permitted to marry a harlot),
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italic">lex lulex de maritandis ordiaibus</hi>
                        (18 B.C. ) forbade
the marriage of a senator with a prostitute.
                    </note>
                    or
that he had no father to warn him; and further
that there was an additional reason against his son's
conduct, namely, that he should not revive the old
family scandal nor reproach his father with his
marriage and his mother with the hard necessity
of her former life, nor give a bad example to his
own children in their turn. We may also plausibly
suggest that there is some particularly shameful
feature in the character of the harlot married by
the son, which the father cannot under existing
circumstances tolerate. There are other possible
arguments which I pass by: for I am not now
engaged in declamation, but am merely pointing
out that there are occasions when the speaker may
turn his own drawbacks to good account.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="84" unit="section"/>
                    More arduous difficulties confront us when we have
to deal with a complaint of some shameful act such
as rape, more especially when this is of an unnatural kind. I do not refer to cases when the
victim himself is speaking. For what should he do
but groan and weep and curse his existence, so that
the judge will understand his grief rather than hear
it articulately expressed? But the victim's advocate
will have to exhibit similar emotions, since the
                    <pb xml:id="p.207"/>
                    admission of such wrongs cause more shame to the
sufferer than the criminal.
                    <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>
                    In many cases it is
desirable to soften the harshness of our language
by the infusion of a more conciliatory tone, as, for
example, Cicero did in his speech
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Now lost.</note>
                    dealing with
the children of the proscribed. What fate could
be more cruel than that the children of men of
good birth and the descendants of distinguished
ancestors should be excluded from participation
in public life? For this reason that supreme artist
in playing on the minds of men admits that it is
hard, but asserts that the constitution is so essentially dependent on the laws of Sulla, that their
repeal would inevitably involve its destruction.
Thus he succeeded in creating the impression that
lie was doing something on behalf of those very
persons against whom he spoke.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cicero argued that it was better that a few should suffer
unjustly than that the state should be upset by admitting
them to office. But he admitted that their case was hard
and suggested that it was better for them to live in an
orderly state than run the risks in which revolution would
involve them as well as others.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="86" unit="section"/>
                    I have already
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        iii. 28.
                    </note>
                    pointed out, in dealing with the subject of jests,
how unseemly it is to take the position in life of
individuals as the target for our gibes, and also
have urged that we should refrain from insulting
whole classes, races or communities. But at times
our duty toward our client will force us to say
something on the general character of a whole
class of people, such as freedmen, soldiers, tax farmers or the like.
                    <milestone n="87" unit="section"/>
                    In all these cases the usual
remedy is to create the impression that it is with
reluctance that we introduce topics which must
give pain, while further we shall avoid attacking
everything, and even while using the language
of reproof with regard to the essential point of
attack, shall make up for our censure by praising
our victims in some other connexion.
                    <milestone n="88" unit="section"/>
                    For example,
if we charge soldiers with rapacity, we shall
                    <pb xml:id="p.209"/>
                    qualify our statement by saying that the fact is not
surprising, as they think that they are entitled to
some special reward for the perils they have faced
and the wounds they have sustained. Or, if we
censure them for insolence, we shall add that this
quality is due to the fact that they are more
accustomed to war than to peace. In the case of
freedmen we should disparage their influence: but
we may also give them credit for the industry
which secured their emancipation.
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/>
                    With regard
to foreign nations, Cicero's practice varies. When
he intends to disparage the credibility of Greek
witnesses he admits their distinction in learning
and literature and professes his admiration for their
nation.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">E.g. pro Flacco</hi>
                        xxvi.
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, he has nothing but
contempt for the Sardinians
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In a fragment of
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Scauro.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and attacks the Allobroges as the enemies of Rome.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Font.</hi>
                        viii.
                    </note>
                    In all these cases
none of his remarks, at the time they were made,
were inconsistent with or adverse to the claims of
decorum.
                    <milestone n="90" unit="section"/>
                    If there be anything offensive in the
subject on which we have to speak, it may be
toned down by a studied moderation in our language; for example, we may describe a brutal character as being unduly severe, an unjust man as led
astray by prejudice, an obstinate man as unreasonably tenacious of his opinion. And there are a
large number of cases where we should attempt to
defeat our opponents by reasoning, which forms the
gentlest of all methods of attack.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>
                    To these remarks I would add that all extravagance of any kind is indecorous, and consequently
statements which are in sufficient harmony with the
facts will none the less lose all their grace unless
they are modified by a certain restraint. It is hard
                    <pb xml:id="p.211"/>
                    to give rules as to the exact method in which this
precept should be observed, but the problem will
easily be solved by following the dictates of our own
judgement, which will tell us what it is sufficient to
say and how much the ears of our audience will
tolerate. We cannot weigh or measure our words
by fixed standards: they are like foods, some of
which are more satisfying than others.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="92" unit="section"/>
                    I think I should also add a few brief words to the
effect that not only very different rhetorical virtues
have their special admirers, but that they are often
praised by the same persons. For instance, there is
one passage
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        rxiii. 76. In this and the next passage Quintilian does not quote, but paraphrases.
                    </note>
                    in Cicero where he writes that the
best style is that which we think we can easily
acquire by imitation, but which we find is really
beyond our powers. But in another passage
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        xxviii. 97.
                    </note>
                    he
says that his aim was not to speak in such a manner
that everyone should be confident that he could do
the same, but rather in a style that should be the
despair of all.
                    <milestone n="93" unit="section"/>
                    These two statements may seem to
be inconsistent, but as a matter of fact both alike
deserve the praise which they receive. The difference is due to the fact that cases differ in character.
Those of minor importance are admirably suited by
the simplicity and negligence of unaffected language, whereas cases of greater moment are best
suited by the grand style. Cicero is pre-eminent in
both. Now while eminence in one of these styles
may seem to the inexperienced to be within their
grasp, those who understand know that they are
capable of eminence in neither.
                </p>
                <p>
                    II. Some regard memory as being no more than
one of nature's gifts; and this view is no doubt true
to a great extent; but, like everything else, memory
                    <pb xml:id="p.213"/>
                    may be improved by cultivation. And all the labour
of which I have so far spoken will be in vain unless
all the other departments be co-ordinated by the
animating principle of memory. For our whole
education depends upon memory, and we shall
receive instruction all in vain if all we hear slips
from us, while it is the power of memory alone
that brings before us all the store of precedents,
laws, rulings, sayings and facts which the orator
must possess in abundance and which he must
always hold ready for immediate use. Indeed
it is not without good reason that memory has
been called the treasure-house of eloquence.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But
pleaders need not only to be able to retain a number
of facts in their minds, but also to be quick to take
them in; it is not enough to learn what you have
written by dint of repeated reading; it is just as
necessary to follow the order both of matter and
words when you have merely thought out what you
are going to say, while you must also remember
what has been said by your opponents, and must
not be content merely with refuting their arguments
in the order in which they were advanced, but must
be in a position to deal with each in its appropriate
place.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Nay, even extempore eloquence, in my
opinion, depends on no mental activity so much
as memory. For while we are saying one thing, we
must be considering something else that we are
going to say: consequently, since the mind is always
looking ahead, it is continually in search of something which is more remote: on the other hand,
whatever it discovers, it deposits by some mysterious
process in the safe-keeping of memory, which acts
as a transmitting agent and hands on to the delivery
                    <pb xml:id="p.215"/>
                    what it has received from the imagination.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    I do
not conceive, however, that I need dwell upon the
question of the precise function of memory, although
many hold the view that certain impressions are
made upon the mind, analogous to those which a
signet-ring makes on wax. Nor, again, shall I be so
credulous, in view of the fact that the retentiveness
or slowness of the memory depends upon our
physical condition, as to venture to allot a special
art to memory.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    My inclination is rather to marvel
at its powers of reproducing and presenting a
number of remote facts after so long an interval,
and, what is more, of so doing not merely when we
seek for such facts, but even at times of its own
accord, and not only in our waking moments, but
even when we are sunk in sleep.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And my wonder is
increased by the fact that even beasts, which seem to
be devoid of reason, yet remember and recognise
things, and will return to their old home, however far
they have been taken from it. Again, is it not an
extraordinary inconsistency that we forget recent and
remember distant events, that we cannot recall what
happened yesterday and yet retain a vivid impression
of the acts of our childhood?
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    And what, again, shall
we say of the fact that the things we search for
frequently refuse to present themselves and then
occur to us by chance, or that memory does not
always remain with us, but will even sometimes
return to us after it has been lost? But we should
never have realised the fullness of its power nor its
supernatural capacities, but for the fact that it is
memory which has brought oratory to its present
position of glory.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For it provides the orator not
merely with the order of his thoughts, but even of
                    <pb xml:id="p.217"/>
                    his words, nor is its power limited to stringing
merely a few words together; its capacity for endurance is inexhaustible, and even in the longest
pleadings the patience of the audience flags long
before the memory of the speaker.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    This fact may
even be advanced as an argument that there must
be some art of memory and that the natural gift can
be helped by reason, since training enables us to
do things which we cannot do before we have had
any training or practice. On the other hand, I find
that Plato
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phaedr.</hi>
                        275 A.
                    </note>
                    asserts that the use of written characters
is a hindrance to memory, on the ground, that is, that
once we have committed a thing to writing, we
cease to guard it in our memory and lose it out of
sheer carelessness.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    And there can be no doubt that
concentration of mind is of the utmost importance in
this connexion; it is, in fact, like the eyesight, which
turns to, and not away from, the objects which it
contemplates. Thus it results that after writing
for several days with a view to acquiring by heart
what we have written, we find that our mental effort
has of itself imprinted it on our memory.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The first person to discover an art of memory is
said to have been Simonides,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See x. i. 64.</note>
                    of whom the following
well-known story is told. He had written an ode
of the kind usually composed in honour of victorious
athletes, to celebrate the achievement of one who
had gained the crown for boxing. Part of the sum
for which he had contracted was refused him on
the ground that, following the common practice of
poets, he had introduced a digression in praise of
Castor and Pollux, and he was told that, in view
of what he had done, he had best ask for the rest
of the sum due from those whose deeds he had
                    <pb xml:id="p.219"/>
                    extolled. And according to the story they paid
their debt.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    For when a great banquet was given
in honour of the boxer's success, Simonides was
summoned forth from the feast, to which he had
been invited, by a message to the effect that two
youths who had ridden to the door urgently desired
his presence. He found no trace of them, but what
followed proved to him that the gods had shown
their gratitude.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For he had scarcely crossed the
threshold on his way out, when the banqueting hall
fell in upon the heads of the guests and wrought
such havoc among them that the relatives of the
dead who came to seek the bodies for burial were
unable to distinguish not merely the faces but even
the limbs of the dead. Then it is said, Simonides,
who remembered the order in which the guests had
been sitting, succeeded in restoring to each man his
own dead.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    There is, however, great disagreement
among our authorities as to whether this ode was
written in honour of Glaucus of Carystus, Leocrates,
Agatharcus or Scopas, and whether the house was
at Pharsalus, as Simonides himself seems to indicate
in a certain passage, and as is recorded by Apollodorus, Eratosthenes, Euphorion and Eurypylus of
Larissa, or at Crannon, as is stated by Apollas
Callimachus, who is followed by Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        II. lxxxvi. 352.
                    </note>
                    to whom
the wide circulation of this story is due.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    It is
agreed that Scopas, a Thessalian noble, perished at
this banquet, and it is also said that his sister's son
perished with him, while it is thought that a number
of descendants of an elder Scopas met their death
at the same time.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    For my own part, however, I
regard the portion of the story which concerns
Castor and Pollux as being purely fictitious, since
                    <pb xml:id="p.221"/>
                    the poet himself has nowhere mentioned the occurrence; and he would scarcely have kept silence on
an affair which was so much to his credit.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    This achievement of Simonides appears to have
given rise to the observation that it is an assistance
to the memory if localities are sharply impressed
upon the mind, a view the truth of which everyone
may realise by practical experiment. For when we
return to a place after considerable absence, we not
merely recognise the place itself, but remember
things that we did there, and recall the persons
whom we met and even the unuttered thoughts
which passed through our minds when we were
there before.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Thus, as in most cases, art originates in experiment. Some place is chosen of the
largest possible extent and characterised by the
utmost possible variety, such as a spacious house
divided into a number of rooms. Everything of
note therein is carefully committed to the memory,
in order that the thought may be enabled to run
through all the details without let or hindrance.
And undoubtedly the first task is to secure that
there shall be no delay in finding any single detail,
since an idea which is to lead by association to
some other idea requires to be fixed in the mind
with more than ordinary certitude.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The next step
is to distinguish something which has been written
down or merely thought of by some particular
symbol which will serve to jog the memory; this
symbol may have reference to the subject as a
whole, it may, for example, be drawn from navigation, warfare, etc., or it may, on the other hand,
be found in some particular word. (For even in
cases of forgetfulness one single word will serve to
                    <pb xml:id="p.223"/>
                    restore the memory.) However, let us suppose that
the symbol is drawn from navigation, as, for instance,
an anchor; or from warfare, as, for example, some
weapon. These symbols are then arranged as follows.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    The first though is placed, as it were, in the forecourt;
the second, let us say, in the living-room; the remainder are placed in due order all round the
                    <hi rend="italic">impluvium</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <hi rend="italic">impluvium</hi>
                        was the light-well in the centre of the
                        <hi rend="italic">atrium</hi>
                        with a cistern beneath it to catch the rainwater from
the roof, which sloped inwards.
                    </note>
                    and entrusted not merely to bedrooms and
parlours, but even to the care of statues and the
like. This done, as soon as the memory of the facts
requires to be revived, all these places are visited in
turn and the various deposits are demanded from
their custodians, as the sight of each recalls the
respective details. Consequently, however large the
number of these which it is required to remember,
all are linked one to the other like dancers
hand in hand, and there can be no mistake since
they join what precedes to what follows, no trouble
being required except the preliminary labour of
committing the various points to memory.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    What
I have spoken of as being done in a house, can
equally well be done in connexion with public
buildings, a long journey, the ramparts of a city,
or even pictures. Or we may even imagine such
places to ourselves. We require, therefore,
places, real or imaginary, and images or symbols,
which we must, of course, invent for ourselves. By
images I mean the words by which we distinguish
the things which we have to learn by heart: in
fact, as Cicero says, we use
                    <quote>places like wax tablets and symbols in lieu of letters.</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        II. lxxxvi. 354.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    It will be best to
give his words
                    <hi rend="italic">verbatim:</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        II. lxxxvii. 358.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        We must for this purpose employ a number of remarkable places, clearly
envisaged and separated by short intervals: the
                        <pb xml:id="p.225"/>
                        images which we use must be active, sharply-cut and
distinctive, such as may occur to the mind and strike
it with rapidity.
                    </quote>
                    This makes me wonder all the
more, how Metrodorus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Of Scepsis, the favourite of Mithradates Eupator. See
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        II. lxxxviii. 360. He used the signs of the Zodiac as
aids to the memory, subdividing each into thirty compartments. Quintilian wonders on what principle he can have
made such a division, necessarily purely artificial in nature.
                    </note>
                    should have found three
hundred and sixty different localities in the twelve
signs of the Zodiac through which the sun passes.
It was doubtless due to the vanity and boastfulness
of a man who was inclined to vaunt his memory as
being the result of art rather than of natural gifts.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    I am far from denying that those devices may be
useful for certain purposes, as, for example, if we
have to reproduce a number of names in the order
in which we heard them. For those who use such
aids place the things which have to be remembered
in localities which they have previously fixed in the
memory; they put a table, for instance, in the forecourt, a platform in the hall and so on with the
rest, and then, when they retrace their steps, they
find the objects where they had placed them.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Such
a practice may perhaps have been of use to those
who, after an auction, have succeeded in stating
what object they had sold to each buyer, their statements being checked by the books of the money takers; a feat which it is alleged was performed by
Hortensius. It will, however, be of less service in
learning the various parts of a set speech. For
thoughts do not call up the same images as material
things, and a symbol requires to be specially invented
for them, although even here a particular place may
serve to remind us, as, for example, of some conversation that may have been held there. But how
can such a method grasp a whole series of connected words?
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    I pass by the fact that there are
certain things which it is impossible to represent by
                    <pb xml:id="p.227"/>
                    symbols, as, for example, conjunctions. We may, it
is true, like shorthand writers, have definite symbols
for everything, and may select an infinite number
of places to recall all the words contained in the
five books of the second pleading against Verres,
and we may even remember them all as if they
were deposits placed in safe-keeping. But will not
the flow of our speech inevitably be impeded by the
double task imposed upon our memory?
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    For how
can our words be expected to flow in connected
speech, if we have to look back at separate symbols
for each individual word? Therefore the experts
mentioned by Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        II. lxxxvii. 360. Charmadas or Charmides, an
elder contemporary of Cicero.
                    </note>
                    as having trained their
memory by methods of this kind, namely Charmadas, and Metrodorus of Scepsis, to whom I have
just referred, may keep their systems for their own
use. My precepts on the subject shall be of a
simpler kind.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    If a speech of some length has to be committed
to memory, it will be well to learn it piecemeal,
since there is nothing so bad for the memory as being
overburdened. But the sections into which we divide
it for this purpose should not be very short: otherwise
they will be too many in number, and will break up
and distract the memory. I am not, however, prepared to recommend any definite length; it will depend on the natural limits of the passage concerned,
unless, indeed, it be so long as itself to require subdivision.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    But some limits must be fixed to enable us,
by dint of frequent and continuous practice, to connect
the words in their proper order, which is a task of no
small difficulty, and subsequently to unite the various
sections into a whole when we go over them in
order. If certain portions prove especially difficult to
                    <pb xml:id="p.229"/>
                    remember, it will be found advantageous to indicate
them by certain marks, the remembrance of which
will refresh and stimulate the memory.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    For there can
be but few whose memory is so barren that they will
fail to recognise the symbols with which they have
marked different passages. But if anyone is slow to
recognise his own signs, he should employ the following additional remedy, which, though drawn from the
mnemonic system discussed above,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Sects. 18โ23.</note>
                    is not without its
uses: he will adapt his symbols to the nature of the
thoughts which tend to slip from his memory, using
an anchor, as I suggested above, if he has to speak
of a ship, or a spear, if he has to speak of a battle.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    For symbols are highly efficacious, and one idea
suggests another: for example, if we change a ring
from one finger to another or tie a thread round it,
it will serve to remind us of our reason for so doing.
Specially effective are those devices which lead the
memory from one thing to another similar thing which
we have got to remember; for example, in the case of
names, if we desire to remember the name Fabius,
we should think of the famous Cunctator, whom we
are certain not to forget, or of some friend bearing
the same name.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    This is specially easy with names
such as Aper, Ursus, Naso, or Crispus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Boar, Bear, Long-nose, and Curly respectively.</note>
                    since in
these cases we can fix their origin in our memory.
Origin again may assist us to a better remembrance of derivative names, such as Cicero, Verrius,
or Aurelius.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cicero, a sower of chickpea (
                        <hi rend="italic">cicer</hi>
                        ), according to Pliny
(xviii. 10). Aurelius = Auselius, child of the sun (
                        <hi rend="italic">a sole</hi>
                        )
according to Festus. Verrius unknown.
                    </note>
                    However, I will say no more on this
point.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    There is one thing which will be of assistance to
everyone, namely, to learn a passage by heart from
the same tablets on which he has committed it to
writing. For he will have certain tracks to guide
                    <pb xml:id="p.231"/>
                    him in his pursuit of memory, and the mind's eye
will be fixed not merely on the pages on which the
words were written, but on individual lines, and at
times he will speak as though he were reading aloud.
Further, if the writing should be interrupted by
some erasure, addition or alteration, there are certain
symbols available, the sight of which will prevent us
from wandering from the track.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    This device bears
some resemblance to the mnemonic system which
I mentioned above, but if my experience is worth
anything, is at once more expeditious and more
effective. The question has been raised as to
whether we should learn by heart in silence; it
would be best to do so, save for the fact that under
such circumstances the mind is apt to become indolent, with the result that other thoughts break in.
For this reason the mind should be kept alert by the
sound of the voice, so that the memory may derive
assistance from the double effort of speaking and
listening. But our voice should be subdued, rising
scarcely above a murmur.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, if we
attempt to learn by heart from another reading
aloud, we shall find that there is both loss and gain;
on the one hand, the process of learning will be
slower, because the perception of the eye is quicker
than that of the ear, while, on the other hand, when
we have heard a passage once or twice, we shall be
in a position to test our memory and match it against
the voice of the reader. It is, indeed, important for
other reasons to test ourselves thus from time to time,
since continuous reading has this drawback, that it
passes over the passages which we find hard to remember at the same speed as those which we find less
difficulty in retaining.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    By testing ourselves to see
                    <pb xml:id="p.233"/>
                    whether we remember a passage, we develop greater
concentration without waste of time over the repetition of passages which we already know by heart.
Thus, only those passages which tend to slip from
the memory are repeated with a view to fixing them
in the mind by frequent rehearsal, although as a rule
the mere fact that they once slipped our memory
makes us ultimately remember them with special
accuracy. Both learning by heart and writing have
this feature in common: namely, that good health,
sound digestion, and freedom from other preoccupations of mind contribute largely to the success of
both.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    But for the purpose of getting a real grasp
of what we have written under the various heads,
division and artistic structure will be found of great
value, while, with the exception of practice, which
is the most powerful aid of all, they are practically
the only means of ensuring an accurate remembrance
of what we have merely thought out. For correct
division will be an absolute safeguard against error in
the order of our speech,
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    since there are certain points
not merely in the distribution of the various questions
in our speech, but also in their development (provided we speak as we ought), which naturally come
first, second, and third, and so on, while the connexion
will be so perfect that nothing can be omitted or
inserted without the fact of the omission or insertion being obvious.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    We are told that Scaevola,
after a game of draughts in which he made the first
move and was defeated, went over the whole game
again in his mind on his way into the country, and
on recalling the move which had cost him the game,
returned to tell the man with whom he had been
playing, and the latter acknowledged that he was
                    <pb xml:id="p.235"/>
                    right. Is order, then, I ask you, to be accounted of
less importance in a speech, in which it depends
entirely on ourselves, whereas in a game our opponent
has an equal share in its development?
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    Again, if
our structure be what it should, the artistic sequence will serve to guide the memory. For just
as it is easier to learn verse than prose, so it is
easier to learn prose when it is artistically constructed than when it has no such organisation. If
these points receive attention, it will be possible to
repeat
                    <hi rend="italic">verbatim</hi>
                    even such psssages as gave the impression of being delivered extempore. My own
memory is of a very ordinary kind, but I found that
I could do this with success on occasions when the
interruption of a declamation by persons who had a
claim to such a courtesy forced me to repeat part of
what I had said. There are persons still living, who
were then present to witness if I lie.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    However, if anyone asks me what is the one
supreme method of memory, I shall reply, practice
and industry. The most important thing is to learn
much by heart and to think much, and, if possible,
to do this daily, since there is nothing that is more
increased by practice or impaired by neglect than
memory.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore boys should, as I have already
urged,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See. i. 36; II. vii. I
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    learn as much as possible by heart at the
earliest stage, while all who, whatever their age,
desire to cultivate the power of memory, should
endeavour to swallow the initial tedium of reading
and re-reading what they have written or read, a
process which we may compare to chewing the cud.
This task will be rendered less tiresome if we begin
by confining ourselves to learning only a little at a
time, in amounts not sufficient to create disgust: we
                    <pb xml:id="p.237"/>
                    may then proceed to increase the amount by a line a
day, an addition which will not sensibly increase the
labour of learning, until at last the amount we can
attack will know no limits. We should begin with
poetry and then go on to oratory, while finally we
may attempt passages still freer in rhythm and less
akin to ordinary speech, such, for example, as
passages from legal writers.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    For passages intended
as an exercise should be somewhat difficult in character if they are to make it easy to achieve the end
for which the exercise is designed; just as athletes
train the muscles of their hands by carrying weights of
lead, although in the actual contests their hands will
be empty and free. Further, I must not omit the
fact, the truth of which our daily practice will teach
us, that in the case of the slower type of mind the
memory of recent events is far from being exact.
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    It is
a curious fact, of which the reason is not obvious, that
the interval of a single night will greatly increase
the strength of the memory, whether this be due to
the fact that it has rested from the labour, the
fatigue of which constituted the obstacle to success,
or whether it be that the power of recollection,
which is the most important element of memory,
undergoes a process of ripening and maturing
during the time which intervenes. Whatever the
cause, things which could not be recalled on the
spot are easily co-ordinated the next day, and time
itself, which is generally accounted one of the causes
of forgetfulness, actually serves to strengthen the
memory.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, the abnormally rapid
memory fails as a rule to last and takes its leave as
though, its immediate task accomplished, it had no
further duties to perform. And indeed there is
                    <pb xml:id="p.239"/>
                    nothing surprising in the fact that things which
have been implanted in the memory for some time
should have a greater tendency to stay there.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The difference between the powers of one mind
and another, to which I have just referred, gives rise
to the question whether those who are intending to
speak should learn their speeches
                    <hi rend="italic">verbatim</hi>
                    or whether
it is sufficient to get a good grasp of the essence and
the order of what they have got to say. To this
problem no answer is possible that will be of universal application.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    Give me a reliable memory and
plenty of time, and I should prefer not to permit
a single syllable to escape me: otherwise writing
would be superfluous. It is specially important to
train the young to such precision, and the memory
should be continually practised to this end, that we
may never learn to become indulgent to its failure.
For this reason I regard it as a mistake to permit the
student to be prompted or to consult his manuscript,
since such practices merely encourage carelessness,
and no one will ever realise that he has not got his
theme by heart, if he has no fear of forgetting it.
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    It is this which causes interruptions in the flow of
speech and makes the orator's language halting and
jerky, while he seems as though he were learning
what he says by heart and loses all the grace that a
well-written speech can give, simply by the fact that
he makes it obvious that he has written it. On the
other hand, a good memory will give us credit for
quickness of wit as well, by creating the impression
that our words have not been prepared in the seclusion of the study, but are due to the inspiration
of the moment, an impression which is of the utmost
assistance both to the orator and to his cause.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    For
                    <pb xml:id="p.241"/>
                    the judge admires those words more and fears them
less which he does not suspect of having been
specially prepared beforehand to outwit him.
Further, we must make it one of our chief aims
in pleading to deliver passages which have been
constructed with the utmost care, in such manner
as to make it appear that they are but casually strung
together, and to suggest that we are thinking out
and hesitating over words which we have, as a
matter of fact, carefully prepared in advance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    It should now be clear to all what is the best
course to adopt for the cultivation of memory. If,
however, our memory be naturally somewhat dull
or time presses, it will be useless to tie ourselves
down rigidly to every word, since if we forget any
one of them, the result may be awkward hesitation or even a tongue-tied silence. It is, therefore,
far safer to secure a good grasp of the facts themselves and to leave ourselves free to speak as we
will.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    For the loss of even a single word that we
have chosen is always a matter for regret, and it is
hard to supply a substitute when we are searching
for the word that we had written. But even this
is no remedy for a weak memory, except for those
who have acquired the art of speaking extempore.
But if both memory and this gift be lacking, I
should advise the would-be orator to abandon the
toil of pleading altogether and, if he has any literary
capacity, to betake himself by preference to writing.
But such a misfortune will be of but rare occurrence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    For the rest there are many historical examples
of the power to which memory may be developed by
natural aptitude and application. Themistocles is
said to have spoken excellently in Persian after a
                    <pb xml:id="p.243"/>
                    year's study; Mithridates is recorded to have known
twenty-two languages, that being the number of
the different nations included in his empire;
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">King of Pontus.</note>
                    Crassus,
surnamed the Rich,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Consul, 131 B.C. Commanded in the war against Aristonicus of Pergamum, was defeated and killed.
                    </note>
                    when commanding in Asia had
such a complete mastery of five different Greek
dialects, that he would give judgement in the dialect
employed by the plaintiff in putting forward his
suit; Cyrus is believed to have known the name
of every soldier in his army,
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    while Theodectes
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Rhetorician of first half of fourth century B.C..</note>
                    is
actually said to have been able to repeat any number
of verses after only a single hearing. I remember
that it used to be alleged that there were persons
still living who could do the same, though I never
had the good fortune to be present at such a performance. Still, we shall do well to have faith in
such miracles, if only that he who believes may also
hope to achieve the like.
                </p>
                <p>
                    III.
                    <hi rend="italic">Delivery</hi>
                    is often styled
                    <hi rend="italic">action.</hi>
                    But the first
name is derived from the voice, the second from the
gesture. For Cicero in one passage
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        III. lix. 222.
                    </note>
                    speaks of
                    <hi rend="italic">action</hi>
                    as being
                    <hi rend="italic">a form of speech,</hi>
                    and in another
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        xvii. 55.
                    </note>
                    as being
a
                    <hi rend="italic">kind of physical eloquence.</hi>
                    None the less, he
divides action into two elements, which are the
same as the elements of delivery, namely, voice and
movement. Therefore, it matters not which term
we employ.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But the thing itself has an extraordinarily powerful effect in oratory. For the
nature of the speech that we have composed within
our minds is not so important as the manner in
which we produce it, since the emotion of each
member of our audience will depend on the impression made upon his hearing. Consequently, no
proof, at least if it be one devised by the orator
himself, will ever be so secure as not to lose its force
                    <pb xml:id="p.245"/>
                    if the speaker fails to produce it in tones that drive
it home. All emotional appeals will inevitably fall
flat, unless they are given the fire that voice, look,
and the whole carriage of the body can give them.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For when we have done all this, we may still
account ourselves only too fortunate if we have
succeeded in communicating the fire of our passion
to the judge: consequently, we can have no hope
of moving him if we speak with languor and indifference, nor of preventing him from yielding to the
narcotic influence of our own yawns.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    A proof of this
is given by actors in the theatre. For they add so
much to the charm even of the greatest poets, that
the verse moves us far more when heard than when
read, while they succeed in securing a hearing even
for the most worthless authors, with the result
that they repeatedly win a welcome on the
stage that is denied them in the library.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Now
if delivery can count for so much in themes
which we know to be fictitious and devoid of reality,
as to arouse our anger, our tears or our anxiety, how
much greater must its effect be when we actually
believe what we hear? For my own part I would
not hesitate to assert that a mediocre speech supported by all the power of delivery will be more
impressive than the best speech unaccompanied by
such power.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It was for this reason that Demosthenes, when asked what was the most important
thing in oratory, gave the palm to delivery and
assigned it second and third place as well, until
his questioner ceased to trouble him. We are
therefore almost justified in concluding that he
regarded it not merely as the first, but as the only
virtue of oratory.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This explains why he studied
                    <pb xml:id="p.247"/>
                    under the instruction of the actor Andronicus with
such diligence and success as thoroughly to justify
the remark made by Aeschines to the Rhodians when
they expressed their admiration of the speech of
Demosthenes on behalf of Ctesiphon,
                    <quote>What would you have said if you had heard him yourselves?</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        III. lvi. 213. Aeschincs in exile at Rhodes first
recited his own speech against Ctesiphon, and then by special
request read Demosthenes' reply, the famous
                        <hi rend="italic">De Corona.</hi>
                    </note>
                    Cicero likewise regards
                    <hi rend="italic">action</hi>
                    as the supreme element
of oratory.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He records that Gnaeus Lentulus acquired a greater reputation by his delivery than
by his actual eloquence, and that Gains Gracchus
by the same means stirred the whole Roman people
to tears when he bewailed his brother's death,
while Antonius and Crassus produced a great impression by their command of this quality, though
the greatest of all was that produced by Quintus
Hortensius.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lxvi., lxxxix., xxxviii., xliii., lxxxviii.
                    </note>
                    This statement is strongly supported
by the fact that the latter's writings fall so far
short of the reputation which for so long secured
him the first place among orators, then for a
while caused him to be regarded as Cicero's rival,
and finally, for the remainder of his life assigned
him a position second only to that of Cicero, that
his speaking must clearly have possessed some
charm which we fail to find when we read him.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    And, indeed, since words in themselves count for
much and the voice adds a force of its own to the
matter of which it speaks, while gesture and motion
are full of significance, we may be sure of finding
something like perfection when all these qualities
are combined.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    There are some, however, who consider that delivery which owes nothing to art and everything to
natural impulse is more forcible, and in fact the only
form of delivery which is worthy of a manly speaker.
                    <pb xml:id="p.249"/>
                    But these persons are as a rule identical, either with
those who are in the habit of disapproving of care,
art, polish and every form of premeditation in actual
speaking, as being affected and unnatural, or else
with those who (like Lucius Cotta, according to
Cicero)
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        III. xi. 42.
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lxxiv. 259.
                    </note>
                    affect the imitation of ancient writers both
in their choice of words and even in the rudeness of
their intonation and rhythm.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Those, however, who
think it sufficient for men to be born to enable them
to become orators, are welcome to their opinion, and
I must ask them to be indulgent to the efforts to
which I am committed by my belief that we cannot
hope to attain perfection unless nature is assisted by
study. But I will not be so obstinate as to deny
that to nature must be assigned the first place.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    For
a good delivery is undoubtedly impossible for one
who cannot remember what he has written, or lacks
the quick facility of speech required by sudden
emergencies, or is hampered by incurable impediments of speech. Again, physical uncouthness may
be such that no art can remedy it,
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    while a weak
voice is incompatible with first-rate excellence in
delivery. For we may employ a good, strong voice
as we will; whereas one that is ugly or feeble not
only prevents us from producing a number of effects,
such as a
                    <hi rend="italic">crescendo</hi>
                    or a sudden
                    <hi rend="italic">fortissimo,</hi>
                    but at
times forces faults upon us, making us drop the
voice, alter its pitch and refresh the hoarseness of
the throat and fatigue of the lungs by a hideous
chanting intonation. However, let me now turn to
consider the speaker on whom my precepts will not
be wasted.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    All delivery, as I have already said, is concerned
with two different things, namely, voice and gesture,
                    <pb xml:id="p.251"/>
                    of which the one appeals to the eye and the other
to the ear, the two senses by which all emotion
reaches the soul. But the voice has the first claim
on our attention, since even our gesture is adapted
to suit it.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The first point which calls for consideration is the
nature of the voice, the second the manner in which
it is used. The nature of the voice depends on its
quantity and quality.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The question of quantity is
the simpler of the two, since as a rule it is either
strong or weak, although there are certain kinds of
voice which fall between these extremes, and there
are a number of gradations from the highest notes to
the lowest and from the lowest to the highest.
Quality, on the other hand, presents more variations;
for the voice may be clear or husky, full or thin,
smooth or harsh, of wide or narrow compass, rigid or
flexible, and sharp or flat, while lung-power may be
great or small.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    It is not necessary for my purpose
to enquire into the causes which give rise to these
peculiarities. I need not raise the question whether
the difference lies in those organs by which the
breath is produced, or in those which form the
channels for the voice itself; whether the voice has
a character of its own or depends on the motions
which produce it; whether it be the strength of the
lungs, chest or the vocal organs themselves that
affords it most assistance, since the co-operation of
all these organs is required. For example, it is not
the mouth only that produces sweetness of tone; it
requires the assistance of the nostrils as well, which
carry off what I may describe as the overflow of the
voice. The important fact is that the tone must be
agreeable and not harsh.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    The methods of using the
                    <pb xml:id="p.253"/>
                    voice present great variety. For in addition to the
triple division of accents into sharp, grave and circumflex, there are many other forms of intonation
which are required: it may be intense or relaxed,
high or low, and may move in slow or quick time.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    But here again there are many intermediate
gradations between the two extremes, and just as
the face, although it consists of a limited number
of features, yet possesses infinite variety of expression,
so it is with the voice: for though it possesses but
few varieties to which we can give a name, yet every
human being possesses a distinctive voice of his
own, which is as easily distinguished by the ear as
are facial characteristics by the eye.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The good qualities of the voice, like everything
else, are improved by training and impaired by
neglect. But the training required by the orator is
not the same as that which is practised by the singing-master, although the two methods have many
points in common. In both cases physical robustness
is essential to save the voice from dwindling to the
feeble shrillness that characterises the voices of
eunuchs, women and invalids, and the means for
creating such robustness are to be found in walking,
rubbing-down with oil, abstinence from sexual intercourse, an easy digestion, and, in a word, in the
simple life.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Further, the throat must be sound,
that is to say, soft and smooth; for if the throat be
unsound, the voice is broken or dulled or becomes
harsh or squeaky. For just as the sound produced
in the pipe by the same volume of breath varies
according as the stops are closed or open, or the
instrument is clogged or cracked, so the voice is
strangled if the throat be swollen, and muffled if it
                    <pb xml:id="p.255"/>
                    is obstructed, while it becomes rasping if the throat
is inflamed, and may be compared to an organ with
broken pipes in cases where the throat is subject to
spasms.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the presence of some obstacle may
divide the breath just as a pebble will divide shallow
waters, which, although their currents unite again
soon after the obstruction is past, still leave a hollow
space in rear of the object struck. An excess of
moisture also impedes the voice, while a deficiency
weakens it. As regards fatigue, its effect is the same
as upon the body: it affects the voice not merely at
the moment of speaking, but for some time afterwards.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    But while exercise, which gives strength in
all cases, is equally necessary both for orators and
singing-masters, it is a different kind of exercise
which they require. For the orator is too much
occupied by civil affairs to be able to allot fixed
times for taking a walk, and he cannot tune his
voice through all the notes of the scale nor spare
it exertion, since it is frequently necessary for him
to speak in several cases in succession.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is the
same regime suitable as regards food: for the orator
needs a strong and enduring voice rather than one
which is soft and sweet, while the singer mellows all
sounds, even the highest, by the modulation of his
voice, whereas we have often to speak in harsh and
agitated tones, must pass wakeful nights, swallow
the soot that is produced by the midnight oil and
stick to our work though our clothes be dripping
with sweat.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, we must not attempt to
mellow our voice by coddling it nor accustom it to
the conditions which it would like to enjoy, but
rather give it exercise suited to the tasks on which
it will be employed, never allowing it to be impaired
                    <pb xml:id="p.257"/>
                    by silence, but strengthening it by practice, which
removes all difficulties.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    The best method for securing such exercise is to learn passages by heart (for if
we have to speak extempore, the passion inspired by
our theme will distract us from all care for our voice),
while the passages selected for the purpose should
be as varied as possible, involving a combination
of loud, argumentative, colloquial and modulated
utterance, so that we may prepare ourselves for all
exigencies simultaneously. This will be sufficient.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    Otherwise your delicate, over trained voice will
succumb before any unusual exertion, like bodies
accustomed to the oil of the training school, which
for all the imposing robustness which they display
in their own contests, yet, if ordered to make a day's
march with the troops, to carry burdens and mount
guard at night, would faint beneath the task and
long for their trainers to rub them down with oil and
for the free perspiration of the naked limbs.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Who
would tolerate me if in a work such as this I were
to prescribe avoidance of exposure to sun, wind, rain
or parching heat? If we are called upon to speak
in the sun or on a windy, wet or warm day, is that a
reason for deserting the client whom we have undertaken to defend? While as for the warning given
by some that the orator should not speak when
dyspeptic, replete or drunk, or immediately after
vomiting, I think that no sane person would dream
of declaiming under such circumstances.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    There is,
however, good reason for the rule prescribed by all
authorities, that the voice should not be overstrained
in the years of transition between boyhood and manhood, since at that period it is naturally weak, not, I
think, on account of heat, as some allege (for there
                    <pb xml:id="p.259"/>
                    is more heat in the body at other periods), but rather
on account of moisture, of which at that age there is
a superabundance.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    For this reason the nostrils and
the breast swell at this stage, and all the organs
develop new growth, with the result that they are
tender and liable to injury. However, to return to
the point, the best and most realistic form of exercise
for the voice, once it has become firm and set, is, in
my opinion, the practice of speaking daily just as we
plead in the courts. For thus, not merely do the
voice and lungs gain in strength, but we acquire a
becoming deportment of the body and develop grace
of movement suited to our style of speaking.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    The rules for delivery are identical with those for the
language of oratory itself. For, as our language must
be correct, clear, ornate and appropriate, so with our
delivery; it will be correct, that is, free from fault, if
our utterance be fluent, clear, pleasant and
                    <quote>urbane,</quote>
                    that is to say, free from all traces of a rustic or a foreign
accent.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    For there is good reason for the saying we so
often hear,
                    <quote>He must be a barbarian or a Greek</quote>
                    :
since we may discern a man's nationality from the
sound of his voice as easily as we test a coin by its ring.
If these qualities be present, we shall have those harmonious accents of which Ennius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ann.</hi>
                        ix. 305 (Vahlen).
                    </note>
                    expresses his
approval when he describes Cethegus as one whose
                    <quote>words rang sweetly,</quote>
                    and avoid the opposite effect,
of which Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        xv. 58.
                    </note>
                    expresses his disapproval by saying,
                    <quote>They bark, not plead.</quote>
                    For there are many faults
of which I spoke in the first book
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        I. i. 37; v. 32; viii. 1 and xi. 1
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    when I discussed
the method in which the speech of children should
be formed, since I thought it more appropriate to
mention them in connexion with a period of life
when it is still possible to correct them.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Again, the
                    <pb xml:id="p.261"/>
                    delivery may be described as correct if the voice be
sound, that is to say, exempt from any of the defects
of which I have just spoken, and if it is not dull,
coarse, exaggerated, hard, stiff, hoarse or thick, or
again, thin, hollow, sharp, feeble, soft or effeminate,
and if the breath is neither too short nor difficult to
sustain or recover.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    The delivery will be clear if, in the first place, the
words are uttered in their entirety, instead of being
swallowed or clipped, as is so often the case, since
too many people fail to complete the final syllables
through over-emphasising the first. But although
words must be given their full phonetic value, it is a
tiresome and offensive trick to pronounce every letter
as if we were entering them in an inventory.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    For
vowels frequently coalesce and some consonants disappear when followed by a vowel. I have already
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">ix. iv. 40.</note>
                    given an example of both these occurrences:โ
                    <hi rend="italic">mullum ille et terris.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        i.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    Further, we avoid placing two
consonants near each other when their juxtaposition
would cause a harsh sound; thus, we say
                    <hi rend="italic">pellexit</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">collegiate</hi>
                    and employ other like forms of which I have
spoken elsewhere.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IX. iv. 37.</note>
                    It is with this in mind that
Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lxxiv. 259.
                        <quote>suavitas vocis et lenis appellatio literarum</quote>
                        (
                        <quote>
                            the sweetness of his voice and the delicacy
with which he pronounced the various letters.
                        </quote>
                        )
                    </note>
                    praises Catulus for the sweetness with which
he pronounced the various letters. The second
essential for clearness of delivery is that our
language should be properly punctuated, that is
to say, the speaker must begin and end at the
proper place. It is also necessary to note at what
point our speech should pause and be momentarily
suspended (which the Greeks term
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(podiastolh\</foreign>
                    and
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(postigmh\</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>A slight stop,</quote>
                        corresponding to our
                        <quote>comma</quote>
                    </note>
                    and when it should come to a full stop.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    After the words
                    <hi rend="italic">arma virumque cano</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                        i. 1.
                    </note>
                    there is a momentary suspension, because
                    <hi rend="italic">virum</hi>
                    is connected with
                    <pb xml:id="p.263"/>
                    what follows, the full sense being given by
                    <hi rend="italic">virum Troiae qui primus ab oris,</hi>
                    after which there is a similar suspension. For although the mention of the
hero's destination introduces an idea different from
that of the place whence he came, the difference does
not call for the insertion of a stop, since both ideas
are expressed by the same verb
                    <hi rend="italic">venit.</hi>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    After
                    <hi rend="italic">Italiam</hi>
                    comes a third pause, since
                    <hi rend="italic">fato profugus</hi>
                    is parenthetic and breaks up the continuity of the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">Italian, Lavinaque.</hi>
                    For the same reason there is a
fourth pause after
                    <hi rend="italic">profulgus.</hi>
                    Then follows
                    <hi rend="italic">Lavinaque venit litora,</hi>
                    where a stop must be placed, as at this
point a new sentence begins. But stops themselves
vary in length, according as they mark the conclusion
of a phrase or a sentence.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    Thus after
                    <hi rend="italic">litora</hi>
                    I shall
pause and continue after taking breath. But when
I come to
                    <hi rend="italic">atque altae moenia Romae</hi>
                    I shall make a full
stop, halt and start again with the opening of a fresh
sentence.
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    There are also occasionally, even in
periods, pauses which do not require a fresh breath.
For although the sentence
                    <hi rend="italic">in coetu vero populi Romani, negotium publicumn gerens, magister equilum,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        II. xxv. 63. See
                        <hi rend="italic">Quint.</hi>
                        VIII. iv. 8.
                    </note>
                    etc., contains a number of different
                    <hi rend="italic">cola,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See IX. iv. 22, 67, 123. The name
                        <hi rend="italic">colon</hi>
                        is applied to the
longer clauses contained in a period, as opposed to the shorter,
which are styled
                        <hi rend="italic">commata.</hi>
                    </note>
                    expressing a number
of different thoughts, all these
                    <hi rend="italic">cola</hi>
                    are embraced by
a single period: consequently, although short pauses
are required at the appropriate intervals, the flow of
the period as a whole must not be broken. On the
other hand, it is at times necessary to take breath without any perceptible pause: in such cases we must do
so surreptitiously, since if we take breath unskilfully,
it will cause as much obscurity as would have resulted
from faulty punctuation. Correctness of punctuation
may seem to be but a trivial merit, but without it
all the other merits of oratory are nothing worth.
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.265"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    Delivery will be ornate when it is supported by
a voice that is easy, strong, rich, flexible, firm, sweet,
enduring, resonant, pure, carrying far and penetrating the ear (for there is a type of voice which
impresses the hearing not by its volume, but by its
peculiar quality): in addition, the voice must be
easily managed and must possess all the necessary
inflexions and modulations, in fact it must, as the
saying is, be a perfect instrument, equipped with
every stop: further, it must have strong lungs to
sustain it, and ample breathing power that will be
equal to all demands upon it, however fatiguing.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    The
deepest bass and the highest treble notes are unsuited to oratory: for the former lack clearness and,
owing to their excessive fullness, have no emotional
power, while the latter are too thin and, owing to
excess of clearness, give an impression of extravagance and are incompatible with the inflexions
demanded by delivery and place too great a strain
upon the voice.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    For the voice is like the strings of
a musical instrument; the slacker it is the deeper
and fuller the note produced, whereas if it be
tightened, the sound becomes thinner and shriller.
Consequently, the deepest notes lack force, and the
higher run the risk of cracking the voice. The orator
will, therefore, employ the intermediate notes, which
must be raised when we speak with energy and
lowered when we adopt a more subdued tone.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    For the first essential of a good delivery is evenness. The voice must not run joltingly, with
irregularity of rhythm and sound, mixing long and
short syllables, grave accents and acute, tones loud
and low, without discrimination, the result being that
this universal unevenness produces the impression of
                    <pb xml:id="p.267"/>
                    a limping gait. The second essential is variety of
tone, and it is in this alone that delivery really consists.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    I must warn my readers not to fall into the
error of supposing that evenness and variety are incompatible with one another, since the fault opposed
to evenness is unevenness, while the opposite of
variety is that which the Greeks term
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">monoei/deia,</foreign>
                    or
uniformity of aspect. The art of producing variety
not merely charms and refreshes the ear, but, by the
very fact that it involves a change of effort, revives
the speaker's flagging energies. It is like the relief
caused by changes in position, such as are involved
by standing, walking, sitting and lying, none of
which can be endured for a long time together.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    But the most important point (which I shall proceed
to discuss a little later) is the necessity of adapting
the voice to suit the nature of the various subjects
on which we are speaking and the moods that they
demand: otherwise our voice will be at variance with
our language. We must, therefore, avoid that which
the Greeks call
                    <hi rend="italic">monotony,</hi>
                    that is to say, the unvarying exertion both of lungs and voice. By this I do
not simply mean that we must avoid saying everything in a loud tone, a fault which amounts to
madness, or in a colloquial tone, which creates an
impression of lifelessness, or in a subdued murmur,
which is utterly destructive of all vigour.
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    What I
mean is this: within the limits of one passage and the
compass of one emotion we may vary our tone to a
certain, though not a very great extent, according
as the dignity of the language, the nature of the
thought, the conclusion and opening of our sentences or transitions from one point to another, may
demand. Thus, those who paint in monochrome
                    <pb xml:id="p.269"/>
                    still represent their objects in different planes, since
otherwise it would have been impossible to depict
even the limbs of their figures.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    Let us take as an
example the opening of Cicero's magnificent speech
in defence of Milo. Is it not clear that the orator
has to change his tone almost at every stop? it is the
same face, but the expression is changed.
                    <hi rend="italic">Etsi vereor, iudices, ne turpe sit,</hi>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">pre fortissimo viro dicere incipientem timere.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        i. 1
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                        <quote>
                            Although I fear, gentlemen, that it
may be discreditable that I should feel afraid on rising to
defend the harvest of men, and though it is far from becoming
that, whereas Titus Annius is more concerned for the safety
of the State than for his own, I
                            <hi rend="italic">should</hi>
                            he unable to bring a
like degree of courage to aid me in pleading his cause; still,
the strange appearance of this novel tribunal dismays my
eyes, which, whithersoever they turn, look in vain for the
customary aspect of the forum and the time-honoured usage
of the courts. For your bench is not surrounded, as it used
to be, by a ring of spectators,
                        </quote>
                        etc.
                    </note>
                    Although the general tone of the passage is
restrained and subdued, since it is not merely an
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium,</hi>
                    but the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium</hi>
                    of a man suffering from
serious anxiety, still something fuller and bolder is
required in the tone, when he says
                    <hi rend="italic">pro fortissiomo viro,</hi>
                    than when he says
                    <hi rend="italic">etsi cereor and turpe sit</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">timere.</hi>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    But his second breath must be more vigorous, partly
owing to the natural increase of effort, since we
always speak our second sentence with less timidity,
and partly because he indicates the high courage of
Milo:
                    <hi rend="italic">minimeque deceat, cum</hi>
                    T. Annius ipse magis de
                    <hi rend="italic">rei publicae salute quam de sua perturbetur.</hi>
                    Then he
proceeds to something like a reproof of himself:
                    <hi rend="italic">me ad eius causam parem animi maguitudinem adferre non posse.</hi>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    The next clause suggests a reflexion on the
conduct of others:
                    <hi rend="italic">tamen haec novi iudicii nova forma terret oculos.</hi>
                    And then in what follows he opens
every stop, as the saying is:
                    <hi rend="italic">
                        qui, quocunque inciderunt,
consuetudinem fori et pristinum morem iudiciorum requirunt:
                    </hi>
                    while the next clause is even fuller and freer:
                    <hi rend="italic">non enim corona cousessus vester cinctus est, ut solebat.</hi>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    I have called attention to these points to make it
clear that there is a certain variety, not merely in
                    <pb xml:id="p.271"/>
                    the delivery of
                    <hi rend="italic">cola,</hi>
                    but even in that of phrases consisting of one word, a variety the lack of which
would make every word seem of equal importance.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The voice, however, must not be pressed beyond
its powers, for it is liable to be choked and to become less and less clear in proportion to the increase
of effort, while at times it will break altogether and
produce the sound to which the Greeks have given
a name derived from the crowing of cocks before the
voice is developed.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        What this word was is not known. Perhaps merely
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">kokkusmo/s.</foreign>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    We must also beware of confusing our utterance by excessive volubility, which
results in disregard of punctuation, loss of emotional
power, and sometimes in the clipping of words. The
opposite fault is excessive slowness of speech, which
is a sign of lack of readiness in invention, tends by
its sluggishness to render our hearers inattentive,
and, further, wastes the time allotted to us for speaking,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">aquam perdit.</hi>
                        Lit. wastes water. The reference is to
the clepsydra or water-clock employed for the measurement
of time.
                    </note>
                    a consideration which is of some importance.
Our speech must be ready, but not precipitate, under
control, but not slow,
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    while we must not take breath
so often as to break up our sentence, nor, on the
other hand, sustain it until it fails us from exhaustion.
For the sound produced by loss of breath is disagreeable; we gasp like a drowning man and fill our lungs
with long drawn inhalations at in appropriate moments,
giving the impression that our action is due not to
choice, but to compulsion. Therefore, in attacking
a period of abnormal length, we should collect our
breath, but quickly, noiselessly and imperceptibly.
On other occasions we shall be able to take breath
at the natural breaks in the substance of our speech.
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    But we must exercise our breathing capacity to make
it as great as possible. To produce this result Demosthenes used to recite as many successive lines as
                    <pb xml:id="p.273"/>
                    possible, while he was climbing a hill. He also, with
a view to securing fluency free from impediment,
used to roll pebbles under his tongue when speaking
in the privacy of his study.
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes the breath,
although capable of sustained effort and sufficiently
full and clear, lacks firmness when exerted, had for
that reason is liable to become tremulous, like bodies
which, although to all appearances sound, receive
insufficient support from the sinews. This the Greeks
call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">brasmo/s.</foreign>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">bra/gxos</foreign>
                        is generally read, but the word is used in the
sense of
                        <quote>hotrseness,</quote>
                        which is not what Quintilian describes.
I would read
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">brasmo/s,</foreign>
                        a word meaning
                        <quote>effervescence,</quote>
                        <quote>shaking,</quote>
                        <quote>shivering.</quote>
                        Here =
                        <hi rend="italic">tremolo.</hi>
                    </note>
                    There are some too who, owing to
the loss of teeth, do not draw in the breath naturally,
but suck it in with a hissing sound. There are
others who pant incessantly and so loudly that it
is perfectly audible within them: they remind one
of heavily-laden beasts of burden straining against
the yoke.
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    Some indeed actually affect this mannerism, as though to suggest that they are struggling
with the host of ideas that crowd themselves upon
them and oppressed by a greater flood of eloquence
than their throats are capable of uttering. Others,
again, find a difficulty in opening their mouths, and
seem to struggle with their words; and, further,
although they are not actually faults of the voice,
yet since they arise out of the use of the voice,
I think this is the most appropriate place for
referring to the habit of coughing and spitting with
frequency while speaking, of hawking up phlegm
from the depths of the lungs, like water from a
well,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">trochea</hi>
                        is a windlass used for raising water from a
well.
                    </note>
                    sprinkling the nearest of the bystanders with
saliva, and expelling the greater portion of the
breath through the nostrils.
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    But any of these faults
are tolerable compared with the practice of chanting
instead of speaking, which is the worst feature of
our modern oratory, whether in the courts or in the
                    <pb xml:id="p.275"/>
                    schools, and of which I can only say that I do not
know whether it is more useless or more repugnant
to good taste. For what can be less becoming to
an orator than modulations that recall the stage and
a sing-song utterance which at times resembles the
maudlin utterance of drunken revellers?
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    What can
be more fatal to any emotional appeal than that the
speaker should, when the situation calls for grief,
anger, indignation or pity, not merely avoid the
expression of those emotions which require to be
kindled in the judge, but outrage the dignity of
the courts with noises such as are dear to the
Lycians and Carians? For Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        xviii. 57.
                    </note>
                    has told us that
the rhetoricians of Lycia and Caria come near to
singing in their perorations. But, as a matter of tact,
we have somewhat overstepped the limits imposed by
the more restrained style of singing.
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    I ask you,
does anyone sing, I will not say when his theme is
murder, sacrilege or parricide, but at any rate when
he deals with figures or accounts, or, to cut a long
story short, when he is pleading in any kind of
lawsuit whatever? And if such a form of intonation
is to be permitted at all, there is really no reason
why the modulations of the voice should not be
accompanied by harps and flutes, or even by cymbals,
which would be more appropriate to the revolting
exhibitions of which I am speaking.
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    And yet we
show no reluctance in indulging this vicious practice.
For no one thinks his own singing hideous, and it
involves less trouble than genuine pleading. There
are, moreover, some persons who, in thorough conformity with their other vices, are possessed with a
perpetual passion for hearing something that will
soothe their ears. But, it may be urged, does not
                    <pb xml:id="p.277"/>
                    Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        xviii. 57.
                    </note>
                    himself say that there is a suggestion of
singing in the utterance of an orator? And is not
this the outcome of a natural impulse? I shall
shortly proceed to show to what extent such musical
modulations are permissible: but if we are to call
it singing, it must be no more than a suggestion
of singing, a fact which too many refuse to
realise.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    But it is now high time for me to explain what I
mean by appropriate delivery. Such appropriateness
obviously lies in the adaptation of the delivery to
the subjects on which we are speaking. This quality
is, in the main, supplied by the emotions themselves,
and the voice will ring as passion strikes its chords.
But there is a difference between true emotion on
the one hand, and false and fictitious emotion on
the other. The former breaks out naturally, as in
the case of grief, anger or indignation, but lacks
art, and therefore requires to be formed by methodical
training.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    The latter, on the other hand, does imply
art, but lacks the sincerity of nature: consequently
in such cases the main thing is to excite the appropriate feeling in oneself, to form a mental picture
of the facts, and to exhibit an emotion that cannot
be distinguished from the truth. The voice, which
is the intermediary between ourselves and our
hearers, will then produce precisely the same
emotion in the judge that we have put into it. For
it is the index of the mind, and is capable of expressing all its varieties of feeling.
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore when we
deal with a lively theme, the flow of the voice is
characterised by fullness, simplicity and cheerfulness; but when it is roused to battle, it puts forth
all its strength and strains every nerve. In anger
                    <pb xml:id="p.279"/>
                    it is fierce, harsh and intense, and calls for frequent
filling of the lungs, since the breath cannot be sustained for long when it is poured forth without
restraint. When it is desired to throw odium upon
our opponents, it will be somewhat slower, since,
as a rule, it is none save the weaker party takes
refuge in such tactics. On the other hand, in flattery,
admission, apology or question it will be gentle and
subdued.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    If we advise, warn, promise or console,
it will be grave and dignified, modest if we express
fear or shame, bold in exhortation, precise in argument, full of modulations, suggestive of tears and
designedly muffled in appeals for pity, whereas in
digression it will be full and flowing, and will have
all the resonance that is characteristic of confidence;
in exposition of facts or conversations it will be
even and pitched half-way betwixt high and low.
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    But it will be raised to express violent emotion, and
sink when our words are of a calmer nature, rising
and falling according to the demands of its theme.
                </p>
                <p>
                    However, for the moment I will defer speaking
of the variations in tone required by different topics,
and will proceed first to the discussion of gesture
which conforms to the voice, and like it, obeys the
impulse of the mind. Its importance in oratory is
sufficiently clear from the fact that there are many
things which it can express without the assistance
of words.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    For we can indicate our will not merely
by a gesture of the hands, but also with a nod from
the head: signs take the place of language in the
dumb, and the movements of the dance are frequently full of meaning, and appeal to the emotions
without any aid from words. The temper of the
mind can be inferred from the glance and gait,
                    <pb xml:id="p.281"/>
                    and even speechless animals show anger, joy, or the
desire to please by means of the eye and other
physical indications.
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is it wonderful that gesture which depends on various forms of movement
should have such power, when pictures, which are
silent and motionless, penetrate into our innermost
feelings with such power that at times they seem
more eloquent than language itself. On the other
hand, if gesture and the expression of the face are
out of harmony with the speech, if we look cheerful
when our words are sad. or slake our heads when
making a positive assertion, our words will not only
lack weight, but will fail to carry conviction.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    Gesture and movement are also productive of grace.
It was for this reason that Demosthenes used to
practise his delivery in front of a large mirror, since,
in spite of the fact that its reflexions are reversed,
he trusted his eyes to enable him to judge accurately
the effect produced.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The head, being the chief member of the body,
has a corresponding importance in delivery, serving
not merely to produce graceful elect, but to illustrate our meaning as well.
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    To secure grace it is
essential that the head should be carried naturally
an erect. For a droop suggests humility, while if
it be thrown back it seems to express arrogance, if
inclined to one side it gives an impression of languor,
while if it is held too stiffly and rigidly it appears
to indicate a rude and savage temper. Further, it
should derive appropriate motion from the subject
of our pleading, maintaining harmony with the gesture and following the movement of the hands and
side.
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    For the eyes are always turned in the same
direction as the gesture, except when we are called
                    <pb xml:id="p.283"/>
                    upon to condemn or concede something or to express
abhorrence, when we shall show our aversion by
turning away the face and by thrusting out our
hands as though to repel the thought, as in the
lines:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Ye gods, such dread calamity avert!</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                iii. 620.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    or
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Not for me</l>
                                <l part="N">To claim such honour!</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                i. 335.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    The methods by which the head may express our
meaning are manifold. For in addition to those
movements which indicate consent, refusal and
affirmation, there are those expressive of modesty,
hesitation, wonder or indignation, which are well
known and common to all. But to confine the
gesture to the movement of the head alone is regarded as a fault by those who teach acting as well
as by professors of rhetoric. Even the frequent
nodding of the head is not free from fault, while
to toss or roll it till our hair flies free is suggestive
of a fanatic.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    By far the greatest influence is exercised by the
glance. For it is by this that we express supplication, threats, flattery, sorrow, joy, pride or submission. It is on this that our audience hang, on
this that they rivet their attention and their gaze,
even before we begin to speak. It is this that
inspires the hearer with affection or dislike, this
that conveys a world of meaning and is often more
eloquent than all our words.
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently in plays
destined for the stage, the masters of the art of
delivery design even their masks to enhance the
emotional effect. Thus, in tragedy, Aerope will be
                    <pb xml:id="p.285"/>
                    sad, Medea fierce, Ajax bewildered, Hercules truculent.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    In comedy, on the other hand, over and
above the methods adopted to distinguish between
slaves, pimps, parasites, rustics, soldiers, harlots,
maidservants, old men stern and mild, youths moral
or luxurious, married women and girls, we have
the important rรดle of the father who, because at
times he is excited and at others call, has one
eyebrow raised and the other normal, the custom
among actors being to turn that side of the face to
the audience which best suits the role.
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    But of the
various elements that go to form the expression,
the eyes are the most important, since they, more
than any-thing else, reveal the temper of the mind,
and without actual movement will twinkle with
merriment or be clouded with grief. And further,
nature has given them tears to serve as interpreters
of our feelings, tears that will break forth for sorrow
or stream for very joy. But, when the eyes move,
they become intent, indifferent, proud, fierce, mild,
or angry; and they will assume all these characters
according as the pleading may demand.
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    But they
must never he fixed or protruding, languid or sluggish, lifeless, lascivious, restless, nor swim with a
moist voluptuous glance, nor look aslant nor leer
in amorous fashion, nor yet must they seem to
promise or ask a boon. As for keeping them fully
or partially closed while speaking, surely none save
an uneducated man or a fool would dream of doing
such a thing.
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>
                    And in addition to all these forms of
expression, the upper and lower eyelids can render
service in support of the eyes.
                    <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
                    The eyebrows also
may be used with great effect. For to some extent
they mould the expression of the eyes and
                    <pb xml:id="p.287"/>
                    determine that of the forehead. It is by means of the
eyebrows that we contract, raise or smooth the
latter: in fact, the only thing which has greater
influence over it is the blood, which moves in conformity with the emotions that control the mind,
causing a blush on a skin that is sensitive to shame,
and giving place to an icy pallor under the influence
of fear, whereas, when it is under control, it produces a peaceful complexion, intermediate between
the two.
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                    Complete immobility in the eyebrows is
a fault, as also is excess of mobility or the tendency
to raise one and lower the other, as in the comic
mask which I mentioned just now: while it is a
further blemish if they express a feeling out of
keeping with the words we utter. For they show
anger by contraction, grief by depression and cheerfulness by their expansion. They are also dropped
or raised to express consent or refusal respectively.
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
                    It is not often that the lips or nostrils can be
becomingly employed to express our feelings, although they are often used to indicate derision,
contempt or loathing. For to
                    <quote>wrinkle the nostrils</quote>
                    (as Horace says),
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ep.</hi>
                        I. v. 23.
                    </note>
                    or blow them out, or twitch them,
or fret them with our finger, or snort through them
with a sudden expulsion of the breath, or stretch
them wide or push them up with the flat of the
hand are all indecorous, since it is not without reason
that censure is passed even on blowing the nose too
frequently.
                    <milestone n="81" unit="section"/>
                    It is also an ugly habit to protrude the
lips, open them with a sudden smack,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        It is hard to distinguish between
                        <hi rend="italic">scindere</hi>
                        and
                        <hi rend="italic">didurere.</hi>
                        I have adopted a suggestion of Spalding's.
                    </note>
                    compress
them, draw them apart and bare the teeth, or twist
them awry to one side till they almost reach the
ear, or to curl them in scorn, or let them droop, or
allow the voice to escape only on one side. It is
                    <pb xml:id="p.289"/>
                    also unbecoming to lick or bite them, since their
motion should be but slight even when they are
employed in forming words. For we must speak
with the mouth rather than the lips.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="82" unit="section"/>
                    The neck must be straight, not stiff or bent
backward. As regards the throat, contraction and
stretching are equally unbecoming, though in different ways. If it be stretched, it causes strain
as well, and weakens and fatigues the voice,
while if the chin be pressed down into the chest
it makes the voice less distinct and coarsens it,
owing to the pressure on the windpipe.
                    <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>
                    It is, as a
rule, unbecoming to raise or contract the shoulders.
For it shortens the neck and produces a mean and
servile gesture, which is even suggestive of dishonesty when men assume an attitude of flattery,
admiration or fear.
                    <milestone n="84" unit="section"/>
                    In continuous and flowing passages a most becoming gesture is slightly to extend
the arm with shoulders well thrown back and the
fingers opening as the hand moves forward. But
when we have to speak in specially rich or impressive style, as, for example, in the passage
                    <hi rend="italic">saxa atiqu solitudines voci respondent,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Arh.</hi>
                        viii. 19. See VIII. iii. 75 and IX. iv. 44.
                        <quote>Rocks and solitude make answer to the voice.</quote>
                    </note>
                    the arm will be thrown out
in a stately sidelong sweep and the words will, as
it were, expand in unison with the gesture.
                    <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>
                    As
for the hands, without which all action would be
crippled and enfeebled, it is scarcely possible to
describe the variety of their motions, since they are
almost as expressive as words. For other portions
of the body merely help the speaker, whereas the
hands may almost be said to speak.
                    <milestone n="86" unit="section"/>
                    Do we not
use them to demand, promise, summon, dismiss,
threaten, supplicate, express aversion or fear, question
or deny? Do we not employ them to indicate joy,
                    <pb xml:id="p.291"/>
                    sorrow, hesitation, confession, penitence, measure,
quantity, number and time?
                    <milestone n="87" unit="section"/>
                    Have they not power
to excite and prohibit, to express approval, wonder
or shame? Do they not take the place of adverbs
and pronouns when we point at places and things?
In fact, though the peoples and nations of the earth
speak a multitude of tongues, they share in common
the universal language of the hands.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="88" unit="section"/>
                    The gestures of which I have thus far spoken are
such as naturally proceed from us simultaneously
with our words. But there are others which indicate things by means of mimicry. For example,
you may suggest a sick man by mimicking the
gesture of a doctor feeling the pulse, or a harpist by
a movement of the hands as though they were
plucking the strings. But this is a type of gesture
which should be rigorously avoided in pleading.
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/>
                    For
the orator should be as unlike a dancer as possible,
and his gesture should be adapted rather to his
thought than to his actual words, a practice which
was indeed once upon a time even adopted by the
more dignified performers on the stage. I should,
therefore, permit him to direct his hand towards his
body to indicate that he is speaking of himself, or to
point it at some one else to whom he is alluding,
together with other similar gestures which I need
not mention. But, on the other hand, I would not
allow him to use his hands to imitate attitudes or to
illustrate anything he may chance to say.
                    <milestone n="90" unit="section"/>
                    And this
rule applies not merely to the hands, but to all
gesture and to the voice as well. For in delivering
the period
                    <hi rend="italic">stetit soleatus praetor populi Romani,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        There in his slippers stood the praetor of the Roman
people."
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        v. xxxiii. 86: see
                        <hi rend="italic">VIII.</hi>
                        iii. 64.
                    </note>
                    it
would be wrong to imitate Verres leaning on his
mistress, or in uttering the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">caedebatur in medio</hi>
                    <pb xml:id="p.293"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">foro Messanae</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        v. lxii 162.
                        <quote>He was scourged in the midst of the market-place of Messina.</quote>
                    </note>
                    to make the side writhe, as it does
when quivering beneath the lash, or to utter shrieks,
such as are extorted by pain.
                    <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>
                    For even comic actors
seem to me to commit a gross offence against the
canons of their art when, if they have in the course
of some narrative to quote either the words of an old
man (as, for example, in the prologue to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Hydria</hi>
                    ),
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Plays of Menander.</note>
                    or of a woman (as in the (
                    <hi rend="italic">Georgus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Plays of Menander.</note>
                    ), they litter them
in a tremulous or a treble voice, notwithstanding the
fact that they are playing the part of a young man.
So true is it that certain forms of imitation may be
a blemish even in those whose whole art consists in
imitation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="92" unit="section"/>
                    One of the commonest of all the gestures consists
in placing the middle finger against the thumb and
extending the remaining three: it is suitable to the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordum,</hi>
                    the hand being moved forward with an
easy motion a little distance both to right and left,
while the head and shoulders gradually follow the
direction of the gesture. It is also useful in the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of facts,</hi>
                    but in that case the hand must be
moved with firmness and a little further forward,
while, if we are reproaching or refuting our adversary, the same movement may be employed with
some vehemence and energy, since such passages
permit of greater freedom of extension.
                    <milestone n="93" unit="section"/>
                    On the
other hand, this same gesture is often directed sideways towards the left shoulder: this is a mistake,
although it is a still worse fault to thrust the arm
across the chest and gesticulate with the elbow.
The middle and third fingers are also sometimes
turned under the thumb, producing a still more
forcible effect than the gesture previously described,
but not well adapted for use in the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium</hi>
                    or
                    <hi rend="italic">state-</hi>
                    <pb xml:id="p.295"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">meant of facts.</hi>
                    <milestone n="94" unit="section"/>
                    But when three fingers are doubled
under the thumb, the finger, which Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        II. xlv. 188.
                    </note>
                    says
that Crassus used to such effect, is extended. It is
used in denunciation and in indication (whence its
name of index finger), while if it be slightly dropped
after the hand has been raised toward the shoulder,
it signifies affirmation, and if pointed as it were
face downwards toward the ground, it expresses
insistence. It is sometimes also used to indicate
number.
                    <milestone n="95" unit="section"/>
                    Again, if its top joint is lightly gripped on
either side, with the two outer fingers slightly
curved, the little finger rather less than the third,
we shall have a gesture well suited for argument.
But for this purpose the same gesture is rendered
more emphatic by holding the middle joint of the
finger and contracting the last two fingers still
further to match the lower position of the middle
finger and thumb.
                    <milestone n="96" unit="section"/>
                    The following gesture is admirably adapted to accompany modest language: the
thumb and the next three fingers are gently converged to a point and the hand is carried to the
neighbourhood of the month or chest, then relaxed
palm downwards and slightly advanced.
                    <milestone n="97" unit="section"/>
                    It was
with this gesture that I believe Demosthenes to
have commenced the timid and subdued exordium
of his speech in defence of Ctesiphon, and it was,
I think, in such a position that Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Arch.</hi>
                        i. 1.
                    </note>
                    held his
land, when he said,
                    <quote>If I have any talent, though I am conscious how little it is.</quote>
                    Slightly greater
freedom may be given to the gesture by pointing
the fingers down and drawing the hand in towards
the body and then opening it somewhat more rapidly
in the opposite direction, so that it seems as though
it were delivering our words to the audience.
                    <milestone n="98" unit="section"/>
                    <pb xml:id="p.297"/>
                    Sometimes we may hold the first two fingers apart without,
however, inserting the thumb between them, the
remaining two pointing inwards, while even the two
former must not be fully extended.
                    <milestone n="99" unit="section"/>
                    Sometimes,
again, the third and little finger may be pressed in to
the palm near the base of the thumb, which in its
turn is pressed against the middle joints of the first
and middle fingers; at others the little finger is
sometimes drooped obliquely, or the four fingers may
be relaxed rather than extended and the thumb
slanted inwards: this last gesture is well adapted to
pointing to one side or marking the different points
which we are making, the had being carried palmupwards to the left and swept back to the right
face-downwards.
                    <milestone n="100" unit="section"/>
                    The following short gestures are
also employed: the hand may be slightly hollowed
as it is when persons are making a vow, and then
moved slightly to and fro, the shoulders swaying
gently in unison: this is adapted to passages where
we speak with restraint and almost with timidity.
Wonder is best expressed as follows: the hand turns
slightly upwards and the fingers are brought in to
the palm, one after the other, beginning with the
little finger; the hand is then opened and turned
round by a reversal of this motion.
                    <milestone n="101" unit="section"/>
                    There are various
methods of expressing interrogation; but, as a rule,
we do so by a turn of the hand, the arrangement of
the fingers being indifferent. If the first finger
touch the middle of the right-hand edge of the
thumb-nail with its extremity, the other fingers
being relaxed, we shall have a graceful gesture well
suited to express approval or to accompany
                    <hi rend="italic">statements of facts,</hi>
                    and to mark the distinction between our
different points.
                    <milestone n="102" unit="section"/>
                    There is another gesture not unlike
                    <pb xml:id="p.299"/>
                    the preceding, in which the remaining three fingers
are folded: it is much employed by the Greeks both
for the left hand and the right, in rounding off their
                    <hi rend="italic">enthymemes,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Rhetorical or incomplete syllogisms. But see V. x. 2.
xiv. 1
                    </note>
                    detail by detail. A gentle movement of
the hand expresses promise or assent, a more violent
movement suggests exhortation or sometimes praise.
There is also that familiar gesture by which we drive
home our words, consisting in the rapid opening
and shutting of the hand: but this is a common
rather than an artistic gesture.
                    <milestone n="103" unit="section"/>
                    Again, there is the
somewhat unusual gesture in which the hand is
hollowed and raised well above the shoulder with a
motion suggestive of exhortation. The tremulous
motion now generally adopted by foreign schools is,
however, fit only for the stage. I do not know why
some persons disapprove of the movement of the
fingers, with their tops converging, towards the
mouth. For we do this when we are slightly surprised, and at times also employ it to express fear or
entreaty when we are seized with sudden indignation.
                    <milestone n="104" unit="section"/>
                    Further, we sometimes clench the hand and press
it to our breast when we are expressing regret or
anger, an occasion when it is not unbecoming even
to force the voice through the teeth in phrases such
as
                    <quote>What shall I do now?</quote>
                    <quote>What would you do?</quote>
                    To point at something with the thumb turned back
is a gesture which is in general just, but is not, in my
opinion, becoming to an orator.
                    <milestone n="105" unit="section"/>
                    Motion is generally
divided into six kinds, but circular motion must be
regarded as a seventh. The latter alone is faulty
when applied to gesture. The remaining motionsโ
that is, forward, to right or left and up or downโall
have their significance, but the gesture is never
directed to what lies behind us, though we do at
                    <pb xml:id="p.301"/>
                    times throw the hand back.
                    <milestone n="106" unit="section"/>
                    The best effect is produced by letting the motion of the hand start from
the left and end on the right, but this must be done
gently, the hand sinking to rest and avoiding all
appearance of giving a blow, although at the end of
a sentence it may sometimes be allowed to drop, but
must quickly be raised again: or it may occasionally,
when we desire to express wonder or dissent, spring
back with a rapid motion.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In this connexion the earlier instructors in the art
of gesture rightly added that the movement of the
hand should begin: and end with the thought that is
expressed. Otherwise the gesture will anticipate or
lag behind the voice, both of which produce an
unpleasing effect.
                    <milestone n="107" unit="section"/>
                    Some, through excess of subtlety,
have erroneously prescribed that there should be an
interval of three words between each movement;
but this rule is never observed, nor can it be. These
persons, however, were desirous that there should be
some standard of speed or slowness (a most rational
desire), with a view to avoid prolonged inactivity on
the part of the hands as well as the opposite fault,
into which so many fall, of breaking up the natural
flow of their delivery by continual motion.
                    <milestone n="108" unit="section"/>
                    There is
another still more common error, which is less easy
of detection. Language possesses certain imperceptible stresses, indeed we might almost call them
feet, to which the gesture of most speakers conforms.
Thus there will he one movement at
                    <hi rend="italic">novum crimen,</hi>
                    another at
                    <hi rend="italic">Giai Caesar,</hi>
                    a third at
                    <hi rend="italic">et ante diem,</hi>
                    a fourth at
                    <hi rend="italic">non auditum,</hi>
                    a fifth at
                    <hi rend="italic">propinquus meus,</hi>
                    a
sixth at
                    <hi rend="italic">ad te</hi>
                    and others at
                    <hi rend="italic">Quintus Tubero</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">detulit.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Lig.</hi>
                        i. 1.
                        <quote>
                            It is a new charge, Gaius Caesar, a
chartgo hitherto, unheard of, that my kinsman, Quintus Tubero,
has brought to your notice.
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="109" unit="section"/>
                    From this springs a further error, namely,
that young men, when writing out their speeches,
                    <pb xml:id="p.303"/>
                    devise all their gestures in advance and consider as
they compose how the hand is to fall at each
particular point. A further unfortunate result is
that the movement of the hand, which should end
on the right, frequently finishes on the left.
                    <milestone n="110" unit="section"/>
                    It is
therefore better, in view of the fact that all speech
falls into a number of brief clauses, at the end of
which we can take breath, if necessary, to arrange
our gesture to suit these sections. For example, the
words
                    <hi rend="italic">novum crimes, Gai Caesar,</hi>
                    in a sense form a
phrase complete in itself, since they are followed by
a conjunction, while the next words,
                    <hi rend="italic">et ante hanc diem non auditum,</hi>
                    are also sufficiently self-contained. To
these phrases the motions of the hand must be conformed, before the speech has passed beyond the
calmness of tone on which it opens.
                    <milestone n="111" unit="section"/>
                    But when increasing warmth of feeling has fired the orator, the
gesture will become more frequent, in keeping with
the impetus of the speech. Some places are best
suited by a rapid, and others by a restrained delivery.
In the one case we pass rapidly on, fire a volley of
arguments and hurry upon our way; in the other, we
drive home our points, force them on the hearer and
implant them in his mind. But the slower the
delivery, the greater its emotional power: thus,
Rosins was rapid and ESOPs weighty in his delivery,
because the former was a comic and the latter a
tragic actor.
                    <milestone n="112" unit="section"/>
                    The same rule applies to the movemints. Consequently on the stage young men and
old, soldiers and married women all walk sedately,
while slaves, maidservants, parasites and fishermen
are more lively in their movements. But instructors
in the art of gesture will not permit the hand to be
raised above the level of the eyes or lowered beneath
                    <pb xml:id="p.305"/>
                    that of the breast; since it is thought a grave blemish
to lift it to the top of the head
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The general sense is clear, though the text is unsetsfactory and scarcely translatable.
                    </note>
                    or lower it to the lower
portions of the belly.
                    <milestone n="113" unit="section"/>
                    It may be moved to the left
within the limits of the shoulder, but no further
without loss of decorum. On the other hand, when,
to express our aversion, we thrust our hand out to
the left, the left shoulder must be brought forward
in unison with the head, which will incline to the
right.
                    <milestone n="114" unit="section"/>
                    It is never correct to employ the left hand
alone in gesture, though it will often conform its
motion to that of the right, as, for example, when
we are counting our arguments on the fingers, or
turn the palms of the hands to the left to express
our horror of something,
                    <milestone n="115" unit="section"/>
                    or thrust them out in front
or spread them out to right and left, or lower them in
apology or supplication (though the gesture is not
the same in these two cases), or raise them in adoration, or stretch them out in demonstration or invocation, as in the passage,
                    <quote>
                        Ye hills and groves of Alba,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                            xxxi. 85.
                        </note>
                    </quote>
                    or in the passage from Gracchus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See
                        <hi rend="italic">Cic.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        III. lvi. 214.
                    </note>
                    :
                    <quote>
                        Whither, alas!
shall I turn me? To the Capitol? Nay, it is wet
with my brother's blood. To my home?
                    </quote>
                    etc.
                    <milestone n="116" unit="section"/>
                    For
in such passages greater emotional effect is produced if both hands co-operate, short gestures being
best adapted to matters of small importance and
themes of a gentle or melancholy character, and
longer gestures to subjects of importance or themes
calling for joy or horror.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="117" unit="section"/>
                    It is desirable also that I should mention the faults
in the use of the hands, into which even experienced
pleaders are liable to fall. As for the gesture of
demanding a cup, threatening a flogging, or indicating
the number 500 by crooking the thumb,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Le.</hi>
                        crooking the thumb against the forefinger to
represent the symbol D.
                    </note>
                    all of which
are recorded by writers on the subject, I have never
                    <pb xml:id="p.307"/>
                    seen them employed even by uneducated rustics.
                    <milestone n="118" unit="section"/>
                    But I know that it is of frequent occurrence for a
speaker to expose his side by stretching his arm too
far, to be afraid in one case of extending his hand
beyond the folds of his cloak, and in another to
stretch it as far as it will go, to raise it to the roof,
or by swinging it repeatedly over his left shoulder to
deliver such a rain of blows to the rear that it is
scarcely safe to stand behind him, or to make a circular
sweep to the left, or by casting out his hand at
random to strike the standers-by or to flap both
elbows against his sides.
                    <milestone n="119" unit="section"/>
                    There are others, again,
whose hands are sluggish or tremulous or inclined to
saw the air; sometimes, too, the fingers are crooked
and brought down with a run from the top of the
head, or tossed up into the air with the hand turned
palm upwards. There is also a gesture, which consists in inclining the head to the right shoulder,
stretching out the arm from the ear and extending
the hand with the thumb turned down. This is a
special favourite with those who boast that they
speak
                    <quote>with uplifted hand.</quote>
                    <milestone n="120" unit="section"/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>
                        with exaggerated violence. See II. xii. 9.
                    </note>
                    To these latter we may
add those speakers who hurl quivering epigrams
with their fingers or denounce with the hand upraised, or rise on tiptoe, whenever they say something
of which they are specially proud. This last proceeding may at times be adopted by itself; but they
convert it into a blemish by simultaneously raising
one or even two fingers as high as they can reach, or
heaving up both hands as if they were carrying something.
                    <milestone n="121" unit="section"/>
                    In addition to these faults, there are those
which spring not from nature, but from nervousness,
such as struggling desperately with our lips when
they refuse to open, making inarticulate sounds, as
                    <pb xml:id="p.309"/>
                    though something were sticking in our throat, when
our memory fails us, or our thoughts will not come
at our call; rubbing the end of our nose, walking up
and down in the midst of an unfinished sentence,
stopping suddenly and courting applause by silence,
with many other tricks which it would take too long
to detail, since everybody has his own particular
faults.
                    <milestone n="122" unit="section"/>
                    We must take care not to protrude the chest
or stomach, since such an altitude arches the back,
and all bending backwards is unsightly. The flanks
must conform to the gesture; for the motion of the
entire body contributes to the effect: indeed, Cicero
holds that the body is more expressive than even the
hands. For in the
                    <hi rend="italic">de Orator</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">xviii. 59.</note>
                    he says,
                    <quote>
                        There must
be no quick movements of the fingers, no marking
time with the finger-tips, but the orator should
control himself by the poise of the whole trunk and
by a manly inclination of the side.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="123" unit="section"/>
                    Slapping the
thigh, which Clean is said to have been the first to
introduce at Athens, is in general use and is becoming
as a mark of indignation, while it also excites the
audience. Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lax. 278.
                    </note>
                    regrets its absence in Calidius,
                    <quote>There was no striking of the forehead,</quote>
                    he complains,
                    <quote>nor of the thigh.</quote>
                    With regard to the
forehead I must beg leave to differ from him: for it
is a purely theatrical trick even to clap the hands or
beat the breast.
                    <milestone n="124" unit="section"/>
                    it is only on rare occasions, too,
that it is becoming to touch the breast with the
finger-tips of the hollowed hand, when, for example,
we address ourselves or speak words of exhortation,
reproach or commiseration. But if ever we do employ
this gesture, it will not be unbecoming to pull back
the toga at the same time. As regards the feet, we
need to be careful about our gait and the attitudes
                    <pb xml:id="p.311"/>
                    in which we stand. To stand with the right foot
advanced or to thrust forward the same foot and
hand are alike unsightly.
                    <milestone n="125" unit="section"/>
                    At times we may rest our
weight on the right foot, but without any corresponding inclination of the chest, while, in any case,
the gesture is better suited to the comic actor than to
the orator. It is also a mistake, when resting on the
left foot, to lift the right or poise it on tiptoe. To
straddle the feet is ugly if we are standing still, and
almost indecent if we are actually moving. To start
forward may be effective, provided that we move but
a short distance and do so but rarely and without
violence.
                    <milestone n="126" unit="section"/>
                    It will also at times be found convenient
to walk to and fro, owing to the extravagant pauses
imposed by the plaudits of the audience; Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Orat.</hi>
                        xviii. 59.
                    </note>
                    however, says that this should be done only on rare
occasions, and that we should take not more than a
few steps. On the other hand, to run up and down,
which, in the ease of Manlius Sure,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See VI. iii. 54.</note>
                    Domitius Afer
called overdoing it, is sheer folly, and there was no
little wit in the question put by Virginias Flatus to
a rival professor, when he asked how many miles he
had declaimed.
                    <milestone n="127" unit="section"/>
                    I know, too, that some authorities
warn us not to walk with our backs turned to the
judges, but to move diagonally and keep our eyes
fixed on the panel. This cannot be done in private
trials, but in such cases the space available is small
and the time during which our backs are turned is of
the briefest.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The normal arrangement was for the president of the
court and judges to sit on a
                        <hi rend="italic">tribunal</hi>
                        or dais. The advocates
and parties to the suit were on the ground in front. When
pleading before a large jury the orator could walk diagonally,
half-facing the jury, without at any rate turning his back on
too many at a time. When, however, there was but a single
judge, as in a private trial, the feat would he more difficult,
But apparently the court took up less room in such cases,
and the orator's peregrinations would be but small. See
ยง 134 note.
                    </note>
                    On the other hand, we are permitted
at times to walk backwards gradually. Some even
jump backwards, which is merely ludicrous.
                    <milestone n="128" unit="section"/>
                    Stamping the foot is, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        iii. lix. 220.
                    </note>
                    says, effective when done
on suitable occasions, that is to say, at the commence
meant or close of a lively argument, but if it be
                    <pb xml:id="p.313"/>
                    frequently indulged in, it brands the speaker as a
fool and ceases to attract the attention of the judge.
There is also the unsightly habit of swaying to right
and left, and shifting the weight from one foot to
the other. Above all, we must avoid effeminate
movements, such as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lxii.
                    </note>
                    ascribes to Titus, a circumstance which led to a certain kind of dance being
nicknamed Titus.
                    <milestone n="129" unit="section"/>
                    Another reprehensible practice
is that of nodding frequently and rapidly to either
side, a mannerism for which the elder Curio
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        Cic.
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lx.
                    </note>
                    was derided by Julius, who asked who it was who was speaking in a boat, while on another occasion, when Curio
had been tossing himself about in his usual manner,
while Octaves, his colleague, was sitting beside him
bandaged and reeking with medicaments on account
of ill-health, Spiciness remarked,
                    <quote>
                        Octaves, you can
never be sufficiently grateful to your colleague: for
if he wasn't there, the flies would have devoured you
this very day where you sit.
                        <milestone n="130" unit="section"/>
                    </quote>
                    The shoulders also
are apt to be jerked to and fro, a fault of which
Demosthenes is said to have cured himself by
speaking on a narrow platform with a spear hanging
immediately above his shoulder, in order that, if in
the heat of his eloquence he failed to avoid this
fault, he might have his attention called to the
fact by a prick from the spear. The only condition
that justifies our walking about while speaking is
if we are pleading in a public trial before a large
number of judges and desire specially to impress our
arguments upon them individually.
                    <milestone n="131" unit="section"/>
                    The practice
adopted by some of throwing the toga back over the
shoulder, while they draw up the fold to their waist
with the right hand, and use the left for gesticulation
as they walk up and down and discourse, is not to
                    <pb xml:id="p.315"/>
                    be tolerated; for even to draw back the left hand
while extending the right is an objectionable habit.
This reminds me of an extremely foolish trick, which
I think I ought to mention, that some speakers have
of employing the intervals when the audience are
applauding by whispering in someone's ear or jesting
with their friends or looking back at their clerks, as
if telling them to make a note of some gratuity to
be dispensed to their supporters.
                    <milestone n="132" unit="section"/>
                    On the other
hand, when we are making some explanation to the
judge, more especially if the point be somewhat
obscure, a slight inclination in his direction will be
not unbecoming. But to lean forward towards the
advocate seated on the benches of our opponent is
offensive, while, unless we are genuinely fatigued, it
is a piece of affectation to lean back among our own
friends and to be supported in their arms; the same
remark also applies to the practice of being prompted
aloud or reading from manuscript as though uncertain of our memory.
                    <milestone n="133" unit="section"/>
                    For all these mannerisms impair the force of our speaking, chill the
effect of emotional appeals and make the judge
think that he is not being treated with sufficient
respect. To cross over to the seats of our opponents
borders on impudence, and Cassius Severus showed
a neat turn of wit when he demanded that a barrier
might be erected between himself and an opponent
who behaved in this fashion. Moreover, though to
advance towards our opponent may at times produce
an impression of passionate energy, the return to
our former position will always prove correspondingly
tame.
                    <milestone n="134" unit="section"/>
                    Many of the rules which I have given will
require modification by those who have to plead
before judges seated on a dais.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Astonish (in a note on the
                        <hi rend="italic">Divination</hi>
                        of Cicero) explains
that in minor cases tried by
                        <hi rend="italic">tribuni, triumviri, quaestores</hi>
                        and other minor officils, the judges sat on ordinary benches,
not on a raised
                        <hi rend="italic">tribuat.</hi>
                    </note>
                    For in such
                    <pb xml:id="p.317"/>
                    cases the face must be raised somewhat higher, so
that the speaker's eyes may be fixed on the president
of the court: for the same reason his gestures must
also be carried a little higher, while there are other
details which will readily occur to my reader without
any mention from me. Similar modifications will
be likewise necessary for those who plead sitting.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        XI. i. 44, which shows that the cases in question are
those submitted to arbitration.
                    </note>
                    For this is done, as a rule, only in cases of minor
importance, where delivery will necessarily be more
restrained, and certain defects are inevitable.
                    <milestone n="135" unit="section"/>
                    For
example, when the speaker sits on the left side of the
judge, he will have to advance his right foot, while
if he be seated on the right, many of his gestures
must be made from right to left, in order that they
may be addressed to the judge. Personally, I note
that many speakers start up at the conclusion of
individual periods, while some proceed to walk to
and fro for a little: it is for them to decide whether
this is becoming or not: I will merely remark that,
when they do this, they are not pleading seated.
                    <milestone n="136" unit="section"/>
                    It was a common custom, which has not entirely
disappeared, to drink or even to eat while pleading;
but I shall not permit my ideal orator to do anything
of the kind. For if a man cannot endure the
burdens imposed by oratory without having recourse
to such remedies, he should not find it a serious
hardship to give up pleading altogether, a course
which is far preferable to acknowledging his contempt
both for his profession and his audience.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="137" unit="section"/>
                    With regard to dress, there is no special garb
peculiar to the orator, but his dress comes more
under the public eye than that of other men. It
should, therefore, be distinguished and manly, as,
indeed, it ought to be with all men of position. For
                    <pb xml:id="p.319"/>
                    excessive care with regard to the cut of the toga,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In putting on the toga, it was thrown first over the left
shoulder, so that about 6 feet hung in front and about 12
behind. This longer portion was then carried round under
the right arm and then diagonally across the chest (like a
                        <hi rend="italic">balleus,</hi>
                        or belt) and over the left shoulder again. A fold of
this portion hanging in front formed the
                        <hi rend="italic">sinus.</hi>
                        The original
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        feet hanging in front from the left shoulder now hung
below the rest. A portion was pulled up from above and
Allowed to hang over the edge of that portion of the toga
which Quintilian compares to a
                        <hi rend="italic">balleus.</hi>
                        This was known
as the
                        <hi rend="italic">umbo,</hi>
                        and is described by Quintilian as
                        <hi rend="italic">pars quae ultima imponitur.</hi>
                        He recommends that a considerable
portion should be thus pulled up and allowed to hang fairly
low in front over the edge of the
                        <hi rend="italic">balteus,</hi>
                        that the weight
of the hanging portion might balance the remainder of the
original 6 feet of toga hanging from the left shoulder, keep
it in place and prevent it from slipping lack into its original
position. The toga was very nearly semicircular in shape,
which explains Quintilian's statement that it should be
round. For further details see
                        <hi rend="italic">Companion to Latin Studies,</hi>
                        Camb. Univ. Press, p. 191.
                    </note>
                    the style of the shoes, or the arrangement of the
hair, is just as reprehensible as excessive carelessness. There are also details of dress which are
altered to some extent by successive changes in
fashion. The ancients, for example, wore no folds,
and their successors wore them very short.
                    <milestone n="138" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently it follows that in view of the fact that their
arms were, like those of the Greeks, covered by the
garment, they must have employed a different form of
gesture in the exordium from that which is now in
use. However, I am speaking of our own day. The
speaker who has not the right to wear the broad
stripe,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Worn by senators.</note>
                    will wear his girdle in such a way that the
front edges of the tunic fall a little below his knees,
while the edges in rear reach to the middle of his
hams. For only women draw them lower and only
centurions higher.
                    <milestone n="139" unit="section"/>
                    If we wear the purple stripe, it
requires but little care to see that it fills becomingly;
negligence in this respect sometimes excites criticism. Among those who wear the broad stripe, it is
the fashion to let it hang somewhat lower than in
garments that are retained by the girdle. The toga
itself should, in my opinion, be round, and cut to
fit, otherwise there are a number of ways in which it
may be unshapely. Its front edge should by preference reach to the middle of the shin, while tie back
should be higher in proposition as the girdle is higher
                    <pb xml:id="p.321"/>
                    behind than in front.
                    <milestone n="140" unit="section"/>
                    The fold is most becoming,
if it fall to a point a little above the lower edge of
the tunic, and should certainly never fall below it.
The other fold which passes obliquely like a belt
under the right shoulder and over the left, should
neither be too tight nor too loose. The portion of
the toga which is last to be arranged should fall
rather low, since it will sit better thus and be
kept in its place. A portion of the tunic also should
be drawn back in order that it may not fall over the
arm when we are pleading, and the fold should be
thrown over the shoulder, while it will not be
unbecoming if the edge be turned back.
                    <milestone n="141" unit="section"/>
                    On the
other hand, we should not cover the shoulder and
the whole of the throat, otherwise our dress will be
unduly narrowed and will lose the impressive effect
produced by breadth at the chest. Tire left arm
should only be raised so far as to form a right angle
at the elbow, while the edge of the toga should fall
in equal lengths on either side.
                    <milestone n="142" unit="section"/>
                    The hand should
not be overloaded with rings, which should under no
circumstances encroach upon the middle joint of
the finger. The most becoming attitude for the
hand is produced by raising the thumb and slightly
curving the fingers, unless it is occupied with holding manuscript. But we should not go out of our
way to carry the latter, for it suggests an acknowledgement that we do not trust our memory, and is
a hindrance to a number of gestures.
                    <milestone n="143" unit="section"/>
                    The ancients
used to let the toga fall to the heels, as the Greeks
are in the habit of doing with the cloak: Plotius
and Nigidius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Plotins Gallus, a rhetorician, and Nigidius Figulus, an
encyclopaedic writer, both contemporaries of Cicero.
                    </note>
                    both recommend this in the books
which they wrote about gesture as practised in
their own day. I am consequently all the more
                    <pb xml:id="p.323"/>
                    surprised at the view expressed by so learned a
man as Plinius Secundus, especially since it occurs
in a book which carries minute research almost to
excess:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This work of the elder Pliny was called
                        <hi rend="italic">Studiusus.</hi>
                    </note>
                    for he asserts that Cicero was in the
habit of wearing his toga in such a fashion to conceal his varicose veins, despite the fact that this
fashion is to be seen in the statues of persons who
lived after Cicero's day.
                    <milestone n="144" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the short cloak,
bandages used to protect the legs, mufflers and
coverings for the ears, nothing short of ill-health
can excuse their use.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But such attention to our dress is only possible at
the beginning of a speech, since, as the pleading
develops, in fact, almost from the beginning of the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of facts,</hi>
                    the fold will slip down from the
shoulder quite naturally and as it were of its own
accord, while when we come to arguments and
commonplaces, it will be found convenient to throw
back the toga from the left shoulder, and even to
throw down the fold if it should stick.
                    <milestone n="145" unit="section"/>
                    The left
hand may be employed to pluck the toga from the
throat and the upper portion of the chest, for by
now the whole body will be hot. And just as at
this point the voice becomes more vehement and
more varied in its utterance, so the clothing begins
to assume something of a combative pose.
                    <milestone n="146" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, although to wrap the toga round the left
hand or to pull it about us as a girdle would be
almost a symptom of madness, while to throw back
the fold from its bottom over the right shoulder
would be a foppish and effeminate gesture, and
there are yet worse effects than these, there is, at
any rate, no reason why we should not place the
looser portions of the fold under the left arm, since
                    <pb xml:id="p.325"/>
                    it gives an air of vigour and freedom not ill-suited
to the warmth and energy of our action.
                    <milestone n="147" unit="section"/>
                    When,
however, our speech draws near its close, more
especially if fortune shows herself kind, practically
everything is becoming; we may stream with sweat,
show signs of fatigue, and let our dress fall in careless disorder and the toga slip loose from us on
every side.
                    <milestone n="148" unit="section"/>
                    This fact makes me all the more surprised that Pliny should think it worth while to
enjoin the orator to dry his brow with a handkerchief in such a way as not to disorder the hair,
although a little later he most properly, and with a
certain gravity and sternness of language, forbids
us to rearrange it. For my own part, I feel that
dishevelled locks make an additional appeal to the
emotions, and that neglect of such precautions
creates a pleasing impression.
                    <milestone n="149" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand,
if the toga falls down at the beginning of our
speech, or when we have only proceeded but a little
way, the failure to replace it is a sign of indifference,
or sloth, or sheer ignorance of the way in which
clothes should be worn.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The above are the chief adornments and faults
of delivery. But there are a number of further
considerations which the orator must bear in mind.
                    <milestone n="150" unit="section"/>
                    In the first place there is the question as to the
character of speaker, judges and audience. For
just as the methods of speaking may justifiably be
varied to suit the characteristics of different orators
and different judges, so it is with delivery. The
same characteristics of voice, gesture and gait are
not equally becoming in the presence of the
emperor, the senate, the people, and magistrates,
or in private and public trials, or in making a
                    <pb xml:id="p.327"/>
                    request to the praetor for the appointment of a judge
to hear our case, and in actual pleading. Anyone
who will reflect upon the matter will realise the
nature of the differences involved, as he will also be
able to realise the nature of the subject on which
he is speaking and the effect which he desires to
produce.
                    <milestone n="151" unit="section"/>
                    The considerations with regard to the
subject are four in number, of which the first has
reference to the case as a whole. For the case may
be of a gloomy or a cheerful nature, an anxious
business, or one that calls for no alarm, and may
involve issues of great or trivial importance. We
ought, therefore, never to be so preoccupied over
particular portions of a case as to forget to consider
the case as a whole.
                    <milestone n="152" unit="section"/>
                    The second point is concerned
with the different aspects of the various portions of
the speech, that is, the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium, statement of facts, arguments</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">peroration.</hi>
                    The third concerns the
thoughts, which will vary according to the subject
matter and the emotions which we require to
awaken. The fourth has reference to the words,
which must be given appropriate expression, unless
their force is to be entirely wasted, although it is an
error to attempt to make our delivery reproduce the
sense of every single word.
                    <milestone n="153" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, in panegyric, funeral orations excepted, in returning thanks,
exhortations and the like, the delivery must be
luxuriant, magnificent, and grand. On the other
hand, in funeral or consolatory speeches, together
with most of those in defence of accused persons,
the delivery will be melancholy and subdued.
When we speak in the senate, it will be authoritative, when we address the people, dignified, and
when we are pleading in private cases, restrained.
                    <pb xml:id="p.329"/>
                    As regards the respective portions of speeches,
thoughts and words, I must speak at somewhat
greater length, as the problems involved are manifold.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="154" unit="section"/>
                    There are three qualities which delivery should
possess. It should be conciliatory, persuasive and
moving, and the possession of these three qualities
involves charm as a further requisite. A conciliatory
effect may be secured either by charm of style or
by producing an impression of excellence of character,
which is in some mysterious way clearly revealed
both by voice and gesture. A persuasive effect, on
the other hand, is produced by the power of assertion,
which is sometimes more convincing even than actual
proof.
                    <milestone n="155" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Would those statements,</quote>
                    says Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        lxxx. 278.
                    </note>
                    to
Calidius,
                    <quote>have been delivered by you in such a manner if they had been true?</quote>
                    And again,
                    <quote>
                        You
were far from kindling our emotions. Indeed, at
that point of your speech we could scarcely keep
ourselves awake.
                    </quote>
                    We must therefore reveal both
confidence and firmness, above all, if we have the
requisite authority to back them.
                    <milestone n="156" unit="section"/>
                    The method of
arousing the emotions depends on our power to
represent or imitate the passions. Therefore when
the judge in private, or the usher in public cases,
calls upon us to speak, we must rise with deliberation.
We shall then, to make our garb the more becoming,
and to secure a moment for reflexion, devote a brief
space to the arrangement of our toga or even, if
necessary, to throwing it on afresh; but it must
be borne in mind that this injunction applies only
to cases in the courts; for
                    <hi rend="italic">we</hi>
                    must not do this if
we are speaking before the emperor or a magistrate,
or in cases where the judge sits in a position of
superior authority.
                    <milestone n="157" unit="section"/>
                    Even when we turn to the judge,
                    <pb xml:id="p.331"/>
                    and have requested and received the praetor's permission to address the court, we must not break forth
at once into speech, but should allow ourselves a few
moments for reflexion. For the display of such care
on the part of one who is about to speak attracts the
audience and gives the judge time to settle down.
                    <milestone n="158" unit="section"/>
                    Homer
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        iii. 217.
                    </note>
                    inculcates this practice by placing before
us the example of Ulysses, whom he describes as
having stood for a while with eyes fixed on the
ground and staff held motionless, before he poured
forth his whirlwind of eloquence. In this preliminary
delay there are certain pauses, as the actors call
them, which are not unbecoming. We may stroke
our head, look at our hand, wring the fingers, pretend to summon all our energies for the effort,
confess to nervousness by a deep sigh, or may adopt
any other method suited to our individual character,
while these proceedings may be extended over some
time, if we find that the judge is not yet giving us
his attention.
                    <milestone n="159" unit="section"/>
                    Our attitude should be upright, our
feet level and a slight distance apart, or the left may
be very slightly advanced. The knees should be
upright, but not stiff; the shoulders relaxed, the face
stern, but not sad, expressionless or languid: the
arms should be held slightly away from the side,
the left hand being in the position described above,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Sect. 142.</note>
                    while the right, at the moment when our speech
begins, should be slightly extended beyond the fold
of the toga with the most modest of gestures, as
though waiting for the commencement.
                    <milestone n="160" unit="section"/>
                    For it is
a mistake to look at the ceiling, to rub the face and
give it a flush of impudence, to crane it boldly forward, to frown in order to secure a fierce expression,
or brush back the hair from the forehead against its
                    <pb xml:id="p.333"/>
                    natural direction in order to produce a terrifying
effect by making it stand on end. Again, there are
other unseemly tricks, such as that so dear to the
Greeks of twitching our fingers and lips as though
studying what to say, clearing the throat with a
loud noise, thrusting out one foot to a considerable
distance, grasping a portion of the toga in the left
hand, standing with feet wide apart, holding ourselves
stiffly, leaning backwards, stooping, or bunching our
shoulders toward the back of the head, as wrestlers
do when about to engage.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="161" unit="section"/>
                    A gentle delivery is most often best suited to the
                    <hi rend="italic">exordium.</hi>
                    For there is nothing better calculated
than modesty to win the good-will of the judge,
although there are exceptions to the rule, since, as I
have already pointed out,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IV. i. 40.</note>
                    all
                    <hi rend="italic">exordia</hi>
                    are not delivered
in the same manner. But, generally speaking, a
quiet voice, a modest gesture, a toga sitting well
upon the shoulder, and a gentle motion of the sides
to right and left, accompanied by a corresponding
movement of the eyes, will all be found to produce
a becoming effect.
                    <milestone n="162" unit="section"/>
                    In the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of facts</hi>
                    the hand
should on most occasions be further extended, the
toga allowed to slip back, the gestures sharply distinguished and the voice colloquial, but slightly more
emphatic, while there should also be uniformity of
tone. Such, at any rate, should be the delivery of
a passage such as the following:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        pro Lig.
                        <hi rend="italic">i.</hi>
                        2.
                    </note>
                    <quote>For Quintus Ligarius, since there was no hint of the likelihood of the war in Africa,</quote>
                    or
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Cluenet.</hi>
                        v. 11.
                    </note>
                    <quote>Aulus Cluentius Habitus, this man's father.</quote>
                    But different methods may be
called for in this same portion of the speech, in
passionate utterances such as,
                    <quote>The mother-in-law weds her son-in-law,</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Cluent. v.</hi>
                        14.
                    </note>
                    or in pathetic passages such
                    <pb xml:id="p.335"/>
                    as,
                    <quote>
                        There in the market-place of Laodicea was displayed a grievous and afflicting spectacle for all the
province of Asia to behold.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="163" unit="section"/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Verr.</hi>
                        xxx. 76
                    </note>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italic">proofs,</hi>
                    however,
require the utmost variety of delivery. For to state
them and distinguish between their various points,
and to examine witnesses, we employ something not
far removed from a colloquial tone, as is also the case
in anticipating objections, which is really another
form of statement. But in all these cases we sometimes deride, and sometimes mimic our opponents.
                    <milestone n="164" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">Argument,</hi>
                    being as a rule of a livelier, more energetic
and aggressive character, demands a type of gesture
adapted to its style, that is to say, it should be bold
and rapid. There are certain portions of our arguments that require to be pressed home with energy,
and in these our style must be compact and concentrated.
                    <hi rend="italic">Digressions,</hi>
                    as a rule, are characterised by
gentleness, calm and placidity, as, for example, in
Cicero's description of the Rape of Proserpine,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        IV. iii. 13.
                    </note>
                    his
picture of Sicily,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        IV. iii. 13.
                    </note>
                    or his panegyric of Pompey.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In the lost
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Cornelio: cp.</hi>
                        IV. iii. 13.
                    </note>
                    For
naturally passages which deal with subjects lying
outside the main question in dispute demand a less
combative tone.
                    <milestone n="165" unit="section"/>
                    There are occasions on which we
may adopt a gentle manner in depreciating our
opponents by giving a picture of their character, as
in the following passage:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        From the lost
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Galio.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        I seemed to see some
persons entering the room and others leaving it,
while others were staggering to and fro under the
influence of wine.
                    </quote>
                    Under such circumstances we
may even allow the gesture to match the voice, and
may employ a gentle movement from side to side:
but this motion should be confined to the hands, and
there should be no movement of the flanks.
                    <milestone n="166" unit="section"/>
                    There
are a number of gradations of tone which may be
                    <pb xml:id="p.337"/>
                    employed to kindle the feeling of the judges. The
most vehement tones that an orator is ever called
upon to use will be employed in passages such as
the following:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Liq.</hi>
                        iii. 7 and 6.
                    </note>
                    <quote>When the war was begun, Caesar, and was, in fact, well on its way to a conclusion.</quote>
                    For he has just said:
                    <quote>I will use my voice to its fullest power, that all the Roman people may hear me.</quote>
                    On the other hand, a lower tone, not devoid
of a certain charm, should be employed in passages
such as:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Liq.</hi>
                        iii. 9.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        What was that sword of yours doing,
'Tubero, that sword that was drawn on the field of
Pharsalus?
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="167" unit="section"/>
                    But the utterance must be fuller,
slower, and consequently sweeter, when the orator
says,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Phil.</hi>
                        ii. xxv. 63.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        But in an assembly of the Homan people,
and when he was performing his official functions.
                    </quote>
                    In this passage every sound should e drawn out,
we should dwell upon the vowel-sounds and speak
fill-throated. Still fuller should be the stream of our
voice in the invocation,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        xxxi. 85.
                    </note>
                    <quote>You, hills and groves of Alba</quote>
                    ; while a tone not far removed from chanting,
and dying away to a cadence, should be employed in
delivering the phrase,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Arch.</hi>
                        viii. 19.
                    </note>
                    <quote>Rocks and solitudes answer to the voice.</quote>
                    <milestone n="168" unit="section"/>
                    These are the modulations denounced
by Demosthenes
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Cor. 90.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and Aeschines,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">In Ctes.</hi>
                        72.
                    </note>
                    but they do not
necessarily for that reason merit our disapprobation.
For as each of these orators taunts the other with
making use of them, it is clear that they were employed
by both. We may be sure that Demosthenes did not
restrict himself to his ordinary simplicity of tone when
he swore by those that fought for their country at
Marathon, Plataea and Salamis,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Cor.</hi>
                        60.
                    </note>
                    nor did Aeschines
employ a colloquial utterance when he lamented for
the fate of Thebes.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">In Ctes.</hi>
                        49.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="169" unit="section"/>
                    There is also an entirely different
tone, which might be described as lying almost
                    <pb xml:id="p.339"/>
                    outside the range of the instrument. The Greeks
call it bitterness, and it consists in an extravagant
acerbity almost beyond the compass of the human
voice. It is employed in passages such as,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Rab. perd.</hi>
                        vi. 18.
                    </note>
                    <quote>
                        Why
do you not restrain those cries, the proof of your
folly and the evidence of your small numbers?
                    </quote>
                    But the extravagance of which I spoke will come
in at the opening, where the orator cries,
                    <quote>Why do you not restrain?</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="170" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <hi rend="italic">peroration,</hi>
                    if it involves a recapitulation,
requires an even utterance of short, clear-cut
clauses. If, on the other hand, it is designed to
stir the emotions of the judges, it will demand
some of the qualities already mentioned. If it aims
at soothing them, it should How softly; if it is to
rouse them to pity, the voice must be delicately
modulated to a melancholy sweetness, which is at
once most natural and specially adapted to touch
the heart. For it may be noted that even orphans
and widows have a certain musical quality in the
lamentations which they utter at funerals.
                    <milestone n="171" unit="section"/>
                    A
muffled voice, such as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brutt.</hi>
                        xxxviii. 141.
                    </note>
                    says was possessed
by Antonius, will also be exceedingly effective under
such circumstances, since it has just the natural
tone which we seek to imitate. Appeals to pity
are, however, of two kinds: they may be marked
by an admixture of indignation, as in the passage
just quoted
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">ยง 162.</note>
                    describing the condemnation of Philodamus, or they may be coupled with appeals for
mercy, in which case their tone will be more subdued.
                    <milestone n="172" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore although there is a suggestion of
the chanting tone in the delivery of such passages
as
                    <quote>In an assembly of the Roman people</quote>
                    (for he did
not utter these words in a contentious tone), or in
                    <pb xml:id="p.341"/>
                    <quote>Ye hills and groves of Alba</quote>
                    (for he did not say this
as though he were appealing to them or calling them
to witness), the ensuing phrases
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        xxxvii. 102.
                    </note>
                    require infinitely
greater modulation and longer-drawn harmonies:
                    <quote>Ah, woe is me, unhappy that I am!</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>What shall I reply to my children?</quote>
                    and
                    <quote>
                        You, Milo, had
the power to recall me to my country with the aid of
these men, and shall I be powerless by their aid to
keep you in that same country, your native land
and mine?
                    </quote>
                    or when he offers to sell the property of
Gaius Rabirius at one sesterce,
                    <quote>Ah, what a sad and bitter task my voice is called on to perform!</quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Rab. Post,</hi>
                        xvii. 46.
                        <hi rend="italic">addicit,</hi>
                        lit.
                        <quote>knocks down</quote>
                        :
                        <hi rend="italic">praeconium,</hi>
                        lit.
                        <quote>the task of the public crier.</quote>
                    </note>
                    Again,
                    <milestone n="173" unit="section"/>
                    it is a most effective device to confess in the peroration
that the strain of grief and fatigue is overpowering,
and that our strength is sinking beneath them, as
Cicero does in his defence of Milo:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Mil.</hi>
                        xxxviii. 105.
                    </note>
                    <quote>But here I must make an end: I can no longer speak for tears.</quote>
                    And
in such passages our delivery must conform to our
words.
                    <milestone n="174" unit="section"/>
                    It may be thought that there are other points
which should be mentioned in connexion with the
duties of the orator in this portion of his speech, such
as calling forward the accused, lifting up his children
for the court to see, producing his kinsfolk, and
rending his garments; but they have been dealt
with in their proper place.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">VI. i. 30.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Such being the variety entailed by the different
portions of our pleading, it is sufficiently clear that
our delivery must be adapted to our matter, as I
have already shown, and sometimes also, though
not always conform to our actual words, as I have
just remarked.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">ยง 173.</note>
                    <milestone n="175" unit="section"/>
                    For instance, must not the words,
                    <quote>This poor wretched, poverty-stricken man,</quote>
                    be
uttered in a low, subdued tone, whereas,
                    <quote>A hold and violent fellow and a robber,</quote>
                    is a phrase
                    <pb xml:id="p.343"/>
                    requiring a strong and energetic utterance? For
such conformity gives a force and appropriateness
to our matter, and without it the expression of
the voice will be out of harmony with our thought.
                    <milestone n="176" unit="section"/>
                    Again, what of the fact that a change of delivery
may make precisely the same words either demonstrate or affirm, express reproach, denial, wonder or
indignation, interrogation, mockery or depreciation?
For the word
                    <quote>thou</quote>
                    is given a different expression
in each of the following passages:
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Thou this poor kingdom dost on me bestow.</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                i. 78.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    and
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Thou vanquish him in song?</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Ecl.</hi>
                                iii. 25.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    and
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="N">Art thou, then, that Aeneas?</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen</hi>
                                i. 617.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    and
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <cit>
                            <quote>
                                <l part="F">And of fear,</l>
                                <l part="N">Do thou accuse me, Drances!</l>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl default="false">
                                <hi rend="italic">Aen.</hi>
                                xi. 383.
                            </bibl>
                        </cit>
                    </quote>
                    To cut a long matter short, if my reader will take
this or any other word he chooses and run it through
the whole gamut of emotional expression, he will
realise the truth of what I say.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="177" unit="section"/>
                    There is one further remark which I must add,
namely, that while what is becoming is the main
consideration in delivery, different methods will often
suit different speakers. For this is determined by
a principle which, though it is obscure and can
hardly be expressed in words, none the less
exists: and, though it is a true saying
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. xxix. 132
                    </note>
                    that
                    <quote>the main secret of artistic success is that whatever we do should become us well,</quote>
                    none the
less, despite the fact that such success cannot be
                    <pb xml:id="p.345"/>
                    attained without art, it is impossible entirely to communicate the secret by the rules of art.
                    <milestone n="178" unit="section"/>
                    There are
some persons in whom positive excellences have no
charm, while there are others whose very faults give
pleasure. We have seen the greatest of comic actors,
Demetrius and Stratocles, win their success by
entirely different merits. But that is the less
surprising owing to the fact that the one was at his
best in the rรดles of gods, young men, good fathers
and slaves, matrons and respectable old women,
while the other excelled in the portrayal of sharptempered old men, cunning slaves, parasites, pimps
and all the more lively characters of comedy. For
their natural gifts differed. For Demetrius' voice,
like his other qualities, had greater charm, while
that of Stratocles was the more powerful.
                    <milestone n="179" unit="section"/>
                    But
yet more noticeable were the incommunicable
peculiarities of their action. Demetrius showed
unique gifts in the movements of his hands, in
his power to charm his audience by the longdrawn sweetness of his exclamations, the skill with
which he would make his dress seem to puff out
with wind as he walked, and the expressive movements of the right side which he sometimes introduced with effect, in all of which things he was
helped by his stature and personal beauty.
                    <milestone n="180" unit="section"/>
                    On the
other hand, Stratocles'
                    <hi rend="italic">forte</hi>
                    lay in his nimbleness
and rapidity of movement, in his laugh (which,
though not always in keeping with the character
lie represented, he deliberately employed to awaken
answering laughter in his audience), and finally, even
in the way in which he sank his neck into his
shoulders. If either of these actors had attempted
any of his rival's tricks, he would have produced a
                    <pb xml:id="p.347"/>
                    most unbecoming effect. Consequently, every man
must get to know his own peculiarities and must
consult not merely the general rules of technique,
but his own nature as well with a view to forming
his delivery.
                    <milestone n="181" unit="section"/>
                    But there is no law of heaven which
prohibits the possession of all or at any rate the
majority of styles by one and the same person. I
must conclude this topic with a remark which applies
to all my other topics as well, that the prime essential
is a sense of proportion. For I am not trying to
form a comic actor, but an orator. Consequently,
we need not study all the details of gesture nor, as
regards our speaking, be pedantic in the use we
make of the rules governing punctuation, rhythm
and appeals to the emotions.
                    <milestone n="182" unit="section"/>
                    For example, if an
actor has to speak the following lines on the stage:
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ter.
                        <hi rend="italic">Eun.</hi>
                        I. i. 1.
                    </note>
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">What shall I do then? Not go, even now,</l>
                            <l part="N">Now when she calls me? Or shall I steel my soul</l>
                            <l part="N">No longer to endure a harlot's insults?</l>
                        </quote>
                    </quote>
                    he will hesitate as in doubt, will vary the modulations
of his voice, together with the movements of hand
and head. But oratory has a different flavour and
objects to elaborate condiments, since it consists in
serious pleading, not in mimicry.
                    <milestone n="183" unit="section"/>
                    There is, therefore, good reason for the condemnation passed on a
delivery which entails the continual alteration of
facial expression, annoying restlessness of gesture
and gusty changes of tone. And it was a wise saying
that the ancient orators borrowed from the Greeks,
as is recorded by Popilius Laenas, to the effect that
there is too much
                    <quote>business</quote>
                    in such delivery.
                    <milestone n="184" unit="section"/>
                    The
instructions given by Cicero on this subject, as on all
others, are quite admirable; I allude to the passages
                    <pb xml:id="p.349"/>
                    which I have already quoted from his
                    <hi rend="italic">Orator,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">ยง 122.</note>
                    while
there are similar observations in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Brutus</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        xxxviii. 141.
                    </note>
                    with
reference to Marcus Antonius. But to-day a rather
more violent form of delivery has come into fashion
and is demanded of our orators: it is well adapted to
certain portions of a speech, but requires to be kept
under control. Otherwise, in our attempt to ape
the elegances of the stage, we shall lose the authority
which should characterise the man of dignity and
virtue.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>