<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panegyric on the Consulshiip of Fl. Manlius Theodorius</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. I</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date type="printing">1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/claudian01clau#page/336/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa013.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.337" TEIform="pb"/>
               <div1 type="poem" n="praef" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PREFACE</head>
         <p>

Wilt dare to sing, my Muse, when so great, so
august an assembly shall be thy critic? Does not
thine own renown forbid thee? 'Tis greater now than
thou deservest; how hard then to enhance, how
disgraceful to diminish it! Or has thine assurance
grown through ever dwelling in the camp, and does
the soldier now wholly possess the poet's breast?
</p>
         <p>Behold the flower of the Roman senate, the majesty,
the pride, the heroes of Gaul. The whole earth
is my audience, my song shall sound in the ears
of all the world. Alack! Love for our consul
constrains too strongly. Jove, 'tis said, when he
would fain learn its extent (for he knew not the
bounds of his own empire) sent forth two eagles
of equal flight from the East and from the West.
</p>
         <p>On Parnassus, as they tell, their twin flights met;
the Delphic heaven brought together the one bird
and the other. Our Emperor needs no eagles to
teach him the magnitude of his domains; yourselves
are preceptors more convincing. 'Tis this assembly
that gives to me the measure of the universe; here
I see gathered all the brilliance of the world.
<pb id="v.1.p.339"/>
         </p>
         <pb id="v.1.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
               </div1>
               <div1 type="poem" n="1" id="poem.17" org="uniform" sample="complete" part="N">
         <head>PANEGYRIC</head>
         <p>

Virtue is its own reward; alone with its far-flung
splendour it mocks at Fortune; no honours raise
it higher nor does it seek glory from the mob's
applause. External wealth cannot arouse its desires,
it asks no praise but makes its boast of self-contained
riches, and unmoved by all chances it looks down
upon the world from a lofty citadel. Yet in its own
despite importunate honours pursue it, and offer
themselves unsought; that the lictor coming from
the farm hath ofttimes proved and a consul sought
for even at the plough. Thou, too, who wert at
leisure to study the mysteries of nature and the
heavens, thou who hadst served thy time and
retired from the law courts where thou hadst toiled
so long, art once more enfolded by a like dignity,
which, raising thee aloft, sets in thy returning hands
the familiar rein. The consulship now is thine,
Theodorus, nor is there now aught left to add to
thy virtues or to the glory of thy name. Thou art
now at the summit of both; from thine earliest
years thy character was thus formed, the whole
course of thy life was worthy of the curule chair;
thy earliest youth outrivalled age. Even then
thy mind was hoar, thy pleasant talk weighty, thy
<pb id="v.1.p.341"/>
converse the admiration and delight of all that
heard it. The wealth of thy triumphant eloquence
soon overflowed the forum and brought safety to
the accused. Yea, this most august assembly was
astonied at thy pleading, as it was twice to applaud
thy governance. Next, a part of Libya approved
the administration which it now in its entirety enjoys;
but thy brief stay won for thee a pledge of perpetual
love, and public statues bear witness with enduring
eloquence that thou wert a nation's guardian.
</p>
         <p>Macedonia was next committed to thy care and
the walls of Pella, enriched once by conquered
Hydaspes. The mildness of thy rule brought to the
country entrusted to thee such joy as it once knew
under warlike Philip or when the empire of Indian
Porus fell to Alexander's arms.
</p>
         <p>But Rome could not spare thy services longer to
the provinces; she chose rather to have thee for
her own; thou comest to give edicts to the world,
to make reply to suppliants. A monarch's utterance
has won dignity from thine eloquence, never can
the majesty of Rome recall when she spoke more
worthily. After this the offerings and wealth of
the world, the tribute of the empire, is entrusted
to thy care; the gold washed down by the rivers
and that dug out of deep Thracian mines by the
skill of pale-faced Bessi who track the hidden seams
— all is thine.
</p>
         <p>As a sailor skilled in wielding the oar is at first set
in charge of but a side of the vessel, then, when he
can manage the lofty prow and is able, thanks to his
long experience of the sea, to know beforehand what
storms and tempests the vessel is like to encounter,
he has charge of the helm and is entrusted with the
<pb id="v.1.p.343"/>
direction of the entire ship; so when thou hadst
long given illustrious proofs of thy character, the
empire of Rome summoned thee to govern not a
part but the whole of itself, and set thee as ruler over
all the rulers of the world. The seas of Spain, the
German ocean obeyed thee and Britain, so far
removed from our continent. Rivers of all lands
observed thy statutes, slow-flowing Saône, swift
Rhone, and Ebro rich in gold. How often did the
Rhine, in those districts where the barbarians dwell,
lament that the blessings of thy rule extended
not to both banks! All the lands the setting sun
bathes in its rays, all that its last brilliance illumines
are entrusted to the charge of one man.
</p>
         <p>So swiftly did thy career fill office after office;
a single period of life was enough for the round of
dignities and gave to thy youthful years every step
on fortune's ladder.
</p>
         <p>When repose was earned and now, after reaching
the highest place, glory, laying care aside, seeks
refuge in a private life, genius again wins reward
from other tasks. No part of life is lost: all that is
withdrawn from the law courts is devoted to the
study, and thy mind in turn either bestows its efforts
on the State or its leisure on the Muses. Once
more thou readest the secrets of ancient Athens,
examining the discoveries with which each sage
has enriched posterity and noting what hosts of
disciples the varying schools produce.
</p>
         <p>For some hold that air 1 is the first beginning of
all things, others that water is, others again derive
the sum of things from fire. Another, destined to
<pb id="v.1.p.345"/>
fall self-immolated into Etna's fiery crater, reduces
God to principles of dispersion and re-collection and
binds again in resumed friendship all that discord
separates. This philosopher allows no authority to
the senses and denies that the truth can be perceived.
</p>
         <p>Another seeks to explain the suspension
of the world in space by the rapid revolution of the
sky (whence else the world would fall) and kindles
day's fires by the whirl of a rushing rock. That
fearless spirit, not content with the covering of
but one sky, flies through the limitless void and,
scorning a limit, conceives in one small brain a
thousand worlds. Others make wandering atoms
clash with blind blows, while others again set up
deities and banish chance.
</p>
         <p>Thou dost adorn the obscure learning of Greece
with Roman flowers, 1 skilled to shape speech in
happy interchange and weave truth's garland with
alternate knots. All the lore of Socrates' school,
the learning that echoed in Cleanthes' lecture-room,
the thoughts of the stoic Chrysippus in his retreat,
all the laughter of Democritus, all that Pythagoras
spoke by silence — all the wisdom of the ancients
is stored in that one brain whence it issues forth
the stronger for its concentration. The ancients
gain fresh lustre and, scorning Athens, the Academy
migrates to Latium under a nobler master, the more
exactly at last to learn by what end happiness guides
its path, what is the rule of the good, the goal
of the right; what division of virtue should be
set to combat and overthrow each separate vice, and
what part of virtue it is that curbs injustice, that
causes reason to triumph over fear, that holds lust
in check. How often hast thou taught us the nature
<pb id="v.1.p.347"/>
of the elements and the causes of matter's cease-
less change; what influence has given life to the
stars, moving them in their courses; what quickens
with movement the universal frame. Thou tellest
why the seven planets strive backward towards the
East, doing battle with the firmament; whether
there is one lawgiver to different movements or
two minds govern heaven's revolution; whether
colour is a property of matter or whether objects
deceive our sight and owe their colours to reflected
light; how the moon causes the ebb and flow of the
tide; which wind brings about the thunder's crash,
which collects the rain clouds and by which the hailstones
are formed; what causes the coldness of snow
and what is that flame that ploughs its shining furrow
through the sky, hurls the swift thunderbolt, or sets
in heaven's dome the tail of the baleful comet.
</p>
         <p>Already had the anchor stayed thy restful bark,
already thou wert minded to go ashore; fruitful
leisure charmed and books were being born for immortality,
when, of a sudden. Justice looked down
from the shining heaven and saw thee at thine ease,
saw Law, too, deprived of her great interpreter. She
stayed not but, wreathing her chaste forehead with a
band, left the gates of Autumn where the Standard-
bearer dips towards the south and the Scorpion makes
good the losses of the night. Where'er she flies a
peace fell upon the birds, and howling beasts laid
aside their rage. Earth rejoices in the return of a
deity lost to her since the waning of the age of gold.
</p>
         <p>Secretly Justice enters the walls of Milan, Liguria's
city, and penetrating with light step the holy palace
finds Theodorus marking in the sand those heavenly
movements which reverent Memphis discovered by
<pb id="v.1.p.349"/>
anxious reckoning. He sought the forces that move
the heavens, the fixed (though errant) path of the
planets, the calculation which predicts the overshadowing
of the sun and its surely-fixed eclipse,
and the line that sentences the moon to be left in
darkness by shutting out her brother. Soon as
from afar he beheld the shining face of the Maiden 1
and recognized the goddess, reverencing that dear
countenance, he hurries to meet her, effacing from
the sand the diagrams he had drawn.
</p>
         <p>The goddess was the first to speak. <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Manlius,
in whom are gathered all the virtues unalloyed, in
whom I see traces of ancient justice and manners
moulded of a purer metal, thou hast devoted time
enough now to study; all these years have the
Muses reft from me my pupil. Long has Law demanded
thy return to her allegiance. Come, devote
thyself once more to my service, and be not content
with the glory of thy past. To the service of mankind
what boundary ever set the limits? Wisdom
accepts no ends for herself. Then, too, to many
has this office fallen, as well it might, but only
the worthy return thereto; reappointment to office
is the best commendation of office well held, and
virtue brings back him whom chance elects. Deemst
thou it a better and a worthier aim to spend thy
days in exploring Nature's secret laws? Dost thou
think it was thy Plato's precepts raised his country
to glory rather than he 2 who, in obedience to the
oracle, sank the Persian fleet, put his city on shipboard
and saved from the Medes Athens destined
for the flames? Lycurgus could dower the mothers
of Sparta with a man's courage and by his austere
laws correct the weakness of their sex; by for-
<pb id="v.1.p.351"/>
bidding his fellow-citizens to put a coward's trust in
walls, he set Lacedemon to face wars more securely
in her nakedness; but all the teaching of Pythagoras
and his years of silence never crushed the
infamous licentiousness of Sparta's colony Tarentum.
</p>
               <p>Besides, beneath such an emperor, who could
refuse office? Was ever merit more richly rewarded?
Who is so insensate as not to wish to
meet Stilicho in council? Has ever any age produced
his equal in prudence or in bravery? Now would
Brutus love to live under a king; to such a court
Fabricius would yield, the Catos themselves long
to give service. Seest thou not how my sister
Mercy blunts the cruel sword of war; how Piety
rises to embrace the two noble brothers; how
Treason laments her broken weapons and the
snakes, writhing in death upon the Furies' wounded
heads, lick their chains with enfeebled venom?
Peace and loyalty are triumphant. All the host of
heaven leaves the stars and wanders from peaceful city
to peaceful city. Return thou with us, Theodorus.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>Then Theodorus made answer: <q direct="unspecified">From my long
accustomed fields, goddess, thou urgest me to
return, summoning to thy standard one grown
rusty in the distant countryside. What else has
been my care all these years but to break up the
stubborn fallow-land into furrows, to know the
nature of the soil, the rocky land suitable to the
growth of trees, the country where the olive will
flourish, the fields that will yield rich harvests of
grain or the hills which my vineyards may clothe?
I have served my time; am I to hearken once more
to the dreadful trumpet? Is the old helmsman
again to brave the seas whose lore he has forgotten?
<pb id="v.1.p.353"/>
My fame has long been gathered in and where it
is 'tis in safe custody; am I to suffer its being put
to the hazard? Full well do I realize that habit
is a stronger force than nature, nor am I ignorant
of the rapidity with which we forget an art that we
have ceased to exercise. The whip of an unpractised
charioteer is powerless to urge on his horses;
the hand that is unaccustomed thereto cannot bend
the bow. And yet it were unjust, I admit, to refuse
aught to Justice. Thou first didst draw man from
his woodland cave and free the human race from its
foul manner of life. Thanks to thee we practise
law and have put off the temper of wild beasts.
Whosoever has drunk of thee with pure heart
will rush fearless through flames, will sail the
wintry seas, and overcome unarmed the densest
company of foemen. Justice is to the just as rain
to temper even the heat of Ethiopia, a breath
of spring to journey with him across the deserts of
Scythia.</q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake he and took from the goddess' hand the
four reins that lay stretched along the huge pole of
Justice's car. The first harnesses the rivers Po and
Tiber and Italy with all her glittering towns; the
second guides Numidia and Carthage; the third
runs out across the land of Illyria; the last holds
Sardinia, Corsica, three-cornered Sicily and the coasts
beaten by the Tyrrhenian wave or that echo to the
Ionian. The splendour and magnitude of the undertaking
troubled thee not one whit; but as the
lofty summit of Olympus, far removed from the
winds and tempests of the lower air, its eternal
bright serene untroubled by any cloud, is lifted
above the rain storms and hears the hurricane rushing
<pb id="v.1.p.355"/>
beneath its feet while it treads upon the thunder's
roar; so thy patient mind, unfettered by cares so
manifold, rises high above them; thou art ever
the same, no hatred can compel thee, no affection
induce thee, to swerve from the path of justice.
</p>
         <p>For why should any speak of riches scorned and
a heart unallured by gain? These might perhaps
be virtues in others: absence of vice is no praise
to bestow on thee. The calm of a god banishes
anger from thy voice; the spirit of moderation
shines from thine eyes; passion never inflames
that glance or fills with blood the angry veins;
never is a tempest heralded on thy changed countenance.
</p>
         <p>Nay, thou punishest the very criminals
without show of anger and checkest their evil-doing
with unruffled calm. Never dost thou gnash with
thy teeth upon them nor shout orders for them to
be chastised.
</p>
         <p>He is a savage who delights in punishment and
seems to make the vengeance of the laws his own;
when his heart is inflamed with the poison of wrath
he is goaded by fury and rushes on knowing nothing
of the cause and eager only to do hurt. But he
whom reason, not anger, animates is a peer of the
gods, he who, weighing the guilt, can with deliberation
balance the punishment. Let others boast them
of their bloody swords and wish to be feared for
their ferocity, while they fill their treasuries with
the goods of the condemned. Gently flows the Nile,
yet is it more beneficent than all rivers for all that
no sound reveals its power. More swiftly the broad
Danube glides between its quiet banks. Huge
Ganges flows down to its mouths with gently moving
current. Let torrents roar horribly, threaten weary
<pb id="v.1.p.357"/>
bridges, and sweep down forests in their foaming
whirl; 'tis repose befits the greater; quiet authority
accomplishes what violence cannot, and that mandate
compels more which comes from a commanding calm.
Thou art as deaf to the prayers of injustice as
thou art generous and attentive where the demand
is just. Pride, that ever accompanies office, has not
so much as dared to touch thy mind. Thy look is
a private citizen's nor allows that it has deserved
what it thinks to have but grown 1; but full of stately
modesty shines forth a gravity that charms because
pride is banished. What sedition, what madness
of the crowd could see thee and not sink down
appeased? What country so barbarous, so foreign
in its customs, as not to bow in reverence before
thy mediation? Who that desires the honied
charm of polished eloquence would not desert the
lyre-accompanied song of tuneful Orpheus? In
every activity we see thee as we see thee in thy
books, describing the creation of the newly-fashioned
earth or the parts of the soul; we recognize thy
character in thy pages.
</p>
         <p>The Emperor has not been slow in rewarding thy
merit. The robe that links Senate-house and
palace, that unites nobles with their prince — the
robe that he himself has four times worn, he hath
at the year's end handed on to thee, and left his
own curule chair that thou mightest follow him.
</p>
         <p>Grow, ye virtues; be this an age of prosperity!
</p>
         <p>The path of glory lies open to the wise; merit is
sure of its reward; industry dowered with the gifts
it deserves. Arts, rise from the slumber into which
depraved ambition had forced you! Envy cannot
hold up her head while Stilicho and his godlike
<pb id="v.1.p.359"/>
son-in-law direct the state. Here is no pollution
of the consul's office, no shameful names disgrace
the Latin fasti; here the consulship is an honour
reserved for the brave, given only to senators,
never a source of scandal to Rome's city.1
Now had Fame, announcing our good fortune,
winged her way to Aonia whose groves she stirred
with the tidings of the new consul. Helicon raised
a hymn of praise, Aganippe flowed with waters
more abundant, the streams of song laughed with
flowers. Then Urania, her hair wreath-crowned,
Urania whose hand had oft directed Manlius' compass
in marking out the starry spheres, thus
addressed the other Muses: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Sisters, can we
bear to be absent this longed-for day? Shall we
not visit our consul's door and the house we
have always loved? Better known to us is it than
Helicon; gladly we draw the curule chair and bear
the fasces. Bring marvels for the people's delight
and make known his name in the famed theatres.
</p>
               <p>Do thou, Erato, go visit the palace of Neptune
beneath the sea and beg for four swift coursers such
that even Arion could not snatch the prize from
them. Let the Circus be graced by every steed
to whose proud neighing Baetis re-echoes, who
drinks of Tagus' shining pools and sprinkles his
mane with its liquid gold.
</p>
               <p>Calliope, ask thou of Alcides the oil of the
wrestling-ground. Let all the company proved in the
games at Elis follow thee and the athletes who have
won fame with Olympian Jove.
</p>
               <p>Fly, Clio, to Taygetus' heights and leafy Maenalus
and beg Diana not to spurn thy petition but help
the amphitheatre's pomp. Let the goddess herself
<pb id="v.1.p.361"/>
choose out brave hunters cunningly to lasso the necks
of wild animals and to drive home the hunting-
spear with unfailing stroke. With her own hand let
her lead forth from their caverns fierce beasts and
captive monsters, laying aside her bloodthirsty bow.
Let bears be gathered together, whereat, as they
charge with mighty bulk, Helice may gaze in wonder
from Lycaon's stars  Let smitten lions roar till the
people turn pale, lions such as Cybele would be
fain to harness to her Mygdonian chariot or
Hercules strangle in his mighty arms. May leopards,
lightning-swift, hasten to meet the spear's wound,
beasts that are born of an adulterous union what
time the spotted sire did violence to the nobler lion's
mate: of such beasts their markings recall the sire,
their courage the dam. Whatsoever is nourished
by the fields of Gaetulia rich in monsters, whatsoever
lurks beneath Alpine snows or in Gallic woods, let
it fall before the spear. Let large streams of
blood enrich the arena and the spectacle leave
whole mountains desolate.
</p>
               <p>Nor let gentler games lack the delights we bring:
let the clown be there to move the people's laughter
with his happy wit, the mime whose language is
in his nod and in the movements of his hands, the
musician whose breath rouses the flute and whose
finger stirs the lyre, the slippered comedian to whose
voice the theatre re-echoes, the tragedian towering
on his loftier buskin; him too whose light touch can
elicit loud music from those pipes of bronze that
sound a thousand diverse notes beneath his wandering
fingers and who by means of a lever stirs to song
the labouring water.2 Let us see acrobats who hurl
themselves through the air like birds and build
<pb id="v.1.p.363"/>
pyramids that grow with swift entwining of their
bodies, to the summit of which pyramid rushes
a boy fastened by a thong, a boy who, attached
there by the foot or leg, executes a step-dance
suspended in the air. Let the counterweights be
removed and the mobile crane descend, lowering on
to the lofty stage men who, wheeling chorus-wise,
scatter flames; let Vulcan forge balls of fire to roll
innocuously across the boards, let the flames appear
to play about the sham beams of the scenery and a
tame conflagration, never allowed to rest, wander
among the untouched towers. Let ships meet in
mimic warfare on an improvised ocean and the
flooded waters be lashed to foam by singing oarsmen.
</p>
               <p>As consul at once and stateliest master, upborne
by a twofold fame, let Manlius go forth among the
peoples, read in his own books and in our calendars.
May the sire's example be followed by the son 1
and handed on to a grandson, nor these first fasces
ever lack succession. May his race pass on purple-
clad, may the generations, each to each, hand on the
axes, and obedient to the ordinance of fate, Manlius
after Manlius add one more consul to the tale.</p>
            </q>
            <pb id="v.1.p.365"/>
         </p>
                        </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>