<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight books - 7</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight Books</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1857</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/4/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="447" xml:id="p.447"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="book">
                <head>BOOK VII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Two magistrates were added, the praetorship and curule aedileship. A
                        pestilence rages in the city, which carries off the celebrated Furius
                        Camillus. Scenic representations first introduced. Curtius leaps on
                        horseback completely armed into a gulf in the forum. Titus Manlius, having
                        slain a Gaul in single combat, who challenged any of the Roman soldiers,
                        takes from him a golden chain, and hence gets the name of Torquatus. Two new
                        tribes are added, called the Pomptine and Publilian. Licinius Stolo is
                        condemned on a law which he himself had carried, for possessing more than
                        five hundred acres of land. Marcus Valerius, surnamed Corvinus, from having
                        with the aid of a crow killed a Gaul, who challenged him, is on the
                        following year elected consul, though but twenty-three years old. A treaty
                        of friendship made with the Carthaginians. The Campanians, overpowered by
                        the Samnites, surrender themselves to the Roman people, who declare war
                        against the Samnites. P. Decius Mus saves the Roman army, when brought into
                        very great danger by the consul A. Cornelius. Conspiracy and revolt of the
                        Roman soldiers in the garrison of Capua. They are brought to a sense of
                        duty, and restored to their country, by Marcus Valerius Corvus, dictator.
                        Successful operations against the Hernicians, Gauls, Tiburtians,
                        Privernians, Tarquinians, Samnites, and Volscians. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> THIS year will be remarkable for the
                    consulship of a man of mean birth, remarkable for two new magistracies, the
                    praetorship and curule aedileship. These honours the patricians claimed to
                    themselves, in consideration of one consulship having been conceded to the
                    plebeians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The commons gave the consulship to
                    Lucius Sextius, by whose law it had been obtained. The patricians by their
                    popular influence obtained the praetorship for Spurius Furius Camillus, the son
                    of Marcus, the aedileship for Cneius Quinctius Capitolinus and Publius Cornelius
                    Scipio, men of their own rank. To Lucius Sextius, the patrician colleague
                    assigned was Lucius Aemilius Mamercinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In
                    the beginning of the year mention was made both of the Gauls, who, after having
                    strayed about through Apulia, it was now rumoured were forming into a body; and
                    also <pb n="448" xml:id="p.448"/> concerning a revolt of the Hernicians.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When all business was purposely deferred,
                    so that nothing should be transacted through means of the plebeian consul,
                    silence was observed on all matters, and a state of inaction like to a
                    justitium; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> except that, the tribunes not
                    suffering it to pass unnoticed that the nobility had arrogated to themselves
                    three patrician magistracies as a compensation for one plebeian consul, sitting
                    in curule chairs, clad in the praetexta like consuls; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> the praetor, too, administering justice, and as if
                    colleague to the consuls, and elected under the same auspices, the senate were
                    in consequence made ashamed to order the curule aediles to be elected from among
                    the patricians. It was at first agreed, that they should be elected from the
                    commons every second year: afterwards the matter was left open. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Then, in the consulate of Lucius Genucius and Quintus
                    Servilius, affairs being tranquil both at home and abroad, that they might at no
                    period be exempt from fear and danger, a great pestilence arose. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> They say that a praetor, a curule aedile, and three
                    plebeian tribunes died of it, and that several other deaths took place in
                    proportion among the populace; and that pestilence was made memorable chiefly by
                    the death of Marcus Furius, which, though occurring at an advanced age, was
                    still much lamented. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For he was a truly
                    extraordinary man under every change of fortune; the first man in the state in
                    peace and war, before he went into exile; still more illustrious in exile,
                    whether by the regret felt for him by the state, which, when in captivity,
                    implored his aid when absent; or by the success with which, when restored to his
                    country, he restored that country along with himself. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For five and twenty years afterwards (for so many years
                    afterwards did he live) he uniformly preserved his claims to such great glory,
                    and was deemed deserving of their considering him, next after Romulus, a second
                    founder of the city of Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The pestilence continued both for this and the
                    following year, Caius Sulpicius Peticus and Caius Licinius Stolo being consuls.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During that year nothing worth recording
                    took place, except that for the purpose of imploring the favour of the gods,
                    there was a Lectisternium, the third time since the building of the city.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when the violence of the disease was
                    alleviated neither by human measures nor by divine interference, their minds
                    being broken down by superstition, <pb n="449" xml:id="p.449"/> among other
                    means of appeasing the wrath of heaven, scenic plays also are said to have been
                    instituted, a new thing to a warlike people (for hitherto there had been only
                    the shows of the circus). But the matter was trivial, (as all beginnings
                    generally are,) and even that itself from a foreign source. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Without any poetry, or gesticulating in imitation of such
                    poetry, actors were sent for from Etruria, dancing to the measures of a
                    musician, and exhibited, according to the Tuscan fashion, movements by no means
                    ungraceful. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The young men afterwards began to
                    imitate these, throwing out at the same time among each other jocular
                    expressions in uncouth verses; nor were their gestures irrelevant to their
                    language. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Wherefore the matter was received
                    with approbation, and by frequent use was much improved. To the native
                    performers the name of <hi rend="italics">histriones</hi> was given, because <hi
                        rend="italics">hister,</hi> in the Tuscan vocabulary, was the name of an
                    actor, <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> who did not, as formerly, throw out
                    alternately artless and unpolished verses like the Fescennine at random, but
                    represented medleys complete with metre, the music being regularly adjusted for
                    the musician, and with appropriate gesticulation. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Livius, who several years after, giving up medleys, was the
                    first who ventured to digest a story with a regular plot, (the same being,
                    forsooth, as all were at that time, the actor of his own pieces,) after having
                    broken his <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> voice from having been too
                    repeatedly called on, and after having sought permission, is said to have placed
                    a boy before the musician to chaunt, and to have performed the gesticulations
                    with considerably freer movement, because the employment of his voice was no
                    impediment to him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thence commenced the
                    practice of chaunting to the actors according to their manual gesticulations,
                    and the dialogues only were left to their voice. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When by this arrangement the business of the scenic
                    performances was called away from laughter and intemperate mirth, and the
                    amusement became gradually converted into an art, the young men, leaving to
                    regular actors the performance of plays, began themselves, according to the
                    ancient usage, to throw out ludicrous jests comprised in verses, which from that
                    time were called <hi rend="italics">exodia,</hi> and were collected chiefly from
                    the Atellan farces. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Which kind of amusement,
                    received from the Osci, the young kept to themselves, nor did they suffer it to
                    be debased by regular players. Hence it remains an established usage that the
                    actors of the Atellan farces are neither degraded <pb n="450" xml:id="p.450"/>
                    from their tribe, and may serve in the army, as if having no connexion with the
                    profession of the stage. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Among the trifling
                    beginnings of other matters, it seemed to me that the first origin of plays also
                    should be noticed; that it might appear how from a moderate commencement it has
                    reached its present extravagance, scarcely to be supported by opulent kingdoms. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, the first introduction of plays,
                    intended as a religious expiation, neither relieved their minds from religious
                    awe, nor their bodies from disease. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nay more,
                    when the circus being inundated by the overflowing of the Tiber happened to
                    interrupt the middle of the performance, that indeed, as if the gods were now
                    turned from them, and despised their efforts to soothe their wrath, excited
                    great terror. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, Cneius Genucius and
                    Lucius Aemilius Mamercinus being a second time consuls, when the searching for
                    expiations harassed their minds, more than the diseases did their bodies, it is
                    said to have been collected from the memory of the more aged, that a pestilence
                    had formerly been relieved, on the nail being driven by a dictator. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Induced by this superstitious circumstance, the
                    senate ordered a dictator to be appointed for the purpose of driving the nail.
                    Lucius Manlius Imperiosus being appointed, named Lucius Pinarius master of the
                    horse. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There is an ancient law written in
                    antique letters and words, that whoever is supreme officer should drive a nail
                    on the ides of September. It was driven into the right side of the temple of
                    Jupiter supremely good and great, on that part where the temple of Minerva is.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They say that the nail was a mark of the
                    number of years elapsed, because letters were rare in those times, and that the
                    law was referred to the temple of Minerva, because number is the invention of
                    that goddess. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cincius, a careful writer on
                    such monuments, asserts that there were seen at Volsinii also nails fixed in the
                    temple of Nortia, a Tuscan goddess, as indices of the number of years.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Marcus Horatius, being consul, according
                    to law dedicated the temple of Jupiter the best and greatest the year after the
                    expulsion of kings; the solemnity of fixing the nail was afterwards transferred
                    from the consuls to the dictators, because theirs was a superior office. The
                    custom being afterwards dropped, it seemed a matter of sufficient importance in
                    itself, on account of which a dictator should be appointed. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For which reason Lucius Manlius being appoint- <pb n="451"
                        xml:id="p.451"/> ed, just as if he had been appointed for the purpose of
                    managing the business of the state in general, and not to acquit it of a
                    religious obligation, being ambitious to manage the Hernician war, harassed the
                    youth by a severe levy, and at length, all the plebeian tribunes having risen up
                    against him, whether overcome by force or shame, he resigned the dictatorship. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Notwithstanding this, in the commencement of
                    the ensuing year, Quintus Servilius Ahala, Lucius Genucius being consuls, a day
                    of trial is appointed for Manlius, by Marcus Pomponius, tribune of the commons.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His severity in the levies, carried not
                    only to the fining of the citizens, but even to the laceration of their bodies,
                    those who had not answered to their names being some beaten with rods, others
                    thrown into prison, was hateful; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and more
                    hateful than all was his violent temper, and the surname of Imperiosus,
                    offensive to a free state, adopted by him from an ostentation of severity, which
                    he exercised not more against strangers than his nearest friends, and even those
                    of his own blood. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And among other things, the
                    tribune alleged as a charge against him that <quote> he had banished his son, a
                        youth convicted of no improper conduct, from the city, home, household gods,
                        forum, light, from the society of his equals, and consigned him in a manner
                        to a prison or workhouse; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> where a youth of
                        dictatorian rank, born of a very high family, should learn by his daily
                        suffering that he was descended of a truly imperious father. And for what
                        offence? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> because he was not eloquent, nor
                        ready in discourse. Which defect of nature, whether ought it to be treated
                        with leniency if there were a particle of humanity in him, or ought it to be
                        punished, and rendered more remarkable by harsh treatment? The dumb beasts
                        even, if any of their offspring happen to be badly formed, are not the less
                        careful in nourishing and cherishing them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        But Lucius Manlius aggravated the misfortune of his son by severity, and
                        further clogged the slowness of his intellects; and if there were in him
                        even the least spark of natural ability he extinguished it by a rustic life
                        and a clownish education, and keeping him among cattle. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By these charges the minds of all were
                    exasperated against him more than that of the young man himself: <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> nay, on the contrary, being grieved that he was even
                    the cause of <pb n="452" xml:id="p.452"/> public odium and accusations to his
                    father, that all the gods and men might know that he would rather afford aid to
                    his father than to his enemies, he forms the design, characteristic of a rude
                    and rustic mind no doubt, and though of a precedent not conformable to the rules
                    of civil life, yet commendable for its filial piety. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Having furnished himself with a knife, without the
                    knowledge of any one he proceeds early in the morning into the city, and from
                    the gate straightway to the house of Marcus Pomponius the tribune: he tells the
                    porter, that he wanted to see his master immediately, and bid him to announce
                    that he was Titus Manlius, son of Lucius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Being introduced immediately, (for he had hopes that the youth, incensed against
                    his father, brought either some new charge, or some advice to accomplish the
                    project,) after mutual greeting, he says that there were some matters which he
                    wished to transact with him in private. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then,
                    all persons being ordered to withdraw to a distance, he draws his dagger; and
                    standing over the couch with his dagger ready to strike, he threatens that he
                    would immediately stab him, unless he would swear in the words which he would
                    dictate, that <quote>he never would hold a meeting of the commons for the
                        purpose of prosecuting his father.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The tribune alarmed, (for he saw the steel
                    glittering before his eyes, himself alone and unarmed; the other a young man,
                    and very powerful, and what was no less terrifying, savagely ferocious in his
                    bodily strength,) swears in the terms in which he was obliged; and afterwards
                    acknowledged that forced by this proceeding he gave up his undertaking.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor though the commons would have
                    preferred that an opportunity was afforded them of passing sentence on so cruel
                    and tyrannical a culprit, they were not much displeased that the son had dared
                    to act so in behalf of his father; and that was the more commendable in this,
                    that such great severity on the part of the father had not weaned his mind from
                    his filial affection. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Wherefore the pleading
                    of his cause was not only dispensed with for the father, but the matter even
                    became a source of honour to the young man; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    and when it had been determined on that year for the first time that tribunes of
                    the soldiers for the legions should be appointed by suffrage, (for before that
                    the commanders themselves used to appoint them, as they now do those whom they
                    call Rufuli,) he obtained the second place among six, without <pb n="453"
                        xml:id="p.453"/> any merit of a civil or military nature to conciliate
                    public favour; as he had spent his youth in the country and at a distance from
                    all intercourse with the world. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the same year the middle of the forum is
                    said to have fallen in to an immense depth, forming a sort of vast cave, either
                    by reason of an earthquake, or some other violent cause; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> nor could that gulf be filled up by throwing earth into it,
                    every one exerting himself to the utmost, until by the admonition of the gods an
                    inquiry began to be instituted, as to what constituted the chief strength of the
                    Roman people? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for the soothsayers declare that
                    must be devoted to that place, if they desired the Roman state to be perpetual.
                    Then they tell us that Marcus Curtius, a youth distinguished in war, reproved
                    them for hesitating, whether there was any greater Roman good than arms and
                    valour. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Silence being made, looking to the
                    temples of the immortal gods, which command a view of the forum, and towards the
                    Capitol, and extending his hands at one time towards heaven, at another towards
                    the infernal gods, through the gaping aperture of the earth, he devoted himself:
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> then, mounted on a horse accoutred in the
                    most gorgeous style possible, he plunged in full armour into the opening, and
                    offerings and the fruits of the earth were thrown in over him by the multitude
                    of men and women, and the lake was called Curtian not from Curtius Mettus, the
                    ancient soldier of Titus Tatius, but from this circumstance. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> If any way would lead one's inquiry to the truth, industry
                    would not be wanting: now, when length of time precludes all certainty of
                    evidence, we must stand by the rumour of tradition; and the name of the lake
                    must be accounted for from this more recent story. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> After due attention being paid to so great a prodigy, the
                    senate, during the same year, being consulted regarding the Hernicians, (after
                    having sent heralds to demand restitution in vain,) voted, that a motion be
                    submitted on the earliest day to the people on the subject of declaring war
                    against the Hernicians, and the people, in full assembly, ordered it. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> That province fell by lot to the consul Lucius
                    Genucius. The state was in anxious suspense, because he was the first plebeian
                    consul that was about to conduct a war under his own auspices, being sure to
                    judge of the good or bad policy of establishing a community of honours,
                    according as the matter should turn out. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Chance so arranged it, <pb n="454" xml:id="p.454"/> that Genucius, marching
                    against the enemy with a considerable force, fell into an ambush; the legions
                    being routed by reason of a sudden panic, the consul was slain after being
                    surrounded by persons who knew not whom they had slain. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> When this news was brought to Rome, the patricians, by no
                    means so grieved for the public disaster, as elated at the unsuccessful guidance
                    of the plebeian consul, every where exclaim, <quote> They might now go, and
                        elect consuls from the commons, they might transfer the auspices where it
                        was impious to do so. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The patricians
                        might by a vote of the people be driven from their own exclusive honour:
                        whether had this inauspicious law availed also against the immortal gods?
                        They had vindicated their authority, their auspices; which as soon as ever
                        they were defiled by one by whom it was contrary to human and divine law
                        that they should have been, the destruction of the army with its leader was
                        a warning, that elections should hereafter be conducted in utter violation
                        of the rights of birth. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The senate-house and the forum resound with
                    expressions such as these. Appius Claudius, because he had dissuaded the law,
                    and now with greater authority blamed the issue of a measure which had been
                    found fault with by himself, the consul Servilius appoints dictator by the
                    general wish of the patricians, and a levy and cessation of business are
                    procaimed. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the dictator and the new legions could
                    arrive among the Hernicians, matters were conducted with great success under the
                    direction of Caius Sulpicius the lieutenant-general, making use of a favourable
                    opportunity. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the Hernicians, who after the
                    death of the consul came up contemptuously to the Roman camp with the certainty
                    of taking it, a sally was made by the exhortations of the consul, the minds of
                    the soldiers also being full of rage and indignation. The Hernicians were much
                    disappointed in their hopes of approaching the rampart; in such complete
                    confusion did they retire from thence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then on
                    the arrival of the dictator the new army is joined to the old, the forces are
                    doubled; and the dictator in a public assembly, by bestowing praises on the
                    lieutenant-general and the soldiers by whose valour the camp had been defended,
                    at the same time raises the spirits of those who heard their own deserved
                    praises, and at the same time stimulates the others to rival such valour.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With no less vigour <pb n="455"
                        xml:id="p.455"/> are the military preparations made on the part of the
                    enemy, who, mindful of the honour previously acquired, and not ignorant that the
                    enemy had increased their strength, augment their forces also. The entire
                    Hernician race, all of military age, are called out. Eight cohorts, each
                    consisting of four hundred men, the chosen strength of their people, are levied.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This, the select flower of their youth,
                    they filled with hope and courage by their having decreed that they should
                    receive double pay. They were exempt also from military work, that, being
                    reserved for the single labour of fighting, they might feel that they should
                    make exertions more than are made by ordinary men. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> They are placed in an extraordinary position in the field,
                    that their valour might be the more conspicuous. A plain two miles in breadth
                    separated the Roman camp from the Hernicians; in the middle of this, the spaces
                    being about equal on both sides, they came to an engagement. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> At first the fight was kept up with doubtful hope; the
                    Roman cavalry having repeatedly essayed to no purpose to break the enemy's line
                    by their charge. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When their fighting as
                    cavalry was less marked by success than by great efforts, the cavalry, having
                    first consulted the dictator, and then obtained his permission, leaving their
                    horse behind, rush forward in front of the line, with a loud shout, and
                    recommence the battle after a new style; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> nor
                    could they be resisted, had not the extraordinary cohorts, possessing equal
                    vigour both of body and spirit, thrown themselves in their way. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the contest is carried on between the
                    leading men of the two states. Whatever the common fortune of war carried off
                    from either side, the loss was many times greater than can be estimated by the
                    numbers: the rest, an armed populace, as if they had delegated the fight to the
                    leading men, rest the issue of their own success on the bravery of others.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Many fall on both sides; more are wounded.
                    At length the horsemen, chiding each other, asking, <quote>what now
                        remained,</quote> if neither when mounted they had made an impression on the
                    enemy, nor as infantry did they achieve any thing of moment; what third mode of
                    fighting did they wait for? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Why had they so
                    fiercely rushed forward before the line, and fought in a post not belonging to
                    them? Aroused by these mutual chidings, they raise the shout anew, and press
                    forward; and <pb n="456" xml:id="p.456"/> first they made the enemy shrink, then
                    made them give way, and at length fairly made them turn their backs. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Nor is it easy to say what circumstance obtained the
                    advantage against strength so well matched; except that the constant fortune of
                    both people might have raised or depressed their spirits. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans pursued the Hernicians in their flight to their
                    camp; they refrained from attacking the camp, because it was late. The fact of
                    not having finished the sacrifices with success detained the dictator, so that
                    he could not give the signal before noon, and hence the contest was protracted
                    till night. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Next day the camp of the
                    Hernicians was deserted, and some wounded men were found left behind, and the
                    main body of the fugitives was routed by the Signians, as their standards were
                    seen passing by their walls but thinly attended, and dispersed over the country
                    in precipitate flight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor was the victory an
                    unbloody one to the Romans; a fourth part of the soldiers perished; and, where
                    there was no less of loss, several Roman horsemen fell. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following year, when the consuls Caius
                    Sulpicius and Caius Licinius Calvus led an army against the Hernicians, and
                    finding no enemy in the country took their city Ferentinum by storm, as they
                    were returning thence, the Tiburtians shut their gates against them. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Though many complaints had been made on both sides
                    before this, this was the determining cause why war was declared against the
                    Tiburtian people, restitution having been demanded through heralds. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> It is sufficiently ascertained that Titus Quinctius
                    Pennus was dictator that year, and that Servius Cornelius Maluginensis was his
                    master of the horse. Macer Licinius writes, that he was named by the consul for
                    the purpose <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> of holding the elections,
                    because his colleague hastening to have the elections over before undertaking
                    the war, that he might continue the consulship, he thought it right to thwart
                    his ambitious designs. This being designed as a compliment to his own family,
                    renders the authority of Licinius of the less weight. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> As I find no mention of that circumstance in the more
                    ancient annals, my mind inclines me to consider that the dictator was appointed
                    on account of the Gallic war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On that year,
                    certainly, the Gauls pitched their camp at the third stone on the Salarian road,
                    at the further side of the bridge of the Anio. The dictator, after he had
                    proclaimed a cessation of civil business on <pb n="457" xml:id="p.457"/> account
                    of the Gallic tumult, bound all the younger citizens by the military oath; and
                    having set forth from the city with a great army, pitched his camp on the hither
                    bark of the Anio.. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The bridge lay between both
                    armies, neither side attempting to break it down, lest it should be an
                    indication of fear. There were frequent skirmishes for the possession of the
                    bridge; nor could it be clearly determined who were masters of it, the
                    superiority being so indecisive. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A Gaul of
                    very large stature advanced on the bridge, then unoccupied, and says with as
                    loud a voice as he could exert, <quote> Let the bravest man that Rome now
                        possesses come forward here to battle, that the event of an engagement
                        between us both may show which nation is superior in war. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was for a long time silence among the
                    young Roman nobility, as they were both ashamed to decline the contest, and
                    unwilling to claim the principal post of danger. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Then Titus Manlius, son of Lucius, the same who had freed his father from the
                    vexatious persecution of the tribune, proceeds from his station to the dictator:
                        <quote> Without your commands, general, I would never fight out of the
                        ordinary course, not though I should see certain victory before me.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If you permit me, I wish to show that
                        brute, who insolently makes such a parade before the enemy's line, that I am
                        sprung from that family which dislodged a body of Gauls from the Tarpeian
                        rock. </quote> Then the dictator says, <quote> Titus Manlius, may you
                        prosper for your valour and dutiful affection to your father and your
                        country. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Go on, and make good the
                        invincibility of the Roman name with the aid of the gods. </quote> His
                    companions then arm the youth; he takes a footman's shield, girds himself with a
                    Spanish sword, fit for a close fight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When
                    armed and equipped, they lead him out against the Gaul, who exhibited stolid
                    exultation, and (for the ancients thought that also worthy of mention) thrust
                    out his tongue in derision. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They then retire
                    to their station; and the two being armed, are left in the middle space, lore
                    after the manner of a spectacle, than according to the law of combat, by no
                    means well matched, according to those who judged by sight and appearance.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The one had a body enormous in size,
                    glittering in a vest of various colours, and in armour painted and inlaid with
                    gold; the other had a middle stature, as is seen among soldiers, and a mien
                    unostentatious, in arms fit <pb n="458" xml:id="p.458"/> for ready use rather
                    than adapted for show. He had no song, no capering, nor idle flourishing of
                    arms, but his breast, teeming with courage and silent rage, had reserved all its
                    ferocity for the decision of the contest. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When
                    they took their stand between the two armies, the minds of so many individuals
                    around them suspended between hope and <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> fear,
                    the Gaul, like a huge mass threatening to fall on that which was beneath it,
                    stretching forward his shield with his left hand, discharged an ineffectual cut
                    of his sword with a great noise on the armour of his foe as he advanced towards
                    him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Roman, raising the point of his
                    sword, after he had pushed aside the lower part of the enemy's shield with his
                    own, and closing on him so as to be exempt from the danger of a wound,
                    insinuated himself with his entire body between the body and arms of the foe,
                    with one and immediately with another thrust pierced his belly and groin, and
                    stretched his enemy now prostrate over a vast extent of ground. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Without offering the body of the prostrate foe any
                    other indignity, he despoiled it of one chain; which, though smeared with blood,
                    he threw around his neck. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Dismay with
                    astonishment now held the Gauls motionless. The Romans, elated with joy,
                    advancing from their post to meet their champion, with congratulations and
                    praises conduct him to the dictator. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Among
                    them uttering some uncouth jests in military fashion somewhat resembling verses,
                    the name of Torquatus was heard: this name, being kept up, became afterwards an
                    honour to the descendants even of the family. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    The dictator added a present of a golden crown, and before a public assembly
                    extolled that action with the highest praises. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And, indeed, of so great moment was the
                    contest with respect to the issue of the war in general, that on the night
                    following the army of the Gauls, having abandoned their camp in confusion,
                    passed over into the territory of Tibur, and from thence soon after into
                    Campania, having concluded an alliance for the purpose of war, and being
                    abundantly supplied with provision by the Tiburtians. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> That was the reason why, on the next year, Caius Paetelius
                    Balbus, consul, though the province of the Hernicians had fallen to the lot of
                    his colleague, Marcus Fabius Ambustus, led an army, by order of the people,
                    against the Tiburtians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To whose assistance
                    when the Gauls came back from Campania, dreadful devastations were com- <pb
                        n="459" xml:id="p.459"/> mitted in the Lavican, Tusculan, and Alban
                    territories. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And though the state was
                    satisfied with a consul as leader against the Tiburtian enemy, the alarm created
                    by the Gauls rendered it necessary that a dictator should be appointed. Quintus
                    Servilius Ahala having been appointed, named Titus Quinctius master of the
                    horse; and with the sanction of the senate, vowed the great games, should that
                    war turn out successfully. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The dictator then,
                    having ordered the consular army to remain to confine the Tiburtians to their
                    own war, bound all the younger citizens by the military oath, none declining the
                    service. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A battle was fought not far from the
                    Colline gate with the strength of the entire city, in the sight of their
                    parents, wives, and children: which being great incitements to courage, even
                    when these relatives are absent, being now placed before their eyes, fired the
                    soldiers at once with feelings of shame and compassion. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Great havoc being made on both sides, the Gallic army is at
                    length worsted. In their flight they make for Tibur, as being the main stay of
                    the war; and being intercepted whilst straggling by the consul Paetelius not far
                    from Tibur, and the Tiburtians having come out to bring them aid, they are with
                    the latter driven within the gates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Matters
                    were managed with distinguished success both by the dictator and the consul. And
                    the other consul, Fabius, at first in slight skirmishes, and at length in one
                    single battle, defeated the Hernicians, when they attacked him with all their
                    forces. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The dictator, after passing the
                    highest encomiums on the consuls in the senate and before the people, and
                    yielding up the honour of his own exploits to them, resigned his dictatorship.
                    Paetelius enjoyed a double triumph, over the Gauls and the Tiburtians. Fabius
                    was satisfied with entering the city in ovation. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The Tiburtians derided the triumph of Paetelius; <quote>for
                        where,</quote> they said, <quote> had he encountered them in the field? that
                        a few of their people having gone outside the gates to witness the flight
                        and confusion of the Gauls, on seeing an attack made on themselves, and that
                        those who came in the way were slaughtered without distinction, had retired
                        within the city. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Did that seem to the
                        Romans worthy of a triumph? They should not consider it an extraordinary and
                        wondrous feat to raise a tumult at the enemy's gates, as they should soon
                        see greater confusion before their own walls. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly in the year following, Marcus
                    Popilius <pb n="460" xml:id="p.460"/> Laenas and Cneius Manlius being consuls,
                    during the first silence of the night having set out from Tibur with an army
                    prepared for action, they came to the city of Rome. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The suddenness of the thing, and the panic occurring at
                    night, occasioned some terror among them on being suddenly aroused from sleep;
                    further, the ignorance of many as to who the enemy were or whence they had come.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However they quickly ran to arms, and
                    guards were posted at the gates, and the walls were secured with troops; and
                    when daylight showed but an inconsiderable force before the walls, and that the
                    enemy were none other than the Tiburtines, the consuls, having gone forth from
                    the two gates, attack on either side the army of these now advancing up to the
                    walls; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and it became obvious that they had
                    come relying rather on the opportunity than on their valour, for they hardly
                    sustained the first charge of the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nay
                    more, it was evident that their coming proved an advantage to the Romans, and
                    that a disturbance just arising between the patricians and commons was checked
                    by the dread of a war so near them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the
                    next war there was another irruption of the enemy, more terrible to the country
                    than to the city. The Tarquinians overran the Roman frontiers, committing
                    depredations on that side more especially where they are contiguous to Etruria;
                    and restitution being demanded in vain, the new consuls, Cneius Fabius and Caius
                    Plautius, proclaimed war on them by order of the people; and that province fell
                    to the lot of Fabius, the Hernicians to Plautius. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> A rumour of a Gallic war also was gaining ground.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But amid their many terrors, they had some
                    consolation from a peace granted to the Latins at their own request, as also
                    from a considerable reinforcement of soldiers received from them in conformity
                    with an old treaty, which they had for several years ceased to observe.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the Roman cause was supported by this
                    aid, the tidings that the Gauls had come to Praeneste and were encamped near to
                    Pedum, were less heeded. It was determined that Caius Sulpicius should be
                    appointed dictator. Caius Plautius the consul, being sent for for the purpose,
                    nominated him; Marcus Valerius was assigned as master of the horse to the
                    dictator. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These having selected the best of
                    the soldiers out of the two consular armies, led them against the Gauls. This
                    war was more tedious than was satisfactory to either party. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When at <pb n="461" xml:id="p.461"/> first the Gauls only
                    were desirous of fighting, afterwards the Roman soldiers considerably surpassed
                    the ferocity of the Gauls in their ardour for arms and battle; it by no means
                    met the approbation of the dictator when no urgent necessity existed to run any
                    hazard against an enemy, whose strength time and inconvenient situation would
                    daily impair, in total inactivity, without provisions previously laid up or any
                    fortified situation; besides, being persons of such minds and bodies, that all
                    their force lay in brisk exertion, whilst the same flagged by short delay.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On these considerations the dictator
                    protracted the war, and denounced a severe penalty against any one who should
                    fight against the enemy without orders. The soldiers, being much dissatisfied
                    with this, first censured the dictator, in their conversation, when on guard and
                    on the watches; sometimes they found fault with the patricians in general, for
                    not having commanded the war to be conducted by the consuls. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That an excellent general, an extraordinary commander, had been
                        selected, who thinks that whilst he does nothing victory will fly down from
                        heaven into his lap. </quote> Afterwards they gave expression to these same
                    sentiments openly during the day, and to others still more outrageous; that
                        <quote> they would either fight without the general's orders, or would
                        proceed in a body to Rome. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The centurions, too, began to mix with the
                    soldiers; and they murmured not only in their own quarters, but now their
                    observations began to be confounded together at head-quarters and at the
                    general's tent, and the crowd increased to the magnitude of an assembly, and
                    they now shouted from all quarters that <quote> they should go forthwith to the
                        dictator; that Sextus Tullius should speak in behalf of the army, so as
                        became his courage. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Tullius was now for the seventh time first
                    centurion of a legion, nor was there in the army, at least among those who
                    served in the infantry, a man more distinguished by his conduct. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> He, at the head of a body of the soldiers, proceeds
                    to the tribunal, and to Sulpicius, not more surprised at the crowd than at
                    Tullius, the leader of the crowd, a soldier most obedient to command, he says:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Dictator, the whole army, conceiving that they have been condemned by
                        you of cowardice, and kept without their arms by way of disgrace, has
                        entreated me to plead their cause before you. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In truth, if having deserted our post any where, if
                        turning our backs to the enemy, <pb n="462" xml:id="p.462"/> if the
                        disgraceful loss of our standards could be laid to our charge, I would still
                        think it but just that we should obtain this from you, that you would suffer
                        us to redeem our fault by our bravery, and to blot out the memory of our
                        disgrace by newly acquired glory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even the
                        legions defeated at the Allia, when they afterwards set out from Veii,
                        recovered by their valour the same country which they had lost through a
                        panic. We, by the bounty of the gods, your good fortune, and that of the
                        Roman people, have both our cause and our glory uninjured. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Though of glory I would scarcely venture to say any
                        thing; since both the enemy scoff at us with every kind of insult, as women
                        hiding ourselves behind a rampart; and you, our general, what we grieve at
                        still more, judge your army to be without spirit, without arms, without
                        hands; and before you had made trial of us, you have so despaired of us, as
                        to consider yourself to be the leader of a set of maimed and disabled men.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For what else shall we believe to be
                        the reason why you, a veteran general, most valiant in war, sit down with
                        hands folded, as they say. But however it may be, it is fitter that you
                        should seem to doubt of our courage than we of yours. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> If however this plan of proceeding be not your own, but
                        a public one, if some concerted scheme of the patricians, and not the Gallic
                        war, keeps us exiled from the city, from our homes, I beg that you consider
                        what I may say here, as addressed not by soldiers to their general, but to
                        the patricians by the commons, who tell you that as ye have your separate
                        plans, so will they have theirs. Who in the name of goodness can be angry
                        that we (consider ourselves) your soldiers, not your slaves? <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> as men who have been sent to war, not into exile?
                        as men who, if any one give the signal, and lead them out into the field,
                        will fight as becomes men and Romans? as men who, if there be no need of
                        arms, would spend their idle time in Rome rather than in a camp? <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Consider these observations as addressed to the
                        patricians. As your soldiers, we entreat you, general, to afford us an
                        opportunity of fighting. We both desire to conquer, and also to conquer with
                        you for our leader; to confer on you the distinguished laurel, with you to
                        enter the city in triumph; following your car with congratulations and
                        rejoicings, to approach the temple of Jupiter supremely great and good. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The entreaties of the multitude followed the
                    speech of Tullius; and from every <pb n="463" xml:id="p.463"/> side they cried
                    out, that he would give the signal, that he would order them to take arms. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator, though he saw that a good result
                    was brought about by a precedent not to be approved of, yet took on himself to
                    do what the soldiers wished, an inquires of Tullius privately, what the nature
                    of this transaction was, or on what precedent it was done? <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Tullius earnestly entreated the dictator <quote> not to
                        believe him forgetful of military discipline, of himself, nor of the respect
                        due to his general; that he had not declined to put himself at the head of
                        the excited multitude, who generally were like to their instigators, lest
                        any other person might step forward, such an excited multitude were wont to
                        elect. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That for his own part he would do
                        nothing without the orders of his general; that he also however must
                        carefully see, that he keep the army in obedience. That minds so excited
                        could not be put off: that they would choose for themselves time and place,
                        if they were not granted by the general. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While they are conversing in this way, it so
                    happened, that as a Gaul was driving away some cattle feeding on the outside of
                    the rampart two Roman soldiers took them from him. Stones were throw at them by
                    the Gauls, then a shout was raised at the next Roman post, and several ran
                    forward on both sides. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And now matters were
                    not far from a regular engagement, had no the contest been quickly stopped by
                    the centurions. By this event the testimony of Tullius was certainly confirmed
                    with the dictator; and the matter not admitting of further delay, a proclamation
                    is issued that they were to fight on the day following. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator however, as one who went into the field
                    relying more on the courage of his men than on their numerical strength, began
                    to look about and consider how he might by some artifice strike terror into the
                    enemy. With a sagacious mind he devises a new project, which many generals both
                    of our own and of foreign countries have since adopted, some indeed in our own
                    times. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He orders the panniers to be taken from
                    the mules, and two side-cloths only being left, he mounts the muleteers on them,
                    equipped with arms partly belonging to the prisoners, and some to the sick.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> About a thousand of these being equipped,
                    he mixes with them one hundred horsemen, and orders them to go up during the
                    night into the mountains over the camp and to conceal <pb n="464" xml:id="p.464"
                    /> themselves in the woods, and not to stir from thence, till they should
                    receive a signal from him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As soon as day
                    dawned, he himself began to extend his line along the bottom of the mountain,
                    for the express purpose that the enemy should face the mountains. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The measures for infusing groundless terror being
                    now completed, which terror indeed proved almost more serviceable than real
                    strength, the leaders of the Gauls first believed that the Romans would not come
                    down to the plain: then when they saw them begin on a sudden to descend, they
                    also, on their part eager for the fight, rush forward to the encounter; and the
                    battle commenced before the signal could be given by the leaders. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls attacked the right wing with greater
                    fierceness, nor could they have been withstood, had not the dictator happened to
                    be on the spot, rebuking Sextus Tullius by name, and asking him, <quote> Was it
                        in this way he had engaged that the soldiers would fight? <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Where now were the shouts of those demanding their
                        arms? where the threats that they would commence the fight without the
                        orders of their general? Behold the general himself calling them with a loud
                        voice to battle, and advancing in arms before the front of the line.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Would any of those now follow him, who
                        were just now to have led the way; fierce in the camp, but cowards in the
                        field? </quote> What they heard was all true; wherefore shame applied such
                    strong incentives, that they rushed upon the weapons of the enemy, their
                    attention being turned away from the thought of danger. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This onset, which was almost frantic at first, threw the
                    enemy into disorder; then the cavalry charging them whilst thus disordered, made
                    them turn their backs. The dictator himself, when he saw their line wavering in
                    one direction, carries round some troops to the left wing, where he saw a crowd
                    of the enemy collected, and gave to those who were on the mountain the signal
                    which had been agreed on. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When a new shout
                    arose from that quarter also, and they seemed to make their way in an oblique
                    direction, down the mountain to the camp of the Gauls; then through fear lest
                    they should be cut off from it, the fight was given up, and they were carried
                    towards the camp with precipitate speed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Where
                    when Marcus Valerius, master of the horse, who, after having routed their left
                    wing, was riding towards the enemies' entrenchment, met them, they turn their
                    flight to the mountains and woods: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and <pb
                        n="465" xml:id="p.465"/> the greater part of them were there intercepted by
                    the fallacious show of horsemen, and the muleteers, and of those whom panic had
                    carried into the woods, a dreadful slaughter took place after the battle was
                    ended. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor did any one since Camillus obtain a
                    more complete triumph over the Gauls than Caius Sulpicius. A considerable weight
                    of gold taken from the Gallic spoils, which he enclosed in hewn stone, he
                    consecrated in the Capitol. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The same year the
                    consuls also were engaged in fighting with various success. For the Hernicians
                    were vanquished and subdued by Cneius Plautius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> His colleague Fabius fought against the Tarquinians without caution or
                    prudence; nor was the loss sustained in the field so much [a subject of regret]
                    as that the Tarquinians put to death three hundred and seven Roman soldiers,
                    their prisoners, by which barbarous mode of punishment the disgrace of the Roman
                    people was rendered considerably more remarkable. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> To this disaster moreover was added, the laying waste of
                    the Roman territory, which the Privernatians, and afterwards the people of
                    Velitrae, committed by a sudden incursion. The same year two tribes, the
                    Pomptine and Publilian, were added. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                    votive games, which Marcus Furius in his dictatorship had vowed, were performed;
                    and a proposition was then for the first time made to the people regarding
                    bribery at elections by Caius Paetilius, tribune of the commons, with the
                    approbation of the senate; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and by that bill
                    they thought that the ambition of new men in particular, who had been accustomed
                    to go around the markets and places of meeting, was checked. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not equally pleasing to the patricians on the
                    following year was a law passed in the consulship of Caius Marcius and Cneius
                    Manlius, by Marcus Duilius and Lucius Maenius, tribunes of the commons,
                    regarding the interest of money at twelve per cent., and the people received and
                    passed it with much more eagerness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In
                    addition to the new wars determined on the preceding year, a new enemy arose in
                    the Faliscians, in consequence of a double charge; both that their youth had
                    taken up arms in conjunction with the Tarquinians, and because they had refused
                    to restore to the demand of the Roman heralds those who had fled to Falerii,
                    after the unsuccessful battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That province
                    fell to the lot of Cneius Manlius, Marcius led the army into the Privernatian
                    territory, which, from the long continuance of peace, was in a flourishing <pb
                        n="466" xml:id="p.466"/> condition; and he enriched the soldiers with
                    abundance of spoil. To the great quantity of effects he added an act of
                    munificence; for, by setting aside nothing for public use, he favoured the
                    soldier in his endeavours to accumulate private property. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When the Privernatians had taken their post in a
                    well-fortified camp under their own walls, having summoned the soldiers to an
                    assembly, he says to them, <quote> I now give to you the camp and city of the
                        enemy for plunder, if you promise me that you will exert yourselves bravely
                        in the field, and that you are not better prepared for plunder than for
                        fighting. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With loud shouts they call for the signal, and
                    elated and buoyed up with certain confidence, they proceed to the battle. Then,
                    in front of the line, Sextus Tullius, whom we have already mentioned, exclaims,
                        <quote>Behold, general,</quote> says he, <quote>how your army are performing
                        their promises to you;</quote> and laying aside his javelin, he attacks the
                    enemy sword in hand. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The whole van follow
                    Tullius, and at the first onset put the enemy to flight; then pursuing them,
                    when routed, to the town, when they were just applying the scaling ladders to
                    the walls, they received the city on a surrender. A triumph was had over the
                    Privernatians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nothing worth mentioning was
                    achieved by the other consul, except that he, by an unusual precedent, holding
                    an assembly of the tribes in the camp at Sutrium, he passed a law regarding the
                    twentieth part of the value of those set free by manumission. As by this law no
                    small revenue was added to the treasury, now low, the senate gave it their
                    sanction. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But the tribunes of the commons,
                    influenced not so much by the law as by the precedent, passed a law, making it a
                    capital offence for any one in future to summon an assembly of the people at a
                    distance from the city; for if that were allowed, there was nothing, no matter
                    how destructive to the people, that might not be done by soldiers, who had sworn
                    allegiance to their consul. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The same year
                    Caius Licinius Stolo was condemned in a fine of ten thousand <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses,</hi> on his own law, by Marcus Popillius Laenas, because he
                    possessed in conjunction with his son a thousand acres of land, and because he
                    had attempted to evade the law by emancipating his son. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next two consuls, Marcus Fabius Ambustus a
                    second time, and Marcus Popillius Laenas a second time, had two wars on their
                    hands. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The one with the Tiburtians was easy,
                        <pb n="467" xml:id="p.467"/> which Licinius managed, who drove the enemy
                    into their city, and laid waste their lands. The Faliscians and Tarquinians
                    routed the other consul in the commencement of the fight. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> From these parties the utmost terror was raised, in
                    consequence of their priests, who, by carrying before them lighted torches and
                    the figures of serpents, and advancing with the gait of furies, disconcerted the
                    Roman soldiers by their extraordinary appearance; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and then indeed they ran back to their entrenchments, in
                    all the hurry of trepidation, as if frenzied or thunderstruck; and then when the
                    consul, and lieutenant-generals, and tribunes began to ridicule and chide them
                    for being frightened like children at mere sights, shame suddenly changed their
                    minds; and they rushed, as if blindfold, on those very objects from which they
                    had fled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having, therefore, dissipated the
                    idle contrivance of the enemy having attacked those who were in arms, they drove
                    their whole line before them, and having got possession of the camp also on that
                    day, and obtained great booty, they returned victorious, uttering military
                    jests, both on the stratagem of the enemy as also on their own panic. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Then the whole Etruscan nation is aroused, and under
                    the conduct of the Tarquinians and Faliscians, they come to Salinae. To meet
                    this alarm, Caius Marcius Rutilus, being appointed dictator, the first plebeian
                    who was so, named Caius Plautius, also a plebeian, master of the horse.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This was deemed an indignity by the
                    patricians, that the dictatorship also was now become common, and with all their
                    exertions they prevented any thing from either being decreed or prepared for the
                    dictator, for the prosecution of that war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    With the more promptitude, on that account, did the people order things, as
                    proposed by the dictator. Having set out from the city, along both sides of the
                    Tiber, and transporting his army on rafts <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    whithersoever his intelligence of the enemy led him, he surprised many of them
                    straggling about in scattered parties, laying waste the lands. Moreover, he
                    suddenly attacked their camp and took it; and eight thousand of the enemy being
                    made. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> prisoners, all the rest being either
                    slain or driven out of the Roman territory, he triumphed by order of the people,
                    without the sanction of the senate. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Because
                    they neither wished that the consular elections should be held by a plebeian
                    dictator or consul, and the other consul, Fabius, was detained by the war,
                    matters came to an interregnum. There <pb n="468" xml:id="p.468"/> were then
                    interreges in succession, Quintus Servilius Ahala, Marcus Fabius, Cneius
                    Manlius, Caius Fabius, Caius Sulpicius, Lucius Aemilius, Quintus Servilius,
                    Marcus Fabius Ambustas. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the second
                    interregnum a dispute arose, because two patrician consuls were elected: and the
                    tribunes protesting, Fabius the interrex said, that <quote> it was a law in the
                        twelve tables, that whatever the people ordered last should be law and in
                        force; that the suffrages of the people were their orders. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When the tribunes by their protest had been
                    able to effect nothing else than to put off the elections, two patricians were
                    chosen consuls, Caius Sulpicius Peticus a third time, Marcus Valerius Publicola;
                    and on the same day they entered into office. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the four hundredth year after the building
                    of the city of Rome, and the thirty-fifth after its recovery from the Gauls, the
                    consulship being taken away from the commons after eleven years, consuls, both
                    patricians, entered into office after the interregnum, Caius Sulpicius Peticus a
                    third time, and Marcus Valerius Publicola. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    During this year Empulum was taken from the Tiburtians with a struggle not worth
                    mentioning; whether the war was waged there under the auspices of the two
                    consuls, as some have stated; or whether the lands of the Tarquinians were laid
                    waste by the consul Sulpicius about the same time that Valerius led the troops
                    against the Tiburtians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls had a more
                    arduous contest at home with the commons and tribunes. As two patricians had
                    received the consulship, they considered that not only their resolution, but
                    their honour also, was involved in their consigning it to two patricians.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For if the consulship were made a plebeian
                    magistracy, they must either yield it up entirely, or possess it entire, which
                    possession they had received from their fathers unimpaired. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The commons on the other hand loudly remonstrate; <quote>
                        Why did they live; why were they reckoned in the number of citizens; if they
                        collectively cannot maintain that which was acquired by the firmness of two
                        men, Lucius Sextius and Caius Licinius? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        That either kings, or decemvirs, or, if there be any denomination of power
                        more offensive, would be submitted to rather than see both the consuls
                        patricians, or rather than not obey and rule in turn; <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> but the one half, located in perpetual power, thinks
                        the commons born for no other purpose than to be subservient. </quote> The
                    tribunes are not <pb n="469" xml:id="p.469"/> remiss in encouraging the
                    disturbances; but amid the excited state of all scarcely any are distinguished
                    as leaders. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they had several times gone
                    down to the Campus Martius to no purpose, and when many days of meeting had been
                    spent in seditious movements; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> at length the
                    resentment of the commons, overcome by the perseverance of the consuls, broke
                    out to such a degree, that the commons followed in sorrow the tribunes,
                    exclaiming, that there was an end of liberty; that not only the Campus should be
                    relinquished, but the city also as being held captive and oppressed by the
                    tyranny of the patricians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consuls,
                    deserted by a part of the people, finish the election nevertheless with the
                    small number [who attended]. Both the consuls elected were patricians, Marcus
                    Fabius Ambustus a third time, Titus Quinctius. In some annals I find Marcus
                    Popilius mentioned as consul instead of Titus Quinctius. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Two wars were conducted with success on that
                    year: and they forced the Tiburtians by force of arms to a surrender. The city
                    of Sassula was taken from them; and the other towns would have shared the same
                    fate, had not the entire nation laid down their arms, and put themselves under
                    the protection of the consul. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A triumph was
                    obtained by him over the Tiburtians: in other respects the victory was a mild
                    one. Rigorous severity was practised against the Tarquinians. A great many being
                    slaughtered in the field, out of a great number of prisoners three hundred and
                    fifty-eight were selected, all of the highest rank, to be sent to Rome; the rest
                    of the multitude were put to the sword. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nor
                    were the people more merciful towards those who had been sent to Rome. They were
                    all beaten with rods and beheaded in the middle of the forum. That was the
                    punishment retaliated on the enemy for their butchering the Romans in the forum
                    of Tarquinii. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The successes in war induced the
                    Samnites to seek their friendship. A courteous answer was returned to their
                    ambassadors by the senate: they were received into an alliance by a treaty.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman commons had not the same success
                    at home as in war. For though the burden of interest money had been relieved by
                    fixing the rate at one to the hundred, the poor were overwhelmed by the
                    principal alone, and submitted to confinement. On this account, the commons took
                    little heed either of the two consuls being patricians, or the management of the
                    elections, by reason of their private <pb n="470" xml:id="p.470"/> distresses.
                    Both consulships therefore remained with the patricians. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls appointed were Caius Sulpicius Paeticus a
                    fourth time, Marcus Valerius Publicola a second time. Whilst the state was
                    occupied with the Etrurian war, [entered into] because a report prevailed that
                    the people of Caere had joined the Tarquinians through compassion for them from
                    their relationship, ambassadors from the Latins drew their attention to the
                    Volscians, bringing tidings that an army enlisted and fully armed was now on the
                    point of attacking their frontiers; from thence that they were to enter the
                    Roman territory in order to commit depredations. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> The senate therefore determined that neither affair should be neglected; they
                    ordered that troops should be raised for both purposes, and that the consuls
                    should cast lots for the provinces. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    greater share of their anxiety afterwards inclined to the Etrurian war; after it
                    was ascertained, from a letter of the consul Sulpicius, to whom the province of
                    Tarquinii had fallen, that the land around the Roman Salinae had been
                    depopulated, and that part of the plunder had been carried away into the country
                    of the people of Caere, and that the young men of that people were certainly
                    among the depredators. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The senate therefore,
                    having recalled the consul Valerius, who was opposed to the Volscians, and who
                    had his camp on the frontiers of Tusculum, ordered him to nominate a dictator.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He nominated Titus Manlius, son of
                    Lucius. He, after he had appointed Aulus Cornelius Cossus his master of the
                    horse, content with the consular army, declared war against the Caeritians by
                    order of the people, with the sanction of the senate. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then for the first time were the Caeritians
                    seized with a real dread of war, as if there was greater power in the words of
                    the enemy to indicate war than in their own acts, who had provoked the Romans by
                    devastation; and they perceived how ill suited the contest was to their
                    strength. They repented of their depredations, and cursed the Tarquinians as the
                    instigators of the revolt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nor did any one
                    think of preparing arms and hostilities; but each strenuously urged the
                    necessity of sending ambassadors to sue for pardon for their error. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> When their ambassadors applied to the senate, being
                    referred by the senate to the people, they implored the gods, whose sacred
                    utensils they had received in the Gallic war and <pb n="471" xml:id="p.471"/>
                    treated with all due ceremony, that the same compassion for them might influence
                    the Romans now in a flourishing condition, which had formerly influenced
                    themselves when the state of the Roman people was distressed; and turning to the
                    temple of Vesta, they invoked the bonds of hospitality subsisting [between
                    themselves] and the flamens and vestals entered into by them with holy and
                    religious zeal: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Would any one believe that persons, who possessed such merits, had
                        suddenly become enemies without cause? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> or
                        if they had committed any act in a hostile manner, that they had, through
                        design rather than under the influence of error from frenzy, so acted, as to
                        cancel their former acts of kindness by recent injuries, more especially
                        when conferred on persons so grateful, and that they would choose to
                        themselves as enemies the Roman people, now in the most flourishing state
                        and most successful in war, whose friendship they had cultivated when they
                        were distressed? That they should not call it design, which should rather be
                        called force and necessity. That the Tarquinians, passing through their
                        territory with a hostile army, after they had asked for nothing but a
                        passage, forced with them some of their peasants, to accompany them in that
                        depredation, which was charged on them as a crime. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That they were prepared to deliver them up, if it
                        pleased them that they should be delivered up; or that they should be
                        subjected to punishment, if [they desired] that they should be punished.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That Caere, the sanctuary of the Roman
                        people, the harbourer of its priests, the receptacle of the sacred utensils
                        of Rome, they should suffer to escape, in regard to the ties of hospitality
                        contracted with the vestals, and in regard to the religious devotion paid to
                        their gods, intact and unstained with the charge of hostilities committed. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The people were influenced not so much by [the
                    merits of] the present case, as by their former deserts, so as to be unmindful
                    rather of the injury than of the kindness. Peace was therefore granted to the
                    people of Caere, and it was resolved that the making of a truce for one hundred
                    years should be referred to a decree of the senate. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Against the Faliscians, implicated in the same charge, the
                    force of the war was turned; but the enemy was no where found. Though their
                    territories were visited in all directions with devastation, they refrained from
                    besieging the towns; and the legions being brought back to <pb n="472"
                        xml:id="p.472"/> Rome, the remainder of the year was spent in repairing the
                    walls and the towers, and the temple of Apollo was dedicated. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of the year a dispute between the
                    patricians and commons suspended the consular elections, the tribunes refusing
                    to allow the elections to be held, unless they were held conformably to the
                    Licinian law; the dictator being determined to do away with the consulate
                    altogether from the state, rather than to make it common to the patricians and
                    the commons. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly when, the elections
                    being repeatedly adjourned, the dictator resigned his office, matters came to an
                    interregnum. Upon this, when the interreges found the commons incensed against
                    the fathers, the contest was carried on by various disturbances to the eleventh
                    interrex. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes held out as their plea,
                    the protection of the Licinian law. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The people
                    had the painful sense of the increasing weight of interest nearer to their
                    hearts; and their private troubles became predominant amid the public contests.
                    Through the wearisome effects of which the patricians ordered Lucius Cornelius
                    Scipio, the interrex, for peace' sake to observe the Licinian law in the
                    election of consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To Publius Valerius
                    Publicola, Caius Marcius Rutilus, a plebeian, was assigned as a colleague. Once
                    their minds were disposed to concord, the new consuls, setting about to relieve
                    the affair of the interest money also, which seemed to prevent perfect
                    unanimity, made the payment of the debts a matter of public concern, five
                    commissioners having been appointed, whom from their management of the money
                    they called bankers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By their justice and
                    diligence they deserved to have their names signalized by the records of every
                    history. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were Caius Duilius, Publius
                    Decius Mus, Marcus Papirius, Quintus Publilius, and Titus Aemilius; who
                    underwent a task most difficult to be managed, and dissatisfactory in general to
                    both parties, certainly always so to one, both with moderation in other
                    respects, as well as at the public expense, rather than with any loss [to the
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> creditors]. For the tardy debts and
                    those which were more troublesome, rather by the inertness of the debtors than
                    by want of means, either the treasury paid off, tables with money being placed
                    in the forum, in such a manner that the public was first secured; or a
                    valuation, at equitable prices, of their property freed them; so that not only
                    without injury, but even without com- <pb n="473" xml:id="p.473"/> plaints on
                    either side, an immense amount of debt was cleared off. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> After this a groundless alarm of an Etrurian war, as there
                    was a report that the twelve states had conspired, rendered it necessary that a
                    dictator should be appointed. Caius Julius was nominated in the camp, (for the
                    decree of the senate was sent thither to the consuls,) to whom Lucius Aemilius
                    was attached as master of the horse. But all things were quiet abroad. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An attempt made at home by the dictator, to
                    have the election of two patrician consuls, brought the government to an
                    interregnum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The two interreges, Caius
                    Sulpicius and Marcus Fabius, succeeded in that which the dictator had in vain
                    attempted, scil. in having both the consuls elected from the patricians, the
                    people being rather more appeased in consequence of the service done them in
                    lightening their debts. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The persons elected
                    were, Caius Sulpicius Peticus himself, who first resigned the office of
                    interrex, and Titus Quinctius Pennus. Some attach the name of Kaeso, others that
                    of Caius to Quinctius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They both set out to
                    the war, Quinctius to the Faliscian, Sulpicius to the Tarquinian; and the enemy
                    no where meeting them in the field, they waged war more against the lands than
                    the men, by burning and laying waste every thing, by the <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> debilitating effects of which, as of a slow consumption,
                    the pertinacity of both states was so broken, that they solicited a truce, first
                    from the consuls, then through their permission from the senate. They obtained a
                    truce for forty years. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus the concern
                    regarding the two wars which were hanging over them being laid aside, whilst
                    there was some repose from arms, it was determined that a census should be
                    instituted, because the payment of the debt had changed the owners of much
                    property. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But when the assembly was proclaimed
                    for the appointment of censors, Caius Marcius Rutilus, who had been the first
                    plebeian dictator, having declared himself a candidate for the censorship,
                    disturbed the harmony of the different orders. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    This step he seemed to have taken at an unseasonable time; because both the
                    consuls then happened to be patricians, who declared that they would take no
                    account of him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But he both succeeded in his
                    undertaking by his own perseverance, and the tribunes aided him by recovering a
                    right lost in the election of the consuls; and both the worth of the man brought
                    him to the <pb n="474" xml:id="p.474"/> level of the highest honour, and also
                    the commons were anxious that the censorship also should be brought within their
                    participation through the medium of the same person who had opened a way to the
                    dictatorship. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor was any dissent [from this
                    feeling] evinced at the election, so that Marcius was elected censor along with
                    Cneius Manlius. This year also had Marcus Fabius as dictator, not by reason of
                    any terror of war, but in order that the Licinian law should not be observed at
                    the consular elections. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Quintus Servilius was
                    attached to the dictator as master of the horse. Nor yet did the dictatorship
                    render that combination of the senators more effectual at the consular
                    elections, than it had proved at that of the censors. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Popillius Laenas was chosen consul on
                    the part of the commons, Lucius Cornelius Scipio on that of the patricians.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fortune even rendered the plebeian consul
                    more distinguished; for when news was brought that a vast army of the Gauls had
                    pitched their camp in the Latin territory, Scipio being attacked with a serious
                    fit of illness, the Gallic war was intrusted out of course to Popillius.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He having raised an army with great
                    energy, after he had ordered the younger citizens to assemble in arms outside
                    the Capuan gate, and the quaestors to carry the standards from the treasury to
                    the same place, having completed four legions, he gave the surplus of the men to
                    the praetor Publius Valerius Publicola, recommending to the senate to raise
                        <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> another army, which might be a reserve
                    to the state against the sudden contingencies of war. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He himself, after sufficiently preparing and arranging
                    every thing, proceeds towards the enemy; and in order to ascertain their
                    strength before he should hazard a decisive action, he commenced drawing an
                    intrenchment on a hill, the nearest he could select to the camp of the Gauls.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They being a fierce race and of an eager
                    turn for fighting, when, on descrying the standards of the Romans at a distance,
                    they drew out their forces, as expecting to commence the battle forthwith, when
                    they perceived that neither the opposite army descended into the plain, and that
                    the Romans were protected both by the height of the ground and also by the
                    entrenchments, supposing that they were dismayed with fear, and also more
                    exposed to attack, because they were intent on the work, they advance with a
                    furious shout. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the side of <pb n="475"
                        xml:id="p.475"/> the Romans neither the works were interrupted, (it was the
                    triarii who were employed at them,) but the battle was commenced by the hastati
                    and the principes, who stood in front of the workmen armed and prepared for the
                    fight. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides their own valour, the higher
                    ground aided them, so that all the spears and javelins did not fall ineffectual,
                    as when thrown on the same level, (as is generally the case,) but being steadied
                    by their own weight they took effect; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and the
                    Gauls weighed down by the weapons, with which they had their bodies transfixed,
                    or their shields rendered too cumbrous by those sticking in them. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> When they advanced almost up the steep at a run,
                    becoming irresolute, they at first halted; then when the very delay shook the
                    courage of the one party, and raised that of the enemy, being then pushed
                    backwards they fell one upon the other, and produced a carnage among themselves
                    more shocking than the carnage [caused by the enemy]. For more were crushed by
                    the precipitate rout, than there were slain by the sword. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nor as yet was the victory decided in favour
                    of the Romans; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> another difficulty still was
                    remaining for them after they had descended into the plain; for the great
                    numbers of the Gauls being such as to prevent all feeling of such a disaster,
                    raised up fresh troops against the victorious enemy, as if a new army rose up
                    once more. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And the Romans stood still,
                    suppressing their ardour; both because the struggle had to be undergone a second
                    time by them wearied as they were, and the consul, having his left arm well nigh
                    transfixed with a javelin, whilst he exposed himself incautiously in the van,
                    had retired for a short time from the field. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And now, by the delay, the victory was on the point of being relinquished, when
                    the consul, having had his wound tied up, riding back to the van, cries out,
                        <quote> Soldiers, why do you stand? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You
                        have not to do with a Latin or Sabine enemy, whom, when you have vanquished
                        by your arms, from an enemy you may make an ally; against brutes we have
                        drawn our swords. Their blood must be drawn or ours given to them. You have
                        repulsed them from your camp, you have driven them headlong down the valley,
                        you stand on the prostrated bodies of your foes. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Fill the plains with the same carnage as you have
                        filled the mountains; do not wait till they fly, you standing still;
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> your standards must be advanced, you
                            <pb n="476" xml:id="p.476"/> must proceed against the enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Roused again by these exhortations, they drive
                    back from their ground the foremost companies of the Gauls, and by forming
                    wedges, they break through the centre of their body. By these means, the enemy
                    being disunited, as being now without regular command, or subordination of
                    officers, they turn their violence against their own; and being dispersed
                    through the plains, and carried beyond their own camp in their precipitate
                    flight, they make for the citadel of Alba, which met their eyes as the most
                    elevated among hills of equal altitude. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    consul, not pursuing them beyond the camp, because the wound weakened him, and
                    he was unwilling to expose his wearied army to hills occupied by the enemy,
                    bestowed the entire plunder of the camp on the soldiers, and led back his army,
                    victorious and enriched with the Gallic spoils, to Rome. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The consul's wound occasioned a delay of the triumph, and
                    the same cause made the senate wish for a dictator, that there might be some one
                    who, the consuls being both sick, should hold the elections. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Furius Camillus being nominated dictator, Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio being attached as master of the horse, restored to the
                    patricians their former possession of the consulship. He himself being, for that
                    service, elected consul, had Appius Claudius Crassus named as his colleague. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the new consuls entered on their
                    office, a triumph was celebrated by Popillius over the Gauls amid the great
                    applause of the commons; and they, in a low voice, frequently asked one another,
                    whether any one was dissatisfied with a plebeian consul. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> At the same time they found fault with the dictator, who
                    had obtained the consulship as a bribe for having infringed the Licinian law,
                    more dishonourable for the private ambition [evinced] thereby than for the
                    injury inflicted on the public, so that, when dictator, he might have himself
                    appointed consul. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The year was remarkable for
                    many and various commotions. The Gauls [descending] from the Alban mountains,
                    because they were unable to endure the severity of the winter, straggling
                    through the plains and the parts adjoining the sea, committed devastations.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The sea was infested by fleets of the
                    Greeks; and the borders of the Antian shore, and the mouth of the Tiber; so that
                    the maritime plunderers, encountering those on land, fought on one occasion an
                    obstinate fight, and separated, the Gauls to their camp, the Greeks back to
                    their <pb n="477" xml:id="p.477"/> ships, doubting whether they should consider
                    themselves as vanquished or victors. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Among
                    these the greatest alarm arose at the circumstance, that assemblies of the Latin
                    states were held at the grove of Ferentina; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and an unequivocal answer was given to the Romans on their ordering soldiers
                    from them, <quote> that they should cease to issue their orders to those of
                        whose assistance they stood in need: that the Latins would take up arms in
                        defence of their own liberty, rather than for the dominion of others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate becoming uneasy at the defection of
                    their allies, whilst two foreign wars existed at the same time, when they
                    perceived that those whom fidelity had not restrained, should be restrained by
                    fear, ordered the consuls to exert to the utmost the energies of their authority
                    in holding a levy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For that they should depend
                    on an army of their countrymen, since their allies were deserting them. Ten
                    legions are said to have been levied, consisting each of four thousand two
                    hundred infantry and three hundred horse. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such
                    a newly-raised army, if any foreign force should assail, the present power of
                    the Roman people, which is scarcely confined within the whole world, could not
                    easily raise now, if concentrated upon one point: so true it is, we have
                    improved in those particulars only about which we are solicitous, riches and
                    luxury. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Among the other distressing events of
                    this year, Appius Claudius, one of the consuls, dies in the midst of the
                    preparations for the war; and the whole direction of affairs devolved on
                    Camillus; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> over whom, the only consul, it did
                    not appear seemly that a dictator should be appointed, either in consideration
                    of his high character, which should not be made subordinate to the dictatorship,
                    or on account of the auspicious omen of his surname with respect to a Gallic
                    war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consul, then, having stationed two
                    legions to protect the city, and divided the remaining eight with the praetor
                    Lucius Pinarius, mindful of his father's valour, selects the Gallic war for
                    himself without any appeal to lots: the praetor he commanded to protect the
                    sea-coast, and to drive the Greeks from the shore. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> And after he had marched down into the Pomptine territory,
                    because he neither wished to engage on the level ground, no circumstance
                    rendering it necessary, and he considered that the enemy were sufficiently
                    subdued, by preventing from plunder persons whom necessity obliged to live on
                    what was so obtained, he selected a suitable place for a fixed encampment. <pb
                        n="478" xml:id="p.478"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Where when they were spending the time in
                    quiet in their quarters, a Gaul, remarkable for his size and the appearance of
                    his arms, came forward; and striking his shield with his spear, after he had
                    procured silence, through an interpreter he challenged any one of the Romans to
                    contend with him with the sword. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was a
                    tribune of the soldiers, a young man, Marcus Valerius, who considering himself
                    not less worthy of that distinction than Titus Manlius, having first ascertained
                    the consul's pleasure, advanced fully armed into the middle space. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The human contest was rendered less remarkable by
                    reason of the interposition of the divine power. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> For just as the Roman was commencing the encounter, a crow settled suddenly
                    on his helmet, facing the enemy, which, as an augury sent from heaven, the
                    tribune at first received with pleasure. Then he prayed that whatever god or
                    goddess had sent him the auspicious bird, would willingly and kindly aid him.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Wondrous to relate, the bird not only kept
                    the place it had once taken, but as often as the encounter was renewed, raising
                    itself on its wings, it attacked the face and eyes of the foe with its beak and
                    talons, until Valerius slays him, terrified at the sight of such a prodigy, and
                    confounded both in his vision and understanding. The crow soaring out of sight
                    makes towards the east. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hitherto the advanced
                    guards on both sides remained quiet. When the tribune began to strip the body of
                    the slain enemy, neither the Gauls any longer confined themselves to their post,
                    and the Romans began to run to their successful champion with still greater
                    speed. There a scuffle taking place around the body of the prostrate Gaul, a
                    desperate fight is stirred up. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And now the
                    contest is carried on not by the companies of the nearest posts, but by the
                    legions pouring out from both sides. The soldiers exulting in the victory of the
                    tribune, and also at such favour and attention from the gods, are commanded by
                    Camillus to advance against the enemy: and he, pointing to the tribune
                    distinguished by the spoils, <quote>Soldiers,</quote> said he, <quote>imitate
                        this man; and around their fallen leader strew heaps of Gauls.</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Gods and men assisted at that fight; and the
                    struggle was carried on against the Gauls with a fury by no means equivocal in
                    its result, so thoroughly were both armies impressed with the respective success
                    of the two soldiers, between whom the single combat had taken place. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="479" xml:id="p.479"/> Among the first party, whose encounter had called
                    out the others, there was a desperate encounter: the rest of the soldiery,
                    before they came within throw of a weapon, turned their backs. At first they
                    were dispersed through the Volscians and the Falernian territory; thence they
                    made for Apulia and the upper sea. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    consul, calling an assembly, after heaping praises on the tribune, bestows on
                    him ten oxen and a golden crown. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He himself,
                    being commanded by the senate to take charge of the maritime war, joined his
                    camp to that of the praetor. There because matters seemed to be delayed by the
                    dastardly conduct of the Greeks, who did not venture into the field, with the
                    approbation of the senate, he nominated Titus Manlius Torquatus dictator.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The dictator, after appointing Aulus
                    Cornelius Cossus his master of the horse, held the consular elections, and with
                    the greatest applause of the people he returned Marcus Valerius Corvus (for that
                    was his surname from thenceforth) as consul though absent, the rival of his own
                    glory, then three and twenty years of age. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As
                    colleague to Corvus, Marcus Popillius Laenas, a plebeian, was assigned to be
                    consul for the fourth time. Nothing memorable occurred between Camillus and the
                    Greeks; neither the one were warriors by land, nor the Romans by sea. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> At length, when they were repelled from the shore,
                    among other things necessary for use, water also failing, they abandoned Italy.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> To what state or what nation that fleet
                    belonged, there is nothing certain. I would be most inclined to think that they
                    belonged to the tyrants of Sicily; for the farther Greece, being at that time
                    wearied by intestine war, was now in dread of the power of the Macedonians. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The armies being disbanded, whilst there was
                    both peace abroad, and tranquillity at home by reason of the concord of the
                    different orders, lest matters might be too happy, a pestilence having attacked
                    the state, compelled the senate to order the decemvirs to inspect the Sibylline
                    books, and by their suggestion a lectisternium took place. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The same year a colony was led to Satricum by the Antians,
                    and the city, which the Latins had demolished, was rebuilt. And a treaty was
                    concluded at Rome with the Carthaginian ambassadors, they having come to request
                    friendship and an alliance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The same
                    tranquillity continued at home and abroad, during the consulate of Titus Manlius
                    Torquatus and Caius Plautius. <pb n="480" xml:id="p.480"/> Only the interest of
                    money from twelve was reduced to six per cent; and the payment of the debts was
                    adjusted into equal portions of three years, on condition that the fourth
                    payment should be made at the present time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    And then also, though a portion of the commons were distressed, still public
                    credit engrossed the attention of the senate in preference to the difficulties
                    of private individuals. Their circumstances were relieved most effectually,
                    because a cessation was introduced of the taxes and levy. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On the third year after Satricum was rebuilt by the
                    Volscians, Marcus Valerius Corvus having been elected consul for the second time
                    with Caius Poetelius, when news had been brought from Latium, that ambassadors
                    from Antium were going round the states of the Latins to excite a war, being
                    ordered to attack the Volscians, before greater numbers of the enemy should be
                    assembled, proceeds to Satricum with his army ready for action. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> And when the Antians and other Volscians met him, their
                    forces being previously prepared, in case any movement should be made on the
                    part of Rome, no delay of engaging took place between the two parties incensed
                    with long pent-up hate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Volscians, a
                    nation more spirited to renew hostilities than to carry on war, being defeated
                    in the fight, make for the walls of Satricum in a precipitate flight; and their
                    reliance in their walls not being sufficiently strong, when the city,
                    encompassed by a continuous line of troops, was now on the point of being taken
                    by scalade, they surrendered to the number of four thousand soldiers, besides
                    the unarmed multitude. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The town was demolished
                    and burnt; only they kept the fire from the temple of Mother Matuta. The entire
                    plunder was given up to the soldiers. The four thousand who had surrendered were
                    considered exclusive of the spoil; these the consul when triumphing drove before
                    his chariot in chains; afterwards by selling them he brought a great sum of
                    money into the treasury. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There are some who
                    state that this body of captives consisted of slaves; and this is more probable
                    than that persons who had surrendered were exposed to sale. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Fabius Dorso and Servius Sulpicius
                    Camerinus succeeded these consuls. After this the Auruncan war commenced in
                    consequence of a sudden attempt at depredation: <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> and through fear lest this act of one state might be the concerted scheme of
                    the whole Latin nation, Lucius Furius being created <pb n="481" xml:id="p.481"/>
                    dictator, as if against all Latium already in arms, nominated Cneius Manlius
                    Capitolinus his master of the horse. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when,
                    a suspension of public business being proclaimed, (a measure usually adopted
                    during great alarms,) the levy was held without exemptions, the legions were led
                    against the Auruncans with all possible expedition. The spirit of freebooters
                    rather than of enemies was found there. They were vanquished therefore in the
                    first encounter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However the dictator, both
                    because they had commenced hostilities without provocation, and presented
                    themselves to the contest without reluctance, considering that the aid of the
                    gods should also be engaged, vowed a temple to Juno Moneta in the heat of the
                    battle, and when he returned victorious to Rome, obliged by his vow, he resigned
                    his dictatorship. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate ordered duumvirs
                    to be appointed to have the temple built suitably to the grandeur of the Roman
                    people; the site destined for it was in the citadel, where the ground was on
                    which the house of Marcus Manlius Capitolinus had stood. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls, having employed the dictator's army for the
                    Volscian war, took Sora from the enemy, having attacked them by surprise. The
                    temple of Moneta is dedicated the year after it had been vowed, Caius Marcius
                    Rutilus being consul for the third time, and Titus Manlius Torquatus for the
                    second time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A prodigy immediately followed
                    the dedication, similar to the ancient one of the Alban mount. For it both
                    rained stones, and during the day night seemed to be spread [over the sky]; and
                    on the books being inspected, the state being filled with religious scruples, it
                    was resolved by the senate that a dictator should be nominated for the purpose
                    of regulating the ceremonies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Publius Valerius
                    Publicola was nominated; Quintus Fabius Ambustus was assigned to him as master
                    of the horse. It was determined that not only the tribes, but the neighbouring
                    states also should offer supplications: and a certain order was appointed for
                    them on what day each should offer supplication. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Severe sentences of the people are said to have been passed on that year
                    against usurers, for whom a day of trial had been appointed by the aediles.
                    Matters came to an interregnum, there being no particular reason on record.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the interregnum, both the consuls
                    were elected from the patricians, Marcus Valerius Corvus a third time, and Aulus
                    Cornelius Cossus, so that it would seem that such was the end aimed at. <pb
                        n="482" xml:id="p.482"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Henceforward shall be recorded wars of greater
                    importance, both by the strength of the belligerent powers, by the distance of
                    the countries, or the length of time during which they were carried on. For in
                    that year arms were taken up against the Samnites, a nation powerful both in
                    wealth and in arms. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Pyrrhus followed as an
                    enemy the war of the Samnites carried on with various success, the Carthaginians
                    followed Pyrrhus. How great a mass of events! How often have extreme dangers
                    been encountered, that the empire might be raised to its present magnitude,
                    which is now scarcely sustained! <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the cause
                    of the war between the Samnites and Romans, as they had been joined in alliance
                    and friendship, came from without; it originated not among themselves.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the Samnites had unjustly taken up
                    arms, because they had the advantage in strength, against the Sidicinians, the
                    weaker party being obliged to have recourse to the aid of the more powerful,
                    unite themselves to the Campanians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As the
                    Campanians brought to the relief of their allies rather a name than strength,
                    enervated as they were by luxury, they were beaten in the Sidicinian territory
                    by men who were inured to the use of arms, and then brought on themselves the
                    entire burthen of the war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the Samnites,
                    taking no further notice of the Sidicinians, having attacked the Campanians as
                    being the chief of the neighbouring states, from whom the victory might be
                    equally easy, and a greater share of spoil and glory, after they had secured
                    Tifata, a ridge of hills hanging over Capua, with a strong garrison, they march
                    down from thence with their army formed in a square into the plain which lies
                    between Capua and Tifata. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There a second
                    battle was fought; and the Campanians, after an unsuccessful fight, being driven
                    within their walls, when the flower of their youth being cut down, no hope was
                    nigh at hand, they were obliged to sue for aid from the Romans. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their ambassadors, being introduced into the
                    senate, spoke as near as possible to this purport: <quote> Conscript fathers,
                        the Campanian state has sent us to you, to solicit from you friendship for
                        ever, and present aid, which if we had solicited whilst our affairs were
                        prosperous, as it would have commenced more readily, so would it have been
                        bound by a weaker tie. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For then, as we
                        should have recollected that we entered into friendship on equal terms, we
                        might be equally friendly as <pb n="483" xml:id="p.483"/> now, but less
                        submissive and compliant with your wishes Now, won over by your compassion
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> for us, and defended by your aid in
                        our critical circumstances, it is incumbent on us that we show our sense
                        also of the kindness received; lest we should seem ungrateful, and
                        undeserving of aid from either god or man. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Nor, indeed, do I think that because the Samnites first became your allies
                        and friends, such a circumstance is sufficient to prevent our being admitted
                        into friendship; but merely shows that they excel us in priority and in the
                        degree of honour; for no provision has been made in your treaty with the
                        Samnites that you should not form any new treaties. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It has ever been with you a sufficient title to your
                        friendship, that he who sought it desired to be a friend of yours.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> We, Campanians, though our present
                        state forbids us to speak in high terms, not yielding to any state save you
                        in the extent of our city, or in the fertility of our land, come into
                        friendship with you, no inconsiderable accession in my opinion to your
                        flourishing condition. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We shall be in the
                        rear of the Aequans and Volscians, the eternal enemies of this city,
                        whenever they may stir; and whatever ye shall be the first to perform in
                        defence of our safety, the same shall we ever do in defence of your empire
                        and glory. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those nations which lie between
                        us and you being reduced, which both your bravery and good fortune makes it
                        certain will soon be the case, you will then have an uninterrupted empire
                        extending even to us. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It is distressing
                        and painful, what our condition obliges us to confess. Conscript fathers,
                        matters are come to this, that we Campanians must be the property either of
                        friends or enemies. If you defend us, yours; if you desert us, we shall be
                        the property of the Samnites. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Consider,
                        then, whether you would rather that Capua and all Campania should be added
                        to your power or to that of the Samnites. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        Romans, it is surely but just, that your compassion and your aid should lie
                        open to all men; to those, however, chiefly, who, whilst they afford it
                        beyond their means to others imploring aid, have themselves been involved in
                        this distress. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Although we fought
                        nominally for the Sidicinians, in reality for ourselves, when we saw a
                        neighbouring state assailed by the nefarious plunder of the Samnites; and
                        after the Sidicinians had been consumed, we saw that the conflagration would
                        pass over to ourselves. For the Samnites do <pb n="484" xml:id="p.484"/> not
                        come to attack us, because they resent an injury received, but because they
                        are glad that a pretext has been presented to them. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> If this were the gratification of their resentment, and
                        not an occasion for satiating their ambition, <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> was it not sufficient that they cut down our legions
                        once in the Sidicinian territory, a second time in Campania itself? What
                        sort of resentment must that be, which the blood shed in two pitched battles
                        cannot satiate? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> To this add the laying
                        waste of our lands; the spoil of men and cattle driven away, the burning and
                        ruin of our country-houses, every thing destroyed by fire and sword. Could
                        not resentment be satisfied with this? But ambition must be satiated. That
                        hurries them on to besiege Capua. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> They
                        either wish to destroy that most beautiful city, or to possess it
                        themselves. But, Romans, do you take possession of it in your kindness,
                        rather than suffer them to hold it by injustice. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> I am not addressing a people who decline just wars; but
                        still, if you make but a show of your aid, I do not think that you will have
                        occasion for war. The contempt of the Samnites has just reached to us; it
                        soars not higher. Accordingly, Romans, we may be protected even by the
                        shadow of your aid: whatever after this we shall possess, whatever we
                        ourselves shall be, determined to consider all that as yours. <milestone
                            n="18" unit="section"/> For you the Campanian field shall be ploughed;
                        for you the city of Capua shall be made populous; you shall be to us in the
                        light of founders, parents, ay, even immortal gods. <milestone n="19"
                            unit="section"/> There shall be no colony of your own which shall
                        surpass us in attachment and loyalty to you. Grant to the Campanians,
                        conscript fathers, your nod, and your irresistible favour, and bid us hope
                        that Capua will be safe. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> With what crowds
                        of persons of all classes attending us do you suppose that we set out from
                        thence how, think you, did we leave every place full of vows and tears?
                            <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> In what a state of expectation do you
                        suppose that the senate are, the Campanian nation, our wives and our
                        children? <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> I am certain that the entire
                        multitude are standing at the gates, looking forward to the road that leads
                        from hence, anxious as to what answer you may order us, conscript fathers,
                        to bring back to them, in their solicitude and suspense of mind. <milestone
                            n="23" unit="section"/> One kind of answer may bring them safety,
                        victory, light, and liberty what the other may, I feel horror to think.
                        Determine there- <pb n="485" xml:id="p.485"/> fore about us, as about
                        persons who will be your future friends and allies, or as persons who are to
                        have no existence any where. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors then withdrawing, after the
                    senate had been consulted, though to a great many, their city the greatest and
                    wealthiest in Italy, their land the most fertile, and situated near the sea,
                    seemed likely to prove a granary to the Roman people for all varieties of
                    provision; still the faith of their engagements was more regarded than such
                    great advantages, and the consul, by the direction of the senate, answered as
                    follows: <quote> Campanians, the senate considers you deserving of aid.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But it is meet that friendship be so
                        established with you, that no prior friendship and alliance be violated. The
                        Samnites are united in a treaty with us. Therefore we refuse you arms
                        against the Samnites, which would be a violation of duty to the gods first,
                        and then to men. We will as divine and human law requires, send ambassadors
                        to our allies and friends to entreat that no violence be committed against
                        you? </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To this the chief of the embassy replied, (for
                    such were the instructions they had brought from home,) <quote> Since you are
                        not willing to defend by just force our possessions against violence and
                        injustice, at least you will defend your own. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Wherefore, conscript fathers, we surrender the
                        Campanian people, and the city of Capua, their lands, the temples of the
                        gods, all things divine and human, into your jurisdiction and that of the
                        Roman people; whatever we shall suffer henceforth, being determined to
                        suffer as men who have surrendered to you. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On these words, all extending their hands
                    towards the consuls, bathed in tears they fell prostrate in the porch of the
                    senate-house. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The fathers, affected at the
                    vicissitude of human greatness, seeing that a nation abounding in wealth, noted
                    for luxury and pride, from which a little time since their neighbours had
                    solicited assistance, was now so broken in spirit, as to give up themselves and
                    all they possessed into the power of others; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    moreover, their honour also seemed to be involved in not betraying those who had
                    surrendered, nor did they consider that the people of the Samnites would act
                    fairly, if they should attack a territory and a city which had become the
                    property of the Roman people by a surrender. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It was resolved therefore, that ambassadors should be sent forthwith to the
                    Samnites; instructions were given <quote> that they <pb n="486" xml:id="p.486"/>
                        should lay before the Samnites the entreaties of the Campanians, the answer
                        of the senate duly mindful of the friendship of the Samnites, and finally
                        the surrender that had been concluded. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        That they requested, in consideration of the friendship and alliance
                        subsisting between them, that they would spare their subjects; and that they
                        would not carry hostilities into that territory which had become the
                        property of the Roman people. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If by
                        gentle measures they did not succeed, that they should denounce to the
                        Samnites in the name of the senate and Roman people, to withhold their arms
                        from the city of Capua and the Campanian territory. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When the ambassadors urged these matters in
                    the assembly of the Samnites, so fierce an answer was returned, that they not
                    only said that they would prosecute that war, but their magistrates, having gone
                    out of the senate-house, in the very presence of the ambassadors, summoned the
                    prefects of the cohorts; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and with a distinct
                    voice commanded them, to proceed forthwith into the Campanian territory, in
                    order to plunder it. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The result of this embassy being reported at
                    Rome, the care of all other concerns being laid aside, the senate, having
                    despatched heralds to demand satisfaction, and, because this was not complied
                    with, war being proclaimed in the usual way, they decreed that the matter should
                    be submitted to the people at the very earliest opportunity; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and both the consuls having set out from the city by order
                    of the people with two armies, Valerius into Campania, Cornelius into Samnium,
                    the former pitches his camp at Mount Gaurus, the latter at Saticula. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The legions of the Samnites met with Valerius first;
                    for they thought that the whole weight of the war would incline to that side. At
                    the same time resentment stimulated them against the Campanians, that they
                    should be so ready at one time to lend aid, at another to call in aid against
                    them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But as soon as they beheld the Roman
                    camp, they fiercely demanded the signal each from his leader; they maintained
                    that the Roman would bring aid to the Campanian with the same fate with which
                    the Campanian had done to the Sidicinian. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Valerius, having delayed for a few days in slight skirmishes for the purpose of
                    making trial of the enemy, displayed the signal <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> for battle, exhorting his men in few words <quote> not to
                        let the new war or the new enemy terrify them. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> In proportion as they should carry their arms to a
                        greater <pb n="487" xml:id="p.487"/> distance from the city, the more and
                        more unwarlike should the nation prove to be against whom they should
                        proceed That they should not estimate the valour of the Samnites by the
                        defeats of the Sidicinians and Campanians. Let the combatants be of what
                        kind they may be, that it was necessary that one side should be vanquished.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That as for the Campanians indeed,
                        they were undoubtedly vanquished more by circumstances flowing from
                        excessive luxury and by their own want of energy than by the bravery of the
                        enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What were the two successful wars
                        of the Samnites, during so many ages, against so many glorious exploits of
                        the Roman people, who counted almost more triumphs than years since the
                        building of their city? who held subdued by their arms all the states around
                        them, the Sabines, Etruria, the Latins, Hernicians, Aequans, Volscians,
                        Auruncans? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> who eventually drove by flight
                        into the sea, and into their ships, the Gauls, after slaughtering them in so
                        many engagements? That soldiers ought both to enter the field relying on
                        their national military renown, and on their own valour, and also to
                        consider under whose command and auspices the battle is to be fought;
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> whether he be one which is to be
                        listened to as a pompous exhorter, bold merely in words, unacquainted with
                        military labours, or one who knows how to wield arms himself also, to
                        advance before the standards, and to show himself in the midst of the
                        danger. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> My acts, not my words merely, I
                        wish you to follow; and to seek from me not military orders only, but
                        example also. It was not by intrigues merely, nor by cabals usual among the
                        nobles, but by this right hand, I procured for myself three consulships, and
                        the highest eulogies. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There was a time
                        when this could be said; [no wonder,] for you were a patrician, and sprung
                        from the liberators of your country; and that family of yours had the
                        consulship the same year that the city had consuls. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Now the consulship lies open in common to us patricians
                        and to you plebeians; nor is it, as formerly, the prize of birth, but of
                        valour. Look forward, therefore, soldiers, to even the highest honour.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Though you, as men, have, with the
                        approbation of the gods, given me this new surname of Corvus, the ancient
                        surname of our family, Publicolae, has not been erased from my memory.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> I ever do and ever have cultivated
                        the good will of the Roman commons abroad and at home, as a private man and
                        in public <pb n="488" xml:id="p.488"/> offices, high and low, as tribune
                        equally as when consul, with the same undeviating line of conduct through
                        all my successive consulships. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Now, with
                        respect to that which is at hand, with the aid of the gods, join with me in
                        seeking a new and complete triumph over the Samnites. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Never was a general on a more familiar footing
                    with his soldiers, by his performing all the duties among the lowest of the
                    soldiers without reluctance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Moreover in the
                    military sports, wherein equals vie with their equals in contests of swiftness
                    and strength, affable and condescending, he conquered and was conquered with the
                    same countenance; nor did he spurn any competitor who should offer; in his acts
                    kind according to the occasion; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> in his
                    conversation no less mindful of the ease of others than of his own dignity; and,
                    a thing than which nothing is more agreeable to the people, he administered his
                    offices by the same line of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> conduct by which
                    he had gained them. The whole army therefore, cheering the exhortation of their
                    leader with the utmost alacrity, march forth from the camp. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The battle commenced with equal hopes and equal strength on
                    both sides, as much as any battle ever did, with confidence in themselves, and
                    without contempt of their enemies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their
                    recent exploits and their double victory a few days before, increased the
                    spirits of the Samnites on the other side; the glories of four hundred years and
                    victory coeval with the building of their city [had the same effect] on the
                    Romans; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> to both sides, however, the
                    circumstance of the enemy being a new one gave additional anxiety. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The battle was a proof what spirits they possessed;
                    for they maintained the conflict in such a manner, that, for a considerable
                    time, the armies inclined to neither side. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Then the consul, thinking that some confusion should be caused among them, since
                    they could not be overpowered by force, endeavours to disorder their foremost
                    battalions by a charge of cavalry. And when he saw them wheel their troops
                    within a narrow compass in fruitless disorder, and that they could not open a
                    passage to the enemy, riding back to the van of the legions, after leaping from
                    his horse, he says, <quote> Soldiers, this is the task for us infantry;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> come on, as ye shall see me making
                        way with my sword, in whatever direction I shall advance into the enemy's
                        line, so let each man, with all his might, beat down those who oppose him.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> All those places, where their erected
                        spears now <pb n="489" xml:id="p.489"/> glitter, you shall see cleared by
                        widely-extended slaughter. </quote> He had uttered these words, when the
                    cavalry by order of the consul turn to the wings, and open a passage for the
                    legions to the centre of the line. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> First of
                    all, the consul attacks the enemy, and slays him whom he happened to engage.
                    Those on the right and left, fired at this sight, commence a dreadful fight,
                    each with the foe opposite him. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Samnites
                    obstinately stand their ground, though they receive more wounds than they
                    inflict. The battle had now lasted for a considerable time, great slaughter
                    occurred around the standards of the Samnites; in no part was there a flight, so
                    firmly had they made up their minds to be vanquished by death alone. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Wherefore the Romans, when they perceived their
                    strength to relax by fatigue, and but a small part of the day still remained,
                    fired with fury, rush upon the enemy. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then
                    for the first time it appeared that they were giving ground, and that the matter
                    was inclining to a flight; then the Samnites were taken, some slain; nor would
                    many have survived, had not night terminated the victory rather than the battle.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Both the Romans confessed, that they had
                    never fought with a more determined enemy; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    and the Samnites, on being asked what cause first drove them to fly after being
                    so determined, said, that it was the eyes of the Romans which seemed to them to
                    flash fire, and their distracted looks, and furious aspect; that more of terror
                    arose from thence, than from any thing else. Which terror they confessed not
                    only in the issue of the battle, but in their departure by night. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> Next day the Romans take possession of the deserted
                    camp of the enemy, whither all the Campanians flocked to congratulate them. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But this joy was well nigh alloyed by a great
                    loss sustained in Samnium. For the consul Cornelius, having set out from
                    Saticula, incautiously led his army into a mountainous tract, passable through a
                    deep defile, and beset on all sides by the enemy; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> nor did he perceive the enemy stationed over his head,
                    until a retreat could no longer be made with safety. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Whilst the Samnites delayed only till he should bring down
                    his entire army into the valley; Publius Decius, a tribune of the soldiers,
                    espies in the tract a hill higher than the rest, hanging over the enemies' camp,
                    rather steep to be ascended by an encumbered army, not difficult for such as
                    were lightly armed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He says therefore to the
                    consul, greatly alarmed in mind, "Aulus Cor- <pb n="490" xml:id="p.490"/>
                    nelius, do you perceive that elevated point above the enemy? That is the bulwark
                    of our hope and safety, if we briskly gain possession of it, which the Samnites
                    in their blindness have given up. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Only give me
                    the first rank and spearmen of one legion; when with these I shall have gained
                    the summit, do you proceed hence free from all apprehension, and save yourself
                    and the army. For the enemy, lying beneath us and [exposed thereby] to all our
                    weapons, will not be able to stir without destruction to themselves. After that
                    either the good fortune of the Roman people or our own bravery will extricate
                    us. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Being commanded by the consul, he received
                    the body of men [required] and proceeds by <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    secret paths through the mountain, nor was he observed by the enemy until he
                    approached the place which he was making for. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Then, whilst all were struck with astonishment, after he had attracted the eyes
                    of all to himself, he both afforded the consul time to draw off his army to more
                    advantageous ground, and he himself was posted on the top of the hill.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Samnites, whilst they march their
                    forces now in this direction, now in that, having lost the opportunity of
                    effecting either object, can neither pursue the consul, unless through the same
                    defile in which they had him a little before exposed to their weapons, nor march
                    up the rising ground over themselves, which had been seized on by Decius.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But both their resentment stimulated them
                    more against the latter, who had taken from them the favourable opportunity of
                    achieving their object, and also the proximity of the place, and the paucity of
                    the enemy; and one time they would fain surround the hill on all sides with
                    armed men, so as to cut off Decius from the consul; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> at another time they wished to open a passage, so that they
                    may fall on them when they had descended into the defile. Before they had
                    determined on what they should do, night came on them. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Decius at first entertained a hope, that he would have to
                    engage them from the higher ground, as they ascended against the steep; then
                    surprise took possession of him, that they neither commenced the fight, nor if
                    they were deterred from that by the unevenness of the ground, that they did not
                    surround him with works and a circumvallation. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> Then summoning the centurions to him, he said, <quote> What ignorance of war
                        and indolence is that? or how did such men obtain a victory over the
                        Sidicinians and Campanians? You see that their <pb n="491" xml:id="p.491"/>
                        battalions move to and fro, that sometimes they are collected to one spot,
                        at other times they are drawn out. As for work, no one attempts it, when we
                        might by this time have been surrounded with a rampart. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Then indeed should we be like to them, if we delay
                        longer here than is expedient. Come on, accompany me; that whilst some day
                        light remains, we may ascertain in what places they put their guards, in
                        what direction an escape may lie open from hence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> All these points he carefully observed, clad
                    in a soldier's vest, the centurions whom he took with him being also in the
                    attire of common soldiers, lest the enemy might notice the general going the
                    round. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then having placed watch-guards, he commands
                    the ticket to be issued to all the rest, that when the signal had been given by
                    the trumpet of the second watch, they should assemble to him in silence fully
                    armed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whither when they had assembled in
                    silence according to the orders issued, <quote>Soldiers,</quote> says he,
                        <quote> this silence is to be observed in listening to me, waving the
                        military mode of expressing assent. When I shall have thoroughly explained
                        my sentiments to you, then such of you as shall approve the same, will pass
                        over; we will follow that line of conduct which shall meet the judgment of
                        the majority. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now hear what I meditate in
                        mind. The enemy have surrounded you, not brought hither in flight, nor left
                        behind through cowardice. By valour you seized this ground; by valour you
                        must make your way from it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By coming
                        hither you have saved a valuable army of the Roman people; by forcing your
                        way hence, save yourselves. You have proved yourselves worthy, though few in
                        number, of affording aid to multitudes, whilst you yourselves stand in need
                        of aid from no one. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You have to do with
                        that enemy, who on yesterday, through their supineness, availed themselves
                        not of the fortunate opportunity of destroying our whole army, who did not
                        see this hill so advantageously situate hanging over their heads, until it
                        was seized on by us; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> who with so many
                        thousand men did not prevent us so few from the ascent, and did not surround
                        us with a rampart when in possession of the ground, though so much of the
                        day still remained. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That enemy which with
                        their eyes open and awake you so baffled, it is incumbent on you now to
                        beguile, buried, as they are, in sleep; nay, it is absolutely necessary. For
                        our affairs are in that situation, <pb n="492" xml:id="p.492"/> that I am
                        rather to point out to you your necessity than to propose advice. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> For whether you are to remain or to depart hence,
                        can no longer be matter of deliberation, since, with the exception of your
                        arms, and courage mindful of those arms, fortune has left you nothing, and
                        we must die of famine and thirst, if we are more afraid of the sword than
                        becomes men and Romans. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Therefore our only
                        safety is to sally forth from this and to depart. That we must do either by
                        day or by night. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But lo! another point
                        which admits of less doubt; for if daylight be waited for, what hope is
                        there, that the enemy, who have now encompassed the hill on every side, as
                        you perceive, with their bodies exposed at disadvantage, will not hem us in
                        with a continued rampart and ditch? If night then be favourable for a sally,
                        as it is, this is undoubtedly the most suitable hour of night. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> You assembled here on the signal of the second
                        watch, a time which buries mortals in the profoundest sleep. You will pass
                        through their bodies lulled to sleep, either in silence unnoticed by them,
                        or ready to strike terror into them, should they perceive you, by a sudden
                        shout. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Only follow me, whom you have
                        followed. The same fortune which conducted us hither, will I follow. Those
                        of you to whom these measures seem salutary, come on, pass over to the
                        right. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They all passed over, and followed Decius as
                    he proceeded through the intervals which lay between the guards. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> They had now passed the middle of the camp, when a
                    soldier, striding over the bodies of the watchmen as they lay asleep, occasioned
                    a noise by striking one of their shields. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When
                    the watchman, being aroused by this, stirred the next one to him, and those who
                    were awake stirred up others, not knowing whether they were friends or foes,
                    whether it was the garrison that sallied forth or the consul had taken their
                    camp; Decius, having ordered the soldiers to raise a shout, as they were no
                    longer unobserved, disheartens them by panic whilst still heavy from sleep, by
                    which being <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> perplexed, they were neither
                    able to take arms briskly, nor make resistance, nor to pursue them. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> During the trepidation and confusion of the Samnites,
                    the Roman guard, slaying such of the guards as came in their way, reached the
                    consul's camp. A considerable portion of night still remained, and things now
                    appeared to be in safety; when Decius says, <quote> Roman soldiers, be honoured
                        for your <pb n="493" xml:id="p.493"/> bravery. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Your journey and return ages shall extol. But to behold
                        such bravery light and day are necessary; nor do you deserve that silence
                        and night should cover you, whilst you return to the camp with such
                        distinguished glory. Here let us wait in quiet for the daylight. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> His words they obeyed. And as soon as it was
                    day, a messenger being despatched to the camp to the consul, they were aroused
                    from sleep with great joy; and the signal being given by ticket, that those
                    persons returned safe who had exposed their persons to evident danger for the
                    preservation of all, rushing out each most anxiously to meet them, they applaud
                    them, congratulate them, they call them singly and collectively their
                    preservers, they give praises and thanks to the gods, they raise Decius to
                    heaven. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This was a sort of camp triumph for
                    Decius, who proceeded through the middle of the camp, with his guard fully
                    armed, the eyes of all being fixed on him, and all giving him equal honour with
                    the consul. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they came to the general's
                    tent, the consul summons them by sound of trumpet to an assembly; and commencing
                    with the well-earned praises of Decius, he adjourned the assembly on the
                    interposition of Decius himself, <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> who
                    advising the postponement of every thing else, whilst the occasion was still
                    present, persuaded the consul to attack the enemy, whilst still in consternation
                    from the panic of the night, and dispersing in separate detachments around the
                    hill, [adding] that he believed that some who had been sent out in pursuit of
                    him where straggling through the forest. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    legions were ordered to take arms; and having departed from the camp, as the
                    forest was now better known by means of scouts, they are led onwards to the
                    enemy through a more open tract. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Having
                    unexpectedly attacked the enemy when off their guard, since the soldiers of the
                    Samnites straggling in every direction, most of them unarmed, were not able
                    either to rally, nor to take arms, nor to betake themselves within the rampart,
                    they first drive them in a panic into the camp: then they take the camp itself,
                    having dislodged the guards. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The shout spread
                    around the hill; and puts each to flight from their respective posts. Thus a
                    great part yielded to an enemy they had not seen. Those whom the panic had
                    driven within the rampart (they amounted to thirty thousand) were all slain; the
                    camp was plundered. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Matters being thus conducted, the consul,
                    having sum- <pb n="494" xml:id="p.494"/> moned an assembly, pronounces a
                    panegyric on Decius, not only that which had been commenced on a previous
                    occasion, but as now completed by his recent deserts; and besides other military
                    gifts, he presents him with a golden crown and one hundred oxen, and with one
                    white one of distinguished beauty, richly decorated with gilded horns.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The soldiers who had been in the guard
                    with him, were presented with a double allowance of corn for ever; for the
                    present, with an ox and two vests each. Immediately after the consuls' donation,
                    the legions place on the head of Decius a crown of grass, indicative of their
                    deliverance from a blockade, expressing their approbation of the present with a
                    shout. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Decorated with these emblems, he
                    sacrificed the beautiful ox to Mars; the hundred oxen he bestowed on the
                    soldiers, who had been with him in the expedition. On the same soldiers the
                    legions conferred, each a pound of corn and a pint of wine; and all these things
                    were performed with great alacrity, with a military shout, a token of the
                    approbation of all. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The third battle was
                    fought near Suessula, in which the army of the Samnites, having been routed by
                    Marcus Valerius, having summoned from home the flower of their youth, determined
                    on trying their strength by a final contest. From Suessula messengers came in
                    great haste to Capua, and from thence horsemen in full speed to the consul
                    Valerius, to implore aid. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The troops were
                    immediately put in motion; and the baggage in the camp being left with a strong
                    guard, the army moves on with rapidity; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and
                    they select at no great distance from the enemy a very narrow spot (as, with the
                    exception of their horses, they were unaccompanied by a crowd of cattle and
                    servants). The army of the Samnites, as if there was to be no delay in coming to
                    an engagement, draw up in order of battle; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    then, when no one came to meet them, they advance to the enemy's camp in
                    readiness for action. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There when they saw the
                    soldiers on the rampart, and persons sent out to reconnoitre in every direction,
                    brought back word into how narrow a compass the camp had been contracted,
                    inferring thence the scanty number of the enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> The whole army began to exclaim, that the trenches ought to be filled up, the
                    rampart to be torn down, and that they should force their way into the camp; and
                    by that temerity the war would have been soon over, had not the generals
                    restrained the impetuosity of the soldiers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    However, <pb n="495" xml:id="p.495"/> as their own numbers bore heavily on their
                    supplies, and in consequence, first of their sitting down so long at Suessula,
                    and then by the delay of the contest, they were not far from a want of
                    provisions, it was determined, whilst the enemy remained shut up as if through
                    fear, that the soldiers should be led through the country to forage; <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> [supposing] in the mean time, that all supplies
                    would fail the Romans also, who having marched in haste, had brought with him
                    only as much corn as could be carried on his shoulders amid his arms. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> The consul, after he had observed the enemy
                    scattered through the country, that the posts were left but insufficiently
                    attended, having in a few words encouraged his men, leads them on to besiege the
                    camp. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After he had taken this on the first
                    shout and contest, more of the enemy being slain in their tents than at the
                    gates and rampart, he ordered the captive standards to be collected into one
                    place, and having left behind two legions as a guard and protection, after
                    giving them strict order that they should abstain from the booty, until he
                    himself should return; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> having set out with
                    his troops in regular order, the cavalry who had been sent on driving the
                    dispersed Samnites as it were by hunting toils, he committed great slaughter
                    among them. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> For in their terror they could
                    neither determine by what signal they should collect themselves into a body,
                    whether they should make for the camp, or continue their flight to a greater
                    distance. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> And so great was their terror, and
                    so precipitate their flight, that to the number of forty thousand shields,
                    though by no means were so many slain, and one hundred and seventy standards,
                    with those which had been taken in the camp, were brought to the consul.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Then they returned to the enemy's camp;
                    and there all the plunder was given up to the soldiers. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The result of this contest obliged the
                    Faliscians, who were on terms of a truce, to petition for a treaty of alliance
                    from the senate; and diverted the Latins, who had their armies already prepared,
                    from the Roman to a Pelignian war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nor did the
                    fame of such success confine itself within the limits of Italy; but the
                    Carthaginians also sent ambassadors to Rome to congratulate them, with an
                    offering of a golden crown, to be placed in Jupiter's shrine in the Capitol. Its
                    weight was twenty-five pounds. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both consuls
                    triumphed over the Samnites, whilst Decius followed distinguished with <pb
                        n="496" xml:id="p.496"/> praises and presents, when amid the rough jesting
                    of the soldiers the name of the tribune was no less celebrated than that of the
                    consuls. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The embassies of the Campanians and
                    Suessulans were then heard; and to their entreaties it was granted that a
                    garrison should be sent thither, in order that the incursions of the Samnites
                    might be repelled. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Capua, even then by no
                    means favourable to military discipline, alienated from the memory of their
                    country the affections of the soldiers, which were debauched by the supply of
                    pleasures of all kinds; and schemes were being formed in winter-quarters for
                    taking away Capua from the Campanians by the same kind of wickedness as that by
                    which they had taken it from its original possessors: <quote> and not
                        undeservedly would they turn their own example against themselves.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For why should the Campanians, who
                        were neither able to defend themselves nor their possessions, occupy the
                        most fertile land of Italy, and a city worthy of that land, rather than the
                        victorious army, who had driven the Samnites from thence by their sweat and
                        blood? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Was it reasonable that men who had
                        surrendered to them should have the full enjoyment of that fertile and
                        delightful country; that they, wearied by military toil, had to struggle in
                        an insalubrious and arid soil around their city, or within the city to
                        suffer the oppressive and exhausting weight of interest-money daily
                        increasing? </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These schemes agitated in secret cabals, and
                    as yet communicated only to a few, were encountered by the new consul Caius
                    Marcius Rutilus, to whom the province of Campania had fallen by lot, Quintus
                    Servilius, his colleague, being left behind in the city. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly when he was in possession of all these
                    circumstances just as they had occurred, having ascertained them through the
                    tribunes, matured by years and experience, (for he was consul now for the fourth
                    time, and had been dictator and censor,) thinking it the wisest proceeding to
                    frustrate the violence of the soldiers, by prolonging their hope of executing
                    their project whenever they might wish, he spreads the rumour, that the troops
                    were to winter in the same towns on the year after also. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For they had been cantoned throughout the cities of
                    Campania, and their plots had spread from Capua to the entire army. This
                    abatement being given to the eagerness of their projects, the mutiny was set at
                    rest for the present. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, having led out his army to the
                    summer <pb n="497" xml:id="p.497"/> campaign, determined, whilst he had the
                    Samnites quiet, to purge the army by sending away the turbulent men; by telling
                    some that their regular time had been served; that others were weighed down by
                    years and debilitated in bodily vigour. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some
                    were sent away on furloughs, at first individuals, then some cohorts also, on
                    the plea that they had wintered far from their home and domestic affairs.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When different individuals were sent to
                    different places under pretence of the business of the service, a considerable
                    number were put out of the way; which multitude the other consul detained in
                    Rome under different pretences. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And first
                    indeed, not suspecting the artifice, they returned to their homes by no means
                    with reluctance. After they saw that neither those first sent returned to their
                    standards, and that scarcely any others, except those who had wintered in
                    Campania, and chiefly the fomenters of the mutiny, were sent away; at first
                    wonder, and then certain fear entered their minds, that their schemes had been
                    divulged; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "that now they would have to suffer
                    trials, discoveries, the secret punishments of individuals, and the tyrannical
                    and cruel despotism of the consuls and the senate. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Those who were in the camp, discuss these things in secret
                    conferences, seeing that the sinews of the conspiracy had been got rid of by the
                    artifice of the consul. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> One cohort, when they
                    were at no great distance from Anxur, posted itself at Lautulae, in a narrow
                    woody pass between the sea and the mountains, to intercept those whom the consul
                    was dismissing under various pretences (as has been already mentioned). Their
                    body was now becoming strong in numbers; nor was any thing wanting to complete
                    the form of a regular army, except a leader. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Without order, therefore, they come into the Alban territory committing
                    depredations, and under the hill of Alba Longa, they encompass their camp with a
                    rampart. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The work here being completed, during
                    the remainder of the day they discuss their different opinions regarding the
                    choice of a commander, not having sufficient confidence in any of those present.
                    Whom could they invite out from Rome? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What
                    individuals of the patricians or of the commons was there, who would either
                    knowingly expose himself to such imminent danger, or to whom could the cause of
                    the army, set mad by ill-treatment, be safely committed? <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> On the following day, when the same subject of deliberation
                    detained <pb n="498" xml:id="p.498"/> them, some of the straggling marauders
                    ascertained and brought an account, that Titus Quinctius cultivated a farm in
                    the Tusculan territory, forgetful of the city and its honours. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> This was a man of patrician family, whose military career,
                    which was passed with great glory, having been relinquished in consequence of
                    one of his feet being lamed by a wound, he determined on spending his life in
                    the country far from ambition and the forum. His name once heard, they
                    immediately recognised the man; and with wishes for success, ordered him to be
                    sent for. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There was, however, but little hope
                    that he would do any thing voluntarily; they resolved on employing force and
                    intimidation. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Accordingly those who had been
                    sent for the purpose, having entered the house in the silence of the night, and
                    surprising Quinctius overcome in sleep, threatening that there was no
                    alternative, either authority and honour, or death, in case he resisted, unless
                    he followed, they force him to the camp. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Immediately on his arrival he was styled general, and whilst he was startled at
                    the strange nature of the sudden occurrence, they convey to him the ensigns of
                    honour, and bid him lead them to the city. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Then having torn up their standard, more under the influence of their own
                    impetuosity than by the command of their general, they arrive in hostile array
                    at the eighth stone on the road, which is now the Appian; <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> and would have proceeded immediately to the city, had they
                    not heard that an army was coming to meet them, and that Marcus Valerius Corvus
                    was nominated dictator against them, and Lucius Aemilius Mamercinus master of
                    the horse. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as they came in sight and recognised
                    the arms and standards, instantly the recollection of their country softened the
                    resentment of all. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not yet were they so hardy
                    as to shed the blood of their countrymen, nor had they known any but foreign
                    wars, and secession from their own was deemed the extreme of rage. Accordingly
                    now the generals, now the soldiers sought a meeting for a negotiation.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Quinctius, who was satiated with arms
                    [taken up] even in defence of his country, much more so against it; Corvus, who
                    entertained a warm affection for all his countrymen, chiefly the soldiers, and
                    above others, for his own army, advanced to a conference. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> To him, being immediately recognised, silence was granted
                    with no less respect by his adversaries, than by <pb n="499" xml:id="p.499"/>
                    his own party: he says, <quote> Soldiers, at my departure from the city, I
                        prayed to the immortal gods, your public deities as well as mine, and
                        earnestly implored their goodness so, that they would grant me the glory of
                        establishing concord among you, not victory over you. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> There have been and there will be sufficient
                        opportunities, whence military fame may be obtained: on this occasion peace
                        should be the object of our wishes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What I
                        earnestly called for from the immortal gods when offering up my prayers, you
                        have it in your power to grant to me, if you will remember, that you have
                        your camp not in Samnium, nor among the Volscians, but on Roman ground; that
                        those hills which you behold are those of your country, that this is the
                        army of your countrymen; that I am your own consul, under whose guidance and
                        auspices ye last year twice defeated the legions of the Samnites, twice took
                        their camp by storm. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Soldiers, I am Marcus
                        Valerius Corvus, whose nobility ye have felt by acts of kindness towards
                        you, not by ill-treatment; the proposer of no tyrannical law against you, of
                        no harsh decree of the senate; in every post of command more strict on
                        myself than on you. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And if birth, if
                        personal merit, if high dignity, if public honours could suggest arrogance
                        to any one, from such ancestors have I been descended, such a specimen had I
                        given of myself, at such an age did I attain the consulship, that when but
                        twenty-three years old I might have been a proud consul, even to the
                        patricians, not to the commons only. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> What
                        act or saying of mine, when consul, have ye heard of more severe than when
                        only tribune? With the same tenor did I administer two successive
                        consulships; with the same shall this uncontrollable office, the
                        dictatorship, be administered. So that I shall be found not more indulgent
                        to these my own soldiers and the soldiers of my country, than to you, I
                        shudder to call you so, its enemies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Ye
                        shall therefore draw the sword against me, before I draw it against you.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On that side the signal shall be
                        sounded, on that the shout and onset shall begin, if a battle must take
                        place. Determine in your minds, on that which neither your fathers nor
                        grandfathers could; neither those who seceded to the Sacred Mount, nor yet
                        those who afterwards posted themselves on the Aventine. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Wait till your mothers and wives come out to meet you
                        from the city with dishevelled hair, as they did formerly to Coriolanus. At
                        that <pb n="500" xml:id="p.500"/> time the legions of the Volscians, because
                        they had a Roman for their leader, ceased from hostilities; will not ye, a
                        Roman army, desist from an unnatural war? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Titus Quinctius, under whatever circumstances you stand on that side,
                        whether voluntarily or reluctantly, if there must be fighting, do you then
                        retire to the rear. With more honour even will you fly, and turn your back
                        to your countryman, than fight against your country. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Now you will stand with propriety and honour among the
                        foremost to promote peace; and may you be a salutary agent in this
                        conference. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Require and offer that which
                        is just; though we should admit even unjust terms, rather than engage in an
                        impious combat with each other. </quote> Titus Quinctius, turning to his
                    party with his eyes full of tears, said, <quote> In me too, soldiers, if there
                        is any use of me, ye have a better leader for peace than for war. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> For that speech just now delivered, not a
                        Volscian, nor a Samnite expressed, but a Roman: your own consul, your own
                        general, soldiers: whose auspices having already experienced for you, do not
                        wish to experience them against you. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The
                        senate had other generals also, who would engage you with more animosity;
                        they have selected the one who would be most indulgent to you, his own
                        soldiers, in whom as your general you would have most confidence. <milestone
                            n="18" unit="section"/> Even those who can conquer, desire peace: what
                        ought we to desire? <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Why do we not,
                        renouncing resentment and hope, those fallacious advisers, resign ourselves
                        and all our interests to his tried honour? </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> All approving with a shout, Titus Quinctius,
                    advancing before the standards, declared that <quote> the soldiers would be
                        obedient to the dictator; he entreated that he would espouse the cause of
                        his unfortunate countrymen, and having espoused it, he would maintain it
                        with the same fidelity with which he had wont to administer public affairs.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> That for himself individually he made
                        no terms: that he would found his hope in nothing else but in his innocence.
                        That provision should be made for the soldiers, as provision had been made
                        by the senate, once for the commons, a second time for the legions, so that
                        the secession should not be visited with punishment. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The dictator, having lauded Quinctius, and
                    having bid the others to hope for the best, returned back to the city with all
                    speed, and, with the approbation of the senate, proposed to the people in the
                    Peteline grove, that the secession should not be <pb n="501" xml:id="p.501"/>
                    visited with chastisement on any of the soldiers. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He also en- treated, with their permission, that no one
                    should either in jest or earnest upbraid any one with that proceeding. A
                    military devoting law was also passed, that the name of any soldier once
                    enrolled, should not be erased unless with his own consent; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and to the law [a clause] was added that no one, after he
                    had been a tribune of the soldiers, should afterwards be a centurion. That
                    demand was made by the conspirators on account of Publius Salonius; who in
                    alternate years was both tribune of the soldiers and first centurion, which they
                    now call <hi rend="italics">primi pili.</hi>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The soldiers were incensed against him,
                    because he had always been opposed to their recent measures, and had fled from
                    Lantulae, that he might have no share in them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly when this alone was not obtained from the senate through their
                    regard for Salonius, then Salonius, conjuring the conscript fathers, that they
                    would not value his promotion more highly than the concord of the state,
                    prevailed in having that also carried. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Equally
                    ineffectual was the demand, that some deductions should be made from the pay of
                    the cavalry, (they then received triple,) because they had opposed the
                    conspiracy. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Besides these, I find in some writers that
                    Lucius Genucius, tribune of the commons, proposed to the people, that no one
                    should be allowed to practise usury; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> likewise
                    provision was made by other enactments, that no one should fill the same office
                    within ten years; nor hold two offices on the same year; and that it should be
                    allowed that both the consuls should be plebeians. If all these concessions were
                    made to the people, it is evident that the revolt possessed no little strength.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In other annals it is recorded, that
                    Valerius was not appointed dictator, but that the entire business was managed by
                    the consuls; and also that that bang of conspirators were driven to arms not
                    before they came to Rome, but at Rome; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and
                    that it was not on the country-house of Titus Quinctius, but on the residence of
                    Caius Manlius the assault was made by night, and that he was seized by the
                    conspirators to become their leader: that having proceeded thence to the fourth
                    mile-stone, they posted themselves in a well-defended place; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and that it was not with the leaders mention of a
                    reconciliation originated; but that suddenly, when the armies marched out to
                    battle fully armed, a mutual saluta- <pb n="502" xml:id="p.502"/> tion took
                    place; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that mixing together the soldiers began
                    to join hands, and to embrace each other with tears; and that the consuls, on
                    seeing the minds of the soldiers averse from fighting, made a proposition to the
                    senate concerning the re-establishment of concord. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> So that among ancient writers nothing is agreed on, except
                    that there was a mutiny, and that it was composed. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Both the report of this disturbance, and the heavy war
                    entered into with the Samnites, alienated some states from the Roman alliance:
                    and besides the treaty of the Latins, which now for a long time was not to be
                    depended on, the Privernians also by a sudden incursion laid waste Norba and
                    Setia, Roman colonies in their neighbourhood. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
