<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 5-7 - 7</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books V, VI and VII With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1924: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.357"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="book">
                <head>Book VII</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year will stand out as the one in which a
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 366-365</note>
                    <quote>new man</quote> held the consulship, and also for the establishment of
                    two new magistracies, the praetorship and the curule aedileship. These dignities
                    the patricians had devised for themselves, to compensate them for the second
                    consulship, which they had granted to the commons. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The plebs bestowed their consulship on Lucius Sextius, by
                    whose law it had been won. The patricians, through their influence in the Campus
                    Martius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Where the voting took
                        place.</note> obtained the praetorship for Spurius Furius Camillus, the son
                    of Marcus, and the aedileship for Gnaeus Quinctius Capitolinus and Publius
                    Cornelius Scipio, who belonged to their own houses. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Aemilius Mamercus was chosen from the patricians as
                    colleague of Lucius Sextius. Early in the year there was some talk about the
                    Gauls —who having at first scattered through Apulia were now rumoured to be
                    gathering —and about a defection on the part of the Hernici. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The patricians purposely deferred all action, in order that
                    the plebeian consul might have no hand in anything; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> it seemed from the general hush and lack of bustle as
                    though a cessation of the courts had been proclaimed; save that the tribunes
                    would not suffer it to pass in silence that the nobles, in return for one
                    plebeian consul, had got three patrician magistrates for themselves, who wore
                    the purple-bordered toga and sat, like consuls, <pb n="p.359"/> in curule
                    chairs, while the praetor even dealt out <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 366-365</note> justice —having
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> been elected as a colleague to the consuls
                    and under the same auspices. In consequence of this criticism the senate was
                    ashamed to order that the curule aediles be chosen from the patricians.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first it was arranged to take them from
                    the plebs in alternate years: later the election was thrown open without
                    distinction. </p>
                <p> Then came the consulship of Lucius Genucius and Quintus Servilius. There was
                    neither party strife nor war to disturb the peace, but lest there should ever be
                    freedom from fear and danger, a great pestilence broke out. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> It is stated that a censor, a curule aedile, and three
                    plebeian tribunes died, with a correspondingly large number from the rest of the
                    population. But what chiefly made this pestilence noteworthy was the death of
                    Marcus Furius, who, though ripe in years, was bitterly regretted. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> For he was truly a man of singular excellence whether
                    in good or evil fortune; foremost in peace and in war before his banishment, and
                    in exile even more distinguished, whether one thinks of the yearning of his
                    countrymen who called on him in his absence to save their captured City, or of
                    the success with which on being restored to his country he restored the country
                    itself at the same time; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> after this for five
                    and twenty years —for he survived so long —he maintained his glorious
                    reputation, and was deemed worthy of being named next after Romulus, as Rome's
                    second Founder. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The pestilence lasted during both this and the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 364</note>
                    following year, the consulship of Gaius Sulpicius Peticus and Gaius Licinius
                    Stolo. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the latter year nothing memorable
                    occurred, except that with the <pb n="p.361"/> object of appeasing the divine
                    displeasure they made <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        364</note>
                    <hi rend="italics">a lectisternium,</hi> or banquet to the gods, being the third
                    in the history of the City; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The first
                        lectisternium was in 399 B.., and is described at v. xiii. 5 sq. The second
                        is not mentioned by Livy. It may have occurred in 392 (v. xxxi. 5). </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and when neither human wisdom nor the help of
                    Heaven was found to mitigate the scourge, men gave way to superstitious fears,
                    and, amongst other efforts to disarm the wrath of the gods, are said also to
                    have instituted scenic entertainments. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This
                    was a new departure for a warlike people, whose only exhibitions had been those
                    of the circus; but indeed it began in a small way, as most things do, and even
                    so was imported from abroad. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy
                        distinguishes five stages in the development of scenic entertainments: (1)
                        dances, accompanied by the flute; (2) improvisation of rude verses in
                        addition to the music and dancing; (3) medleys, of a musical character,
                        accompanied by flute and dance; (4) the comedy with a regular plot, special
                        singers for the lyric parts, etc.; (5) the addition of an after-play, <hi
                            rend="italics">exodium</hi> or <hi rend="italics">Atellana.</hi> With
                        this account, Horace, <hi rend="italics">Epistles</hi> II. i. 139 ff. should
                        be compared. </note> Without any singing, without imitating the action of
                    singers, players who had been brought in from Etruria danced to the strains of
                    the flautist and performed not ungraceful evolutions in the Tuscan fashion.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next the young Romans began to imitate
                    them, at the same time exchanging jests in uncouth verses, and bringing their
                    movements into a certain harmony with the words. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> And so the amusement was adopted, and frequent use kept it alive. The native
                    professional actors were called <hi rend="italics">histriones,</hi> from <hi
                        rend="italics">ister,</hi> the Tuscan word for player; they no longer —as
                    before —alternately <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> threw off rude lines
                    hastily improvised, like the Fescennines, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The name was derived by the ancients either from
                        Fescennia, a place in Etruria, or from <hi rend="italics">fascinum,</hi> a
                        phallic symbol. </note> but performed medleys, full of musical measures, to
                    melodies which were now written out to go with the flute, and with appropriate
                    gesticulation. </p>
                <pb n="p.363"/>
                <p> Livius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livius Andronicus, a Greek
                        captured at Tarentum, produced the first translation of a Greek play into
                        Latin, in <date when="-0240">240 B.C.</date>
                    </note> was the first, some years later, to abandon <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.</note> 364 <hi rend="italics"
                        >saturae</hi> and compose a play with a plot. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Like everyone else in those days, he acted his own pieces;
                    and the story goes that when his voice, owing to the frequent demands made upon
                    it, had lost its freshness, he asked and <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    obtained the indulgence to let a boy stand before the flautist to sing the
                    monody, while he acted it himself, with a vivacity of gesture that gained
                    considerably from his not having to use his voice. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> From that time on actors began to use singers to accompany
                    their gesticulation, reserving only the dialogue parts for their own delivery.
                    When this type of performance had begun to wean <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> the drama from laughter and informal jest, and the play had
                    gradually developed into art, the young men abandoned the acting of comedies to
                    professionals and revived the ancient practice of fashioning their nonsense into
                    verses and letting fly with them at one another; this was the source of the
                    after-plays which came later to be called <hi rend="italics">exodia,</hi> and
                    were usually combined with Atellan farces. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The Atellan was a species of comedy acquired from the Oscans, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Atella was a little town in Campania.
                            <hi rend="italics">Atellanae</hi> were coarse farces presenting certain
                        stock characters, Maccus. Pappus, Bucco, and Dossenus. The Oscans were a
                        branch of the Samnites and lived in Campania. </note> and the young men kept
                    it for themselves and would not allow it to be polluted by the professional
                    actors; that is why it is a fixed tradition that performers of Atellan plays are
                    not disfranchised, but serve in the army as though they had no connexion with
                    the stage. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Actors were regularly
                        reckoned in the <hi rend="italics">aerarii</hi> or lowest class of citizens,
                        who were not permitted to serve in the army. </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Amongst the humble origins of other
                    institutions it has seemed worth while to set down the early history of the
                    play, that it might be seen how sober were the beginnings of <pb n="p.365"/> an
                    art that has nowadays reached a point where <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 364</note> opulent kingdoms could
                    hardly support its mad extravagance. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, the plays thus for the first time
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 363</note>
                    introduced by way of expiation neither freed men's minds of religious fears nor
                    their bodies of disease. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Indeed, it fell out
                    quite otherwise; for the games were in full swing when an inundation of the
                    Tiber flooded the circus and put a stop to them, an accident which —as though
                    the gods had already turned away, rejecting the proffered appeasement of their
                    anger —filled the people with fear. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And so
                    when Gnaeus Genucius and Lucius Aemilius Mamercus (for the second time) were
                    consuls, and men's minds were more troubled by the search for means of
                    propitiation than were their bodies by disease, it is said that the elders
                    recollected that a pestilence had once been allayed by the dictator's driving a
                    nail. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The instance here referred to
                        may have occurred in <date when="-0435">435 B.C.</date> , when Quintus
                        Servilius Prisous was dictator (Iv. xxi 6-9). </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Induced thereto by this superstition, the
                    senate ordered the appointment of a dictator to drive the nail. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Manlius Imperiosus was appointed, and named Lucius
                    Pinarius master of the horse. </p>
                <p> There is an ancient law, recorded in archaic words and letters, that the chief
                    magistrate shall on the thirteenth of September drive a nail; the tablet was
                    formerly affixed to the right side of the temple of Jupiter Optimus Maximus,
                    where Minerva's chapel is. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This nail served,
                    they say, in those days of little writing, to mark the number of years, and the
                    law was confided to the chapel of Minerva, for the reason <pb n="p.367"/> that
                    number was an invention of that goddess. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 363</note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> (Cincius, a careful student of such memorials,
                    asserts <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> We do not know whether Livy
                        alludes to a book or to an oral communication. It has been suggested that
                        Cinciusnot otherwise known —may have been an antiquary of Livy's own time.
                    </note> that at Volsinii, too, nails may be seen in the temple of Nortia, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">A goddess of Fortune.</note> an Etruscan
                    goddess, driven in to indicate the number of <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    years.) Marcus Horatius the consul dedicated the temple of Jupiter Optimus
                    Maximus in accordance with this law, in the year after the expulsion of the
                    kings; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The text here is uncertain,
                        but Livy seems to mean that Horatius in dedicating the temple also drove the
                        first nail. </note> later the ceremony of driving the nail was transferred
                    from consuls to dictators, because theirs was the higher authority. Then, after
                    the custom had been allowed to lapse, it was thought to be of sufficient
                    importance to warrant the appointment of a dictator for that very <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> purpose. It was for this reason that Manlius was
                    designated, who, however, as though appointed to wage war and not to discharge a
                    religious obligation, aspired to conduct the war with the Hernici, and hunted
                    down the men of military age in a rigorous levy; but in the upshot, opposed by
                    the united efforts of all the tribunes of the plebs, he yielded either to force
                    or to a sense of shame, and resigned his dictatorship. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, at the beginning of the ensuing
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 362</note> year
                    —the consulship of Quintus Servilius Ahala and Lucius Genucius —Manlius was put
                    upon his trial by Marcus Pomponius, a tribune of the plebs. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The people hated him for the severity of his levy, in which
                    they had endured not only fines but bodily distress, some having suffered
                    stripes for failure to respond to their names and others having been dragged off
                    to prison; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but more than all else they hated
                    the man's cruel disposition and his surname, Imperiosus, which offended a free
                    state and had been assumed in ostentation of the truculence which <pb n="p.369"
                    /> he used as freely with his nearest friends and his <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 362</note> own family as with
                    strangers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Amongst other charges the tribune
                    cited the man's behaviour to his son: the youth, he said, had been found guilty
                    of no misconduct, yet Manlius had excluded him from the City, from his home and
                    household gods, from the Forum, the light of day, and the fellowship of his
                    young friends, <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> consigning him to slavish
                    drudgery in a kind of gaol or work-house, where a youth of distinguished birth
                    and the son of a dictator might learn by his daily wretchedness how truly
                        <quote>imperious</quote> was the father that had begot him. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Yes, but what was the young man's fault? Why, he had been a
                    little slow of speech —unready with his tongue! But ought not his father to have
                    healed and mended this infirmity of nature —if he had a particle of humanity
                    about him —instead of chastising it and by persecution making it conspicuous?
                    Why even the dumb brutes, if one of their young is unfortunate, do none the less
                    cherish it and foster it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But Lucius Manlius
                    was aggravating his son's evil plight by evil treatment, and was doubling the
                    burden on his heavy wits; and any spark of native talent that might be there he
                    was quenching in the rustic life and clownish bringing up amongst the dumb
                    brutes where he kept him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Everyone was incensed by these charges, except
                    the young man himself. He, on the contrary, was vexed to be the cause of
                    additional dislike and accusation of his father; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> and that all gods and men might know that he had rather help his father than
                    his father's enemies, he conceived a plan, in keeping to be sure with his rude
                    and uncouth spirit, which, though it set no pattern of civic conduct, was yet
                        <pb n="p.371"/> praiseworthy for its filial piety. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Without anybody's <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 362</note> knowledge, he girded himself with a knife in
                    the early morning, and coming to the City, made his way at once from the gate to
                    the house of Marcus Pomponius, the tribune. There he told the porter that he
                    must see his master instantly, and bade him say that it was Titus Manlius, the
                    son of Lucius. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Being presently admitted —for
                    it seemed likely that he was moved with wrath against his father, or was
                    bringing some fresh charge or plan of action —he received and returned the
                    salutation of his host, and then announced that there were matters of which he
                    wished to speak to him without witnesses. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When
                    they had all been sent away, he drew his knife, and standing over the tribune's
                    couch with his weapon ready, he threatened that unless the man should swear, in
                    the terms he himself should dictate, never to hold a council of the plebs for
                    the purpose of accusing his father, he would immediately stab him. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The frightened tribune, seeing the blade flash in his
                    face, and perceiving himself to be alone and unarmed, and the other to be a
                    stalwart youth, and, what was no less terrifying, foolhardy by reason of his
                    strength, took the oath that was required of him, and afterwards publicly
                    declared that he had been compelled by force to relinquish his undertaking.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And the plebs, however much they would
                    have liked to be given the opportunity to cast their votes in the case of so
                    cruel and insolent a defendant, were yet not displeased that a son had dared
                    such a deed in defence of his parent; and they praised it all the more, because
                    the father's shocking harshness had made no difference in the son's filial
                    devotion. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And so not only was the arraignment
                    of the father <pb n="p.373"/> dismissed, but the youth himself gained
                    distinction from <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        362</note> the affair; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for in the election
                    of military tribunes for the legions, which had that year for the first time
                    been resolved upon —until then the generals themselves had nominated them, as
                    they do to-day those who are known as <hi rend="italics">Rufuli</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Pseudo-Asconius, on Cic. <hi
                            rend="italics">Act. 1 in Verr.</hi> 30 says: <quote> There are two kinds
                            of military tribunes, the first consisting of those called <hi
                                rend="italics">Rufuli;</hi> these are ordinarily appointed in the
                            army; the others are the <hi rend="italics">comitiati,</hi> who are
                            designated at the comitia in Rome. </quote>
                    </note> —he was chosen second of the six, though neither at home nor in the
                    field had he done aught to merit popularity, and no wonder, since his youth had
                    been passed in the country, remote from the gatherings of men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> That same year, whether owing to an earthquake
                    or to some other violent force, it is said that the ground gave way, at about
                    the middle of the Forum, and, sinking to an immeasurable depth, left a
                    prodigious chasm. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This gulf could not be
                    filled with the earth which everyone brought and cast into it, until admonished
                    by the gods, they began to inquire what it was that constituted the chief
                    strength of the Roman People; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for this the
                    soothsayers declared that they must offer up, as a sacrifice to that spot, if
                    they wished the Roman Republic to endure. Thereupon Marcus Curtius, a young
                    soldier of great prowess, rebuked them, so the story runs, for questioning
                    whether any blessing were more Roman than arms and valour. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> A hush ensued, as he turned to the temples of the immortal
                    gods which rise above the Forum, and to the Capitol, and stretching forth his
                    hands, now to heaven, and now to the yawning chasm and to the gods below,
                    devoted himself to death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After which, mounted
                    on a horse caparisoned with all possible splendour, he plunged fully armed into
                    the gulf; and crowds of men and women threw offerings and fruits in after him.
                    It was he, they say, and not Curtius Mettius, the soldier <pb n="p.375"/> of
                    Titus Tatius in days of old, who gave his name to <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 362</note> the Curtian Lake. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">See I. xii. 10 and xiii. 5, with
                        note.</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Diligence would not be wanting, were there any
                    path which could lead the inquirer to the truth; as it is, one must hold by the
                    tradition, where antiquity will not allow us to be certain; and the name of the
                    pool is better known from this more recent legend. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After the expiation of this great portent, the
                    senate dealt in the same year with the question of the Hernici, and having
                    dispatched fetials to demand reparations, without avail, resolved to submit to
                    the people for their approval, at the earliest possible day, a declaration of
                    war against that nation. In a crowded assembly the people voted for war, and the
                    consul Lucius Genucius was by lot intrusted with the conduct of it. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The citizens were in a fever of suspense, since he
                    would be the first plebeian consul to conduct a war under his own auspices, and
                    they would judge by the sequel whether they had done well or ill to throw these
                    honours open. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It so happened that Genucius,
                    marching in great force against the enemy, plunged into an ambuscade. The
                    legions, in a sudden panic, were put to flight, and the consul was surrounded
                    and slain by men who knew not whom they had taken. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> When the news reached Rome, the patricians, by no means so
                    cast down by the general disaster as elated at the unlucky generalship of the
                    plebeian consul, filled the City with their taunts. Let them go and choose
                    consuls from the plebs! Let them transfer the auspices to those who might not
                    have them without sin! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They had been able by
                    a plebiscite to expel the patricians from their rightful honours: had their
                    unsanctioned <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The law had been passed
                        in an assembly presided over by a tribune, who had not the right to take
                        auspices. </note> law prevailed also against the immortal gods? The gods <pb
                        n="p.377"/> themselves had vindicated their divine authority and their <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 362</note> auspices;
                    for these had no sooner been touched by one who had no legal or religious
                    warranty for so doing, than the army and its general had been annihilated, as a
                    lesson never again to overturn the rights of the patrician families in
                    conducting an election. Such words as these resounded through the Curia and the
                    Forum. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius had urged the
                    rejection of the law, and this now gave his words the greater weight, as he
                    denounced the outcome of a policy which he himself had censured. Him, therefore,
                    the consul Servilius, with the approval of the patricians, appointed dictator.
                    An enrolment was proclaimed, and the courts were suspended. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But before the dictator and his new levies
                    were got to the country of the Hernici, the lieutenant Gaius Sulpicius,
                    profiting by a favourable opportunity, had fought a brilliant engagement.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Hernici, whom the consul's death had
                    made contemptuous, approached the Roman camp with every expectation of taking it
                    by storm; but the soldiers, heartened by their general and bursting with anger
                    and resentment, made a sortie, and so far were the Hernici from attacking the
                    stockade, as they had hoped to do, that they actually fell back in confusion
                    from the ground. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then came the dictator, and
                    the new army was joined to the old and the forces doubled. Calling the men
                    together, Appius lauded the lieutenant and his soldiers, by whose bravery the
                    camp had been defended; thus at the same stroke he encouraged those who heard
                    themselves deservedly commended, and stimulated the others to emulation of their
                    conduct. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor were the enemy less energetic in
                    making ready for the war; mindful of the glory they had won <pb n="p.379"/>
                    before, and aware that the forces of their adversaries <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 362</note> had been augmented, they
                    also strengthened theirs. All who bore the name of Hernici and were of military
                    age were called upon, and eight cohorts were formed, each numbering four hundred
                    of their best men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This choice flower of their
                    manhood they inspired with additional hope and courage by a decree which allowed
                    them double pay. They were exempted, also, from military tasks, in order that,
                    being reserved for the one labour of fighting, they might be sensible of an
                    obligation to exert themselves beyond the capacity of ordinary men. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Finally, they were assigned a post in the battle
                    outside the line, to make their bravery the more conspicuous. </p>
                <p> A plain extending for two miles separated the Roman camp from the Hernici. In
                    the middle of this plain, at a spot almost equidistant from both camps, the
                    battle was fought. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At first the event of the
                    struggle was in doubt and nothing came of the oft-repeated attempts of the Roman
                    horse to break the enemy's line. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Finding their
                    charges ineffectual, despite their efforts, they consulted the dictator and with
                    his permission left their horses, and, rushing to the front with a mighty cheer,
                    inaugurated a new kind of fighting. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There
                    would have been no stopping them, had it not been for the special cohorts, who
                    flung themselves across their path with a vigour and gallantry equal to their
                    own. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The struggle then lay between the best men of
                    both nations, and whatever losses the chance of war inflicted on either side
                    were serious out of all proportion to their number. The common herd of soldiers,
                    as though they had made over the battle to their betters, rested their future on
                    the bravery of <pb n="p.381"/> others. Many on both sides were slain and more
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 362</note> were
                    wounded. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At length the knights began to rail
                    at one another. What else, they asked, was there to do, if they had neither
                    beaten the enemy when mounted, nor were able to accomplish anything on foot?
                    What third kind of battle were they waiting for? <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> What good had they done by dashing boldly out in front of the line and
                    fighting in a place that belonged to others? Stirred by these mutual reproaches,
                    they advanced with renewed cheering, and first they made the enemy yield, then
                    forced them back, and finally routed them in no uncertain fashion. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> What it was that turned the scale, where forces were
                    so evenly matched, would be hard to say, unless the fortune regularly attendant
                    on each nation had the power to quicken or to daunt their resolution. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans chased the fleeing Hernici clear to their
                    camp, which, owing to the lateness of the hour, they refrained from attacking;
                    —the dictator had been unable to give the battle-signal before noon, having
                    failed for a long time to obtain favourable omens, for which reason the struggle
                    had been protracted until night. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> —On the
                    following day the camp was discovered to have been deserted by the fleeing
                    Hernici, and a few of their wounded were found, whom they had left behind. The
                    column of fugitives was passing the walls of Signia, when the townsfolk espied
                    their thinly attended ensigns, and falling upon them, scattered them in headlong
                    flight across the country. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Yet the Romans got
                    no bloodless victory: they lost a fourth part of their foot, and a number of
                    Roman horsemen fell, which was no less grave a loss. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next year the consuls Gaius Sulpicius and
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 361</note> Gaius
                    Licinius Calvus led an army against the <pb n="p.383"/> Hernici, and not finding
                    the enemy abroad, captured <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B. C. 361</note> their city of Ferentinum by assault. As they were
                    returning thence, the men of Tibur closed their gates against them. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Many complaints had before this been bandied back and
                    forth between the two peoples, but this new offence made the Romans finally
                    determine that after sending the fetials to demand redress they would declare
                    war on the Tiburtine people. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is well established that Titus Quinctius
                    Poenus was dictator that year and that Servius Cornelius Maluginensis was master
                    of the horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Licinius Macer <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Tribune of the plebs in <date
                            when="-0073">73 B.C.</date> and author of annals written from the
                        democratic standpoint (Introd. p. xxix). </note> states that the appointment
                    was for the purpose of holding an election and was made by Licinius the consul,
                    who, because his colleague was in haste to hold the election before the
                    campaign, so that he might succeed himself in the consulship, felt obliged to
                    thwart his evil designs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the praise which
                    he seeks to bestow on his own family makes the testimony of Licinius less
                    weighty, and since I find no mention of the circumstance in the older annals, I
                    am more disposed to think that it was a Gallic war which occasioned the
                    appointment of a dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In any case, this
                    was the year in which the Gauls encamped at the third milestone on the Salarian
                    road, beyond the bridge over the Anio. </p>
                <p> The dictator having, by reason of the Gallic rising, proclaimed a suspension of
                    the courts, administered the oath to all of military age. Then marching out of
                    the City with a great army he pitched his camp on the hither bank of the stream.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The bridge lay between, and neither side
                    would break it down, lest it be regarded as a sign of fear. There were frequent
                    skirmishes for the possession of the bridge, and yet, so evenly matched were
                    their forces, it could not be <pb n="p.385"/> determined who were masters of it.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then a Gaul <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 361</note> of extraordinary size
                    advanced upon the empty bridge, and making his voice as loud as possible, cried
                    out, <quote> Let him whom Rome now reckons her bravest man come out and fight,
                        that we two may show by the outcome which people is the superior in war.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The young Roman nobles were for a long time
                    silent. Ashamed to decline the challenge, they were loath to volunteer for a
                    service of transcendent peril. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then Titus
                    Manlius, the son of Lucius, who had rescued his father from the persecution of
                    the tribune, left his station and went to the dictator. <quote>Without your
                        orders, General,</quote> he said, <quote> I would fain never leave my place
                        to fight, not though I saw that victory was assured; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> but if you permit me, I would show that beast who
                        dances out so boldly before the standards of the enemy, that I come of the
                        family that hurled the column of Gauls from the Tarpeian Rock. </quote> To
                    whom the dictator made answer, <quote> Success attend your valour, Titus
                        Manlius, and your loyalty to father and to country! <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Go, and with Heaven's help make good the unconquerable
                        Roman name. </quote> The young man's friends then armed him; he assumed the
                    shield of a foot-soldier, and to his side he buckled a Spanish sword, convenient
                    for close fighting. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Spanish sword
                        was short and pointed, and a sword of this type <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> —required by the story —is what Livy means. The <hi
                            rend="italics">name</hi> for it is anachronistic here. </note> Armed and
                    accoutred, they led him forth to the Gaul, who in his stupid glee —for the
                    ancients have thought even this worth mentioning —thrust his tongue out in
                    derision. They then retired to their station, and the two armed men were left by
                    themselves in the midst, like gladiators more than soldiers, and by no means
                    evenly matched, to judge from <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> outward show.
                    One <pb n="p.387"/> had a body extraordinary for its size, and resplendent <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 361</note> in a coat of
                    shifting hues and armour painted and chased with gold: the other was of a
                    middling stature for a soldier, and his arms were but indifferent to look at,
                    being suitable but <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> not ornate. He neither sang
                    nor danced about with idle flourishes of his weapons, but his bosom swelled with
                    courage and silent wrath, and all his ferocity was reserved for the crisis of
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the combat. When they had taken their
                    ground between the two embattled armies, while the hearts of the surrounding
                    multitude were suspended betwixt hope and fear, the Gaul, whose huge bulk
                    towered <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> above the other, advanced his shield
                    with the left arm, to parry the attack of his oncoming enemy, and delivered a
                    slashing stroke with his sword, that made a mighty clatter but did <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> no harm. The Roman, with the point of his weapon
                    raised, struck up his adversary's shield with a blow from his own against its
                    lower edge; and slipping in between the man's sword and his body, so close that
                    no part of his own person was exposed, he gave one thrust and then immediately
                    another, and gashing the groin and belly of his enemy brought him headlong to
                    the ground, where he lay stretched out over a <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    monstrous space. To the body of his fallen foe he offered no other indignity
                    than to despoil it of one thing —a chain which, spattered with blood, he cast
                    round his <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> own neck. The Gauls were transfixed
                    with fear and wonder, while the Romans, quitting their station, ran eagerly to
                    meet their champion and brought him with praise and gratulation to <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> the dictator. Amidst the rude banter thrown out by
                    the soldiers in a kind of verse, was heard the appellation of Torquatus, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the man with a chain, or necklace. </note> and
                    thereafter <pb n="p.389"/> this was given currency as an honoured surname, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 361</note> used even
                    by descendants of <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> the family. The dictator
                    gave him, besides, a golden chaplet, and loudly extolled that fight of his in a
                    public speech. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And in fact the combat was of so great <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 360</note> consequence
                    to the issue of the whole war, that the army of the Gauls withdrew in
                    trepidation from their camp on the succeeding night and crossed over into the
                    territory of Tibur. There they formed a military alliance with the Tiburtes, and
                    having been liberally assisted by them with provisions, they soon departed and
                    went into Campania. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was the reason why in
                    the following year the consul Gaius Poetelius Balbus, when his colleague Marcus
                    Fabius Ambustus had been appointed to the campaign with the Hernici, was
                    commanded by the people to march against the men of Tibur. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To aid their allies, the Gauls returned from Campania, and
                    the cruel devastations which ensued in the districts of Labici, Tusculum, and
                    Alba were clearly instigated and directed by the Tiburtes. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Against the Tiburtine foe the state was satisfied to be
                    commanded by a consul; but the Gallic invasion required the appointment of a
                    dictator. The choice fell on Quintus Servilius Ahala, who designated Titus
                    Quinctius master of the horse, and, instructed by the senate, made a vow to
                    celebrate the great games, in the event of a successful termination of the war.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Directing the consular army to remain
                    where they were, in order to confine the Tiburtes to their own field of action,
                    the dictator administered the oath to all the young men, none of whom
                    endeavoured to avoid the service. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The battle
                    was fought not far from the Colline <pb n="p.391"/> Gate. The Romans put forth
                    all their strength <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        360</note> in full sight of their parents and their wives and children.
                    These are powerful incentives to courage even when unseen, but being then in
                    full view, set the soldiers on fire with a sense of honour and compassion.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The slaughter was great on both sides, but
                    at last the Gallic army was driven off. In their flight they turned towards
                    Tibur, as though it had been the stronghold of the Gallic war; as they straggled
                    on, they encountered the consul Poetelius, not far from the town, and when the
                    Tiburtes came out to their assistance they were beaten back through the gates
                    along with the Gauls. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The affair was admirably
                    handled by the consul as well as by the dictator. And the other consul Fabius
                    defeated the Hernici —at first in little skirmishes, but ultimately in one
                    remarkable battle, in which the enemy attacked with all their forces. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The dictator, having handsomely lauded the consuls in
                    the senate and before the people, even giving them the credit for his own
                    achievements, resigned his office. Poetelius celebrated a double triumph over
                    the Gauls and the Tiburtes: it was thought enough for Fabius that he should
                    enter the City in an ovation. </p>
                <p> The Tiburtes ridiculed the triumph of Poetelius. Where was it, they asked, that
                    he had fought a battle with them? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A handful
                    of people had gone outside the gates to look on at the flight and panic of the
                    Gauls, and finding that they too were attacked and that all who came in the way
                    of the Romans were cut down without discrimination, had retired within their
                    walls; this was the great achievement that the Romans had deemed worthy of a
                    triumph! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That they might not regard it as too
                    wonderful and <pb n="p.393"/> great a thing to cause a flurry at their enemy's
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 360</note>
                    gates, they should themselves behold a greater panic in front of their own
                    walls. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Accordingly, in the following year, when <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 359-358</note> Marcus
                    Popilius Laenas and Gnaeus Manlius were consuls, a hostile expedition set out
                    from Tibur and arrived in the first silence of the night, at the walls of Rome.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was terrifying to be suddenly waked out
                    of sleep by a surprise and a night alarm; moreover many of the people knew not
                    who their enemies were nor whence they had come; nevertheless the call to arms
                    was quickly given, and watches were set at the gates and the walls were manned.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when the first light showed the enemy
                    before the City to be in no great force, and only the men of Tibur, the consuls
                    sallied out at two gates and assailed them on both flanks as they were now
                    drawing near the walls. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was evident that in
                    coming they had relied more on opportunity than on courage, for they scarcely
                    withstood the first shock of the Roman onset. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In fact their expedition was confessedly a good thing for the Romans, and the
                    fear occasioned by so near an enemy repressed a quarrel that was already in the
                    air, between the patricians and the plebs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another hostile incursion was more terrifying
                    to the countryside. The Tarquinienses, bent on plundering, ranged over the Roman
                    territory, particularly that part which adjoins Etruria; and demands for
                    reparation proving futile, the new consuls, Gaius Fabius and Gaius Plautius,
                    declared war against them, as commanded by the people. This campaign fell to
                    Fabius, that against the Hernici to Plautius. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.395"/>
                <p> Rumours of a Gallic war began also to be rife. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 359-358</note> But with many perils,
                    there was this consolation, that they had granted peace to the Latins, at their
                    desire, and had received a large force of soldiers from them, under the terms of
                    an ancient treaty which the Latins had for many years disregarded. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Thus strengthened, the Romans heard soon after with
                    small concern that the Gauls had come to Praeneste and had then pitched their
                    camp in the vicinity of Pedum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They resolved
                    on making Gaius Sulpicius dictator, and sent for Gaius Plautius the consul to
                    appoint him; Marcus Valerius was named as his master of the horse. These two
                    marched against the Gauls, with the choicest troops from both the consular
                    armies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The war was considerably more protracted than
                    was pleasing to either side. At first only the Gauls had been eager for battle;
                    but later the Romans far exceeded the Gauls in the ardour with which they would
                    run to arm themselves and fight. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Yet the
                    dictator was by no means willing, being under no compulsion, to hazard his
                    fortune against an enemy whom each day made less formidable, as he lingered on
                    in an unfriendly country, without a magazine of food, and without adequate
                    defences —an enemy, too, whose strength and courage lay wholly in attacking, and
                    languished as soon as there came a slight delay. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Upon these considerations the dictator spun
                    out the war and threatened to punish anyone severely who should fight the enemy
                    without his orders. The soldiers were mortified at this. At first they grumbled
                    among themselves about the dictator, when on picket-duty or watching in the
                    night, and <pb n="p.397"/> sometimes railed at the senators collectively for not
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 359-358</note>
                    having given the consuls charge of the war; a fine general they had chosen, a
                    unique commander, who thought that without his lifting a finger victory would
                    fly down from heaven into his lap! <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But they
                    presently began to utter these same sentiments quite openly and in the light of
                    day, and even bolder things than these: they would not wait, they declared, for
                    the general's orders, but would either fight or go in a body to Rome. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> The centurions began to mingle with the soldiers;
                    the murmuring was not confined to little knots of men, but in the main street
                    and before the commander's tent there was now one general clamour; the throng
                    increased to the bigness of an assembly, and on every side shouts were heard
                    that they should go instantly to the dictator, and that Sextus Tullius should be
                    spokesman for the army, as became his courage. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now the seventh campaign in which
                    Tullius had served as first centurion, nor was there anyone in the army, at
                    least among the foot-soldiers, more distinguished for his services. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> At the head of the men, who followed in a body, he
                    approached the platform, where the amazement of Sulpicius on seeing the mob was
                    not greater than at seeing it led by Tullius, a soldier most obedient to
                    authority. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>By your leave, Dictator,</quote> he began, <quote> the entire army,
                        deeming itself condemned in your mind for cowardice and almost deprived of
                        its arms by way of humiliation, has asked me to plead its cause with you.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For my part, even if we could be
                        taunted with anywhere quitting a post, with turning our backs on the foe,
                        with shamefully losing our standards, I should still think you ought to
                        hearken <pb n="p.399"/> to our entreaty that we be permitted to redeem our
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                            359-358</note> fault with valour, and by winning new renown blot out the
                        memory of our disgrace. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Even the legions
                        that were routed at the Allia afterwards set out from Veii and by manful
                        conduct won back the very City their cowardice had lost. In our case, thanks
                        to the kindness of the gods and to your good fortune and that of the Roman
                        People, both our cause and our glory are unimpaired. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Yet I hardly dare to mention glory, since the enemy
                        flout us with every species of insult, as though we were women cowering
                        behind our rampart; and since you, our general —a thing far harder to bear
                        —regard us as an army without spirit, without swords, and without hands, and
                        ere you have given us a trial, have so despaired of us as to reckon yourself
                        a commander of cripples and weaklings. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For
                        how else can we account for it, that you, an experienced and fearless
                        general, should, as they say, be sitting down with folded hands? Indeed,
                        however this may be, it is more reasonable that you should seem to distrust
                        our bravery, than that we should seem to distrust yours. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> But if this is not your own but public policy, and if
                        some agreement amongst the senators, and not the Gallic war, keeps us in
                        exile from the City and from our homes, then I beg you to hear what I have
                        to say, as though it were spoken not by his soldiers to a general but by the
                        plebs to the patricians —for if the plebs, even as you have your policies,
                        should assert that they proposed likewise to have theirs, who, pray, could
                        be angry with them? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I say, then, we are
                        your soldiers, not your slaves; you have sent us to war, not into
                        banishment; if anyone would give us the signal and lead us into battle, we
                        are <pb n="p.401"/> ready to quit us in the fight like men and Romans: <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 359-358</note> but
                        if there be no occasion for our arms, we had rather spend our leisure in
                        Rome than in a camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus much we would
                        say to the patricians. But of you, our general, we, your soldiers, beg that
                        you give us an opportunity of fighting. We are eager not only to conquer,
                        but to conquer under your leadership; to win for you the glorious laurel; to
                        enter the City with you in the march of triumph; and following your chariot,
                        to approach the throne of Jupiter Optimus Maximus with gratulations and
                        rejoicings. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The speech of Tullius was supported by the
                    entreaties of the crowd, who on all sides clamoured for the signal and the
                    command to arm. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though the dictator felt that a good thing had
                    been carried out in a way to set a bad example, yet he undertook to do as the
                    soldiers wished. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In private he questioned
                    Tullius what this proceeding meant and on what precedent he had acted. Tullius
                    earnestly besought the dictator not to believe that he had forgotten the
                    training of a soldier, nor forgotten himself and the honour due to his
                    commander: the crowd, he said, had become excited; crowds were generally like
                    their leaders, and he had not refused to lead it, for fear that some other might
                    come forward, of the sort that an unruly mob was likely to choose; for his own
                    part he would do nothing without the approval of his general. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But Sulpicius, he continued, must none the less be very
                    wary himself, to keep the army in hand; postponement would not do, where
                    feelings were so exasperated; the men would choose for themselves a time and
                    place for fighting, if their general did not provide them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> While they were talking thus, <pb n="p.403"/> it chanced
                    that a Gaul attempted to drive off certain <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 359-358</note> sumpter animals that
                    were grazing outside of the stockade, and two Roman soldiers took them away from
                    him. These men were stoned by the Gauls. Whereupon a shout arose in the Roman
                    outpost, and men ran forward on both sides. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    And now the mellay was likely to end in a regular battle, had not the centurions
                    speedily parted the combatants. Sulpicius was assured by this incident that
                    Tullius spoke truth, and, the situation admitting of no delay, he announced a
                    general engagement for the morrow. </p>
                <p> Yet the dictator was entering a struggle in which he relied more on the spirit
                    of his troops than on their strength. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He began
                    therefore to cast about and every way to consider how he might strike terror
                    into the enemy by some stratagem. His cleverness produced a new expedient, which
                    many generals both of our own and foreign countries —some even in the present
                    age —have since employed. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">e. g.</hi> C. Marius at Aquae Sextiae (Frontinus, II. iv.
                        6), and Julius Caesar at Gergovia ( <hi rend="italics">Bell. Gall.</hi> VII.
                        xlv. 2). Bannockburn has been cited as a modern instance. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Commanding the muleteers to remove the
                    packsaddles from the mules, leaving only a pair of saddle-cloths on each, and
                    arming them, partly with captured weapons, partly with those belonging to the
                    sick, he mounted them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Having in this way made
                    out near a thousand, he mixed a hundred cavalrymen with them and ordered them to
                    go up by night on to the mountains above the camp and conceal themselves in the
                    woods, and not to stir from thence until they received a signal from him.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The dictator himself, as soon as it was
                    light, began to deploy his front along the lower slopes, on purpose to make the
                    enemy take their stand facing the mountains where the preparations had been made
                    for inspiring them with a fear which, groundless <pb n="p.405"/> though it was,
                    yet served the Romans almost better <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 359-358</note> than actual strength. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At first the Gallic leaders supposed that the Romans would
                    not come down into the plain; then, when they saw that they had suddenly begun
                    to descend, they also, being themselves eager for the combat, rushed into
                    battle, and the fighting began before the signal could be given by the generals. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The right wing of the Gauls attacked fiercely,
                    and it would have been impossible to stop them, if the dictator had not happened
                    to be there. Calling out to Sextus Tullius by name, he chid him and asked if
                    this was the kind of fighting he had promised that the men should do. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Where were those shouts with which they had called
                    for arms? Where were their threats that they would begin the battle without the
                    general's orders? Here was their general himself, who with a loud voice summoned
                    them to fight, and advanced, sword in hand, in the very van! <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Of those who but now were ready to lead, was there none to
                    follow? They might swagger in camp; in the field they were arrant cowards. What
                    he said was the truth, and so stung them with shame that they rushed on the
                    weapons of the enemy in utter forgetfulness of danger. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This well-nigh frenzied onset first threw their enemies
                    into disarray, and before they could recover their confusion the cavalry charged
                    and routed them. The dictator himself, as soon as he saw that a part of their
                    line was wavering, turned the infantry attack against their left, where he
                    descried a throng of the enemy gathering, and made the appointed signal to those
                    on the mountain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And when they too raised a
                    shout and were seen to <pb n="p.407"/> be moving obliquely down the mountain in
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 359-358</note>
                    direction of the Gallic camp, the enemy, fearing to be shut out, ceased fighting
                    and rushed pell-mell for their entrenchments. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    There however they were met by Marcus Valerius, the master of the horse, who,
                    having scattered the enemy's right wing, was then riding up to their works;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> whereupon they turned and fled towards the
                    mountains and the woods, where very many of them were intercepted by the
                    muleteers masquerading as cavalry; and those whose fright had carried them into
                    the woods were pitilessly slaughtered, after the battle had died down.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Not since the time of Marcus Furius has
                    anyone celebrated a Gallic triumph that was better deserved than that of Gaius
                    Sulpicius. He also collected from the spoils a considerable weight of gold,
                    which he walled up with hewn stone in the Capitol, and so dedicated. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the same year the consuls, too, waged war
                    with varying success. Gaius Plautius defeated the Hernici and reduced them to
                    subjection; his colleague Fabius showed neither prudence nor skill in his battle
                    with the Tarquinienses. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And yet the disaster
                    experienced on the field was overshadowed by the fact that the Tarquinienses
                    slew three hundred and seven captured Roman soldiers as a sacrifice —an act of
                    savage cruelty that greatly emphasized the humiliation of the Roman People.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In addition to this defeat, the Romans
                    suffered the devastation of their fields in sudden incursions made by the
                    Privernates, and afterwards by the Veliterni. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the same year two tribes were added; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Bringing up the total number at this
                        time to twenty-seven. </note> the Pomptine and the Publilian; the votive
                    games, <pb n="p.409"/> which Marcus Furius had vowed as dictator, were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 359-358</note> given;
                    and a statute against bribery was then for the first time laid before the people
                    by Gaius Poetelius, tribune of the plebs, with the approbation of the senate.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> By this measure they thought to have
                    suppressed corrupt practices, particularly on the part of men risen from the
                    people, who were wont to haunt the country fairs and gathering-places. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Less agreeable to the senate was a measure
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 357</note> which
                    came up in the following year, in the consulship of Gaius Marcius and Gnaeus
                    Manlius. It fixed the rate of interest at one per cent., and was carried through
                    by Marcus Duillius and Lucius Menenius, tribunes of the plebs. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The commons ratified it much more eagerly than they had
                    done the other law. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Tacitus tells us
                        ( <hi rend="italics">Annals</hi> VI. xvi.) that the twelve Tables had
                        forbidden a higher rate of interest. If so, the tribunes were merely
                        reviving an obsolete enactment. The words <hi rend="italics">unciarium
                            fenus</hi> clearly mean a rate of one twelfth but just how that rate was
                        applied is very doubtful. It may be 1/12 of the whole principal or 1/12 of 1
                        per cent.; the period may be one month or one year; and, finally, the year
                        may be 10 months or 12. The rate in modern terms may then be 1 per cent. (as
                        translated here), 8 1/3 per cent. as assumed by Frank, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Economic Survey of Ancient Rome,</hi> I. 282), 10 per cent. (cf.
                        Weissenborn <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi> ) or 100 per cent. (so
                        apparently Last, Camb, Anc. Hist. VII. 476). </note>
                </p>
                <p> Besides the new wars determined on in the previous year, the Faliscans also rose
                    up as enemies. They were charged with two offences: their youth had fought on
                    the side of the Tarquinienses; and they had refused the demand of the fetials
                    that they should give up the Romans who had taken refuge in Falerii, after the
                    defeat. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This command was assigned to Gnaeus
                    Manlius. Marcius led an army into the territory of Privernum, unravaged during a
                    long period of peace, and loaded his troops with booty. This abundance he
                    administered bountifully, and sequestering nothing to the public treasury,
                    encouraged the men to augment their private fortunes. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Privernates having encamped in front of their town,
                    within strong intrenchments, Marcius called his soldiers together and thus
                    addressed them: <quote> I give you now for booty the camp and city of our
                        enemies, if you promise me <pb n="p.411"/> that in the battle you will play
                        the part of men, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                            357</note> and be not more ready to plunder than to fight. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They clamoured loudly for the signal and
                    entered the battle with spirit, emboldened by no uncertain expectations. There
                    in the fore-front Sextus Tullius, who has been mentioned before, cried out,
                        <quote>Look, general, and see how your army keeps the promises it gave
                        you!</quote> Then, laying down his javelin, he drew his sword and charged
                    the foe. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All of the front line followed
                    Tullius, and putting the enemy to flight at the first shock, pursued them to the
                    town, where the Romans were already bringing up their scaling ladders to the
                    wall, when the place surrendered. A triumph was celebrated over the Privernates. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The other consul accomplished nothing worth
                    recording, except that without precedent he got a law passed in his camp before
                    Sutrium —the men voting by tribes —which levied a tax of one-twentieth on
                    manumissions. The Fathers ratified this law, since it brought in no small
                    revenue to the empty treasury; but the tribunes of the plebs, troubled less by
                    the law than by the precedent established, had it made a capital offence for
                    anyone thereafter to summon the people to the comitia away from Rome. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> If this should be permitted, there was nothing, they
                    argued, however baneful to the people, which could not be carried through by the
                    votes of soldiers sworn to obey their consul. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Within a distance of one mile from the walls a citizen
                        might appeal from the decision of a consul, but beyond that point the
                        consul's authority was absolute. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the same year Gaius Licinius Stolo was
                    prosecuted under his own statute by Marcus Popilius Laenas, and condemned to pay
                    a fine of ten thousand <hi rend="italics">asses,</hi> on the charge that he held
                    with his son a thousand <hi rend="italics">iugera</hi> of land, and by
                    emancipating his son <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">From his paternal
                        authority.</note> had evaded the law. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> By the Licinio-Sextian legislation of 367 it had been
                        forbidden that anybody should hold more than 500 <hi rend="italics">iugera.
                            cf.</hi> VI. xxxv. 5. </note>
                </p>
                <pb n="p.413"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> New consuls now came in, Marcus Fabius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 356-355</note> Ambustus
                    and Marcus Popilius Laenas, each for the second time. They had two wars.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One of these was easy; it was waged by
                    Laenas against the Tiburtes, and he shut up the enemy within their city and
                    pillaged their fields. The other consul was routed by the Faliscans and
                    Tarquinienses in his first engagement. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    panic was chiefly due to this, that their priests, bearing serpents and blazing
                    torches before them, came rushing on like Furies, and utterly dismayed the Roman
                    soldiers with the extraordinary sight. At first they were like men frantic and
                    distraught, and flung themselves in a disordered mob into their own works.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then when the consul, the lieutenants and
                    the tribunes laughed at them and upbraided them for being scared like children
                    at idle tricks, shame caused a sudden revulsion in their feelings, and they
                    rushed, as if blinded, on the very objects from which they had fled. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> In this spirit they brushed aside the enemy's vain
                    paraphernalia, and hurling themselves on his real fighting men, they routed the
                    whole army, and even captured the camp that day. As they returned victorious
                    with the rich plunder they had won, they jested in soldier-fashion and scoffed
                    not only at the enemy's devices but at their own fright as well. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> All who bore the Etruscan name then rose in arms, and
                    led by the men of Tarquinii and Falerii, advanced as far as Salinae. To meet
                    this fearful danger Gaius Marcius Rutulus was made dictator, the first that was
                    ever appointed from the plebs, and he named a plebeian also, Gaius Plautius, to
                    be master of the horse. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the patricians
                    thought it shameful that even the dictatorship should now <pb n="p.415"/> be
                    common; and they exerted all their influence <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 356-355</note> to prevent anything
                    being decreed or made ready for the dictator, to carry on that war. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> For which reason the people voted the more promptly
                    everything that the dictator proposed. Marching out from the City and setting
                    his army across the Tiber by means of rafts, wherever a rumour <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> of the enemy called him, he surprised many
                    straggling pillagers as they roamed about the fields, on both sides of the
                    river; he also captured their camp in a surprise attack, and with it eight
                    thousand soldiers; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and having slain the rest,
                    or driven them out of Roman territory, was granted a triumph by the people, but
                    without the authorization of the senate. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Compare the story of Valerius and Horatius at III.
                        lxiii. 11. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The patricians were not willing that a
                    consular election should be held by a plebeian, whether dictator or consul, and
                    the other consul being detained by the war, the state relapsed into an
                    interregnum. The office of interrex was held successively by Quintus Servilius
                    Ahala, Marcus Fabius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps
                        identical with the M. Fabius Ambustus of VI. xxii., xxxiv., xxxvi.; perhaps
                        with the M. Fabius Dorsuo of VII. xxviii. </note> Gnaeus Manlius, Gaius
                    Fabius, Gaius Sulpicius, Lucius Aemilius, Quintus Servilius, and Marcus Fabius
                    Ambustus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the second interregnum a
                    controversy arose because two patricians were on the point of being named as
                    consuls; and when the tribunes sought to veto the announcement, the interrex
                    Fabius declared that the Twelve Tables enacted that whatsoever the people
                    decreed last should have the binding force of law, and their votes were also a
                    decree. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The tribunes gained nothing more by
                    their intervention than a postponement of the comitia, and two patrician consuls
                    were elected, namely Gaius Sulpicius Peticus (for the third time) and Marcus
                    Valerius Publicola. They entered office that very day, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 354</note>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <pb n="p.417"/> in the four hundredth year from the founding of Rome <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 354</note> and the
                    thirty-fifth from its recovery from the Gauls, depriving the plebs of the
                    consulship they had enjoyed for ten years. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Empulum was won that year from the Tiburtes without any memorable battle being
                    fought; whether, as some writers state, the campaign was conducted there under
                    the auspices of the two consuls; or whether the lands belonging to Tarquinii
                    were ravaged by the consul Sulpicius at the same time that Valerius led his
                    legions against the Tiburtes. </p>
                <p> The consuls had a harder struggle at home, with the plebs and the tribunes.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They held that honour as well as courage
                    required of them that, even as two patricians had received the consulship, so
                    they should hand it over to successors who were both patricians: <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> indeed they ought rather to withdraw from the
                    consulship altogether, that it might at once become a plebeian magistracy, or
                    else retain undivided that control which they had inherited entire from their
                    fathers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the other side, the plebeians were
                    asking angrily why they lived, why they were counted a part of the state, if
                    they were unable by their collective efforts to maintain what the courage of two
                    men, Lucius Sextius and Gaius Licinius, had won for them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> It were better to put up with kings or decemvirs, or —if
                    possible —a <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> more stern type of government than
                    theirs, rather than see the consuls both patricians and have no turns at obeying
                    and commanding, while a part of the people thought themselves established
                    forever in authority and the commons born for no other end than servitude.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There was no lack of tribunes to promote
                    disturbances, but where all were so excited, to begin with, the leaders were
                    hardly to <pb n="p.419"/> be discerned. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After
                    the people had several times <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 354</note> gone down to the Campus Martius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Where the voting took place.</note> to
                    no purpose, and many meeting days had been spent in rioting, the persistence of
                    the consuls finally prevailed. The plebs, thereupon, in a burst of resentment,
                    followed their tribunes, who cried out that liberty was lost and that they ought
                    now to leave not only the voting-field but the City, too, which was taken
                    captive and enslaved by the tyranny of the patricians. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls, being deserted by half the people,
                    nevertheless, despite the paucity of voters, completed the election. The
                    successful candidates were both patricians, Marcus Fabius Ambustus (for the
                    third time) and Titus Quinctius. In certain annals I find Marcus Popilius given
                    as consul instead of Titus Quinctius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Two wars were successfully prosecuted this
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 353</note> year,
                    and the Tarquinienses and Tiburtes were forced to make submission. From the
                    latter their city of Sassula was taken, and the rest of their towns would have
                    met with the same fortune, had the whole nation not laid down their arms and
                    cast themselves upon the mercy of the consul. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    A triumph was celebrated over them, but in all other respects the victory was
                    used with clemency. The men of Tarquinii were shown no ruth; many were slain in
                    the field of battle, and out of the vast number taken prisoners three hundred
                    and fifty-eight were selected —the noblest of them all —to be sent to Rome, and
                    the rest of the populace were put to the sword. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Neither were the People less stern towards those who had been sent to Rome,
                    but scourged them all with rods in the middle of the Forum and struck off their
                    heads. Such was the vengeance they exacted of their enemies for the Romans
                    sacrificed <pb n="p.421"/> in the market-place of Tarquinii. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chap. xv. § 10.</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their success in <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 353</note> war induced the Samnites
                    also to apply for their friendship. The senate made a courteous answer to their
                    ambassadors, and granted them a treaty of alliance. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman commons were not so fortunate at
                    home as in the field. For notwithstanding they had been relieved of usury by the
                    adoption of a one per cent. rate, the very poor found even the principal sum a
                    crushing burden, and were being bound over to their creditors. Hence it was that
                    neither the incumbency of two patrician consuls, nor concern for the elections
                    or affairs of state, could divert the thoughts of the plebeians from their
                    personal distresses. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly both
                    consulships continued in the hands of the patricians; Gaius Sulpicius Peticus
                    was elected for the fourth time, and Marcus Valerius Publicola for the second. </p>
                <p> While the citizens were occupied with thoughts of an Etruscan war —for it was
                    rumoured that the people of Caere, out of compassion for their kinsmen of
                    Tarquinii, had made common cause with them —came envoys from the Latins and
                    turned their thoughts upon the Volsci, with a report that they had mustered and
                    equipped an army, which was even then descending upon Latium, from whence it
                    would invade and devastate the territory of the Romans. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The senate therefore resolved that neither threat must be
                    neglected; and ordered that legions should be enrolled for both campaigns, and
                    that the consuls should decide the commands by lot. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> But the Etruscan war afterwards came to be their chief
                    concern, on the receipt of a dispatch from the consul Sulpicius, who had
                    received the assignment <pb n="p.423"/> to Tarquinii, with the news that the
                    countryside <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.
                        C.353</note> lying near the Roman salt-works had been pillaged, and a part
                    of the booty carried into the borders of the Caerites, whose soldiers had,
                    without question, been amongst the depredators. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> And so the senate recalled Valerius the consul, who was opposing the Volsci
                    and had his camp close to the Tusculan frontier, and ordered him to nominate a
                    dictator. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> His choice fell upon Titus Manlius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">sc. Torquatus. See chap. v. § 3
                        and chap. x. § 13.</note> the son of Lucius, who appointed as master of the
                    horse Aulus Cornelius Cossus. Asking for no more than the consular army, the
                    dictator, by the senate's authority, and at the bidding of the people,
                    proclaimed war on the Caerites. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was then that the Caerites realized for the
                    first time the full danger of war, as if the words of their enemies conveyed a
                    more emphatic hint of it than their own acts, though they had pillaged the
                    Romans and harried them. Beginning then to perceive how inadequate was their
                    strength to such a quarrel, they repented of their raid, and cursed the
                    Tarquinienses, who had encouraged them to fall away. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Nobody made ready his arms and prepared for war, but one
                    and all bade dispatch ambassadors to Rome, to beg forgiveness for their error.
                    The envoys, having approached the senate, were sent by them to be dealt with by
                    the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Calling on the gods whose sacred
                    emblems they had received and religiously protected in the Gallic war, they
                    besought them to inspire the Romans in their prosperity with such compassion for
                    the men of Caere as they themselves had formerly shown for Rome in her time of
                    tribulation. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See v. xl. 7 and 1.
                        3.</note> Then, turning to the shrine of Vesta, they invoked the flamens and
                    Vestals whom they had <pb n="p.425"/> entertained with a pure and scrupulous
                    hospitality. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        353</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Could anyone, they asked, believe that those
                    who had deserved so well of the Romans had suddenly turned enemies without
                    reason? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> or that if they had in fact committed
                    an act of hostility, it had been deliberately planned, and had not rather been
                    owing to a fit of madness? Would they undo their own kindness of old, especially
                    kindness to such grateful friends, with new misdeeds; and choose to be enemies
                    of the Roman People in their flourishing state and at the height of their
                    success in war, when they had sought their friendship in the hour of their
                    adversity? Let them not give the name of <quote>purpose</quote> to what should
                    properly be called <quote>force</quote> and <quote>necessity.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Tarquinienses, marching in hostile array
                    through their territories, had sought nothing of them save permission to pass,
                    but had drawn certain rustics after them in their train, who had borne a part in
                    the pillaging with which the people of Caere were now taxed. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> If it pleased the Romans that these men should be
                    surrendered, they would surrender them; if they would have them punished, they
                    should be made to suffer. But Caere, the sanctuary of the Roman People, the
                    hostel of its priests and refuge of the Roman religion, let them preserve intact
                    and unstained by the imputation of making war, for the sake of the hospitality
                    it had shown their Vestals and the reverence it had paid their gods. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The people were moved, not so much by their present
                    claims as by their ancient merits, and chose rather to forget an injury than a
                    kindness. So peace was granted to the people of Caere, and it was resolved that
                    a truce of a hundred years be made, and recorded on a table of bronze.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The <pb n="p.427"/> brunt of the war was
                    turned against the Faliscans, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 353</note> who lay under the same accusation; but the
                    enemy were nowhere encountered. Having ranged over their lands and laid them
                    waste, the Romans refrained from attacking their cities, and led their legions
                    home. The rest of the year was consumed in repairing the walls and towers, and a
                    temple was dedicated to Apollo. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the latter part of the year the consular
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 352</note>
                    election was broken off by a quarrel between the patricians and the plebs: the
                    tribunes refused to permit the assembly to be held unless it were held agreeably
                    to the Licinian law, and the dictator was obstinately determined rather to
                    remove the consulship root and branch out of the state than to throw it open to
                    patricians and plebs without distinction. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    assembly was therefore repeatedly adjourned, until the dictator's term had
                    expired, and the state reverted to an interregnum. The interreges found the
                    commons hostile to the patricians, and the factional struggle continued until
                    there had been eleven interreges. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes
                    continually vaunted their backing of the Licinian law: the plebs were more
                    concerned with the distress they suffered from the increasing weight of usury,
                    and their private worries broke out into public quarrels. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Worn out with these, the senate ordered Lucius Cornelius
                    Scipio, the interrex, for harmony's sake to observe the Licinian law at the
                    consular election. Publius Valerius Publicola <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Brother of the Marcus Valerius of chap. xxiii. §
                        3.</note> was elected, with a plebeian colleague named Gaius Marcius
                    Rutulus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Now that the minds of men were once
                    inclined to concord, the new consuls set themselves to obtain relief in the
                    matter of usury also, which appeared to be the sole <pb n="p.429"/> obstacle to
                    harmony. They made the discharge of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 352</note> debts a concern of the state, appointing five
                    commissioners, whom they called bankers, from their having the disposition of
                    the money. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These men by their impartiality and
                    diligence fairly earned the distinction which attaches, in all the histories, to
                    the names of Gaius Duillius, Publius Decius Mus, Marcus Papirius, Quintus
                    Publilius, and Titus Aemilius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the
                    discharge of a very difficult duty, involving always a hardship for one of the
                    parties, and in most instances for both, they managed matters wisely in other
                    respects, and, in particular, they expended without throwing away the public
                    funds. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For with long-standing accounts,
                    embarrassed more by the debtors' neglect than by their lack of means, they dealt
                    in one of the following ways: either they paid them out of the treasury —taking
                    security for the people first —at the banking tables they had set up in the
                    Forum; or they settled them upon a valuation, at fair prices, of the debtor's
                    effects. And so, not only without injustice, but even without complaint from
                    either side, a vast amount of indebtedness was cleared off. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A groundless fear of war with Etruria, on a
                    report that the twelve nations had conspired, compelled the appointment of a
                    dictator. The appointment was made in camp —for thither had the resolution of
                    the senate been sent to the consuls —and Gaius Julius became dictator, with
                    Lucius Aemilius for master of the horse. But abroad all was serene, <milestone
                        n="22" unit="chapter"/> while at home an attempt, made through the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 351</note> dictator,
                    to obtain the return of patricians to both consulships, brought the state to an
                    interregnum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The two interreges who were put
                    in, Gaius Sulpicius <pb n="p.431"/> and Marcus Fabius, brought to pass what the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 351</note>
                    dictator had vainly striven for; and the plebs being now grown more tractable,
                    thanks to the help lately granted them in the relief of debt, both men elected
                    consuls were patricians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These were that very
                    Gaius Sulpicius Peticus, who was the earlier of the two interreges, and Titus
                    Quinctius Poenus. (Some give Caeso, others Gaius, as the praenomen of
                    Quinctius.) <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Both marched out to fight,
                    Quinctius against the Faliscans, Sulpicius against the Tarquinienses; but
                    nowhere encountering their enemies in battle, they warred rather with the land,
                    which they burnt and pillaged, than with men; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    until the obstinacy of both peoples was overcome, as by the wasting of a
                    lingering illness, and they requested a truce, first of the consuls, and later,
                    by their permission, of the senate. They were granted one for forty years. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The anxiety arising from two threatening wars
                    being thus allayed, it was resolved that while there was some rest from arms
                    they would take the census; for the settlement of debts had brought about the
                    change of ownership in many properties. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But
                    when notice had been given of an assembly for the election of censors, an
                    announcement that he should be a candidate on the part of Gaius Marcius Rutulus,
                    who had been the first plebeian dictator, played havoc with the harmony of the
                    orders; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for he seemed to have taken this step
                    at an untoward time, since both the consuls, as it fell out, were then
                    patricians, who declared that they would receive no votes for him; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> but Rutulus himself held firmly to his purpose, and
                    the tribunes aided him with all their power, in the hope of <pb n="p.433"/>
                    recovering what they had lost in the election of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 351</note> consuls; and not only was
                    the man's own greatness equal to any honour, however lofty, but the plebs
                    desired that they might be called to share the censorship by the same man who
                    had opened up for them a path to the dictatorship. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> There was no dissenting opinion shown at the assembly, and
                    Marcius was elected, along with Manlius Naevius. </p>
                <p> There was a dictator in this year also, namely, Marcus Fabius, not because of
                    any threatened war, but to prevent the observance of the Licinian law in the
                    consular election. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Quintus Servilius was
                    assigned to the dictator as master of the horse. But the dictatorship made the
                    unanimity of the patricians no more potent in the election of consuls than it
                    had been in the election of censors. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 350</note>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/> Marcus Popilius Laenas was chosen from the
                    plebs, Lucius Cornelius Scipio from the patricians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fortune even made the plebeian consul the more
                    illustrious, for the news that a huge army of Gauls had encamped in Latium found
                    Scipio afflicted with a grave disorder, and the conduct of the war was entrusted
                    by special arrangement to Popilius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He levied
                    troops with energy, and ordered all the young men to assemble under arms outside
                    the Porta Capena, at the temple of Mars, commanding the quaestors to convey the
                    standards thither, from the treasury. After filling up four legions, he turned
                    over the supernumeraries to the praetor, Publius Valerius Publicola, urging the
                    senators to enroll <pb n="p.435"/> a second army as a national reserve against
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C 350</note>
                    uncertain emergencies of war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Having at length
                    concluded all the necessary preparations, he himself marched against the enemy;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and that he might first learn their
                    strength before putting it to the test of a decisive battle, he seized and began
                    to fortify an eminence as close as he could find to the camp of the Gauls.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These, being a fierce people and by nature
                    eager for the combat, on beholding the Roman ensigns in the distance, at once
                    drew out their line, as if for instant battle. But perceiving that the Romans
                    did not descend into the plain, but sought to protect themselves not only by
                    their position but even with a rampart, they supposed them to be panic-stricken
                    and at the same time the more open to attack for being just then taken up with
                    their task. They advanced, therefore, with hideous yells. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans without a pause in their work, on which the
                    reserves were engaged, began the action with their troops of the first and
                    second lines, who had been standing alert and armed in front of the working
                    party. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides their valour, they had an
                    advantage from the elevation, for their javelins and spears, instead of falling
                    without effect, as they mostly do when thrown on a level field, were steadied by
                    their own weight and all struck home. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    Gauls were burdened with the missiles which had either transfixed their bodies,
                    or, sticking in their shields, had made them very heavy; their dash had carried
                    them almost up the slope, but first they halted, uncertain what to do, and then
                    —for <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the mere delay had abated their ardour
                    and increased that of their foes —they were thrown back, and falling one upon
                        <pb n="p.437"/> another wrought greater carnage than even their <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 350</note> enemies had
                    done; for so headlong was the rout, that more were trodden under foot than slain
                    with the sword. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the Romans were not yet sure of victory;
                    on descending into the plain they found another fight awaiting them. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For the Gallic host, superior to any feeling for such
                    losses, sprang up like a new army, and urged their fresh troops against the
                    victorious foe. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans, slowing down, came
                    to a halt, for they were confronted, weary as they were, with a second struggle,
                    and the consul, rashly exposing himself in the van, had received a javelin in
                    his left shoulder that had like to have gone clean through it, and had withdrawn
                    for a brief space from the fight. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And now the
                    delay had almost lost them the victory, when the consul, whose wound had been
                    dressed, rode up again to the front. <quote>Why are you standing there, my
                        men?</quote> he exclaimed. <quote> You have no Latin or Sabine foe to deal
                        with, whom you may overcome in fight and transform from an enemy into an
                        ally; we have drawn the sword against wild beasts, and we must have their
                        blood or yield them ours. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You have
                        repulsed them from your camp, you have driven them headlong down a sloping
                        valley, you stand on heaps of your slain enemies; cover the plain with the
                        same carnage you have spread upon the mountains. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Do not wait for the enemy to flee from you, while you
                        stand still; you must move forward and attack them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Roused once more to action by these
                    exhortations, they drove back the foremost of the Gallic maniples, and then,
                    forming in wedges, burst through into the midst of the main <pb n="p.439"/>
                    array; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> whereat the barbarians were thrown into
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 350</note>
                    confusion, having no definite orders nor commanders, and, turning, charged upon
                    their fellows; and so, dispersed about the fields, and even carried past their
                    own camp in the rout, they made for the highest point in the range of hills that
                    met their eyes, namely, the Alban Citadel. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy seems to have in mind the summit now called Monte
                        Cavo, though it is strangely described as <hi rend="italics">editissimum
                            inter aequales tumulos.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul did not pursue them beyond their
                    camp, for his wound was troubling him, and he was unwilling to send his troops
                    against the hills which the enemy had occupied. Giving over to his soldiers the
                    entire booty of the camp, he led back his army, flushed with victory and
                    enriched with the Gallic spoils, to Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    consul's triumph was delayed by reason of his wound, which also made the senate
                    wish for a dictator, that there might be someone —in the illness of the consuls
                    —who could hold the election. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Lucius Furius
                    Camillus was appointed to that office, and Publius Cornelius Scipio was made his
                    master of the horse. Camillus restored to the patricians their ancient
                    possession of the consulship, and in recognition of this service was himself,
                    with their warm support, elected consul, and announced the election of Appius
                    Claudius Crassus as his colleague. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the new consuls entered office, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Probably, at this time, on the 1st of
                        July.</note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 348</note> Popilius
                    celebrated his triumph over the Gauls, with great enthusiasm on the part of the
                    plebeians, who, muttering low, would often ask each other if anyone regretted
                    the choice of a plebeian <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> consul. At the same
                    time they railed against Camillus, who by declaring himself elected consul, when
                    he was dictator, had got a reward, they said, for his contempt of the Licinian
                    law more disgraceful for his personal cupidity than for the injury done the
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> commonwealth. </p>
                <pb n="p.441"/>
                <p> The year was signalized by many and various <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 348</note> disturbances. The Gauls came
                    down from the Alban hills, having been unable to endure the sharpness of the
                    winter, and ranging over the plains and sea-coast, laid waste the <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> country. The sea was infested by fleets of Greeks,
                    and so were the seaboard of Antium, the Laurentine district, and the mouth of
                    the Tiber. It happened once that the sea-robbers encountered the land-raiders,
                    and a hard-fought battle ensued, from which the Gauls withdrew to their camp and
                    the Greeks to their ships, alike uncertain whether they had been defeated or
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> victorious. But by far the greatest of
                    these alarms was occasioned by councils of the Latin tribes, assembled at the
                    grove of Ferentina, and the unambiguous reply vouchsafed by them to a demand for
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> soldiers. Let the Romans, they said, have
                    done with issuing commands to those whose assistance they required: the Latins
                    would sooner bear arms in behalf of their own liberty than of an alien
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> domination. Involved in two foreign wars
                    at once, and worried besides by the defection of their allies, the senate
                    perceived that those whom loyalty had not restrained must be restrained by fear,
                    and bade the consuls exert the full extent of their authority in levying troops:
                    for they must depend on a soldiery of citizens, when their allies were leaving
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> them. They say that soldiers were enlisted
                    everywhere, not in the City alone but in the country, and ten legions were
                    embodied, each of four thousand two hundred foot and three hundred <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> horse. The raising of a new army of this size to-day,
                    in case of any aggression from abroad, could not easily be compassed by the
                    concentration on one object of the <pb n="p.443"/> existing resources of the
                    Roman People, though <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        348</note> the world hardly contains them; so strictly has our growth been
                    limited to the only things for which we strive, —wealth and <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> luxury. </p>
                <p> Among the untoward occurrences of this year was the death of one of the consuls,
                    Appius Claudius, in the midst of the preparations for <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> war. The administration of the state passed to Camillus,
                    over whom, as sole consul, —whether owing to his general high standing, which
                    deserved not to be subordinated to the dictatorship, or to the happy omen, in a
                    Gallic rising, of his surname, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> His
                        father, the great Camillus, had defeated the Gauls after their capture of
                        Rome (v. xlix.). </note> —the Fathers concluded it not meet to set a
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> dictator. The consul appointed two
                    legions to defend the City, and divided the other eight with Lucius Pinarius the
                    praetor. Having a lively recollection of his father's prowess, he took upon
                    himself, without drawing lots, the conduct of the Gallic war, and commanded the
                    praetor to secure the seaboard and prevent the Greeks from <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> landing. Then, marching down into the Pomptine district, he
                    chose a suitable site for a permanent camp; for he had no mind to meet the enemy
                    in the field, unless compelled to do so, believing that he should effectually
                    subdue them if he kept them from making raids, since they subsisted necessarily
                    on plunder. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While they were there quietly passing the time
                    in guard-duty, a Gaul came out to them, remarkable for his great stature and his
                    armour, and, smiting his spear against his shield and thereby obtaining silence,
                    challenged the Romans, through an interpreter, to send a man to fight with him.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was a young tribune of the soldiers,
                    named Marcus Valerius, who, regarding himself as no less <pb n="p.445"/> worthy
                    of that honour than Titus Manlius had been, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 348</note> first ascertained the
                    consul's wishes, and then armed himself and advanced into the midst. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> But the human interest of the combat was eclipsed by
                    the intervention of the gods; for the Roman was in the very act of engaging,
                    when suddenly a raven alighted on his helmet, facing his adversary. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This the tribune first received with joy, as a
                    heaven-sent augury, and then prayed that whosoever, be it god or goddess, had
                    sent the auspicious bird might attend him with favour and protection. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Marvellous to relate, the bird not only held to the
                    place it had once chosen, but as often as the combatants closed, it rose on its
                    wings and attacked the enemy's face and eyes with beak and talons, till he was
                    terror-struck with the sight of such a portent, and bewildered at once in his
                    vision and his mind, was dispatched by Valerius, —whereupon the raven flew off
                    towards the east and was lost to sight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Hitherto the outguards on either side had stood quietly by; but when the tribune
                    began to despoil the corpse of his fallen foe, the Gauls remained no longer at
                    their station, and the Romans ran up even more swiftly to the victor. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> There a scuffle, arising over the body of the
                    prostrate Gaul, led to a desperate fight that was not long confined to the
                    maniples of the nearest outposts, for the legions, rushing out on both sides,
                    carried on the battle. Camillus ordered his soldiers to fall on, elated as they
                    were by the tribune's victory, elated too by the present assistance of the gods;
                    and pointing to the tribune, decked out in his spoils, he cried, <quote> Here is
                        your pattern, soldiers! <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Bring down the
                        Gauls in troops around their prostrate leader! </quote>
                    <pb n="p.447"/> Both gods and men helped in that battle, and they <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 348</note> fought it
                    out with the Gauls to a conclusion that was never doubtful, so clearly had each
                    side foreseen the result implicit in the outcome of the single combat.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Between those who began the fray, and by
                    their conflict drew in the others, there was a bitter struggle; but the rest of
                    the Gallic host turned tail ere they came within the cast of a javelin. At first
                    they scattered among the Volsci and through the Falernian countryside; from
                    there they made their way into Apulia or to the Tuscan Sea. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consul assembled his soldiers, and having
                    eulogized the tribune, bestowed on him ten oxen and a golden coronet; Camillus
                    himself was commanded by the senate to take charge of the operations on the
                    coast, and accordingly joined forces with the praetor. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The campaign there seemed likely to be long drawn out, for
                    the Greeks were poltroons and refused to risk an engagement. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore, on the authorization of the senate, appointed
                    Titus Manlius Torquatus to be dictator, that an election might be held. The
                    dictator, after naming Aulus Cornelius Cossus master of the horse, presided over
                    a consular election, and announced, amid great popular rejoicings, that the
                    choice had fallen —in his absence —upon a youth of twenty-three, the Marcus
                    Valerius Corvus —for this was his surname from that time —who had rivalled
                    Manlius's own glorious achievement. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As
                    colleague of Corvus they elected the plebeian Marcus Popilius Laenas to be for
                    the fourth time consul. With the Greeks, Camillus fought no memorable action;
                    they were no warriors on land, nor were the Romans on the sea. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> In the end, being kept off shore, and their <pb n="p.449"/>
                    water giving out, as well as other necessaries, they <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 348</note> abandoned Italy. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> To what people or race their fleet belonged is
                    uncertain. I am most inclined to think that they were Sicilian tyrants; for
                    Greece proper was at that time exhausted with civil wars and trembled, even
                    then, at the power of the Macedonians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the armies had been disbanded, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 347-346</note> and
                    there was peace with other nations, and —thanks to the goodwill betwixt the
                    orders —quietness at home, that the happiness of the citizens might not pass all
                    bounds, a pestilence attacked them and the senate was compelled to order the ten
                    commissioners <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For these commissioners
                        see VI. xlii. 2.</note> to consult the Sibylline Books. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> By their direction a lectisternium <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See v. xiii. 6 and note there.</note> was held. In the
                    same year a colony was sent out to Satricum by the Antiates, and that city,
                    which had been destroyed by the Latins, was rebuilt. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Further, a treaty was entered into at Rome with envoys of
                    the Carthaginians, who had come seeking friendship and an alliance. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is the first mention in Livy of a
                        treaty with the Carthaginians, and Diodorus (XVI. lxix.) also speaks of it
                        as the first, but Polybius (III. xxii.) tells of a treaty between Rome and
                        Carthage made in the first year of the Republic ( <date when="-0509">509
                            B.C.</date> ). </note>
                </p>
                <p> The same peaceful conditions continued at home and abroad during the consulship
                    of Titus Manlius Torquatus and Gaius Plautius. But the rate of interest was
                    reduced from one to one-half per cent., <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> chap. xvi. § 1 and note. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and debts were made payable, one-fourth down
                    and the remainder in three annual instalments; even so some of the plebeians
                    were distressed, but the public credit was of greater concern to the senate than
                    were the hardships of single persons. What did the most to lighten the burden
                    was the omission of the war-tax and the levy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the second year after the rebuilding of
                    Satricum by the Volsci, Marcus Valerius Corvus became consul for the second
                    time, with Gaius Poetelius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A report having
                    come out of Latium that emissaries of the <pb n="p.451"/> Antiates were
                    circulating amongst the Latin peoples <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 347-346</note> with a view to stir up war, Valerius was
                    ordered to deal with the Volsci before more enemies should arise, and marched to
                    the attack of Satricum. There he was opposed by the Antiates and the other
                    Volsci, with forces which they had levied in advance, in case any measures
                    should be taken by the Romans; and both sides being actuated by inveterate
                    hatred, the battle was joined without delay. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Volsci, a race more spirited in beginning than in prosecuting war, were
                    defeated in the struggle and fled in disorder to the walls of Satricum. Indeed,
                    they put no great reliance even in their walls, for when the city had been
                    encircled with troops and was on the point of being escaladed, they surrendered,
                    being in number about four thousand soldiers, besides the unarmed populace.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The town was dismantled and burnt; only
                    the temple of Mater Matuta <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> An Italian
                        goddess associated with birth and the dawn, and widely worshipped; in
                        Satricum apparently the chief deity. <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Warde
                        Fowler, <hi rend="italics">Festivals,</hi> p. 155. </note> was saved from
                    the flames. All the booty was given to the soldiers. The four thousand who had
                    surrendered were not reckoned a part of the spoils; these the consul sent in
                    chains before his chariot when he triumphed, and they were subsequently sold,
                    and brought in a great sum to the treasury. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Some think that this multitude of captives consisted of slaves, and this is more
                    likely than that surrendered men were sold. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These consuls were succeeded by Marcus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> Fabius
                    Dorsuo and Servius Sulpicius Camerinus. War then broke out with the Aurunci, in
                    consequence of a raid which they unexpectedly executed. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was feared that this act of a single nation might be the
                    joint design of all of the Latin name, and a dictator was appointed —as though
                    to <pb n="p.453"/> oppose a Latium already up in arms —in the person <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> of
                    Lucius Furius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After naming Gnaeus Manlius
                    Capitolinus to be his master of the horse, he suspended the courts, and having
                    levied troops without exemptions —as was customary in great emergencies —he led
                    them with all possible speed against the Aurunci. These he discovered to possess
                    the spirit of freebooters rather than of enemies, and so brought the war to a
                    conclusion in the first engagement. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Howbeit
                    the dictator, considering that they had been the aggressors in the war and were
                    accepting battle without shrinking, saw fit to summon even the gods to help him,
                    and in the heat of the encounter vowed a temple to Juno Moneta. This vow the
                    result made binding, and the dictator having returned to Rome victorious,
                    resigned his authority. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate ordered
                    that two commissioners should be designated to erect the temple in a style
                    becoming to the grandeur of the Roman People, and a site was appointed for it in
                    the Citadel, where once had stood the house of Marcus Manlius Capitolinus.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls, employing the dictator's army
                    for the Volscian war, made a surprise attack upon the enemy and captured Sora. </p>
                <p> The temple of Moneta was dedicated the next year after it was vowed, when Gaius
                    Marcius Rutulus was consul for the third time and Titus Manlius Torquatus for
                    the second. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The dedication was immediately
                    followed by a prodigy like the one which had happened long before on the Alban
                    Mount; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">I. xxxi. 1.</note> for a shower
                    of stones fell, and a curtain of night seemed to stretch across the sky; and
                    when the Books <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the Sibylline Books. </note> had been consulted
                    and the City was filled with forebodings of divine displeasure, the <pb
                        n="p.455"/> senate resolved on the appointment of a dictator, to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note>
                    establish days of worship. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The choice fell on
                    Publius Valerius Publicola, who was given Quintus Fabius Ambustus as master of
                    the horse. They determined that not only the Roman tribes but the neighbouring
                    peoples also should offer supplications; and they appointed an order for them,
                    on what day each should make entreaty. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It is
                    handed down that during this year the people rendered severe judgments against
                    usurers, who had been brought to trial by the aediles. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The state —for no specially memorable reason —reverted to
                    an interregnum, which was followed —so that this might appear to have been
                    intended —by the election to both consulships of patricians, namely Marcus
                    Valerius Corvus, for the third time, and Aulus Cornelius Cossus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Wars of greater magnitude, in respect both of
                    the forces of our enemies and of the remoteness of their countries and the long
                    periods of time involved, now fall to be related. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For in that year the sword was drawn against the Samnites,
                    a people powerful in arms and in resources; and hard upon the Samnite war, which
                    was waged with varying success, came war with Pyrrhus, and after that with the
                    Carthaginians. How vast a series of events! How many times the extremity of
                    danger was incurred, in order that our empire might be exalted to its present
                    greatness, hardly to be maintained! <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now the
                    cause of the war between the Romans and the Samnites, who had been united in
                    friendship and alliance, was of external origin and not owing to themselves.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Samnites had unjustly attacked the
                    Sidicini, because they happened to be more powerful than they, and the Sidicini,
                    driven in their <pb n="p.457"/> need to fly for succour to a more wealthy
                    nation, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        345-343</note> had attached themselves to the Campanians. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Campanians had brought reputation rather than real
                    strength to the defence of their allies; enervated by luxury, they had
                    encountered a people made hardy by the use of arms, and being defeated in the
                    territory of the Sidicini, had then drawn down the full force of the war upon
                    themselves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the Samnites, disregarding the
                    Sidicini and attacking the Campanians —the very stronghold of their neighbours,
                    —from whom they would gain full as easy a victory and more plunder and renown,
                    had seized and with a strong force occupied Tifata — a range of hills looking
                    down on Capua —and thence had descended in battle-order into the plain that lies
                    between. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There a second battle had been
                    fought, and the Campanians, being worsted, had been shut up within their walls;
                    and having, after the loss of their choicest troops, no prospect of relief at
                    hand, had been driven to seek assistance of the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their ambassadors, on being introduced into
                    the senate, spoke substantially as follows: "The Campanian people has sent us to
                    you as ambassadors, Conscript Fathers, to solicit your lasting friendship and
                    present help. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Had we sought this amity when
                    our affairs were prosperous, though it had been begun more quickly, yet had it
                    been contracted with a weaker bond; for in that case, as those who remembered
                    that they had joined with you in friendship on an equal footing, though perhaps
                    as much your friends as now, we should have been less subject and beholden to
                    you; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> as it is, attached to you by your
                    compassion <pb n="p.459"/> and defended in our time of trouble by your aid,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 345-343</note> we
                    must lovingly remember the benefit also, lest we appear as ingrates and
                    undeserving of any help, divine or human. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor
                    do I think, in sober truth, that the circumstance of the Samnites having become
                    your allies and friends before ourselves should make against our being received
                    into your friendship, though it entitle them to an advantage over us in respect
                    of priority and rank; and indeed there was no stipulation in your treaty with
                    the Samnites that you should make no further treaties. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "It has ever been with you a sufficiently just
                    cause for friendship that he who sought you desired to be friends with you.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> We Campanians, though our present plight
                    will not suffer us to boast, are inferior neither in the splendour of our city,
                    nor yet in the fertility of our soil, to any people but yourselves; and in
                    associating ourselves with you we bring, as I think, no small accession to your
                    prosperity. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As often as the Aequi and the
                    Volsci —perpetual enemies of this city —shall stir abroad, we shall be upon
                    their backs, and what you will have done first for our preservation, that we
                    will ever do for your empire and your glory. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    When once you have subdued these nations that lie between our boundaries and
                    your own —a thing which your valour and good fortune guarantee will speedily
                    come to pass —your rule will extend unbroken all the way to our frontier.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Grievous and pitiful is the confession
                    that our misfortune obliges us to make: to that pass, Conscript Fathers, are we
                    Campanians come that we must be the chattels either of our friends or of our
                    enemies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Defend us, and we are yours; desert
                    us, and the Samnites will possess us. Consider <pb n="p.461"/> therefore whether
                    it be your preference that Capua and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> all Campania augment Rome's power, or that
                    of Samnium. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "It is meet that your compassion, Romans, and
                    your succour should be open to all mankind, but especially to those who in
                    endeavouring beyond their strength to grant these blessings to the prayers of
                    others, have come themselves to require them most of all. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> And yet we fought but ostensibly for the Sidicini, in
                    reality for ourselves, since we saw that a people on our borders was being
                    cruelly despoiled by the brigand Samnites, and that, once that conflagration had
                    consumed the Sidicini, it would spread to us. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Nor at this very moment are the Samnites come to attack us out of resentment for
                    any injury received, but rejoicing rather that a pretext has been afforded them.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Otherwise, if this were the satisfaction
                    of revenge and not an opportunity to appease their greed, was it not enough that
                    first in the territory of Sidicinum, and again in Campania itself, they made
                    slaughter of our legions? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> What wrath is this,
                    that is so implacable that the blood two armies have poured out cannot appease
                    it? Add to this the devastation of our lands and the booty they have driven off,
                    both men and cattle; add the burning and destruction of our farm-houses and the
                    general havoc fire and sword have wrought. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Could not all this placate their wrath? Nay, but their greed must be appeased.
                    It is this that hurries them to the siege of Capua; they must needs either
                    destroy the fairest of cities, or themselves become its masters. <milestone
                        n="17" unit="section"/> But do you, Romans, sooner gain it by your
                    generosity than suffer them to have it by their malice. I am not speaking before
                    a people that <pb n="p.463"/> refuses righteous wars; still, if you make but a
                    show <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. c. 345-343</note>
                    of helping us, you will have, I think, no need of going to war. <milestone
                        n="18" unit="section"/> As far as to ourselves does the scorn of the
                    Samnites reach, it mounts not higher; accordingly the shadow of your help is
                    able, Romans, to protect us, and whatever thereafter we shall have, whatever we
                    ourselves shall be, we shall consider wholly yours. <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/> For you shall be ploughed the Campanian plain, for you
                    shall the city of Capua be crowded; you shall be to us as founders, parents, and
                    immortal gods; you shall have no colony that surpasses us in obedience and
                    loyalty. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Grant the favour of your countenance, Conscript Fathers, and of your
                        unconquered might, to the Campanians, and bid them hope that Capua will be
                        saved. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> With what thronging crowds of
                        every sort were we accompanied, think you, at our setting out? How did we
                        leave on every hand prayers and tears! <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> In
                        what suspense are now the senate and the people of Campania, our wives and
                        our children! Well I know that all the people are standing at the gates,
                        their eyes fixed on the northern road. What message, Conscript Fathers, do
                        you hid us carry back to their perplexed and troubled spirits? <milestone
                            n="23" unit="section"/> One answer would bring salvation, victory,
                        light, and liberty; the other —I shrink from the ominous prediction! Do you
                        therefore deliberate regarding us, as regarding those who shall either be
                        your allies and friends, or else have no being anywhere. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ambassadors were then made to withdraw
                    while the senate considered their request. It was evident to many that the
                    largest and wealthiest city of Italy, with a very fertile territory near the <pb
                        n="p.465"/> sea, would in times of scarcity be a store-house for <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> the
                    Roman People. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Yet this great advantage was of
                    less moment with them than their honour, and the consul, being so instructed by
                    the senate, returned the following answer to the ambassadors: <quote> Men of
                        Campania, the senate holds you worthy of assistance; but on such terms only
                        can we become your friends as shall not violate an older friendship and
                        alliance. The Samnites and we are united by a covenant; we must therefore
                        refuse to make war in your behalf upon the Samnites, for this would be to
                        wrong first gods, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> the gods who were witnesses and guardians
                            of the treaty. </note> and then men; we will, however, dispatch envoys,
                        as is right and just, to entreat our allies and friends to do you no
                        violence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To this the leader of the delegation answered
                    —in accordance with instructions they had brought with them: — <quote> Since you
                        decline to use a righteous violence to protect from violence and injustice
                        what belongs to us, you will at least defend your own; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> to your sovereignty, therefore, Conscript Fathers, and
                        to the sovereignty of the Roman People, we surrender the people of Campania
                        and the city of Capua, with our lands, the shrines of our gods, and all
                        things else, whether sacred or profane; whatever we endure henceforth, we
                        shall endure as your surrendered subjects. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When these words had been pronounced, they all
                    stretched forth their hands in supplication to the consul, and weeping bitterly,
                    threw themselves face downwards on the floor of the entrance to the Curia.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Fathers were profoundly moved by the
                    vicissitudes of human fortune, considering how that great and opulent people,
                    famed for its luxury and pride, of whom a little while before its neighbours <pb
                        n="p.467"/> had sought assistance, was become so broken in <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 345-343</note> spirit
                    as to yield itself up with all its possessions to the dominion of another.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They now held it to be a point of honour
                    not to betray those who were become their subjects; neither did they think that
                    the Samnite people would deal justly, if they attacked a country and a city,
                    which, by surrendering, had become the property of the Roman People. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The senate accordingly voted to dispatch ambassadors
                    to the Samnites, without loss of time. Their instructions were to inform the
                    Samnites what the Campanians had asked, how the senate, mindful of the
                    friendship of the Samnites, had replied to them, and lastly how they had
                    surrendered; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> they were then to request that
                    the Samnites, out of regard for the friendship and alliance of the Romans, would
                    spare their subjects, and make no hostile incursion into a territory which
                    belonged now to the Roman People; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> if soft
                    words proved ineffectual, they were to warn the Samnites, in the name of the
                    Roman People and the senate, not to meddle with the city of Capua or the
                    Campanian domain. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But the Samnites, when
                    these things were represented to them in their council <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Samnites were a loose federation comprising the
                        following tribes: the Hirpini, the Caudini, the Pentri, the Caraceni, and
                        perhaps the Frentani (Weissenborn). </note> by the envoys, behaved so
                    insolently as not only to declare that they meant to carry on the war, but their
                    magistrates stepping out of the senate-house —while the envoys stood by
                    —summoned <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> the commanders of their cohorts,
                    and with a loud voice gave them orders to proceed at once to make a raid upon
                    Campania. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of this embassy reached Rome,
                    the Fathers, putting aside all other business, sent fetials to demand redress,
                    and failing to obtain it, declared war after the customary fashion. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the fetials and their procedure in
                        declaring war, see I. xxiv. 4 and xxxii. 5, with notes. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They <pb n="p.469"/> then voted that the
                    people be asked to ratify this <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 345-343</note> action at the earliest possible moment; and
                    being commanded so to do, both consuls took the field; and Valerius marching
                    into Campallia and Cornelius into Samnium, the one encamped at the foot of Mount
                    Gaurus, the other near Saticula. It was Valerius whom the Samnite levies
                    encountered first —for that was the direction which they expected the invasion
                    to take. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Campanians moreover had incurred
                    their sharp resentment, having been so ready now to render aid against them, now
                    to invoke it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But when they beheld the Roman
                    camp, they began, every man for himself, to call loudly on their leaders for the
                    battle-signal, affirming that the Romans would have no better fortune in helping
                    the Campanians than these had experienced in helping the Sidicini. </p>
                <p> Valerius, having delayed not many days for the purpose of testing the enemy in
                    small skirmishes, hung out the signal for a battle. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> But first he spoke a few words of encouragement to his
                    soldiers, bidding them have no fear of a strange war and a strange enemy.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With every advance of their arms from
                    Rome, he said, they came to nations that were more and more unwarlike.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They must not judge of the courage of the
                    Samnites by the defeats they had administered to the Sidicini and Campanians.
                    Whatever their respective qualities, it was inevitable that when they fought
                    together, one side should be vanquished. As for the Campanians, there was no
                    question they had been beaten rather by the enervation resulting from excessive
                    luxury and by their own effeminacy, than by the strength of their enemies.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Furthermore, what were the Samnites' two
                    successful wars in so many ages, as <pb n="p.471"/> against the many glorious
                    achievements of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        345-343</note> Roman People, who could count almost more triumphs than the
                    years since their City had been founded; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> who
                    had subjugated by their arms all the nations round about them, the Sabines,
                    Etruria, the Latins, the Hernici, the Aequi, the Volsci, and the Aurunci; who
                    after beating the Gauls time after time in battle, had ended by compelling them
                    to flee to the sea-board and their ships? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He
                    said that they ought, as they went into action, not only to rely every man on
                    his own courage and martial glory, but also to consider under whose command and
                    auspices they would have to fight; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> whether he
                    were one who only merited a hearing as a brilliant orator, warlike only in his
                    words, and ignorant of military operations, or one who knew himself how to
                    handle weapons, to advance before the standards, and to play his part in the
                    press and turmoil of a battle. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Soldiers,</quote> he cried, <quote> it is my deeds and not my words I
                        would have you follow, and look to me not only for instruction but for
                        example. Not with factions, nor with the intrigues common amongst the
                        nobles, but with this right hand, have I won for myself three consulships
                        and the highest praise. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Time was when it
                        might have been said: Ah, but you were a patrician and sprung from the
                        liberators of your country, and your family held the consulship in the very
                        year that saw the institution of that office.' <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> But now the consulship lies open on equal terms to us,
                        the nobles, and to you plebeians, nor is it any longer a reward of birth,
                        but of merit. Have regard, therefore, soldiers, in every instance, to great
                        honours. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Though you men have given me,
                        with Heaven's sanction, my surname of Corvinus, <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> This, the later form of the name, is found here and
                            in chap. xl. § 3, though in other places Livy gives the earlier form,
                            Corvus. </note> I have <pb n="p.473"/> not forgot the ancient surname of
                        our family —the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                            345-343</note>
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Publicolae: <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified">
                            <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi>
                            <quote>Friends of the People.</quote> See II. viii. 1. </note> at home
                        and in the field, as a private citizen, in little magistracies and in great
                        ones, as consul no less than as tribune, and with the same undeviating
                        course through all my successive consulships, have I cherished, and cherish
                        still, the Roman plebs. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Now, with
                        Heaven's good help, to the work we have in hand! Seek with me a novel
                        triumph never yet won from the Samnites! </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was never a commander who more endeared
                    himself to his men by cheerfully sharing all their duties with the meanest of
                    the soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At the military sports, too, in
                    which those of a like age contend with one another in strength and swiftness, he
                    was easy-going and good-natured; he would win or lose without changing
                    countenance, nor did he scorn to match himself with anyone who challenged him;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> in his acts his kindness was suited to the
                    circumstances, in his speech he had regard to the liberty of others no less than
                    to his own dignity; finally —and nothing can be more popular than this —he
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> was the same in office that he had been
                    while a candidate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was therefore with
                    incredible eagerness that the whole army, after listening to the general's
                    speech, marched out of camp. </p>
                <p> The battle began, if ever battle did, with like hopes on both sides and equal
                    strength, and a self-confidence which yet was not mixed with contempt for the
                    enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Samnites were' emboldened by their
                    recent exploits and by their double victory of a few days before, the Romans on
                    their part by the glories of four centuries and a victorious career that dated
                    from the founding of <pb n="p.475"/> the City; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    each side nevertheless experienced some <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> anxiety at meeting an
                    untried foe. The engagement testified how resolute they were, for they so fought
                    that for some time neither battle-line gave ground. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then the consul, thinking that he must inspire his enemies
                    with fear, since he could not drive them back by force, attempted by sending in
                    the cavalry to 'throw their front ranks into disorder. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But when he saw that nothing came of the confused fighting
                    of the squadrons, as they tried to manœuvre in a narrow space, and that they
                    could not break the enemy's line, he rode back: to the front ranks of his
                    legions, and, dismounting from his horse, exclaimed, <quote> Soldiers, it is for
                        us, the infantry, to accomplish yonder task! <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Come, as you shall see me making a path for myself with
                        my sword wherever I advance against the enemy's line, so do you every man
                        strike down whom you encounter; all that array where now uplifted spears are
                        glancing you shall see laid open with great carnage. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No sooner had he said these words, than the
                    horsemen, by the consul's order, drew off towards the wings and left the legions
                    room to attack the centre. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consul was the
                    very foremost in the charge, and slew the man he chanced to meet with. Kindled
                    by this sight, the Romans on the right and on the left pushed forward, every man
                    of them, and fought a memorable combat; the Samnites stood manfully at bay, but
                    they took more strokes than they delivered. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The battle had now lasted a considerable
                    time; there was dreadful slaughter about the standards of the Samnites, but as
                    yet no retreating anywhere, so determined were they to be overcome by naught but
                    death. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> And so the Romans, who saw that their
                        <pb n="p.477"/> strength was fast ebbing away in weariness and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 345-343</note> that
                    little daylight yet remained, were filled with rage, and hurled themselves
                    against the enemy. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Then for the first time
                    were there signs of giving way and the beginning of a rout; then were the
                    Samnites captured or slain; nor would many have survived, if night had not ended
                    what was now a victory rather than a battle. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans admitted that never had they fought with a more stubborn adversary;
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> and the Samnites, on being asked what it
                    was that first had turned them, resolute as they were, to flight, replied that
                    it was the eyes of the Romans, which had seemed to blaze, and their frenzied
                    expression and infuriated looks; this it was more than anything else that had
                    caused their panic. And this panic stood confessed not alone in the outcome of
                    the fight but in the night-retreat that followed. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> On the morrow the Romans took possession of the deserted
                    camp, and thither the whole population of Capua streamed out to congratulate
                    them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But this rejoicing came near to being marred
                    by a great reverse in Samnium. For the consul Cornelius, marching from Saticula,
                    had unwarily led his army into a forest which was penetrated by a deep defile,
                    and was there beset on either hand by the enemy; <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> nor, until it was too late to withdraw with safety, did he perceive that they
                    were posted on the heights above him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> While
                    the Samnites were only holding back till he should send down the whole column
                    into the bottom of the valley, Publius Decius, a tribune of the soldiers, espied
                    a solitary hill, which rising above the pass, commanded the enemy's camp, and
                    though arduous <pb n="p.479"/> of access to an army encumbered with baggage, was
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 385-343</note>
                    not difficult for men in light marching order. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He accordingly said to the consul, who was much perturbed: <quote> Do you see,
                        Aulus Cornelius, that summit that rises above the enemy? <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It is the fortress of our hope and safety, if we are
                        prompt to seize it, since the Samnites have been so blind as to neglect it.
                        Give me no more than the first and second lines of a single legion; <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The legion was drawn up in three
                            lines; in the first were the <hi rend="italics">hastati,</hi> in the
                            second the <hi rend="italics">principes,</hi> and behind these the <hi
                                rend="italics">triarii.</hi>
                        </note> when with these I have mounted to the top, do you go forward
                        fearlessly and save yourself and the army; for the enemy, exposed to all our
                        missiles, will not be able to stir without bringing destruction on
                        themselves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As for us, thereafter the
                        fortune of the Roman People or our own manhood will extricate us. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Being commended by the consul and receiving
                    his detachment, he advanced under cover through the wood, nor did the enemy
                    perceive him till he had nearly reached the place which he wished to gain.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They were then all overcome with
                    astonishment and dread, and while they turned, every man of them, and gazed at
                    him, the consul was given time to withdraw his army to more favourable ground,
                    and Decius himself took his post on the top of the hill. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Samnites, turning their standards now this way and now
                    that, threw away both opportunities; they could not pursue the consul, except
                    through the same defile where a little before they -had held him at the mercy of
                    their javelins, nor could they charge up the hill which Decius had captured over
                    their heads. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But not only did their
                    resentment urge them rather against those who had snatched victory from their
                    grasp, but so also did the nearness of the place and the fewness of its <pb
                        n="p.481"/> defenders; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and first they
                    would be for surrounding <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B. C. 345-343</note> the hill with troops, so as to cut Decius off from the
                    consul, and next for leaving his road open, so that they might attack him when
                    he was got down into the valley. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Before they
                    had made up their minds, night overtook them. </p>
                <p> Decius at first had hopes of fighting from the higher ground, as they mounted
                    the hill; then he marvelled that they neither began to attack, nor, if they were
                    deterred from that design by the difficulty of the ground, attempted to shut him
                    in with trench and rampart. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then, calling the
                    centurions to him, he said: <quote> What want of military skill, what
                        slothfulness can that be? How did those people conquer the Sidicini and
                        Campanians? You see their standards moving now this way, now that, first
                        closing in together, then deploying, while no man falls to work, though we
                        might ere this have been fenced in with a palisade. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Then in truth should we be no better than they, were we
                        to tarry here longer than suits our interest. Come on then and follow me, so
                        that while there is yet a little light we may find out where they post their
                        guards, and where the way out from this place lies open. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Wrapped in a common soldier's cloak and
                    accompanied by his centurions, who were also dressed like privates, lest the
                    enemy should notice that the general was on his rounds, he investigated all
                    these matters. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next, having disposed the sentries, he
                    commanded that the word be passed to everybody, that on hearing the trumpet
                    sound for the second watch they should silently arm and present themselves
                    before him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they had assembled there <pb
                        n="p.483"/> without a word, as he had ordered, he thus began: <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note>
                    <quote> You must preserve this silence, soldiers, as you listen to me, omitting
                        all soldier-like acclaim. When I have finished explaining my plan, then
                        those of you who find it good will quietly pass over to the right; on
                        whichever side the majority shall be, we will abide by their decision.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hear now what I have in mind. The
                        enemy has not invested you here as men who ran away or were left behind
                        through laziness: it was by valour that you took the place, and by valour
                        you must escape from it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By coming hither
                        you saved a splendid army for the Roman People; save yourselves by breaking
                        out. You are worthy to have carried help, though few, to greater numbers,
                        and to have needed no man's help yourselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> You have an enemy to deal with who neglected yesterday through indolence
                        an opportunity of destroying our whole army; who failed to see the
                        importance of this hill by which he is commanded, until we had taken it;
                        who, though we were so few and his own thousands so many, neither kept us
                        from gaining the ascent, nor, when the place was ours and much daylight
                        still remained, surrounded us with entrenchments. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> An enemy whom you thus eluded while he was wide awake
                        and watching, you ought to baffle when he is overcome with sleep. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Indeed it is necessary that you do so, for our
                        situation is such that I am rather pointing out your necessity to you than
                        advocating a plan. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nor truly can it be a
                        debatable question whether you should stay or go away from here, since
                        Fortune has left you nothing but your arms and the spirit to employ them,
                        and we must die of hunger and thirst, if we dread the <pb n="p.485"/>
                        sword's point more than it is fitting men and Romans <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 345-343</note> should. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> Our one way of safety, then, is to break through
                        and get away. We must do this either in the day-time or at night. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> But this, look you, is a question that is even
                        less in doubt, for if we should wait for dawn, what hope is there that the
                        enemy would not hem us in with a continuous trench and rampart, who has now,
                        as you see, encompassed the hill on every hand with the bodies of his men
                        lying below us. And yet, if night is favourable for our sally, as it is,
                        this is surely the fittest hour of the night. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> You have come together on the signal of the second
                        watch, when sleep lies heaviest on mortals;: you will make your way among
                        drowsy forms, either eluding them unsuspected in your silence, or ready, if
                        they should perceive you, to affright them with a sudden shout. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> Do but follow me, whom you have followed
                        hitherto; I will follow that same Fortune that has led us hither. Now then
                        let those who approve my plan step over-to the right. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They all crossed over. Decius then made his
                    way through the spaces left unguarded, and they followed him. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They had already got half way through the camp, when a
                    soldier in stepping over the bodies of some sleeping sentries struck his shield
                    and made a sound. A sentry was awakened by this, and having shaken his
                    neighbour, they stood up and began to rouse the rest, not knowing whether they
                    had to do with friends or foes, whether the party on the hill were escaping, or
                    the consul had captured the camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Decius,
                    seeing that they were discovered, gave the order to his men, and they set up
                    such a shout that the Samnites, <pb n="p.487"/> who had been stupefied with
                    sleep, were now in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        345-343</note> addition <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> breathless with
                    terror, which prevented them from either arming promptly or making a stand
                    against the Romans or pursuing them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During
                    the fright and confusion amongst the Samnites, the Romans cut down such guards
                    as they came across, and proceeded towards the consul's camp. </p>
                <p> It wanted yet some time till daylight, and they now appeared to be in safety,
                    when Decius said, <quote> All honour to your courage, Roman soldiers! <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Your expedition and return shall be renowned
                        through all the ages. But the light of day is needed to set off such
                        gallantry, nor do you merit that your glorious return to camp should be
                        accomplished in silence and under cover of night. Let us wait here quietly
                        until the dawn. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They did as he sail. With the first rays of
                    light they sent forward a courier to the consul, and the camp was woke with loud
                    rejoicings. When word was sent round that those were returning safe and sound,
                    who in behalf of the general safety, had exposed their bodies to no uncertain
                    peril, they all poured out to meet them, and, each for himself, praised and
                    congratulated them, calling them their saviours, one and all. To the gods they
                    offered praise and thanks, and Decius they extolled to the skies. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Now followed a triumph for Decius in the camp, as he
                    marched through the midst with his battalion under arms. All eyes were directed
                    towards him, and paid the tribune equal homage with the consul. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When they reached headquarters, the consul bade the trumpet
                    sound an assembly, and fell to lauding Decius, as he deserved. But Decius,
                    interrupting him, induced him to defer his speech; <pb n="p.489"/> then, urging
                    that all other considerations should <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 345-343</note> be postponed whilst they had such an
                    opportunity at hand, he persuaded him to attack the enemy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> They were now, he said, bewildered by the night alarm and
                    dispersed about the: hill in separate detachments, and he doubted not that a
                    party would have been sent out after him and would be wandering through the
                    forest. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The troops were commanded to arm, and
                    marching out of camp, were led by a more open route —for, thanks to their
                    scouts, the forest was now better known to them —in the direction of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These they caught quite off their guard
                    by a surprise attack, for the Samnite soldiers were scattered far and wide, and
                    most of them were without their weapons, Unable either to assemble or to arm or
                    to regain their works, they were first driven headlong into their camp, and then
                    the outposts were routed and the camp itself was taken. The shouting was heard
                    all round the hill and sent the detachments flying from their several stations.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Thus a great part of the Samnites fled
                    without coming into contact with the enemy. Those whom panic had driven within
                    the? enclosure —to the number of some thirty thousand —were all put to the
                    sword, and the camp was spoiled. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The battle having sped thus, the consul called
                    an assembly, and pronounced a panegyric upon Decius, in which he rehearsed, in
                    addition to his former services, the fresh glories which his bravery had
                    achieved. Besides other military gifts, he bestowed on him a golden chaplet and
                    a hundred oxen, and one choice white one, fat, and with gilded horns. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The soldiers who had been on the <pb n="p.491"/> hill
                    with him were rewarded with a double: ration <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> in perpetuity, and for
                    the present an ox apiece and two tunics. Following the consul's award, the
                    legions, accompanying the gift with their cheers, placed on Decius's head a
                    wreath of grass, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This decoration was
                        next in importance to the <hi rend="italics">corona aurea</hi> or <hi
                            rend="italics">triumphalis.</hi> It was made of green grass plucked from
                        the place which had been beleaguered. </note> to signify his rescuing them
                    from a siege; and his own detachment crowned him with a second wreath,
                    indicative of the same honour. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Adorned with
                    these insignia, he sacrificed the choice ox to Mars, and presented the hundred
                    others to the soldiers who had served with him on the expedition. To these same
                    soldiers the legions contributed a pound of spelt and a pint of wine for each
                    man. All these awards were carried out amid the greatest cheerfulness, the
                    shouts of the soldiers testifying to the general approval. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A third engagement was fought at Suessula, for
                    the Samnites, after the rout inflicted on them by Marcus Valerius, had called
                    out all the men they had of military age, determined to try their fortune in a
                    final encounter. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From Suessula the alarming
                    news was carried to Capua, whence gallopers were dispatched to Valerius the
                    consul, to implore assistance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The troops were
                    immediately set in motion, and leaving behind the baggage and a strong garrison
                    for the camp, made a rapid march, and being got within a short distance of the
                    enemy, encamped in a very small compass, for they had only their horses with
                    them and neither beasts of burden nor a crowd of camp-followers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Samnites, assuming that the battle would
                    not be delayed, formed up in line; then, as no one came out to meet them, they
                    advanced against the enemy's camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they
                    saw the soldiers on the rampart, and when the scouts whom they had <pb n="p.493"
                    /> dispatched to spy out the camp on every hand <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.345-343</note> reported how straitened
                    its dimensions were, inferring thence the paucity of their foes, the whole army
                    began to murmur that they ought to fill up the trenches, breach the rampart, and
                    burst into the enclosure; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and their rashness
                    would have brought the war to a conclusion, had not the commanders restrained
                    the ardour of their men. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But since their
                    numbers were a burden on the commissariat, and since, owing first to their
                    sitting down before Suessula and afterwards to the delay in fighting, they were
                    almost reduced to want for everything, they decided that while the enemy were
                    cowering within their works, they would send their soldiers over the
                    country-side to forage: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> meantime the Romans,
                    remaining inactive, would be reduced to destitution, for they had come in light
                    marching order, with only so much corn as they could carry, along with their
                    armour, on their shoulders. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Seeing the Samnites dispersed about the
                    fields, and their stations thinly manned, the consul addressed a few words of
                    encouragement to his soldiers and led them to the assault of the enemy's camp.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Having taken it at the first shout and
                    rush, and slain more men in their tents than at the gates and on the
                    breastworks, he ordered the captured standards to be collected in one spot.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then, leaving two legions to guard them
                    and defend the place, — with strict injunctions to refrain from spoiling until
                    he himself returned, —he marched out in serried column, and sending the cavalry
                    on before to surround the scattered Samnites, as with a cordon of hunters, and
                    so drive them in, he made a prodigious slaughter of them. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> For in their terror they were <pb n="p.495"/> unable to
                    agree either under what standard they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 345-343</note> should rally, or whether they should make
                    for their camp or direct their flight towards some more remote place; <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> and so great was their discomfiture and panic, that
                    the Romans brought in to the consul no less than forty thousand shields —though
                    not near so many men were slain —and of military standards, including those
                    which had been captured in the camp, no fewer than a hundred and seventy.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> The victors then returned to the enemy's
                    camp and there the plunder was all given to the soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fortunate outcome of this war not <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 342</note> only
                    impelled the Faliscans, with whom there was a truce, to ask the senate for a
                    treaty, but caused the Latins, whose armies were ready to take the field, to
                    transfer their attack from Rome to the Paeligni. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Nor was the fame of this success confined to Italy; even the Carthaginians
                    sent their envoys to Rome, with congratulations and the gift of a golden crown,
                    weighing five and twenty pounds, to be placed in the shrine of Jupiter on the
                    Capitol. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both consuls triumphed over the
                    Samnites, and after them came Decius, conspicuous in his decorations and so
                    renowned, that the soldiers in their rude jests named the tribune no less often
                    than the consuls. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The deputations of the Campanians and the
                    Suessulani were then heard, and a favourable reply was made to their petition
                    that a garrison should be dispatched, to remain through the winter with them and
                    protect them against inroads by the Samnites. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Capua was even then a far from wholesome place
                    for military discipline, and with its means for <pb n="p.497"/> gratifying every
                    pleasure proved so fascinating to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 342</note> soldiers that they forgot their native land, and
                    formed a project, while in winter quarters, for taking the city away from the
                    Campanians by the same wicked practice by which the Campanians had taken it from
                    its ancient inhabitants. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> the Etruscans, see IV. xxxvii. 2. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There would be a certain justice, they argued,
                    in turning their own example against them. Besides, why should the most fertile
                    land in Italy, and a city worthy of the land, belong to the Campanians, who were
                    incapable of defending either themselves or their possessions? Why, rather,
                    should it not belong to the conquering army, which had toiled and bled to drive
                    the Samnites out of it? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Was it fair that their
                    surrendered subjects should enjoy that fertile and agreeable tract, while they,
                    exhausted with campaigning, wrestled with the arid and noxious soil in the
                    neighbourhood of Rome, or endured the ruinous usury that had fastened on the
                    City and was increasing from one day to the next? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These schemes, discussed in secret cabals and
                    not yet communicated to all the troops, were discovered by the new consul, Gaius
                    Marcius Rutulus, to whom the lot had assigned Campania for his province, leaving
                    Quintus Servilius, his colleague, in charge at Rome. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And so having found out through his tribunes exactly what
                    had taken place, Rutulus, who was of ripe years and experience, —for the present
                    consulship was his fourth and he had been both dictator and censor —thought that
                    his best course would be to frustrate the men's impetuosity, by encouraging the
                    hope that they would be able at any time they chose to carry out their plan.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He accordingly set on foot a rumour that
                    the garrisons <pb n="p.499"/> would winter in the same towns in the following
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 342</note> year
                    also, —for they had been distributed among the cities of Campania and from Capua
                    their designs had spread to the entire army, —and the conspirators being thus
                    afforded time for breathing, the sedition subsided for the present. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul having led out his troops to the
                    summer encampment, and finding the Samnites quiet, resolved to purge the army of
                    its troublemakers by discharging them.: Of some of them he said that they had
                    served out their time; of others, that they were now too old or deficient in
                    sturdiness. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To some he granted furlough,
                    singling out individuals at first, but later dismissing certain cohorts, on the
                    ground that they had passed the winter far from their homes and their affairs.
                    Many, too, were sent off on some pretext of military employment, some one way,
                    some another. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All these the other consul and
                    the praetor detained at Rome, alleging a variety of reasons. And at first, not
                    suspecting a trick, they were far from sorry to visit their homes again.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Later on, when they saw that the first to
                    go failed to rejoin the colours, and that practically none were dismissed but
                    those who had wintered in Campania, and particularly such of these as had
                    encouraged the conspiracy, they marvelled at first, and presently began to
                    entertain very definite fears that their designs had come to light: <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> soon there would be investigations, soon informations
                    would be lodged, they would soon be punished in secret, one by one, and would be
                    made to feel the unrestrained and cruel despotism with which the consuls and the
                    senate governed them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Such were the fears that
                    were secretly put about by the soldiers <pb n="p.501"/> in the camp, for they
                    saw that the sinews of their <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 342</note> plot had been plucked out by the consul's
                    artifice. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> One cohort which was stationed not far from
                    Anxur <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Later called Tarracina.</note>
                    went into camp near Lautulae, in the narrow pass between the sea and the
                    mountains, where they could intercept those whom the consul continued to
                    dismiss, on one pretext or another, as has been said before. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> They were soon a very numerous body, and lacked no
                    essential element of an army except a general. And so, without order, and
                    pillaging as they went, they proceeded as far as the Alban country, and under
                    the ridge of Alba Longa encamped and threw up a rampart. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Having finished the work, they employed the remainder of
                    the day in wrangling over the choice of a general, for they had no great
                    confidence in anyone there present. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But whom
                    could they summon from Rome? What patrician or plebeian was there who would
                    wittingly expose himself to so great a danger, or to whom the cause of the army,
                    maddened by its wrongs, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As Livy has
                        mentioned no particular grievance, it is supposed that lie refers to the
                        oppressive usury. </note> could fitly be committed? <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> On the following day, while-they were debating the same
                    question, certain of their roving foragers reported having learned that Titus
                    Quinctius was living on a farm near Tusculum, with no thoughts of the City or
                    its honours. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This man, who belonged to a
                    noble family, had won great distinction in the wars, but a lameness in one of
                    his feet, resulting from a wound, had put an end to his campaigning, and had
                    determined him to take up his residence in the country, far from the Forum and
                    from politics. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> On hearing his name they
                    remembered the man at once, and bade send for him, invoking a blessing on this
                    step. But there being little prospect that <pb n="p.503"/> he would voluntarily
                    assist them, they resolved on <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 342</note> employing threats and violence. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Coming therefore to his farm-house in the silence of
                    the night, those who had been dispatched upon this errand caught Quinctius sound
                    asleep, and offering him no choice but authority and rank, or death, —with
                    which, when he held back, they threatened him, unless he would go along with
                    them —they carried him off to the camp. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Once
                    there they immediately hailed him General, and dazed as he was by the astounding
                    suddenness of it all, conferred on him the insignia of that office and bade him
                    lead them to the City. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Then, more on their
                    own impulse than by the counsel of their general, they pulled up their standards
                    and marched in warlike array as far as the eighth milestone, on what is now the
                    Appian Way; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> whence they would at once have
                    gone on to the City, had they not learned that an army was coming to oppose
                    them, under Marcus Valerius Corvus, who had been created dictator for that
                    purpose, with Lucius Aemilius Mamercus as master of the horse. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as they came within sight of one
                    another and recognized one another's arms and ensigns, all were at once reminded
                    of their fatherland, and their anger cooled. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Men were not yet so hardy in shedding the blood of countrymen; they knew no wars
                    but those with outside nations, and thought that frenzy could go no further than
                    secession from their people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And so on either
                    side both the leaders and their men began to seek for ways to meet and confer
                    together. For Quinctius was sated with war, even war in behalf of his country,
                    to say nothing of fighting against it; <pb n="p.505"/> and the affection of
                    Corvinus embraced all his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B. C. 342</note> fellow-citizens, particularly the soldiers, and above all
                    others, his own army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He now came forward to
                    parley, and being recognized, was instantly accorded a silent attention, in
                    which his opponents showed as great respect for him as did his followers. </p>
                <p>
                    <quote>Soldiers,</quote> he began, <quote> as I was setting forth from the City,
                        I adored your gods and mine, and humbly besought them of their goodness to
                        vouchsafe to me the glory of reconciling, not of conquering you. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> There have been wars in plenty, and will be
                        others, where men may win renown: in this crisis we must seek for peace.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The petition which I made to the
                        immortal gods, as I offered up my prayer, you are able of yourselves to
                        grant me, if you are willing to reflect that your camp is pitched not in
                        Samnium nor among the Volsci, but on Roman soil; that those hills which you
                        see are in your native land; that this army is made up of your
                        fellow-citizens; that I am your consul, under whose command and auspices you
                        twice last year defeated the Samnite legions, and twice stormed their camp.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I am Marcus Valerius Corvus, soldiers,
                        whose patrician blood has declared itself in kindnesses done you, not in
                        injuries; I have urged no insolent law against you, no cruel senatorial
                        resolution; in every position of authority I have been sterner to myself
                        than to you. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And in truth if any man's
                        family, if any man's own worth, if any man's dignities and honours have been
                        able to inspire pride in him, my birth was such, I had given such proof of
                        my capacity, and had achieved so young the highest magistracy, that I might
                        easily, on becoming consul at the age of three and twenty, <pb n="p.507"/>
                        have been overbearing even towards the nobles, not <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 342</note> merely towards the
                        plebs. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But what have you heard that I said
                        or did, when consul, more tyrannical than my words and deeds as tribune? In
                        that same spirit I administered two subsequent consulships; in that same
                        spirit shall this dictatorship with its dread power be administered; so that
                        I shall be no gentler to these my soldiers and the soldiers of my country,
                        than to you —I shudder to say the word, —our enemies. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> You shall therefore sooner draw sword on me than I on
                        you. It is on your side that the trumpets will sound, on your side that the
                        battle-cry will be raised and the attack begin, if fight we must. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Steel your hearts to do that which neither your
                        fathers nor yet your grandfathers could resolve upon —neither those who
                        seceded to the Sacred Mount, nor those who later encamped upon the Aventine.
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See II. xxxii and II.
                            1.</note>
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Wait until to each of you —as once to
                        Coriolanus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See II. xl.</note>
                        —your mothers and wives come forth from the City with dishevelled hair. On
                        that day the legions of the Volsci ceased fighting, because they had a Roman
                        leader: will you, an army of Romans, not relinquish this impious war?
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius, whatever be your
                        position over there —whether you have taken it voluntarily or against your
                        will, —if we must do battle, do you retire to the rear; you will even flee
                        with less discredit, turning your back upon your fellow-citizens, than you
                        will incur in fighting against your country. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Now, however, to make peace you will stand with honour
                        and credit amongst the foremost, and will be a salutary mediator at this
                        conference. Let your men ask what is reasonable, and receive it; yet must we
                        rather put up with what is not, than join together in impious strife.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.509"/>
                <p> Titus Quinctius turned with streaming eyes and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 342</note> addressed his people:
                        <quote> I, too, soldiers, if I am of any use to you, can better lead you to
                        peace than into war. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> For it was no
                        Volscian or Samnite that just spoke those words, but a Roman. It was your
                        consul, your general, soldiers. You have proved his auspices in your own
                        behalf; seek not to prove their worth against you. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> The senate had other leaders who would have made more
                        ruthless war on you; but they have chosen him who would deal most mercifully
                        with you, his men; one in whom, as in your general, you might place the most
                        utter confidence. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Peace is the goal
                        desired even by those who are able to conquer: what then ought our desire to
                        be? <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> Nay, let us abandon wrath and hope
                        —deceitful counsellors —and commit ourselves and all our cause to a man of
                        known fidelity! </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A shout of approval burst from every throat,
                    and Titus Quinctius, advancing in front of the standards, announced that the
                    soldiers would submit to the dictator's authority. He begged him to undertake
                    the cause of his wretched fellow-citizens, and having done so to forward it with
                    the same fidelity with which he had been used to deal with the interests of the
                    state. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For himself privately, he said, he
                    demanded no assurance, he had no wish to found a hope on aught but innocence.
                    But the soldiers must be assured, as in their fathers' day the plebs had been,
                    and, on a second occasion, the legions, that they should not be punished for
                    secession. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy said nothing of such
                        a stipulation at the time of the first reconciliation; for the circumstances
                        attending the second, see II. liv. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After praising Quinctius and bidding the rest
                    be of good cheer, the dictator galloped back to the City, and having secured the
                    authority of the <pb n="p.511"/> Fathers, got the people to enact a law, in the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 342</note>
                    Peteline Wood, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> vI. xx. 11 and note there. </note> that none of
                    the soldiers should be held to answer for the secession. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He begged them also, as citizens, to grant him the favour
                    that none would make the incident a matter of reproach to any, either in jest or
                    in earnest. There was also passed a military law, under penalty of devotion,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Whoever broke a <hi
                            rend="italics">lex sacrata</hi> was <hi rend="italics">ipso facto</hi>
                        consecrated to the lower gods, and became an outlaw. </note> to the effect
                    that the name of no one enrolled as a soldier might be struck off the list,
                    except with his own consent. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To this a
                    provision was added that no one might later command a century in the legion
                    where he had been a military tribune. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The law protected insolvent debtors, whose goods might not be seized so long
                        as they were in the service, and also assured the soldier of his rightful
                        share of such emoluments as the campaign might produce. With regard to the
                        addition, the commentators are doubtful what its object was; perhaps it was
                        felt as unfair to the rest that one who had enjoyed the (elective)
                        tribuneship should next year be appointed to the but slightly less desirable
                        post of first centurion. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This clause was demanded by the conspirators
                    on account of Publius Salonius, who in almost regular alternation was tribune of
                    the soldiers one year, and chief centurion —whom they now call <quote>centurion
                        of the first javelin</quote> —the next. The men were incensed at Salonius
                    because lie had always opposed their mutinous schemes, and had fled from
                    Lautulae that he might not share in them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And
                    so, when this one provision would have failed of enactment by the senate, out of
                    consideration for Salonius, he himself besought the Fathers not to think more
                    highly of his distinction than of harmony in the state, and induced them to pass
                    this also. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> An equally shameless demand was
                    made that the pay of the cavalry should be reduced —they served at that time for
                    treble pay —on the ground that they had opposed the conspiracy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In addition to these transactions, I find in
                    certain writers that Lucius Genucius, a tribune of the plebs, proposed to the
                    plebs that it should be <pb n="p.513"/> unlawful to lend at interest. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Also that it was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.342</note> provided in other
                    plebiscites that no one might hold the same office twice within ten years, nor
                    two offices in one year; and that it should be legal for both consuls to be
                    chosen from the plebs. If all these concessions were made to the commons, it is
                    evident that the revolt possessed no little strength. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Other annalists have recorded that Valerius was not made
                    dictator, but that the whole affair was managed through the consuls, and that it
                    was not before they came to Rome, but in Rome, that this great company of
                    conspirators was dismayed into arming; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    further, that the night attack was made, not on the farm of Titus Quinctius, but
                    on the town house of Gaius Manlius, and that it was he whom the conspirators
                    seized and made their leader. Thence they proceeded —according to this account
                    —to the fourth milestone, where they entrenched a camp. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Nor was it the leaders who suggested a reconciliation, but
                    suddenly, when the two armies had marched out in <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> battle array, salutations were exchanged, and the soldiers,
                    mingling together, began tearfully to clasp hands and embrace each other, so
                    that the consuls, seeing the men to be in no mood for fighting, had been
                    compelled to lay proposals before the senate for the re-establishment of
                    harmony. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thus in no single instance do the
                    ancient authorities agree, except that there was a sedition, and that it was
                    composed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The report of this sedition, in conjunction
                    with the dangerous war entered upon with the Samnites, caused several nations to
                    forsake their alliance with the Romans, and not only were the Latins unfaithful
                    to the treaty —as they had been for some time —but the Privernates even, in a
                    sudden raid, laid waste the neighbouring Roman colonies of Norba and Setia. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
