<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>First Oration Against Lucius Catilina</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts speech and section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
    <cRefPattern n="speech" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts speech</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="speech" delim="."/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--<encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>-->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-04-20" who="Lisa Cerrato">minor edits</change>
   <change when="2016-03-14" who="Zach Himes">Converted section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
<text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
    <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi013.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">
   
        <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="speech">
    <head>THE FIRST ORATION OF M. T. CICERO AGAINST LUCIUS CATILINA. DELIVERED IN THE SENATE.</head>
    
<div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">     
<head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>Lucius Catiline, a man of noble extraction, and who had already been praetor, had been a
      competitor of Cicero's for the consulship; the next year he again offered himself for the
      office, practicing such excessive and open bribery, that Cicero published a new law against
      it, with the additional penalty of ten years' exile; prohibiting likewise all shows of
      gladiators from being exhibited by a candidate within two years of the time of his suing for
      any magistracy, unless they were ordered by the will of a person deceased. Catiline, who knew
      this law to be aimed chiefly at him, formed a design to murder Cicero and some others of the
      chief men of the senate, on the day of election, which was fixed for the twentieth of October.
      But Cicero had information of his plans, and laid them before the senate, on which the
      election was deferred, that they might have time to deliberate on an affair of so much
      importance. The day following, when the senate met, he charged Catiline with having
      entertained this design, and Catiline's behaviour had been so violent, that the senate passed
      the decree to which they had occasionally recourse in times of imminent danger from treason or
      sedition, “Let the consuls take care that the republic suffers no harm.” This decree invested
      the consuls with absolute power, and suspended all the ordinary forms of law, till the danger
      was over. On this Cicero doubled his guards, introduced some additional troops into the city,
      and when the elections came on, he wore a breastplate under his robe for his protection; by
      which precaution he prevented Catiline from executing his design of murdering him and his
      competitors for the consulship, of whom Decius Junius Silanus and Lucius Licinius Murena were
      elected. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>Catiline was rendered desperate by this his second defeat, and resolved without further
      delay to attempt the execution of all his schemes. His greatest hopes lay in Sulla's veteran
      soldiers, whose cause he had always espoused. They were scattered about in the different
      districts and colonies of <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; but he had actually
      enlisted a considerable body of them in Etruria, and formed them into a little army under the
      command of Manlius, a centurion of considerable military experience, who was only waiting for
      his orders. He was joined in his conspiracy by several senators of profligate lives and
      desperate fortunes, of whom the chiefs were Publius Cornelius Lentulus, Caius Cethegus,
      Publius Autronius, Lucius Cassius Longinus, Marcus Porcius Lecca, Publius Sulla, Servilius
      Sulla, Quintus Curius, Lucius Vargunteius, Quintus Annius, and Lucius Bestia. These men
      resolved that a general insurrection should be raised throughout all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>; that Catiline should put himself at the head of the
      troops in Etruria; that <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> should be set on fire
      in many places at once and that a general massacre should be made of all the senate, and of
      all their enemies, of whom none were to be spared but the sons of Pompey, who were to be kept
      as hostages, and as a check upon their father, who was in command in the east. Lentulus was to
      be president of their councils, Cassius was to manage the firing of the city, and Cethegus the
      massacre. But, as the vigilance of Cicero was the greatest obstacle to their success, Catiline
      desired to see him slain before he left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>; and
      two knights, parties to the conspiracy, undertook to visit him early on pretence of business,
      and to kill him in his bed. The name of one of them was Caius Cornelius. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>Cicero, however, had information of all the designs of the conspirators, as by the intrigues
      of a woman called Fulvia, the mistress of Curius, he had gained him over, and received
      regularly from him an account of all their operations. He sent for some of the chief men of
      the city and informed them of the plot against himself; and even of the names of the knights
      who were to come to his house, and of the hour at which they were to come. When they did come
      they found the house carefully guarded, and all admission refused to them. He was enabled also
      to disappoint an attempt made by Catiline to seize on the town of <placeName key="perseus,Praeneste">Praeneste</placeName>, which was a very strong fortress, and would
      have been of great use to him. The meeting of the conspirators had taken place on the evening
      of the sixth of November. On the eighth Cicero summoned the senate to meet in the temple of
        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName> in the Capitol, a place which was only used
      for this purpose on occasions of great danger. (There had been previously several debates on
      the subject of Catiline's treasons and design of murdering Cicero, and a public reward had
      actually been offered to the first discoverer of the plot. But Catiline had nevertheless
      continued to dissemble; had offered to give security for his behaviour, and to deliver himself
      to the custody of any one whom the senate chose to name, even to that of Cicero himself.).
      Catiline had the boldness to attend this meeting, and all the senate, even his own most
      particular acquaintance, were so astonished at his impudence that none of them would salute
      him; the consular senators quitted that part of the house in which he sat, and left the bench
      empty; and Cicero himself was so provoked at his audacity, that, instead of entering on any
      formal business, he addressed himself directly to Catiline in the following invective.</p></div>
    
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>When, O Catiline, do you mean to cease abusing our patience? How long is that madness of
     yours still to mock us? When is there to be an end of that unbridled audacity of yours,
     swaggering about as it does now? Do not the nightly guards placed on the Palatine Hill—do not
     the watches posted throughout the city—does not the alarm of the people, and the union of all
     good men—does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in this most defensible
     place—do not the looks and countenances of this venerable body here present, have any effect
     upon you? Do you not feel that your plans are detected? Do you not see that your conspiracy is
     already arrested and rendered powerless by the knowledge which every one here possesses of it?
     What is there that you did last night, what the night before— where is it that you were—who was
     there that you summoned to meet you—what design was there which was adopted by you, with which
     you think that any one of us is unacquainted? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Shame on the age and on its principles! The senate is aware of these things; the consul sees
     them; and yet this man lives. Lives! aye, he comes even into the senate. He takes a part in the
     public deliberations; he is watching and marking down and checking off for slaughter every
     individual among us. And we, gallant men that we are, think that we are doing our duty to the
     republic if we keep out of the way of his frenzied attacks. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>You ought, O Catiline, long ago to have been led to execution by command of the consul. That
     destruction which you have been long plotting against us ought to have already fallen on your
     own head. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>What? Did not that most illustrious man, Publius Scipio, <note anchored="true">This was
      Scipio Nasica, who called on the consul Mucius Scaevola to do his duty and save the republic;
      but as he refused to put any one to death without a trial, Scipio called on all the citizens
      to follow him, and stormed the Capitol, which Gracchus had occupied with his party, and slew
      many of the partisans of Gracchus, and Gracchus himself.</note> the Pontifex Maximus, in his
     capacity of a private citizen, put to death Tiberius Gracchus, though but slightly undermining
     the constitution? And shall we, who are the consuls, tolerate Catiline, openly desirous to
     destroy the whole world with fire and slaughter? For I pass over older instances, such as how
     Caius Servilius Ahala with his own hand slew Spurius Maelius when plotting a revolution in the
     state. There was—there was once such virtue in this republic, that brave men would repress
     mischievous citizens with severer chastisement than the most bitter enemy. For we have a
     resolution <note anchored="true"> This resolution was couched in the form <foreign xml:lang="lat">Videant Consules nequid respublica detrimenti capiat</foreign>; and it exempted
      the consuls from all obligation to attend to the ordinary forms of law, and invested them with
      absolute power over the lives of all the citizens who were intriguing against the republic.
     </note> of the senate, a formidable and authoritative decree against you, O Catiline; the
     wisdom of the republic is not at fault, nor the dignity of this senatorial body. We, we
     alone,—I say it openly, —we, the consuls, are waiting in our duty. </p></div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>The senate once passed a decree that Lucius Opimius, the consul, should take care that the
     republic suffered no injury. Not one night elapsed. There was put to death, on some mere
     suspicion of disaffection, Caius Gracchus, a man whose family had borne the most unblemished
     reputation for many generations. There was slain Marcus Fulvius, a man of consular rank, and
     all his children. By a like decree of the senate the safety of the republic was entrusted to
     Caius Marius and Lucius Valerius, the consuls. Did not the vengeance of the republic, did not
     execution overtake Lucius Saturninus, a tribune of the people, and Caius Servilius, the
     praetor, without the delay of one single day? But we, for these twenty days have been allowing
     the edge of the senate's authority to grow blunt, as it were. For we are in possession of a
     similar decree of the senate, but we keep it locked up in its parchment—buried, I may say, in
     the sheath; and according to this decree you ought, O Catiline, to be put to death this
     instant. You live,—and you live, not to lay aside, but to persist in your audacity. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>I wish, O conscript fathers, to be merciful; I wish not to appear negligent amid such danger
     to the state; but I do now accuse myself of remissness and culpable inactivity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p> A camp is pitched in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, at
     the entrance of Etruria, in hostility to the republic; the number of the enemy increases every
     day; and yet the general of that camp, the leader of those enemies, we see within the
     walls—yes, and even in the senate, —planning every day some internal injury to the republic.
      <note anchored="true">This is the same incident that is the subject of the preceding oration
      in defence of Rabirius.</note> If, O Catiline, I should now order you to be arrested, to be
     put to death, I should, I suppose, have to fear lest all good men should say that I had acted
     tardily, rather than that any one should affirm that I acted cruelly. But yet this, which ought
     to have been done long since, I have good reason for not doing as yet; I will put you to death,
     then, when there shall be not one person possible to be found so wicked, so abandoned, so like
     yourself, as not to allow that it has been rightly done. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> As
     long as one person exists who can dare to defend you, yet shall live; but you shall live as you
     do now, surrounded by my many and trusty guards, so that you shall not be able to stir one
     finger against the republic: many eyes and ears shall still observe and watch you, as they have
     hitherto done, though you shall not perceive them. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>For what is there, O Catiline, that you can still expect, if night is not able to veil your
     nefarious meetings in darkness, and if private houses cannot conceal the voice of your
     conspiracy within their walls;—if everything is seen and displayed? Change your mind: trust me:
     forget the slaughter and conflagration you are meditating. You are hemmed in on all sides; all
     your plans are clearer than the day to us; let me remind you of them. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p> Do you recollect that on the 21st of October I said in the senate, that on a
     certain day, which was to be the 27th of October, C. Manlius, the satellite and servant of your
     audacity, would be in arms? Was I mistaken, Catiline, not only in so important, so atrocious,
     so incredible a fact, but, what is much more remarkable, in the very day? I said also in the
     senate that you had fixed the massacre of the nobles for the 28th of October, when many chief
     men of the senate had left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, not so much for the
     sake of saving themselves as of checking your designs. Can you deny that on that very day you
     were so hemmed in by my guards and my vigilance, that you were unable to stir one finger
     against the republic; when you said that you would be content with the flight of the rest, and
     the slaughter of us who remained? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> What? when you made sure
     that you would be able to seize <placeName key="perseus,Praeneste">Praeneste</placeName> on the
     first of November by a nocturnal attack, did you not find that that colony was fortified by my
     order, by my garrison, by my watchfulness and care? You do nothing, you plan nothing, you think
     of nothing which I not only do not hear, but which I do not see and know every particular of.
      <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Listen while I speak of the night before. You shall now see that I watch far more actively
     for the safety than you do for the destruction of the republic. I say that you came the night
     before (I will say nothing obscurely) into the Scythe-dealers' street, to the house of Marcus
     Lecca; that many of your accomplices in the same insanity and wickedness came here too. Do you
     dare to deny it? Why are silent? I will prove it if you do deny it; for I see here in the
     senate some men who were there with you. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>O ye immortal gods, where on earth are we? in what city are we living? what constitution is
     ours? There are here,—here in our body, O conscript fathers, in this the most holy and
     dignified assembly of the whole world, men who meditate my death, and the death of all of us,
     and the destruction of this city, and of the whole world. I, the consul see them; I ask them
     their opinion about the republic, and I do not yet attack, even by words, those who ought to be
     put to death by the sword. You were, then, O Catiline, at Lecca's that night; you divided
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> into sections; you settled where every one was
     to go; you fixed whom you were to leave at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, whom
     you were to take with you; you portioned out the divisions of the city for conflagration; you
     undertook that you yourself would at once leave the city, and said that there was then only
     this to delay you, that I was still alive. Two Roman knights were found to deliver you from
     this anxiety, and to promise that very night, before daybreak, to slay me in my bed. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> All this I knew almost before your meeting had broken up. I
     strengthened and fortified my house with a stronger guard; I refused admittance, when they
     came, to those whom you sent in the morning to salute me, and of whom I had foretold to many
     eminent men that they would come to me at that time. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>As, then, this is the case, O Catiline, continue as you have begun. Leave the city at last
     the gates are open; depart. That Manlian camp of yours has been waiting too long for you as its
     general. And lead forth with you all your friends, or at least as many as you can; purge the
     city of your presence; you will deliver me from a great fear, when there is a wall between me
     and you. Among us you can dwell no longer—I will not bear it, I will not permit it, I will not
     tolerate it.. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p> Great thanks are due to the immortal gods, and
     to this very Jupiter Stator, in whose temple we are, the most ancient protector of thus city,
     that we have already so often escaped so foul, so horrible, and so deadly an enemy to the
     republic. But the safety of the commonwealth must not be too often allowed to be risked on one
     man. As long as you, O Catiline, plotted against me while I was the consul elect, I defended
     myself not with a public guard, but by my own private diligence. When, in the next consular
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia</foreign>, you wished to slay me when I was actually consul,
     and your competitors also, in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName>, I
     checked your nefarious attempt by the assistance and resources of my own friends, without
     exciting any disturbance publicly. In short, as often as you attacked me, I by myself opposed
     you, and that, too, though I saw that my ruin was connected with great disaster to the
     republic. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> But now you are openly attacking the entire
     republic. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>You are summoning to destruction and devastation the temples of the immortal gods, the houses
     of the city, the lives of all the citizens; in short, all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. Wherefore, since I do not yet venture to do that which is the best thing,
     and which belongs to my office and to the discipline of our ancestors, I will do that which is
     more merciful if we regard its rigour, and more expedient for the state. For if I order you to
     be put to death, the rest of the conspirators will still remain in the republic; if as I have
     long been exhorting you, you depart, your companions, those worthless dregs of the republic,
     will be drawn off from the city too. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> What is the matter,
     Catiline? Do you hesitate to do that which I order you which you were already doing of your own
     accord? The consul orders an enemy to depart from the city. Do you ask me, Are you to go into
     banishment? I do not order it; but, if you consult me, I advise it. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>For what is there, O Catiline, that can now afford you any pleasure in this city? for there
     is no one in it, except that band of profligate conspirators of yours, who does not fear
     you,—no one who does not hate you. What brand of domestic baseness is not stamped upon your
     life? What disgraceful circumstance is wanting to your infamy in your private affairs? From
     what licentiousness have your eyes, from what atrocity have your hands, from what iniquity has
     your whole body ever abstained? Is there one youth, when you have once entangled him in the
     temptations of your corruption, to whom you have not held out a sword for audacious crime, or a
     torch for licentious wickedness? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>What? when lately by the death of your former wife you had made your house empty and ready
     for a new bridal, did you not even add another incredible wickedness to this wickedness? But I
     pass that over, and willingly allow it to be buried in silence, that so horrible a crime may
     not be seen to have existed in this city, and not to have been chastised. I pass over the ruin
     of your fortune, which you know is hanging over you against the ides of the very next month; I
     come to those things which relate not to the infamy of your private vices, not to your domestic
     difficulties and baseness, but to the welfare of the republic and to the lives and safety of us
     all. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Can the limit of this life, O Catiline, can the breath of
     this atmosphere be pleasant to you, when you know that there is not one man of those here
     present who is ignorant that you, on the last day of the year, when Lepidus and Tullus were
     consuls, stood in the assembly armed; that you had prepared your hand for the slaughter of the
     consuls and chief men of the state, and that no reason or fear of yours hindered your crime and
     madness, but the fortune of the republic? And I say no more of these things, for they are not
     unknown to every one. How often have you endeavoured to slay me, both as consul elect and as
     actual consul? how many shots of yours, so aimed that they seemed impossible to be escaped,
     have I avoided by some slight stooping aside, and some dodging, as it were, of my body? You
     attempt nothing, you execute nothing, you devise nothing that call be kept hid from me at the
     proper time; and yet you do not cease to attempt and to contrive. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> How often already has that dagger of yours been wrested from your hands? how
     often has it slipped through them by some chance, and dropped down? and yet you cannot any
     longer do without it; and to what sacred mysteries it is consecrated and devoted by you I know
     not, that you think it necessary to plunge it in the body of the consul. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But now, what is that life of yours that you are leading? For I will speak to you not so as
     to seem influenced by the hatred I ought to feel, but by pity, nothing of which is due to you.
     You came a little while ago into the senate in so numerous an assembly, who of so many friends
     and connections of yours saluted you? If this in the memory of man never happened to any one
     else, are you waiting for insults by word of mouth, when you are overwhelmed by the most
     irresistible condemnation of silence? Is it nothing that at your arrival all those seats were
     vacated? that all the men of consular rank, who had often been marked out by you for slaughter,
     the very moment you sat down, left that part of the benches bare and vacant? With what feelings
     do you think you ought to bear this? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p> On my honour, if my
     slaves feared me as all your fellow-citizens fear you, I should think I must leave my house. Do
     not you think you should leave the city? If I saw that I was even undeservedly so suspected and
     bated by my fellow-citizens, I would rather flee from their sight than be gazed at by the
     hostile eyes of every one. And do you, who, from the consciousness of your wickedness, know
     that the hatred of all men is just and has been long due to you, hesitate to avoid the sight
     and presence of those men whose minds and senses you offend? If your parents feared and hated
     you, and if you could by no means pacify them, you would, I think, depart somewhere out of
     their sight. Now, your country, which is the common parent of all of us, hates and fears you,
     and has no other opinion of you, than that you are meditating parricide in her case; and will
     you neither feel awe of her authority, nor deference for her judgment, nor fear of her power?</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And she, O Catiline, thus pleads with you, and after a
     manner silently speaks to you:—There has now for many years been no crime committed but by you;
     no atrocity has taken place without you; you alone unpunished and unquestioned have murdered
     the citizens, have harassed and plundered the allies; you alone have had power not only to
     neglect all laws and investigations, but to overthrow and break through them. Your former
     actions, though they ought not to have been borne, yet I did bear as well as I could; but now
     that I should be wholly occupied with fear of you alone, that at every sound I should dread
     Catiline, that no design should seem possible to be entertained against me which does not
     proceed from your wickedness, this is no longer endurable. Depart, then, and deliver me from
     this fear; that, if it be a just one, I may not be destroyed; if an imaginary one, that at
     least I may at last cease to fear. </p></div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>If, as I have said, your country were thus to address you, ought she not to obtain her
     request, even if she were not able to enforce it? What shall I say of your having given
     yourself into custody? what of your having said, for the sake of avoiding suspicion, that you
     were willing to dwell in the house of Marcus Lepidus? And when you were not received by him,
     you dared even to come to me, and begged me to keep you in my house; and when you had received
     answer from me that I could not possibly be safe in the same house with you, when I considered
     myself in great danger as long as we were in the same city, you came to Quintus Metellus, the
     praetor, and being rejected by him, you passed on to your associate, that most excellent man,
     Marcus Marcellus, who would be, I suppose you thought, most diligent in guarding you, most
     sagacious hi suspecting you, and most bold in punishing you; but how far can we think that man
     ought to be from bonds and imprisonment who has already judged himself deserving of being given
     into custody? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Since, then, this is the case, do you hesitate, O Catiline, if you cannot remain here with
     tranquillity, to depart to some distant laud, and to trust your life, saved from just and
     deserved punishment, to flight and solitude? Make a motion, say you, to the senate, (for that
     is what you demand) and if thus body votes that you ought to go into banishment, you say that
     you will obey. I will not make such a motion, it is contrary to my principles, and yet I will
     let you see what these men think of you. Be gone from the city, O Catiline, deliver the
     republic from fear; depart into banishment, if that is the word you are waiting for. What now,
     O Catiline? Do you not perceive, do you not see the silence of these men; they permit it, they
     say nothing; why wait you for the authority of their words when you see their wishes in their
     silence?</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But had I said the same to this excellent young man,
     Publius Sextius, or to that brave man, Marcus Marcellus, before this time the senate would
     deservedly have laid violent hands on me, consul though I be, in this very temple. But to you,
     Catiline, while they are quiet they approve, while they permit me to speak they vote, while
     they are silent they are loud and eloquent. And not they alone, whose authority forsooth is
     dear to you, though their lives are unimportant, but the Roman knights too, those most
     honourable and excellent men, and the other virtuous citizens who are now surrounding the
     senate, whose numbers you could see, whose desires you could know, and whose voices you a few
     minutes ago could hear,—yes, whose very hands and weapons I have for some time been scarcely
     able to keep off from you; but those, too, I will easily bring to attend you to the gates if
     you leave these places you have been long desiring to lay waste. </p></div><milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And yet, why am I speaking? that anything may change your purpose? that you may ever amend
     your life? that you may meditate flight or think of voluntary banishment? I wish the gods may
     give you such a mind; though I see, if alarmed at my words you bring your mind to go into
     banishment, what a storm of unpopularity hangs over me, if not at present, while the memory of
     your wickedness is fresh, at all events hereafter. But it is worthwhile to incur that, as long
     as that is but a private misfortune of my own, and is unconnected with the dangers of the
     republic. But we cannot expect that you should be concerned at your own vices, that you should
     fear the penalties of the laws, or that you should yield to the necessities of the republic,
     for you are not, O Catiline, one whom either shame can recall from infamy, or fear from danger,
     or reason from madness.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Wherefore, as I have said before, go forth, and if you to
     make me, your enemy as you call me, unpopular, go straight into banishment. I shall scarcely be
     able to endue all that will be said if you do so; I shall scarcely be able to support my load
     of unpopularity if you do go into banishment at the command of the consul; but if you wish
     serve my credit and reputation, go forth with your ill-omened band of profligates; betake
     yourself to Manilius, rouse up the abandoned citizens, separate yourself from the good ones,
     wage war against your country, exult in your impious banditti, so that you may not seem to have
     been driven out by me and gone to strangers, but to have gone invited to your own
      friends.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Though why should I invite you, by whom I know men have been already sent on to wait in arms
     for you at the forum Aurelium; who I know has fixed and agreed with Manlius upon a settled day;
     by whom I know that that silver eagle, which I trust will be ruinous and fatal to you and to
     all your friends, and to which there was set up in your house a shrine as it were of your
     crimes, has been already sent forward. Need I fear that you can long do without that which you
     used to worship when going out to do murder, and from whose altars you have often transferred
     your impious hand to the slaughter of citizens? </p></div><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You will go at last where your unbridled and mad desire has been long hurrying you. And this
     causes you no grief; but an incredible pleasure. Nature has formed you, desire has trained you,
     fortune has preserved you for this insanity. Not only did you never desire quiet, but you never
     even desired any war but a criminal one; you have collected a baud of profligates and worthless
     men, abandoned not only by all fortune but even by hope.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Then what happiness will you enjoy with what delight will
     you exult in what pleasure will you revel! when in so numerous a body of friends, you neither
     hear nor see one good man. All the toils you have gone through have always pointed to this sort
     of life; your lying on the ground not merely to lie in wait to gratify your unclean desires,
     but even to accomplish crimes; your vigilance, not only when plotting against the sleep of
     husbands, but also against the goods of your murdered victims, have all been preparations for
     this. Now you have an opportunity of displaying your splendid endurance of hunger, of cold, of
     want of everything; by which in a short time you will find yourself worn out. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p> All this I effected when I procured your rejection from the consulship, that
     you should be reduced to make attempts on your country as an exile, instead of being able to
     distress it as consul, and that that which had been wickedly undertaken by you should be called
     piracy rather than war. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Know that I may remove and avert, O conscript fathers, any in the least reasonable complaint
     from myself; listen, I beseech you, carefully to what I say, and lay it up in your inmost
     hearts and minds. In truth, if my country, which is far dearer to me than my life,—if all
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>,—if the whole republic were to address me,
     “Marcus Tullius, what are you doing? will you permit that man to depart whom you have
     ascertained to be an enemy? whom you see ready to become the general of the war? whom you know
     to be expected in the camp of the enemy as their chief; the author of all this wickedness, the
     head of the conspiracy, the instigator of the slaves and abandoned citizens, so that he shall
     seem not driven out of the city by you, but let loose by you against the city? Will you not
     order him to be thrown into prison, to be hurried off to execution, to be put to death with the
     most prompt severity? What hinders you? is it the customs of our ancestors? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p> But even private men have often in this republic slain mischievous
     citizens.—Is it the laws which have been passed about the punishment of Roman citizens? But in
     this city those who have rebelled against the republic have never had the rights of
     citizens.—Do you fear odium with posterity? You are showing fine gratitude to the Roman people
     which has raised you, a man known only by your own actions, of no ancestral renown, through all
     the degrees of honour at so early an age to the very highest office, if from fear of
     unpopularity or of any danger you neglect the safety of your fellow-citizens. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p> But if you have a fear of unpopularity, is that arising from the imputation
     of vigour and boldness, or that arising from that of inactivity and indecision most to be
     feared? When <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> is laid waste by war, when cities
     are attacked and houses in flames, do you not think that you will be then consumed by a perfect
     conflagration of hatred?” <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>To this holy address of the republic, and to the feelings of those men who entertain the same
     opinion, I will make this short answer:—If, O conscript fathers, I thought it best that
     Catiline should be punished with death, I would not have given the space of one hour to this
     gladiator to live in. If, forsooth, those excellent men and most illustrious cities not only
     did not pollute themselves, but even glorified themselves by the blood of Saturninus, and the
     Gracchi, and Flaccus, and many others of old time, surely I had no cause to fear lest for
     slaying this parricidal murderer of the citizens any unpopularity should accrue to me with
     posterity. And if it did threaten me to ever so great a degree, yet I have always been of the
     disposition to think unpopularity earned by virtue and glory, not unpopularity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Though there are some men in this body who either do not see what threatens, or dissemble
     what they do see; who have fed the hope of Catiline by mild sentiments, and have strengthened
     the rising conspiracy by not believing it; influenced by whose authority many, and they not
     wicked, but only ignorant, if I punished him would say that I had acted cruelly and
     tyranically. But I know that if he arrives at the camp of Manlius to which he is going, there
     will be no one so stupid as not to see that there has been a conspiracy; no one so hardened as
     not to confess it. But if this man alone were put to death, I know that this disease of the
     republic would be only checked for awhile, not eradicated for ever. But if he banishes himself;
     and takes with him all his friends, and collects at one point all the ruined men from every
     quarter, then not only will this full-grown plague of the republic be extinguished and
     eradicated, but also the root and seed of all future evils </p></div><milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>We have now for a long time, O conscript fathers, lived among these dangers and machinations
     of conspiracy; but somehow or other, the ripeness of all wickedness, and of this long-standing
     madness and audacity, has come to a head at the time of my consulship. But if this man alone is
     removed from this piratical crew, we may appear, perhaps, for a short time relieved from fear
     and anxiety, but the danger will settle down and lie hid in the veins and bowels of the
     republic. As it often happens that men afflicted with a severe disease, when they are tortured
     with heat and fever, if they drink cold water, seem at first to be relieved, but afterwards
     stiffer more and more severely; so this disease which is in the republic, if relieved by the
     punishment of this man, will only get worse and worse, as the rest will be still alive.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, O conscript fathers, let the worthless be gone,—let them separate themselves from
     the good,—let them collect in one place,—let them, as I have often said before, be separated
     from us by a wall; let them cease to plot against the consul in his own house,—to surround the
     tribunal of the city praetor,—to besiege the senate-house with swords,—to prepare brands and
     torches to burn the city; let it, in short, be written on the brow of every citizen, what are
     his sentiments about the republic. I promise you this, O conscript fathers, that there shall be
     so much diligence in us the consuls, much authority in you, so much virtue in the Roman
     knights, so much unanimity in all good men, that you shall see everything made plain and
     manifest by the departure of Catiline,—everything checked and punished. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>With these omens, O Catiline, be gone to your impious and nefarious war, to the great safety
     of the republic, to your own misfortune and injury, and to the destruction of those who have
     joined themselves to you in every wickedness and atrocity. Then do you, O Jupiter, who were
     consecrated by Romulus with the same auspices as this city, whom we rightly call the stay of
     this city and empire, repel this man and his companions from your altars and from the other
     temples,—from the houses and walls of the city,—from the lives and fortunes of all the
     citizens; and overwhelm all the enemies of good men, the foes of the republic, the robbers of
     Italy, men bound together by a treaty and infamous alliance of crimes, dead and alive, with
     eternal punishments.</p></div>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="speech">
    <head>THE SECOND ORATION OF M. T. CICERO AGAINST LUCIUS CATILINA. ADDRESSED TO THE PEOPLE. </head>
    
     <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
      <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
     <p>Catiline did not venture to make any reply to the former speech, but he begged the senate
      not to be too hasty in believing everything which was said to his prejudice by one who had
      always been his enemy, as Cicero had; and alleged his high birth, and the stake which he had
      in the prosperity of the commonwealth, as arguments to make it appear improbable that he
      should seek to injure it; and called Cicero a stranger, and a new inhabitant of <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. But the senate interrupted him with a general outcry,
      calling him traitor and parricide. Upon which, being rendered furious and desperate, he
      declared aloud what he had before said to Cato, that since he was circumvented and driven
      headlong by his enemies, he would quench the flame which his enemies were kindling around him
      in the common ruin. And so he rushed out of the temple. On his arrival at his own house he
      held a brief conference with the other conspirators, in which it was resolved that he should
      go at once to the camp of Manlius, and return as speedily as he could at the head of the army
      which was there awaiting him. Accordingly, that night he left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> with a small retinue, and made the best of his way towards Etruria. His
      friends gave out that he had gone into voluntary banishment at <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName>; and spread that report through the city the next morning, in order
      to excite odium against Cicero, as having driven him out without any trial or proof of his
      guilt. But Cicero was aware of his motions, and knew that he had previously sent a quantity of
      arms, and military ensigns, and especially a silver eagle which he had been used to keep in
      his own house with a superstitious reverence, because it had been used by the great Marius in
      his expedition against the Cimbri. However, he thought it desirable to counteract the story of
      his having gone into exile, and therefore summoned the people into the forum, and made them
      the following speech.</p></div>
    
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>At length, O Romans, we have dismissed from the city, or driven out, or, when he was
     departing of his own accord, we have pursued with words, Lucius Catiline, mad with audacity,
     breathing wickedness, impiously planning mischief to his country, threatening fire and sword to
     you and to this city. He is gone, he has departed, he has disappeared, he has rushed out. No
     injury will now be prepared against these walls within the walls themselves by that monster and
     prodigy of wickedness. And we have, without controversy, defeated him, the sole general of this
     domestic war. For now that dagger will no longer hover about our sides; we shall not be afraid
     in the campus, in the forum, in the senate-house,—yes, and within our own private walls, he was
     moved from his place when he was driven from the city. Now we shall openly carry on a regular
     war with an enemy without hindrance. Beyond all question we ruin the man; we have defeated him
     splendidly when we have driven him from secret treachery into open warfare. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p>But that he has not taken with him his sword red with blood as he
     intruded—that he has left us alive,—that we wrested the weapon from his hands,—that he has left
     the citizens safe and the city standing, what great and overwhelming grief must you think that
     this is to him. Now he lies prostrate, O Romans, and feels himself stricken down and abject,
     and often casts back his eyes towards this city, which he mourns over as snatched from his
     jaws, but which seems to me to rejoice at having vomited forth such a pest, and cast it out of
     doors. </p></div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But if there be any one of that disposition which all men should have, who yet blames me
     greatly for the very thing in which my speech exults and triumphs,—namely, that I did not
     arrest so capital mortal an enemy rather than let him go,—that is not my fault, O citizens, but
     the fault of the times. Lucius Catiline ought to have been visited with the severest
     punishment, and to have been put to death long since; and both the customs of our ancestors,
     and the rigour of my office, and the republic, demanded this of me; but how many, think you,
     were there who did not believe what I reported? how many who out of stupidity did not think so?
     how many who even defended him,—how many who, out of their own depravity, favoured him? If, in
     truth, I had thought that, if he were removed, all danger would he removed from you, I would
     long since have cut off Lucius Catiline, had it been at the risk, not only of my popularity,
     but even of my life.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But as I saw that, since the matter was not even then
     proved to all of you, if I had punished him with death, as he had deserved, I should be borne
     down by unpopularity, and so be unable to follow up his accomplices, I brought the business on
     to this point that you might be able to combat openly when you saw the enemy without disguise.
     But how exceedingly I think this enemy to be feared now that he is out of doors, you may see
     from this—that I am vexed even that be has gone from the city with but a small retinue. I wish
     he had taken with him all his forces. He has taken with him Tongillus, with whom he had been
     said to have a criminal intimacy, and Publicius, and Munatius, whose debts contracted in
     taverns could cause no great disquietude to the republic. He has left behind him others—you all
     know what men they are, how overwhelmed with debt, how powerful, how noble. </p></div><milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, with our Gallic legions, and with the levies which Quintus Metellus has raised in
     the Picenian and Gallic territory, and with these troops which are every day being got ready by
     us, I thoroughly despise that army composed of desperate old men, of clownish profligates, and
     uneducated spendthrifts; of those who have preferred to desert their bail rather than that
     army, and which will fall to pieces if I show them not the battle array of our army, but an
     edict of the praetor. I wish he had taken with him those soldiers of his, whom I see hovering
     about the forum, standing about the senate-house, even coming into the senate, who shine with
     ointment, who glitter in purple; and if they remain here, remember that that army is not so
     much to be feared by us as these men who have deserted the army. And they are the more to be
     feared, because they are aware that I know what they are thinking of and yet they are not
     influenced by it.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> I know to whom <placeName key="tgn,7010380">Apulia</placeName> has been allotted, who has Etruria, who the Picenian territory, who the
     Gallic district, who has begged for himself the office of spreading fire and sword by night
     through the city. They know that all the plans of the preceding night are brought to me. I laid
     them before the senate yesterday. Catiline himself was alarmed, and fled. Why do these men
     wait? Verily, they are greatly mistaken if they think that former lenity of mine will last
     forever. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>What I have been waiting for, that I have gained,—namely, that you should all see that a
     conspiracy has been openly formed against the republic; unless, indeed, there be any one who
     thinks that those who are like Catiline do not agree with Catiline. There is not any longer
     room for lenity; the business itself demands severity. One thing, even now, I will grant,—let
     them depart, let them be gone. Let them not suffer the unhappy Catiline to pine away for want
     of them. I will tell them the road. He went by the Aurelian road. If they make haste, they will
     catch him by the evening. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>O happy republic, if it can cast
     forth these dregs of the republic! Even now, when Catiline alone is got rid of; the republic
     seems to me relieved and refreshed; for what evil or wickedness can be devised or imagined
     which he did not conceive? What prisoner, what gladiator, what thief; what assassin, what
     parricide, what forger of wills, what cheat, what debauchee, what spendthrift, what adulterer,
     what abandoned woman, what corrupter of youth, what profligate, what scoundrel can be found in
     all Italy, who does not avow that he has been on terms of intimacy with Catiline? What murder
     has been committed for years without him? What nefarious act of infamy that has not been done
     by him? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>But in what other man were there ever so many allurements for youth as in him, who both
     indulged in infamous love for others, and encouraged their infamous affections for himself,
     promising to some enjoyment of their lust, to others the death of their parents, and not only
     instigating them to iniquity, but even assisting them in it. But now, how suddenly had he
     collected, not only out of the city, but even out of the country, a number of abandoned men? No
     one, not only at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, but in every corner of
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, was overwhelmed with debt whom he did not
     enlist in this incredible association of wickedness. </p></div><milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And, that you may understand the diversity of his pursuits and the variety of his designs,
     there was no one in any school of gladiators, at all inclined to audacity, who does not avow
     himself to be an intimate friend of Catiline,—no one on the stage, at all of a fickle and
     worthless disposition, who does not profess himself his companion. And he, trained in the
     practice of insult and wickedness, in enduring cold, and hunger, and thirst, and watching, was
     called a brave man by those fellows, while all the appliances of industry and instruments of
     virtue were devoted to lust and atrocity. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>But if his companions follow him,—if the infamous herd of desperate men depart from the city,
     O happy shall we be, fortunate will be the republic, illustrious will be the renown of my
     consulship. For theirs is no ordinary insolence,—no common and endurable audacity. They think
     of nothing but slaughter, conflagration, and rapine. They have dissipated their patrimonies,
     they have squandered their fortunes. Money has long failed them, and now credit begins to fail;
     but the same desires remain which they had in their time of abundance. But if in their drinking
     and gambling parties they were content with feasts and harlots, they would be in a hopeless
     state indeed; but yet they might be endured. But who can bear this,—that indolent men should
     plot against the bravest,—drunkards against the sober,—men asleep against men awake,—men lying
     at feasts, embracing abandoned women, languid with wine, crammed with food, crowned with
     chaplets, reeking with ointments, worn out with lust, belch out in their discourse the murder
     of all good men, and the conflagration of the city? 
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But I am confident that some fate is hanging over these men;
     and that the punishment long since due to their iniquity, and worthlessness, and wickedness,
     and lust, is either visibly at hand or at least rapidly approaching. And if my consulship shall
     have removed, since it cannot cure them, it will have added, not some brief span, but many ages
     of existence to the republic. For there is no nation for us to fear,—no king who can make war
     on the Roman people. All foreign affairs are tranquilized, both by land and sea, by the valour
     of one man. Domestic war alone remains. The only plots against us are within our own walls,—the
     danger is within,—the enemy is within. We must war with luxury, with madness, with wickedness.
     For this war, O citizens, I offer myself as the general. I take on myself the enmity of
     profligate men. What can be cured, I will cure, by whatever means it may be possible. What must
     be cut away, I will not suffer to spread, to the ruin of the republic. Let them depart, or let
     them stay quiet; or if they remain in the city and in the same disposition as at present, let
     them expect what they deserve. </p></div><milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But there are men, O Romans, who say that Catiline has been driven by me into banishment. But
     if I could do so by a word, I would drive out those also who say so. Forsooth, that timid, that
     excessively bashful man could not bear the voice of the consul; as soon as he was ordered to go
     into banishment, he obeyed, he was quiet. Yesterday, when I had been all but murdered at my own
     house, I convoked the senate in the temple of Jupiter Stator; I related the whole affair to the
     conscript fathers; and when Catiline came thither, what senator addressed him? who saluted him?
     who looked upon him not so much even as an abandoned citizen, as an implacable enemy? Nay the
     chiefs of that body left that part of the benches to which he came naked and empty. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> On this I, that violent consul, who drive citizens into
     exile by a word, asked of Catiline whether he had been at the nocturnal meeting at Marcus
     Lecca's, or not; when that most audacious man, convicted by his own conscience, was at first
     silent. I related all the other circumstances; I described what he had done that night, where
     he had been, what he had arranged for the next night, how the plan of the whole war had been
     laid down by him. When he hesitated, when he was convicted, I asked why he hesitated to go
     whither he had been long been preparing to go; when I knew that arms, that the axes, the
      <foreign xml:lang="lat">fasces</foreign>, and trumpets, and military standards, and that silver
     eagle to which he had made a shrine in his own house, had been sent on? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> Did I drive him into exile who I knew had already entered upon war? I suppose
     Manlius, that centurion who has pitched his camp in the Faesulan district, has proclaimed war
     against the Roman people in his own name; and that camp is not now waiting for Catiline as its
     general, and he, driven indeed into exile, will go to <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName>, as they say, and not to that camp. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>O the hard lot of those, not only of those who govern, but even of those who save the
     republic. Now, if Lucius Catiline, hemmed in and rendered powerless by my counsels, by my
     toils, by my dangers, should on a sudden become alarmed, should change his designs, should
     desert his friends, should abandon his design of making war, should change his path from this
     course of wickedness and war, and betake himself to flight and exile, he will not be said to
     have been deprived by me of the arms of his audacity, to have been astounded and terrified by
     my diligence, to have been driven from his hope and from his enterprise, but, uncondemned and
     innocent, to have been driven into banishment by the consul by threats and violence; and there
     will be some who will seek to have him thought not worthless but unfortunate, and be considered
     not a most active consul, but a most cruel tyrant. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> I am not
     unwilling, O Romans, to endure this storm of false and unjust unpopularity as long as the
     danger of this horrible and nefarious war is warded off from you. Let him be said to be
     banished by me as long as he goes into banishment; but, believe me, he will not go. I will
     never ask of the immortal gods, O Romans, for the sake of lightening my own unpopularity, for
     you to hear that Lucius Catiline is leading an army of enemies, and is hovering about in arms;
     but yet in three days you will hear it. And I much more fear that it will be objected to me
     some day or other, that I have let him escape, rather than that I have banished him. But when
     there are men who say he has been banished because he has gone away, what would these men say
     if he had been put to death? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Although those men who keep saying that Catiline is going to <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName> do not complain of this so much as they fear it; for there is not one
     of them so inclined to pity, as not to prefer that he should go to Manlius rather than to
      <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName>. But he, if he had never before planned
     what he is now doing, yet would rather be slain while living as a bandit, than live as an
     exile; but now, when nothing has happened to him contrary to his own wish and design,—except,
     indeed, that he has left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> while we are alive,—let
     us wish rather that he may go into exile than complain of it. </p></div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But why are we speaking so long about one enemy; and about that enemy who now avows that he
     is one; and whom I now do not fear, because, as I have always wished, a wall is between us; and
     are saying nothing about those who dissemble, who remain at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, who are among us? Whom, indeed, if it were by any means possible, I should
     be anxious not so much to chastise as to cure, and to make friendly to the republic; nor, if
     they will listen to me, do I quite know why that may not be. For I will tell you, O Romans, of
     what classes of men those forces are made up, and then, if I can, I will apply to each the
     medicine of my advice and persuasion.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> There is one class of them, who, with enormous debts, have
     still greater possessions, and who can by no means be detached from their affection to them. Of
     these men the appearance is most respectable, for they are wealthy, but their intention and
     their cause are most shameless. Will you be rich in lands, in houses, in money, in slaves, in
     all things, and yet hesitate to diminish your possessions to add to your credit? What are you
     expecting? War? What! in the devastation of all things, do you believe that your own
     possessions will be held sacred? do you expect an abolition of debts? They are mistaken who
     expect that from Catiline. There may be schedules made out, owing to my exertions, but they
     will be only catalogues of sale. Nor can those who have possessions be safe by any other means;
     and if they had been willing to adopt this plan earlier, and not, as is very foolish, to
     struggle on against usury with the profits of their farms, we should have them now richer and
     better citizens. But I think these men are the least of all to be dreaded, because they can
     either be persuaded to abandon their opinions, or if they cling to them, they seem to me more
     likely to form wishes against the republic than to bear arms against it. </p></div><milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is another class of them, who, although they are harassed by debt, yet are expecting
     supreme power; they wish to become masters. They think that when the republic is in confusion
     they may gain those honours which they despair of when it is in tranquillity. And they must, I
     think, be told the same as every one else,—to despair of obtaining what they are aiming at;
     that in the first place, I myself am watchful for, am present to, am providing for the
     republic. Besides that, there is a high spirit in the virtuous citizens, great unanimity, great
     numbers, and also a great body of troops. Above all that, the immortal gods will stand by and
     bring aid to this invincible nation, this most illustrious empire, this most beautiful city,
     against such wicked violence. And if they had already got that which they with the greatest
     madness wish for, do they think that in the ashes of the city and blood of the citizens, which
     in their wicked and infamous hearts they desire, they will become consuls and dictators and
     even kings? Do they not see that they are wishing for that which, if they were to obtain it,
     must be given up to some fugitive slave, or to some gladiator? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is a third class, already touched by age, but still vigorous from constant exercise; of
     which class is Manlius himself; whom Catiline is now succeeding. These are men of those
     colonies which Sulla established at <placeName key="perseus,Faesulae">Faesulae</placeName>,
     which I know to be composed, on the whole, of excellent citizens and brave men; but yet these
     are colonists, who, from becoming possessed of unexpected and sudden wealth, boast themselves
     extravagantly and insolently; these men, while they build like rich men, while they delight in
     farms, in litters, in vast families of slaves, in luxurious banquets, have incurred such great
     debts, that, if they would be saved, they must raise Sulla from the dead; and they have even
     excited some countrymen, poor and needy men, to entertain the same hopes of plunder as
     themselves. And all these men, O Romans, I place in the same class of robbers and banditti.
     But, I warn them, let them cease to be mad, and to think of proscriptions and dictatorships;
     for such a horror of these times is ingrained into the city, that not even men, but it seems to
     me that even the very cattle would refuse to bear them again. </p></div><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is a fourth class, various, promiscuous and turbulent; who indeed are now overwhelmed;
     who will never recover themselves; who, partly from indolence, partly from managing their
     affairs badly, partly from extravagance, are embarrassed by old debts; and worn out with bail
     bonds, and judgments, and seizures of their goods, are said to be betaking themselves in
     numbers to that camp both from the city and the country. These men I think not so much active
     soldiers as lazy insolvents; who, if they cannot stand at first, may fall, but fall so, that
     not only the city but even their nearest neighbours know nothing of it. For I do not understand
     why, if they cannot live with honour, they should wish to die shamefully; or wily they think
     they shall perish with less pain in a crowd, than if they perish by themselves. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is a fifth class, of parricides, assassins, in short of all infamous characters, whom I
     do not wish to recall from Catiline, and indeed they cannot be separated from him. Let them
     perish in their wicked war, since they are so numerous that a prison cannot contain them. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is a last class, last not only in number but in the sort of men and in their way of
     life; the especial body-guard of Catiline, of his levying; yes, the friends of his embraces and
     of his bosom; whom you see with carefully combed hair, glossy, beardless, or with well-trimmed
     beards; with tunics with sleeves, or reaching to the ankles; clothed with veils, not with
     robes; all the industry of whose life, all the labour of whose watchfulness, is expended in
     suppers lasting till daybreak. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>In these bands are all the gamblers, all the adulterers, all the unclean and shameless
     citizens. These boys, so witty and delicate, have learnt not only to love and to be loved, not
     only to sing and to dance, but also to brandish daggers and to administer poisons; and unless
     they are driven out, unless they die, even should Catiline die, I warn you that the school of
     Catiline would exist in the republic. But what do those wretches want? Are they going to take
     their wives with them to the camp? how can they do without them, especially in these nights?
     and how will they endure the <placeName key="tgn,7008531">Apennines</placeName>, and these
     frosts, and this snow? unless they think that they will bear the winter more easily because
     they have been in the habit of dancing naked at their feasts. O war much to be dreaded, when
     Catiline is going to have his bodyguard of prostitutes! </p></div><milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Array now, O Romans, against these splendid troops of Catiline, your guards and your armies;
     and first of all oppose to that worn-out and wounded gladiator your consuls and generals; then
     against that banished and enfeebled troop of ruined men lead out the flower and strength of all
      <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> instantly the cities of the colonies and
     municipalities will match the rustic mounds of Catiline; and I will not condescend to compare
     the rest of your troops and equipments and guards with the want and destitution of that
     highwayman. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> But if, omitting all these things in which we
     are rich and of which he is destitute,—the senate, the Roman knights, the people, the city, the
     treasury, the revenues, all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, all the provinces,
     foreign nations,—if I say, omitting all these things, we choose to compare the causes
     themselves which are opposed to one another, we may understand from that alone how thoroughly
     prostrate they are. For on the one side are fighting modesty, on the other wantonness; on the
     one chastity, on the other uncleanness; on the one honesty, on the other fraud; on the one
     piety, on the other wickedness; on the one consistency, on the other insanity; on the one
     honour, on the other baseness; on the one continence, on the other lust; in short, equity,
     temperance, fortitude, prudence, all the virtues contend against iniquity with luxury, against
     indolence, against rashness, against all the vices; lastly, abundance contends against
     destitution, good plans against baffled designs, wisdom against madness, well-founded hope
     against universal despair. In a contest and war of this sort, even if the zeal of men were to
     fail, will not the immortal gods compel such numerous and excessive vices to be defeated by
     these most eminent virtues? </p></div><milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And as this is the case, O Romans, as I have said before, defend your house with guards and
     vigilance. <pb n="302"/> I have taken care and made arrangements that there shall be sufficient
     protection for the city without distressing you and without any tumult. All the colonists and
     citizens of your municipal towns, being informed by me of this nocturnal sally of Catiline,
     will easily defend their cities and territories; the gladiators which he thought would be his
     most numerous and most trusty band, although they are better disposed than part of the
     patricians, will be held in cheek by our power. Quintus Metellus, whom I, making provision for
     this, sent on to the Gallic and Picenian territory, will either overwhelm the man, or will
     prevent all his motions and attempts; but with respect to the arrangement of all other matters,
     and maturing and acting on our plans, we shall consult the senate, which, as you are aware, is
     convened. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Now once more I wish those who have remained in the city, and who, contrary to the safety of
     the city and of all of you, have been left in the city by Catiline, although they are enemies,
     yet because they were born citizens, to be warned again and again by me. If my lenity has
     appeared to any one too remiss, it has been only waiting that that might break out which was
     lying hid. As to the future, I cannot now forget that this is my country, that I am the consul
     of these citizens; that I must either live with them, or die for them. There is no guard at the
     gate, no one plotting against their path; if any one wishes to go, he can provide for himself;
     but if any one stirs in the city, and if I detect not only any action, but any attempt or
     design against the country, he shall feel that there are in this city vigilant consuls, eminent
     magistrates, a brave senate, arms, and prisons; which our ancestors appointed as the avengers
     of nefarious and convicted crimes. </p></div><milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And all this shall be so done, O Romans, that affairs of the greatest importance shall be
     transacted with the least possible disturbance; the greatest dangers shall be avoided without
     any tumult; an internal civil war the most cruel and terrible in the memory of man, shall be
     put an end to by me alone in the robe of peace acting as general and commander-in-chief. And
     this I will so arrange, O Romans, that if it can be by any means managed, even the most
     worthless man shall not suffer the punishment of his crimes in this city. But if the violence
     of open audacity, if danger impending over the republic drives me of necessity from this
     merciful disposition, at all events I will manage this, which seems scarcely even to be hoped
     for in so great and so treacherous a war, that no good man shall fall, and that you may all be
     saved by the punishment of a few. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>And I promise you this, O Romans, relying neither on my own prudence, nor on human counsels,
     but on many and manifest intimations of the will of the immortal gods; under whose guidance I
     first entertained this hope and this opinion; who are now defending their temples and the
     houses of the city, not afar off, as they were used to, from a foreign and distant enemy, but
     here on the spot, by their own divinity and present help. And you, O Romans, ought to pray to
     and implore them to defend from the nefarious wickedness of abandoned citizens, now that all
     the forces of all enemies are defeated by land and sea, this city which they have ordained to
     be the most beautiful and flourishing of all cities.</p></div>
   </div>
     
   <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="speech">
    <head>THE THIRD ORATION OF M. T. CICERO AGAINST LUCIUS CATILINA. ADDRESSED TO THE PEOPLE.</head>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
     <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>While Cicero was addressing the preceding speech to the people, a debate was going on in the
      senate of which we have no account. In the meanwhile Catiline, after staying a few days on the
      road to raise the country as he passed along, where his agents had been previously busy among
      the people, proceeded to Manlius's army with the <foreign xml:lang="lat">fasces</foreign> and
      all the ensigns of military command displayed before him. Upon this news the senate
      immediately declared him and Manlius public enemies; they offered pardon to all his followers
      who should return to their duty by a certain day and ordered the consuls to make new levies,
      and that Antonius should follow Catiline with his army, and Cicero remain behind to protect
      the city.
     <milestone unit="para"/>In the meantime Lentulus, and the other conspirators who remained behind, were proceeding
      with their designs. And among other steps, they decided on endeavouring to tamper with some
      ambassadors from the Allobroges, <note anchored="true">The Allobroges occupied the districts
       of Dauphiné and Savoy.</note> who were at that moment within the city, as the Allobroges were
      supposed not to be very well affected to the Roman power. At first these ambassadors appear to
      have willingly given ear to their proposals; but after a while they began to consider the
      difficulty of the business proposed to them, and the danger which would ensue to their state
      if it failed after they had become implicated in it and accordingly they revealed the business
      to Quintus Fabius Sanga, the patron of their city, who communicated it to Cicero. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>Cicero desired the ambassadors to continue to listen to the proposals of the conspirators,
      till they had become fully acquainted with the extent of the plot, and till they were able to
      furnish him with full evidence against the actors in it; and by his suggestion they required
      the conspirators to furnish them with credentials to show to their countrymen. This was
      thought reasonable by Lentulus and his party, and they accordingly appointed a man named
      Vulturcius to accompany them, who was to introduce them to Catiline on their road, in order to
      confirm the agreement, and to exchange pledges with him, and Lentulus also furnished them with
      a letter to Catiline under his own hand and seal, though not signed. Cicero being privately
      informed of all these particulars, concerted with the ambassadors the time and manner of their
      leaving Rome by night, and had them arrested on the Mulvian bridge, about a mile from the
      city, with these letters and papers in their possession. This was all done, and they brought
      as prisoners to Cicero's house early in the morning. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>Cicero immediately summoned the senate and at the same time he sent for Lentulus, Cethegus,
      and others of the conspirators who were more especially implicated, such as Gabinius and
      Statilius, who all came immediately to his house, being ignorant of the discovery that had
      taken place. Being informed also that a quantity of arms had been provided by Cethegus for the
      purpose of the conspiracy, he orders Caius Sulpicius, one of the praetors, to search his
      house, and he did so, and found a great number of swords and daggers ready cleaned and fit for
      use. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>He then proceeds to meet the senate in the Temple of Concord, with the ambassadors and
      conspirators in custody. He relates the whole affair to them, and introduces Vulturcius to be
      examined before them. Cicero, by the order of the senate, promises him pardon and reward if he
      reveals what he knew. On which he confesses everything; tells them that he had letters from
      Lentulus to Catiline to urge him to avail himself of the assistance of the slaves, and to lead
      his army with all exposition against Rome in order, when the city had been set on fire, and
      the massacre commenced, that he might be able to intercept and destroy those who fled. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>Then the ambassadors were examined, who declared that they had received letters to the chief
      men of their nation from Lentulus, Cethegus, and Statilius; and that they, and Lucius Cassius
      also, begged them to send a body of cavalry into Italy, and that Lentulus assured them, from
      the Sibylline books, that he was the third Cornelius who was destined to reign at Rome. <note anchored="true">Cinna and Sulla had been the two former Cornelii.</note> The letters were
      produced and opened. On the sight of them the conspirators respectively acknowledged them to
      be theirs, and Lentulus was even so conscience-stricken that he confessed his whole crime. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>The senate passed a vote acknowledging the services of Cicero in the most ample terms, and
      voted that Lentulus should he deposed from his office of praetor, and, with all the other
      conspirators, committed to safe custody. Cicero, after the senate adjourned, proceeded to the
      forum and gave an account to the people of everything which had passed, both in regard to the
      steps that he had taken to detect the whole conspiracy, and to convict the conspirators and
      also of what had taken place in the senate, and of the votes and resolutions which that body
      had just passed. 
     <milestone unit="para"/>While the prisoners were before the senate he had copies of their examinations and
      confessions taken down, and dispersed through Italy and all the provinces. This happened on
      the third of December.</p></div>
    
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You see this day, O Romans, the republic, and all your lives, your goods, your fortunes, your
     wives and children, this home of most illustrious empire, thus most fortunate and beautiful
     city, by the great love of the immortal gods for you, by my labours and counsels and dangers,
     snatched from fire and sword, and almost from the very jaws of fate, and preserved and restored
     to you.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And if those days on which we are preserved are not less
     pleasant to us, or less illustrious, than those on which we are born, because the joy of being
     saved is certain, the good fortune of being born uncertain, and because we are born without
     feeling it, but we are preserved with great delight; yes; since we have, by our affection and
     by our good report, raised to the immortal gods that Romulus who built this city, he, too, who
     has preserved this city, built by him, and embellished as you see it, ought to be held in
     terror by you and your posterity; for we have extinguished flames which were almost laid under
     and placed around the temples and shrines, and houses and walls of the whole city; we have
     turned the edge of swords drawn against the republic, and have turned aside their points from
     your throats.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p> And since all this has been displayed in the
     senate, and made manifest, and detected by me, I will now explain it briefly, that you, O
     citizens, that are as yet ignorant of it, and are in suspense, may be able to see how great the
     danger was, how evident and by what means it was detected and arrested. First of all, since
     Catiline, a few days ago, burst out of the city, when he had left behind the companions of his
     wickedness, the active leaders of this infamous war, I have continually watched and taken care,
     O Romans, of the means by which we might be safe amid such great and such carefully concealed
     treachery. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Further, when I drove Catiline out of the city, (for I do not fear the unpopularity of this
     expression, when that is more to be feared that I should be blamed because he has departed
     alive,) but then when I wished him to be removed, I thought either that the rest of the band of
     conspirators would depart with him, or that they who remained would be weak and powerless
     without him. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And I, as I saw that those whom I knew to be inflamed with the greatest madness and
     wickedness were among us, and had remained at Rome, spent ail my nights and days in taking care
     to know and see what they were doing, and what they were contriving that, since what I said
     would, from the incredible enormity of the wickedness, make less impression on your ears, I
     might so detect the whole business that you might with all your hearts provide for your safety,
     when you saw the crime with your own eyes. Therefore, when I found that the ambassadors of the
     Allobroges had been tampered with by Publius Lentulus, for the sake of exciting a Transalpine
     war and commotion in Gaul, and that they, on their return to Gaul, had been sent with letters
     and messages to Catiline on the same road, and that Vulturcius had been added to them as a
     companion, and that he too had had letters given him for Catiline, I thought that an
     opportunity wits given me of contriving what was most difficult, and which I was always wishing
     the immortal gods might grant, that the whole business might be manifestly detected not by me
     alone, but by the senate also, and by you. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, yesterday I summoned Lucius Flaccus and C. Pomtinus, the praetors, brave men and
     well-affected to the republic. I explained to them the whole matter, and showed them what I
     wished to have done. But they, full of noble and worthy sentiments towards the republic,
     without hesitation, and without any delay, undertook the business, and when it was evening,
     went secretly to the Mulvian bridge, and there so distributed themselves in the nearest villas,
     that the Tiber and the bridge was between them. And they took to the same place, without any
     one having the least suspicion of it, many brave men, and I had sent many picked young men of
     the prefecture of Reate, whose assistance I constantly employ in the protection of the
     republic, armed with swords. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p> In the meantime, about the end
     of the third watch, when the ambassadors of the Allobroges, with a great retinue and Vulturcius
     with them, began to come upon the Mulvian bridge, an attack is made upon them; swords are drawn
     both by them and by our people; the matter was understood by the praetors alone, but was
     unknown to the rest. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Then, by the intervention of Pomtinus and Flaccus, the fight which had begun was put an end
     to; all the letters which were in the hands of the whole company are delivered to the praetors
     with time seals unbroken; the men themselves are arrested and brought to me at daybreak. And I
     immediately summoned that most worthless contriver of all this wickedness, Gabinius, as yet
     suspecting nothing; after him, P. Statilius is sent for, and after him Cethegus; but Lentulus
     was a long time in coming,—I suppose, because, contrary to his custom, he had been up a long
     time the night before, writing letters. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>But when those most noble and excellent men of the whole city, who, hearing of the matter,
     came in crowds to me in the morning, thought it best for me to open the letters before I
     related the matter to the senate, lest, if nothing were found in them, so great a disturbance
     might seem to have been caused to the state for nothing, I said I would never so act as shrink
     from referring matter of public danger to the public council. In truth if, O Romans, these
     things which had been reported to me had not been found in them, yet I did not think I ought,
     in such a crisis of the republic, to be afraid of the imputation of over-diligence. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> I quickly summoned a full senate, as you saw; and meantime, without any
     delay, by the advice of the Allobroges, I sent Caius Sulpicius the praetor, a brave man, to
     bring whatever arms he could find in the house of Cethegus, whence he did bring a great number
     of swords and daggers. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I introduced Vulturcius without the Gauls. By the command of the senate, I pledged him the
     public faith for his safety. I exhorted him fearlessly to tell all he knew. Then, when he had
     scarcely recovered himself from his great alarm, he said: that he had messages and letters for
     Catiline, from Publius Lentulus, to avail himself of the guard of the slaves, and to come
     towards the city with his army as quickly as possible; and that was to be done with the
     intention that, when they had set fire to the city on all sides as it had been arranged and
     distributed, and had made a great massacre of the citizens, he might be at hand to catch those
     who fled, and to join himself to the leaders within the city. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
     But the Gauls being introduced, said that an oath had been administered to <pb n="308"/> them,
     and letters given them by Publius Lentulus, Cethegus, and Statilius, for their nation; and that
     they had been enjoined by them, and by Lucius Cassius, to send cavalry into Italy as early as
     possible; that infantry should not be wanting; and that Lentulus had assured him, from the
     Sibylline oracles and the answers of soothsayers, that he was that third Cornelius to whom the
     kingdom and sovereignty over this city was fated to come; that Cinna and Sulla had been before
     him; and that he had also said that was the year destined to the destruction of this city and
     empire, being the tenth year after the acquittal of the virgins, and the twentieth after the
     burning of the Capitol. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> But they said there had been this
     dispute between Cethegus and the rest,—that Lentulus and others thought it best that the
     massacre should take place and the city be burnt at the Saturnalia, but that Cethegus thought
     it too long to wait. <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>And, not to detain you, O Romans, we ordered the letters to be brought forward which were
     said to have been given them by each of the men. First I showed his seal to Cethegus; he
     recognised it: we cut the thread; we read the letter. It was written with his own hand: that he
     would do for the senate and people of the Allobroges what he had promised their ambassadors;
     and that he begged them also to do what their ambassadors had arranged. Then Cethegus, who a
     little before had made answer about the swords and daggers which had been found in his house,
     and had said that he had always been fond of fine arms, being stricken down and dejected at the
     reading of his letters, convicted by his own conscience, became suddenly silent. Statilius,
     being introduced, owned his handwriting and his seal. His letters were read, of nearly the same
     tenor: he confessed it. Then I showed Lentulus his letters, and asked him whether he recognised
     the seal? He nodded assent. But it is, said I, a well-known seal;—the likeness of your
     grandfather, a most illustrious man, who greatly loved his country and his fellow-citizens; and
     it even though silent, ought to have called you back from such wickedness. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Letters are read of the same tenor to the senate and people of the Allobroges. I offered him
     leave, if he wished to say anything of these matters: and at first he declined to speak; but a
     little afterwards, when the whole examination had been gone through and concluded, he rose. He
     asked the Gauls what he had had to do with them? why they had come to his house? and he asked
     Vulturcius too. And when they had answered him briefly and steadily, under whose guidance they
     had come to him, and how often; and when they asked him whether he had said nothing to them
     about the Sibylline oracles, then he on a sudden, mad with wickedness, showed how great was the
     power of conscience; for though he might have denied it, he suddenly, contrary to every one's
     expectation confessed it: so not only did his genius and skill in oratory, for which he was
     always eminent, but even through the power of his manifest and detected wickedness, that
     impudence in which he surpassed all men, and audacity deserted him.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But Vulturcius on a sudden ordered the letters to be
     produced and opened which he said had been given to him for Catiline, by Lentulus. And though
     Lentulus was greatly agitated at that, yet he acknowledged his seal and his handwriting; but
     the letter was anonymous, and ran thus:—“Who I am you will know from him whom I have sent to
     you: take care to behave like a man, and consider to what place you have proceeded, and provide
     for what is now necessary for you: take care to associate to yourself the assistance of every
     one, even of the powerless.” Then Gabinius being introduced, when at first he had begun to
     answer impudently, at last denied nothing of those things which the Gauls alleged against him.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p> And to me, indeed, O Romans, though the letters, the seals,
     the handwriting, and the confession of each individual seemed most certain indications and
     proofs of wickedness, yet their colour, their eyes, their countenance, their silence, appeared
     more certain still; for they stood so stupefied, they kept their eyes so fixed on the ground,
     at times looking stealthily at one another, that they appeared now not so much to be informed
     against by others as to be informing against themselves. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Having produced and divulged these proofs, O Romans, I consulted the senate what ought to be
     done for the interests of the republic. Vigorous and fearless opinions were delivered by the
     chief men, which the senate adopted without any variety; and since the decree of the senate is
     not yet written out, I will relate to you from memory, O citizens, what the senate has decreed.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p> First of all, a vote of thanks to me is passed in the most
     honourable words, because the republic has been delivered from the greatest dangers by my
     valour <pb n="310"/> and wisdom, and prudence. Then Lucius Flaccus and Caius Pomtinus, the
     praetors, are deservedly and rightly praised, because I had availed myself of their brave and
     loyal assistance. And also, praise is given to that brave man, my colleague, because he had
     removed from his counsels, and from the counsels of the republic, these who had been
     accomplices in this conspiracy. And they voted that Publius Lentulus, when he had abdicated the
     praetorship, should be given into custody; and also, that Caius Cethegus, Lucius Statilius,
     Publius Gabinius, who were all present, should be given into custody: and the same decree was
     passed against Lucius Cassius, who had begged for himself the office of burning the city;
     against Marcus Caparius, to whom it had been proved that Apulia had been allotted for the
     purpose of exciting disaffection among the shepherds; against Publius Furius, who belongs to
     the colonies which Lucius Sulla led to Faesulae; against Quintus Manlius Chilo, who was always
     associated with this man Furius in his tampering with the Allobroges; against Publius Umbrenus,
     a freedman, by whom it was proved that the Gauls were originally brought to Gabinius. 
    <milestone unit="para"/>And the senate, O citizens, acted with such lenity, that, out of so great a conspiracy, and
     such a number and multitude of domestic enemies, it thought that since the republic was saved,
     the minds of the rest might be restored to a healthy state by the punishment of nine most
     abandoned men. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> And also a supplication <note anchored="true">A supplication was a solemn thanksgiving to the gods, decreed by the senate, when all the
      temples were opened and the statues of the gods placed in public upon couches (<foreign xml:lang="lat">pulvinaria</foreign>), to which the people offered up their thanksgivings and
      prayers. It was usually decreed on the intelligence arriving of any great victory, and the
      number of days which it was to last was proportioned to the importance of the victory. It was
      generally regarded as a prelude to a triumph. Of course, from what has been said, it must have
      been usually confined to generals; who laid aside the toga on leaving the city to assume the
      command of the army, and assumed the <foreign xml:lang="lat">paludamentum</foreign>, or
      military robe. </note> was decreed in my name, (which is the first time since the building of
     the city that such an honour has ever been paid to a man in a civil capacity,) to the immortal
     gods, for their singular kindness. And it was decreed in these words, “because I had delivered
     the city from conflagrations, the citizens from massacre, and Italy from war.” And if this
     supplication be compared with others, O citizens, there is this difference between them,—that
     all others have been appointed because of the successes of the republic; this one alone for its
     preservation. And that which was the first thing to be done, has been done and executed; for
     Publius Lentulus, though, being convicted by proofs and, by his own confession, by the judgment
     of the senate he had lost not only the rights of a praetor but also those of a citizen, still
     resigned his office; so that though Caius Marcius, that most illustrious of men, had no
     scruples about putting to death Caius Glaucius the praetor against whom nothing had been
     decreed by name, still we are relieved from that scruple in the case of Publius Lentulus, who
     is now a private individual. </p></div><milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Now, since, O citizens you have the nefarious leaders of this most wicked and dangerous war
     taken prisoners and in your grasp, you ought to think that all the resources of Catiline,—all
     his hopes and all his power, now that these dangers of the city are warded off, have fallen to
     pieces. And, indeed, when I drove him from the city I foresaw in my mind, O citizens, that if
     Catiline were removed, I had no cause to fear either the drowsiness of Publius Lentulus, or the
     fat of Lucius Cassius, or the mad rashness of Cassius Cethegus. He alone was to be feared of
     all these men, and that, only as long as he was within the walls of the city. He knew
     everything, he had access to everybody. He had the skill and the audacity to address, to tempt
     and to tamper with every one. He had acuteness suited to crime; and neither tongue nor hand
     ever failed to support that acuteness. Already he had men he could rely on chosen and
     distributed for the execution of all other business and when he had ordered anything to be done
     he did not think it was done on that account. There was nothing to which he did not personally
     attend and see to,—for which he did not watch and toil. He was able to endure cold, thirst, and
     hunger. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Unless I had driven this man, so active, so ready, so audacious, so crafty, so vigilant in
     wickedness, so industrious in criminal exploits, from his plots within the city to the open
     warfare of the camp, (I will express my honest opinion, O citizens,) I should not easily have
     removed from your necks so vast a weight of evil. He would not have determined on the
     Saturnalia <note anchored="true">The Saturnalia was a feast of Saturn at which extraordinary
      licence and indulgence was allowed to all the slaves; it took place at the end of December,
      while this speech of Cicero was delivered early in November.</note> to massacre you he would
     not <pb n="312"/> have announced the destruction of the republic, and even the day of its doom
     so long beforehand,—he would never have allowed his seal and his letters, the undeniable
     witnesses of his guilt, to be taken, which now, since he is absent, has been so done that no
     larceny in a private house has ever been so thoroughly and clearly detected as this vast
     conspiracy against the republic. But if Catiline had remained in the city to this day,
     although, as long as he was so, I met all his designs and withstood them; yet, to say the
     least, we should have had to fight with him, and should never, while he remained as an enemy in
     the city, have delivered the republic from such dangers, with such ease, such tranquillity, and
     such silence. </p></div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Although all these things, O Romans, have been so managed by men that they appear to have
     been done and provided for by the order and design of the immortal gods; and as we may
     conjecture this because the direction of such weighty affairs scarcely appears capable of
     having been carried out by human wisdom; so, too, they have at this time so brought us present
     aid and assistance, that we could almost behold them without eyes. For to say nothing of those
     things, namely, the firebrands seen in the west in the night time, and the heat of the
     atmosphere,—to pass over the falling of thunderbolts and the earthquakes,—to say nothing of all
     the other portents which have taken place in such number during my consulship, that the
     immortal gods themselves have been seeming to predict what is now taking place; yet, at all
     events, this which I am about to mention, O Romans, must be neither passed over nor omitted.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>For you recollect, I suppose, when Cotta and Torquatus were consuls, that many towers in the
     Capitol were struck with lightning, when both the images of the immortal gods were moved, and
     the statues of many ancient men were thrown down, and the brazen tablets on which the laws were
     written were melted. Even Romulus, who built this city, was struck, which, you recollect, stood
     in the Capitol, a gilt statue, little and sucking, and clinging to the teats of the wolf. And
     when at this time the soothsayers were assembled out of all Etruria, they said that slaughter,
     and conflagration, and the overthrow of the laws, and civil and domestic war, and the fall of
     the whole city and empire was at hand, unless the immortal gods, being appeased in every
     possible manner, by their own power turned aside, as I may say, the very fates themselves.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, according to their answers, games were celebrated for ten days, nor was anything
     omitted which might tend to the appeasing of the gods. And they enjoined also that we should
     make a greater statue of Jupiter, and place it in a lofty situation, and (contrary to what had
     been done before) turn it towards the east. And they said that they hoped that if that statue
     which you now behold looked upon the rising of the sun, and the forum, and the senate-house,
     that those designs which were secretly formed against the safety of the city and empire would
     be brought to light so as to be able to be thoroughly seen by the senate and by the Roman
     people. And the consuls ordered it to be so placed; but so great was the delay in the work,
     that it was never set up by the former consuls nor by us before this day. </p></div><milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Here who, O Romans can there be so obstinate against the
     truth, so headstrong, so void of sense, as to deny that all these things which we see, and
     especially this city, is governed by the divine authority and power of the immortal gods?
     Forsooth, when this answer had been given, that massacre, and conflagration, and ruin was
     prepared for the republic; and that, too, by profligate citizens, which, from the enormity of
     the wickedness, appeared incredible to some people, you found that it had not only been planned
     by wicked citizens, but had even been undertaken and commenced. And is not this fact so present
     that it appears to have taken place by the express will of the good and mighty Jupiter, that,
     when this day, early in the morning, both the conspirators and their accusers were being led by
     my command through the forum to the Temple of Concord, at that very time the statue was being
     erected? And when it was set up and turned towards you and towards the senate the senate and
     you yourselves saw everything which had been planned against the universal safety brought to
     light and made manifest.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And on this account they deserve even greater hatred and
     greater punishment, for having attempted to apply their fatal and wicked fire, not only to your
     houses and homes, but even to the shrines and temples of the Gods. And if I were to say that it
     was I who resisted them, I should take too much to myself and ought not to be borne. He—he,
     Jupiter, resisted them, He determined that the Capitol should be safe, he saved these temples,
     he saved this city, he saved all of you. <pb n="314"/> It is under the guidance of the immortal
     gods, O Romans, that I have cherished the intention and desires which I have, and have arrived
     at such undeniable proofs. Surely, that tampering with the Allobroges would never have taken
     place, so important a matter would never have been so madly entrusted, by Lentulus and the rest
     of our internal enemies, to strangers and foreigners, such letters would never have been
     written, unless all prudence had been taken by the immortal gods from such terrible audacity.
     What shall I say? That Gauls, men from a state scarcely at peace with us, the only nation
     existing which seems both to be able to make war on the Roman people, and not to be unwilling
     to do so,—that they should disregard the hope of empire and of the greatest success voluntarily
     offered to them by patricians; and should prefer your safety to their own power—do you not
     think that that was caused by divine interposition? especially when they could have destroyed
     us, not by fighting, but by keeping silence. </p></div><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, O citizens, since a supplication has been decreed at all the altars, celebrate
     those days with your wives and children; for many just and deserved honours have been often
     paid to the immortal gods, but juster ones never. For you have been snatched from a most cruel
     and miserable destruction, and you have been snatched from it without slaughter, without
     bloodshed, without an army, without a battle. You have conquered in the garb of peace, with me
     in the garb of peace for your only general and commander.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Remember, O citizens, all civil dissensions, and not only
     those which you have heard of but these also which you yourselves remember and have seen.
     Lucius Sulla crushed Publius Sulpicius<note anchored="true">Sulpicius procured a law to be
      passed for taking the command against Mithridates from Sulla and giving it to Marius; Sulla
      came to Rome with his army and slew Sulpicius, when Marius fled to Africa. Sulla made Octavius
      and Cinna consuls, who quarreled after he was gone, and Cinna went over to the party of
      Marius, who returned to Rome. Lepidus and Catulus were consuls the year after the death of
      Sulla, and they quarreled because Lepidus wished to rescind all the acts of Sulla. Lepidus was
      defeated, fled to Sardinia, and died there.</note>; he drove from the city Caius Marius the
     guardian of this city; and of many other brave men some he drove from the city, and some he
     murdered. Cnaeus Octavius the consul drove his colleague by force of arms out of the city; all
     this place was crowded with heaps of carcasses and flowed with the blood of citizens;
     afterwards Cinna and Marius got the upper hand; and then most illustrious men were put to
     death, and the spirits of the state were extinguished. Afterwards Sulla avenged the cruelty of
     this victory; it is needless to say with what a diminution of the citizens and with what
     disasters to the republic Marcus Lepidus disagreed with that most eminent and brave man
     Quintus, Catulus. His death did not cause as much grief to the republic as that of the others. 
     </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And these dissensions, O Romans, were such as concerned not
     the destruction of the republic, but only a change in the constitution. They did not wish that
     there should be no republic, but that they themselves should be the chief men in that which
     existed; nor did they desire that the city should be burnt, but that they themselves should
     flourish in it. And yet all those dissensions, none of which aimed at the destruction of the
     republic, were such that they were to be terminated not by a reconciliation and concord, but
     only by internecine war among the citizens. But in this war alone, the greatest and most cruel
     in the memory of man,—a war such as even the countries of the barbarians have never waged with
     their own tribes,—a war in which this law was laid down by Lentulus, and Catiline, and Cassius
     and Cethegus that every one, who could live in safety as long as the city remained in safety,
     should be considered as an enemy, in this war I have so managed matters, O Romans that you
     should all be preserved in safety; and though your enemies had thought that only such a number
     of the citizens would be left as had held out against an interminable massacre and only so much
     of the city as the flames could not devour, I have preserved both the city and the citizens
     unhurt and undiminished. </p></div><milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> And for these exploits, important as they are, O Romans, I
     ask from you no reward of virtue, no badge of honour, no monument of my glory, beyond the
     everlasting recollection of this day. In your minds I wish all my triumphs, all my decorations
     of honour; the monuments of my glory, the badges of my renown, to be stored and laid up.
     Nothing voiceless can delight me, nothing silent,—nothing, in short, such as even those who are
     less worthy can obtain. In your memory, O Romans, my name shall be cherished, in your
     discourses it shall grow, in the monuments of your letters it shall grow old and strengthen;
     and I feel assured <pb n="316"/> that the same day which I hope will be for everlasting; will
     be remembered for ever, so as to tend both to the safety of the city and the recollection of my
     consulship; and that it will be remembered that there existed in this city at the same time two
     citizens, one of whom limited the boundaries of your empire only by the regions of heaven, not
     by those of the earth, while the other preserved the abode and home of that same empire.
      </p></div><milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But since the fortune and condition of those exploits which I have performed is not the same
     with that of those men who have directed foreign wars—because I must live among those whom I
     have defeated and subdued, they have left their enemies either slain or crushed,—it is your
     business, O Romans, to take care, if their good deeds are a benefit to others, that mine shall
     never be an injury to me. For that the wicked and profligate designs of audacious men shall not
     be able to injure you, I have taken care; it is your business to take care that they do not
     injure me. Although, O Romans, no injury can be done to me by them,—for there is a great
     protection in the affection of all good men, which is procured for me for ever; there is great
     dignity in the republic, which will always silently defend me; there is great power in
     conscience, and those who neglect it when they desire to attack me will destroy themselves.
      </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>There is moreover that disposition in me, O Romans, that I not only will yield to the
     audacity of no one, but that I always voluntarily attack the worthless. And if all the violence
     of domestic enemies being warded off from you turns itself upon me alone, you will have to take
     care, O Roman; in what condition you wish those men to be for the future, who for your safety
     have exposed themselves to unpopularity and to all sorts of dangers. As for me, myself; what is
     there which now can be gained by me for the enjoyment of life, especially when neither in
     credit among you, nor in the glory of virtue, do I see any higher point to which I can be
     desirous to climb? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>That indeed I will take care of; O Romans, as a private man to uphold and embellish the
     exploits which I have performed in my consulship: so that if there has been any unpopularity
     incurred in preserving the republic, it may injure those who envy me, and may tend to my glory.
     Lastly, I will so behave myself in the republic as always to remember what I have done, and to
     take care that they shall appear to have been done through virtue, and not by chance. Do you, O
     Romans, since it is now night ,worship that Jupiter, the guardian of this city and of
     yourselves, and depart to your homes; and defend those homes, though the danger is now removed,
     with guard and watch as you did last night, That you shall not have to do so long, and that you
     shall enjoy perpetual tranquillity, shall, O Romans, be my care.</p></div>
   </div>
   <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="speech">
    <head> THE FOURTH ORATION OF M. T. CICERO AGAINST LUCIUS CATILINA. DELIVERED IN THE
     SENATE.</head>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
     <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
     <p><milestone unit="para"/>The night after the events mentioned in the argument to the preceding oration, Cicero's wife
      Terentia, with the vestal virgins was performing at home the mystic rites of the Bona Dea
      while Cicero was deliberating with his friends on the best mode of punishing the conspirators.
      Terentia interrupted their deliberations by coming in to inform them of a prodigy which had
      just happened that after the sacrifice in which she had been engaged was over the fire revived
      spontaneously; on which the vestal virgins had sent her to him to inform him of it, and to bid
      him pursue what he was then thinking of and intending for the good of his country, since the
      goddess had given this sign that she was watching over his safety and glory.
     <milestone unit="para"/>The next day the senate ordered public rewards to the ambassadors and to Vulturcius; and
      showed signs of intending to proceed with extreme rigour against the conspirators when on a
      sudden rumours arose of plots having been formed by the slaves of Lentulus and Cethegus for
      their masters' rescue; which obliged Cicero to double all the guards, and determined him to
      prevent any repetition of such attempts by bringing before the senate without delay the
      question of the punishment of the prisoners. On which account he summoned the senate to meet
      the next morning.
     <milestone unit="para"/>There were many difficulties in the matter. Capital punishments were unusual and very
      unpopular at Rome. And there was an old law of Porcius Lecca, a tribune of the people, which
      granted to all criminals who were capitally condemned an appeal to the people; and also a law
      had been passed, since his time, by Caius Gracchus, to prohibit the taking away the life of
      any citizen without a formal hearing before the people. And these considerations had so much
      weight with some of the senators, that they absented themselves from the senate during this
      debate, in order to have no share in sentencing prisoners of such high rank to death. The
      debate was opened by Silanus, the consul elect, who declared his opinion that those in
      custody, and those also who should be taken subsequently, should all be put to death. Everyone
      who followed him agreed with him, till Julius Caesar, the praetor elect, (who has been often
      suspected of having at least to some extent, privy to the conspiracy,) rose, and in an
      elaborate speech proposed that they should not be put to death, but that their estates should
      be confiscated, and they themselves kept in perpetual confinement. Cato opposed him with great
      earnestness. But some of Cicero's friends appeared inclined to Caesar's motion, thinking it a
      safer measure for Cicero himself; but when Cicero perceived this, he rose himself; and
      discussed the opinions both of Silanus and Caesar in the following speech, which decided the
      senate to vote for their condemnation. And as soon as the vote had passed, Cicero went
      immediately from the senate house, took Lentulus from the custody of his kinsman Lentulus
      Spinther, and delivered him to the executioner. The other conspirators, Cethegus, Statilius,
      Gabinius, were in like manner conducted to execution by the praetors; and Cicero was conducted
      home to his house in triumph by the whole body of the senate and by the knights, the whole
      multitude following him, and saluting him as their deliverer.</p></div>
    
    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I see, O conscript fathers, that the looks and eyes of you all are turned towards me; I see
     that you are anxious not only for your own danger and that of the republic, but even, if that
     be removed, for mine. Your good-will is delightful to one amid evils, and pleasing amid grief;
     but I entreat you, in the name of the immortal gods, lay it aside now, and, forgetting my
     safety, think of yourselves and of your children. If indeed, this condition of the consulship
     has been allotted to me, that I should bear all bitterness, all pains and tortures, I will bear
     them not only bravely but even cheerfully, provided that by my toils dignity and safety are
     procured for you and for the Roman people.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> I am that consul, O conscript fathers, to whom neither the
     forum in which all justice is contained, nor the Campus Martius, <note anchored="true">The
       <foreign xml:lang="lat">Campus Martius</foreign> was consecrated or restored to Mars after the
      expulsion of the Tarquins; the <foreign xml:lang="lat">comitia centuriata</foreign> at which
      all magistrates were created were held there.</note> consecrated to the consular assemblies,
     nor the senate house, the chief assistance of all nations, nor my own home, the common refuge
     of all men, nor my bed devoted to rest, in short, not even this seat of honour, this curule
     chair has ever been free from the danger of death, or from plots and treachery. I have been
     silent about many things, I have borne much, I have conceded much, I have remedied many things
     with some pain to myself amid the alarm of you all. Now if the immortal gods have determined
     that there shall be this end to my consulship that I should snatch you, O conscript fathers,
     and the Roman people from miserable slaughter, your wives and children and the vestal virgins
     from most bitter distress, the temples and shrines of the gods and this most lovely country of
     all of us, from impious flames, all Italy from war and devastation, then whatever fortune is
     laid up for me by myself it shall be borne. If, indeed, Publius Lentulus, being led on by
     soothsayers believed that his name was connected by destiny with the destruction of the
     republic, why should not I rejoice that my consulship has taken place almost by the express
     appointment of fate for the preservation of the republic? </p></div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, O conscript fathers, consult the welfare of yourselves, provide for that of the
     republic; preserve yourselves, your wives, your children, and your fortunes; defend the name
     and safety of the Roman people; cease to spare me, and to think of me. For, in the first place,
     I ought to hope that all the gods who preside over this city will show me gratitude in
     proportion as I deserve it; and in the second place, if anything does happen to me, I shall
     fall with a contented and prepared mind; and, indeed, death cannot be disgraceful to a brave
     man, nor premature to one of consular rank, nor miserable to a wise man. Not that I am a man of
     so iron a disposition as not to be moved by the grief of a most dear and affectionate brother
     now present, and by the tears of all these men by whom you now see me surrounded. Nor does my
     fainting wife, my daughter prostrate with fear, and my little son whom the republic seems to me
     to embrace as a sort of hostage for my consulship, the son-in-law who, awaiting the end of that
     day, is now standing in my sight, fail often to recall my mind to my home. I am moved by all
     these circumstances, but in such a direction as to wish that they all may be safe together with
     you, even if some violence overwhelms me, rather than that both they and are should perish
     together with the republic.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Wherefore, O conscript fathers, attend to the safety of the
     republic; look round upon all the storms which are impending, unless you guard against them. It
     is not Tiberius Gracchus, who wished to be made a second time a tribune of the people; it is
     not Caius Gracchus, who endeavoured to excite the partisans <pb n="320"/> of the agrarian law;
     it is not Lucius Saturninus, who slew Memmius, who is now in some danger, who is now brought
     before the tribunal of your severity. They are now in your hands who withstood all Rome, with
     the object of bringing conflagration on the whole city, massacre on all of you, and of
     receiving Catiline; their letters are in your possession, their seals, their handwriting, and
     the confession of each individual of them; the Allobroges are tampered with, the slaves are
     excited, Catiline is sent for; the design is actually begun to be put in execution, that all
     should be put to death, so that no one should be left even to mourn the name of the republic,
     and to lament over the downfall of so mighty a dominion. </p></div><milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>All these things the witnesses have informed you of; the prisoners have confessed, you by
     many judgments have already decided; first, because you have thanked me in unprecedented
     language, and have passed a vote that the conspiracy of abandoned men has been laid open by my
     virtue and diligence; secondly, because you have compelled Publius Lentulus to abdicate the
     praetorship; again, because you have voted that he and the others about whom you have decided
     should be given into custody; and above all because you have decreed a supplication in my name,
     an honour which has never been paid to any one before acting in a civil capacity; last of all
     because yesterday you gave most ample rewards to the ambassadors of the Allobroges and to Titus
     Vulturcius; all which acts are such that they, who have been given into custody by name,
     without any doubt seem already condemned by you. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>But I have determined to refer the business to you as a fresh matter, O conscript fathers,
     both as to the fact, what you think of it and as to the punishment, what you vote. I will state
     what it behoves the consul to state. I have seen for a long time great madness existing in the
     republic, and new designs being formed, and evil passions being stirred up; but I never thought
     that so great, so destructive a conspiracy as this was being meditated by citizens. Now to
     whatever point your minds and opinions incline, you must decide before night. You see how great
     a crime has been made known to you; if you think that but few are implicated in it you are
     greatly mistaken; this evil has spread wider than you think; it has spread not only throughout
     Italy, but it has even crossed the Alps, and creeping stealthily on, it has already occupied
     many of the provinces; it can by no means be crushed by tolerating it, and by temporising with
     it; however you determine on chastising it, you must act with promptitude. </p></div><milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>I see that as yet there are two opinions. One that of Decius Silanus, who thinks that those
     who have endeavoured to destroy all these things should be punished with death the other, that
     of Caius Caesar, who objects to the punishment of death, but adopts the most extreme severity
     of all other punishment. Each acts in a manner suitable to his own dignity and to the magnitude
     of the business with the greatest severity. The one thinks that it is not right that those, who
     have attempted to deprive all or us and the while Roman people of life, to destroy the empire,
     to extinguish the name of the Roman people, should enjoy life and the breath of heaven common
     to us all, for one moment; and he remembers that this sort of punishment has often been
     employed against worthless citizens in this republic. The other feels that death was not
     appointed by the immortal gods for the sake of punishment, but that it is either a necessity of
     nature, or a rest from toils and miseries; therefore wise men have never met it unwillingly,
     brave men have often encountered it even voluntarily. But imprisonment and that too perpetual,
     was certainly invented for the extraordinary punishment of nefarious wickedness; therefore he
     proposes that they should be distributed among the municipal towns. This proposition seems to
     have in it injustice if you command; it difficulty if you request it. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Let it, however, be so decreed if you like. For I will undertake, and, as I hope, I shall
     find one who will not think it suitable to his dignity to refuse what you decide on for the
     sake of the universal safety. He imposes besides a severe punishment on the burgesses of the
     municipal town if any of the prisoners escape; he surrounds them with the most terrible guard,
     and with everything worthy of the wickedness of abandoned men. And he proposes to establish a
     decree that no one shall be able to alleviate the punishment of those whom he is condemning by
     a vote of either the senate or the people. He takes away even hope, which alone can comfort men
     in their miseries; besides this, he votes that their goods should be confiscated; he leaves
     life <pb n="322"/> alone to these infamous men, and if he had taken that away; he would have
     relieved them by one pang of many tortures of mind and body, and of all the punishment of their
     crimes. Therefore, that there might be some dread in life to the wicked, men of old have
     believed that there were some punishments of that sort appointed for the wicked in the shades
     below; because in truth they perceived that if this were taken away death itself would not be
     terrible. </p></div><milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Now, O conscript fathers, I see what is my interest; if you follow the opinion of Caius
     Caesar, (since he has adopted this path in the republic which is accounted the popular one,)
     perhaps since he is the author and promoter of this opinion, the popular violence will be less
     to be dreaded by me; if you adopt the other opinion, I know not whether I am not likely to have
     more trouble; but still let the advantage of the republic outweigh the consideration of my
     danger. For we have from Caius Caesar, as his own dignity and as the illustrious character of
     his ancestors demanded, a vote as a hostage of his lasting good-will to the republic; it has
     been clearly seen how great is the difference between the lenity of demagogues, and a
     disposition really attached to the interests of the people. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p>
     I see that of those men who wish to be considered attached to the people one man is absent,
     that they may not seem forsooth to give a vote about the lives of Roman citizens. He only three
     days ago gave Roman citizens into custody, and decreed me a supplication, and voted most
     magnificent rewards to the witnesses only yesterday. It is not now doubtful to any one what he,
     who voted for the imprisonment of the criminals, congratulation to him who had detected them,
     and rewards to those who had proved the crime, thinks of the whole matter, and of the cause.
     But Caius Caesar considers that the Sempronian <note anchored="true">The Sempronian law was
      proposed by Caius Gracchus, B.C. <date when="-0123">123</date>, and enacted that the people
      only should decide respecting the life or civil condition of a citizen. It is alluded to also
      in the oration <bibl n="Cic. Rab.Perd. 4">Pro Rabir. c. 4</bibl>, where Cicero says, “Caius
      Gracchus passed a law that no decision should be come to about the life of a Roman citizen
      without your command,” speaking to the <foreign xml:lang="lat">Quirites</foreign>.</note> law
     was passed about Roman citizens, but that he who is an enemy of the republic can by no means be
     a citizen; and moreover that the very proposer of the Sempronian law suffered punishment by the
     command of the people. He also denies that Lentulus, a briber and a spendthrift, after he has
     formed such cruel and bitter plans about the destruction of the Roman people and the ruin of
     this city, can be called a friend of the people. Therefore this most gentle and merciful man
     does not hesitate to commit Publius Lentulus to eternal darkness and imprisonment, and
     establishes a law to all posterity that no one shall be able to boast of alleviating his
     punishment or hereafter to appear a friend of the people to the destruction of the Roman
     people. He adds also the confiscation of their goods, so that want also and beggary may be
     added to all the torments of mind and body. </p></div><milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, if you decide on this you give me a companion in my address, dear and acceptable
     to the Roman people; or if you prefer to adopt the opinion of Silanus, you will easily defend
     me and yourselves from the reproach of cruelty, and I will prevail that it shall be much
     lighter. Although, O conscript fathers, what cruelty can there be in chastising the enormity of
     such excessive wickedness? For I decide from my own feeling. For so may I be allowed; to enjoy
     the republic in safety in your company, as I am not moved to be somewhat vehement in this cause
     by any severity of disposition, (for who is more merciful than I am?) but rather by a singular
     humanity and mercifulness. For I seem to myself to see this city, the light of the world and
     the citadel of all nations, falling on a sudden by one conflagration. I see in my mind's eye
     miserable and unburied heaps of cities in my buried country; the sight of Cethegus and his
     madness raging amid your slaughter is ever present to my sight. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> But when I have set before myself Lentulus reigning, as he himself confesses
     that he had hoped was his destiny, and this Gabinius arrayed in the purple and Catiline arrived
     with his army, then I shudder at the lamentation of matrons, and the flight of virgins and of
     boys and the insults of the vestal virgins; and because these things appear to me exceedingly
     miserable and pitiable, therefore I show myself severe and rigorous to those who have wished to
     bring about this state of things. I ask, forsooth, if any father of a family, supposing his
     children had been slain by a slave, his wife murdered, his house burnt, were not to inflict on
     his slaves the severest possible punishment would he appear clement and merciful or most
     inhuman and cruel? To me he would seem unnatural and hard-hearted who did not soothe his own
     pain and anguish by the pain and torture of the criminal. And so we, <pb n="324"/> in the case
     of these men who desired to murder us, and our wives, and our children,—who endeavoured to
     destroy the houses of every individual among us, and also the republic, the home of all,—who
     designed to place the nation of the Allobroges on the relics of this city, and on the ashes of
     the empire destroyed by fire;—if we are very rigorous, we shall be considered merciful; if we
     choose to be lax, we must endure the character of the greatest cruelty, to the damage of our
     country and our fellow-citizens. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Unless, indeed, Lucius <note anchored="true">The
      brother-in-law of Lucius Caesar was Marcus Fulvius, whose death, at the command of Opimius the
      consul, is referred to at <bibl n="Cic. Catil. 2.1">Cat. 2. chap1</bibl>. He sent his son to
      the consul to treat for his surrender, whom Opimius sent back the first time, and forbade to
      return to him; when he did return, he put him to death.</note> Caesar, a thoroughly brave man
     and of the best disposition towards the republic, seemed to any one to be too cruel three, days
     ago, when he said that the husband of his own sister, a most excellent woman, (in his presence
     and in his hearing,) ought to be deprived of life,— when he said that his grandfather had been
     put to death by command of the consul and his youthful son, sent as an ambassador by his
     father, had been put to death in prison. And what deed had they done like these men? had they
     formed any plan for destroying the republic? At that time great corruption was rife in the
     republic, and there was the greatest strife between parties. And, at that time, the grandfather
     of this Lentulus, a most illustrious man, put on his armour and pursued Gracchus; he even
     received a severe wound that there might be no diminution of the great dignity of the republic.
     But this man, his grandson, invited the Gauls to overthrow the foundations of the republic; he
     stirred up the slaves, he summoned Catiline, he distributed us to Cethegus to be massacred, and
     the rest of the citizens to Gabinius to be assassinated, the city he allotted to Cassius to
     burn, and the plundering and devastating of all Italy he assigned to Catiline. You fear, I
     think, lest in the case of such unheard of and abominable wickedness you should seem to decide
     anything with too great severity; when we ought much more to fear lest by being remiss in
     punishing we should appear cruel to our country, rather than appear by the severity of our
     irritation too rigorous to its most bitter enemies. </p></div><milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>But O conscript fathers, I cannot conceal what I hear; for sayings are bruited about, which
     come to my ears, of those men who seem to fear that I may not have force enough to put in
     execution the things which you determine on this day. Everything is provided for, and prepared,
     and arranged, O conscript fathers, both by my exceeding care and diligence, and also by the
     still greater zeal of the Roman people for the retaining of their supreme dominion, and for the
     preserving of the fortunes of all. All men of all ranks are present, and of all ages; the forum
     is full, the temples around the forum are full, all the approaches to this place and to this
     temple are full. For this is the only cause that has ever been known since the first foundation
     of the city, in which all men were of one and the same opinion—except those, who, as they saw
     they must be ruined, preferred to perish in company with all the world rather than by
     themselves.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> These men I except, and I willingly set apart from the
     rest; for I do not think that they should be classed in the number of worthless citizens, but
     in that of the most bitter enemies. But, as for the rest, O ye immortal gods! in what crowds,
     with what zeal, with what virtue do they agree in defence of the common dignity and safety. Why
     should I here speak of the Roman knights? who yield to you the supremacy in rank and wisdom, in
     order to vie with you in love for the republic,—whom this day and this cause now reunite with
     you in alliance and unanimity with your body reconciled after a disagreement of many years. And
     if we can preserve for ever in the republic this union now established in nay consulship, I
     pledge myself to you that no civil and domestic calamity can hereafter reach any part of the
     republic. I see that the tribunes of the treasury—excellent men—have united with similar zeal
     in defence of the republic, and all the notaries. <note anchored="true">The notaries at Rome
      were in the pay of the state; they were chiefly employed in making up the public accounts. In
      the time of Cicero it seems to have been lawful for any one to obtain the office of <foreign xml:lang="lat">scriba</foreign> by purchase, (see <bibl n="Cic. Ver. 2.2.79">Cic. in Verr.
       2.79</bibl>,) and freedmen and their sons frequently availed themselves of this privilege.
     </note> For as this day had by chance brought them in crowds to the treasury, I see that they
     were diverted from an anxiety for the money due to them, from an expectation of their capital,
     to a regard for the common safety. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> The entire multitude of
     honest men, even the poorest is present; for who is there to whom these temples, the sight of
     the city, the possession of liberty,—in short; this light and this soil of his, common to us
     all, is not both dear and pleasant and delightful? <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>It is worth while, O conscript fathers, to know the inclinations of the freedmen; who, having
     by their good fortune obtained the rights of citizens, consider this to be really their
     country, which some who have been born here, and born in the highest rank, have considered to
     be not their own country, but a city of enemies. But why should I speak of men of this body
     whom their private fortunes, whom their common republic, whom, in short, that liberty which is
     most delightful has called forth to defend the safety of their country? There is no slave who
     is only in an endurable condition of slavery who does not shudder at the audacity of citizens,
     who does not desire that these things may stand, who does not contribute all the good-will that
     he can, and all that he dares, to the common safety.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Wherefore, if this consideration moves any one, that it
     has been heard that some tool of Lentulus is running about the shops,—is hoping that the minds
     of some poor and ignorant men may be corrupted by bribery; that, indeed, has been attempted and
     begun, but no one has been found either so wretched in their fortune or so abandoned in their
     inclination as not to wish the place of their seat and work and daily gain, their chamber and
     their bed, and, in short, the tranquil course of their lives, to be still preserved to them.
     And far the greater part of those who are in the shops,—yes, indeed, (for that is the more
     correct way of speaking,) the whole of this class is of all the most attached to tranquillity;
     their whole stock, indeed, their whole employment and livelihood, exists by the peaceful
     intercourse of the citizens, and is wholly supported by peace. And if their gains are
     diminished whenever their shops are shut, what will they be when they are burnt? </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p> And, as this is the case, O conscript fathers, the protection of the
     Roman people is not wanting to you; do you take care that you do not seem to be wanting to the
     Roman people. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
    <milestone unit="para"/>You have a consul preserved out of many dangers and plots, and from death itself not for his
     own life, but for your safety. All ranks agree for the preservation of the republic with heart
     and will, with zeal, with virtue, with their voice. Your common country, besieged by the hands
     and weapons of an impious conspiracy, stretches forth her hands to you as a suppliant; to you
     she recommends herself to you she recommends the lives of all the citizens, and the citadel,
     and the Capitol, and the altars of the household gods, and the eternal inextinguishable fire of
     Vesta, and all the temples of all the gods, and the altars and the walls and the houses of the
     city. Moreover, your own lives, those of your wives and children, the fortunes of all men, your
     homes, your hearth; are this day interested in your decision.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> You have a leader mindful of you, forgetful of himself—an
     opportunity which is not always given to men; you have all ranks, all individuals, the whole
     Roman people, (a thing which in civil transactions we see this day for the first time,) full of
     one and the same feeling. Think with what great labour this our dominion was founded, by what
     virtue this our liberty was established, by what kind favour of the gods our fortunes were
     aggrandized and ennobled, and how nearly one night destroyed them all. That this may never
     hereafter be able not only to be done, but not even to be thought of you must this day take
     care. And I have spoken thus, not in order to stir you up who almost outrun me myself but that
     my voice, which ought to be the chief voice in the republic, may appear to have fulfilled the
     duty which belongs to me as consul. </p></div><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>Now, before I return to the decision, I will say a few words concerning myself. As numerous
     as is the band of conspirators—and you see that it is very great,—so numerous a multitude of
     enemies do I see that I have brought upon myself. But I consider them base and powerless and
     despicable and abject. But if at any time that band shall be excited by the wickedness and
     madness of any one, and shall show itself more powerful than your dignity and that of the
     republic, yet. O conscript fathers, I shall never repent of my actions and of my advice. Death,
     indeed, which they perhaps threaten me with, is prepared for all men; such glory during life as
     you have honoured me with by your decrees no one has ever attained to. For you have passed
     votes of congratulation to others for having governed the republic successfully, but to me
     alone for having saved it.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> Let Scipio be thought illustrious, he by whose wisdom and
     valour Hannibal was compelled to return into Africa, and to depart from Italy. Let the second
     Africanus be extolled with conspicuous praise, who destroyed two cities most hostile to this
     empire, Carthage and Numantia. Let Lucius Paullus be thought a great man, he whose triumphal
     car was graced <pb n="328"/> by Perses, previously a most powerful and noble monarch. Let
     Marius be held in eternal honour, who twice delivered Italy from siege, and from the fear of
     slavery. Let Pompey be preferred to them all—Pompey, whose exploits and whose virtues are
     bounded by the same districts and limits as the course of the sun. There will be, forsooth,
     among the praises of these men, some room for my glory, unless haply it be a greater deed to
     open to us provinces whither we may fly, than to take care that those who are at a distance
     may, when conquerors; have a home to return to. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Although in one point the circumstances of foreign triumph are better than those of domestic
     victory; because foreign enemies, either if they be crushed become one's servants, or if they
     be received into the state, think themselves bound to us by obligations; but those of the
     number of citizens who become depraved by madness and once begin to be enemies to their
     country,—those men, when you have defeated their attempts to injure the republic, you can
     neither restrain by force nor conciliate by kindness. So that I see that an eternal war with
     all wicked citizens has been undertaken by me; which, however, I am confident can easily be
     driven back from me and mine by your aid, and by that of all good men, and by the memory of
     such great dangers, which will remain, not only among this people which has been saved, but in
     the discourse and minds of all nations forever. Nor, in truth, can any power be found which
     will be able to undermine and destroy your union with the Roman knights, and such unanimity as
     exists among all good men. </p></div><milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p>
    <milestone unit="para"/>As, then, this is the case, O conscript fathers, instead of my military command—instead of
     the army,——instead of the province <note anchored="true">Cicero, in order to tempt Antonius to
      aid him in counteracting the treasonable designs of Catiline, had given up to him the province
      of Macedonia, which had fallen to his own lot; and having accepted that or Cisalpine Gaul in
      exchange for it, he gave that also to Quintus Metellus; being resolved to receive no
      emolument, directly or indirectly, from his consulship.</note> which I have neglected, and the
     other badges of honour which have been rejected by me for the sake of protecting the city and
     your safety,—in place of the ties of clientship and hospitality with citizens in the provinces,
     which, however, by my influence in the city, I study to preserve with as much toil as I labour
     to acquire them,—in place of all these things, and in reward for my singular zeal in your
     behalf, and for this diligence in saving the republic which you behold, I ask nothing of you
     but the recollection of this time and of my whole consulship. And as long as that is fixed in
     your minds, I still think I am fenced round by the strongest wall. But if the violence of
     wicked men shall deceive and overpower my expectations, I recommend to you my little son, to
     whom, in truth, it will be protection enough, not only for his safety, but even for his dignity
     if you recollect that he is the son of him who has saved all these things at his own single
     risk. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>
    
    <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, O conscript fathers, determine with care, as you have begun, and boldly,
     concerning your own safety, and that of the Roman people, and concerning your wives and
     children; concerning your altars and your hearths your shrines and temples; concerning the
     houses and homes of the whole city; concerning your dominion, your liberty and the safety of
     Italy and the whole republic. For you have a consul who will not hesitate to obey your decrees,
     and who will be able as long as he lives, to defend what you decide on and of his own power to
     execute it. <note anchored="true">This speech was spoken, and the criminals executed, on the
      fifth of December. But Catiline was not yet entirely overcome. He had with him in Etruria two
      legions,—about twelve thousand men; of which, however, not above one quarter were regularly
      armed. For some time by marches and counter marches he eluded Antonius, but when the news
      reached his army of the fate of the rest of the conspirators it began to desert him in great
      numbers. He attempted to escape into Gaul but found himself intercepted by Metellus who had
      been sent thither by Cicero with three legions. Antonius is supposed not to have been
      disinclined to connive at his escape if he had not been compelled as it were by his quaestor
      Sextus and his lieutenant Petreius to force him to a battle, in which, however, Antonius
      himself being ill of the gout did not take the command, which devolved on Petreius who after a
      severe action destroyed Catiline and his whole army, of which every man is said to have been
      slain in the battle.</note></p></div>
   </div>
  </div>
 </body></text>


</TEI>
