<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five -
                    42</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol.
                    A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title> History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end,
                                with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="1958" xml:id="p.1958"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="book">
                <head>Book XLII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, the censor, spoiled the temple of Juno at La-
                        cinium of the marble tiles, to roof a temple which he was dedicating. The
                        tiles were returned by a decree of the senate. Eumenes, the king of Asia,
                        complained before the senate of Perseus, the king of Macedon; the outrages
                        of the latter are laid before the Roman people. And when a war was
                        proclaimed against him on account of these, Publius Licinius Crassus, the
                        consul to whom it was intrusted, passed over into Ma- cedon, and in trifling
                        expeditions and cavalry actions, fought with Perseus in Thessaly, by no
                        means successfully. An arbiter was appointed by the senate to decide
                        concerning land disputed between Masinissa and the Carthaginians.
                        Ambassadors were sent to request of the allied states and kings, that they
                        would abide by their agreements, as the Rhodians wavered. The lustrum was
                        closed by the censors. Two hundred and fifty-seven thousand two hundred and
                        thirty-one citizens were rated. It includes besides, the successes gained
                        over the Corsicans and Ligurians. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Lucius Postumius Albinus and Marcus
                    Popilius Laenas brought before the senate first of all the distribution of the
                    provinces, Liguria was assigned the joint province of both, with directions that
                    they should enlist new legions, by which they would hold that province (two were
                    decreed to each); and also ten thousand foot and six hundred horse of the Latin
                    confederates; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and as a supplement to the army
                    in Spain, three thousand Roman foot and two hundred horse. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> One thousand five hundred Roman foot and one hundred horse
                    wore ordered to be raised; with which the praetor, to whose lot Sardinia might
                    fall, should cross over to Corsica, and carry on the war there; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and it was further ordered, that in the mean time the
                    former praetor, Marcus Atilius, should obtain the province of Sardinia. The
                    praetors then cast lots for their provinces. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Aulus Atilius Serranus obtained the city jurisdiction; Caius Cluvius Saxula,
                    that between natives and foreigners; Numerius Fabius Buteo, Hither Spain; Mar-
                        <pb n="1959" xml:id="p.1959"/> cus Matienus, Farther Spain; Marcus Furius
                    Crassipes, Sicily; and Caius Cicereius, Sardinia. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The senate resolved that, before the magistrates went
                    abroad, Lucius Postumius should go into Campania, to fix the bounds between the
                    lands which were private property and those which belonged to the public; for it
                    was understood that individuals, by gradually extending their bounds, had taken
                    possession of a very considerable share of the common lands. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He, being enraged with the people of Praeneste because,
                    when he had gone thither as a private individual to offer sacrifice in the
                    temple of Fortune, no honour had been paid him, either in public or private, by
                    the people of Praeneste, before he set out from Rome, sent a letter to
                    Praeneste, ordering the chief magistrate to meet him, and to provide him lodging
                    at the public expense; and that, at his departure, cattle should be ready to
                    carry his baggage. No consul before him ever put the allies to any trouble or
                    expense whatever. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Magistrates were furnished
                    with mules, tents, and every other requisite for a campaign, in order that they
                    might not make any such demands. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They had
                    private lodgings, in which they behaved with courtesy and kindness, and their
                    houses at Rome were always open to their hosts with whom they used to lodge.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Ambassadors indeed sent to any place, on
                    a sudden emergency, demanded each a single horse in the several towns through
                    which their journey lay; but the allies never contributed any other portion of
                    the expense of the Roman magistrates. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    resentment of the consul, which, even if well founded, ought not to have been
                    exerted during his office, and the <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> too
                    modest or too timid acquiescence of the Praenestines, gave to the magistrates,
                    as if by an approved precedent, the privilege of imposing orders of this sort,
                    which grew more burdensome daily. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the beginning of this year the ambassadors,
                    who had been sent to Aetolia and Macedon, returned, and reported that "they had
                    not been able to obtain an interview with Perseus, as some of his court said
                    that he was abroad, others that he was sick; both of which were false pretences.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, that it was quite evident
                    that war was in preparation, and that he would no longer put off the appeal to
                    arms. That in Aetolia, likewise, the dissensions grew daily more violent; and
                    the leaders of the contending parties were not to be restrained by their
                    authority." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As a war with Macedon was <pb
                        n="1960" xml:id="p.1960"/> daily expected, the senate resolved, that before
                    it broke out, all prodigies should be expiated, and the favour of such gods, as
                    should be found expressed in the books of the Fates, invoked by supplications.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was said that at Lanuvium the
                    appearance of large fleets was seen in the air; that at Privernum black wool
                    grew out of the ground; that in the territory of Veii, at Remens, a shower of
                    stones fell; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and that the whole Pomptine
                    district was covered with clouds of locusts; also that in the Gallic province,
                    where a plough was at work, fishes sprung up from under the earth as it was
                    turned. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On account of these prodigies the
                    books of the Fates were accordingly consulted, and the decemvirs directed both
                    to what gods, and with what victims, sacrifloes should be offered; likewise that
                    a supplication should be performed, in expiation of the prodigies; and also that
                    another, which had been vowed in the preceding year for the health of the
                    people, should be celebrated, and likewise a solemn festival. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, sacrifices were offered in accordance with the
                    written directions of the decemvirs. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year, the temple of Juno Lacinia
                    was uncovered. Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, the censor, was erecting a temple to
                    Equestrian Fortune, which he had vowed when praetor during the Celtiberian war,
                    with anxious desire that it should not be surpassed by any other at Rome, either
                    in size or magnificence. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thinking that he
                    would add a very great ornament to this temple if the tiles were marble, he went
                    to Bruttium, and stripped off about the half of those belonging to the temple of
                    the Lacinian Juno; for he computed that so many would be sufficient to cover the
                    one he was building. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Ships were in readiness
                    to take on board the materials, while the allies were deterred by the authority
                    of the censor from preventing the sacrilege. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    When the censor returned, the marble was landed and carried to the temple; but
                    though he made no mention of the place from which it was brought, yet such an
                    affair could not be concealed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly,
                    considerable murmuring arose in the senate; from all sides of the house a demand
                    was made that the consuls should lay that matter before the senate. When the
                    censor, on being summoned, appeared in the senate-house, they all, both
                    separately and in a body, inveighed against him with great asperity. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> They cried out that <quote> he was not content with
                            <pb n="1961" xml:id="p.1961"/> violating the most venerable temple in
                        all that part of the world, a temple which neither Pyrrhus nor Hannibal had
                        violated; but he had stripped it shamefully, and almost demolished it.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Though created censor for the purpose
                        of regulating men's manners, and bound in duty, according to
                        long-established rules, to enforce the repairing of edifices for public
                        worship, and the keeping them in due order, he had nevertheless gone about
                        through the cities of the allies, stripping the roofs of their sacred
                        buildings, and even demolishing them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In a
                        word, what might be deemed scandalous if practised on private houses, he
                        committed against the temples of the immortal gods; and that he involved the
                        Roman people in the guilt of impiety, building temples with the ruins of
                        temples; as if the deities were not the same in all places, but that some
                        should be decorated with the spoils of others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When it was evident what were the sentiments
                    of the senators, before their opinion was asked; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> when the question was put, they unanimously concurred in
                    voting, that a contract should be entered into for carrying the tiles back to
                    the temple, and that atonements should be offered to Juno. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> What regarded the atonements was carefully executed; the
                    contractors made a report that they were obliged to leave the marble in the
                    court of the temple, because no workman could be found who knew how to replace
                    the same. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Of the praetors who set out for the provinces,
                    Numerius Fabius, on his way to Hither Spain, died at Marseilles. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Therefore when this was announced by envoys from
                    Marseilles, the senate resolved that Publius Furius and Cneius Servilius, to
                    whom successors had been sent, should cast lots to determine which of them
                    should hold the government of Hither Spain, with a continuation of authority;
                    and the lot determined, very fortunately, that Publius Furius, whose province it
                    had formerly been, should continue. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> During the
                    same year, on its appearing that large tracts of land in Gaul and Liguria, which
                    had been taken in war, lay unoccupied, the senate passed a decree, that those
                    lands should be dis- tributed in single shares; <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> and Aulus Titilius, city praetor, in pursuance of the said decree, appointed
                    ten commissioners for that purpose, namely, Marcus Aemilius Lepidus, Caius
                    Cassius, Titus Aebutius Carus, Caius Tremellius, Publius Cornelius Cethe- gus,
                    Quintus and Lucius Appuleius, Marcus Caecilius, Caius <pb n="1962"
                        xml:id="p.1962"/> Salonius, and Caius Munatius. They apportioned ten acres
                    to each Roman, and three to each Latin colonist. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> During the same time in which these transactions took place, ambassadors came
                    to Rome from Aetolia with representations of the quarrels and dissensions
                    subsisting in that country; likewise Thessalian ambassadors, announcing the
                    transactions in Macedon. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus, revolving in his mind the war, which
                    had been resolved on during the life-time of his father, endeavoured, by sending
                    embassies, and by promising a great deal more than he performed, to attach to
                    himself not only the commonwealth of Greece, but also each particular state.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> However the feelings of the majority were
                    inclined in his favour, and much better disposed towards him than Eumenes,
                    although all the states of Greece, and most of the leading men, were under
                    obligations to the latter for benefits and gifts; and although he so conducted
                    himself in his sovereignty, that the cities which were under his dominion would
                    not exchange their condition for that of any free state. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> On the contrary, there was a general report that Perseus,
                    after his father's death, had killed his wife with his own hand; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> that Apelles, formerly the agent of his treachery in
                    the destruction of his brother, and on that account sought anxiously by Philip,
                    for punishment, being in exile, was invited by him, after the death of his
                    father, by great promises, to receive a guerdon for rendering so important
                    services, and was secretly put to death. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Although he had rendered himself infamous by many other murders, both of his own
                    relations and of others, and possessed not one good quality to recommend him,
                    yet the Grecian states in general gave him the preference to Eumenes, who was so
                    affectionate towards his relations, so just towards his subjects, and so liberal
                    towards all mankind; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> either because they were
                    so prejudiced by the fame and dignity of the Macedonian kings, as to despise a
                    kingdom lately formed, or were led by a wish for a change in affairs, and wished
                    him to be exposed to the arms of the Romans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Aetolians were not the only people in a state of distraction, on account of
                    the intolerable burden of their debts: the Thessalians were in the same
                    situation; and the evil, acting by contagion like a pestilence, had spread into
                    Perrhaebia also. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As soon as it was known that
                    the Thessalians were in arms, the senate sent <pb n="1963" xml:id="p.1963"/>
                    Appius Claudius, as ambassador, to examine and adjust their affairs. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> He severely reprimanded the leaders of both parties;
                    and after cancelling so much of the debts as had been accumulated by iniquitous
                    usury, which he did with the consent of the greater part of the creditors
                    themselves, he ordered the remaining just debts to be discharged by annual
                    payments. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Affairs in Perrhaebia were arranged
                    in the same manner by the same Appius. In the mean time, Marcellus, at Delphi,
                    gave a hearing to the disputes of the Aetolians, which they maintained with no
                    less hostile acrimony than they had shown against each other in the heat of
                    their civil war. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Perceiving that they vied
                    with each other in inconsiderate violence, he did not choose to make any
                    determination, to lighten or aggravate the grievances of either party, but
                    required of both alike to cease from hostilities, and, forgetting what was past,
                    to put an end to their quarrels. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The good
                    faith of the mutual reconciliation was confirmed by a reciprocal exchange of
                    hostages. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Corinth was agreed upon as the place where the
                    hostages should be lodged. Marcellus crossed over from Delphi, and the Aetolian
                    council, into Peloponnesus, where he had summoned a diet of the Achaeans.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There, by the praises which he bestowed on
                    that nation, for having resolutely maintained their old decree, which prohibited
                    the admission of the Macedonian kings within the limits of their territories, he
                    manifested the inveterate hatred of the Romans towards Perseus; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and this hatred broke out into effect the sooner, in
                    consequence of king Eumenes coming to Rome, and bringing with <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> him a written statement of the preparations made for war,
                    which he had drawn up, after a full inquiry into every particular. Five
                    ambassadors were now sent to the king, in order to take a view of affairs in
                    Macedon. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The same were ordered to proceed to
                    Alexandria to Ptolemy, to renew the treaty of friendship. These were Caius
                    Valerius, Cneius Lutatius Cerco, Quintus Baebius Sulca, Marcus Cornelius
                    Mammula, and Marcus Caecilius Denter. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> About
                    the same time, came ambassadors from king Antiochus; and the principal of them,
                    called Apollonius, being admitted to an audience of the senate, presented, on
                    behalf of his king, many and reasonable apologies for paying the tribute later
                    than the day appointed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>He now brought,</quote> he said, <quote> the whole of <pb n="1964"
                            xml:id="p.1964"/> it, that the king might require no favour except the
                        delay of time. He brought besides a present of gold vases, in weight five
                        hundred pounds. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Antiochus requested, that
                        the treaty of alliance and amity, which had been made with his father, might
                        be renewed with him; and that the Roman people might demand from him every
                        service which might be required from a king who was a good and faithful
                        ally: that he would never be remiss in the performance of any duty.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such had been the kindness of the
                        senate towards him when he was at Rome, such the courtesy of the young men,
                        that, among all ranks of men, he was treated as a sovereign, not as a
                        hostage. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> A gracious answer was returned to the
                    ambassadors, and Aulus Atilius, city praetor, was ordered to renew with
                    Antiochus the alliance formerly made with his father. The city quaestors
                    received the tribute, and the censors the golden vases; and the business of
                    placing them in whatever temples they should judge proper, was assigned to them.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> One hundred thousand <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 322 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were presented to the ambassador, and a house at the public cost was
                    given him for his accommodation, and it was ordered that his expenses should be
                    paid as long as he would remain in Italy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                    ambassadors, who had been in Syria, represented him as standing in the highest
                    degree of favour with the king, and a very warm friend to the Roman people. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following were the events in the provinces
                    during this year. Caius Cicereius, praetor in Corsica, fought the enemy in a
                    pitched battle, in which seven thousand of the Corsicans were slain, and more
                    than one thousand seven hundred taken. During the engagement the praetor vowed a
                    temple to Juno Moneta. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Peace was then granted
                    to the Corsicans, on their petitioning for it, and a contribution was imposed,
                    of two hundred thousand pounds' weight of wax. Cicereius crossed over from
                    Corsica, which he had reduced to subjection, to Sardinia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> In Liguria, also, a battle was fought in the territory of
                    Satiella, at the town of Carystas. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A large
                    army of Ligurians had assembled there, who, for some time after Marcus Popilius'
                    arrival, kept themselves within the walls; but afterwards, when they perceived
                    that the Roman general would lay siege to the town, they marched out beyond the
                    gates, and drew up in order of battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    consul did not <pb n="1965" xml:id="p.1965"/> decline an engagement, as that was
                    the object which he endeavoured to gain by threatening a siege. The fight was
                    maintained for more than three hours, in such a manner, that the hope of victory
                    leaned to neither side; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but when the consul
                    perceived that the Ligurian battalions no where gave ground, he ordered the
                    cavalry to mount their horses, and charge in three places at once, with all
                    possible violence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A great part of the horse
                    broke through the middle of the enemy's line, and made their way to the rear of
                    the troops engaged, owing to which manœuvre, terror was struck into the
                    Ligurians. They fled in different directions on all sides. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Very few ran back into the town, because in that quarter,
                    chiefly, the cavalry had thrown themselves in their way. So obstinate a contest
                    swept off great numbers of the Ligurians, and many perished in the flight; ten
                    thousand of them are said to have been killed, and more than seven hundred
                    taken, in various places; besides which, the victors brought off eighty-two of
                    their military standards. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor was the victory
                    gained without loss of blood; above three thousand of the conquerors fell in the
                    conflict; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> for as neither party gave way, the
                    foremost on both sides were cut off. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Ligurians re-assembled in one body,
                    after their scattered flight, they found that a much greater number of their
                    countrymen were lost than left alive (for there were not above ten thousand men
                    surviving); on which they surrendered. They did not stipulate for any terms, yet
                    entertained hopes that the consul would not treat them with greater severity
                    than former commanders. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But he immediately
                    took their arms from them, razed their town, and sold themselves and their
                    effects; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and he then sent a letter to the
                    senate, relating the services which he had performed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> When Aulus Atilius, the praetor, read this letter in the
                    council, (for the other consul, Postumius, was absent, being employed in
                    surveying the lands in Campania,) the proceeding appeared to the senate in a
                    heinous light; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> that the people of Satiella, who alone, of all the Ligurian nation, had
                        not borne arms against the Romans, should be attacked, when not offering
                        hostilities, and even after surrendering themselves in dependence on the
                        protection of the Roman people, should be butchered and exterminated, that
                        so many thousands of innocent persons suffering, who had implored the
                        protection of the Roman people, estab- <pb n="1966" xml:id="p.1966"/> lished
                        the worst possible precedent, calculated to deter any one from ever
                        venturing to surrender to them; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> dragged as
                        they were away into various parts of the country, and made slaves to those
                        who were formerly the avowed enemies of Rome, though now reduced to quiet.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That for these reasons the senate
                        ordered, that the consul, Marcus Popilius, should reinstate the Ligurians in
                        their liberty, repaying the purchase-money to the buyers, and should
                        likewise use his best endeavours to recover and restore their effects.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That arms should be made for them, as
                        soon as possible; and that the consul should not depart from his province
                        before he restored to their country the Ligurians that had surrendered. That
                        victory derived its lustre from conquering the enemy in arms, not from
                        cruelty to the vanquished. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul exerted the same ferocious spirit
                    in disobeying the senate, which he displayed towards the Ligurians. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> He immediately sent the legions into winter quarters
                    at Pisae, and, full of resentment against the senators and the praetor, went
                    home to Rome; where, instantly assembling the senate in the temple of Bellona,
                    he used many invectives against the praetor, who, <quote> when he ought to have
                        proposed to the senate that thanksgiving <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                        should be offered to the immortal gods, on account of the happy successes
                        obtained by the Roman arms, had procured a decree of the senate against him,
                        in favour of the enemy, by which he might transfer his victory to the
                        Ligurians; and, though only a praetor, he had ordered the consul, in a
                        manner, to be surrendered to them: he therefore gave notice, that he would
                        sue to have him fined. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> From the senate he
                        demanded, that they should order the decree of the senate passed against him
                        to be cancelled; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and that the
                        thanksgiving, which they, though they were far from him, ought to have voted
                        on the authority of his letter, sent from abroad, with an account of the
                        success of the arms of the commonwealth, should, now when he was present, be
                        voted; first, in consideration of the honour due to the immortal gods, and
                        next, out of some kind of regard to himself. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Being censured to his face no less severely
                    than in his absence, in the speeches of several of the senators, and having
                    obtained neither request, he returned to his province. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The other consul, Postumius, after spending the whole
                    summer in surveying the lands, without even seeing his province, came <pb
                        n="1967" xml:id="p.1967"/> home to Rome to hold the elections. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> He appointed Caius Popillius Laenas and Publius
                    Aelius Ligus, consuls. Then Caius Licinius Crassus, Marcus Junius Pennus,
                    Spurius Lucretius, Spurius Cluvius, Cneius Sicinius, and Caius Memmius, a second
                    time, were elected praetors. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The lustrum was closed this year. The censors
                    were Quintus Fulvius Flaccus and Lucius Postumius Albinus, the latter of whom
                    performed the ceremony. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this survey were
                    rated two hundred and sixty-nine thousand and fifteen Roman citizens. The number
                    was considerably less, because the consul, Lucius Postumius, gave public orders,
                    in assembly, that none of the Latin allies (who, according to the edict of the
                    consul, Caius Claudius, ought to have gone home) should be surveyed at Rome, but
                    all of them in their respective countries. Their censorship was conducted with
                    perfect harmony and zeal for the public good. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They disfranchised and degraded from their
                    tribes every one whom they expelled the senate, or from whom they took away his
                    horse; nor did either approve a person censured by the other. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Fulvius, at this time, dedicated the temple of Equestrian
                    Fortune, which he had vowed six years before, and when proconsul in Spain,
                    during the battle with the Celtiberians; he also exhibited stage-plays, which
                    lasted four days, in one of which the performance was in the circus. Lucius
                    Cornelius Lentulus, decemvir in religious matters, died this year, and Aulus
                    Postumius Albinus was substituted in his room. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Such great crowds of locusts were suddenly brought by the wind over the sea into
                    Apulia, that they covered the country far and wide with their swarms. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> In order to remove this pest, so destructive to the
                    fruits of the earth, Caius Sicinius, praetor elect, was sent in command, with a
                    vast multitude of people assembled, to gather them up, and spent a considerable
                    time in that business. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The beginning of the
                    year in which Caius Popilius and Publius Aelius were consuls, was employed in
                    the disputes which had arisen in the last. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    senators were desirous that the business respecting the Ligurians should be
                    re-considered, and the decree renewed. Aelius, the consul, was willing to
                    propose it, but Popillius warmly interceded for his brother, both with his
                    colleague and the senate; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and by giving
                    notice, that if they would pass any vote on the subject he would enter his
                    protest, he deterred him from proceeding <pb n="1968" xml:id="p.1968"/> in the
                    matter. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The senate being hereby equally
                    incensed against them, persisted the more obstinately in their intention; and
                    when they took into consideration the distribution of the provinces, although
                    Macedon was earnestly sought by the consuls, because a war with Perseus was
                    daily expected, yet the Ligurians were assigned as the province of both.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They declare that they would not vote
                    Macedonia to them, unless the question were put on the affair of Marcus
                    Popilius. The consuls afterwards demanded that they might be authorized to raise
                    either new armies, or recruits to fill up the old; both demands were refused.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> To the praetors also, when seeking a
                    reinforcement for Spain, a refusal is given: to Marcus Junius for Hither Spain,
                    and to Spurius Lucretius for the Farther. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Caius Licinius Crassus obtained by lot the city jurisdiction; Cneius Sicinius,
                    the foreign; Caius Memmius, Sicily; and Spurius Cluvius, Sardinia. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> The consuls, enraged against the senate on account
                    of this conduct, having proclaimed an early day for the Latin festival, declared
                    openly that they would go away to their province, and would not transact any
                    kind of business, except what belonged to their own government. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias writes, that, in this
                    consulate, Attalus, brother to king Eumenes, came to Rome as ambassador, to lay
                    heavy charges against Perseus, and give an account of his preparations for war.
                    But the greater number of historians, and those deemed most worthy of credit,
                    assert, that Eumenes came in person. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Eumenes
                    then, on his arrival, being received with every degree of respect which the
                    Roman people judged suitable, not merely to his deserts, but also to their own
                    former favours, bestowed on him in great abundance, was introduced to the
                    senate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He said, that <quote> The cause of his
                        coming to Rome, besides his wish to visit those gods and men who had placed
                        him in a situation beyond which he could not presume to form a wish, was,
                        that he might in person forewarn the senate to counteract the designs of
                        Perseus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, beginning with the projects of Philip,
                    he mentioned his murder of Demetrius, because that prince was averse to a war
                    with Rome; that the Bastarnian nation was summoned from their homes, that,
                    relying on their aid, he might pass over into Italy. <quote> While his thoughts
                        were busied in plans of this sort, he was surprised by the approach of
                        death, and left his kingdom to the person whom he knew to be, of all men,
                            <pb n="1969" xml:id="p.1969"/> the bitterest foe to the Romans.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Perseus therefore, </quote> said he,
                    "having received this scheme of a war, as a legacy bequeathed by his father, and
                    descending to him along with the crown, advances and improves it, as his primary
                    object, by every means that he can devise. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                    is powerful, in respect of the number of his young men, since a long peace has
                    produced a plentiful progeny; he is powerful in respect to the resources of his
                    kingdom, and powerful, likewise, in respect to his age. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And as, at his time of life, he possesses vigour of body,
                    so his mind has been thoroughly trained, both in the theory and practice of war;
                    for even from his childhood he became inured to it, in his father's tent, not
                    only in the wars against the neighbouring states, but also against the Romans,
                    being employed by him in many and various expeditions. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Already, since he has received the government, he has, by a
                    wonderful train of prosperous events, accomplished many things which Philip,
                    after using <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> his best efforts, could never
                    effect, either by force or artifice. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> There is added to his strength such a degree of influence as is usually
                        acquired, in a great length of time, by many and important kindnesses. For,
                        in the several states throughout Greece and Asia, all men revere the dignity
                        of his character; nor do I perceive for what deserts, for what generosity,
                        such uncommon respect is paid him; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> neither
                        can I with certainty say whether it occurs through some good fortune
                        attending him, or whether, what I mention with reluctance a general dislike
                        to the Romans attaches men to his interest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Even among sovereign princes he is great by his influence. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> He married the daughter of Seleucus, a match
                        which he did not solicit, but to which he was solicited by her friends; and
                        he gave his sister in marriage to Prusias, in compliance with his earnest
                        prayers and entreaties. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both these
                        marriages were solemnized amidst congratulations and presents from
                        innumerable embassies, and were escorted by the most renowned nations,
                        acting as bridal attendants. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Bœotians
                        could never be brought, by all the intrigues of Philip, to sign a treaty of
                        friendship with him; but now, a treaty with Perseus is engraved at three
                        different places, at Thebes, in Delos, in the most venerable and celebrated
                        temple, and at Delphi. Then, in the diet of Achaia, (only that the
                        proceeding was quashed by a few persons, threatening them with the <pb
                            n="1970" xml:id="p.1970"/> displeasure of the Roman government,) the
                        business was nearly effected of allowing him admission into Achaia.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But, as to the honours formerly paid
                        to myself, (whose kindness to that nation have been such, that it is hard to
                        say whether my public or private benefactions were the greater,) they have
                        been lost, partly through neglect, and partly by hostile means. Who does not
                        know that the Aetolians, lately, on occasion of their intestine broils,
                        sought protection, not from the Romans, but from Perseus? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> For, while he is upheld by these alliances and
                        friendships, he has at home such preparations of every requisite for war,
                        that he wants nothing from abroad. He has thirty thousand foot and five
                        thousand horse, and is laying up a store of corn for ten years, so that he
                        can be independent of his own territory or that of his enemies with respect
                        to provisions. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He has amassed money to
                        such an amount, as to have in readiness the pay of ten thousand mercenary
                        soldiers, besides the Macedonian troops, for the same number of years, as
                        well as the annual revenue accruing from the royal mines. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> He has stored up arms for three times that number of
                        men; and has Thrace under subjection, from which, as a never-failing spring,
                        he can draw supplies of young men if ever Macedon should become exhausted.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The rest of his discourse contained
                    exhortations to timely exertions: <quote>Conscript fathers,</quote> said he,
                        <quote> I make these representations to you, and they are not founded on
                        uncertain rumours, and too readily believed by me, because I wished such
                        charges against my enemy to be true; but on a clear discovery of the facts,
                        as if I had been sent by you to reconnoitre, and I were now relating what
                        took place before my eyes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nor would I
                        have left my kingdom, which you have rendered ample and highly respectable,
                        and crossed such a tract of sea, to injure my own credit by offering you
                        unauthenticated reports. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I saw the most
                        remarkable states of Asia and Greece, every day, gradually unfolding their
                        sentiments, and ready to proceed, shortly, to such lengths as would not
                        leave them room for repentance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I saw
                        Perseus, not confining himself within the limits of Macedonia, but seizing
                        some places by force of arms, and seducing, by favour and kindness, those
                        which could not be subdued by force. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I
                        perceived the unfair footing on which matters stood, while he was preparing
                        war against you, and you bestowing on him the security of peace; <pb
                            n="1971" xml:id="p.1971"/> although, to my judgment, he did not appear
                        to be preparing, but rather waging war. He dethroned Abrupolis, your ally
                        and friend. He put to death Artetarus, the Illyrian, another ally and friend
                        of yours, because he heard that some information had been written to you by
                        him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He managed that Eversa and
                        Callicrates, the Thebans, who were leading men in their state, should be
                        taken off, because, in the council <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of
                        the Bœotians, they had spoken with more than ordinary freedom against him,
                        and declared that they would inform you of what was going on. He carried
                        succour to the Byzantians, contrary to the treaty. He made war on Dolopia.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He overran Thessaly and Doris with an
                        army, in order to take advantage of the civil war then raging, and by the
                        help of the party which had the worst cause to crush the other which had
                        more justice on its side. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He raised
                        universal confusion and disorder in Thessaly and Perrhaebia, by holding out
                        a prospect of an abolition of debts, that, by the means of the multitude of
                        debtors thereby attached to his interest, he might overpower the nobles.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Since he has performed all these acts
                        with your acquiescence and silent endurance, and has seen Greece yielded up
                        to him by you, he firmly believes that he will not meet with one opponent in
                        arms, until he arrives in Italy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> How safe
                        or how honourable this might be for you, you yourselves may consider; for my
                        part, I thought it would certainly reflect dishonour on me, if Perseus
                        should come into Italy to make war, before I, your ally, came to warn you to
                        be on your guard. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Having discharged this
                        duty, necessarily incumbent on me, and, in some measure, freed and
                        exonerated my faith; what can I do further, but beseech the gods and
                        goddesses that you may adopt such measures as will prove salutary to
                        yourselves, to your commonwealth, and to us your allies and friends who
                        depend upon you? </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> His discourse made a deep impression on the
                    senate. However, for the present, no one, without doors, could know any thing
                    more than that the king had been in the senate- house, in such secrecy were the
                    deliberations of the senate involved; and it was not until after the conclusion
                    of the war, that the purport of king Eumenes' speech, and the answer to it,
                    transpired. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In a few days after, the senate
                    gave audience to the ambassadors of Perseus. But their feelings as well as their
                    ears were so prepossessed by king Eumenes, that every plea offered in his
                    justification by the ambassadors, and every <pb n="1972" xml:id="p.1972"/>
                    argument to alleviate the charges against him, were disregarded. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> They were still further exasperated by the immoderate
                    presumption of Harpalus, chief of the embassy, who said, that <quote> the king
                        was indeed desirous and even anxious, that credit should be given to him
                        when pleading in his excuse that he had neither said nor done any thing
                        hostile; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but that, if he saw them
                        obstinately bent on finding out a pretence for war, he would defend himself
                        with determined courage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The fortune of
                        war was open to all and the issue uncertain. </quote> All the states of
                    Greece and Asia were full of curiosity to learn what the ambassadors of Perseus,
                    and what Eumenes, had effected with the senate; and most of them, on hearing of
                    the latter's journey to Rome, which they supposed might produce material
                    consequences, had sent ambassadors thither who pretended other business.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Among the rest came an embassy from
                    Rhodes, at the head of which was a person named Satyrus, who had no kind of
                    doubt but that Eumenes had included his state in the accusations brought against
                    Perseus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He therefore endeavoured, by every
                    means, through his patrons and friends, to get an opportunity of debating the
                    matter with Eumenes in presence of the senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    When he obtained this, he inveighed against that king with intemperate
                    vehemence, as having instigated the people of Lycia to an attack on the
                    Rhodians, and as being more oppressive to Asia than Antiochus had been.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He delivered a discourse flattering
                    indeed, and acceptable to the states of Asia, (for the popularity of Perseus had
                    spread even to them,) but very displeasing to the senate, and disadvantageous to
                    himself and his nation. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This apparent
                    conspiracy against Eumenes, increased, indeed, the favour of the Romans towards
                    him; so that every kind of honour was paid, and the most magnificent presents
                    were made him; among which were a curule chair and an ivory sceptre. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the embassies were dismissed, when
                    Harpalus went back into Macedon with all the haste he could, and told the king
                    that he had left the Romans, not indeed making immediate preparations for war,
                    but in such an angry temper, that it was very evident they would not defer it
                    long; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Perseus himself, who all along believed
                    that this would be the case, now even wished for it, as he thought himself at
                    the highest pitch of power that he could ever expect to attain. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He was more violently incensed against Eumenes than against
                        <pb n="1973" xml:id="p.1973"/> any other; and being desirous of commencing
                    the war with his bloodshed, he suborned Evander, a Cretan, commander of the
                    auxiliaries, and three Macedonians, who were accustomed to the perpetration of
                    such deeds, to murder that king; and gives them a letter to a woman called
                    Praxo, an acquaintance of his, the wealthiest and most powerful person at
                    Delphi. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was generally known that Eumenes
                    intended going up to Delphi to sacrifice to Apollo. The assassins having
                    reconnoitred the ground with Evander, sought for nothing else than a fit place
                    to execute their design. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the road from
                    Cirrha to the temple, before you come to the places thickly inhabited, there was
                    a wall on the left side of a narrow path projecting a little from the
                    foundation, by which single persons could pass; the part on the right formed a
                    precipice of considerable depth by the sinking of the ground. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Behind this wall they concealed themselves, and raised up
                    steps to it, that from thence, as from a fortress, they might discharge their
                    weapons on the king, as he passed by. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At
                    first, as he came up from the sea, he was surrounded by a multitude of his
                    friends and attendants; afterwards the increasing narrowness of the road made
                    the train thinner about him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they arrived
                    at the spot where each was to pass singly, the first who advanced on the path
                    was Pantaleon, an Aetolian of distinction, who was at the time in conversation
                    with the king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The assassins now, starting up,
                    rolled down two huge stones, by one of which the head of the king was struck,
                    and by the other the shoulder; and being stunned by the blow, many stones having
                    been cast on him after falling, he tumbled from the sloping path down the
                    precipice. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The rest of his friends and
                    attendants, on seeing him fall, fled different ways; but Pantaleon, with great
                    intrepidity and resolution, kept his ground, in order to protect the king. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assassins might, by making a short circuit
                    of the wall, have run down and completed their business; yet they fled off
                    towards the top of Parnassus with such precipitation, that as one of them, by
                    being unable to keep up with the rest through the pathless and steep grounds,
                    retarded their flight, they killed him lest he should be taken, and a discovery
                    ensue. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The friends, and then the guards and
                    servants of the king, ran together and raised him up, while stunned by the
                    wound, and quite insensible. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> However, they <pb
                        n="1974" xml:id="p.1974"/> perceived, from the warmth of his body, and the
                    breath remaining in his lungs, that he was still alive, but had little or no
                    hopes that he would ever recover. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some of his
                    guards having pursued the tracks of the assassins, when they had reached even as
                    far as the summit of Parnassus, and had fatigued themselves in vain, returned
                    without being able to overtake them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As the
                    Macedonians set about the deed injudiciously; so, after making the attempt with
                    boldness, they abandoned it in a manner both foolish and cowardly. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> His friends on the next day bore to his ship the
                    king, now in possession of his faculties, and then, having drawn their vessels
                    across the neck of the isthmus, they cross over to Aegina. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Here his cure was conducted with such secrecy, his
                    attendants admitting no one, that a report of his death was carried into Asia.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Attalus also gave more ready credence to
                    it than was worthy the harmony of brothers; for he talked, both to Eumenes'
                    consort, and to the governor of the citadel, as if he had actually succeeded to
                    the crown. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This, afterwards, came to the
                    knowledge of the king; who, though he had determined to dissemble, and to pass
                    it over in silence, yet could not refrain, at their first meeting, from rallying
                    Attalus, on his premature haste to get his wife. The report of Eumenes' death
                    spread even to Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time, Caius Valerius, who had
                    been sent ambassador to examine the state of Greece, and to observe the
                    movements of king Perseus, returned from that country, and made a report of all
                    things, which agreed with the accusations urged by Eumenes. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He brought with him from Delphi, Praxo, the woman whose
                    house had served as a receptacle for the assassins; and Lucius Rammius, a
                    Brundusian, who was the bearer of the following information. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Rammius was a person of the first distinction at
                    Brundusium, accustomed to entertain in his house the Roman commanders, and such
                    ambassadors as came that way from foreign powers, especially those of the kings.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> By these means he had formed an
                    acquaintance with Perseus, although he was distant from him; and in consequence
                    of a letter from him, which gave hopes of a more intimate friendship, and of
                    great advantages to accrue to him, he went on a visit to the king, and, in a
                    short time, found himself treated with particular familiarity, and drawn,
                    oftener than he wished, into private conversations. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="1975" xml:id="p.1975"/> Perseus, after promises of the highest rewards,
                    pressed him, with the most earnest solicitations, <quote> as all the commanders
                        and ambassadors of the Romans used to lodge at his house, to procure poison
                        to be given to such of them as he should point out by letter; </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and told him, that, <quote> as he knew the
                        preparation of poison to be attended with the greatest difficulty and
                        danger, and that ordinarily it could not be administered without the privity
                        of several; besides, the issue was uncertain, whether doses sufficiently
                        powerful to produce the desired effect, or calculated to escape detection,
                        might be given; —he <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> would, therefore, give
                        him some which neither in administering nor when administered could be
                        discovered by any means. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Rammius dreading, lest, in case of refusal, he
                    should himself be the first on whom the poison would be tried, promised
                    compliance, and departed; but did not wish to return to Brundusium, without
                    first holding a conference with Caius Valerius, the ambassador, who was said to
                    be at that time in the neighbourhood of Chalcis. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Having first laid his information before him, by his order he accompanied him
                    to Rome, where, being brought before the senate, he gave them an account of what
                    had passed. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These discoveries were added to the
                    information which had been given by Eumenes, and effected, that Perseus should
                    the sooner be judged an enemy; as the senate perceived that he did not content
                    himself with preparing, with the spirit of a king, for a fair and open war, but
                    pushed his designs by all the base clandestine means of assassination and
                    poison. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The conduct of the war is conferred on
                    the new consuls; but, in the mean time, an order was given, that Cneius
                    Sicinius, the praetor, whose province was the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"
                    /> jurisdiction between natives and foreigners, should raise soldiers who should
                    be led with all expedition to Brundusium, and thence carried over into Apollonia
                    in Epirus, in order to secure the cities on the seacoasts; in order that the
                    consul, who should have Macedon as his province, might put in his fleet with
                    safety, and land his troops with convenience. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Eumenes was detained a long time at Aegina, by a dangerous and difficult cure;
                    but, as soon as he could remove with safety, he went home to Pergamus, and set
                    on foot the most vigorous preparations for war, since the late atrocious
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> villany of Perseus now stimulated him,
                    in addition to the ancient enmity which subsisted between them. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Am- <pb n="1976" xml:id="p.1976"/> bassadors soon came from
                    Rome, with congratulations on his escape from so great a danger. When the war
                    with Macedon was deferred to the next year, (the other praetors having gone away
                    to their provinces,) Marcus Junius and Spurius Lucretius, to whom the Spanish
                    affairs had fallen, by importuning the senate with frequent repetitions of the
                    same request, obtained at last that a reinforcement for their army should be
                    given them, viz. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> three thousand foot and one
                    hundred and fifty horse, for the Roman legions; they are ordered to levy, from
                    the allies, for the confederate troops, five thousand foot and three hundred
                    horse: these forces were carried by the new praetors into Spain. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the same year, because, in consequence of
                    the inquiries made by the consul Postumius, a large portion of the lands of
                    Campania, which had been usurped by private persons indiscriminately, in various
                    parts, had been recovered to the public, Marcus Lucretius, plebeian tribune,
                    published a proposal for an order of the people, that the censors should let the
                    Campanian land to farm; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> a measure which had
                    been omitted during so many years, since the taking of Capua, that the
                    greediness of individuals might have clear room to work in. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> After war, though not yet proclaimed, had been resolved on,
                    while the senate was anxious to know which of the several kings would espouse
                    their cause, and which that of Perseus, ambassadors came to Rome from
                    Ariarathes, bringing with them his younger son. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> The purport of their message was, that <quote> the king had sent his son to
                        be educated at Rome, in order that he might even from childhood be
                        acquainted with the manners and the persons of the Romans; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and he requested, that they would allow him to be not
                        only under the protection of his particular friends, but likewise the care,
                        and in some measure the guardianship, of the public. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This embassy was highly pleasing to the
                    senate; and they ordered, that Cneius Sicinius, the praetor, should hire a
                    furnished house for the accommodation of the young prince and his attendants.
                    Then that which they sought was given to ambassadors of the Thracians, who were
                    disputing among themselves, and requesting the friendship and alliance of the
                    Roman people, and presents of the amount of two thousand <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 6 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 9 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were sent to each; for the Romans were rejoiced that these states were
                    gained as <pb n="1977" xml:id="p.1977"/> allies, the more so, as they lay at the
                    back of Macedon. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But, in order to acquire a
                    clear knowledge of every thing in Asia and in the islands, they sent ambasadors,
                    Tiberius Claudius Nero and Marcus Decimus, with orders to go to Crete <milestone
                        n="8??" unit="section"/> and Rhodes, to renew the treaties of friendship,
                    and at the same time to observe whether the affections of the allies had been
                    tampered with by Perseus. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the minds of the public were in a state
                    of extreme anxiety and suspense with respect to the impending war, in
                    consequence of a storm happening in the night the pillar in the Capitol,
                    ornamented with beaks of ships, <hi rend="italics">which had been</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">erected</hi> in the first Punic war by the consul <hi
                        rend="italics">Marcus Aemilius,</hi> whose colleague was Servius Fulvius,
                    was shattered to pieces, even to the very foundation, by lightning. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> This event, being deemed a prodigy, was reported to
                    the senate, who ordered, that it should be laid before the aruspices, and that
                    the decemvirs should consult the books. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    decemvirs, in answer, directed that the city should be purified; that a
                    supplication, and prayers, for the averting of misfortunes should be offered,
                    and victims of the larger kinds sacrificed both in the Capitol at Rome, and at
                    the promontory of Minerva in Campania; and that games should be celebrated as
                    soon as possible in honour of Jupiter supremely good and great, during ten days,
                    All these directions were carefully executed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The aruspices an- swered, that the prodigy would prove happy in the issue; that
                    it portended extension of territory and destruction of enemies; for those beaks
                    of ships which the storm had scat- tered were spoils. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There were other occurrences which oc- casioned religious
                    apprehensions: it was said, that at the town of Saturnia showers of blood fell
                    during three successive days; that an ass with three feet was foaled at Calatia;
                    that a bull, with five cows, were killed by one stroke of lightning; and that a
                    shower of earth had fallen at Auximum. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On
                    account of these prodigies, also, public worship was performed, and a
                    supplication and festival observed for one day. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls had not yet gone to their
                    provinces; for they would not comply with the senate, in proposing the business
                    respecting Marcus Popilius; and, on the other hand, the senate was determined to
                    proceed on no other until that was done. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    general resentment against Popilius was aggravated by a letter received from
                    him, in which he mentioned <pb n="1978" xml:id="p.1978"/> that he had, as
                    proconsul, fought a second battle with the Ligurians of Statiella, six thousand
                    of whom he had killed. On account of the injustice of this attack, the rest of
                    the states of the Ligurians took up arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then
                    not only was Popilius, in his absence, severely censured in the senate, for
                    having, contrary to all laws, human and divine, made war on a people who had
                    submitted to terms, and stirred up to rebellion states that were disposed to
                    live in peace, but also the consuls for not having proceeded to that province.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Encouraged by the unanimous opinion of the
                    senators, two plebeian tribunes, Marcus Marcius Sermo and Quintus Marcius Sylla,
                    declared publicly that they would institute a suit for a fine to be laid on the
                    consuls, if they did not repair to their destination. They likewise read before
                    the senate a proposal for an order of the people respecting the Ligurians, which
                    they intended to publish. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By it a regulation
                    was made, <quote> that in case any of the surrendered Statiellans should not be
                        restored to liberty before the calends of August, then next ensuing, the
                        senate, on oath, should appoint a magistrate to inquire into the business,
                        and to punish the person through whose wicked practices he had been brought
                        into slavery; </quote> and accordingly, by direction of the senate, they
                    proclaimed the same in public. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before the
                    departure of the consuls, the senate gave audience, in the temple of Bellona, to
                    Caius Cicereius, praetor of the former year. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After recounting what he had performed in
                    Corsica, he demanded a triumph; but this being refused, he rode in state on the
                    Alban mount; a mode of celebration for victory without public authority, which
                    had now become usual. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The people, with
                    universal approbation, passed and ratified the order proposed by Marcius,
                    respecting the Ligurians; and in pursuance of this resolution of the people,
                    Caius Licinius, praetor, desired the senate to appoint a person to conduct the
                    inquiry, according to the order; whereupon the senate directed that he himself
                    should conduct it. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls repaired, at last, to their
                    province, and received the command of the army from Marcus Popilius. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> But the latter did not dare to go home to Rome, lest
                    he might plead his cause while the senate were so highly displeased with him,
                    the people still more exasperated, and before a praetor likewise who had taken
                    the opinion of the senate on <pb n="1979" xml:id="p.1979"/> an inquiry pointed
                    against him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the people met
                    his evasion by the menace of another order, —that if he did not come into the
                    city of Rome before the ides of November, Caius Licinius should judge and
                    determine respecting him, though absent. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When
                    he, dragged by this fetter, had returned, his presence in the senate called
                    forth general hatred. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There, when he was
                    censured by the severe reproaches of many, a decree was passed, that the
                    praetors, Caius Licinius and Cneius Sicinius, should take care that such of the
                    Ligurians as had not been in open arms since the consulate of Quintus Fulvius
                    and Lucius Manlius, should all be restored to liberty; and that the consul,
                    Caius Popilius, should assign them lands on the farther side of the Po. By this
                    decree many thousands were restored in this manner, led beyond the Po, and
                    received portions of land accordingly. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Popi- lius, being tried by the Marcian law, twice pleaded his cause before Caius
                    Licinius; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but at a third hearing, the praetor,
                    overcome by his regard for the absent consul, and the prayers of the Popilian
                    family, ordered the defendant to appear on the ides of March, on which day the
                    new magistrates were to enter into office; so that he, being then in a private
                    capacity, could not preside at the trial. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thus
                    was the order of the people, respecting the Ligurians, eluded by artifice. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There were at this time in Rome ambassadors
                    from Carthage, and also Gulussa, son of Masinissa, between whom very warm words
                    passed, in presence of the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    Carthaginians complained that, <quote> besides the district, about which
                        ambassadors were formerly sent from Rome, to determine the matter on the
                        spot, Masinissa had, within the last two years, by force of arms, possessed
                        himself of more than seventy towns and forts in the Carthaginian
                        territories. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This was easy for him, who
                        cared for nothing. But the Carthaginians, being tied down by treaty, were
                        silent; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> for they were prohibited from
                        carrying arms beyond their own frontiers; and although they knew that if
                        they forced the Numidians thence, they would wage the war within their own
                        territory, yet they were deterred by another clause in the treaty, too clear
                        to be mistaken, in which they were expressly forbidden to wage war against
                        the allies of the Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the
                        Carthaginians could not longer endure his pride, his cruelty, and his
                        avarice. They were sent, </quote> they said, <quote> to beseech the <pb
                            n="1980" xml:id="p.1980"/> senate to grant them one of these three
                        things: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> either that they should fairly
                        decide what belonged to each, as became an ally of both; or give permission
                        to the Carthaginians to defend themselves in a just war against unjust
                        attacks; or finally, if favour swayed more with them than the truth, to fix
                        at once how much of the property of others they wished should be bestowed on
                        Masinissa. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the senate would certainly
                        be more moderate in their grants, and they themselves would know the extent
                        of them; whereas, he would set no limits but the arbitrary dictates of his
                        own ambition. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If they could obtain none of
                        these, and if they had, since the peace granted by Publius Scipio, been
                        guilty of any transgression, they begged that the Romans themselves would
                        rather inflict the punishment. They preferred a secure bondage under Roman
                        masters, to a state of freedom exposed to the injustice of Masinissa.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was better for them to perish at
                        once, than to continue to breathe under the will of an executioner. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After these words, they burst into tears,
                    prostrated themselves on the ground, and, in this posture, excited both
                    compassion for themselves, and <hi rend="italics">no less displeasure</hi>
                    against the king. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was then voted, that Gulussa should be
                    asked what answer he had to make to these charges; or that, if it were more
                    agreeable to him, he should first tell on what business he had come to Rome.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Gulussa said, that <quote> it was not easy
                        for him to speak on subjects concerning which he had no instructions from
                        his father; and that it would have been hard for his father to have given
                        him instructions, when the Carthaginians neither disclosed the business
                        which they intended to bring forward, nor even their design of going to
                        Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That they had, for several nights,
                        held private consultations, composed of nobles, in the temple of
                        Aesculapius, from whence ambassadors were despatched with secret information
                        to Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This was his father's reason for
                        sending him into Italy, that he might entreat the senate not to give credit
                        to the common enemy accusing him, whom they hated for no other cause than
                        his inviolable fidelity to the Roman people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After hearing both parties, the senate, on the
                    question being put respecting the demands of the Carthaginians, ordered this
                    answer to be given, that <quote> it was their will that Gulussa should, without
                        delay, return to Numidia, and desire his <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        father to send ambas- <pb n="1981" xml:id="p.1981"/> sadors immediately to
                        the senate, to answer the complaints of the Carthaginians, and to give
                        notice to that people to come and support their allegation. They had
                        hitherto paid to Masinissa, and would continue to pay him, all the honour in
                        their power; that they could not sacrifice justice to favour. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Their wish was, that the lands should every where
                        be possessed by the real owners; nor did they intend to establish new
                        boundaries, but that the old ones should be observed. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> When they vanquished the Carthaginians, they left them
                        in possession of cities and lands, not with the purpose of <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> stripping them by acts of injustice in time of
                        peace of what they had not taken from them by the right of war. </quote>
                    With this answer the Carthaginians, and the prince, were dismissed. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The customary presents were sent to both parties,
                    and the other attentions which hospitality required were performed with all
                    courtesy. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time Cneius Servilius Caepio,
                    Appius Claudius Centho, and Titus Annius Luscus, who had been sent ambassadors
                    to Macedonia, to demand restitution and renounce the king's friendship,
                    returned, and inflamed to a still greater degree the senate, already predisposed
                    to hostilities against Perseus, by relating, in order, what they had seen and
                    heard. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They said, that <quote> through all the
                        cities of Macedonia they saw preparations for war, carried on with the
                        utmost diligence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they arrived at the
                        residence of the king, they were refused admission to him for many days; at
                        last, when, despairing of a conference, they were just setting out, then at
                        length they were called back from their journey and brought before him.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That the leading subjects in their
                        discourse were, the treaty concluded with Philip, and, after his father's
                        death, renewed with himself; in which he was expressly prohibited from
                        carrying his arms beyond his own dominions, and, likewise, from making war
                        on the allies of the Roman people. They then laid before him, in order, the
                        true and well-authenticated accounts which they themselves had lately heard
                        from Eumenes, in the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They took
                        notice, besides, of his having held a secret consultation, in Samothracia,
                        with ambassadors from the states of Asia; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        and told him, that the senate thought proper that satisfaction should be
                        given for these injuries, as well as restitution, <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> to them and their allies, of their property, which he
                        held contrary to the <pb n="1982" xml:id="p.1982"/> tenor of the treaty.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On this the king, being inflamed,
                        spoke at first harshly, frequently upbraiding the Romans with pride and
                        avarice, and with ambassadors coming one after another to pry into his words
                        and actions; and with thinking proper that he should speak and do all things
                        in compliance with their nod and order. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        After speaking a long time with great loudness and violence, he ordered them
                        to return the next day, for he intended to give his answer in writing. Then
                        the written answer was given to them; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> of
                        which the purport was, that the treaty concluded with his father in no
                        respect concerned him; that he had suffered it to be renewed, not because he
                        approved of it, but because, being so lately come to the throne, he had to
                        endure every thing. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If they chose to form
                        a new engagement with him, they ought first to agree on the terms; if they
                        could bring themselves to make a treaty on an equal footing, he would
                        consider what was to be done on his part, and he was convinced that they
                        would provide for the interests of their own state. After this, he hastily
                        turned away, and they were desired to quit the palace. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> They then declared, that they renounced his friendship
                        and alliance; at which he was highly exasperated, stopped, and with a loud
                        voice charged them to quit his dominions within three days. They departed
                        accordingly; and neither on their coming, nor while they staid, was any kind
                        of attention or hospitality shown them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Thessalian and Aetolian ambassadors were
                    then admitted to audience. It pleased the senate, that a letter should be sent
                    to the consuls, directing, that whichever <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                    of them was most able should come to Rome to elect magistrates, in order that
                    they might know what commanders the state was about to employ. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, during that year, performed no
                    business of the republic that deserved much notice. It appeared more
                    advantageous to the republic, that the Ligurians, who had been highly
                    exasperated, should be pacified and appeased. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    While a Macedonian war was expected, ambassadors from Issa gave them reason to
                    suspect the inclinations of Gentius, king of Illyria; for they complained that
                        <quote>he had, a second time, ravaged their country;</quote> affirming
                    likewise, that <quote> the kings of Macedon and Illyria lived on terms of the
                        closest intimacy; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that both were
                        preparing, in concert, for war against the Romans, and that there were then
                        in Rome <pb n="1983" xml:id="p.1983"/> Illyrian spies, under the appearance
                        of ambassadors, and who were sent thither by the advice of Perseus, to
                        ascertain what was going on. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Illyrians, being called before the senate,
                    said, that they were sent by their king, to justify his conduct, if the Issans
                    should make any complaint against him. They were then asked why they had not
                    applied to some magistrate, that they might, according to the regular practice,
                    be furnished with lodging and entertainment, that their arrival might be known,
                    and the business on which they came; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> when they
                    hesitated in their reply, they were ordered to retire out of the senate-house.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was not thought proper to give them any
                    answer, as delegates, because they had not applied for an audience of the
                    senate; they resolved, <quote> that ambassadors should be sent to the king, to
                        announce to him the complaints made by the allies of his having ravaged
                        their country; and that he acted unjustly, since he did not refrain from
                        offering injury to their allies. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On this embassy Aulus Terentius Varro, Caius
                    Plaetorius, and Caius Cicereius, were sent. The ambassadors, who had been sent
                    to the several kings in alliance with the state, came home from Asia, and
                    reported that <quote> they had conferred in it with Eumenes; in Syria, with
                        Antiochus; and at Alexandria, with Ptolemy; all of whom, though strongly
                        solicited by embassies from Perseus, remained perfectly faithful to their
                        engagements, and gave assurances of their readiness to execute every order
                        of the Roman people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That they had also
                        visited the allied states; that all were firm in their attachment, except
                        the Rhodians, who seemed to be wavering, and infected by the counsels of
                        Perseus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Ambassadors had come from the Rhodians, to
                    exculpate them from the imputations which, they knew, were openly urged against
                    them; but a resolution was made, that <quote>an audience of the senate should be
                        given, when the new magistrates came into office.</quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate were of opinion, that the
                    preparations for war should be deferred no longer. The duty is assigned to Caius
                    Licinius, that out of the old galleys laid up in the docks at Rome, which might
                    be rendered serviceable, he should refit and get ready for sea fifty ships.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> If any were wanting to make up that
                    number, that he should write to his colleague, Caius Memmius, in Sicily,
                    directing him to repair and fit out such vessels as were in that province, so
                    that they might <pb n="1984" xml:id="p.1984"/> be sent, with all expedition, to
                    Brundusium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Caius Licinius, the praetor, was
                    ordered to enlist Roman citizens of the rank of freed-men's sons, to man
                    twenty-five ships; Cneius Sicinius, to levy, from the allies, an equal number
                    for the other twenty-five, and likewise to require from the Latin confederates
                    eight thousand foot and four hundred horse. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Aulus Atilius Serranus, who had been praetor the year before, was commissioned
                    to receive these troops at Brundusium, and transport them to Macedon; and Cneius
                    Sicinius, the praetor, to keep them in readiness for embarkation. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> By direction of the senate, Caius Licinius, the
                    praetor, wrote to the consul, Caius Popilius, to order the second legion, which
                    was the oldest then in Liguria, together with four thousand foot and two hundred
                    horse, of the Latin nation, to be in Brundusium on the ides of February.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With this fleet, and this army, Cneius
                    Sicinius, being continued a year in command for the purpose, was ordered to take
                    care of the province of Macedon until a new governor should arrive. All these
                    measures, which the senate voted, were vigorously executed; thirty-eight
                    quinqueremes were drawn out of the docks; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Porcius Licinus was appointed to the command, with directions to conduct
                    them to Brundusium, and twelve were sent from Sicily; three commissaries were
                    despatched into Apulia and Calabria, to buy up corn for the fleet and army;
                    these were Sextus Digitius, Titus Juventius, and Marcus Caecilius. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> When all things were in readiness, the praetor,
                    Cneius Sicinius, in his military robes, set out from the city and went to
                    Brundusium. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, Caius Popilius, came home to Rome
                    when the year had almost expired, much later than had been directed by the vote
                    of the senate; to whom it had seemed advantageous to the republic, that
                    magistrates should be elected as soon as possible, when so important a war was
                    impending. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Therefore the consul did not
                    receive a favourable hearing from the senate, when he spoke in the temple of
                    Bellona of his acts among the Ligurians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There
                    were frequent interruptions and questions, why he had not restored to liberty
                    the Ligurians, who had been oppressed by his brother? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The election was held on the day appointed by proclamation,
                    the twelfth before the calends of March. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls chosen were, Publius Licinius Crassus and Caius Cassius Longinus. Next
                    day were elected praetors, Caius Sulpicius Galba, <pb n="1985" xml:id="p.1985"/>
                    Lucius Furius Philus, Lucius Canuleius Dives, Caius Lucre- tius Gallus, Caius
                    Caninius Rebilus, and Lucius Villius Annalis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The provinces decreed to these praetors were, the two civil jurisdictions in
                    Rome, Spain, Sicily, and Sardinia; and one of them was kept disengaged, that he
                    might be employed wherever the senate should direct. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The senate ordered the consuls elect, that, on whatever day
                    they would enter on their office, having sacrificed victims of the larger kind,
                    they should pray to the gods that the war, which the Roman people intended to
                    engage in, might prove fortunate in the issue. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    On the same day the senate passed an order, that the consul, Caius Popilius,
                    should vow games, of ten days' continuance, to Jupiter supremely good and great,
                    with offerings in all the temples, if the commonwealth should remain for ten
                    years in its present state. Pursuant to this vote, the consul made a vow in the
                    Capitol, that the games should be celebrated, and the offerings made, at such
                    expense as the senate should direct, when not less than a hundred and fifty
                    persons were present. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That vow was expressed
                    in terms dictated by Lepidus, the chief pontiff. There died this year, of the
                    public priests, Lucius Aemilius Papus, decemvir of religious rites, and Quintus
                    Fulvius Flaccus, a pontiff who had been censor the year before. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The latter died in a shocking manner: he had
                    received an account, that, of his two sons who were in the army in Illyria, one
                    was dead, and the other labouring under a heavy and dangerous malady: <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> his grief and fears, together, overwhelmed his
                    reason, and his servants, on going into his chamber in the morning, found him
                    hanging by a rope. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> There was a general
                    opinion, that, since his censorship, his understanding had not been sound; and
                    the report was popular, that the resentment of Juno Lacinia, for the spoil
                    committed on her temple, had caused the derangement of his intellects.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius Messala was substituted
                    decemvir in the place of Aemilius; and Cneius Domitius Aenobarbus, though a mere
                    youth, was chosen into the priesthood as pontiff in the room of Fulvius. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this consulate of Publius Licinius and
                    Caius Cassius, not only the city of Rome, but the whole of Italy, with all the
                    kings and states both in Europe and in Asia, had their attention fixed on the
                    approaching war between Rome and Macedon. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not
                    only old hatred, but also recent anger, be- <pb n="1986" xml:id="p.1986"/> cause
                    by the villany of Perseus he had been almost slaughtered like a victim at
                    Delphi, urged Eumenes against him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Prusias,
                    king of Bithynia, resolved to keep clear of hostilities, and to wait the event;
                    for as he did not think it proper to carry arms on the side of the Romans
                    against his wife's brother, so he trusted that, in case of Perseus proving
                    victorious, his favour might be secured through the means of his sister.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Ariarathes, king of Cappadocia, besides
                    having, in his own name, promised aid to the Romans, had, ever since he was
                    allied by affinity to Eumenes, united with him in all his plans, whether of war
                    or peace. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Antiochus indeed entertained designs
                    on the kingdom of Egypt, since he despised the unripe age of Ptolemy, and the
                    inactive disposition of his guardians, and thought that he might, by raising a
                    dispute about Cœlesyria, find sufficient pretext for proceeding to extremities,
                    and carry on a war there without any impediment, while the Roman arms were
                    employed against Macedon: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> yet, by his
                    ambassadors to the senate, and to their ambassadors sent to him, he made the
                    fairest promises. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Ptolemy, on account of his
                    age, was then influenced by the will of others; and his guardians, at the same
                    time while they were preparing for war with Antiochus, to secure possession of
                    Cœlesyria, promised the Romans every support in the war against Macedon.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Masinissa both assisted the Romans with
                    supplies of corn, and prepared to send into the field, to their assistance, a
                    body of troops and a number of elephants, with his son Misagenes. He so arranged
                    his plans as to answer every event that might take place; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> for if success should attend the Romans, he judged that his
                    own affairs would rest in their present state, and that he ought to seek for
                    nothing further, as the Romans would not suffer violence to be offered to the
                    Carthaginians; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and if the power of the
                    Romans, which at that time protected the Carthaginians, should be reduced, then
                    all Africa would be his own. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Gentius, king of
                    Illyria, had indeed given cause of suspicion to the Romans; but he had not yet
                    determined which party to espouse, and it was believed that he would join either
                    one or the other through some sudden impulse of passion, rather than from any
                    rational motive. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Cotys, the Thracian king of
                    the Odrysians, was openly in favour of the Macedonians. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the inclinations of the several
                    kings, while <pb n="1987" xml:id="p.1987"/> in the free nations and states the
                    plebeians, favouring as usual the weaker cause, were almost universally inclined
                    to the Macedonians and their king; but among the nobles might be observed
                    different views. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One party was so warmly
                    devoted to the Romans, that, by the excess of their zeal, they diminished their
                    own influence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of these a few were actuated by
                    their admiration of the justice of the Roman government; but by far the greater
                    number supposed that they would become powerful in their state, if they
                    displayed remarkable exertions. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A second party
                    wished to court the king's favour, as debt, and despair of their affairs, while
                    the same constitution remained, urged them hastily to complete revolution; and
                    others, through a fickleness of temper, followed Perseus as the more popular
                    character. A third party, the wisest and the best, wished, in case of being
                    allowed the choice of a master, to live under the Romans rather than under the
                    king. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Yet, could they have had the free
                    disposal of events, they wished that neither party should become more powerful
                    by the destruction of the other, but rather that, the strength of both being
                    uninjured, peace should continue on that account; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> for thus the condition of their states would be the
                    happiest, as one party would always protect a weak state from any ill treatment
                    intended by the other. Judging thus, they viewed in silence from their safe
                    position the contest between the partisans of the two contending powers.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consuls, having on the day of their
                    entering on office, in compliance with the order of the senate, sacrificed
                    victims of the larger kinds in all the temples where the lectisternium was
                    usually celebrated for <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> the greater part of'
                    the year, and having from them collected omens that their prayers were accepted
                    by the immortal gods, reported to the senate that the sacrifices had been duly
                    performed, and prayers offered respecting the war. The aruspices declared, that
                        <quote> if any new undertaking was intended, it ought to be proceeded in
                        without delay; that victory, triumphs, and extension of empire were
                        portended. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The senate then resolved, that <quote> the
                        consuls should, on the first proper day, propose to the people assembled by
                        centuries, —that whereas Perseus, son of Philip, and king of Macedon,
                        contrary to the league struck with his father, and after Philip's death
                        renewed with himself, had committed hostilities on the allies of Rome, had
                        wasted their lands, and seized their <pb n="1988" xml:id="p.1988"/> towns,
                        and also had formed a design of making war on the Roman people, and had for
                        that purpose prepared arms, troops, and a fleet; unless he gave satisfaction
                        concerning those matters, that war should be proclaimed against him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The question was carried among the commons.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then a decree of the senate was passed,
                    that <quote> the consuls should settle between themselves, or cast lots, for the
                        provinces of Italy and Macedon; that the one to whose lot Macedon fell
                        should seek redress by force of arms from king Perseus, and all who
                        concurred in his designs, unless they made amends to the Roman people.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was ordered that four new legions should be
                    raised, two for each consul. This in particular was assigned to the province of
                    Macedon, that although five thousand foot and two hundred horse were assigned to
                    the other consul's legions, according to the ancient practice, six thousand foot
                    and three hundred horse were ordered to be enlisted for each of the legions that
                    were to serve in Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of the allied
                    troops also, the number was augmented in the army ordered into Macedon, —namely,
                    sixteen thousand foot and eight hundred horse, besides the six hundred horsemen
                    carried thither by Cneius Sicinius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For Italy,
                    twelve thousand foot and six hundred horse of the allies were deemed sufficient.
                    The following remarkable concession was made to the service in Macedon; the
                    consul was authorized to enlist at his option veteran centurions and soldiers,
                    as old as fifty years. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> An unusual mode of
                    proceeding with regard to the military tribunes was also introduced on the same
                    occasion: for the consuls, by direction of the senate, recommended to the
                    people, that, for that year, the military tribunes should not be created by
                    their suffrages; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but that the consuls and
                    praetors should exercise their judgment and discrimination in their selection.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their respective commands were assigned to
                    the praetors in the following manner: he to whose lot it fell to be employed
                    wherever the senate should direct, had orders to go to Brundusium, to the fleet,
                    that he might <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> then review the crews, and,
                    dismissing such men as appeared unfit for the service, enlist in their places
                    sons of freed-men, taking care that two-thirds should be Roman citizens, and the
                    remainder allies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For supplying provisions to
                    the ships and legions, from Sicily and Sardinia, it was resolved, that the
                    praetors <pb n="1989" xml:id="p.1989"/> who obtained the government of those
                    provinces should be enjoined to levy a second tenth on the Sicilians and
                    Sardinians, and that this corn should be conveyed into Macedon, to the army.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The lots gave Sicily to Caius Caninius
                    Rebilus; Sardinia, to Lucius Furius Philus; Spain, to Lucius Canuleius; the city
                    jurisdiction, to Caius Sulpicius Galba; and the foreign, to Lucius Villius
                    Annalis. The lot of Caius Lucretius Gallus was to be employed wherever the
                    senate should direct. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls had a slight dispute, rather than
                    a great contest, about their province. Cassius said, that <quote> he would
                        select Macedon without casting lots, nor could his colleague, without
                        perjury, abide their determination. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When
                        he was praetor, to avoid going to his province, he made oath in the public
                        assembly, that he had sacrifices to perform on stated days, in a stated
                        place, and that they could not be duly performed in his absence; and surely
                        they could no more be performed duly in his absence when he was consul, than
                        when he was praetor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If the senate thought
                        proper to pay more regard to what Publius Licinius wished, in his
                        consulship, than to what he had sworn in his praetorship, he himself, for
                        his part, would at all events be ruled by that body. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the question was put, the senators
                    thought it would be a degree of arrogance in them to refuse a province to him,
                    since the Roman people had not denied him the consulship. They, however, ordered
                    the consuls to cast lots. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Macedonia fell to
                    Publius Licinius, Italy to Caius Cassius. They then cast lots for the legions:
                    when it fell to the lot of the first and third to go over into Macedonia; and of
                    the second and fourth, to remain in Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls held the levy with much greater care than usual. Licinius enlisted even
                    veteran centurions and soldiers; and many of them volunteered, as they saw that
                    those men who had served in the former Macedonian war, or in Asia, had become
                    rich. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the military tribunes cited the
                    centurions, and especially those of the highest rank, twenty-three of them, who
                    had held the first posts, appealed to the tribunes of the people. Two of that
                    body, Marcus Fulvius Nobilior and Marcus Claudius Marcellus, wished to refer the
                    matter to the consuls; <quote> the cognizance of it ought to rest with those to
                        whom the levy and the war were intrusted: </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but the rest declared, that <pb n="1990"
                        xml:id="p.1990"/> since the appeal had been made to them, they would examine
                    into the affair; and, if there were any injustice in the case, would support
                    their fellow-citizens. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The business, therefore, came into the court
                    of the tribunes. Thither Marcus Popilius, a man of consular dignity, the
                    centurions, and the consul came. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul
                    then required that the matter might be discussed in a general assembly; and,
                    accordingly, the people were summoned. On the side of the centurions, Marcus
                    Popilius, who had been consul two years before, argued thus: that <quote> as
                        military men they had served out their regular time, and that they possessed
                        bodies worn out through age and continual hardships. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Nevertheless, they did not refuse to give the public
                        the benefit of their services, they only entreated that they might be
                        favoured so far, that posts inferior to those which they had formerly held
                        in the army should not be assigned to them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul, Publius Licinius, first ordered
                    the decree of the senate to be read, in which war was determined against
                    Perseus; and then the other, which directed that as many veteran centurions as
                    could be procured should be enlisted for that war; and that no exemption from
                    the service should be allowed to any who was not upwards of fifty years of age.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then entreated that, <quote> at a time
                        when a new war was breaking out so near to Italy, and with a most powerful
                        king, they would not either obstruct the military tribunes in making the
                        levies, or prevent the consul from assigning to each person such a post as
                        best suited the convenience of the public; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        and that, if any doubt should arise in the proceedings, they might refer it
                        to the decision of the senate. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consul had said all that he thought
                    proper, Spurius Ligustinus, one of those who had appealed to the plebeian
                    tribunes, requested permission from the consul and tribunes to speak a few words
                    to the people. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By the permission of them all
                    he spoke, we are told, to this effect: <quote> Romans, I am Spurius Ligustinus,
                        of the Crustuminian tribe, and sprung from the Sabines. My father left me
                        one acre of land, and a small cottage, in which I was born and educated, and
                        I dwell there to-day. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As soon as I came to
                        man's estate, my father married me to his brother's daughter, who brought
                        nothing with her but independence and modesty; except, indeed, a degree of
                        fruitfulness that would have better suited <pb n="1991" xml:id="p.1991"/> a
                        wealthier family. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We have six sons and two
                        daughters; the latter are both married; of our sons, four are grown up to
                        manhood, the other two are as yet boys. I became a soldier in the consulate
                        of Publius Sulpicius and Caius Aurelius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        In the army which was sent over into Macedon I served as a common soldier,
                        against Philip, for two years; and in the third year, Titus Quintius
                        Flamininus, in reward of my good conduct, gave me the command of the tenth
                        company of spearmen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When Philip and the
                        Macedonians were subdued, and we were brought back to Italy and discharged,
                        I immediately went as a volunteer, with the consul Marcus Porcius into
                        Spain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Those who have had experience of
                        him, and of other generals in a long course of service, know that no single
                        commander living was a more accurate observer and judge of merit. This
                        commander judged me deserving of being set at the head of the first company
                        of spearmen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A third time I entered as a
                        volunteer in the army which was sent against the Aetolians and king
                        Antiochus; and Manius Acilius gave me the command of the first company of
                        first-rank men. After Antiochus was driven out of the country, and the
                        Aetolians were reduced, we were brought home to Italy, where I served the
                        two succeeding years in legions that were raised annually. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> I afterwards made two campaigns in Spain; one under
                        Quintus Fulvius Flaccus, the other under Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus,
                        praetors. I was brought by Flaccus among others whom he brought home from
                        the province to attend his triumph, out of regard to their good services.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At the request of Tiberius Gracchus,
                        I went with him to his province. Four times within a few years was I first
                        centurion of my corps; thirty-four times I was honoured by my commanders
                        with presents for bravery. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I have
                        received six civic crowns, I have fulfilled twenty-two years of service in
                        the army, and I am upwards of fifty years of age. But, if I had neither
                        served out all my campaigns, nor was entitled to exemption on account of my
                        age, yet Publius Licinius, as I can supply you with four soldiers instead of
                        myself, it were reasonable that I should be discharged. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> But I wish you to consider these words merely as a
                        state of my case; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> as to offering any
                        thing as an excuse from service, that is what I will never do, so long as
                        any officer, enlisting troops, shall believe me fit for it. What rank the
                        military tribunes may think I deserve, rests with their power. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> That no one in the <pb n="1992" xml:id="p.1992"
                        /> army may surpass me in a zealous discharge of duty, I shall use my best
                        endeavours; and that I have always acted on that principle, my commanders
                        and my comrades can testify. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And now,
                        fellow-soldiers, you who assert your privilege of appeal, as you have never,
                        in your youthful days, done any act contrary to the directions of the
                        magistrates and the senate, now too you ought to be amenable to the
                        authority of the senate and consuls, and to think every post honourable in
                        which you can act for the defence of the commonwealth. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having finished his speech, he was highly
                    commended by the consul, who led him from the assembly into the senate- house,
                    where, by order of the senate, he again received public thanks; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and the military tribunes, in consideration of his
                    meritorious behaviour, made him first centurion in the first legion. The rest of
                    the centurions, dropping the appeal, submissively answered to their names in the
                    levy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That the magistrates might the sooner go
                    into their provinces, the Latin festival was celebrated on the calends of June;
                    and as soon as that solemnity was ended, Caius Lucretius, the praetor, after
                    sending forward every thing requisite for the fleet, went to Brundusium.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Besides the armies which the consuls were
                    forming, Caius Sulpicius Galba, the praetor, was commissioned to raise four city
                    legions, with the regular number of foot and horse, and to choose out of the
                    senate four military tribunes to command them; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    likewise, to require from the Latin allies fifteen thousand foot, with twelve
                    hundred horse; that this army should be prepared to act wherever the senate
                    should order. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At the desire of the consul,
                    Publius Licinius, the following auxiliaries were ordered to join the army of
                    citizens and allies under his command: two thousand Ligurians; a body of Cretan
                    archers (whose number was not specified, the order only mentioning whatever
                    succours the Cretans, on being applied to, should send); likewise the Numidian
                    cavalry and elephants. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To settle concerning
                    these last, ambassadors were sent to Masinissa and the Carthaginians, — Lucius
                    Postumius Albinus, Quintus Terentius Culleo, and Caius Aburius: also, to Crete,
                    —Aulus Postumius Albinus, Caius Decimius, and Aulus Licinius Nerva. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this time arrived ambassadors from Perseus.
                    It was the pleasure of the fathers that they should not be permitted to come
                    into the city; as the senate had already <pb n="1993" xml:id="p.1993"/> decreed,
                    and the people had ordered, a declaration of war against their king and the
                    Macedonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Being introduced before the
                    senate in the temple of Bellona, they spoke in the following manner: that
                        <quote> king Perseus wondered what could be their motive for transporting
                        troops into Macedon; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that if the
                        senate could be prevailed on to recall them, the king would, at their
                        arbitration, satisfactorily account for any injuries of which their allies
                        might complain. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Spurius Carvilius had been sent home from
                    Greece, by Cneius Sicinius, for the purpose of attending this business, and was
                    present in the senate. He charged the king with taking military occupation of
                    Perrhaebia, storming several cities of Thessaly, and other enterprises, in which
                    he was either actually employed or preparing to engage; and the ambassadors were
                    called on to answer to those points. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After
                    they declined to do so, declaring that they had no further instructions, they
                    were ordered to tell their king, that <quote> the consul Publius Licinius would
                        soon be in Macedon at the head of an army. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        To him he might send ambassadors, if he were disposed to give satisfaction,
                        but there was no use in his sending any more to Rome; for none of them would
                        be permitted to pass through Italy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After they were thus dismissed, a charge was
                    given to Publius Sicinius, to insist on their quitting Italy within eleven days,
                    and to send Spurius Carvilius to guard them, until they embarked. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Such were the transactions at Rome, before the
                    departure of the consuls for their provinces. Cneius Sicinius, who, before the
                    expiration of his office, had been sent to Brundusium to the fleet and army, had
                    by this time transported into Epirus five thousand foot and three hundred horse,
                    and was encamped at Nymphaeum, in the territory of Apollonia. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> From which place he sent tribunes, with two thousand men,
                    to take possession of the forts of the Dassaretians and Illyrians; as those
                    people themselves solicited garrisons, to secure them from the inroads of the
                    Macedonians in their neighbourhood. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days after, Quintus Marcius, Aulus
                    Atilius, Publius Cornelius Lentulus, Servius Cornelius Lentulus, and Lucius
                    Decimius, who were sent ambassadors to Greece, carried with them one thousand
                    soldiers to Corcyra; where they divided the troops among them, and settled what
                    districts they were to visit. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Decimius was
                    sent to Gentius, king of Illyria, <pb n="1994" xml:id="p.1994"/> with
                    instructions to sound him, as to whether he retained any regard for former
                    friendship; and even to prevail on him to take part in the war. The two
                    Lentuluses were sent to Cephallenia, that they might cross over from it into
                    Peloponnesus; and, before the winter, make a circuit round the western coast.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The circuit of Epirus, Aetolia, and
                    Thessaly is intrusted to Marcius and Atilius; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    they were directed to take a view afterwards of Bœotia and Eubœa, and then to
                    pass over to Peloponnesus, where, by appointment, they were to meet the
                    Lentuluses. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Before they set out on their
                    several routes from Corcyra, a letter was brought from Perseus, in which he
                    inquired the reason of the Romans sending troops into Greece, and taking
                    possession of the cities. They did not think proper to give him any answer in
                    writing; but they told his messenger, who brought the letter, <quote>for the
                        sake of guarding the cities themselves.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Lentuluses, going round the cities of
                    Peloponnesus, after exhorting all the states, without distinction, as they had
                    assisted the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Romans with fidelity and
                    spirit, first in the war with Philip, and then in that with Antiochus, to assist
                    them now, in like manner, against Perseus, heard some murmuring in the
                    assemblies; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> for the Achaeans were highly
                    offended that they, who, from the very first rise of the war with Macedon, had
                    given every instance of friendship to the Romans, and had been open enemies to
                    the Macedonians in the war with Philip, should be treated on the same footing
                    with the Messenians and Elians, who had borne arms on the side of Antiochus
                    against the Roman people, and who, being lately incorporated in the Achaean
                    union, made heavy complaints, as if they were <milestone n="9??" unit="section"
                    /> made over to the victorious Achaeans as a prize. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Marcius and Atilius went up to Gitanae, a
                    town of Epirus, about ten miles from the sea, a council of Epirotes being held
                    there, they were listened to with universal approbation; and they sent thence
                    four hundred young men of that country to Orestae, to protect those whom they
                    had freed from the dominion of the Macedonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> From this place they proceeded into Aetolia; where, having waited a few days,
                    until a praetor was chosen, in the room of one who had died, and the election
                    having fallen on Lyciscus, who was well known to be a friend to the interest of
                    the Romans, they passed over into Thessaly. The envoys of the Acarnanians and
                    the exiles <pb n="1995" xml:id="p.1995"/> of the Bœotians came thither.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Acarnanians had orders to represent
                    that <quote> whatever offences they had been guilty of towards the Romans, first
                        in the war with Philip, and afterwards in that with Antiochus, in
                        consequence of being misled by the professions of those kings, they had
                        found an opportunity to expiate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Since in
                        spite of their demerits they had experienced the clemency of the Roman
                        people, so they would now, by their endeavours to merit favour, make trial
                        of its generosity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Bœotians were upbraided with having united
                    themselves in alliance with Perseus; but they threw the blame on Ismenias, the
                    leader of a party, and alleged, that <quote>several states were drawn into that
                        measure, contrary to their own judgment:</quote> to which Marcius replied,
                    that <quote> this would appear, as they intended to give to every one of the
                        states the power of judging for itself. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The council of the Thessalians was held at
                    Larissa. There too the Thessalians had a wide field for giving thanks to the
                    Romans for the blessing of liberty conferred on them; and the ambassadors,
                    because they had been vigorously assisted by the Thessalians in the wars with
                    Philip and Antiochus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The feelings of the
                    assembly were acted on by this mutual acknowledgment of favours to such a degree
                    that they voted every measure which the Romans wished. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Soon after this meeting, ambassadors arrived from king
                    Perseus, chiefly through reliance on a connexion of hospitality subsisting
                    between him and Marcius, which had existed between their fathers. The
                    ambassadors began by reminding him of this bond of amity, and then requested him
                    to give the king an opportunity of conferring with him. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Marcius answered, that <quote> he had received from his
                        father the same account of the friendship and hospitable connexion between
                        him and Philip; and the consideration of that connexion induced him to
                        undertake the present embassy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> That he
                        would not have so long delayed giving the king a meeting, could it have been
                        done without inconvenience; and that now he and his colleague would, as soon
                        as it should be in their power, come to the river Peneus, where the passage
                        was from Omolium to Dium; messengers being previously sent to announce it to
                        the king. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus, on this, withdrew from Dium into the
                    heart of the kingdom, having conceived a slight inspiration of hope from the
                    expression of Marcius, that he had undertaken the <pb n="1996" xml:id="p.1996"/>
                    embassy out of regard to him. After a few days they all met at the appointed
                    place. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king's suite was a large one, since
                    a crowd of friends attended him, as well as his body-guards. The ambassadors
                    came with a train not inferior in numbers, as many accompanied them from
                    Larissa, and also the delegates of many states, who had met them there, wishing
                    to carry home information on the positive testimony of what they themselves
                    should hear. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All men felt a strong curiosity
                    to behold a meeting between so powerful a king, and the ambassadors of the first
                    people in the world. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After they came within
                    sight, on the opposite sides of the river, some time was spent in sending
                    messengers from one to the other, to settle which of the two should cross it;
                    for one party thought the compliment due to royal majesty, the other to the fame
                    of the Roman people, especially as Perseus had requested the conference.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcius by a jest roused them from their
                    delay: — <quote>Let the younger,</quote> said he, <quote>cross over to the
                        elder; the son to the father:</quote> for his own surname was Philip. The
                    king was easily persuaded to comply; but then another perplexity arose, about
                    the number he should bring over with him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                    thought it would be proper to be attended by his whole retinue; but the
                    ambassadors required that he should either come with three attendants only, or
                    if he brought so great a band, that he should give hostages that no treachery
                    should be used during the conference. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                    accordingly sent as hostages Hippias and Pantaucus, two of his particular
                    friends, and whom he had sent as ambassadors. The hostages were demanded not so
                    much to get a pledge of good faith, as to make it apparent to the allies, that
                    the king did not meet the ambassadors on a footing of equal dignity. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Their salutations were not like those between
                    enemies, but kind and friendly; and seats being placed for them, they sat down
                    together. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After a short silence, Marcius began thus: —
                        <quote> I suppose you expect us to give an answer to your letter sent to
                        Corcyra, in which you ask the reason, why we ambassadors come attended by
                        soldiers, and why we send garrisons into the cities? <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> To this your question I dread either to refuse an
                        answer, lest it should appear haughty in me, or to give a true one, lest, to
                        your ears, it might seem too harsh. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But
                        since the person who infringes a treaty must be reproved, either <pb
                            n="1997" xml:id="p.1997"/> with words or with arms, as I could wish that
                        the war against you had been intrusted to any other rather than to myself,
                        so I will undergo the task, however disagreeable, of uttering rough language
                        against my friend, as physicians, when they, for the recovery of health,
                        sometimes apply painful remedies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        senate is of opinion that, since you came to the throne, you have acted but
                        in one particular as you ought to have done, and that is, in sending
                        ambassadors to Rome to renew <hi rend="italics"> the treaty made with your
                            father, —and yet it would have been better never to have renewed it,
                        </hi> (they think,) than afterwards to violate it. You expelled from his
                        throne Abrupolis, an ally and friend of the Roman people. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> You gave refuge to the murderers of Artetarus, that it
                        might appear that you were pleased at his assassination, to say nothing
                        worse; though they put to death a prince, who, of all the Illyrians, was the
                        most faithful to the Roman nation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You
                        marched with an army through Thessaly and the Malian territory to Delphi,
                        contrary to the treaty. You likewise, in violation of it, sent succours to
                        the Byzantians. You concluded by an oath a separate alliance with the
                        Bœotians our confederates, which you had no right to do. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As to Eversa and Callicritus, the Theban ambassadors,
                        who were slain in returning from Rome, I wish rather to inquire who were
                        their murderers, than to charge any one of the crime. To whom else than your
                        agents can the civil war in Aetolia, and the deaths of the principal
                        inhabitants, be imputed? The country of the Dolopians was ravaged by you in
                        person. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> King Eumenes, when he was
                        returning from Rome to his own dominions, was almost butchered, as a victim,
                        at the altars in consecrated ground, at Delphi, and it grieves me to know
                        the person whom he accuses. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> With regard to
                        the secret crimes which the host at Brundusium states in his communication,
                        I take it for certain, that all the particulars were written you from Rome,
                        and that your ambassadors reported them to you. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> There was one way by which you might have avoided my
                        speaking of these matters, which was, by not inquiring why we brought troops
                        into Macedonia, or sent garrisons into the cities of our allies. When you
                        had asked the question, it would have been more haughty to keep silence,
                        than to answer according to truth. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Out of
                        regard to the friendship derived to us from our fathers, I am really
                        disposed to listen favourably to whatever you may <pb n="1998"
                            xml:id="p.1998"/> say, and wish that you may afford me some grounds of
                        pleading your cause before the senate. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this the king answered, —"A cause which
                    would approve itself good if tried before impartial judges, I must plead before
                    judges who are at the same time my accusers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Of the circumstances laid to my charge, some are of such a nature that I know
                    not whether I ought not to glory in them; others there are which I would not
                    blush to confess; and others, which as they are backed by bare assertions, it
                    will be sufficient to deny. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Supposing that I
                    were this day to stand a trial, according to your laws, what does either the
                    Brundusian informer, or Eumenes, allege against me that would be deemed a
                    well-founded accusation, and not rather a malicious aspersion? Had Eumenes
                    (although both in his public and private capacity he has done many grievous
                    injuries to so many people) no other enemy than me? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Could I not find a better agent for the perpetration of
                    wickedness than Rammius, whom I had never seen before, nor had any probability
                    of ever seeing again? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then, I must give an
                    account of the Thebans, who, it is well known, perished by shipwreck; and of the
                    death of Artetarus, with regard to whom nothing more is alleged against me, than
                    that his murderers lived in exile in my dominions. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> I will not object to the injustice of this assumption,
                    provided you will admit it on your side; and will acknowledge that, whatever
                    exiles have taken refuge in Rome or in Italy, you are yourselves abettors of the
                    crimes for which they have been condemned. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If
                    you admit not this principle, as other nations will not, neither will I. In
                    truth, what advantage were it to any one that exile lay within his grasp, if no
                    where was there room for an exile? As soon however as I understood from your
                    representations, that those men were in Macedon, I ordered that search should be
                    made for them, and that they should quit the kingdom; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and I prohibited them for ever from setting foot on my
                    dominions. These accusations are brought against me as if I were a criminal
                    pleading my cause; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the others affect me as a
                    king, and must derive their decision from the treaty which exists between you
                    and me. For if it is thus expressed in that treaty, that even if any one would
                    wage war against me, I am not permitted to protect my kingdom; I must then
                    confess I have infringed it, by defending myself with arms against <pb n="1999"
                        xml:id="p.1999"/> Abrupolis, an ally of the Roman people. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> But, on the other hand, if it is both allowed by the
                    treaty, and is an axiom established by the law of nations, that arms may be
                    repelled by arms; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> how, I pray you, ought I to
                    have acted when Abrupolis had spread devastation over the frontiers of my
                    kingdom as far as Amphipolis, carried off great numbers of free persons, a vast
                    multitude of slaves, and many thousands of cattle? Ought I to have lain quiet,
                    and let him proceed until he came in arms to Pella, into my very palace?
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But, allowing that I avenged my wrongs in
                    a just war, yet he ought not to have been subdued, and made to suffer the evils
                    which occur to the vanquished. Nay, but when I, who was the person attacked,
                    underwent the hazard of all these, how can he, who was the cause of the war,
                    complain if they happened to fall upon himself? <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> As to my having punished the Dolopians by force of arms, I mean not, Romans,
                    to defend myself in the same manner; because, whether they deserved that
                    treatment or not, I acted in right of my own sovereign authority: for they were
                    under my sovereign power and dominion, annexed to my father's territories by
                    your decree. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Nor, even if I were to give an
                    account of my conduct, I do not say to you, nor my other confederates, but even
                    to such as disapprove of a severe and unjust exercise of authority, even over
                    slaves, would I appear to have carried my severity against them beyond the
                    limits of justice and equity; for they slew Euphranor, the governor whom I had
                    set over them, in such a manner, that death was the slightest of his sufferings. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> But, when I proceeded to visit Larissa, Antron, and Pteleos, (that I
                        might be within a convenient distance to pay vows, due long before,) I went
                        up to Delphi, in order to offer sacrifice; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        and here, with the purpose of aggravating the imputed guilt, it is
                        subjoined, that I went with an army, with intent to do what I now complain
                        of your doing, —to seize the towns, and put garrisons in the citadels.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now, call together, in assembly, the
                        states of Greece, through which I marched; and if any one person complain of
                        ill treatment, offered by a soldier of mine, I will not deny that I may
                        appear, under a pretence of sacrificing, to have had a different object.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We sent aid to the Aetolians and
                        Byzantians, and made a treaty of friendship with the Bœotians. These
                        proceedings, of whatever nature they may be, have been repeatedly avowed by
                        my ambas- <pb n="2000" xml:id="p.2000"/> sadors; and, what is more, excused
                        before your senate, where I had several of my judges not so favourable as
                        you, Quintus Marcius, my paternal friend and guest. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But at that time, my accuser, Eumenes, had not come to
                        Rome; one who, by misrepresenting and distorting every occurrence, rendered
                        it suspicious and odious, and endeavoured to persuade you that Greece could
                        not be in a state of freedom, nor enjoy your kindness, while the kingdom of
                        Macedon subsisted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The wheel will come
                        round; people will soon be found who will insist, that Antiochus was in vain
                        removed beyond the mountains of Taurus; that Eumenes is more burdensome to
                        Asia than Antiochus was; and that your allies can never enjoy peace so long
                        as there is a palace at Pergamus: for this was raised as a citadel over the
                        heads of the neighbouring states. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quintus
                        Marcius and Aulus Atilius, I am aware that the charges which were made by
                        you, and my reply to them, will have just so much weight as the ears and the
                        tempers of the hearers are disposed to allow them to have; and that the
                        question what I have done, or with what intention, is not of so much
                        importance, as what construction you may put on what has been done.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I am conscious to myself that I have
                        not, knowingly, done wrong; and that, if I have done any wrong, erring
                        through imprudence, I am capable of receiving correction and reformation
                        from these reproofs. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I have certainly
                        committed no fault that is incurable, or deserving punishment by war and
                        plunder: for surely the fame of your clemency and consistency of conduct,
                        spread over the world, is ill-founded, if, on such causes as are scarcely
                        deserving of complaint or expostulation, you take up arms against kings in
                        alliance with you. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As he uttered these words with the apparent
                    approbation of the ambassadors, Marcius advised him to send ambassadors to Rome,
                    as he thought it best to try every expedient to the last, and to omit nothing
                    that might afford any prospect of peace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    consideration still remained, how the ambassadors might travel with safety; and
                    although, to this end, it was necessary that the king should ask a truce, which
                    Marcius wished for, and in fact had no other view in consenting to the
                    conference, yet he granted it with apparent reluctance, and as a great favour to
                    the persons requesting it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At that juncture
                    the Romans had not made sufficient preparations for war; they had no army, no
                    general: whereas Perseus had every <pb n="2001" xml:id="p.2001"/> ## thing
                    prepared and ready; and if a delusive hope of peace had not blinded his
                    judgment, he might have commenced hostilities at a time most advantageous to
                    himself and distressing to his enemies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the
                    breaking up of this conference, (the truce being ratified by both parties,) the
                    Roman ambassadors bent their route towards Bœotia, where great commotions were
                    now beginning; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> for several of the states
                    withdrew themselves from the union of the general confederacy of the Bœotians,
                    from the time that the answer of the ambassadors was announced, that <quote> it
                        would appear what particular states were displeased at the formation of the
                        alliance with the king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First deputies from Chaeronea, then others
                    from Thebes, met the Romans on the road, and assured them, that they were not
                    present in the council wherein that alliance was resolved on. The ambassadors,
                    giving them no answer at the time, ordered that they should go with them to
                    Chalcis. At Thebes a violent dissension arose out of another contest. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The party defeated in the election of praetors of
                    Bœotia, resolving to revenge the affront, collected the multitude, and passed a
                    decree at Thebes, that the new Bœotarchs should not be admitted into the cities.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All the persons thus exiled betook
                    themselves to Thespiae; being recalled from it (for they were received there
                    without hesitation) to Thebes, owing to a change in the minds of the people,
                    they passed a decree that the twelve persons who, without being invested with
                    public authority, had held an assembly and council, should be punished by
                    banishment: and afterwards the new praetor, (he was Ismenias, a man of
                    distinction and power,) by another decree, condemns them, although absent, to
                    capital punishment. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They had fled to Chalcis;
                    and thence they proceeded to Larissa, to the Romans, and threw on Ismenias alone
                    the blame of the alliance concluded with Perseus, asserting that the contest
                    originated in a party dispute; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> yet
                    ambassadors from both sides waited on the Romans, as did the exiles, accusers of
                    Ismenias, and Ismenias himself. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When they were all arrived at Chalcis, the
                    chiefs of the other states, each by a particular decree of their own, renounced
                    the alliance of Perseus, and joined themselves to the Romans, a circumstance
                    which gave very great pleasure to the latter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Ismenias recommended, that the Bœotian nation should be placed under the orders
                    of Rome; on which so <pb n="2002" xml:id="p.2002"/> violent a dispute arose,
                    that, if he had not fled for shelter to the tribunal of the ambassadors, he
                    would not have <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> been far from losing his life
                    by the hands of the exiles and their abettors. Thebes itself, the capital of
                    Bœotia, was in a violent ferment, one party struggling hard to bring the state
                    over to the king, the other to the Romans; and multitudes had come together,
                    from Coronae and Haliartus, to support the decree in favour of Perseus.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But by the firmness of the chiefs, (who
                    desired them to judge, from the defeats of Philip and Antiochus, how great must
                    be the power and fortune of the Roman empire,) the same multitude was overcome,
                    and not only resolved that the alliance with the king should be cancelled, but
                    also, to gratify the ambassadors, sent the promoters of that alliance to
                    Chalcis; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and ordered, that the state should be
                    recommended to the protection of the Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Marcius and Atilius heard the Thebans with joy, and advised both them and each
                    state separately to send ambassadors to Rome to renew the treaty. They required,
                    above all things, that the exiles should be restored; and condemned by their own
                    decree the advisers of the treaty with the king. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Having thus disunited the members of the Bœotian council, which was their
                    grand object, they proceeded to Peloponnesus, after summoning Servius Cornelius
                    to Chalcis. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> An assembly was summoned to meet
                    them at Argos, where they demanded nothing more from the Achaeans, than the
                    furnishing of one thousand soldiers, which were sent as a garrison to defend
                    Chalcis until a Roman army should come into Greece. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcius and Atilius having finished the
                    business that was to be done in Greece, returned to Rome in the beginning of
                    winter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> An embassy had been despatched thence,
                    about the same time, into Asia, to the several islands. The ambassadors were
                    three; Tiberius Claudius, Publius Postumius, and Marcus Junius. These, making a
                    circuit among the allies, exhorted them to undertake the war against Perseus, in
                    conjunction with the Romans; and the more powerful any state was, the more
                    earnestly they requested them, judging that the smaller states would follow the
                    lead of the greater. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Rhodians were
                    esteemed of the utmost consequence on every account; because they could not only
                    countenance the war, but also assist in it by their own strength, having,
                    pursuant to the advice of Hegesilochus, forty ships ready for sea. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="2003" xml:id="p.2003"/> This man being chief magistrate, whom they call
                    Prytanis, had, by many arguments, prevailed on the Rhodians to banish the hope
                    of courting the favour of kings, which they had, in repeated instances, found
                    fallacious; and to maintain firmly the alliance with Rome (which was the only
                    one in the earth that could be relied on for strength or honour). He told them,
                    that <quote> a war was upon the point of breaking out with Perseus: <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> that the Romans would expect the same naval
                        armament which they had seen lately in that with Antiochus, and formerly in
                        that with Philip: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that they would be
                        hurried, in the hasty equipment of a fleet, when it ought to be sent at
                        once, unless they immediately set about the repairing and manning of their
                        ships: and that they ought to do this with the greatest diligence, in order
                        to refute, by the evidence of facts, the imputations thrown on them by
                        Eumenes. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Roused by these arguments, they showed to the
                    Roman ambassadors, on their arrival, a fleet of forty ships rigged and fitted
                    out, so that it might appear that they did not require to be urged. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> This embassy had great effect in conciliating the
                    affections of the states in Asia. Decimius alone returned to Rome without
                    effecting any thing, and disgraced by the suspicion of having received money
                    from the Illyrian kings. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Perseus, after the conference with the
                    Romans, had retired into Macedon, he sent ambassadors to Rome to carry on the
                    negotiation for peace commenced with Marcius, giving them letters, to be
                    delivered at Byzantium and Rhodes. The purport of the letters to all was the
                    same, viz. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that he had conferred with the
                    Roman ambassadors. What he had heard from them, and what he had said, was,
                    however, represented in such a manner that he might seem to have had the
                    advantage in the debate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In presence of the
                    Rhodians, the ambassadors added, that <quote> they were confident of a
                        continuation of peace, for it was by the advice of Marcius and Atilius that
                        they were sent to Rome. But if the Romans should commence their hostilities,
                        contrary to treaty, it would then be the business of the Rhodians to labour,
                        with all their power and all their interest, for the re-establishment of
                        peace; and that, if they should effect nothing by their mediation, they
                        ought then to take such measures as would prevent the dominion of the whole
                        world from coming into the hands of one nation only. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> That, as this was a matter of general concern, so it
                            <pb n="2004" xml:id="p.2004"/> was peculiarly interesting to the
                        Rhodians, as they surpassed the other states in dignity and power, which
                        must be held on terms of servility and dependence, if there were no other
                        resource for redress than the Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both the letter and the discourse of the
                    ambassadors were received by the Rhodians with every appearance of kindness, but
                    by no means exerted any influence in working a change in their minds, for by
                    this time the best-judging party had the superior influence. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> By a public order this answer was given: —that <quote> the
                        Rhodians wished for peace; but, if war should take place, they hoped that
                        the king would not expect or require from them any thing that might break
                        off their ancient friendship with the Romans, the fruit of many and great
                        services performed on their part both in war and peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Macedonians, on their way home from
                    Rhodes, visited also the states of Bœotia, Thebes, Coronaea, and Haliartus; for
                    it was thought that the measure of abandoning the alliance with the king, and
                    joining the Romans, was extorted from them against their will. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The Thebans were not influenced by his representations,
                    though they were somewhat displeased with the Romans, on account of the sentence
                    passed on their nobles, and the restoration of the exiles; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> but the Coronaeans and Haliartians, out of a kind of
                    natural attachment to kings, sent ambassadors to Macedon, requesting the aid of
                    a body of troops to defend them against the insolent tyranny of the Thebans.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To this application the king answered,
                    that, <quote> on account of the truce concluded with the Romans, it was not in
                        his power to send troops; but he recommended to them, to guard themselves
                        against ill-treat- ment from the Thebans, as far as they were able, without
                        affording the Romans a pretext for venting their resentment on him. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Marcius and Atilius returned to Rome,
                    they reported in the Capitol the result of their embassy, in such a manner that
                    they assumed no greater merit for any one matter, than for having overreached
                    the king by the suspension of arms, and the hope of peace given him; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> for <quote>he was so fully provided,</quote> they
                    said, <quote> with every requisite for the immediate commencement of war, while
                        on their side no one thing was in readiness, that all the convenient posts
                        might have been pre-occupied by him before an army could be transported into
                        Greece; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but, by gaining so much time by
                        the truce, the <pb n="2005" xml:id="p.2005"/> Romans would begin the war
                        better provided with every thing; whereas he would come into the field in no
                        respect better prepared. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They mentioned, also, that <quote> they had so
                        effectually disunited by stratagem the members of the Bœotian council, that
                        they could never again, with any degree of unanimity, connect themselves
                        with the Macedonians. </quote> A great part of the senate approved of these
                    proceedings, as conducted with consummate wisdom; but the older members, and
                    those who retained the ancient simplicity of manners, declared, that <quote> in
                        the conduct of that embassy, they could discover nothing of the Roman
                        genius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their ancestors waged war not by
                        stratagems and attacks in the night, nor by counterfeiting flight and
                        returning unexpectedly on an unguarded foe, nor in such a manner as to glory
                        in cunning more than in real valour. That they were accustomed to proclaim
                        war before they waged it, that they sometimes appointed the day of battle
                        and marked out the ground on which they were to fight. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That with the same honourable feeling information was
                        given to king Pyrrhus of his physician plotting against his life; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> and, from the same motive, they delivered bound,
                        to the Faliscians, the betrayer of their children. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> These were the acts of the Roman law, not resulting
                        from the craft of Carthaginians or the subtlety of Greeks, among whom it is
                        reckoned more glorious to deceive an enemy than to overcome him by force.
                        Sometimes greater present advantages may be acquired by artifice than by
                        bravery. But an adversary's spirit is finally subdued for ever, when the
                        confession has been extorted from him, that he was vanquished, not by
                        artifice, nor by chance, but in a just and open war, in a fair trial of
                        strength hand to hand. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such were the sentiments of the elder members,
                    to whom this modern kind of wisdom was displeasing. But that part of the senate
                    who paid more regard to utility than to honour, prevailed, and passed a vote
                    approving of Marcius' conduct in his former embassy; at the same time ordering
                    that he should be sent again into Greece with some ships, and with authority to
                    act in other matters as he should judge most conducive to the public good.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They also sent Aulus Atilius to keep
                    possession of Larissa in Thessaly; fearing lest, on the expiration of the
                    armistice, Perseus might send troops and secure to himself that metropolis.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For the execution of this, Atilius was
                    ordered to receive from Cneius Sicinius two <pb n="2006" xml:id="p.2006"/>
                    thousand infantry. And three hundred soldiers of the Italian race were given to
                    Publius Lentulus, who <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> had returned from
                    Achaia, that he should fix his quarters at Thebes, in order that Bœotia might be
                    kept in obedience. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After these preparations were made, the
                    senate, notwithstanding their determination for war was fixed, yet judged it
                    proper to give audience to the king's ambassadors. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Their discourse was, principally, a repetition of what had
                    been urged by Perseus in the conference. The accusation of laying the ambush
                    against Eumenes was defended with the greatest care, and yet with the least
                    success, for the thing was manifest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The rest
                    consisted of apologies: but their hearers were not in a temper to be either
                    convinced or persuaded. Orders were given them to quit the city of Rome
                    instantly, and Italy within thirty days. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then
                    orders were given to Publius Licinius, the consul, to whose lot the province of
                    Macedon had fallen, to appoint as early as possible the day for assembling the
                    army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Caius Lucretius, the praetor, whose
                    province was the fleet, sailed from the city with forty quinqueremes; for it was
                    judged proper that some of the vessels that were repaired should be kept at Rome
                    for other exigencies. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The praetor sent forward
                    his brother, Marcus Lucretius, with one quinquereme; ordering him to collect
                    from the allies the ships due by treaty, and to join the fleet at Cephalonia.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He received from the Rhegians one trireme,
                    from the Locrians two, and from the Urites four; and then, coasting along the
                    shore of Italy, until he passed the farthest promontory of Calabria, in the
                    Ionian Sea, he shaped his course over to Dyrrachium. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Finding there ten barks belonging to the Dyrrachians,
                    twelve belonging to the Isseans, and fifty-four to king Gentius, affecting to
                    understand that they had been brought thither for the use of the Romans, he
                    carried them all off, and sailed in three days to Corcyra, and thence directly
                    to Cephalonia. The praetor Caius Lucretius set sail from Naples, and, passing
                    the strait, arrived on the fifth day at Cephalonia. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> There the fleet halted, waiting until the land forces
                    should be carried over, and <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> until the
                    transport vessels, which had been separated from the fleet and scattered over
                    the sea, might rejoin it. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time the consul Publius Licinius,
                    after offering vows in the Capitol, marched out of the city in his military
                    robes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This ceremony is always conducted with
                    great <pb n="2007" xml:id="p.2007"/> dignity and solemnity; on this occasion
                    particularly, it engaged people's eyes and thoughts in an unusual degree, —and
                    this, by reason that they escorted the consul against an enemy formidable and
                    conspicuous both for abilities and resources. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For not only their desire to pay him the customary respect, but an earnest wish
                    to behold the show, and see the commander, to whose wisdom and conduct they
                    intrusted the maintenance of the public safety, brought them together.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then such reflections as these entered
                    their minds: <quote> How various were the chances of war; how uncertain the
                        issue of the contest; how variable the success of arms; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> how frequent the vicissitudes of losses and successes;
                        what disasters often happened through the unskilfulness and rashness of
                        commanders; and on the contrary, what advantages their judgment and valour
                        conferred. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What human being could yet know
                        either the capacity or the fortune of the consul whom they were sending
                        against the enemy; whether they were shortly to see him at the head of a
                        victorious army ascending the Capitol in triumph, to revisit the same gods
                        from whom he now took his departure, or whether they were to give a like
                        cause of exultation to their enemies. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then king Perseus, against whom he was going,
                    had a high reputation, derived from the great martial character of the
                    Macedonian nation, and from his father Philip, who, besides many prosperous
                    achievements, had gained a large share of renown even in his war with the
                    Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Besides too, the name of Perseus
                    himself, which had never ceased, since his accession to the throne, to be the
                    subject of conversation, owing to the expectation of the war. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Two military tribunes, of consular rank, Caius Claudius and
                    Quintus Mucius, were sent with him; and three illustrious young men, Publius
                    Lentulus, and two of the name of Manlius Acidinus, one the son of Marcus
                    Manlius, the other of Lucius. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> With these he
                    went to Brundusium to the army; and sailing over thence with all his forces,
                    pitched his camp at Nymphaeum, in the territory of Apollonia. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days before this, Perseus, after the
                    ambassadors returned from Rome, and cut off every hope of peace, held a council,
                    in which a contest was carried on for some time between different opinions.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Some were of opinion that he ought to pay
                    a tribute, or even to cede a part of his dominions, if they should deprive him
                    of that; in short, that he <pb n="2008" xml:id="p.2008"/> ought not to refuse,
                    for the sake of peace, whatever must be submitted to, nor act in such a manner
                    as would expose himself and his kingdom to such a perilous hazard. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> For, <quote> if he retained undisputed possession of
                        the throne, time and the revolution of affairs might produce many
                        conjunctures, which would enable him not only to recover his losses, but to
                        become formidable to those whom he now had reason to dread. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A considerable majority, however, expressed
                    sentiments of a bolder nature. They insisted that <quote> the cession of any
                        part would be followed by that of the whole kingdom. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans were in want of neither money nor territory:
                        but they considered that all human affairs, even kingdoms and empires, are
                        subject to many casualties. They had themselves broken the power of the
                        Carthaginians, and settled in the neighbourhood a very powerful king, as a
                        yoke on their necks, and had removed Antiochus and his future successors
                        beyond the mountains of Taurus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There now
                        remained only the kingdom of Macedonia near in situation, and such as might,
                        if any where the fortune of Rome should waver, inspire its kings with the
                        spirit of their forefathers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Perseus
                        therefore ought, while his affairs were yet in a state of safety, to
                        consider well in his own mind, whether he should prefer to give <milestone
                            n="8??" unit="section"/> up one part of his dominions after another,
                        until at length, stripped of all power and exiled from his kingdom, he
                        should be reduced to beg from the Romans either Samothracia or some other
                        island, where he might grow old in poverty and contempt; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> or, on the other hand, armed in vindication of his
                        fortune and his honour, as is the part of a brave man, either should endure
                        with patience whatever misfortune the chance of war might bring upon him, or
                        by victory deliver the world from the tyranny of Rome. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> There would be nothing more wonderful in the Romans
                        being driven out of Greece, than in Hannibal's being driven out of Italy;
                        nor, in truth, did they see how it could consist with the character of the
                        prince, to resist with the utmost vigour his brother, who unjustly aspired
                        to the crown, and, after he had fairly obtained it himself, surrender it up
                        to foreigners. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Lastly, that war had its
                        vindication as well as peace, so that nothing was accounted more shameful
                        than to yield up a dominion without a struggle, and nothing more glorious
                        than for a prince to have experienced every kind of fortune in the defence
                        of his crown and dignity. </quote>
                    <pb n="2009" xml:id="p.2009"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The council was held at Pella, in the old
                    palace of the Macedonian kings. <quote>Let us then,</quote> Perseus said,
                        <quote>with the help of the gods, wage war, since that is your
                        opinion;</quote> and, despatching letters to all the commanders of the
                    troops, he concentrated his entire force at Cytium, a town of Macedon.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He himself, after making a royal offering
                    of one hundred victims, which he sacrificed to Minerva, called Alcidemos, set
                    out for Cytium, attended by a band of nobles and guards. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> All the forces, both of the Macedonians and foreign
                    auxiliaries, had already assembled in that place. He encamped them before the
                    city, and drew them all up, under arms, in order of battle, in a plain.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The amount of the whole was forty-three
                    thousand armed men; of whom about one half composed the phalanx, and were
                    commanded by Hippias of Berœa; there were then two thousand selected for their
                    superior strength, and the vigour of their age, out of the whole number of their
                    shield-bearers: this legion they called, in their own language, Agema, and the
                    command of them was given to Leonatus and Thrasippus of Eulyea. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Antiphilus of Edessa commanded the rest of the
                    shield-bearers, about three thousand men. Paeonians, and men from Parorea and
                    Parstrymonia, (places subject to Thrace,) with Agrians, and a mixture of some
                    native Thracians, made up the number of about three thousand men. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Didas, the Paeonian, the murderer of young Demetrius,
                    had armed and embodied these. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were two
                    thousand Gallic soldiers, under the command of Asclepiodotus; three thousand
                    independent Thracians, from Heraclea, in the country of the Sintians, had a
                    general of their own. An equal number nearly of Cretans followed their own
                    general, Susus of Phalasarna, and Syllus of Gnossus. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Leonidas, a Lacedaemonian, commanded a body of five hundred
                    Greeks, of various descriptions: this man was said to be of the royal blood, and
                    had been condemned to exile in a full council of the Achaeans on account of a
                    letter to Perseus, which was intercepted. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Lycho, an Achaean, was the commander of the Aetolians and Bœotians, who did not
                    make up more than the number of five hundred men. These auxiliaries, composed of
                    so many states and so many nations, made up about twelve thousand fighting men.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Of cavalry, he had collected from all
                    parts of Macedon, three thousand: and Cotys, son of Seutha, king of the Odrysian
                    nation, was arrived with one thousand chosen horse- <pb n="2010" xml:id="p.2010"
                    /> men, and nearly the same number of foot. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The total number was thirty-nine thousand foot, and four thousand horse. Most
                    certainly, since the army which Alexander the Great led into Asia, no king of
                    Macedonia had ever been at the head of so powerful a force. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now twenty-six years since peace had
                    been granted to the suit of Philip; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and
                    Macedon, having through all that period enjoyed quiet, was become exceedingly
                    populous, and very many were now grown up, and become qualified for the duties
                    of the field; and owing to the unimportant wars with the neighbouring states of
                    Thrace, which had given them exercise rather than fatigue, were in continual
                    practice of military service. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Besides, a war
                    with Rome having been long meditated by, first, Philip, and afterwards by
                    Perseus, had effected that all things should be arranged and prepared.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The troops performed some few movements,
                    but not the regular course of exercise, only that they might not seem to have
                    stood motionless under arms. He then called them, armed as they were, to an
                    assembly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He himself stood on his tribunal,
                    with his two sons, one on each side of him; the elder of whom, Philip, was by
                    birth his brother, his son by adoption; the younger, named Alexander, was his
                    son by birth. The king exhorted his troops to a vigorous prosecution of the war.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He enumerated the injuries offered by the
                    Romans to Philip and himself; told them, that <quote> his father, having been
                        compelled, by every kind of indignity, to resolve on a renewal of
                        hostilities, was, in the midst of his preparations for war, arrested by
                        fate: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that ambassadors were sent by
                        himself at the same time that soldiers were sent to seize the cities of
                        Greece: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> that then, under the pretext of
                        re-establishing peace, they spun out the winter, by means of a fallacious
                        conference, in order to gain time to make their preparations; that their
                        consul was now coming, with two Roman legions, containing each six thousand
                        foot and three hundred horse, and nearly the same number of auxiliaries; and
                        that, should they even be joined by the troops of Eumenes and Masinissa, yet
                        these could not amount to more than seven thousand foot and two thousand
                        horse. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He desired them, <quote> after hearing the
                        number of the enemy's forces, to reflect on their own army, how far it
                        excelled both in number and in the qualifications of the men, a body of raw
                        recruits, enlisted hastily for the present occasion; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> whereas they them- <pb n="2011" xml:id="p.2011"/>
                        selves had from childhood been instructed in the military art, and had been
                        disciplined and inured to toil in a course of many wars. The auxiliaries of
                        the Romans were Lydians, Phrygians, and Numidians; while his were Thracians
                        and Gauls, the bravest nations in the world. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Their troops had such arms as each needy soldier
                        procured for himself; but those of the Macedonians were furnished out of the
                        royal stores, and had been made with much care at the expense of his father,
                        in a course of many years. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They must
                        bring their provisions not only from a great distance, but expose them to
                        all the hazards of the sea; while he, besides his revenue from the mines,
                        had laid up a store, both of money and food, sufficient for the consumption
                        of ten years. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Macedonians possessed
                        in abundance every advantage, in point of preparation, that depended on the
                        kindness of the gods, or the care of their sovereign: they ought therefore
                        to have the same daring spirit which their fathers had before them;
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> who, after subduing all Europe,
                        passed over into Asia, and opened by their arms a world unknown to fame, and
                        never ceased to conquer until they were stopped by the Red Sea, and when
                        nothing remained for them to subdue. But in truth fortune has determined the
                        present struggle to be carried on, not for the far remote regions of India,
                        but for the possession of Macedon itself. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        When the Romans made war on his father, they held out the specious pretence
                        of liberating Greece; now, they avowedly aimed at reducing Macedon to
                        slavery, that there might be no king in the neighbourhood of the Roman
                        empire, and that no nation, renowned in war, should have the possession of
                        arms; <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> for these must be delivered up to
                        their imperious masters, together with the king and kingdom, if they chose
                        to decline a war, and obey their orders. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Notwithstanding that, during the course of his
                    speech, he was frequently interrupted by the exclamations of the multitude; then
                    truly such shouts arose from the army, expressing indignation and menaces
                    against the foe, and urging him to act with spirit, that he put an end to his
                    discourse. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He only ordered them to be ready to
                    march; because it was reported that the Romans were quitting their camp at
                    Nymphaeum; and then, dismissing the assembly, he went to give audience to
                    deputies from the several states of Macedon, who were <milestone n="3??"
                        unit="section"/> come to offer money and corn, in proportion to the <pb
                        n="2012" xml:id="p.2012"/> abilities of each. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He gave thanks to all, but declined their proffers; telling
                    them that the royal stores were sufficient to answer every purpose. Carriages
                    only were demanded for the conveyance of the engines, and the vast quantity of
                    missile weapons that was prepared, with other military implements. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> He then put his army in motion, directing his route
                    to Eordea; and after encamping at the lake Begorrites, advanced, next day, into
                    Elimea, to the river Haliacmon. Then passing the mountains through a narrow
                    defile, called Cambunii, he marched against the inhabitants of the district
                    called Tripolis, consisting of Azoras, Pythios, and Doliche. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> These three towns hesitated, for a little time, because
                    they had given hostages to the Larissaeans; however, being overcome by the fear
                    of immediate danger, they capitulated. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                    received them with expressions of favour, not doubting that the Perrhaebians
                    would be induced to follow their example; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and
                    accordingly, on his first arrival he got possession of their city, without any
                    reluctance being shown on the part of the inhabitants. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He was obliged to use force against Cyretie, and was even
                    repulsed the first day by bodies of armed men, who defended the gates with great
                    bravery; but on the day following, having assaulted the place with all his
                    forces, he received their surrender before night. </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mylae, the next town, was so strongly
                    fortified, that the inhabitants, from the hopes of their works being
                    impregnable, had conceived too great a degree of confidence. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Not content with shutting their gates against the king,
                    they cast insulting reproaches on himself and on the Macedonians, which
                    behaviour, while it provoked the enemy to attack them with greater rancour,
                    kindled a greater ardour in themselves to make a vigorous defence, as they had
                    now no hopes of pardon. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> During three days,
                    therefore, the town was attacked and defended with great spirit. The great
                    number of Macedonians made it easy for them to relieve each other, and to
                    support the fight by turns; not only wounds, but want of sleep and continual
                    labour, were wearing out the besieged, who guarded the walls by day and night.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the fourth day, when the
                    scaling-ladders were raised on all sides, and one of the gates was attacked with
                    unusual force, the townsmen, who were beaten off the walls, ran together to
                    secure the gate, and made a sudden sally. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Since this was the effect rather of in- <pb n="2013" xml:id="p.2013"/>
                    considerate rage than of a well-grounded confidence in their strength, they
                    being few in number, and worn down with fatigue, were routed by men who were
                    fresh; and having turned their backs, and fled through the open gate, they
                    allowed the enemy to enter through it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    city was thus taken, and plundered, and even the persons of free condition who
                    survived the carnage were sold. The king, after dismantling and reducing to
                    ashes the greater part of the town, removed, and encamped at Phalanna; and next
                    day arrived at Gyrton; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but understanding that
                    Titus Minucius Rufus, and Hippias, the praetor of the Thessalians, had gone into
                    the town with a body of troops, he passed by, without even attempting a siege,
                    and received the submission of Elatia and Gonni, whose inhabitants were dismayed
                    by his unexpected arrival. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Both these towns,
                    particularly Gonni, stand at the entrance of the pass which leads to Tempe; he
                    therefore left the latter under a strong guard of horse and foot, and fortified
                    it, besides, with a triple trench and rampart. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Advancing to Sycurium, he determined to wait there the approach of the Romans;
                    at the same time he ordered his troops to collect corn from all parts of the
                    country subject to the enemy: for Sycurium stands at the foot of Mount Ossa, the
                    southern side of which overlooks the plains of Thessaly, and the opposite side
                    Macedonia and Magnesia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Besides these
                    advantages of situation, the place enjoys a most healthful air, and a never
                    failing supply of water, <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> from the numerous
                    springs which lay around. </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time the Roman consul, marching
                    towards Thessaly, at first found the roads of Epirus clear and open; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> but afterwards, when he proceeded into Athamania,
                    where the country is rugged, and almost impassable, with great labour and by
                    short marches he with difficulty reached Gomphi. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> If, while he was leading his raw troops through such a territory, and while
                    both his men and horses were debilitated by constant toil, the king had attacked
                    him with his army in proper order, and at an advantageous place and time, the
                    Romans themselves do not deny that they must have suffered very great loss in an
                    engagement. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they arrived at Gomphi,
                    without opposition, great contempt of the enemy was added to their joy at having
                    effected their passage through such a dangerous road, since they showed such
                    utter ignorance <pb n="2014" xml:id="p.2014"/> of their own advantages.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, after duly offering sacrifice,
                    and distributing corn to the troops, halted a few days, to give rest to the men
                    and horses; and then, hearing that the Macedonians were over-running Thessaly,
                    and wasting the country of the allies, he led on to Larissa his troops, now
                    sufficiently refreshed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Proceeding thence,
                    when he came within about three miles of Tripolis, (they call the place Scaea,)
                    he encamped on the river Peneus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In the mean
                    time, Eumenes arrived by sea at Chalcis, accompanied by his brothers Attalus and
                    Athenaeus, (bringing with him two thousand foot, the command of whom he gave to
                    the latter,) having left his other brother, Philetaerus, at Pergamus to manage
                    the business of his kingdom. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From thence, with
                    Attalus and four thousand foot and one thousand horse, he came and joined the
                    consul: two thousand foot were left at Chalcis, of which Athenaeus had the
                    command: whither also arrived parties of auxiliaries from every one of the
                    states of Greece; but most of them so small, that their numbers have not been
                    transmitted to us. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Apollonians sent three
                    hundred horse and one hundred foot. Of the Aetolians came a number equal to one
                    cohort, being the entire cavalry of the nation; and of the Thessalians (all
                    their cavalry acted separately) not more than three hundred horsemen were in the
                    Roman camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Achaeans furnished one
                    thousand young men, armed mostly in the Cretan manner. </p>
                <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time, Caius Lucretius, the praetor
                    and naval commander at Cephallenia, having ordered his brother, Marcus
                    Lucretius, to conduct the fleet along the coast of Malea to Chalcis, went
                    himself on board a trireme, and sailed to the Corinthian gulf, that he might as
                    early as possible put the affairs of Bœotia on a proper footing; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> but the voyage proved tedious to him, particularly
                    from the weak state of his health. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcus
                    Lucretius, on his arrival at Chalcis, when he heard that Haliartus was besieged
                    by Publius Lentulus, sent a messenger to him, with an order, in the praetor's
                    name, to retire from the place. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    lieutenant-general, who had undertaken this enterprise with Bœotian troops,
                    raised out of the party that sided with the Romans, retired from the walls.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But the raising of this siege only made
                    room for a new one: for Marcus Lucretius immediately invested Haliartus with
                    troops from on board the fleet, amounting to ten thousand effective men, and who
                    were joined by two thousand of the <pb n="2015" xml:id="p.2015"/> forces of king
                    Eumenes, who were under Athenaeus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Just when
                    they were preparing for an assault, the praetor came up from Creusa. At the same
                    time, ships sent by the allies arrived at Chalcis: two Carthaginian
                    quinqueremes, two triremes from Heraclea in Pontus, four from Chalcedon, a like
                    number from Samos, and also five quinqueremes from Rhodes. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The praetor sent back these to the allies, because there
                    was no where a naval war. Quintus Marcius also came to Chalcis with his ships,
                    having taken Alope, and laid siege to Larissa, called likewise Cremaste.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While such was the state of affairs in
                    Bœotia, Perseus, when, as has been mentioned, he lay encamped at Sycurium, after
                    collecting the corn from all the adjacent parts, sent a detachment to ravage the
                    lands of the Pheraeans; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> hoping that the Romans
                    might be drawn away from their camp to succour the cities of their allies, and
                    then be caught at a disadvantage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And when he
                    saw that they were not put in motion by this disorderly expedition, he
                    distributed all the booty, consisting mostly of cattle of all kinds, among the
                    soldiers, that they might feast themselves with plenty. The prisoners he kept. </p>
                <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both the consul and the king held councils
                    nearly at the same time, to determine in what manner they should begin their
                    operations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king assumed fresh confidence,
                    from the enemy having allowed him, without interruption, to ravage the country
                    of the Pheraeans: and in consequence, resolved to advance directly to their
                    camp, and give them no further time for delay. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On the other side, the Romans were convinced that their inactivity had created a
                    mean opinion of them in the minds of their allies, who were exceedingly offended
                    that aid was not borne to the Pheraeans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While
                    they were deliberating how they should act, (Eumenes and Attalus were present in
                    the council,) a messenger in a violent hurry acquainted them that the enemy were
                    approaching in a great body. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On this the
                    council was dismissed, and an order to take arms instantly issued. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> It was also resolved, that in the mean time a party
                    of Eumenes' troops, consisting of one hundred horse, and an equal number of
                    javelin-bearers on foot, should go put to observe the enemy. Perseus, about the
                    fourth hour of the day, being nearly one thousand paces from the Roman camp,
                    ordered the body of his infantry to halt, and advanced himself in front, with
                    the cavalry and light <pb n="2016" xml:id="p.2016"/> infantry, accompanied by
                    Cotys and the other generals of the auxiliaries. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> They were less than five hundred paces distant, when they descried the Roman
                    horse, which consisted of two cohorts, mostly Gauls, commanded by Cassignatus,
                    and attended by about one hundred and fifty light infantry, Mysians and Cretans.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The king halted, as he knew not the force
                    of the enemy. He then sent forward two troops of Thracians, and two of
                    Macedonians, with two cohorts of Cretans and Thracians. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The fight, as the parties were equal in number, and no
                    reinforcements were sent upon either side, ended without any decided advantage.
                    About thirty of Eumenes' men were killed, among whom fell Cassignatus, general
                    of the Gauls. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Perseus then led back his
                    forces to Sycurium, and the next day, about the same hour, brought up his army
                    to the same ground, and a number of waggons carrying water followed him; for the
                    road for twelve miles had no water, and was very full of dust: and it was
                    apparent that if they came to an engagement on the first view of the enemy, they
                    would be greatly distressed in the fight by thirst. When the Romans remained
                    quiet, and even called in the advanced guards within the rampart; the king's
                    troops returned to their camp. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In this manner
                    they acted for several days, still hoping that the Roman cavalry might attack
                    their rear on their retreat, which would bring on a battle; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> considering, likewise, that when they had once enticed the
                    Romans to some distance from their camp, they could, being superior in both
                    cavalry and light infantry, easily, and in any spot, face about upon them. </p>
                <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this design did not succeed, the king
                    moved his camp nearer the enemy, and fortified it at the distance of five miles
                    from the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From it at the dawn of the
                    next day, having drawn up his line of infantry on the same ground as before, he
                    led up the whole cavalry and light infantry to the enemy's camp. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The sight of the dust rising in great abundance and
                    nearer than usual, caused a great alarm in the Roman camp; and at first they
                    scarcely believed the person announcing the circumstance, because during all the
                    preceding days the Macedonians had never appeared before the fourth hour, and it
                    was now only sun-rise. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Afterwards, when their
                    doubts were removed, by the shouting of great numbers, and the men running off
                    from the gates, great confusion <pb n="2017" xml:id="p.2017"/> ensued. The
                    tribunes, praefects, and centurions hastened to the general's quarters, and
                    their soldiers to their several tents. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Perseus
                    formed his troops within less than five hundred paces of the rampart, round a
                    hill, called Callinicus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> King Cotys, at the
                    head of his countrymen, had the command of the left wing, the light infantry
                    were placed between the ranks of the cavalry and separated them. On the right
                    wing were the Macedonian horse, with whose troops the Cretans were intermixed.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Milo, of Berœa, had the command of these
                    last; Meno, of Antigone, that of the cavalry, and the chief direction of the
                    whole division. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Next to the wings were posted
                    the royal horsemen, and a mixed kind of troops selected out of the auxiliary
                    corps of many nations; the commanders here were Patrocles of Antigone, and Didas
                    the governor of Paeonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the centre was the
                    king; and on each side of him the band called Agema, with the consecrated
                    squadrons of horse; in his front the slingers and javelin-bearers, each body
                    amounting to four hundred. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The command of
                    these he gave to Ion of Thessalonice, and Timanor, a Dolopian. The king's troops
                    were posted in this manner. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the other
                    side, the consul, drawing up his infantry in a line within the trenches, sent
                    out likewise all his cavalry and light infantry, which were marshalled on the
                    outside of the rampart. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Caius Licinius
                    Crassus, the consul's brother, had the command of the right wing, which
                    consisted of all the Italian cavalry, with light infantry intermixed. On the
                    left wing, Marcus Valerius Laevinus commanded the cavalry of the allies, being
                    sent by the states of Greece, and the light infantry of the same nation; Quintus
                    Mucius, with a chosen body of cavalry, levied on the emergency, led the centre.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the front of this body were placed two
                    hundred Gallic horsemen; and of the auxiliaries of Eumenes, three hundred
                    Cyrtians. Four hundred Thessalian horse were posted at a little distance, beyond
                    the left wing. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> King Eumenes and Attalus, with
                    their whole division, stood on the rear, between the rear rank and the rampart. </p>
                <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Formed in this manner, and nearly equal in
                    numbers of cavalry and light infantry, the two armies encountered; the fight
                    being begun by the slingers and javelin-bearers, who preceded the lines.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> First of all the Thracians, just like wild
                    beasts which had been long pent up, rushing on with a hideous yell, fell upon
                    the Italian cavalry in the right wing <pb n="2018" xml:id="p.2018"/> with such
                    fury, that even those men who were fortified against fear, both by experience in
                    war and by their natural courage, were thrown into disorder. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The footmen struck their spears with their swords;
                    sometimes cut the hams of their horse, and sometimes scabbed them in the flanks.
                    Perseus, making a charge on the centre, at the first onset routed the Greeks.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the enemy pressed hard on their rear,
                    the Thessalian cavalry, who had been posted in reserve at a little distance from
                    the left wing, clear of the shock, at first mere spectators of the fight,
                    afterwards, when affairs took this unfortunate turn, were of the utmost service
                    to the Greeks. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For they retreating leisurely,
                    and keeping their ranks, after they joined the auxiliary troops under Eumenes,
                    in concert with him afforded a safe retreat between their ranks to the
                    confederates, who fled in disorder, and as the enemy did not follow in close
                    bodies, they even had the courage to advance, and by that means saved many of
                    the flying soldiers who made towards them. Nor did the king's troops, who in the
                    ardour of the pursuit had fallen into confusion, dare to encounter men regularly
                    formed, and marching with a steady pace. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When
                    the king, victorious in the cavalry action, shouted out <quote>that the war was
                        finished, if they would aid him by even slight exertions,</quote> the
                    phalanx came up seasonably while he was encouraging his troops; for Hippias and
                    Leonatus, as soon as they heard of the victory gained by the horse, without
                    waiting for orders, advanced with all haste, that they might be at hand to
                    second any spirited design. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While the king,
                    struck with the great importance of the attempt, hesitated between hope and
                    fear, Evander, the Cretan, who had been employed by him to waylay king Eumenes
                    at Delphi, after he saw the body of infantry advancing round <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> their standards, ran up, and warmly recommended to him,
                        <quote> not to suffer himself to be so far elated by success, as rashly to
                        risk his all on a precarious chance, when there was no necessity for it.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If he would content himself with the
                        advantage already obtained, and proceed no farther that day, he would have
                        it in his power to make an honourable peace; or if he chose to continue the
                        war, he would be joined by abundance of allies, who would readily follow
                        fortune. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The king's own judgment rather inclined to
                    this plan; wherefore, after commending Evander, he ordered the stand- <pb
                        n="2019" xml:id="p.2019"/> ards to be borne back, and the infantry to return
                    to their camp, and the trumpeters to sound the signal for retreat to the
                    cavalry. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the side of the Romans there were
                    slain that day two hundred horsemen, and not less than two thousand footmen;
                    about two hundred horsemen were made prisoners: but of the king's, only twenty
                    horsemen and forty footmen were killed. </p>
                <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the victors returned to their camp, all
                    were full of joy, but the insolent transports of the Thracians were particularly
                    remarkable; for on their way back they chanted songs, and carried the heads of
                    the enemy fixed on spears. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Among the Romans
                    there was not only grief arising from their ill success, but dread lest the
                    enemy should immediately attack their camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Eumenes advised the consul to take post on the other side of the Peneus, that he
                    might have the river as a defence, until the dismayed troops should recover
                    their spirits. The consul was deeply struck with the shame of an acknowledgment
                    of fear; yet he yielded to reason, and leading over his troops in the dead of
                    the night, fortified a camp on the farther bank. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Next day the king advanced with the intention of provoking the enemy to
                    battle; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and on seeing their camp pitched in
                    safety on the other side of the river, admitted that he had been guilty of error
                    in not pushing the victory the day before, and of a still greater fault, in
                    lying idle during the night; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> for by sending
                    his light-armed troops, without calling out any of his other soldiers, the army
                    of the enemy might in a great measure be destroyed, during their confusion in
                    the passage of the river. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Romans were
                    delivered, indeed, from any immediate fears, as they had their camp in a place
                    of safety; but, among many other afflicting circumstances, their loss of
                    reputation affected them most. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In a council
                    held in presence of the consul, every one concurred in throwing the blame on the
                    Aetolians, insisting that the panic and flight took place first among them; and
                    that then the other allied troops of the Grecian states followed their cowardly
                    example. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Five chiefs of the Aetolians, who
                    were said to be the first persons that turned their backs, were sent to Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Thessalians were publicly commended in a
                    general assembly, and their commanders even received presents for their good
                    behaviour. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The spoils of the enemies who fell
                    in the engagement were brought to the king, out of which he <pb n="2020"
                        xml:id="p.2020"/> made presents, —to some, of remarkable armour, to some, of
                    horses, and to others he gave prisoners. There were above one thousand five
                    hundred shields; the coats of mail and breastplates amounted to more than one
                    thousand, and the number of helmets, swords, and missile weapons of all sorts,
                    was much greater. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These spoils, ample in
                    themselves, were much magnified in a speech which the king made to an assembly
                    of the troops: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> he said, <quote> You have given
                        the prestige of victory to the issue of the war: you have routed the best
                        part of the enemy's force, the Roman cavalry, which they used to boast of as
                        invincible. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For, with them, the cavalry is
                        the flower of their youth; the cavalry is the nursery of their senate; out
                        of them they choose the members of that body, who afterwards are made their
                        consuls; out of them they elect their commanders. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The spoils of these we have just now divided among you.
                        Nor have you a less evident victory over their legions of infantry, who,
                        stealing away in the night through fear of you, filled the river with all
                        the disorderly confusion of people shipwrecked, swimming here and there.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But it will be easier for us to pass
                        the Peneus in pursuit of the vanquished, than it was for them in the hurry
                        of their flight; and, immediately on our passing, we will assault their
                        camp, which we should have taken this morning if they had not run away.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Or if they should choose to meet us in
                        the field, anticipate the same result in an infantry action, as took place
                        yesterday when the cavalry were engaged. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Those troops who had gained the victory, while
                    they bore on their shoulders the spoils of the enemies whom they had killed,
                    were highly animated at hearing their own exploits, and, from what had passed,
                    conceived sanguine hopes of the future; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> while
                    the infantry, especially those of the Macedonian phalanx, were inflamed with
                    emulation of the glory acquired by the others, wishing impatiently for an
                    opportunity to display their exertions in the king's service, and to acquire
                    equal glory from the defeat of the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    king then dismissed the assembly; and next day, marching thence, pitched his
                    camp at Mopsius, a hill situate half way between Tempe and Larissa. </p>
                <milestone n="62" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans, without quitting the bank of the
                    Peneus, removed their camp to a place of greater safety. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Thither came Misagenes, the Numidian, with one thousand
                    horse, and <pb n="2021" xml:id="p.2021"/> a like number of foot, besides
                    twenty-two elephants. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king soon after held
                    a council on the general plan to be pursued; and as the presumption inspired by
                    the late success had by this time subsided, some of his friends ventured to
                    advise him to employ his good fortune as the means of obtaining an honourable
                    peace, rather than to let himself be so far transported with vain hopes, as to
                    expose himself to the hazard of an irretrievable misfortune. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They observed, that <quote> to use moderation in
                        prosperity, and not to confide too much in the calm of present
                        circumstances, was the part of a man of prudence, who deserved success;
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and they recommended it to him to send
                        to the consul, to renew the treaty, on the same terms which his father had
                        received from Titus Quintius, his conqueror; <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> for the war could never be terminated in a more glorious manner than by
                        such a memorable battle, nor could a surer hope of a lasting peace ever
                        occur, than that afforded by existing circumstances, as they were likely to
                        make the Romans, dispirited by their defeat, more willing to come to terms.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But should they, with their native
                        obstinacy, spurn reasonable conditions, then gods and men would bear witness
                        both to the moderation of Perseus, and to the stubborn pride of the others.
                    </quote> The king's inclination was never averse to such measures; therefore
                    this opinion received the approbation of the majority. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The ambassadors sent to the consul had audience in a full
                    council, summoned for the purpose. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They
                    requested that <quote> a peace might be concluded; promising that Perseus should
                        pay the Romans the same tribute which Philip had engaged to pay, and should
                        evacuate the same cities, lands, and places, which Philip had evacuated. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Such were the proposals of the ambassadors.
                    When they withdrew, and the council deliberated concerning them, the Roman
                    firmness prevailed in their determination. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So
                    completely was it the practice of that time, to assume in adversity the
                    countenance of prosperity, and in prosperity to moderate the temper. They
                    resolved to give this answer: <quote> That peace should be granted on this
                        condition only; that the king should give to the senate an entirely
                        unconditional right, of deciding concerning him and all Macedon. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the ambassadors brought back this
                    answer, such as were unacquainted with their usual mode of acting, were
                    astonished at the obstinate perseverance of the <pb n="2022" xml:id="p.2022"/>
                    Romans, and most people <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> advised the king to
                    make no further mention of peace, for <quote>the enemy would soon come to
                        solicit that which they now disdained when offered.</quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Perseus feared this haughtiness, since it
                    proceeded from a confidence in their strength, and increasing the sum of money,
                    with the hope of purchasing peace by treasure, did not cease to solicit the mind
                    of the consul. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After the consul made no
                    change in the answer which he had first given, Perseus, having despaired of
                    peace, returned to Sycurium, from which he had set out, with the intention of
                    trying again the fortune of war. </p>
                <milestone n="63" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news of this cavalry action spread through
                    Greece, produced a discovery of the wishes of the people. For not only those who
                    professed an attachment to the Macedonians, but the generality, who were bound
                    to the Romans under the weightiest obligations, and some who had even felt the
                    power and haughty behaviour of the Macedonians, received the account with joy;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and that for no other cause, than out of
                    an evil passion which the mob displays, even in contests of sports, of favouring
                    the worse and weaker party. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, in
                    Bœotia, the praetor, Lucretius, pushed the siege of Haliartus with all
                    imaginable vigour. And although the besieged had no foreign aid, except some
                    young Coronaeans, who had come into the town at the beginning of the siege, and
                    were without hope of relief, yet they maintained the defence with courage beyond
                    their strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For they made frequent
                    irruptions against the works; and when the ram was applied, they crushed it to
                    the ground, by dropping on it a mass of lead; and whenever those who worked the
                    engine avoided the blow by changing its position, the besieged by working in
                    masses, and collecting stones out of the rubbish, quickly erected a new wall in
                    the room of that which had been demolished. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The praetor, when the progress by machines was too slow, ordered scaling-
                    ladders to be distributed among the companies, resolving to make a general
                    assault on the walls. He thought the number of his men sufficient for this, and
                    the more so because on one side of the city, which is bounded by a morass, it
                    would neither be useful nor practicable to form an attack. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Lucretius himself led two thousand chosen men to a place
                    where two towers, and the wall between them, had been thrown down; hoping that,
                    while he endeavoured to climb over the ruins, <pb n="2023" xml:id="p.2023"/> and
                    the townsmen crowded thither to oppose him, the walls, being left defenceless,
                    in some part or other might be taken by escalade. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The besieged were not remiss in preparing to repel his
                    assault; for, on the ground, overspread with the rubbish, they placed faggots of
                    dry bushes, and standing with burning torches in their hands, they often
                    threatened to set them on fire, in order that, being covered from the enemy by
                    the smoke and flames, they might have time to throw up a wall in the inside.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But a casualty prevented this plan from
                    succeeding; for there fell suddenly such a quantity of rain, as hindered the
                    faggots from being kindled; thus a passage was laid open by drawing the smoking
                    faggots aside; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and while all were attending to
                    the defence of one particular spot, the walls were mounted by escalade in many
                    places at once. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In the first tumult of
                    storming the town the old men and children, whom chance threw in the way, were
                    put to the sword indiscriminately, while the men who carried arms fled into the
                    citadel. Next day, these, having no remaining hope, surrendered, and were sold
                    by public auction. Their number was about two thousand five hundred. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The ornaments of the city, consisting of statues and
                    pictures, with all the valuable booty, were carried off to the ships, and the
                    city was razed to the ground. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The praetor
                    then led his army into Thebes, which fell into his hands without a dispute; when
                    he gave the city in possession to the exiles, and the party that sided with the
                    Romans; and sold, as slaves, the families of those who were of the opposite
                    faction, and favoured the king and the Macedonians. After performing these acts
                    in Bœotia, he returned to the sea-coast to his fleet. </p>
                <milestone n="64" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these events were taking place in
                    Bœotia, Perseus lay a considerable time encamped at Sycurium. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Having learned there that the Romans were busily employed
                    in collecting corn from all the adjacent grounds, and that when it was brought
                    in, they cut off the ears with sickles, each before his own tent, in order that
                    he might thresh it the cleaner, and had by this means formed large heaps of
                    straw in all quarters of the camp: he, supposing that he might set it on fire,
                    ordered torches, faggots, and bundles of tow, dipped in pitch, to be got ready;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and thus prepared, he began his march at
                    midnight, that he might make the attack at the first dawn, and without
                    discovery. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But his stratagem was frustrated:
                    the advanced guards, who were surprised, alarmed the rest of the troops by <pb
                        n="2024" xml:id="p.2024"/> the tumult and terror among them: orders were
                    given to take arms with all speed, and the soldiers were instantly drawn up on
                    the rampart and at the gates in readiness to defend the camp. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Perseus immediately ordered his army to face about; the
                    baggage to go foremost, and the battalions of foot to follow, while himself,
                    with the cavalry and light infantry, kept behind, in order to cover the rear;
                    for he expected, what indeed happened, that the enemy would pursue and harass
                    his rear. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There was a short scuffle between
                    the light infantry, mostly in skirmishing parties. The infantry and cavalry
                    returned to their camp, without any disturbance. After reaping all the corn in
                    that quarter, the Romans removed into the territory of Cranno, which was yet
                    untouched. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While they were encamped there,
                    deeming themselves secure on account of the distance between the camps, and the
                    difficulty of the march, through a country as destitute of water as was that
                    between Sycurium and Cranno, the king's cavalry and light infantry appeared
                    suddenly, at the dawn of day, on the nearest hills, and caused a violent alarm.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They had marched from Sycurium at noon the
                    preceding day, and had left their infantry at the dawn in the next plain.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Perseus stood a short time on the hills,
                    in expectation that the Romans might be induced to come to a cavalry action; but
                    after they did not move, he sent a horseman to order the infantry to return to
                    Sycurium, and he himself soon followed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    Roman horse pursued at a small distance, in expectation of being able to attack
                    such as might disperse and separate; but seeing them retreat in close order, and
                    attentive to their standards and ranks, they desisted, and returned to their
                    camp. </p>
                <milestone n="65" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king, disliking the length of the march,
                    removed his camp from Sycurium to Mopsilum; and the Romans, having cut down all
                    the corn about Cranno, marched into the lands of Phalanna. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When Perseus learnt from a deserter that they carried on
                    their reaping there, without any armed guard, straggling at random through the
                    fields, he set out with one thousand horsemen and two thousand Thracians and
                    Cretans, and after marching with all the speed that he possibly could,
                    unexpectedly fell on the Romans. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nearly a
                    thousand carts, with horses harnessed to them, most of them loaded, were seized,
                    and about six hundred men were taken. The charge of guarding this booty, and
                    conducting it to the camp, he <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> gave <pb
                        n="2025" xml:id="p.2025"/> to a party of three hundred Cretans, and calling
                    in the rest of his infantry and <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the cavalry
                    who were spread about, killing the enemy, he led them against the nearest
                    station, thinking that it might be overpowered without much difficulty.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Lucius Pompeius, a military tribune, was
                    in command; who led his men, who were dismayed by the sudden approach of the
                    enemy, to a hill at a little distance, hoping to defend himself by means of the
                    advantage of the ground, as he was inferior in number and strength. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> There he collected his men in a circular body, that,
                    by closing their shields, they might guard themselves from arrows and javelins;
                    on which Perseus, surrounding the hill with armed men, ordered a party to strive
                    to climb it on all sides, and come to close fighting, and the rest to throw
                    missile weapons against them from a distance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans were environed with dangers, in whatever manner they acted; for they
                    could not fight in a body, on account of the enemy who endeavoured to mount the
                    hill; and, if they broke their ranks in order to skirmish with these, they were
                    exposed to the arrows and javelins. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were
                    galled most severely by the Cestrospendana. A dart, two palms in length, was
                    fixed to a shaft, half a cubit long, and of the thickness of a man's finger;
                    round this, which was made of pine, three feathers were tied, as is commonly
                    done with arrows. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To throw this they used a
                    sling, which had two beds, unequal in size and in the length of the strings.
                    When the weapon was balanced in these, and the slinger whirled it round by the
                    longer string and discharged it, it flew with the rapid force of a leaden
                    bullet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When one half of the soldiers had
                    been wounded by these and other weapons of all kinds, and the rest were so
                    fatigued that they could hardly bear the weight of their arms, the king pressed
                    them to surrender, assured them of safety, and sometimes promised them rewards;
                    but not one could be prevailed on to yield; and hope now dawned on them
                    determined to die. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For when some of the
                    foragers, fleeing back to the camp, had announced to the consul that the party
                    was surrounded; alarmed for the safety of such a number of his countrymen, (for
                    they were near eight hundred, and all Romans,) he set out with the cavalry and
                    light infantry, joined by the newly arrived Numidian auxiliaries, horse, foot,
                    and elephants, and ordered the military tribunes, that the battalions of the
                    legions should follow. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He himself, having <pb
                        n="2026" xml:id="p.2026"/> strengthened the light-armed auxiliaries with his
                    own light infantry, hastened forward at their head to the hill. He was
                    accompanied by Eumenes, Attalus, and the Numidian prince, Misagenes. </p>
                <milestone n="66" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the standards of the Romans first came in
                    sight of the surrounded troops, their spirits were raised from the depth of
                    despair. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Perseus's best plan would have been
                    to have contented himself with his accidental good fortune, in having killed and
                    taken so many of the foragers, and not to have wasted time in attacking this
                    detachment of the enemy; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> or, after he had
                    engaged in the attempt, as he was sensible that he had not a proper force with
                    him, to have gone off, while he might, with safety; instead of which,
                    intoxicated with success, he waited for the arrival of the enemy, and sent
                    messengers in haste to bring up the phalanx, which would have been too late for
                    the emergency. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The men must have engaged in
                    all the disorder of a hurried march, against troops duly formed and prepared.
                    The consul, arriving first, proceeded instantly to action. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Macedonians, for some time, made resistance;
                    afterwards, when they were equal to their enemies in no respect, having lost
                    three hundred foot, and twenty-four of the best of their horse, of what they
                    call the Sacred Cohort, (among whom fell Antimachus, who commanded that body,)
                    they endeavoured to retreat: but this march back was more disorderly and
                    confused than the battle itself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the
                    phalanx, being summoned by a hasty order, was marching at full speed, it met
                    first, in a narrow pass, the carts laden with corn, with the mass of prisoners.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These they put to the sword, and both
                    parties suffered great annoyance; but none waited till the troops might pass in
                    some sort of order, but the soldiers tumbled the loads down a precipice, which
                    was the only possible way to clear the road, and the horses, when they were
                    goaded, pushed furiously through the crowd. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Scarcely had they disentangled themselves from the disorderly throng of the
                    prisoners, when they met the king's party and the discomfited horsemen. And now
                    the shouts of the men, calling to their comrades to go back, raised a
                    consternation not unlike a total rout; insomuch, that if the enemy had ventured
                    to enter the defile, and carry the pursuit a little farther, they might have
                    done them very great damage. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the consul,
                    when he had relieved his party from the hill, <pb n="2027" xml:id="p.2027"/>
                    content with that moderate share of success, led back his troops to the camp.
                    There are writers who state that a general engagement took place that day, in
                    which eight thousand of the enemy were killed, among whom were Sopater and
                    Antipater, two of the king's generals, and about two thousand eight hundred
                    taken, with twenty-seven military standards; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    and that it was not a bloodless victory, for that above four thousand three
                    hundred fell, and five standards of the left wing of the allies were lost. </p>
                <milestone n="67" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This day revived the spirits of the Romans,
                    and struck Perseus with dismay: to such a degree that, after staying at Mopsilum
                    a few days, chiefly out of anxiety to bury his dead, he left a very strong
                    garrison at Gonnus, and led back his army into Macedon. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He left Timotheus, one of his generals, with a small party
                    at Phila, ordering him to endeavour to gain the affection of the Magnesians, by
                    his proximity to them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On his arrival at
                    Pella, he sent his troops to their winter quarters, and proceeded with Cotys to
                    Thessalonica. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There an account was received
                    that Atlesbis, a petty prince of Thrace, and Corragus, an officer belonging to
                    Eumenes, had made an inroad into the dominions of Cotys, and seized on the
                    district called Marene. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Supposing, therefore,
                    that he must send Cotys home to defend his own territories, he honoured him at
                    his departure with very magnificent presents, and paid to his cavalry two
                    hundred talents, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 38,750 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note> which was but half a year's pay, though he had agreed to give them the
                    pay of a whole year. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consul, hearing that
                    Perseus had left the country, marched his army to Gonnus, in hopes of being able
                    to take that town: which standing directly opposite to the pass of Tempe, at its
                    entrance, serves as the safest barrier to Macedon, and renders a descent into
                    Thessaly easy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the city, from the nature
                    of its situation and the strength of the garrison, was impregnable; he therefore
                    gave up the design, and turning his route to Perrhaebia, having taken Mallaea at
                    the first assault, he demolished it; and after reducing Tripolis, and the rest
                    of Perrhaebia, returned to Larissa. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From that
                    place he sent home Eumenes and Attalus, and quartered Misagenes and his
                    Numidians, for the winter, in the nearest towns of Thessaly. One half of his
                    army he distributed through Thessaly, in such a manner that all had commodious
                    winter <pb n="2028" xml:id="p.2028"/> quarters, and served at the same time as a
                    defence to the cities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He sent Quintus Mucius,
                    lieutenant-general, with two thousand men, to secure Ambracia, and dismissed all
                    the allied troops belonging to the Grecian states, except the Achaeans. With the
                    other half of his army he marched into the Achaean Phthiotis; where, finding
                    Pteleum deserted by the inhabitants, he levelled it to the ground. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> He received the voluntary surrender of Antron, and
                    he then marched against Larissa: this city was likewise deserted, the whole
                    multitude taking refuge in the citadel, to which he laid siege. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> First the Macedonians, who constituted the king's
                    garrison, withdrew through fear; and then the townsmen, on being abandoned by
                    them, surrendered immediately. He then hesitated whether he should first attack
                    Demetrias, or take a view of affairs in Bœotia. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> The Thebans, being harassed by the Coronaeans, pressed him to go into Bœotia;
                    wherefore, in compliance with their entreaties, and because that country was
                    better adapted for winter quarters than Magnesia, he led his army thither. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
