<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 42</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="book">
                <head>The Third Macedonian War</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first business of the new consuls was
                        to consult the senate about their provinces and armies. It was decreed that
                        they should both have Liguria for their province and they were each to raise
                        two fresh legions for service in that province and also 10,000 infantry and
                        600 cavalry from the Latin allies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They
                        were also required to call up 3000 Roman infantry and 200 cavalry to
                        reinforce the army in Spain. A further force of 1500 infantry and 100
                        cavalry was to be raised for the operations in Corsica. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> M. Atilius was to remain in charge of Sardinia till his
                        successor arrived. Then the praetors balloted for their provinces.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A. Atilius Serranus received the civic
                        and C. Cluvius Saxula the alien jurisdiction; Hither Spain fell to N. Fabius
                        Buteo; Further Spain to C. Matienus; Sicily to M. Furius Crassipes; Sardinia
                        to C. Cicereius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Before the magistrates
                        left for their provinces the senate decided that L. Postumius should go into
                        Campania to fix the boundaries between the State land and the land in
                        private occupation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was a matter of
                        common knowledge that persons had appropriated a large part of the State
                        domain by gradually advancing their boundaries. Postumius was angry with the
                        Praenestines because when he had gone there in a private capacity to offer a
                        sacrifice in the temple of Fortune, he had not received any marks of honour,
                        either publicly or privately. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> So before he
                        left Rome he sent a despatch to Praeneste ordering the chief magistrate to
                        go out and meet him, to have a place prepared by the municipality where he
                        could stay, and to see that pack animals were ready to carry his luggage
                        when he left. No one before this consul had ever been a burden or expense to
                        the allies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The magistrates were provided
                        with mules and tents and all other requisites simply that they might not
                        requisition anything of the kind from the allies; they enjoyed the
                        hospitality of private citizens whom they treated with courtesy and
                        consideration; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and their own houses in
                        Rome were open to those with whom they were accustomed to stay. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> When officials were despatched to some place on
                        a sudden emergency they only demanded one mule apiece from the towns through
                        which their journey lay. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No other expense
                        was incurred by the allies in the case of Roman magistrates. The
                        vindictiveness of the consul, even if justifiable, ought not in any case to
                        have appeared while he was in office. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The
                        Praenestines unfortunately, whether through modesty or timidity, allowed the
                        matter to pass without protest, and this silence furnished the magistrates
                        with a legal colouring, as though following an unquestioned precedent, to
                        demands which became continuously more burdensome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the year, the
                        commissioners who had visited Aetolia and Macedonia brought back word that
                        no opportunity had been afforded them of meeting Perseus. Some made out that
                        he was ill; others that he was away from home; both stories being equally
                        false. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was, however, quite clear that
                        warlike preparations were on foot, and that it would not be long before
                        Perseus resorted to arms. In Aetolia intestine quarrels were increasing in
                        violence day by day, and the leaders of the opposing factions refused to be
                        kept in check by their authority. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As it
                        was fully expected that there would be war with Macedonia, it was decided
                        that portents should be expiated and prayers offered to win "the peace of
                        the Gods," of those deities, namely, who were mentioned in the Books of
                        Fate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Lanuvium the sight of a great
                        fleet had been witnessed in the heavens; at Privernum the earth had brought
                        forth dark-coloured wool; at Remens in the Veientine district there had been
                        a shower of stones; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the whole of the
                        Pomptine country had been covered with clouds of locusts; in a field in Gaul
                        where the plough was at work, fishes emerged from the turned-up clods.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In consequence of these portents the
                        Books of Fate were consulted, and the Keepers announced to what deities and
                        with what victims sacrifices were to be offered; they further ordered
                        special intercessions for the expiation of the portents, and also others in
                        fulfilment of the vow taken by the people the previous year on the occasion
                        of the pestilence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All was done as the
                        Sacred Books ordered. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was in this year that the temple of
                        Juno Lacinia was unroofed. Q. Fulvius Flaccus, the censor, was building the
                        temple of Fortuna Equestris and was quite determined that there should be no
                        larger or more magnificent temple in Rome. He had vowed this temple during
                        the Celtiberian war, whilst acting as praetor in Spain. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The beauty of the temple would be enhanced, he thought,
                        if it were roofed with marble tiles, and with this object he went down to
                        Bruttium and stripped off half the roof from the temple of Juno Lacinia, as
                        he considered this would furnish sufficient tiles to cover his temple.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Ships were in readiness to transport
                        them, and the natives were deterred by the authority of the censor from any
                        attempt to prevent the sacrilege. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the
                        censor's return the tiles were unloaded and carried to the new temple.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although no hint was dropped as to
                        where they came from, concealment was impossible. Protests were heard in the
                        House, and there was a general demand that the consuls should bring the
                        matter before the senate. The censor was summoned, and his appearance called
                        forth still more bitter reproaches from all sides. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Not content, he was told, with violating the noblest
                        temple in that part of the world, a temple which neither Pyrrhus nor
                        Hannibal had violated, he did not rest till he had cruelly defaced it and
                        almost destroyed it. With its pediment gone and its roof stripped off, it
                        lay open to moulder and decay in the rain. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        The censor is appointed to regulate the public morals; the man who had,
                        following ancient usage, been charged to see that the buildings for public
                        worship are properly closed in and that they are kept in repair-this very
                        man is roaming about amongst the cities of our allies ruining their temples
                        and stripping off the roofs of their sacred edifices. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Even in the case of private buildings such conduct
                        would be thought disgraceful, but he is demolishing the temples of the
                        immortal gods. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By building and beautifying
                        one temple out of the ruins of another he is involving the people of Rome in
                        the guilt of impiety, as though the immortal gods are not the same
                        everywhere, but some must be honoured and adorned with the spoils of others.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was quite clear what the feeling
                        of the House was even before the question was put, and when it was put they
                        were unanimous in deciding that those tiles should be carried back to the
                        temple and that expiatory sacrifices should be offered to Juno. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The religious duty was carefully discharged, but
                        the contractors reported that as there was no one who understood how to
                        replace the tiles they had been left in the precinct of the temple. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One of the praetors, N. Fabius, whilst on
                        his way to take charge of the province of Hither Spain, died at Marseilles.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On receiving the information of his
                        death, the senate decreed that P. Furius and Cn. Servilius, whose successors
                        had been already appointed, should decide by ballot which of them should
                        have his command extended and administer Hither Spain. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> It fell to P. Furius, fortunately, who had been in the
                        province, to retain it. There was a quantity of land taken in the wars with
                        the Ligurians and the Gauls which was lying unappropriated, and the senate
                        passed a resolution that it should be distributed amongst individual
                        holders. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In pursuance of this resolution
                        the City praetor appointed ten commissioners to supervise the allotment, M.
                        Aemilius Lepidus, C. Cassius, T. Aebutus Carus, C. Tremellius, P. Cornelius
                        Cethegus, Quintus and Lucius Apuleius, M. Caecilius, C. Salonius, and C.
                        Menatius. Each Roman citizen received ten jugera, each of the Latin allies,
                        three. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> During this time a delegation from
                        Aetolia went to Rome with an account of their party factions and fights;
                        others from Thessaly to report on the state of things in Macedonia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus was revolving in his mind the war
                        which he had been meditating in his father's life-time, and by promises more
                        than by performance was trying through his agents to enlist the sympathies
                        not only of the Greek States as a whole, but of the separate cities also.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was, however, a large party in
                        his favour and much more inclined to support him than Eumenes, though
                        Eumenes had by his munificent liberality laid all the cities of Greece and
                        most of their leaders under personal obligations to him. His kingly rule,
                        too, had been such that not one of the cities which owned his sway would
                        have changed their condition with that of any autonomous community.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the other hand, there were rumours
                        that Perseus had killed his wife with his own hand, and had put Apelles to
                        death. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Apelles had been his instrument in
                        getting rid of his brother and had fled the country to escape the punishment
                        which Philip sought to inflict on him. After his father's death Perseus had
                        by lavish promises of rewards for his share in the murder enticed him back
                        and then had him assassinated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although he
                        was notorious for many other murders, both of his own subjects and of
                        foreigners, and although he did not possess a single commendable quality,
                        the cities generally preferred him to a king who had shown such affection
                        towards his kindred, such justice towards his subjects and such bountiful
                        generosity towards all men. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Either they
                        were so impressed with the prestige and greatness of Macedonia as to look
                        with contempt on a newly-founded kingdom, or they were eager for a
                        revolutionary change, or else they did not wish to be at the mercy of Rome. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was not in Aetolia only that
                        disturbances had arisen through the heavy pressure of debt; the Thessalians
                        were in the same condition, and the mischief had spread like an epidemic to
                        Perrhaebia also. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When news came that the
                        Thessalians were in arms, the senate at once sent Ap. Claudius to examine
                        the situation and allay the excitement. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        severely censured the leaders on both sides. The debt was swollen by illegal
                        interest, and he reduced the amount with the consent of those who had made
                        it so heavy, and then arranged that the amount legally owing should be paid
                        off by equal instalments in ten years. Affairs in Perrhaebia were settled in
                        the same way. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Marcellus attended the
                        session of the Aetolian council at Delphi and heard the arguments of both
                        sides, who carried on the dispute in the same temper they had shown in the
                        civil war. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He saw that it was a
                        competition in recklessness and audacity, and not wishing to lighten or to
                        aggravate the grievances of either side, he made the same demand on both and
                        asked them to abstain from war and bury their old quarrels in oblivion.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> This reconciliation was mutually
                        guaranteed by the exchange of hostages, and Corinth was agreed upon as the
                        place where the hostages were to reside. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Leaving Delphi and the Aetolian council
                        Marcellus proceeded to the Peloponnese, where he had called a meeting of the
                        Achaean council. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here he commended them
                        for having firmly retained the old decree forbidding the Macedonian kings
                        any approach to their territories, and he made it quite clear that the
                        Romans regarded Perseus as an enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To
                        precipitate hostilities Eumenes went to Rome, taking with him the notes he
                        had made during his enquiry into the warlike preparations going on.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Five commissioners were at the same
                        time sent to the king to see for themselves the state of things in
                        Macedonia, and were instructed to visit Alexandria as well and renew the
                        friendly relations between Ptolemy and Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> The members of the mission were C. Valerius, Cn. Lutatius Cerco, Q.
                        Baebius Sulca, M. Cornelius Mammula, and M. Caecilius Denter. Envoys from
                        Antiochus arrived about the same date. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Their leader, Apollonius, when introduced to the senate, alleged many valid
                        reasons why the king was paying his tribute after the appointed day. He had,
                        however, brought the whole amount, so that no favour need be shown to the
                        king beyond excusing the delay. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He had, in
                        addition, brought a present of golden vases weighing 500 pounds. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The king asked that the friendship and alliance
                        which had been formed with his father might be renewed with him, and that
                        the people of Rome would look to him for all that a friendly monarch could
                        supply; he would never be lacking in any service he could render them.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> During his stay in Rome, he reminded
                        the House, it was due to the kindness of the senate and the friendliness of
                        the younger men that he was treated as a prince more than as a hostage.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The deputation received a gracious
                        reply and the City praetor, A. Atilius, was ordered to renew the alliance
                        with Antiochus which had existed with his father. The tribute was given into
                        the charge of the City quaestors, and the golden vases were handed to the
                        censors with instructions to deposit them in whatever temples they thought
                        fit. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The leader of the deputation
                        received a present of 100,000 ases, and free quarters and hospitality were
                        decreed to him as long as he remained in Italy. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The commissioners who had been in Syria had reported
                        that he held the highest place of honour with the king and was a devoted
                        friend to Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The principal incidents in the provinces
                        this year were the following: C. Cicereius fought a regular engagement in
                        Corsica; 7000 of the enemy were killed and over 1700 made prisoners. During
                        the battle the praetor vowed a temple to Juno Moneta. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> After this the Corsicans begged for peace, which was
                        granted to them on condition of their paying a tribute of 200,000 pounds of
                        wax. After the subjugation of Corsica, Cicereius sailed across to Sardinia.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was a battle also in Liguria at
                        the town of Carystum in the Statellate country. A large force of Ligurians
                        had concentrated there. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the consul
                        M. Popilius reached the place they at first kept within their walls, but
                        when they saw the Romans preparing to attack, they formed their line of
                        battle in front of their gates. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This had
                        been the consul's object in threatening an attack and he lost no time,
                        therefore, in commencing the action. They fought for more than three hours
                        without any certain prospect of victory on either side. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> When the consul found that in no part of the field were
                        the Ligurians giving way, he ordered the cavalry to mount and deliver as
                        fierce a charge as possible on the front and flanks of the enemy's line.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A good many broke through the enemy's
                        centre and got behind the fighting line. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        This created a panic amongst the Ligurians; they broke and fled in all
                        directions, very few reached the town, the cavalry mostly intercepting them.
                        The obstinacy of the fighting proved costly to the Ligurians; 10,000 men are
                        said to have been killed and more than 700 prisoners taken; 82 standards
                        were carried off the field. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The victory
                        was not a bloodless one for the Romans: they lost more than 3000 men;
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the loss fell mainly on the front
                        ranks owing to both sides refusing to give ground. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the battle the Ligurians rallied
                        from their scattered flight and collected together. When they became aware
                        that the number of those lost was greater than that of the survivors-there
                        were not more than 10,000 men-they made their surrender and made it
                        unconditionally in the hope that the consul would not treat them with
                        greater severity than former generals had done. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> However, he deprived them all of their arms, sacked
                        their town and sold them and their property. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> He forwarded a report of what he had done to the senate. As the other
                        consul, Postumius, was occupied with the survey of the fields in Campania,
                        the despatch was read in the House by A. Atilius. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The senators regarded it as an act of gross cruelty
                        that the Statellati, who alone of all the Ligurians had refused to take up
                        arms against Rome, should actually have been attacked without any
                        provocation, and after trusting themselves to the good faith of the Roman
                        people have been tortured to death with every form of cruelty. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> That so many thousands of freeborn persons,
                        guiltless of any crime, should have been sold into slavery, in spite of
                        their appeals to the honour of Rome, is a terrible example and warning
                        against any one henceforth <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> making a
                        surrender, and sharing the fate of those who have been dragged off to
                        various places to be the slaves of men who were formerly the enemies of Rome
                        and are hardly even now at peace with her. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Moved by these considerations the senate determined that M. Popilius should
                        restore the Ligurians to liberty and return the purchase-money, and see that
                        as much of their property as could be recovered should be given back to
                        them; their arms also were to be restored. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        All this was to be done as soon as possible; the consul was not to leave his
                        province till he had replaced the surrendered Ligurians in their homes. He
                        was reminded that the glory of victory was won by overcoming the enemy in
                        fair fight, not by cruelty to those who cannot defend themselves. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The same ungovernable temper which the
                        consul had displayed towards the Ligurians he now showed in refusing to obey
                        the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He at once sent the legions
                        into winter quarters at Pisae and returned to Rome angry with the senate and
                        furious with the praetors. Immediately on his arrival he convened the senate
                        in the temple of Bellona, where he delivered a long an bitter harangue
                        against the praetor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He ought, he said, to
                        have asked the senate to decree honours to the immortal gods for the
                        successes he had won, instead of which he had induced the senate to pass a
                        resolution in favour of the enemy by which he transferred his (the
                        speaker's) victory to the Ligurians and practically ordered the consul to
                        surrender to them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He therefore imposed a
                        fine on him and asked the senators to make an order rescinding the
                        resolution against him and <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> also to do,
                        now that he was in Rome, what they ought to have done when he was away,
                        immediately they received his despatch, namely, to decree a solemn
                        thanksgiving, first as honouring the gods and then as showing at least some
                        regard for him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some of the senators
                        attacked him to his face quite as severely as they had done in his absence,
                        and he returned to his province without either of his demands being
                        conceded. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The other consul, Postumius,
                        spent the summer in surveying the fields and returned to Rome for the
                        elections without even having seen his province. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The new consuls were C. Popilius Laenas and P. Aelius
                        Ligus. The new praetors were C. Licinius Crassus, M. Junius Pennus, Sp.
                        Lucretius, Sp. Cluvius, Cn. Sicinius, and C. Memmius for the second time.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year the lustrum was closed. The
                        censors were Q. Fulvius Flaccus and A. Postumius Albinus; Postumius closed
                        the lustrum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The number of Roman citizens
                        as shown by the census was 269,015, a somewhat smaller number than the
                        previous one. This was owing to the fact that, as the consul explained to
                        the Assembly, all those who had to return to their own cities in compliance
                        with the consul's edict were registered in their own places of residence,
                        none of them in Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The censors had
                        discharged their functions in perfect harmony and in the best interests of
                        the commonwealth. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All those whom they
                        struck off the senatorial roll, or degraded from the order of the equites,
                        they placed amongst the aerarii and expelled from the tribes, and neither of
                        them retained any name which the other censor had rejected. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Fulvius dedicated the temple of Fortuna Equestris,
                        which he had vowed six years previously when fighting with the Celtiberi. He
                        also exhibited the Scenic Games for four days and those in the Circus
                        Maximus for one day. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> L. Cornelius
                        Lentulus, one of the Keepers of the Sacred Books, died this year, and A.
                        Postumius Albinus was appointed in his place. Such clouds of locusts invaded
                        Apulia from the sea that they covered the fields far and wide with their
                        swarms. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To get rid of this destruction to
                        the crops Cn. Sicinius was sent with full powers into Apulia and spent a
                        considerable time in getting together an enormous number of men to collect
                        them. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The following year in which C. Popilius
                        and P. Aelius were the consuls began with the dispute left over from the
                        year before. The senators wanted to discuss the question of the Ligurians
                        and to reaffirm their resolution. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        consul Aelius brought the matter up for discussion; <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Popilius, on his brother's behalf, tried to dissuade
                        both his colleague and the senate from taking any further action and
                        publicly gave out that if they made any decree he should oppose it. He
                        deterred his colleague from going any further; the senate were all the more
                        incensed against both consuls and insisted on carrying the matter through.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So when the allocation of provinces
                        came up and the consuls were anxious to have Macedonia, as a war with
                        Perseus was now imminent, the senate decreed Liguria as the province for
                        both consuls. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> They refused to decree
                        Macedonia unless the case of M. Popilius was gone into. The consuls then
                        demanded to be allowed to raise fresh armies or else reinforcements for the
                        old armies. Both requests were refused. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Two of the praetors asked for reinforcements: M. Junius for Hither Spain and
                        Sp. Lucretius for Further Spain. Their request was also refused. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> C. Licinius Crassus had received the civic and
                        Cn. Sicinius the alien jurisdiction; C. Memmius had Sicily allotted to him,
                        and Sp. Cluvius Sardinia. The consuls were angry with the senate for the
                        course they had taken, and <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> after fixing
                        the Latin Festival at the earliest possible date, gave notice that they
                        should leave for their province and would transact no public business beyond
                        what was connected with the administration of the provinces. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias writes that Attalus, the
                        brother of Eumenes, went to Rome at this time to lay charges against Perseus
                        and to describe his preparations for war. The majority of annalists, and
                        certainly those whom you would prefer to believe, state that Eumenes came in
                        person. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he arrived in Rome he was
                        received with all the honours which the people of Rome considered due to his
                        own merits and quite as much so to the kindnesses which they had heaped upon
                        him in such profusion. After being introduced to the senate he said that he
                        was visiting Rome for two reasons. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> One was
                        his great desire to make acquaintance with the gods and men to whose
                        beneficence he owed his present prosperity, which was such that he did not
                        venture even to wish for anything beyond it. The other reason was that he
                        might warn the senate of the necessity of thwarting the projects of Perseus.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Beginning with a review of Philip's
                        policy he narrated the circumstances of the death of Demetrius, who was
                        opposed to war with Rome. "The Bastarnae," he continued, "were induced to
                        leave their homes that he might have their assistance in the invasion of
                        Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Whilst revolving these schemes in
                        his mind he was surprised by death and left the crown to one whom he knew to
                        be Rome's greatest enemy. The war had thus been left as a heritage to
                        Perseus by his father, bequeathed to him together with the crown, and from
                        the first day of his rule all his plans were laid to feed and foster it.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He has abundant resources; the long
                        years of peace have produced a numerous progeny of men of military age;
                        moreover he is in the prime of life, in the full strength of manhood, and
                        with a mind strengthened and disciplined in the science and practice of war.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From his boyhood he has shared his
                        father's tent and has thus gained experience not only in border wars, but
                        even in the wars with Rome in the various expeditions on which he has been
                        sent. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From the day he ascended the throne
                        he has been marvellously successful in accomplishing many things which his
                        father, after trying every means, was unable to effect either by force or
                        craft; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and his power is enhanced by a
                        personal authority such as is only gained by great and numerous merits in a
                        long course of time. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "For throughout the cities of Greece and
                        Asia all stand in awe of his greatness. I do not see for what merits or
                        munificence such a tribute is paid him, nor can I say for certain whether
                        this is due to the good fortune which attends him or whether, though I
                        shrink from saying <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> it, it is ill-feeling
                        towards Rome that places him so high in their favour. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Even with monarchs he possesses great influence; he
                        married the daughter of Seleucus, and did not ask for her hand; on the
                        contrary, he was invited to make the match; he gave his sister to Prusias in
                        response to his earnest solicitations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At
                        the celebration of both these marriages congratulations and wedding presents
                        were offered by deputations from numberless States, and the proudest nations
                        joined in the processions to bring good luck to the brides. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Boeotians, in spite of all Philip's persuasions,
                        could never be brought to make a formal league of friendship and commit it
                        to writing; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> today the terms of a league
                        with Perseus are recorded in three inscriptions: one at Thebes, another in
                        the venerable world-famed shrine in Delos, and the third at Delphi. And, as
                        a matter of fact, unless a small section of the Achaean council had
                        threatened the rest with the power of Rome, matters would have gone so far
                        that the way into Achaia would have been open to him. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> After all the services I have rendered to that
                        nation-and it is difficult to say whether those to the nation or those to
                        individuals were the greater-the statues set up in my honour have either
                        fallen into decay through neglect, or else have been done away with through
                        hostile malice. Who does not know that in their party conflicts the
                        Aetolians appeal for help not to the Romans, but to Perseus? <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Though he had these friendships and alliances to
                        lean upon, he has made such ample preparations for war at home that he has
                        no need of outside help. He has stored corn for 30,000 infantry and 5000
                        cavalry which will last for ten years, so that he can leave the harvests of
                        his own and of the enemy's fields untouched. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> He is now in possession of so much money that he has a reserve sufficient
                        to pay 10,000 mercenary troops, in addition to his Macedonian force, for the
                        same period. This is irrespective of the revenue from the royal mines. In
                        the arsenals, arms have been accumulated for three armies each as large.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thrace is open to him as a
                        never-failing source from which he can draw fighting men, supposing that the
                        supply from Macedonia should fail." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He closed with an earnest appeal. "I am
                        not, senators, laying these facts before you as bruited in vague rumours, or
                        because I wished such charges against an enemy to be true, and therefore was
                        the more eager to credit them; I am stating the results of my investigations
                        and disclosures just as though you had sent me on a mission of enquiry and I
                        were reporting what I had actually seen. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I
                        would not have left my kingdom, to which you have given such extension and
                        prestige, and undertaken so long a voyage merely to destroy all faith in me
                        by telling you idle tales. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I saw the
                        greatest cities in Greece and Asia unveiling their designs day by day, and
                        soon, were they allowed, they will have gone so far that there will be no
                        room left for repentance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> I have watched
                        Perseus, not confining himself within his own borders, taking armed
                        possession of some places, and where others could not be seized by force,
                        winning them by a show of favour and goodwill. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> I observed how unequal the conditions were; he
                        preparing for war against you and you making peace secure for him, though it
                        seemed to me as if he were not so much preparing for war as actually
                        commencing it. Abrupolis, your friend and ally, he has expelled from his
                        kingdom. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Arthetaurus, the Illyrian, also
                        your friend and ally, he caused to be put to death because he discovered
                        that he had written to you. Euersas and Callicritus, leading men in Thebes,
                        he managed to get put out of <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> the way
                        because they spoke too frankly against him in the council of Boeotia and
                        declared that they should inform you about what was going on. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> He sent help to the Byzantines in violation of
                        the treaty; he levied war on Dolopia; he marched his army through Thessaly
                        and Doris in order that, should civil war break out, he might smash the more
                        respectable party by the means of the more disreputable one. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> He brought about universal confusion in Thessaly
                        and Perrhaebia by holding out the prospect of a cancellation of all debts,
                        so that he might crush the aristocracy by a body of debtors bound by their
                        obligations to him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As you have remained
                        quiet and allowed him to do all this, and as he sees that, as far as you are
                        concerned, Greece has been handed over to him, he takes it for granted that
                        he will meet with no armed opposition before he has landed in Italy.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> How far this is an honourable or safe
                        policy for you to pursue, it is for you to consider. I, at all events, felt
                        that it would be disgraceful on my part if Perseus came and carried war into
                        Italy before I, your ally, had warned you to be on your guard. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> I have discharged the duty incumbent upon me and
                        have relieved myself of what was a burden on my loyalty. What can I do more,
                        except to pray heaven that you may consult the true interest of your
                        commonwealth and of us, your allies and friends, who depend on you?" </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This speech made a great impression on the
                        House, but for the time no one outside could learn anything beyond the fact
                        of the king's presence in the House, in such silence were the proceedings
                        veiled. Only when the war was over did what the king said and what the
                        senate replied leak out. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A few days later
                        the envoys of King Perseus were admitted to an audience. But the minds, no
                        less than the ears, of the senators had been captured by Eumenes, and all
                        that the Macedonian envoys alleged in justification or apology found no
                        hearing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The effrontery of Harpalus, the
                        leader of the embassy, created still more exasperation. He said that the
                        king was anxious that when he declared that he had neither said nor done
                        anything of a hostile character, his statement should be believed.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If, however, he saw that they were
                        obstinately bent upon finding some excuse for war, he should depend upon
                        himself with resolution and courage; the chances of war were the same for
                        both sides and the issue was uncertain. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> All the cities of Greece and Asia were
                        much concerned about the reception which Eumenes and the envoys of Perseus
                        had met with in the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Most of them
                        on learning of the arrival in Rome of the man who, in their opinion, would
                        influence the Romans in the direction of war, sent deputations, ostensibly
                        to discuss other questions. One of these was from Rhodes, and its leader had
                        no doubt whatever that Eumenes had included his city in the indictment
                        against Perseus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Consequently he made
                        every effort through his friends and patrons to get an opportunity of
                        meeting the king in argument before the senate. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As he did not succeed he denounced the king in
                        unmeasured invective, declaring that he had stirred up the Lycians against
                        the Rhodians and was much more oppressive to Asia than Antiochus had ever
                        been. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This language pleased the populace
                        whose sympathies were with Perseus, but it was resented by the senate and
                        did no good either to himself or his fellow-countrymen The hostility shown
                        towards Eumenes by the different States made the Romans all the more
                        determined to show him favour; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> all
                        honours were heaped upon him and most valuable gifts presented to him,
                        including a curule chair and an ivory sceptre. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the deputations were dismissed,
                        Harpalus returned to Macedonia as speedily as possible and informed the king
                        that he had left the Romans not indeed actually preparing for war, but so
                        embittered against him that any one might see they would not long delay.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Perseus himself believed that events
                        would take this turn and now he even wished that they would, as he believed
                        himself to be at the height of his power. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Eumenes was the man he hated most of all, and he determined to begin the war
                        by shedding his blood. He suborned Euander of Crete, a leader of
                        mercenaries, and three Macedonians who were accustomed to lend their
                        services for crimes of this nature, and gave them a letter for Praxo, a
                        friend of his, the wealthiest and most influential woman in Delphi.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was generally understood that
                        Eumenes would go up to Delphi to sacrifice to Apollo. The only thing the
                        assassins needed for executing their project was a suitable spot, and they
                        and Euander traversed the neighbourhood to find one. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the ascent to the temple from Cirrha,
                        before reaching the part covered with buildings, the path, which is so
                        narrow that passengers can only go in single file, has a wall running close
                        to it on the left hand, and on the right a landslip has left an abrupt
                        descent of some depth. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Behind this wall
                        the conspirators concealed themselves and built steps up against it, so that
                        they might hurl missiles on the king as he passed under it. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> As he came up from the sea he was surrounded by a crowd
                        of friends and by his bodyguard, but as the road became narrower, fewer
                        could walk side by side. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When they reached
                        the place where they had to go in single file, Pantaleon, one of the
                        Aetolian leaders, was in front, and the king was engaged in conversation
                        with him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At this moment the assassins
                        appeared above the wall and rolled down two huge stones, one of which hit
                        the king on the head and the other fell on his shoulder. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Stunned by the blow he fell down the steep descent,
                        after many stones had been flung upon him as he lay. All the friends and
                        guards fled except Pantaleon, who fearlessly remained to protect the king.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The assassins could easily have run round
                        the wall to finish off the wounded king, but instead of this they fled up to
                        the ridge of Parnassus as though they had completed their task, and in such
                        haste that one of them, not being able to keep up with them, retarded their
                        flight, and to prevent his being caught and turning informer against them,
                        they killed their comrade. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king's
                        friends ran to where his body lay, followed by the guards and slaves.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They lifted him, still stunned by the
                        blow and unconscious, but they found from the warmth of the body and the
                        breath still remaining in the lungs, that he was still alive, but they had
                        little or no hope of his recovery. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some of
                        the guards followed in the track of the assassins and climbed as far as the
                        top of Parnassus, but their labour was in vain and they returned from their
                        fruitless search. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Macedonians had set
                        about the crime with as much deliberation as daring; they abandoned it with
                        as much haste as cowardice. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The next day
                        the king had recovered consciousness and was carried down to the ship. They
                        first made for Corinth, then the ships were drawn across the neck of the
                        Isthmus and the voyage was continued to Aegina. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Here so much secrecy was observed regarding his
                        progress towards recovery, none being admitted to his room, that a report of
                        his death travelled through Asia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Even
                        Attalus believed it, somewhat more readily indeed than was consistent with
                        harmony between the brothers, for he talked to his brother's wife and to the
                        commandant of the citadel as if he were the undoubted heir to the crown.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Eumenes did not forget this, and
                        though he had determined to dissemble his resentment and preserve silence,
                        he could not restrain himself the first time they met from reproaching him
                        for his premature haste in wooing his wife. The rumour of his death even
                        reached Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just after this incident C. Valerius, who
                        had been sent to Greece to examine the state of the country and discover the
                        designs of Perseus, returned with a report which agreed in all points with
                        the charges brought by Eumenes. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He had
                        brought back with him from Delphi the woman Praxo, whose house had been the
                        meeting-place of the assassins, and also L. Rammius, a native of Brundisium,
                        who laid the following information before the senate. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Rammius was the chief person in Brundisium, and he used
                        to entertain the Roman generals and distinguished ambassadors from foreign
                        nations, especially those who represented monarchy. Through this he became
                        known to Perseus, though he was in a different part of the world, and when
                        he received a letter holding out the prospect of more intimate friendship,
                        and consequently of high fortune, he paid a visit to the king. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> In a short time he found himself on very familiar
                        terms with him, and drawn more often than he could have wished into
                        confidential talks. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The king pressed a
                        proposal upon him and promised him a huge bribe if he would consent to it.
                        As all the Roman generals and ambassadors usually accepted his hospitality,
                        Perseus suggested that he should arrange for poison to be administered to
                        those whose names he should give him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        knew that the preparation of poison was extremely difficult and dangerous,
                        as so many must know of its preparation and, besides that, there is
                        uncertainty as to its working, whether it will be strong enough to
                        accomplish its task or safe as against any discovery. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He would therefore give him a poison which could not be
                        detected by any indication, either whilst being given or afterwards.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Rammius was afraid that, if he
                        refused, he might be the first on whom the poison would be tried, so he
                        promised to do what the king asked, and started for home. He did not,
                        however, want to return to Brundisium before he saw C. Valerius, who was
                        reported to be in the neighbourhood of Chalcis. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He laid the facts before him, and acting on his
                        instructions came with him to Rome. Introduced into the senate he narrated
                        what had taken place. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This information added to that which
                        Eumenes had given hastened their decision to declare Perseus a public enemy;
                        they recognised that he was not meditating an honourable war in the spirit
                        of a king, but was winding his way through every criminal method of
                        assassination and poisoning. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The conduct
                        of the war was left to the new consuls. For the present, however, it was
                        decided that Cn. Sicinius should raise a force, which was to be taken to
                        Brundisium <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> and sail across as soon as
                        possible to Apollonia and Epirus and occupy the cities on the coast, where
                        the consul to whom Macedonia should be allotted could find safe anchorage
                        and disembark his men without trouble. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Eumenes had been detained a considerable time at Aegina, as the dangerous
                        nature of his wounds made his recovery slow and difficult. As soon as it was
                        safe for him to move, he went on to Pergamum and began to make energetic
                        preparations for war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This fresh crime of
                        Perseus intensified his old enmity towards him and proved a powerful
                        incentive. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Delegates from Rome went to
                        congratulate him on his escape from such great peril to his life. The
                        Macedonian war was put off for the year, and nearly all the praetors left
                        for their provinces, with the exception of M. Junius and S. Lucretius. They
                        had received Spain as their province, and after repeated requests they at
                        length prevailed on the senate to allow their army to be reinforced. They
                        were, empowered to raise 3000 infantry and 150 cavalry for the Roman
                        legions, and for the allied contingent 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This force was transported to Spain
                        with the new praetors. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this year a large part of the
                        Campanian district, which had been in many places appropriated by private
                        individuals, was by the survey of the consul Postumius recovered for the
                        State, and M. Lucretius, one of the tribunes of the plebs, gave notice of a
                        proposal that the censors should let out the Campanian land for cultivation,
                        a thing that had not been done through <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                        all the years since the fall of Capua, and as a consequence, the greed of
                        private citizens took its course in the unoccupied land. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> War had now been determined upon, though not yet
                        declared; the senate were waiting to see which of the monarchs would
                        befriend Perseus and who would support them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> Just at this time a mission from Ariarathes arrived, bringing with them
                        the king's young son. They explained that the king had sent his son to be
                        brought up in Rome, so <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> that he might
                        from his boyhood become familiar with Roman manners and Roman men. He asked
                        that they would allow him to be not only under the charge of personal
                        friends but also under the care and guardianship, so to speak, of the State.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate were highly pleased with
                        the proposal, and made a decree that Cn. Sicinius should hire a furnished
                        house where the king's son and his suite could live. Envoys also from
                        Thrace, with the Maedi and Astii, came to ask for alliance and friendship.
                        Their request was granted and each received a present of 2000 ases.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Romans were especially glad that
                        these peoples had been received into alliance, because Thrace lay at the
                        back of Macedonia. But that the whole situation in Asia and the islands
                        might be thoroughly investigated, Tiberius Claudius Nero and M. Decimius
                        were sent with instructions to visit Crete and <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> Rhodes, to renew friendly relations, and at the same
                        time to find out whether the allies of Rome had been tampered with by
                        Perseus. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the citizens were in a state of
                        tense expectancy of a fresh war, the column erected on the Capitol during
                        the Punic war by the colleague of Ser. Fulvius was shattered from top to
                        bottom by a stroke of lightning. This accident was regarded as a portent and
                        reported to the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Keepers of the
                        Sacred Books announced that the City must undergo a lustration; that
                        intercessions and special prayers must be offered; and that animals of the
                        larger size must be sacrificed both at Rome in the Capitol and in Campania
                        at the Promontory of Minerva. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Games were
                        also, as soon as possible, to be celebrated for ten days in honour of
                        Jupiter Optimus Maximus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The reply of the
                        augurs was to the effect that the portent would prove to be favourable, for
                        it portended the widening of frontiers and the destruction of enemies; those
                        ships' beaks which the storm had thrown down had been taken as spoils from
                        the enemy. Other incidents increased the religious terrors. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> It was reported that showers of blood had been falling
                        for three days at Saturnia; an ass was foaled with three legs, and a bull
                        with five cows had been destroyed by a single flash of lightning at Calatia;
                        at Auximium there had been a shower of earth. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> In expiation of these portents, sacrifices were offered
                        and special intercessions for one day, which was observed as a solemn
                        holiday. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Up to this time the consuls had not left
                        for their province. They did not comply with the desire of the senate to
                        bring up the question of Popilius, and the senators were determined not to
                        make any decrees till this was settled. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The feeling against Popilius was intensified by a despatch received from him
                        in which he stated that he had fought another battle with the Statellati and
                        had killed 6000 of them. This iniquitous proceeding of his drove the rest of
                        the Ligurians to arms. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Now, however, it
                        was not only the absent Popilius who was attacked in the senate for having,
                        in defiance of all law, human and divine, commenced an aggressive war upon a
                        people who had made their submission; the consuls also were severely
                        censured for not having gone to their province. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> This attitude of the senate determined two of the
                        tribunes of the plebs-M. Marcius Sermo and Q. Marcius Scylla-to warn the
                        consuls that if they did not go to their province they should impose a fine
                        on them. They also read to the senate the terms of a proposal which they
                        intended to bring forward regarding the treatment of the Ligurians after
                        they had made their submission. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was to
                        the effect that where any of the Statellati who had made their surrender had
                        not been restored to liberty by August 1, the senate should on oath empower
                        a magistrate to seek out and punish the persons through whose criminal act
                        they had passed into slavery. This order, thus sanctioned by the senate, was
                        announced to the Assembly. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before the
                        consuls left the City the senate gave an audience to C. Cicereius in the
                        temple of Bellona. He gave an account. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> of what he had done in Corsica, but his
                        request for a triumph was refused, and he celebrated his triumph on the
                        Alban Mount, without the sanction of the senate, a thing which had become
                        quite customary. Marcius's proposal about the Ligurians received the hearty
                        assent of the plebs, and was carried. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Acting on this plebiscite, C. Licinius consulted the senate as to whom they
                        would choose to conduct the enquiry, and the senators ordered him to conduct
                        it himself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now at last the consuls went to their
                        province and took over the army from M. Popilius. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He did not venture to return to Rome, where the senate
                        were hostile, and the people still more so, for fear of having to stand his
                        trial before the praetor who had submitted to the senate the resolution
                        against him. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His refusal to appear was met
                        by the tribunes of the plebs with the menace of a second resolution to be
                        submitted to the effect that if he had not entered the City of Rome by
                        November 13, Licinius should judge and determine his case in his absence.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Dragged home by this chain he found
                        himself the object of universal odium in the senate. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After many of the senators had lashed him with bitter
                        invectives, the House passed a resolution that the praetors C. Licinius and
                        Cn. Sicinius should make it their business to restore to liberty all
                        Ligurians who had not been in arms against Rome since the consulship of Q.
                        Fulvius and L. Manlius, and that the consul C. Popilius should make them a
                        grant of land on the other side of the Po. By this resolution many thousands
                        recovered their freedom and <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> they were
                        transported across the Po where land was assigned to them. M. Popilius,
                        under the Marcian Decree, appeared on two occasions before C. Licinius.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the third day of his trial the
                        praetor, out of regard for his brother the consul, and yielding to the
                        entreaties of the Popilian family, ordered the defendant to appear again on
                        March 15, the day on which the new magistrates would enter upon office, so
                        that he might not have to adjudicate, being no longer a magistrate.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In this way the decree respecting the
                        Ligurians was evaded by a subterfuge. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A deputation from Carthage was in Rome at
                        that time, as was also Gulussa, Masinissa's son. There was a hot dispute
                        between them in the senate-house. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        grievance of the Carthaginians was that in addition to the territory which
                        had been adjudicated on the spot by the Roman commissioners, Masinissa had
                        during the last two years taken forcible possession of more than seventy
                        towns and forts standing on Carthaginian soil; an easy matter for a man who
                        had no scruples. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As the Carthaginians were
                        bound by their treaty they took no action, for they were forbidden
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> to carry their arms outside their
                        frontiers, though they knew quite well that if they were to drive the
                        Numidians out, they would be warring within their own frontiers. They were,
                        however, deterred by a clear clause in the treaty, which expressly forbade
                        them to engage in war with the allies of Rome. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But the Carthaginians declared that they could no
                        longer endure his insolence and cruelty and avarice; and they explained that
                        they were sent to implore the senate to grant them one of three things,
                        either themselves to decide, as between a king and a people, both of whom
                        were their allies, what belonged to each; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        or to leave the Carthaginians at liberty to defend themselves against unjust
                        attacks in a just and righteous war; or, finally, if personal bias rather
                        than truth swayed the senate, that they should settle once for all how much
                        of other people's property they wished to make a present of to Masinissa.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate would at all events make
                        their gift a more moderate one if they were to know what they had given,
                        whereas Masinissa would fix no limits other than what his greed and ambition
                        might determine. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If they were not to
                        obtain any of these requests, and if they had in any way given offence since
                        Scipio granted them peace, then let the Romans themselves punish them; they
                        preferred the security of servitude under Roman masters rather than a
                        liberty exposed to Masinissa's lawlessness. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> It would, in fact, be better for them to perish at once than to draw
                        their breath at the will of a tyrant and a butcher. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> At these words they burst into tears and fell on their
                        faces, and as they lay there prostrate they aroused not more pity for
                        themselves than displeasure against the king. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The senate decided to ask Gulussa what
                        answer he had to make to these charges, or whether he preferred to state
                        first his object in coming to Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Gulussa said that he was in a difficulty in having to deal with matters
                        about which he had received no instructions from his father, nor would it
                        have been easy for his father to give him instructions, for the
                        Carthaginians had given no indication of the question they were going to
                        raise or even of their intention to visit Rome. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> For several nights their Inner Council had been meeting
                        in secret conclave in the temple of Aesculapius, and in addition to other
                        steps envoys were despatched to Rome with sealed instructions. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> This was his father's reason for sending him to
                        Rome, to ask the senate not to give any credit to the charges which their
                        common foe was bringing against him; the only reason for their hatred was
                        his unswerving loyalty to the people of Rome. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> After giving both sides a hearing the senate debated
                        the requests of the Carthaginians and ordered the following reply to be
                        given: "It is the pleasure of the senate that Gulussa sets out at once for
                        Numidia and announces to his father that he must send envoys to the senate
                        as soon as possible to deal with the complaints of the Carthaginians;
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> he must also warn the Carthaginians to
                        appear and state their case. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The senate is
                        prepared to accord to Masinissa all possible honours in the future as they
                        have done in the past, but they cannot let personal regard take the place of
                        justice. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They wish every man to remain in
                        possession of his own land; it is not their intention to fix new boundaries,
                        but to preserve the old ones. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the
                        Carthaginians were vanquished they allowed them to retain their city and
                        their land; but this was not that they might rob them in a time of peace of
                        what they had not taken from them by the rights of war." <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> So the young prince and the Carthaginians were
                        dismissed, the customary presents were given to each party and in other ways
                        they were hospitably and courteously treated. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Just about this time Cn. Servilius Caepio,
                        Ap. Claudius Centho, and T. Annius Luscus, the three commissioners who had
                        been sent to Macedonia to demand satisfaction and break off friendly
                        relations with Perseus, returned from their mission. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The report of what they had seen and what they had
                        heard inflamed the minds of the senators still more against Perseus. They
                        reported that they had witnessed the most energetic preparations for war
                        being made throughout all the cities in Macedonia. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When they went to see the king there was no opportunity
                        granted them of seeing him for many days; at last, looking upon the prospect
                        of an interview as hopeless, they started for home; only then were they
                        recalled and admitted to the king's presence. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The sum and substance of their address to him was that
                        a treaty had been concluded with Philip and, after his father's death,
                        renewed with him; that in it were clauses expressly forbidding him to carry
                        his arms beyond his frontiers or to make hostile aggression upon the allies
                        of Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then they repeated to him what
                        they had heard Eumenes stating to the senate, all of which was found to be
                        true. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And in addition they reminded the
                        king that he had for several days been having secret interviews at
                        Samothrace with delegates from the cities in Asia. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The senate thought it right that satisfaction should be
                        made for this wrongful act and that they and their allies should have
                        restored to them whatever the king was holding in defiance of treaty rights. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The king was furious and his language
                        intemperate. He accused the Romans of greed and arrogance, and loudly
                        protested against their sending one mission after another to spy upon his
                        words and actions, because they thought it right that he should say and do
                        everything in obedience to their orders. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        At last, after a long and violent harangue, he told them to return on the
                        following day as he wished to give them a written reply. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> In this he is said to have declared that the treaty
                        concluded with his father had nothing to do with him; he had consented to
                        its renewal not because he approved of it, but because having just come to
                        the throne he had to submit to everything. If they wanted to make a fresh
                        treaty with him they must come to an understanding as to its terms.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If they could bring themselves to
                        conclude a treaty on equal terms for both parties, he would see what he had
                        to do and he was sure they would be acting in the best interests of their
                        commonwealth. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> With this he hurried off
                        and they were all beginning to leave the audience-chamber, but not before
                        the commissioners replied that they formally renounced his alliance and
                        friendship. At these words he stopped and in a towering rage shouted out a
                        warning to them to leave his dominions within three days. Under these
                        circumstances they left the country without having received any attention or
                        hospitality during the whole of their stay. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> The Thessalian and Aetolian envoys were the next to be admitted to
                        audience. In order that the senate might know as soon as possible what
                        generals the <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> State would employ, they
                        sent written instructions to the consuls that whichever of them was able to
                        do so should go to Rome to elect the magistrates. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the year the consuls did nothing
                        worth recording, the interests of the republic seemed to be best served by
                        quieting the exasperated Ligurians. Whilst war with Macedonia was
                        anticipated, Gentius, King of the Illyrians, also fell under suspicion.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Envoys from Issus laid complaints
                        before the senate about his ravaging their borders and asserted that he and
                        Perseus were living on the most perfect understanding with each other and
                        were planning war with Rome in close co-operation. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Illyrian spies had been sent to Rome at the instigation
                        of Perseus, ostensibly as envoys, really to find out what was going on. The
                        Illyrians were summoned before the senate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        They said, that they had been sent by the king to clear him of any charges
                        which the Issaeans might bring against him. They were then asked why in that
                        case they had not reported themselves to the proper magistrates so that they
                        might be assigned furnished quarters and their arrival and the object of
                        their coming might be publicly known. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As
                        they were at a loss for a reply, they were told to leave the senate-house,
                        and it was agreed that no reply should be made to them as envoys, since they
                        had made no formal request to appear before the senate. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It was resolved that envoys should be sent to Gentius
                        to inform him of the complaints made against him and to make him understand
                        that the senate regarded him as acting wrongfully in not abstaining from
                        injuring his neighbours. The envoys were A. Terentius Varro, C. Plaetorius,
                        and C. Cicereius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The commissioners who
                        had been sent to interview the friendly monarchs returned from Asia and
                        reported that they had visited Eumenes, Antiochus in Syria, and Ptolemy at
                        Alexandria; that they had all been approached by Perseus, but were keeping
                        perfectly true to their engagements with Rome, and they pledged themselves
                        to carry out all that the people of Rome required. They had also visited the
                        friendly cities and with one exception they were satisfied as to their
                        fidelity. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The one exception was Rhodes,
                        where they found the citizens wavering and imbued by Perseus' ideas.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A deputation had arrived from Rhodes
                        to clear the citizens from charges which they knew were being generally made
                        against them; the senate, however, decided not to grant them an audience
                        till the new consuls had entered upon office. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They felt that the preparations for war
                        ought not to be delayed. The praetor C. Licinius was instructed to select
                        out of the old quinqueremes laid up in the dockyards in Rome all that could
                        be made use of, and to repair and fit out fifty vessels. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> If he was unable to make up that number he was to write
                        to his colleague, C. Memmius, commanding in Sicily, and direct him to refit
                        and get ready for service the ships which were in Sicilian waters, so that
                        they could be sent as soon as possible to Brundisium. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> C. Licinius was to enlist crews for twenty-five ships
                        from Roman citizens of the freedman class, and Cn. Sicinius was to
                        requisition the same number from the allies, and also obtain from them a
                        force of 8000 infantry and 500 cavalry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A.
                        Atilius Serranus, who had been praetor the year before, was selected to take
                        over these soldiers at Brundisium and convey them to Macedonia. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> In order that Cn. Sicinius might have an army
                        ready to sail, C. Licinius was authorised by the senate to write to the
                        consul C. Popilius, requesting him to issue orders for the second legion,
                        most of whom had seen service in Liguria, and an allied contingent of 4000
                        infantry and 200 cavalry, to be at Brundisium by February 13. With this
                        fleet <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> and army Cn. Sicinius was ordered
                        to hold the province of Macedonia until his successor arrived, his command
                        being extended for a year. All the measures which the senate decided upon
                        were energetically carried out. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Thirty-eight quinqueremes were launched from the naval arsenal, and L.
                        Porcius Licinius was placed in command to take them to Brundisium; twelve
                        were sent from Sicily. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Sextius Digitius,
                        T. Juventius, and M. Caecilius were sent into Apulia and Calabria to
                        purchase corn for the fleet and army. When all the preparations were
                        completed, Cn. Sicinius left the City, wearing the paludamentum, en route
                        for Brundisium. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Towards the end of the year the consul C.
                        Popilius returned to Rome much later than the senate considered he ought to
                        have done, in view of the urgency of electing fresh magistrates and the
                        imminence of such a serious war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He did
                        not receive a very favourable hearing when, in the temple of Bellona, he
                        gave an account of his doings in Liguria. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        There were frequent interruptions and questions as to why he had not
                        restored the Ligurians to liberty after his brother's iniquitous treatment
                        of them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Notice of the consular elections
                        was duly given, and they were held February 18. The new consuls were P.
                        Licinius Crassus and C. Cassius Longinus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        The praetors elected on the following day were C. Sulpicius Galba, L. Furius
                        Philus, L. Canuleius Dives, C. Lucretius Gallus, C. Caninius Rebilus, and L.
                        Villius Annalis. The provinces assigned to these praetors were the two
                        jurisdictions in Rome, civic and alien, Spain, Sicily and Sardinia, and one
                        praetor was exempted from the ballot, to be employed as the senate should
                        decide. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The senate ordered the consuls
                        elect to offer due sacrifices of the larger victims, with prayers that the
                        war, which it was in the mind of the Roman people to wage, should have a
                        prosperous issue. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the same sitting the
                        senate decreed that the consul C. Popilius should make a vow pledging the
                        republic that if it should remain <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        without loss or change for ten years, Games should be held in honour of
                        Jupiter Optimus Maximus for ten days and offerings made at all the shrines.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In accordance with this decree the
                        consul made a vow in the Capitol that the Games should take place and the
                        offerings be made at all the shrines, at such a cost as the senate should
                        determine in a session at which not less than 150 were present. Lepidus, the
                        Pontifex Maximus, dictated the words of the vow. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Two members of the State priesthood died this year-L.
                        Aemilius Papus, a Keeper of the Sacred Books, and the pontiff Q. Fulvius
                        Flaccus, who had been censor the year before. He met with a tragic death.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His two sons were serving in Illyria,
                        and he received intelligence that one had died and that the other was
                        dangerously ill. Between grief and anxiety his mind gave way; the slaves, on
                        entering his room in the morning, found that he had hanged himself.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He was considered to be out of his
                        mind at the close of his censorship, and there was a general belief that he
                        had been driven mad by Juno Lacinia, in her anger at his spoliation of her
                        temple. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> M. Valerius Messala was appointed
                        Keeper of the Sacred Books in place of Aemilius, and C. Domitius
                        Ahenobarbus, a young man, was chosen to succeed Fulvius as pontiff. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When P. Licinius and C. Cassius began
                        their consulship, not only the City of Rome, but all kings and commonwealths
                        throughout Europe and Asia, were preoccupied by the approaching war between
                        Rome and Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Eumenes had long
                        regarded Macedonia as his enemy, and now he had a fresh incentive to his
                        hostility in his narrow escape from being slaughtered like a victim at
                        Delphi, through the king's foul treachery. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Prusias, the king of Bithynia, had decided to take no part in the conflict,
                        but quietly to wait on events. He felt sure that the Romans could not
                        possibly think it right for him to bear arms against his brother-in-law, and
                        if Perseus were victorious he knew that he could secure his favour through
                        his sister. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Ariarathes, king of
                        Cappadocia, had already promised to assist the Romans on his own account,
                        and now that he was connected by marriage with Eumenes, he associated
                        himself with all their policy, both in peace and war. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Antiochus was threatening Egypt, and in his contempt
                        for the boy-king and his unenterprising guardians he thought that, by
                        raising the question of Coelo-Syria, he would have a good pretext for war,
                        and be able to prosecute it without hindrance while the Romans were occupied
                        with the Macedonian war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He had, however,
                        made all sorts of promises to the senate in view of the war both by his own
                        legations to Rome and personally to the envoys whom the senate had sent to
                        him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Owing to his age. Ptolemy was under
                        tutelage; his guardians were preparing for war with Antiochus to keep their
                        hold on Coelo-Syria, and were at the same time promising to give the Romans
                        all assistance in their war with Macedonia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> Masinissa gave assistance by supplying corn, and was preparing to send a
                        force with elephants and also his son, Misagenes, to the war. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> He had, however, laid his plans to meet any turn
                        of fortune; if victory fell to the Romans, matters would remain as they
                        were, nor could he make any further advance since the Romans would not allow
                        any aggression on the Carthaginians. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If
                        the power of Rome-the sole protection of the Carthaginians-was broken, all
                        Africa would be his. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Gentius, king of the
                        Illyrians, had brought himself under suspicion, but had not gone so far as
                        to decide for certain which side he should support; it seemed as though
                        whichever he supported, it would be more from impulse than policy.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Thracian Cotys, king of the
                        Odrysae, had already declared for Macedonia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the views which monarchs took of
                        the war. Amongst the free nations and communities the common people were, as
                        usual, almost to a man in favour of the worse side, and supported the king
                        and the Macedonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> You would see great
                        diversity amongst the views and sympathies of the ruling classes. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> One party went so far in their admiration of the
                        Romans that they impaired their influence by their excessive partiality;
                        some, attracted by the justice of Roman rule, a more numerous body, by the
                        prospect of gaining power in their own cities if they rendered conspicuous
                        service. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The other side were sycophants
                        and flatterers of the king; the pressure of debt and the hopelessness of
                        their condition, if things remained as they were, drove many in sheer
                        desperation into revolutionary projects; others supported Perseus from sheer
                        caprice because he was popular. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A third
                        party, comprising the most respectable and sensible men, if they had in any
                        case to choose a master, would have preferred the Romans to Perseus.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If they had been free to choose their
                        condition, they would have had neither side made more powerful through the
                        overthrow of the other, but would have preferred that the strength of both
                        being equally balanced, a lasting peace on equal terms might be established.
                        In this way the cities, placed between the two, would be under the best
                        conditions, for one would always protect the helpless from injury at the
                        hands of the other. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Holding these
                        sentiments they watched in safety and in silence the rivalries of those who
                        supported the two parties. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the day they entered office the
                        consuls, in pursuance of the senate's resolution, visited all the shrines in
                        which there was usually a lectisternium for the greater part of the year,
                        offered sacrifices of the larger victims and learned from the omens given by
                        them that their prayers were accepted by the gods. They then reported to the
                        senate that the prayers and sacrifices had been duly offered. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The augurs made the announcement that if any
                        fresh enterprise was undertaken it ought to be begun without delay; all the
                        portents pointed to victory, triumph and the widening of frontiers.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Good fortune and success being thus
                        promised to Rome, the senate ordered the consuls to summon a meeting of the
                        Assembly in their centuries and submit the following order of the day:
                        "Whereas Perseus, the son of Philip and King of Macedonia, has broken the
                        treaty made with his father and renewed with him, by bearing arms against
                        the allies of Rome, devastating fields and occupying their cities; and
                        whereas he has formed plans for levying war on the people of Rome, and has
                        to this end got together arms, soldiers and ships; be it resolved that war
                        be made upon him unless he gives satisfaction for all these things."
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This resolution was put to the
                        Assembly. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then the senate decided that the consuls
                        should come to a mutual arrangement about their provinces of Italy and
                        Macedonia; failing that, to have recourse to the ballot. The one to whom
                        Macedonia fell was to seek redress by force of arms from Perseus, and those
                        of his party, unless they gave satisfaction to Rome. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Four fresh legions were to be called up, two for each
                        consul. A special provision was made for Macedonia. For the other consul
                        each of the two legions consisted, according to ancient precedent, of 5200
                        infantry; those for Macedonia were each raised to 6000 infantry, and the
                        four legions had each the same complement of 300 cavalry. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The numbers of the allied contingent were also raised
                        for this consul; he was to transport to Macedonia 16,000 infantry and 800
                        cavalry, in addition to the 600 cavalry whom Sicinius had commanded.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A force of 12,000 allied infantry and
                        600 cavalry was considered sufficient for Italy. The consul who was to
                        command in Macedonia was specially empowered to enrol as many veteran
                        centurions and private soldiers as he desired up to fifty years of age.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In view of the Macedonian war, an
                        innovation was made this year in the case of the military tribunes. The
                        consuls received instructions from the senate to propose to the Assembly
                        that they should for that year forgo their claim to elect the military
                        tribunes and leave the consuls and praetors free to appoint them. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The commands were allocated to the praetors as
                        follows: The praetor to whose lot it fell to <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> be at the senate's disposal without an assigned
                        province was to inspect the crews in the fleet at Brundisium, and after
                        removing all who were unfit for service, to select freedmen to take their
                        place, with the proviso that two-thirds should consist of Roman citizens,
                        the remainder to be drawn from the allies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Supplies for the fleet and the legions were to be furnished by Sicily and
                        Sardinia, and the praetors in charge of those islands were charged to
                        requisition a second tenth from the natives, the corn to be carried to the
                        army in Macedonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Sicily fell to C.
                        Caninius Rebilus; Sardinia to L. Furius Philus; Spain to L. Canuleius; the
                        civic jurisdiction to C. Sulpicius Galba; the alien to L. Villius Annalis.
                        The praetor who remained at the disposal of the senate was C. Lucretius
                        Gallus. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls had a disagreement-not a
                        serious dispute-about their province. Cassius said that he was ready to
                        choose Macedonia without a ballot, as his colleague could not ballot with
                        him without violating his oath. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he
                        was made praetor he took an oath before the Assembly that he could not go to
                        his province as he had sacrifices to perform at an appointed place and on
                        stated days, and they could not be duly offered in his absence, when he was
                        consul, any more than when he was praetor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Even should the senate not consider P. Licinius' wishes now that he was
                        consul more deserving of censure than the oath which he had taken as
                        praetor, he would bow to their authority. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        When the matter was put to the vote, the senators thought it would be a
                        high-handed proceeding to refuse a province to the man to whom the people of
                        Rome had not refused the consulship, and ordered the consuls to proceed to
                        ballot. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> P. Licinius obtained Macedonia,
                        and C. Cassius, Italy. They then drew lots for the legions; the first and
                        third were to be taken to Macedonia; the second and fourth to remain in
                        Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls carried out the
                        mobilisation with much more care than at other times. Licinius called up the
                        old soldiers and centurions, and many volunteers gave in their names because
                        they saw that those who had served in the former Macedonian war or against
                        Antiochus were rich men. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The military
                        tribunes were choosing the centurions, not in order of precedence, but
                        picking out the best men, and twenty-three centurions of the front rank
                        appealed to the tribunes of the plebs. Two members of the tribunitian
                        college were for referring the matter to the consuls, on the ground that the
                        decision ought to rest with those to whom the mobilisation had been
                        entrusted. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The rest said they would go
                        into the reasons of the appeal, and if an injustice had been done, they
                        would come to the aid of their fellow-citizens. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The case was argued before the tribunes in
                        their chairs; M. Popilius and the consul were present with the centurions.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul demanded that the matter
                        should be tried before the Assembly, and the Assembly was accordingly
                        convened. M. Popilius, who had been consul two years previously, spoke on
                        behalf of the centurions. He reminded the Assembly that these men had
                        completed their term of military service, and were worn out by age and
                        incessant toil. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Still, they in no way
                        objected to give their services to the State, only they protested against
                        being assigned a position inferior to the one they held when on active
                        service. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul P. Licinius ordered
                        the resolutions passed by the senate to be read, first the one in which the
                        senate decided upon war with Perseus, then the one in which it was
                        determined that as many of the veteran centurions as possible should be
                        called up for the war, and that there should be no exemption for any man who
                        was not over fifty years of age. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He
                        strongly deprecated any step being taken which would hamper the military
                        tribunes in their task of raising troops for a fresh war, so close to Italy
                        and against an extremely powerful monarch, or which would prevent the consul
                        from assigning to each man the rank which, in the best interests of the
                        commonwealth, ought to be assigned to him. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        If any doubt was still felt in the matter, let it be referred to the senate.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the consul had said what he wanted
                        to say, one of those who were appealing to the tribunes-Sp.
                        Ligustinus-begged the consul and the tribunes to allow him to say a few
                        words to the Assembly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They all gave him
                        permission, and he is recorded to have spoken to the following effect:
                        "Quirites, I am Spurius Ligustinus, a Sabine by birth, a member of the
                        Crustuminian tribe. My father left me a jugerum of land and a small cottage
                        in which I was born and bred, and I am living there today. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> As soon as I came of age my father gave me to wife his
                        brother's daughter. She brought nothing with her but her personal freedom
                        and her modesty, and together with these a fruitfulness which would have
                        been enough even in a wealthy house. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We
                        have six sons and two daughters. Four of our sons wear the toga virilis, two
                        the praetexta, and both the daughters are married. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> I became a soldier in the consulship of P. Sulpicius
                        and C. Aurelius. For two years I was a common soldier in the army, fighting
                        against Philip in Macedonia; in the third year T. Quinctius Flamininus gave
                        me in consideration of my courage the command of the tenth company of the
                        hastati. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After Philip and the Macedonians
                        were vanquished and we were brought back to Italy and disbanded, I at once
                        volunteered to go with the consul M. Porcius to Spain. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Men who during a long service have had experience of
                        him and of other generals know that of all living commanders not one has
                        shown himself a keener observer or more accurate judge of military valour.
                        It was this commander who thought me worthy of being appointed first
                        centurion in the hastati. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Again I served,
                        for the third time, as a volunteer in the army which was sent against
                        Antiochus and the Aetolians. I was made first centurion of the principes by
                        Manius Acilius. After Antiochus was expelled and the Aetolians subjugated we
                        were brought back to Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After that I
                        twice took service for a year at home. Then I served in Spain, once under Q.
                        Fulvius Flaccus and again under Ti. Sempronius Gracchus. I was brought home
                        by Flaccus amongst those whom, as a reward for their courage, he was
                        bringing home to grace his triumph. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> I
                        joined Tiberius Gracchus at his request. Four times, within a few years,
                        have I been first centurion in the triarii; four-and-thirty times have I
                        been rewarded for my courage by my commanders; I have received six civic
                        crowns. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I have served for twenty-two
                        years in the army and I am more than fifty years old. But even if I had not
                        served my full time and my age did not give me exemption, still, P.
                        Licinius, as I was able to give you four soldiers for one, namely, myself,
                        it would have been a right and proper thing that I should be discharged.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But I want you to take what I have
                        said simply as a statement of my case. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> So
                        far as anyone who is raising troops judges me to be an efficient soldier, I
                        am not going to plead excuses. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> What rank
                        the military tribunes think that I deserve is for them to decide; I will
                        take care that no man shall surpass me in courage; that I always have done
                        so, my commanders and fellow-campaigners bear witness. And as for you, my
                        comrades, though you are only exercising your right of appeal, it is but
                        just and proper that as in your early days you <milestone n="15??"
                            unit="section"/> never did anything against the authority of the
                        magistrates and the senate, so now, too, you should place yourselves at the
                        disposal of the senate and the consuls and count any position in which you
                        are to defend your country as an honourable one." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had finished speaking, the consul
                        commended him most warmly and took him from the Assembly to the senate.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There, too, he was thanked by the
                        senate, and the military tribunes made him leading centurion in the first
                        legion in recognition of his bravery. The other centurions abandoned their
                        appeal and answered to the roll-call without demur. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> To enable the magistrates to start for their provinces
                        at an earlier date, the Latin Festival was celebrated on June 1. When that
                        function was over, C. Lucretius sent all that was required for the fleet on
                        in advance and then left for Brundisium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        In addition to the armies which the consuls were forming, C. Sulpicius Galba
                        was commissioned to raise four City legions with the full complement of
                        horse and foot, and to select from amongst the senators four military
                        tribunes to command them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He was further
                        to require the Latins and allies to furnish 15,000 infantry and 1200
                        cavalry, so that this army might be ready for service wherever the senate
                        should decide. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In addition to the force of
                        Roman citizens and allied troops, the consul P. Licinius was supplied on his
                        request with the following: 2000 Ligurian mercenaries, a body of Cretan
                        archers-the number not specified-also Numidian cavalry and elephants.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> L. Postumius Albinus, Q. Terentius
                        Culleo, and C. Aburius were sent to Masinissa and the Carthaginians to
                        arrange this. A. Postumius Albinus, C. Decimius, and Aulus Licinius Nerva
                        were also sent to Crete for the same purpose. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this time envoys from Perseus
                        arrived. It was decided that they should not be allowed to enter the town,
                        as the senate and people had already determined on war with their king and
                        the Macedonians. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were admitted to an
                        audience in the temple of Bellona, and told the senate that Perseus was
                        wondering why the armies had been sent to Macedonia. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> If he could induce the senate to recall them, he would
                        give such satisfaction as the senate thought fit for any wrongs of which the
                        allies of Rome complained. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Spurius
                        Carvilius had been sent back from Greece by Cnaeus Sicinius on this same
                        business and was present at this session. He informed the senate how
                        Perrhaebia had been taken by storm and other cities of Thessaly captured,
                        and also what the king was actually doing and what preparations he was
                        making. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The envoys were told to answer
                        these charges; they hesitated and said they had not received any further
                        instructions. On thus they were ordered to carry back to their king the
                        announcement that in a short time the consul P. Licinius would be in
                        Macedonia with his army; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> if the king
                        really meant to give satisfaction, he might send envoys to him. It was
                        useless for him to send any to Rome, as none of them would be allowed to
                        pass through Italy. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With this reply they
                        were sent away, and P. Licinius was instructed to order them to quit Italy
                        within ten days and send Sp. Carvilius to watch them till they went on
                        board. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Cnaeus Sicinius, who before
                        quitting office had been sent to the fleet and army at Brundisium, had
                        landed 5000 infantry and 300 cavalry in Epirus and was now encamped at
                        Nymphaeum in the Apollonian district. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> From
                        there he sent tribunes with 2000 men to occupy the forts of the Dassaretii
                        and the Illyrians, as the people themselves were asking for troops to hold
                        them so that they might be more secure against any attack from their
                        Macedonian neighbours. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days later Q. Marcius, A. Atilius,
                        the two Lentuli, Publius and Servius, and also L. Decimius were sent to
                        Greece, and took with them 2000 men as far as Corcyra. There they arranged
                        what districts to visit and what force each was to take with him. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Decimius was sent to Gentius, the king of the
                        Illyrians, to find out whether he still had any regard for his former
                        friendship with Rome, and if so to induce him to take an active part in the
                        war as an ally. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The two Lentuli were sent
                        to Cephallania that they might sail across to the Peloponnese and round the
                        western coast before winter. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        visitation of Epirus, Aetolia and Thessaly was assigned to Marcius and
                        Atilius, after which they were ordered to survey the state of Boeotia and
                        Euboea and then sail to the Peloponnese. There they arranged to meet the
                        Lentuli. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Before they separated at Corcyra,
                        a despatch was received from Perseus in which he requested to know the
                        reason for the Romans landing an army in Greece and occupying the cities.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was decided that no written reply
                        should be sent, but that the bearer of the despatch should be told that the
                        Romans were doing it for the protection of the cities themselves. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The Lentuli in their visits to the different
                        towns urged upon them all without distinction the duty of giving the Romans
                        the same cordial and loyal assistance against Perseus which they had given
                        in the war with Philip and then afterwards with Antiochus. During their
                        meetings they heard murmurs of dissatisfaction amongst the Achaeans.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They complained that while they had
                        from the very beginning of the Macedonian war rendered every assistance to
                        the Romans and in the war with Philip had been the declared enemies of the
                        Macedonians, they were now put upon the same footing as the people of
                        Messene and Elea who had fought for Antiochus against Rome, and after being
                        incorporated into the Achaean council were handed over <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> to their Achaean conquerors as the prize of war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Marcius and Atilius went up to Gitana
                        in Epirus, about ten miles from the sea, where the national council of
                        Epirus was being held, they received a most favourable hearing, and 400 of
                        the younger men were sent as a protection to those Macedonians who had been
                        freed by the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From there they went
                        into Aetolia and stayed there a few days until a chief magistrate was
                        elected in the place of the one who had died. Lyciscus, who was known to be
                        a supporter of the Romans, was elected, and after his election they crossed
                        over into Thessaly. Here they were visited by envoys from Acarnania and
                        refugees from Boeotia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The envoys were
                        told to announce to the Acarnanians that an opportunity was now offered of
                        atoning for any faults which in reliance on the false promises of the king
                        they had committed against Rome in the war with Philip and then in the war
                        with Antiochus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If their bad behaviour had
                        met with the forbearance, their good behaviour would win the generosity, of
                        Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Boeotians were severely censured
                        for having formed an alliance with Perseus. They threw the blame on
                        Ismenias, the leader of the opposite faction, and declared that some cities
                        had been brought over against the majority of the citizens. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Marcius replied that this would be cleared up as they
                        would give every city the opportunity of deciding for itself. </p>
                    <p> There was a meeting of the national council of Thessaly at Larisa. The
                        Thessalians had abundant material for thanking the Romans for the boon of
                        liberty, and the Roman envoys for expressing their thanks for the
                        whole-hearted assistance they had received from the Thessalians in the wars
                        against Philip and Antiochus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This mutual
                        recognition of services rendered made the assembled council eager to adopt
                        every measure which the Romans wished for. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Close on this meeting came a deputation from Perseus. Their hopes of success
                        rested mainly on the personal tie of hospitality which Marcius had inherited
                        from his father. After alluding to this the delegates asked that the king
                        might be admitted to a personal interview. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Marcius said that he heard from his father that friendly relations had
                        existed with Philip, and bearing that fact in mind he had undertaken this
                        mission. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He would not have put off a
                        conference so long had he been well enough; now, as soon as he could manage
                        it, they would go to the Peneus where the road crosses from Homolium to Dium
                        and send to the king to announce their arrival. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On this Perseus left Dium and went back
                        into Macedonia, cheered by a faint breath of hope because he had heard that
                        Marcius had said it was for his sake that he had undertaken the mission.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They met at the appointed place. The
                        king was attended by a large suite consisting of his personal friends and
                        his bodyguard, and the Romans appeared with quite as numerous an escort,
                        many accompanying them from Larisa, as well as the delegations from the
                        various cities who wanted to take trustworthy reports of what they heard.
                        Men were naturally anxious to witness the meeting of a famous monarch with
                        the representatives of the foremost people in the whole world. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> When they stood to view with only the river
                        between them, there was a slight delay while it was being settled which
                        party should cross the river. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The one
                        party thought that precedence ought to be given to royalty, the other
                        considered that something was due to the great name of Rome, especially as
                        it was Perseus who had sought the interview. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> While they were hesitating Marcius quickened their movements by a jest:
                        "Let the younger come to the elder and"-his own cognomen was
                        "Philippus"-"the son to the father." The king fell in with this at once.
                        Then a fresh difficulty arose as to the number that should accompany him.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king thought that he ought to
                        cross with the whole of his suite, but the Romans said he must cross with
                        three attendants, or if all that number did cross he must give securities
                        against any treachery during the conference. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> He gave as hostages Hippias and Pantauchus, chief among his friends whom
                        he had formerly sent as envoys. The hostages were not so much needed to
                        guarantee the king's good faith as to make the allies see that the king was
                        by no means meeting the Romans on equal teems. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They greeted one another not as foes but in a friendly
                        and genial tone, and then sat down on the seats placed for them. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After a few moments' silence Marcius said:
                        "I suppose you are expecting me to give you a reply to the letter which you
                        sent to Corcyra in which you ask us why we who are envoys have come with
                        soldiers and are distributing garrisons in the various cities. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Not to give you any reply would, I fear, be
                        thought arrogant, whilst a truthful reply would pain you whilst you listened
                        to it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As, however, he who breaks a treaty
                        must be chastised either by word of mouth or by force of arms, and much as I
                        could have wished that war against you had been entrusted to another rather
                        than to me, I will discharge my task of telling my guest-friend some
                        unpleasant truths, however matters stand, like physicians who administer
                        disagreeable remedies to restore a patient's health. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> "As soon as you ascended the throne you
                        did one thing which in the opinion of the senate you were right in doing,
                        you sent an embassy to Rome to renew the treaty, but they hold that it would
                        have been better not to renew it than to violate it after it was renewed.
                        You drove Abrupolis, an ally and friend of Rome, out of his kingdom.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> You sheltered the assassins of
                        Arthetaurus, showing that you were glad-I will not say more-that he was
                        murdered. The man whom they killed was of all the Illyrian princes the most
                        loyal to the cause of Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You marched
                        with an army through Thessaly and the district of Malis up to Delphi,
                        against the provisions of the treaty, and you also sent assistance to the
                        Byzantines. You made a secret and separate treaty, ratified by an oath, with
                        the Boeotians, our allies, which was forbidden. As for the Theban envoys,
                        Euersas and Callicritus, who were murdered on their way to Rome, I prefer to
                        enquire who killed them rather than to charge anyone with it. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Who could possibly be considered responsible for
                        the civil war in Aetolia, and the deaths of the leaders, unless it were your
                        party? The devastation of Dolopia was your own doing. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> When Eumenes was returning from Rome to his kingdom he
                        narrowly escaped being butchered at Delphi, like a victim on consecrated
                        ground before the altar. I shrink from saying whom he accuses of this.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I have certain proof that the secret
                        crimes of which your friend at Brundisium gave us information were all
                        communicated to you in writing by your friends in Rome and reported to you
                        by your envoys. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> My saying all this might
                        have been avoided by you, had you taken a different course and not asked us
                        why the armies were coming into Macedonia and why we are stationing
                        garrisons in the different cities. Had we kept silent, we should have shown
                        you less consideration than we have done by a statement of facts. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Out of regard for the friendship which we have
                        inherited from our fathers I shall give you a favourable hearing, and I only
                        wish that you may furnish me with some grounds for my pleading your cause
                        before the senate." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king replied: "A defence which before
                        impartial judges would be a good one, I have now to make before judges who
                        are also accusers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As to the charges
                        brought up against me, some of them I rather think I ought to be proud of,
                        others I am not ashamed to admit, others again, which are simply assertions,
                        it is enough for me simply to deny. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If I
                        were standing my trial under your laws, what evidence could either the
                        Brundisian informer or Eumenes bring against me which would make their
                        accusations appear true rather than false and malicious? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Eumenes, who oppresses so many of his subjects both in
                        his public and private life, has had, I suppose, no other enemy but me, and
                        I have, it seems, been unable to discover a more capable agent for criminal
                        deeds than Rammius, a man whom I had never seen before, and was never to see
                        again. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I have also to account for the
                        deaths of the Thebans, who everybody knows were drowned at sea, and for the
                        death of Arthetaurus; here, however, no charge is brought against me beyond
                        the fact that his murderers found refuge in my dominions. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> I will not protest against the unfairness of this
                        argument, if you in your turn allow that if any refugees have escaped to
                        Italy or to Rome you were the authors of the crimes of which they have been
                        found guilty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If you, in common with all
                        other nations, refuse to admit this, then I shall be with the rest of the
                        world. Good heavens! what boots it for a man to be free to go into exile, if
                        there is nowhere a place where an exile can go? <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Nevertheless, as soon as I was advised by you and
                        ascertained that these men were in Macedonia, I ordered that search should
                        be made for them, and that they should quit the kingdom, and I forbade them
                        ever to cross my frontiers. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> "These charges have been brought against
                        me as though I were a defendant in a criminal trial, but those others touch
                        my conduct as king, and depend upon the interpretation of the treaty which
                        is in force between us. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If that treaty
                        expressly says that not even if anyone levies war against me am I allowed to
                        defend myself and my realm, then I must admit that I have violated the
                        treaty by defending myself in arms against Abrupolis, an ally of Rome.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If, however, it is allowed by treaty
                        and established as a rule of international law that arms may be repelled by
                        arms, what ought I to have done after Abrupolis had devastated the frontiers
                        of my kingdom right up to Amphipolis, and carried off many freeborn persons,
                        a large body of slaves, and many thousand head of cattle? Was I to keep
                        quiet and let him go on till he had carried his arms into Pella and taken
                        possession of my palace? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Yes, but
                        granting that I was justified in opposing him by force, it is said that he
                        ought not to have been vanquished or suffer all the evils which befall the
                        vanquished. Since it was I who was attacked and ran the risk of all these
                        evils, how can he complain of their happening to him who was the cause of
                        the war? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I am not going to defend my
                        coercion of the Dolopians on the same grounds, Romans, because whatever they
                        may have deserved, I exercised my sovereign rights; they were my subjects, a
                        part of my dominions, assigned by your own decree to my father. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> Seeing that they put to death Euphranor, whom I
                        had appointed governor, with such cruelty that death was the lightest of his
                        sufferings, I cannot possibly be thought to have exercised undue or unjust
                        severity-I do not say by you and your federal allies, but-by those who
                        disapprove of cruelty and injustice even towards slaves. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "But when I left Dolopia to visit the
                        cities of Larisa, Antron and Pteleon, as I was in the neighbourhood of
                        Delphi I went up there for the purpose of offering sacrifice in discharge of
                        vows taken long before. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And to make this
                        charge still more serious it is asserted that I went with an army to do, of
                        course, what I now complain of your doing, to occupy the cities and station
                        garrisons in the citadels. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Summon those
                        Greek cities through which I marched, and should anyone, I do not care who
                        complain of any ill-treatment from my soldiery, I will allow it to be said
                        that under the presence of offering sacrifice I had another object in view.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We sent troops to assist the Aetolians
                        and the Byzantines, and we established friendly relations with the
                        Boeotians. In whatever light these measures are regarded, they were not only
                        made known to you through my envoys, but were even on several occasions
                        defended in your senate, where I had some critics not so fair or just as
                        you, Q. Marcius, my hereditary friend and guest. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> But my accuser, Eumenes, had not yet arrived. </p>
                    <p> "This man, by misrepresenting and distorting all my actions, has made them
                        appear suspicious and treacherous, and he tried to persuade you that Greece
                        could not be really free or enjoy the boon of liberty which you have
                        conferred as long as the kingdom of Macedonia remained intact. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> Well, the wheel will come round full turn:
                        somebody will soon be saying that it was to no purpose that Antiochus had
                        been removed beyond the Taurus. Eumenes is a much greater oppressor of Asia
                        than Antiochus ever was, your allies can have no rest as long as the kingdom
                        of Pergamum exists, it stands like a citadel to command all the States round
                        it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I am quite aware that the charges
                        which you, Q. Marcius and A. Atilius, have brought against me, and the
                        replies which I have made to them, are just what the minds and ears of those
                        present choose to make of them, and that it is not my conduct or my motives
                        that are important, but the light in which you view them. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> I am not conscious of having committed any fault
                        knowingly: whatever lapse I may have been guilty of through imprudence can,
                        I am sure, be corrected and amended through these stern admonitions of
                        yours. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At all events I have done nothing
                        which cannot be remedied, nothing for which you should think it necessary to
                        seek redress by force of arms. Otherwise the fame of your clemency and
                        magnanimity has been carried through the world in vain, if for reasons which
                        are hardly worth discussion you take up arms and levy war upon monarchs who
                        are your allies." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcius listened to his speech approvingly
                        and advised him to send an embassy to Rome. The friends of Perseus thought
                        that every possible means should be tried and that nothing that promised
                        hope should be left undone. The only thing left for discussion was how to
                        secure the envoys a safe journey. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was
                        deemed necessary to ask for an armistice; this was what Marcius particularly
                        wished for, it had been his main object in granting the interview, but he
                        raised difficulties and made a great favour of consenting to it. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The fact was the Romans were at the moment quite
                        unready for war-no army, no general-whilst Perseus had made all his
                        preparations and was completely equipped for war and, had he not been
                        blinded by hopes of peace, would have commenced hostilities at the best time
                        for himself and the worst for his enemies. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        After the armistice was declared the Roman commissioners decided to go to
                        Boeotia. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There was much unrest there owing
                        to the action of certain communities. On learning what the Roman
                        commissioners had said, "that it would soon appear which States disapproved
                        of the secret league with the king," they seceded from the national council
                        of Boeotia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First delegates from
                        Chaeronea, and then some from Thebes, met the commissioners while they were
                        still on their journey, and assured them that they were not present at the
                        meeting of the council when that league was formed. The commissioners gave
                        them no reply at the time and told them to follow them to Chalcis. </p>
                    <p> There had been a violent quarrel at Thebes about another matter. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> The election of the magistrates for Boeotia had
                        taken place, and the defeated party in revenge got the population together
                        and passed a decree that the Boeotarchs should not be admitted into any of
                        the cities. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They went in a body to
                        Thespiae where they were admitted without any hesitation. The Thebans
                        changed their minds and recalled them; a decree was then made that the
                        twelve who had without any authority convened the assembly and held a
                        council should be sent into exile. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then
                        the new magistrate, Ismenias, a man of noble family and great influence,
                        issued a decree condemning them to death. They had fled to Chalcis, and from
                        that city they went to the Roman commissioners at Larisa and threw the whole
                        responsibility for the secret understanding with Perseus upon Ismenias.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This led to a party war, delegates
                        from both sides came to the Romans-the exiles, the accusers of Ismenias and
                        Ismenias himself. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After their arrival in Chalcis the first
                        magistrates of the different cities, in accordance with the decrees of their
                        respective councils, denounced the league with Perseus, to the great
                        gratification of the Romans, and declared themselves on the side of Rome.
                        Ismenias thought that the right course to adopt would be for the Boeotian
                        nation as a whole to place itself under the suzerainty of Rome. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> This led to a quarrel, and if he had not taken
                        refuge at the commissioners' tribunal he would have had a narrow escape from
                        being killed by the exiles and their supporters. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Thebes, the capital of Boeotia, was itself in a state
                        of great excitement, one faction trying to bring the city over to the king,
                        the other to the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> People from
                        Coronea and Haliartus had flocked in crowds to Thebes to defend the decree
                        for alliance with the king. But the magistrates were firm, they pointed to
                        the final defeats of Philip and Antiochus as proving the power and good
                        fortune of the Roman government, and the citizens were at last convinced.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They decreed that the alliance with
                        the king should be put an end to, and sent those who had advocated
                        friendship with Perseus to make their peace with the commissioners, and
                        ordered the citizens to place themselves at the disposal of the
                        commissioners. Marcius and Atilius were glad to hear this decision of the
                        Thebans, and advised them and the other cities to send each their own envoys
                        to renew friendly relations with Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        They insisted on the restoration of the exiles as the first thing, and
                        issued a decree condemning the authors of the alliance with Perseus. Thus,
                        what they wanted most of all, the dissolution of the Boeotian League, was
                        effected. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They then left for the
                        Peloponnese and sent for Ser. Cornelius to Chalcis. A council was summoned
                        to meet them at Argos. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They only asked the
                        Achaeans to furnish them with 1000 soldiers. These were sent to garrison
                        Chalcis until the Roman army landed in Greece. Having thus completed their
                        business in Greece, Marcius and Atilius returned to Rome at the commencement
                        of winter. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A commission was sent about the same time
                        to visit Asia and the islands adjoining. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The commissioners were Tiberius Claudius, Sp. Postumius and M. Junius. As
                        they went about amongst the allies they urged them to join the Romans in the
                        war against Perseus, and the wealthier and more powerful the state the
                        greater attention they paid to it, since the smaller ones would be led by
                        the greater. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Rhodians were regarded as
                        the most important of all, because they were in a position to give not only
                        moral support but material assistance. They had, acting on the advice of
                        Hegesilochus, got forty ships ready for service. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> When he was acting as supreme magistrate-"prytanis"
                        they call him-he had, after many speeches, induced the Rhodians to abandon
                        all those hoses of support from monarchs, which had so often proved vain,
                        and hold to the alliance with Rome, the only one in the whole world which
                        they could depend on for strength and fidelity. A war with Perseus was
                        imminent, the Romans would look for the same naval armament that they had
                        seen lately in the war with Antiochus and in the previous war with Philip.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Unless they began at once to refit
                        their ships and provide them with crews, they would be in all the hurry and
                        confusion of making their fleet ready for sea when it was to be actually
                        sent off. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was all the more important
                        that this should be done that they might give a practical proof of the
                        falseness of the charges which Eumenes had brought against them. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> These arguments had their effect and when the
                        Roman commissioners arrived they were shown a fleet of forty vessels quite
                        ready for sea, a clear proof that they had not waited for the Romans to spur
                        them on. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The work of these commissioners
                        in securing the support of the cities in Asia was of the utmost importance.
                        Decimius alone returned without any success; he was widely suspected of
                        having received bribes from Gentius and the Illyrian princes. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On his return to Macedonia, Perseus sent
                        envoys to Rome to carry on the peace negotiations which he had begun with
                        Marcius, and he gave them letters to take to Byzantium and Rhodes. The
                        purport of the letters was the same for all, he had had an interview with
                        the Roman commissioners. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> What he had heard
                        and said was put in such a way as to make it appear that he had the best of
                        the argument. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In their address to the
                        Rhodians, his envoys said that they were confident that there would be
                        peace, for it was on the advice of Marcius and Atilius that they were sent
                        to Rome. If the Romans in violation of the treaty proceeded to war, then the
                        Rhodians must use all their influence and all their power to restore peace,
                        but if their appeals proved fruitless, then they must make it their business
                        to prevent the power and authority over the whole world from passing into
                        the hands of one single nation. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That was
                        the concern of all the nations, but especially of the Rhodians, by how much
                        the more they surpassed other nations in greatness and prosperity, but they
                        would be enslaved and helpless if they paid no regard to any but the Romans.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The letter and the address of the
                        envoys received a favourable hearing, but they did not avail to make the
                        Rhodians change their minds; the influence and authority of the better
                        citizens prevailed. The answer which they decided to give was to the effect
                        that the Rhodians wanted peace; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> if there
                        was war, the king need not expect or ask for anything from them, since he
                        was trying to break up the long-standing friendship between them and the
                        Romans, a friendship which was the fruit of many valuable services rendered
                        in both peace and war. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On their way back from Rhodes they visited
                        some of the cities of Boeotia-Thebes, Coronea and Haliartus-which it was
                        supposed had been forced against their will to abandon their alliance with
                        Perseus and join the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They made no
                        impression on the Thebans, although there was a strong feeling amongst them
                        against the Romans owing to the severe sentences passed on their leaders and
                        the restoration of the exiles. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But at
                        Coronea and at Haliartus there was a kind of inborn affection for the
                        dynasty, and they sent to Macedonia to ask for a garrison that they might
                        protect themselves against the wanton aggression of Thebes. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The king told them in reply that as there was an
                        armistice between him and the Romans, he could not send any troops to them;
                        still, he advised them to revenge any wrongs that the Thebans might inflict
                        on them, but in such a way as not to give the Romans any pretext for venting
                        their wrath on him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On their return to Rome, Marcius and
                        Atilius reported the results of their mission to the senate in the Capitol.
                        The thing for which they took most credit to themselves was the way in which
                        they had hoodwinked the king by holding out hopes of peace. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> He was so fully provided with all the means of war,
                        whilst they themselves had nothing ready, that all the strategic positions
                        could have been occupied by him before their armies had landed in Greece.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The interval of the armistice,
                        however, would place them on equal terms, he would no longer have the
                        advantage of preparation, the Romans would begin the war better equipped in
                        every way. They had also succeeded by a clever stroke in breaking up the
                        national council of Boeotia, they could never again be united in support of
                        the Macedonians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A good many of the
                        senators approved of these proceedings as showing very skilful management.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The elder senators, however, and
                        others who had not forgotten the moral standards of earlier days, said that
                        they failed to recognise anything of the Roman character in these
                        negotiations. "Our ancestors," they said, "did not conduct their wars by
                        lurking in ambush and making attacks at night, nor by feigning flight and
                        then turning back upon the enemy when he was off his guard. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They did not pride themselves on cunning more than on
                        true courage, it was their custom to declare war before commencing it,
                        sometimes even to give the enemy notice of the time and place where they
                        would fight. This sense of honour made them warn Pyrrhus against his
                        physician, who was <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> plotting against his
                        life, it made them hand over to the Faliscans as a prisoner the betrayer of
                        their children. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This is the true Roman
                        spirit, there is nothing here of the cunning of the Carthaginians or the
                        cleverness of the Greeks, who pride themselves more in deceiving an enemy
                        than in overcoming him in fair fight. Occasionally more can be gained for
                        the time being by craft than by courage, but it is only when you have forced
                        your enemy to confess that he has been overcome not by cleverness nor by
                        accident, but after a fair trial of strength where the rules of war are
                        properly observed-it is only then that his spirit is broken and his defeat a
                        lasting one." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such were the views of the
                        older senators, who regarded the new policy with disfavour, but the majority
                        preferred expediency to honour and signified their approval of what Marcius
                        had done. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It was decided that he should
                        be sent back to Greece with the fifty quinqueremes, and should be at full
                        liberty to act as he thought best in the interest of the republic. A.
                        Atilius was also sent to occupy Larisa in Thessaly, as there was the danger
                        of Perseus sending a garrison there on the expiration of the armistice, and
                        so keeping the capital of Thessaly under his power. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Atilius sent for 2000 infantry from the army of Cnaeus
                        Sicinius to hold the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> P. Lentulus,
                        who had returned from Achaia, was supplied with 300 Italian troops to look
                        after Thebes and overawe Boeotia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These preliminary measures carried out, it
                        was agreed that the senate should give audience to the king's envoys,
                        although war was now definitely resolved upon. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The envoys repeated almost the same arguments which the
                        king had used in his conference with Marcius. Their answer to the charge of
                        plotting against the life of Eumenes was the most laboured part of their
                        speech and the one which made the least impression, for the facts were
                        beyond dispute. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The rest of their speech
                        was apologetic and deprecatory, but their hearers refused to be either
                        convinced or persuaded. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were warned
                        to leave Rome at once and Italy within thirty days. The consul, P. Licinius,
                        who was to command in Macedonia, was warned to fix as early a day as
                        possible for the assembling of his army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        C. Lucretius, who had been put in command of the fleet, sailed from Rome
                        with only forty quinqueremes, as it was decided that some of the refitted
                        ships should be kept at the City for different purposes. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He sent his brother Marcus with one quinquereme to take
                        up the ships which the allies were bound by treaty to furnish and join the
                        main fleet at Cephallania. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> One trireme was
                        provided by Rhegium, two by Locri, and four came from the Sallentines of
                        Uria. Sailing along the coast of Italy and round the furthest headland of
                        Calabria, he crossed the Ionian Sea to Dyrrhachium. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Here he obtained ten vessels from Dyrrhachium itself,
                        twelve from Issa and fifty-four light vessels which belonged to Gentius and
                        which M. Lucretius affected to believe had been got together for the use of
                        the Romans. Carrying them all off, he reached Corcyra after a three days'
                        voyage, and then went direct to Cephallania. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> C. Lucretius sailed from Naples and reached Cephallania in five days.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here the fleet anchored, waiting till
                        the land army had crossed and the transports which had fallen out had
                        rejoined. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now that the consul, P. Licinius,
                        after offering up the prayers in the Capitol, rode out of the City wearing
                        the paludamentum. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This departure of the
                        commander-in-chief was always invested with dignity and grandeur, but now
                        especially all eyes and hearts were turned to the consul as they escorted
                        him on his way to meet a powerful enemy whose reputation for courage and
                        success was spread far and wide. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was
                        not only to honour their chief magistrate that the citizens had collected
                        together, but also to see the leader to whose wisdom and authority they had
                        entrusted the supreme defence of the commonwealth. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> They thought of the chances of war, the caprice of
                        Fortune, the risks and uncertainty of battle the defeats and successes of
                        the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> past-defeats often incurred by the
                        ignorance and rashness of commanders, successes again won by skill and
                        courage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Who of mortal men could know the
                        capability of the consul whom they were sending to war or the fortune which
                        would attend him? Would they presently see him with his victorious army
                        going up to the Capitol in triumphal procession to do homage to those
                        deities from whom he is now departing, or are those deities going to allow
                        that happiness to the enemy? The enemy, again, whom he was going to meet was
                        the far-famed Perseus, the king of the Macedonians, a nation distinguished
                        in war, and the son of Philip, who amongst his many victories had even in
                        the war with Rome added to his reputation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Ever since he ascended the throne, the name of Perseus was continually on
                        men's lips as they spoke of the coming war. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> With these thoughts in their minds men of all sorts and conditions
                        attended the departure of the consul. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> C.
                        Claudius and Q. Mucius, ex-consuls and now military tribunes, were sent with
                        him, and three young nobles, P. Lentulus, and the two Acidini, one the son
                        of Marcus and the other the son of Lucius Manlius. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The consul joined his army at Brundisium and sailing
                        with his whole force to Nymphaeum fixed his camp in the neighbourhood of
                        Apollonia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="50" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days before this, after the return
                        of his envoys had dashed his hopes of peace, Perseus held a council of war.
                        Opposing views led to considerable discussion. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Some thought that they ought to consent to pay an
                        indemnity if it was imposed upon them, or cede a portion of their territory
                        if this were insisted on; in fact, whatever sacrifice was necessary for the
                        sake of peace ought to be made, and no step taken which would expose the
                        king and his subjects to the hazard of fortune where such vital issues were
                        involved. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If he were left in the certain
                        possession of the crown, many things might happen in the future which would
                        enable him not only to recover what he had lost, but even to become
                        formidable to those of whom he now stood in fear. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The majority, however, were much more defiant. Any
                        concessions made, they declared, would involve the loss of the kingdom.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans were not in need of money
                        or territory, but this they knew, that while all human affairs were liable
                        to many accidents, kingdoms and empires were especially so. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> They had shattered the power of the Carthaginians and
                        saddled them with a very powerful monarch to keep them down. They had sent
                        Antiochus and his posterity into banishment beyond the Taurus mountains.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The kingdom of Macedonia alone
                        remained, a near neighbour and ready, whenever Rome lost the good fortune
                        she once enjoyed, to animate the kings of Macedonia with their ancient
                        courage. Whilst, therefore, his realm was still intact, Perseus must decide
                        between two alternatives. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Either he must
                        be prepared to strip himself of all his power, by making one concession
                        after another, and, driven from his kingdom into exile, must beg the Romans
                        to allow him Samothrace or some other island, where, having outlived his
                        kingship, he might grow old in privacy, disgrace and poverty; <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> or else vindicate his fortunes and his dignity in
                        arms, and confront as a brave man ought to do all that the chances of war
                        can bring, and if victorious, deliver the world from its subjection to Rome.
                        The expulsion of the Romans from Greece would not be a more wonderful thing
                        than the expulsion of Hannibal from Italy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> They could not see how he who had resisted his brother to the uttermost
                        in his unlawful attempt to seize the crown could with any consistency resign
                        it to men of alien blood. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The question
                        between peace and war can only arise so far as all are agreed that as there
                        is nothing more disgraceful than to surrender the throne without striking a
                        blow, so there is nothing more glorious than for a king to face all risks in
                        defence of his sovereign dignity and majesty. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="51" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This council was held at Pella, the
                        capital of Macedonia. "Let us then," said Perseus, "wage war with the help
                        of the gods, since thus you decide." <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Written orders were despatched to all his generals and he assembled the
                        whole of his forces at Citium, a town in Macedonia. After sacrificing in
                        regal style one hundred victims to Minerva, whom they call Alcidemos, he set
                        out for Citium, accompanied by a number of court nobles and his bodyguard.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The whole of the army, both
                        Macedonians and auxiliaries, were assembled there. The camp was fixed in
                        front of the city and he drew up all his soldiers in the plain. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The total number of those who bore arms was
                        43,000, nearly half of whom formed the phalanx; Hippias of Beroea was in
                        command. Out of the whole force of caetrati, 2000 men in the prime of
                        strength and manhood were selected to form a body known as the "agema,"
                        their commanders were Leonnatus and Thrasippus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Antiphilus of Edessa was in command of the rest of the
                        caetrati, numbering about 3000 men. The Paeonians and the contingents from
                        Paroria and Parstrymonia, places in the lowlands of Thrace, and the
                        Agrianes, including some Thracian immigrants, made up a force of about 3000.
                        They had been armed and <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> mustered by
                        Didas the Paeonian, the murderer of the young Demetrius. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> There were also 2000 Gauls under Asclepiodotus, a
                        native of Heraclea in Sintice. Three thousand "free" Thracians had their own
                        leader, and about the same number of Cretans followed their own generals,
                        Susus of Phalasarna and Syllus of Gnossus. Leonides the Lacedaemonian was at
                        the head of a mixed force of Greeks. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                        was said to be of royal blood, and after his letter to Perseus had been
                        seized, had been sentenced to banishment in a full council of the Achaeans.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Aetolians and Boeotians, who, all
                        told, did not amount to more than 500 men, were under the command of Lyco,
                        an Achaean. Out of these contingents drawn from so many people and tribes, a
                        force of about 12,000 men was formed. Perseus had collected 3000 cavalry out
                        of the whole of Macedonia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Cotys, the son
                        of Suthis and king of the Odrysae, had come in with a picked force of 1000
                        horse and about the same number of infantry. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Thus the total number of the army was 39,000 infantry
                        and 4000 cavalry. It was generally admitted that, next to the army which
                        Alexander the Great had led into Asia, no Macedonian king had ever possessed
                        so large a force. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="52" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was six-and-twenty years since the
                        peace which Philip sought had been vouchsafed to him. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> During all that time Macedonia had been undisturbed and
                        a new generation had grown up, ripe for military service, and in the small
                        wars with their Thracian neighbours, which exercised rather than exhausted
                        them, they had been constantly trained and disciplined. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The prospect of a war with Rome, which had during the
                        whole period been cherished by Philip and then by Perseus, had led to
                        everything being in a state of readiness and efficiency. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The army performed a few movements, not as regular
                        maneuvers, but simply in order to avoid the appearance of only standing
                        under arms. Perseus then called them, armed as they were, to stand round on
                        parade, and ascended the tribunal with his two sons by his side; <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> the elder one, Philip, his brother by birth, his
                        son by adoption, the younger one, Alexander, his son by birth. He exhorted
                        his soldiers to show their courage in the war, and enumerated the injuries
                        which the Romans had inflicted on his father and on himself. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> His father had been compelled by all the
                        indignities he had suffered to resume hostilities; in the midst of his
                        preparations he had been struck down by fate. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans sent envoys to him (Perseus) to open
                        negotiations and at the same time sent soldiers to occupy the cities of
                        Greece. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the winter was wasted over a
                        conference, ostensibly to bring about a peaceful settlement, but really to
                        give them time to make their preparations. Now the consul was coming with
                        two Roman legions, each with its complement of 300 cavalry and contingents
                        furnished by the allies of about the same strength. Even if the troops sent
                        by Eumenes and Masinissa were counted in, there would not be more than 7000
                        infantry and 2000 cavalry. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The king
                        proceeded: "You have heard what the strength of the enemy is; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> now look at your own army, its superiority in
                        numbers and in the quality of the soldiers as compared with the raw
                        conscripts hastily embodied for this war, soldiers who have from their
                        boyhood been trained in the school of war, disciplined and hardened by so
                        many campaigns. Lydians, Phrygians and Numidians are furnishing troops for
                        the Romans; we have on our side the Thracians, and the most warlike of all
                        nations the Gauls. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Their arms are just
                        what each poverty-stricken soldier has provided himself with; you
                        Macedonians are supplied from the royal arsenal with arms manufactured
                        through all those years under my father's direction and at his cost. Their
                        supplies will have to be brought from a distance and will be exposed to all
                        the chances and accidents of the sea; we have for ten years been storing up
                        money and corn in addition to the revenue from the mines. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Everything which has been provided by the kindness of
                        heaven or by the care and forethought of their king, the Macedonians have in
                        full and overflowing measure. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> You must
                        have the courage which your ancestors had when after subjugating the whole
                        of Europe <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> they crossed over to Asia and
                        opened up by their arms an unknown world, and never ceased to conquer until
                        they were hemmed in by the purple ocean and there was nothing more to
                        conquer. Ay, but now it is not for the remotest shores of India but for the
                        possession of Macedonia that Fortune has called us to this contest.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> When the Romans were at war with my
                        father they put forward the specious pretext that they were liberating
                        Greece, now they are openly aiming at the enslavement of Macedonia in order
                        that Rome may have no monarch on its borders, no nation glorious in war
                        retaining possession of its arms. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> These
                        must be surrendered to your haughty and domineering masters, and your king
                        and kingdom as well, if you are willing to lay aside all thoughts of war and
                        execute their commands." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="53" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There had been frequent bursts of applause
                        all through the speech, but at this point such a shout of indignation and
                        defiance arose, and encouraging cheers for the king, that he brought his
                        speech to a close, only adding that they must be prepared to march, as there
                        was a report that the Romans were already advancing from Nymphaeum.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the troops were dismissed he
                        proceeded to give audience to the deputations from the Macedonian cities who
                        had made offers of money and corn, each according to their ability.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He thanked them all, and excused them
                        from making any contribution as the royal stores were sufficient for all
                        requirements. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He only requested them to
                        furnish wagons to carry the artillery, the enormous quantity of missiles
                        that had been got ready, and other apparatus of war. He now set forward with
                        the whole of his army in the direction of Eordaea, and encamped by Lake
                        Begorritis. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next day he reached the
                        Haliacmon in Elimea. From there he crossed the Cambunian Mountains through a
                        narrow pass and came down to Azorus, Pythoum and Doliche; <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> the natives call these three towns the Tripolis. Here
                        he met with a short delay because they had given hostages to the Larisaeans;
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> in face, however, of the danger
                        threatening them, they made their surrender. He accepted their submission
                        graciously, feeling quite sure that Perrhaebia would do the same. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The inhabitants made no show of resistance and he
                        captured the city as soon as he arrived there. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Cyretia he was forced to attack, and was actually
                        repulsed in the first day's assault by a vigorous charge of armed men from
                        the gates. The next day he attacked in full strength, and before night
                        received the submission of the entire population. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="54" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Mylae, the next town he came to, was so
                        strongly fortified that confidence in the impregnability of their walls made
                        the townsmen defiant; they were not content to close their gates to the
                        king, they even hurled taunts and insults upon him and the Macedonians.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This made their enemy all the more
                        furious in the assault, and the citizens, despairing of pardon, were all the
                        more resolute in their defence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So for
                        three days the city was attacked, with the utmost determination on both
                        sides. The vast numbers of the Macedonians made it easy for them to take
                        their turn in the fighting; the same defenders had to guard the walls night
                        and day, and were becoming exhausted not only by their many wounds, but also
                        by want of sleep and incessant exertion. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        On the fourth day, while the scaling-ladders were being raised against the
                        walls and the gate was being attacked with greater violence than usual, the
                        townsmen, after driving the danger from the walls, ran down to defend the
                        gate and made a sudden sortie. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This was
                        due more to impetuosity and rage than to any well-grounded confidence in
                        their strength and, reduced as they were in numbers and with weary and
                        worn-out bodies, they were repulsed by the enemy who was fresh and vigorous.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They turned and fled, and in their
                        flight through the open gate let in the enemy. In this way the city was
                        taken and sacked; even the free population, as many as survived, were sold
                        as slaves. </p>
                    <p> After wrecking and burning most of the city, Perseus marched on to Phalanna,
                        and on the following day arrived at Gyrto. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        On learning that T. Minucius Rufus and the Thessalian captain-general
                        Hippias had entered this place with a body of troops he did not even attempt
                        an assault, but marched past it and captured Elatia and Gonnus, the
                        inhabitants being utterly dismayed by his unlooked-for appearance.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Both towns are situated at the
                        entrance to the Vale of Tempe, Gonnus lying further within. He garrisoned it
                        with a strong force of infantry and cavalry, and in addition left it
                        defended with a triple moat and rampart. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Marching on to Sycurium he decided to await the enemy there and ordered the
                        army to collect corn in all parts of the hostile territory. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Sycurium is at the foot of Mount Ossa on the
                        south side, it overlooks the plains of Thessaly; behind it lie Macedonia and
                        Magnesia. In addition to these advantages it possesses a perfectly healthy
                        climate and a perennial supply of water which flows <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> in abundance from the many springs round. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="55" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this time the Roman consul was on
                        his way with his army to Thessaly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whilst
                        marching through Epirus he found the country clear and open, but when he had
                        crossed the frontiers of Athamania he had to advance over rough and almost
                        impassable ground. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was with the utmost
                        difficulty and by short marches that he struggled through to Gomphi. If with
                        horses and men knocked up and an army of recruits he had been met by the
                        king with a couple of hundred men in order of battle, at a time and place of
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> his own choosing, the Romans
                        themselves do not deny that they would have suffered a terrible defeat.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After Gomphi was reached without any
                        fighting, there was not only rejoicing at having surmounted a dangerous
                        pass, but also a feeling of contempt for an enemy who was so blind to his
                        advantages. After duly performing the sacrifices and giving out corn to the
                        soldiers, the consul stayed there a few days to rest both man and beast.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On learning that the Macedonians were
                        dispersed far and wide devastating the fields of his allies, he led his
                        soldiers, who were now sufficiently refreshed, towards Larisa. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> When about three miles from the place he fixed
                        his camp at Tripolis-the natives call it Scaea-on the Peneus. Eumenes
                        arrived at this time with his ships at Chalcis. He was accompanied by his
                        brothers Attalus and Athenaeus, the other brother, Philetaerus, being left
                        at Pergamum to protect the kingdom. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From
                        Chalcis he went with Attalus and a force of 4000 infantry and 1000 cavalry
                        to join the consul, 2000 infantry being left in Chalcis under the command of
                        Athenaeus. Other contingents came in from all the Greek States, most of them
                        so small that they have passed into oblivion. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Apollonia sent 300 cavalry and 100 infantry; the
                        cavalry from the whole of Aetolia made up one division, and the Thessalians,
                        who it was hoped would send their entire force, had not more than 300
                        cavalry in the Roman camp. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Achaeans
                        furnished 1500 fighting men, mostly armed in the Cretan fashion. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="56" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> C. Lucretius, commanding the fleet at
                        Cephallania, sent instructions to his brother Marcus to take his ships past
                        the Malean promontory to Chalcis. He himself went on board a trireme and
                        made for the Gulf of Corinth with the view of controlling the position in
                        Boeotia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> His progress was somewhat slow
                        owing to the state of his health. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When M.
                        Lucretius brought up at Chalcis he learnt that Haliartus was being attacked
                        by P. Lentulus, and he sent a message ordering him in the praetor's name to
                        raise the siege. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had commenced
                        operations with those Boeotian troops who were on the side of the Romans,
                        and now he retired from the walls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        abandonment of this attack left the ground free for another; M. Lucretius at
                        once invested the place with a force of 10,000 marines and 2000 of the
                        troops under Athenaeus. Whilst they were getting ready for the assault the
                        praetor appeared on the scene from Creusa. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The ships furnished by the allies were now assembled at Chalcis-two Punic
                        quinqueremes, two triremes from the Pontic Heraclea, four from Chalcedon,
                        the same number from Samos and also five Rhodian quadriremes. As there was
                        no naval war, the praetor sent the vessels back to the various allies.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Q. Marcius also arrived at Chalcis
                        with his fleet, after capturing Alope and storming Larisa Cremaste. While
                        this was the position of affairs in Boeotia, Perseus, as stated above, was
                        encamped at Sycurium. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After he had
                        collected corn from all the country round he sent a detachment to ravage the
                        fields of Pherae, in the hope that as the Romans were drawn further
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> from their base to help the cities
                        of their allies he might be able to surprise them. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> As, however, he found that they were in no way
                        disturbed by his sudden movements, he distributed the plunder, including
                        some prisoners, amongst the soldiers; as it consisted mainly of cattle it
                        provided them with a feast. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="57" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul and the king both held councils
                        of war at the same time, to decide where to commence operations. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The Macedonians had grown bolder after they found
                        that the enemy allowed them to ravage the Pheraean country without offering
                        any resistance, and they thought they ought to go straight up to the Roman
                        camp and give their enemy no room for further delay. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans, on the other hand, felt that their
                        inactivity was damaging their prestige with their allies, and they were
                        particularly disgusted at no help having been given to the Pheraeans.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whilst they were deliberating what
                        steps to take-Eumenes and Attalus were both present-a messenger came in hot
                        haste to say that the enemy were approaching in great force. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The council at once broke up and the signal was
                        given for the soldiers to arm. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A hundred
                        cavalry and the same number of slingers were in the meanwhile sent forward
                        to reconnoitre. It was about the fourth hour of the day, and when he was
                        little more than a mile distant from the Roman camp, Perseus ordered the
                        infantry to halt whilst he himself rode forward with the cavalry and light
                        infantry; Cotys also and the commanders of the other auxiliaries rode
                        forward with him. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were within half a
                        mile of the camp when they caught sight of the enemy cavalry. There were two
                        troops, largely made up of Gauls, under Cassignatus, and about 150 light
                        infantry, partly Mysian, partly Cretan. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        The king halted, uncertain as to the enemy's strength. Then he sent on from
                        the main body two squadrons of Thracian and two of Macedonian horse,
                        together with two Cretan and two Thracian cohorts. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> As the two sides were equal in point of numbers, and no
                        fresh troops came up on either side, the engagement ended in a drawn battle.
                        About thirty of Eumenes' men were killed, amongst them Cassignatus, the
                        Gaulish commander. Perseus then took his force back to Sycurium. The next
                        day the king marched them to the same spot, and at the same hour. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> This time they were followed by water carts, for
                        on their twelve miles' march they were without water and smothered in dust;
                        it was quite clear that if they had to fight as soon as they came in view of
                        the enemy, they would do so whilst suffering from thirst. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans retired their outposts within their lines
                        and remained quiet, whereupon the king's troops returned to camp. They did
                        this for several days, hoping that the Roman cavalry would attack their rear
                        during their withdrawal, whilst they were at a considerable distance from
                        their own <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> camp) then the king's troops,
                        who were superior in cavalry and light infantry, would turn and face the
                        enemy wherever they were. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="58" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As he had not succeeded in his attempt to
                        draw the Romans, the king moved his camp to within a distance of five miles
                        from the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At dawn the infantry were
                        drawn up on the same ground as before and the whole of the cavalry and light
                        infantry marched towards the Roman camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The sight of a cloud of dust, larger and nearer than usual, created some
                        excitement amongst the Romans. At first the news was hardly credited because
                        on all previous occasions the enemy had never appeared before the fourth
                        hour of the day, and now it was sunrise. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        When all doubt was dispelled by the many shouts and men running from the
                        gates there was great confusion. The military tribunes, the officers of the
                        allied troops and the centurions hurried to the headquarters tent; the
                        soldiers ran to their own tents. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Perseus
                        had drawn up his men less than a mile and a half from the Roman lines round
                        a hill called Callinicus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Cotys commanded
                        the left wing with the whole of his native troops, the light infantry being
                        disposed between the ranks of the cavalry. On the right were the Macedonian
                        cavalry, the Cretans being intermixed with them in the same way. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> This body was under the command of Midon of
                        Beroea; the supreme command of the whole cavalry force was in the hands of
                        Meno of Antigonea. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Flanking the two wings
                        were the king's cavalry and a mixed body of auxiliaries drawn from different
                        nationalities. Patrocles and Didas were in charge of these troops.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In the centre of the whole line was
                        the king surrounded by the "agema" and the troops of the "sacred" cavalry.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In front of these he posted the
                        slingers and javelin men, 400 in all, under the command of Ion and
                        Neoptolemus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The consul formed his
                        infantry into line inside the rampart, and sent out the whole of the cavalry
                        and light infantry; they were drawn up in front of the rampart. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> The right wing was commanded by the consul's
                        brother Caius, and comprised the whole of the Italian cavalry with the
                        velites interspersed among them. On the left M. Valerius Laevinus had the
                        cavalry and light infantry from the various cities in Greece. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The centre was held by Quintus Mucius with a
                        picked body of volunteer cavalry. On their front were posted 200 Gaulish
                        troopers and 300 Cyrtians from the auxiliary troops brought by Eumenes; 400
                        Thessalian cavalry were drawn up a short distance beyond the Roman left.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Attalus and Eumenes took ground with
                        the whole of their force in the rear between the hindmost rank and the
                        rampart. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="59" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In this formation the two armies, almost
                        equally matched in the numbers of their cavalry and light infantry, engaged.
                        The battle was begun by the slingers and javelin men, who were in front of
                        the whole line. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> First of all the
                        Thracians, like wild beasts kept in cages and suddenly released, set up a
                        deafening roar and charged the Italian cavalry on the right wing with such
                        fury that, in spite of their experience of war and their native
                        fearlessness, they threw them into disorder. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> The infantry on both sides snapped the lances of the cavalry with their
                        swords, cut at the legs of the horses and stabbed them in the flanks.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Perseus, charging the centre,
                        dislodged the Greeks at the first onslaught, and pressed heavily upon them
                        as they fell back. The Thessalian cavalry had been in reserve, a little
                        distance from the extreme left, outside the fighting and simply watching it,
                        but when the day began to go against them they were of the greatest use.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For by slowly retiring, and keeping
                        their ranks unbroken, they formed a junction with Eumenes' troops, and so
                        afforded a safe retreat within their united ranks to the allied cavalry as
                        they fled in disorder. As the enemy slackened in the pursuit they even
                        ventured to advance and protected many of the fugitives whom they met. The
                        king's troops, separated by the pursuit in all directions, did not venture
                        to come to close quarters with men who were keeping their formation and
                        advancing in a steady line. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The king,
                        victorious in this cavalry action, shouted to his men that if they gave him
                        a little more help the war would be over, and very opportunely for his own
                        encouragement and that of his men, the phalanx appeared on the scene.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Hippias and Leonnatus, hearing of the
                        success of the cavalry, had hastily brought it up on their own initiative,
                        that they might take their part in an action so daringly begun. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> The king was hovering between hope and fear at
                        attempting so great a task, when Euander the Cretan, who had been his
                        instrument in the attempt upon Eumenes' life at Delphi, ran up to him.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He had seen the massed infantry
                        advancing with their standards, and he solemnly warned the king not to be so
                        elated by his good fortune as to stake everything upon a chance which there
                        was no necessity for him to risk. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If he
                        would be contented with what he had gained and kept quiet for the day he
                        would have peace with honour, or if he preferred war, he would have very
                        many allies who would follow his fortunes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> The king was more inclined to this course, so after thanking Euander for
                        his advice, he ordered the standards to be reversed, the infantry to march
                        back to camp and the "retire" to be sounded for the cavalry. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="60" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On that day there fell on the side of the
                        Romans 200 cavalry and not less than 2000 infantry; about 600 were made
                        prisoners. Out of the king's army 20 cavalry and 40 infantry were killed.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On their return to camp the victors
                        were all in high spirits, but the Thracians surpassed all in the insolence
                        of their joy. They returned to camp singing and carrying the heads of their
                        enemies fixed on their spears. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Amongst the
                        Romans there was not only grief at their defeat, but a fear lest the enemy
                        should make a sudden attack on the camp. Eumenes urged the consul to
                        transfer the camp to the opposite bank of the Peneus, that they might have
                        the protection of the river until the shaken soldiers could recover their
                        morale. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul felt bitterly the
                        disgrace of admitting that he was afraid, but yielding to reason, he took
                        the troops across in the dead of night and entrenched himself on the further
                        bank. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The next day the king marched up to
                        provoke his enemy to battle. When he noticed their camp safely fixed across
                        the river he owned that he was wrong in not pressing upon his foe the day
                        before, but still more so in remaining inactive through the night, for had
                        he sent only his light infantry <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> against
                        the enemy during the confusion caused by the passage of the river, their
                        force would to a large extent have been wiped out. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Now that their camp was in a safe position the Romans
                        were relieved from the danger of an immediate attack, but they were much
                        depressed, especially at their loss of prestige. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In the council at the headquarters tent, each in turn
                        threw the blame on the Aetolians, it was with them that the panic and flight
                        began, and the rest of the Greek contingents followed the example of the
                        Aetolians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Five Aetolian officers, said to
                        have been the first who were seen to turn their backs on the enemy, were
                        sent to Rome. The Thessalians were commended before the whole army and their
                        leaders were rewarded for their bravery. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="61" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The spoils taken from the fallen were
                        brought to the king. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These he gave to his
                        soldiers; to some splendid armour, to others horses, and to some prisoners.
                        There were over 1500 shields, the cuirasses and coats of mail numbered more
                        than 1000, the helmets, swords, and missiles of all kinds were much more
                        numerous. The value of these gifts, ample and welcome as they were, was
                        enhanced by the speech which the king made to his army. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> "You have pronounced," he said, "upon the issue of the
                        war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The best part of the Roman army,
                        their cavalry, who used to boast that they were invincible, have been routed
                        by you. Their cavalry are the flower of their youth, the nursery of their
                        senate, the men whose fathers are chosen as consuls, from whom their
                        commanders are selected; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> these are the men
                        whose spoils we have now distributed amongst you. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> And no less a victory have you won over their infantry,
                        those legions who, withdrawn from your reach in a nocturnal flight, filled
                        the river with confusion and disorder like shipwrecked men swimming for
                        their lives. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The passage of the Peneus
                        will be easier for us, the pursuers, than it was for them in their haste to
                        get away, and as soon as we have crossed we shall attack their camp, which
                        we should have taken today if they had not fled. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Or if they are willing to fight in the open field, look
                        for the same result in an infantry battle which you have seen in the cavalry
                        action." <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Those who had taken part in the
                        victory and were carrying the enemy's spoils on their shoulders listened
                        eagerly to the recital of their exploits and formed their hopes of the
                        future from what had already happened. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        The infantry, too, especially the men of the phalanx, were fired by the
                        glory which their comrades had won, and looked forward to the opportunity of
                        doing their king signal service and winning equal glory from their
                        vanquished foe. The soldiers were dismissed, and the next day he marched
                        away and fixed his camp at Mopselus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This
                        is a hill situated at the entrance of the Vale of Tempe and commands a wide
                        view of the plain of Larisa. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="62" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Romans without quitting the river
                        moved their camp into a safer position. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Whilst they were there Misagenes the Numidian came in with 1000 cavalry, the
                        same number of infantry and 22 elephants. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The king was holding a council to decide upon the future conduct of the war,
                        and as his exultation over his victory had cooled down, some of his friends
                        ventured to give him advice. They argued that it would be better for him to
                        take advantage of his good fortune by securing an honourable peace than to
                        buoy himself up with idle hopes and so expose himself to chances that might
                        be irrevocable. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To set a measure to one's
                        prosperity and not to place too much confidence in the smiling fortune of
                        the hour is the part of a wise man who has achieved a deserved success.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Let him send men to the consul with
                        powers to make fresh proposals for peace on the same terms on which his
                        father Philip had accepted peace from the victorious T. Quinctius.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There could be no grander close to the
                        war than the late memorable battle and no surer grounds for hopes of a
                        lasting peace than those which would make the Romans, disheartened as they
                        were by their defeat, ready to come to terms. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> If the Romans should then, with their inbred
                        stubbornness, reject fair terms, gods and men would alike bear witness to
                        the moderation of Perseus and the invincible arrogance of the Romans. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The king never disliked advice of this
                        character, and this policy was approved by the majority of the council. The
                        deputation to the consul were received in audience in a full council.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They asked for peace, and promised
                        that Perseus would give the Romans the amount of tribute which had been
                        agreed upon with his father. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Such were
                        their instructions. In the discussion which followed on their withdrawal
                        Roman firmness won the day. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was the
                        custom in those days to wear the look of prosperity in adverse
                        circumstances, and to curb and restrain the feelings in a time of
                        prosperity. The reply decided upon was that peace would be granted only on
                        the condition that the king placed himself entirely in the hands of the
                        senate and allowed it the unrestricted right of determining his future and
                        that of Macedonia. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When the report of the
                        deputation became known, those who were unacquainted with the Roman
                        character regarded it as an astounding exhibition of obstinacy and any
                        further allusion to peace was generally forbidden. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Those, they said, who spurn the peace now offered will
                        soon come to ask for it. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> It was this very
                        obstinacy that Perseus was afraid of; he looked upon it as due to a
                        confidence in their strength, and on the chance of being able to purchase
                        peace at a price, persisted in his attempts to bribe the consul by
                        constantly increasing the sum offered. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> As
                        the consul adhered to his first reply Perseus despaired of peace and
                        returned to Sycurium, prepared to face the hazards of war once more. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="63" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news of the battle spread through
                        Greece, and in the way it was received the hopes and sympathies of men were
                        disclosed. Not only the open supporters of Macedonia, but most of those who
                        were under the greatest obligations to Rome, some having experienced the
                        violence <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> and tyranny of Perseus, were
                        delighted at hearing it for no other reason than that morbid eagerness which
                        a mob watching gymnastic contests displays in favour of the weaker and more
                        disreputable competitor. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In Boeotia
                        meanwhile Lucretius was pressing the siege of Haliartus with the utmost
                        vigour. Although the besieged neither had nor hoped for any outside help
                        beyond the troops from Coronea who had entered the walls at the beginning of
                        the siege, they kept up their resistance more by courage and resolution than
                        by actual strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They frequently made
                        sorties against the siege works and when a battering-ram was brought up they
                        at one time . . . at another they forced it to the ground by lowering a mass
                        of lead upon it. If they were unable to divert the blows they replaced the
                        old wall by a new one which they hastily built up with the stones of the
                        fallen wall. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As the progress of the siege
                        works was too slow, the praetor ordered the scaling-ladders to be
                        distributed among the maniples as he intended to deliver a simultaneous
                        assault all round the walls. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His numbers,
                        he considered, would suffice for this, as there would be no advantage in
                        attacking that side of the city which was surrounded by a swamp, nor would
                        it be possible to do so. At a point where two towers and the wall between
                        them had been battered down he brought up a picked force of 2000 men in
                        order that while he was forcing his way through the breach, and the
                        defenders were massing together to oppose him, some portion of the walls
                        might be left unmanned and so successfully scaled. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The townsmen were not slow in preparing to meet him. On
                        the ground covered by the ruins of the wall they heaped up faggots of
                        brushwood, and standing on these with burning torches in their hands they
                        were preparing to set the mass on fire in <milestone n="8??" unit="section"
                        /> order that, shut off from the enemy by the conflagration, they might have
                        time to throw up another wall inside. They were accidentally prevented from
                        executing this plan. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Such a heavy shower
                        of rain suddenly fell that it was hardly possible to kindle the brushwood,
                        and when it was alight the fire was extinguished. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> A passage was effected by dragging the smoking faggots
                        out of the way, and as all had turned their attention to defending this one
                        spot, the walls were scaled in many places. In the first confusion of the
                        captured city the old men and boys whom they chanced to meet were killed.
                        The combatants took shelter in the citadel, and as all hope was now lost
                        they surrendered, and were sold as slaves. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> There were about 2500 of them. The adornments of the city, the statues
                        and paintings and all the valuable plunder were placed on shipboard and the
                        place was razed to its foundations. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> From
                        there the army marched to Thebes, which was captured without any fighting,
                        and the consul handed the city over to the refugees and the Roman party. The
                        households and property of the other party, who had worked in the interests
                        of the king and were Macedonian sympathisers, were sold. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="64" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these incidents in Boeotia, Perseus
                        remained for several days in camp at Sycurium. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Here he heard that the Romans were busy cutting and
                        carrying off the corn from the fields and that the men were all in front of
                        their tents cutting off the ears with their sickles that they might rub the
                        corn cleaner, and littering all the camp with great heaps of straw.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This seemed to him a good opportunity
                        for firing the camp, and he gave orders for torches of pinewood and bundles
                        of tow covered with pitch to be got ready. He started at midnight, intending
                        to take the enemy unawares at daybreak. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        All to no purpose. The advanced posts were surprised and their shouts and
                        tumult gave the alarm to the rest. The signal was given to arm instantly for
                        battle and the soldiers were immediately formed up at the gates and on the
                        rampart. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His design on the camp having
                        failed, Perseus countermarched his army and directed the baggage to lead the
                        way, and the standards of the infantry to follow. He himself waited with his
                        cavalry and light infantry to close the column, expecting, as proved to be
                        the case, that the enemy would follow and harass his rear. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> There was some desultory fighting on the part of the
                        light infantry, mainly with the skirmishers; the cavalry and infantry
                        returned to camp without disorder. </p>
                    <p> When the standing corn was cut all round their camp, the Romans moved on to
                        Crannon, where the fields were yet untouched. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Here they remained encamped for some time as they were
                        secure against attack, owing partly to the distance from Sycurium and partly
                        to the difficulty of obtaining water on the road from that place. Suddenly,
                        one morning at daybreak, they were greatly excited at seeing the king's
                        cavalry and light infantry on a range of hills overlooking the camp.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These had started from Sycurium at
                        noon the day before, and just before dawn left the infantry behind on the
                        nearest level ground. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Perseus halted for
                        some time on the hills, thinking that the Romans might be drawn into a
                        cavalry action. As they made no movement, he sent a trooper with orders to
                        the infantry to march back to Sycurium, and in a short time rode after them.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Roman cavalry followed at a
                        moderate interval to pick up stragglers. When they saw the massed infantry
                        marching off in unbroken ranks, they too returned to camp. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="65" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The distance he had to march annoyed the
                        king and he advanced his camp to Mopselus. The Romans, having cut all the
                        standing corn round Crannon, moved into the district of Phalanna. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The king learnt from a deserter that the Romans
                        were dispersed over the country, cutting the corn, without any remaining on
                        guard. He started off with 1000 cavalry and 2000 Thracian and Cretan light
                        infantry. Marching with the utmost possible speed he attacked the Romans
                        when they were least expecting it. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nearly
                        1000 carts most of them loaded, were captured with their teams, and also 600
                        prisoners taken. He gave the plunder to the Cretans to escort back to their
                        camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then he recalled the cavalry and the
                        rest of the infantry, who were everywhere slaughtering the enemy, <milestone
                            n="5??" unit="section"/> and led them against the nearest detachment who
                        were on guard, thinking to overwhelm them without much trouble. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> A military tribune, L. Pomponius, was in command
                        of the detachment and withdrew his men, who were dismayed by the sudden
                        appearance of the enemy, to a hill near by, to serve as a defensive position
                        since he was inferior in numbers and strength. Here he made his soldiers
                        close up in a circular formation, with their shields touching one another,
                        so that they might be protected from the arrows and javelins. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Perseus surrounded the hill with his
                        troops and ordered one body to attempt the ascent of the hill and come to
                        close quarters with the enemy, whilst the others discharged their missiles
                        from a distance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Romans were in very
                        great danger, for they could not fight in close order against those who were
                        struggling up the hill, and if they left their ranks and ran forward they
                        were exposed to the javelins and arrows. They suffered mainly from the
                        cestrosphendons, a novel kind of weapon invented during the war. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> It consisted of a pointed iron head two palms
                        long, fastened to a shaft made of pinewood, nine inches long and as thick as
                        a man's finger. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Round the shaft three
                        feathers were fastened as in the case of arrows, and the sling was held by
                        two thongs, one shorter than the other. When the missile was poised in the
                        centre of the sling, the slinger whirled it round with great force and it
                        flew out like a leaden bullet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Many of
                        the soldiers were wounded by these and by missiles of all kinds, and they
                        were becoming so exhausted that they were hardly capable of holding their
                        weapons. Seeing this, the king urged them to surrender and pledged his word
                        for their safety and promised to reward them. Not a single man had any
                        thought of surrender. They had made up their minds to die, when an
                        unlooked-for gleam of hope appeared. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some
                        of the foragers, who had fled to the camp, informed the consul that the
                        detachment on guard was surrounded. Alarmed for the safety of so many
                        fellow-citizens-there were about 800, all Romans-he sallied forth from the
                        camp with a force of cavalry and infantry, including the new reinforcement
                        of Numidian horse and foot, as well as the elephants. The order was given to
                        the military tribunes to follow with the legionaries. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> Bringing up the velites to stiffen the auxiliary light
                        infantry, he went forward to the hill. Eumenes, Attalus and Misagenes, the
                        Numidian leader, rode by his side. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="66" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As soon as they caught sight of the
                        leading files of their comrades, the spirits of the Romans revived from the
                        depths of despair. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Perseus should have
                        made up his mind after capturing and killing several of the foragers to
                        content himself with this chance success, and not wasted time in
                        beleaguering the detachment. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Or if he did
                        attempt that he ought to have left the field while he could do so safely, as
                        he knew he had no heavy infantry with him. Elated with his success he waited
                        till the enemy appeared, and then sent a hurried message to bring up the
                        phalanx. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was too late to do this now.
                        The phalanx, hastily brought into action and disarranged by the speed of its
                        advance, had to meet troops in proper formation and ready for battle.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, who was first on the
                        ground, at once engaged the enemy. For a short time the Macedonians held
                        their own, but they were completely outmatched, and with a loss of 300
                        infantry and 24 of the select cavalry of the "sacred cohort," including
                        their commander Antimachus, they attempted to leave the field. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> But there was almost more turmoil on their return
                        march than in the battle itself. The phalanx, called up so hurriedly,
                        marched off with equal haste, but where the road narrowed they met the troop
                        of prisoners and the carts loaded with corn, and were brought to a
                        standstill. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There was great excitement and
                        uproar; no one would wait until the troops of the phalanx could make their
                        way through; the soldiers threw the carts over the cliff, the only way of
                        clearing the road, and the animals were lashed till they charged madly among
                        the crowd. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Hardly had they got clear of
                        the column of prisoners when they met the king and his discomfited cavalry,
                        who shouted to them to face about and march back. This created a commotion
                        almost as great as the crash of a falling house; if the enemy had continued
                        the pursuit and ventured into the pass, there might have been a terrible
                        disaster. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul, satisfied with this
                        slight success, recalled the detachment from the hill and returned to camp.
                        According to some authorities, a great battle was fought that day, 8000 of
                        the enemy slain, amongst them two of the king's generals, Sopater and
                        Antipater, 2800 made prisoners, and 27 military standards captured.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nor was the victory a bloodless one.
                        Above 4300 fell in the consul's army, and 5 standards belonging to the left
                        wing lost. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="67" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This day revived the spirits of the Romans
                        and depressed Perseus, so much so that after staying a few days longer at
                        Mopselus, mainly to see to the burial of the men he had lost, he placed a
                        sufficiently strong garrison in Gonnus and withdrew his troops into
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One of the royal governors,
                        Timotheus, was left with a small force at Phila with instructions to try and
                        win over the Magnetes whilst he was in their neighbourhood. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On reaching Pella, Perseus sent his army into winter
                        quarters and then went with Cotys to Thessalonica. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> News reached him there that Autlebis, a Thracian chief,
                        and Corragus, an officer of Eumenes, had invaded the dominions of Cotys and
                        occupied a district called Marene. He felt that he ought to release Cotys
                        and let him go and defend his kingdom. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On
                        his departure he bestowed valuable presents on him. To his cavalry he only
                        doled out 200 talents, half a year's pay, though at first he had agreed to
                        give them a year's stipend. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the consul heard that Perseus had
                        gone he marched up to Gonnus on the chance of getting possession of the
                        town. This place lies at the entrance to the Vale of Tempe, and forms a
                        secure barrier against the invasion of Macedonia from that side, while it
                        affords a convenient descent for the Macedonians into Thessaly. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> As the citadel, owing to its position and the
                        strength of its garrison, was impregnable, the consul abandoned the attempt.
                        Turning his route towards Perrhaebia he took Malloea at the first assault
                        and sacked the town. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After securing
                        Tripolis and the other places in Perrhaebia he returned to Larisa. Eumenes
                        and Attalus went home, and the consul settled Misagenes and his Numidians in
                        the nearest cities of Thessaly. Part of his army he distributed amongst all
                        the cities of Thessaly, that they might have comfortable winter quarters and
                        serve as garrisons for the cities. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Q.
                        Mucius was sent with 2000 men to hold Ambracia, and the consul disbanded all
                        the troops from the friendly States of Greece, except the Achaeans.
                        Advancing with a part of his army into Achaean Phthiotis he razed to its
                        foundations the city of Pteleum, from which the inhabitants had fled, and
                        accepted the voluntary surrender of Antronae. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Then he brought his army up to Larisa. The city was
                        empty; all the population had taken refuge in the citadel, and he commenced
                        an attack upon it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The king's garrison of
                        Macedonians had first left the place through fear, and the townsmen, thus
                        deserted, at once surrendered. He now hesitated whether to attack Demetrias
                        or examine the position in Boeotia. The Thebans, owing to the trouble given
                        them by the Coronaeans, were asking hum to come to their assistance.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In compliance with their request and
                        also because it was more suitable for winter quarters than Magnesia, he led
                        his army into Boeotia. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
