<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
                  <title>Panegyric on the Consuls Probinus and Olybrius</title>
            <author>Claudian</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Claudian, with an English translation, in Two Volumes, Vol. I</title>
                  <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
                  <editor role="editor">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA; London, England</pubPlace>
                     <date type="printing">1922</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/claudian01clau#page/2/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
                     <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                              <state unit="poem"/>
                     </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language id="la">Latin</language>
            <language id="greek">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text id="stoa0089.stoa014.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
         <pb id="v.1.p.3" TEIform="pb"/>
               <div1 type="poem" n="1">
         <p>

Sun, that encirclest the world with reins of flame
and rollest in ceaseless motion the revolving centuries,
scatter thy light with kindlier beams and let thy
coursers, their manes combed and they breathing
forth a rosy flame from their foaming bits, climb
the heavens more jocund in their loftier drawn
chariot. Now let the year bend its new steps for
the consul brothers and the glad months take their
beginning.</p>
         <p>Thou wottest of the Auchenian1 race nor are the
powerful Anniadae unknown to thee, for thou oft
hast started thy yearly journey with them as consuls
and hast given their name to thy revolution. For
them Fortune neither hangs on uncertain favour nor
changes, but honours, firmly fixed, pass to all their
kin. Select what man thou wilt from their family,
'tis certain he is a consul's son. Their ancestors are
<pb id="v.1.p.5"/>
counted by the fasces (for each has held them), the
same recurring honours crown them, and a like
destiny awaits their children in unbroken succession.</p>
         <p>No noble, though he boast of the brazen statues of his
ancestors, though Rome be thronged with senators,
no noble, I say, dare boast himself their equal.</p>
         <p>Give the first place to the Auchenii and let who will
contest the second. It is as when the moon queens
it in the calm northern sky and her orb gleams with
brightness equal to that of her brother whose light
she reflects; for then the starry hosts give place,
Arcturus' beam grows dim and tawny Leo loses his
angry glint, far-spaced shine the Bear's stars in the
Wain, wroth at their eclipse, Orion's shafts grow dark
as he looks in feeble amaze at his strengthless arm.</p>
         <p>Which shall I speak of first? Who has not heard
of the deeds of Probinus of ancient lineage, who
knows not the endless praise of Olybrius?
</p>
         <p>The far-flung fame of Probus1 and his sire lives
yet and fills all ears with widespread discourse: the
years to come shall not silence it nor time o'ercloud
or put an end to it. His great name carries him
beyond the seas, beyond Ocean's distant windings
and Atlas' mountain caverns. If any live beneath the
frozen sky by Maeotis' banks, or any, near neighbours
of the torrid zone, drink Nile's stripling stream,
they, too, have heard. Fortune yielded to his
virtues, but never was he puffed up with success
that engenders pride. Though his life was surrounded
with luxury he knew how to preserve his
uprightness uncorrupted. He did not hide his
wealth in dark cellars nor condemn his riches to
the nether gloom, but in showers more abundant
than rain would ever enrich countless numbers of
<pb id="v.1.p.7"/>
men. The thick cloud of his generosity was ever
big with gifts, full and overflowing with clients was
his mansion, and thereinto there poured a stream
of paupers to issue forth again rich men. His prodigal
hand outdid Spain's rivers in scattering gifts of gold
(scarce so much precious metal dazzles the gaze of
the miner delving in the vexed bowels of the earth),
exceeding all the gold dust carried down by Tagus'
water trickling from unsmelted lodes, the glittering
ore that enriches Hermus' banks, the golden sand
that rich Pactolus in flood deposits over the plains of Lydia.
</p>
         <p>Could my words issue from a hundred mouths,
could Phoebus' manifold inspiration breathe through
a hundred breasts, even so I could not tell of Probus'
deeds, of all the people his ordered governance
ruled, of the many times he rose to the highest
honours, when he held the reins of broad-acred Italy,
the Illyrian coast, and Africa's lands. But his sons
o'ershadowed their sire and they alone deserve to
be called Probus' vanquishers. No such honour
befell Probus in his youth: he was never consul with
his brother. You ambition, ever o'ervaulting itself,
pricks not; no anxious hopes afflict your minds
or keep your hearts in long suspense. You have
begun where most end: but few seniors have attained
to your earliest office. You have finished your race
e'er the full flower of youth has crowned your gentle
cheeks or adolescence clothed your faces with its
pleasant down. Do thou, my Muse, tell their
ignorant poet what god it was granted such a boon
to the twain.
</p>
         <p>When the warlike emperor had with the thunderbolt
of his might put his enemy to flight and freed
<pb id="v.1.p.9"/>
the Alps from fear, Rome, anxious worthily to thank
her Probus, hastened to beg the Emperor's favour
for that hero's sons. Her slaves, Shock and horrid
Fear, yoked her winged chariot; 'tis they who ever
attend Rome with loud-voiced roar, setting wars
afoot, whether she battle against the Parthians or
vex Hydaspes' stream with her spear. The one
fastens the wheels to the hubs, the other drives
the horses beneath the iron yoke and makes them
obey the stubborn bit. Rome herself in the guise of
the virgin goddess Minerva soars aloft on the road by
which she takes possession of the sky after triumphing
over the realms of earth. She will not have her
hair bound with a comb nor her neck made effeminate
with a twisted necklace. Her right side is bare; her
snowy shoulder exposed; her brooch fastens her
flowing garments but loosely and boldly shows her
breast: the belt that supports her sword throws a
strip of scarlet across her fair skin. She looks as
good as she is fair, chaste beauty armed with awe;
her threatening helm of blood-red plumes casts a
dark shadow and her shield challenges the sun in
its fearful brilliance, that shield which Vulcan
forged with all the subtlety of his skill. In it are
depicted the children Romulus and Remus, and
their loving father Mars, Tiber's reverent stream,
and the wolf that was their nurse; Tiber is embossed
in electrum, the children in pure gold, brazen is the
wolf, and Mars fashioned of flashing steel.
</p>
         <p>And now Rome, loosing both her steeds together,
flies swifter than the fleet east wind; the Zephyrs
shrill and the clouds, cleft with the track of the
wheels, glow in separate furrows. What matchless
speed! One pinion's stroke and they reach their
<pb id="v.1.p.11"/>
goal: it is there where in their furthermost parts the
Alps narrow their approaches into tortuous valleys
and extend their adamantine bars of piled-up rocks.
</p>
         <p>No other hand could unlock that gate, as, to their
cost, those two tyrants 1  found; to the Emperor
only they offer a way. The smoke of towers o'erthrown
and of ruined fortresses ascends to heaven.
</p>
         <p>Slaughtered men are piled up on a heap and bring
the lowest valley equal with the hills; corpses
welter in their blood; the very shades are confounded
with the inrush of the slain.
</p>
         <p>Close at hand the victor, Theodosius, happy that
his warfare is accomplished, sits upon the green
sward, his shoulders leaning against a tree. Triumphant
earth crowned her lord and flowers sprang up
from prouder banks. The sweat is still warm upon
his body, his breath comes panting, but calm shines
his countenance beneath his helmet. Such is Mars,
when with deadly slaughter he has devastated the
Geloni and thereafter rests, a dread figure, in
the Getic plain, while Bellona, goddess of war,
lightens him of his armour and unyokes his duststained
coursers; an outstretched spear, a huge
cornel trunk, arms his hand and flashes its tremulous
splendour over Hebrus' stream.
</p>
         <p>When Rome had ended her airy journey and now
stood before her lord, thrice thundered the conscious
rocks and the black wood shuddered in awe. First
to speak was the hero: <q direct="unspecified"> Goddess and friend, mother
of laws, thou whose empire is conterminous with
heaven, thou that art called the consort of the
Thunderer, say what hath caused thy coming:
why leavest thou the towns of Italy and thy native
clime? Say, queen of the world. Were it thy
<pb id="v.1.p.13"/>
wish I would not shrink from toiling neath a
Libyan sun nor from the cold winds of a Russian
midwinter. At thy behest I will traverse all lands
and fearing no season of the year will hazard Meroe
in summer and the Danube in winter.</q>
         </p>
         <p>Then the Queen answered: <q direct="unspecified">
               <p>Full well know I,
far-famed ruler, that thy victorious armies toil for
Italy, and that once again servitude and furious
rebels have given way before thee, overthrown in
one and the same battle. Yet I pray thee add to
our late won liberty this further boon, if in very
truth thou still reverest me. There are among my
citizens two young brothers of noble lineage, the
dearly loved sons of Probus, born on a festal day
and reared in my own bosom. 'Twas I gave the little
ones their cradles when the goddess of childbirth
freed their mother's womb from its blessed burden
and heaven brought to light her glorious offspring.
</p>
               <p>To these I would not prefer the noble Decii nor the
brave Metelli, no, nor the Scipios who overcame the
warlike Carthaginians nor the Camilli, that family
fraught with ruin for the Gauls. The Muses have
endowed them with full measure of their skill; their
eloquence knows no bounds. Theirs not to wanton
in sloth and banquets spread; unbridled pleasure
tempts them not, nor can the lure of youth undermine
their characters. Gaining from weighty cares
an old man's mind, their fiery youth is bridled
by a greybeard's wisdom. That fortune to which
their birth entitles them I beg thee assure them
and appoint for them the path of the coming year.
'Tis no unreasonable request and will be no unheard-
of boon. Their birth demands it should be so.
</p>
               <p>Grant it; so may Scythian Araxes be our vassal
<pb id="v.1.p.15"/>
and Rhine's either bank; so may the Mede be
o'erthrown and the towers that Semiramis built
yield to our standards, while amazed Ganges flows
between Roman cities.</p>
            </q>
         </p>
         <p>To this the king: <q direct="unspecified"> Goddess, thou biddest me do
what I would fain do and askest a boon that I wish
to grant: thy entreaties were not needed for this.
Does forgetfulness so wholly cloud my mind that I
will not remember Probus, beneath whose leadership
I have seen all Italy and her war-weary peoples come
again to prosperity? Winter shall cause Nile's
rising, hinds shall make rivers their element, dark-
flowing Indus shall be ice-bound, terror-stricken
once again by the banquet of Thyestes the sun
shall stay his course and fly for refuge back into the
east, all this ere Probus can fade from my memory.</q>
         </p>
         <p>He spake, and now the speedy messenger hies him
to Rome. Straightway the choirs chant and the
seven hills re-echo their tuneful applause. Joy is in
the heart of that aged mother whose skilled fingers
now make ready gold-embroidered vestment and
garments agleam with the thread which the Seres
comb out from their delicate plants, gathering the
leafy fleece of the wool-bearing trees. These long
threads she draws out to an equal length with the
threads of gold and by intertwining them makes
one golden cord; as fair Latona gave scarlet garments
to her divine offspring when they returned to
the now firm-fixed shrine of Delos their fosterisland,
Diana leaving the forest glades and bleak
Maenalus, her unerring bow wearied with much
hunting, and Phoebus bearing the sword still dripping
with black venom from the slaughtered Python.
</p>
         <p>Then their dear island laved the feet of its acknow-
<pb id="v.1.p.17"/>
ledged deities, the Aegean smiled more gently on
its nurslings, the Aegean whose soft ripples bore
witness to its joy.
</p>
         <p>So Proba 1 adorns her children with vestment
rare, Proba, the world's glory, by whose increase
the power of Rome, too, is increased. You would
have thought her Modesty's self fallen from heaven
or Juno, summoned by sacred incense, turning her
eyes on the shrines of Argos. No page in ancient
story tells of such a mother, no Latin Muse nor
old Grecian tale. Worthy is she of Probus for
a husband, for he surpassed all husbands as she all
wives. 'Twas as though in rivalry either sex had
done its uttermost and so brought about this marriage.
</p>
         <p>Let Pelion vaunt no more that Nereid bride .2
Happy thou that art the mother of consuls twain,
blessed thy womb whose offspring have given the
year their name for its own.
</p>
         <p>So soon as their hands held the sceptres and the
jewel-studded togas had enfolded their limbs the
almighty Sire vouchsafes a sign with riven cloud
and the shaken heavens, projecting a welcoming
flash through the void, thundered with prosperous
omen. Father Tiber, seated in that low valley,
heard the sound in his labyrinthine cave. He stays
with ears pricked up wondering whence this sudden
popular clamour comes. Straightway he leaves his
couch of green leaves, his mossy bed, and entrusts
his urn to his attendant nymphs. Grey eyes flecked
with blue shine out from his shaggy countenance,
recalling his father Oceanus; thick curled grasses
cover his neck and lush sedge crowns his head.
<pb id="v.1.p.19"/>
This the Zephyrs may not break nor the summer
sun scorch to withering; it lives and burgeons
around those brows immortal as itself. From
his temples sprout horns like those of a bull; from
these pour babbling streamlets; water drips upon
his breast, showers pour down his hair-crowned
forehead, flowing rivers from his parted beard.
</p>
         <p>There clothes his massy shoulders a cloak woven by
his wife Ilia, who threaded the crystalline loom
beneath the flood.
</p>
         <p>There lies in Roman Tiber's stream an island
where the central flood washes as 'twere two cities
parted by the sundering waters: with equal threatening
height the tower-clad banks rise in lofty buildings.
</p>
         <p>Here stood Tiber and from this eminence
beheld his prayer of a sudden fulfilled, saw the
twin-souled brothers enter the Forum amid the
press of thronging senators, the bared axes gleam
afar and both sets of fasces brought forth from one
threshold. He stood amazed at the sight and for a
long time incredulous joy held his voice in check.
</p>
         <p>Yet soon he thus began:
<q direct="unspecified"> Behold, Eurotas, river of Sparta, boastest thou
that thy streams have ever nurtured such as these?
Did that false swan 1 beget a child to rival them,
though 'tis true his sons could fight with the heavy
glove and save ships from cruel tempests? Behold
new offspring outshining the stars to which Leda
gave birth, men of my city for whose coming the
Zodiac is now awatch, making ready his hollow
tract of sky for a constellation that is to be. Henceforth
let Olybrius rule the nightly sky, shedding
his ruddy light where Pollux once shone, and
where glinted Castor's fires there let glitter Probinus'
<pb id="v.1.p.21"/>
flame. These shall direct men's sails and vouchsafe
those breezes whereby the sailor shall guide his
bark o'er the calm ocean. Let us now pour libation
to the new gods and ease our hearts with copious
draughts of nectar. Naiads, now spread your snowy
bands, wreath every spring with violets. Let the
woods bring forth honey and the drunken river roll,
its waters changed to wine; let the watering streams
that vein the fields give oft the scent of balsam spice.
Let one run and invite to the feast and banquet-
board all the rivers of our land, even all that wander
beneath the mountains of Italy and drink as their
portion the Alpine snows, swift Vulturnus and Nar
infected with ill-smelling sulphur, Ufens whose
meanderings delay his course and Eridanus into
whose waters Phaethon fell headlong; Liris who
laves Marica's golden oak groves and Galaesus
who tempers the fields of Sparta's colony Tarentum.
This day shall always be held in honour and observed
by our rivers and its anniversary ever celebrated
with rich feastings.</q>
         </p>
         <p>So spake he, and the Nymphs, obeying their sire's
behest, made ready the rooms for the banquet, and
the watery palace, ablaze with gleaming purple,
shone with jewelled tables.
</p>
         <p>O happy months to bear these brothers' name!
</p>
         <p>O year blessed to own such a pair as overlords, begin
thou to turn the laborious wheel of Phoebus' fourfold
circle. First let thy winter pursue its course,
sans numbing cold, not clothed in white snow
nor torn by rough blasts, but warmed with the
south wind's breath: next, be thy spring calm
from the outset and let the limpid west wind's
gentler breeze flood thy meads with yellow flowers.
<pb id="v.1.p.23"/>
May summer crown thee with harvest and autumn
store thee with luscious grapes. An honour that no
age has ever yet known, a privilege never yet heard
of in times gone by, this has been thine and thine
alone — to have had brothers as thy consuls. The
whole world shall tell of thee, the Hours shall
inscribe thy name in various flowers, and age-long
annals hand thy fame down through the long
centuries.
<pb id="v.1.p.25"/>
         </p>
                        </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>