<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Shorter Poems</title>
        <author>Claudian</author>
        <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Bridget Almas</name>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:Mellon">The Mellon Foundation</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2011-09-12</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>Claudian</title>
            <title>with an English translation</title>
            <author>Claudius Claudianus</author>
            <editor role="translator">Maurice Platnauer</editor>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
              <pubPlace>London, England<</pubPlace>
              <date type="printing">1922</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://archive.org/details/claudian02clau#page/174/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl><p>Keyboarding</p></editorialDecl>
      <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
        <state unit="poem"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language id="la">Latin</language>
	<language id="greek">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text id="stoa0089.stoa001.perseus-eng1"><body>
<pb id="v.2.p.175"/>

<div1 type="poem" n="1" id="poem.13"><head>To Stilicho.</head><p>

Crown with a wreath of flowers, Stilicho, that
head more often graced with the shining helmet.
Bid cease the trumpets and let the happy marriagetorch
banish fierce war afar. Let the blood derived
from a kingly race flow on through royal veins.
Do a father's duty and establish the firm bond of
wedlock between thy daughter and adoptive son.
Thou wert an emperor's son-in-law ; now an emperor
will be thine. What cause is there now for envy,
what excuse for jealousy ? Stilicho is at once father
and father-in-law.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="2" id="poem.85"><head>Description of the harbour at Smyrna.</head><p>

The city that meets our gaze veils the mountain
peaks, fronting a tranquil sea. The two headlands
that enclose the harbour protect the quiet
water from the north wind. Here the sea is disarmed
by the encircling land and learns to lie in
undisturbed tranquillity.
<pb id="v.2.p.177"/>

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="3" id="poem.81"><head>To Aeternalis.1</head><p>

Phoebus' every breath from the Castalian spring,
the tripod's every moan within the shrine of prophecy
— all these are poetry. Of prose the Muses will
have none. In poetry only can I express myself,
so wholly does my patron, Apollo, possess me.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="4" id="poem.54"><head>Description of a Herd,</head><p>

Not such were the beauteous herds that the land
once ruled over by triple Geryon produced. Not
such the bulls thou bathest, Clitumnus, in thy
stream for pious vows to offer duly to Tarpeian
Jove. Not such the steer that, they say, scattered
the sand of Tyre 2 what time he brought home his
well-loved burden. Not the fields of Crete, nor
Gnossos that knew of passion for a bull, nor Ida
could have pastured the like. Even he whose
monstrous figure united ill-assorted limbs, the Cretan
child 3 who by his strange form revealed his mother's
shame — even he could scarce have shown a shape so
fair had all his rough limbs resembled those of his
sire.
<pb id="v.2.p.179"/>

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="5" id="poem.86"><head>A distant Scene.</head><p>

There is a place deep buried in a huge bay where
an island, stretching far out into the sea, stills the
rough waves to quiet, and steep cliffs, jutting out
into the broken water, curve themselves into a
peaceful harbourage.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="6" id="poem.78"><head>Anger affords a weapon to him who seeks one,1</head><p>

Whate'er it carries, that rage converts into a
weapon. Wrath supplies all with arms. When an
angry man thirsts for blood anything will serve him
for a spear. Fury turns a stick into a cudgel.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="7" id="poem.87"><head>Statue of a Chariot.</head><p>

1. Who had the skill to fashion so many figures
out of one block of marble ? The chariot melts
into the charioteer ; the horses with one common
accord obey the same reins. These are distinguishable
by their various forms but made from one and
the same material without distinction.

2. The driver is of one piece with the car : to this
are attached the steeds, each joined to, and proceeding
out of, another. How admirable the artist's
skill ! A single block combines within itself all these
bodies : one mass of marble by submitting to the
chisel has grown into all these various shapes.
<pb id="v.2.p.181"/>


</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="8" id="poem.69"><head>Of Polycaste and Perdiccas. 1</head><p>

To what deeds of cruelty will the flames of love
not inspire mankind ? Here is a mother who dares
not love her child, the fruit of her body. Holding
the unhappy boy to her snowy breast and wishing
to give him suck, she conceives for him, though she
is his mother, a shameful passion. Cupid, thou
goest too far ; put down thy cruel quiver. Consult
Venus ; mayhap she feels like pangs.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="9" id="poem.45"><head>The Porcupine.</head><p>

I had heard the strange tale, Stymphalus, that
the birds that haunted thy marshes let fall from them
arrows of death in their flight, and for long I
could not bring myself to believe this story of iron
feathers. But proof is not wanting, and the wellknown
porcupine is warrant for the birds of Hercules.
His long snout is like that of a swine. Stiff
bristles like horns stand up from his forehead.
Red and fierce are his fiery eyes. Under his bristly
back are short legs like those of a small dog. Small
as this animal is, nevertheless Nature has seen fit
to dower him with a wonderful means of defence.
All over the body grows a threatening thicket :
a harvest of brightly coloured spears bristles up ready
<pb id="v.2.p.183"/>
for battle. The roots of these weapons are white
and are firmly fixed in the animal's skin. The
quills are themselves parti-coloured with black bands
and come to a stiff quill-like point, diminishing in
diameter towards the tip which is smooth and sharp.
But his armoury is not fixed like that of the
woodland hedgehog. He can take the offensive
and also protect himself at a distance by the frequent
discharge of these darts of his, hurling through the
air the flying missiles which his own back supplies.
At times like the flying Parthian he wounds his
pursuers ; at times he entrenches himself and strikes
his foe by the discharge of a storm of these terrible
weapons which bristle on his shoulders out of which
they grow. He fights with his whole body, and his
back, as it moves, emits a raucous sound. You
would think it was the trumpet's note stirring an
army to close with the foe and fight. Small is the
animal but great the din. Besides his arms he displays
cunning and a cold, calculated fury that never
wastes its weapons but cautiously contents itself
with threats, for he never expends a dart but in
defence of his life. His aim is sure ; the blow, such
is his skill, unerring, nor can distance delude his
range. The motion of his skin in the act of discharging
ensures the speed, and accurately directs
the flight, of the weapon.
Has human endeavour, with reason to guide it,
ever done the like ? Men rob of their horns the
wild goats of Crete, then they force them to become
pliant over the fire 1 ; they use the guts of cattle to
string their bows ; they tip their arrows with iron
and wing them with feathers. But here is a small
animal whose arms are contained in his own body
<pb id="v.2.p.185"/>
and who needs no external defence. He carries all
his own arms ; himself his own quiver, arrow, and
bow. Alone he possesses all the resources of war.
But if all human activities as they grow have had
their source in imitation we may see here the
exemplar of combat by means of missiles. It is from
him that the Cretans learned to shoot and the Parthians
to strike while in flight. These did but follow
the example of the animal that is armed with arrows.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="10" id="poem.92"><head>Of Beaver's Overcoat. 1</head><p>

'Tis but the shadow of a name that is left. I
cannot call it a coat of beaver, not though Beaver
swear it is one. It cost six shillings. Now you
know what it is like. If you don't believe me,
believe the price.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="11" id="poem.91"><head>On the Tomb of a Beauty.</head><p>

Fate allows not beauty a long life : sudden is the
end of all that is noble and pre-eminent. Here lies
a lovely woman : hers was the beauty of Venus
and hers the illwill of Heaven for a gift so rare.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="12" id="poem.84"><head>Quintius' Baths.</head><p>

Stay awhile and bathe in these waters, traveller ;
then set forth again upon thy journey refreshed.
<pb id="v.2.p.187"/>
An thou become its guest, warm will be thy gratitude
towards him that built this bath and set it by the side
of this long dusty road.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="13" id="poem.79"><head>To a gouty Critic.</head><p>

Canst thou talk of feet ? Dost blame my verses
and criticize my lines, thou whose own feet are so
weak ? This couplet, you say, will scarcely stand :
the scansion is shaky. Dear friend, a gouty man
thinks nothing at all can stand.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="14" id="poem.82"><head>To thank Maximus for a Gift of Honey.</head><p>
Thou dost ever send me sweet gifts, Maximus ;
'tis honey whatsoever thou sendest, methinks.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="15" id="poem.89"><head>The Poor Lover.</head><p>

Biting poverty and cruel Cupid are my foes.
Hunger I can endure ; love I cannot.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="16" id="poem.90"><head>The Same.</head><p>

A hungry pauper am I, a victim fallen to love.
Two ills ; but poverty is the lesser.
<pb id="v.2.p.189"/>
</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="17" id="poem.50"><head>On the Statues of Two Brothers at Catina. 1</head><p>

See these two brothers toiling beneath a burden
piety bade them bear. They deserve the tribute
of divine honours at the hands of all men : at
the sight of them the respectful flames ceased
their ravages and Etna in admiration restrained
his flooding lava. Seizing their parents they set
them upon their shoulders and, with eyes raised to
heaven, hasten their steps. The aged parents,
thus carried aloft by their two sons, impede their
flight, but dear to the children is that very delay.
See, the old man points to the cruel flames ; the
aged mother's trembling lips call upon the gods for
help. Fear has set their hair on end, the bronze
is terror-stricken and a pale shiver runs over all the
metal. In the countenances of the sons is seen
courage in face of danger, and, if fear, then fear for
their burdens, none for themselves. The wind has
blown back their cloaks. One raises his right hand ;
his left is enough to sustain his aged sire. But the
other needs must clasp his burden with both arms,
taking greater care for that it is his mother, one of the
weaker sex, that he bears. This, too, as thou passest
by, leave not unnoted, for well the craftsman's dumb
hands deserve such regard ; both he has moulded
with a likeness such as brothers bear, yet the one
resembles rather his mother, the other his father.
<pb id="v.2.p.191"/>
The artist's cunning has succeeded in expressing
a difference of age in their faces, though a likeness
to either parent is apparent in the features of both
the sons ; while, to ensure a further dissimilarity
in that resemblance, he has varied the tenderness
that either countenance expresses.
Faithful were ye to Nature's law, bright example
of divine justice, model for youth, fond hope of
age ! Wealth ye despised, and dashed into the
flames to rescue nought save your venerable parents.
Not undeservedly, methinks, did such piety quench
the fires in Enceladus' jaws. Vulcan himself checked
the flow of molten lava from Etna that it should
not harm those patterns of filial duty. The very
elements were influenced thereby : father air and
mother earth did their best to lighten the burden.
If signal piety raised Castor and Pollux to the
skies, if Aeneas won immortality by rescuing his
sire from burning Troy, if ancient story has
rendered famous the names of those Argive brothers,
Cleobis and Biton, 1 who harnessed themselves to their
mother's car, why does not Sicily dedicate a temple
to the ageless memory of Amphinomos and Anapius ?
Though the three-cornered isle has many titles to
fame, let her be sure that she has never given birth
to a nobler deed. Let her not weep the destruction
wrought by the spreading flames nor lament the
houses burned down by the fire's fury. The flames
abating had never put affection to the proof; the
great disaster purchased immortal fame.
<pb id="v.2.p.193"/>
</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="18" id="poem.51"><head>Of French Mules.</head><p>

Behold the docile children of fast-flowing Rhone
that at their master's word come together and at
that word disperse. See how they go this way or
that according to the different cries he utters, and,
guided only by his voice, take the path he would
have them take. Though each unguided by the rein
takes his own course and no collar presses upon their
necks they obey as though harnessed and, insensible
to fatigue, hear and follow the directions shouted
by their barbarous master. Though far away from
their owner they nevertheless respect his commands,
obeying the word of the muleteer as it were a bridle.
It is his voice that even at a distance gathers them
together when scattered or scatters them when
gathered together ; this that checks their haste
or quickens their dragging steps. Does he shout
<q> left,</q> they turn them to the left : does he alter
his cry to <q> right,</q> to the right they go. Slaves,
yet without bonds, free, but without licence, they
go unbridled but obedient. Covered with tawny
pelts they haul along the rumbling carts, each
cheerfully doing his fair share. Dost thou wonder
that Orpheus tamed the wild beasts with his song
when the words of a Gaul can guide these swift-footed
mules ?

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="19" id="poem.43"><head>Letter to Gennadius, 1 ex-Proconsul.</head><p>

Glory of all Italy, who dwellest on the pleasant
banks of Rubicon, ornament of the Roman bar
<pb id="v.2.p.195"/>
second only to Cicero, well known to the peoples
of Greece and to Egypt, land of my birth (for both
have feared and loved thy rule), dost thou ask for
poems to appease thy hungry throat ?
By our friendship, I swear there are none at home.
My verses soon learn to trust to their own wings
and leave the nest, flying far afield nor ever returning
to their humble home.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="20" id="poem.52"><head>Of an old Man of Verona who never left his home.</head><p>

Happy he who has passed his whole life mid
his own fields, he of whose birth and old age the
same house is witness ; he whose stick supports
his tottering steps o'er the very ground whereon
he crawled as a baby and whose memory knows
but of one cottage as the scene where so long a
life was played out. No turns of fortune vexed
him with their sudden storms ; 1 he never travelled
nor drank the waters of unknown rivers. He
was never a trader to fear the seas nor a soldier
to dread the trumpet's call ; never did he face the
noisy wrangles of the courts. Unpractised in affairs,
unfamiliar with the neighbouring town, he finds
his delight in a freer view of the sky above him.
For him the recurring seasons, not the consuls,
mark the year : he knows autumn by his fruits and
spring by her flowers. From the selfsame fields he
watches the sun rise and set, and, at his work,
measures the day with his own round of toils. He
remembers yon mighty oak an acorn, and sees the
plantation, set when he was born, grown old along
<pb id="v.2.p.197"/>
with him. Neighbouring Verona is, for him, more distant
than sun-scorched India ; Benacus he accounts
as the Red Sea. But his strength is unimpaired
and the third generation see in him a sturdy, stoutarmed
grandsire. Let who will be a wanderer and
explore farthest Spain : such may have more of a
journey ; he of Verona has more of a life. 1

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="21" id="poem.80"><head>Of Theodore and Hadrian. 2</head><p>

Manlius Theodorus sleeps night and day ; the
sleepless Egyptian steals alike from gods and men.
Peoples of Italy, be this your one prayer — that
Manlius keep awake and the Egyptian sleep.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="22" id="poem.39"><head>Apology to Hadrian.</head><p>

Must the violence of thine anger last so long ?
Are my tears never to cease to flow ? Dost thou
thus suddenly turn thy favour to hatred ? Where,
then, is that leniency that knows not to harm any,
that loving-kindness ? Shall envy have such licence ?
Has the clamour of calumny so prevailed ?
What though rash wrath, though heedless youth
tempted me, though pride urged, though passion
led me astray, yet shouldst thou be above meeting
me with like weapons. Human murmurs never
touch the gods nor do the loose railings of man
disturb the peace of heaven. My punishment has
epigram was probably written in 396 : the apology (next
poem) perhaps the same year.
<pb id="v.2.p.199"/>
been too severe ; spare a fallen foe. Behold me ;
I confess my faults and ask pardon for my sin.
Fierce Achilles showed mercy to the shade of
Hector, Orestes appeased his mother's avenging
furies, Hercules restored to Priam the cities which
he had taken. A king's overthrow won the pity
of Pella's youthful monarch, who wept, men say,
for the death of Darius at a slave's hand, and consoled
his ghost with a lofty mausoleum. To captive
Porus Alexander gave back an ampler kingdom.
'Twas thus the founder of our country 1 spared his
conquered foes. Thine own nobility demands that
thou shouldst follow his example. If it is one of
the gods that I have insulted let him send down
punishment upon me and sate his anger.
Now that I have lost thy favour I am become a
prey to grinding poverty, my house is desolate,
my friends reft from me. Death with torture is
the fate of one, exile of another. What further
losses can I suffer ? What more cruel plagues can
befall me ?
The power to despoil and kill softens anger.
Wild beasts turn away from their stricken prey,
and fierce lions, eager to destroy, abandon the dead
victim, and with a nobler hunger riot only in the flesh
of the warlike steer. Envy has snapped the thread
of my prosperity and turned my happiness into
mourning. I am fordone with punishment and my
pride is broken ; look on me again with favour. Is a
humble client worth so heavy a weight of anger ?
Aeolus makes not trial of himself where the sea's
waters are shallow ; no lowly hill encounters Boreas'
blasts ; 'tis the Alps he shakes, the summit of
Rhodope he harasses. Never doth the lightning
<pb id="v.2.p.201"/>
strike the humble willows nor do the modest shrubs
deserve the Thunderer's angry bolt ; lofty oaks and
agèd ashes are his victims.
Instead of the suppliant's branch plucked from
Minerva's sacred olive, instead of incense, I offer thee
this poem. Have mercy on thy servant. Restore
me, even me, to my former state, heal my cruel
wounds, bid life and honour return to me. Do thou,
who didst overthrow my fortune, build it up again.
Telephus came back cured by the magic of Achilles. 1
The same hand dealt death and healing — an enemy
restoring him to health by the assuagement of the
very pains he had inflicted.
But if neither my prayers nor my tears can soften
thee, spurn the Muses with thy foot and take away
my unlucky decorations, deprive me of my rank,
cast me aside who was once thy companion. A noteworthy
victory this thou hast won over a poor poet ;
redoubtable indeed the spoils that will grace such
a triumph. Let a fellow-countryman's power overwhelm
his wretched fellows. 2 Be my fate told to
our common fatherland and to Pharos, known of all
who sail the distant seas, and let Father Nile raise
his weeping head from out the flood and mourn my
cruel case along the banks of all his seven mouths.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="23" id="poem.74"><head>Apology to Alethius, the Quaestor. 3</head><p>

As I hope never to cross the plains of Ethiopia
beneath a summer sun, never to pass a winter naked
<pb id="v.2.p.203"/>
beneath the northern pole, never to entrust my
bellying sails to the Ionian Sea what time the Kids
bring round the rainy nights, never, driven by the
Furies' hellish blows, to re-read the verses of an
angry pedant, 1 'twas not, I swear, impudent
effrontery that moved me, nor did my tongue
exceed a just outspokenness. I admit I incautiously
found fault with a few lines, not realizing, luckless
wight, the heinousness of my offence. Others
attack the books of Orpheus and nothing is said ;
nor does thy fame, Maro, support thee in safety.
The very father of poetry. Homer, lord of Helicon,
knew the stigma of the censor's pen. Yet neither
Vergil nor Homer complains, for neither was a
quaestor and both were poor. See, then, I applaud !
See, in terror I praise every word and loudly cry
again and again <q>bravo!</q> Let him be appeased
and pardon at last, let him cease from wrath
— and with secure voice recite whate'er he will ; I
applaud.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="24" id="poem.83"><head>The Lobster,</head><p>

Long horns project from his head ; fierce eyes
stand out from his forehead ; his back is protected
by the armour of his self-grown shell. Nature
herself has rendered his skin a sufficient defence,
covering it with small, red, pointed spikes.

<pb id="v.2.p.205"/>
</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="25" id="poem.30"><head>Epithalamium of Palladius and Celerina: Preface 1 </head><p>

Asked to improvise a song in honour of a marriage
I find myself unwilling to refuse the bridegroom
and unable to say no to his father-in-law. The
former was my comrade-in-arms, the latter my
general ; at court the first is of equal rank with
me, the second my superior. Similarity of age
and pursuits made me a friend of Palladius ; age
and dignity set Celerinus far above me. The love
I bear the one demands my good offices as a poet,
the awe in which I hold the other a soldier's obedience :
I must sing.
It chanced that Venus had one day retired into
the bosom of a cave overgrown with vine to woo
sleep mid its alluring cool, and had laid her goddess
limbs on the thick grass, her head upon a heap
of flowers. The vine branches stir gently in the
breeze and sway the full- veined grapes. Slumber
befits the disorder of her brow, the midday heat will
none of coverings, and the leaves show through them
the gleam of her bare breast. Round her He the
nymphs of Ida and hard by beneath a lofty oaktree
the three Graces sleep with interlaced arms.
Here and there, where'er the shade invites them,
repose winged Cupids. Their bows are unstrung
and their quivers hang from the branches of
neighbouring trees, instinct with latent fire. Some
<pb id="v.2.p.207"/>
wake and play or wander through the thickets in
search of birds' nests or take delight in plucking
dewy apples as a gift for Venus or hunt the gadding
vine for grapes, and, poised on their wings, climb
its branches to the very tops of the elm-trees.
Others keep guard over the wood and drive off
the wanton, curious Dryads, the country gods and
the woodland deities, discharging flaming darts at
the amorous Fauns who try from a distance to catch
a glimpse of Venus' bower. Suddenly there arose
cries and shoutings from the neighbouring city ;
joyous acclamations of youth and the strains of the
lyre accompanying dancing in the streets. Through
all the hills of Italy the name of Celerina is chanted
and every field re-echoes that of her husband Palladius.
The pleasant sound reached the goddess' ears ;
aroused by the noise she sat up and with her fair
hands rubbed from her eyes the residue of sleep ;
then, just as she was, her hair disordered, her
breasts uncovered, she leapt from her soft couch
and summoned Hymen from among the unnumbered
Loves that formed her bodyguard. (Him, son of
the Muse, Cytherea chose out and made the patron
god of marriage. Without his sanction is no entry
into wedlock nor is it lawful but with his leave to
uplift the first wedding-torches.) At last he is
found. There he lay stretched beneath a tall planetree
joining with wax pipes of unequal length,
seeking to repeat with his lips Maenalian measures
and pastoral tunes, while, as his mouth ran over
them, he varied his breathing upon the slender reed.
Seeing Venus he stopped ; noiseless to the ground
from out the nerveless grasp of his fingers fell the
<pb id="v.2.p.209"/>
pipe. Affection lights up his eyes ; a modest blush
suffuses those sun-browned cheeks so snowy-white
by nature, clothed, too, with the scarce seen down of
youth where ceased the ne'er cut hair. Silent he
stood and the goddess first addressed him. <q> Wilt
thou, boy, never leave thy beloved song ? Wilt thou
never have enough of thy mother's gifts, ever
devoted to the Muses' task and too eager to rival
thy parent 1? What is it thou dost practise all
alone in the midday heat ? Dost thou now despise
the lyre and seekest thou rather the woods of Lycaeus
and the herds and Echo resounding from the rocks ?
Come hither and tell me the reason for this general
rejoicing. What marriage is this that is attended
with such ceremony and such demonstrations of
joy ? Who is the newly dowered bride ? Of what
country, what race are they that are wed ? Tell
me from what land they spring and what their
parentage. Needs must thou know, for no marriage
can take place without thee and by covenant with
thee are wedlock's joys first tasted.</q>
He replied : <q><p>Long have I been wondering,
goddess, at thy delay, and marvelled that thou didst
take no notice of so world-famed an union. They
are no common folk that now submit them to thy
laws. Two families are united illustrious with
consulships, upheld by the highest offices, in whose
veins flows the noblest blood of all the world. What
island on whose coasts thunder the waves of the Red
Sea, what tract of Ethiopia, what land so far withdrawn
from human intercourse but has heard the
blessings that the affection of his country calls down
on the head of Palladius' sire for his clemency, his
learning, his wit, his genial age ? He has trodden
<pb id="v.2.p.211"/>
every rung of the ladder of honours, has held every
place at court, and reached the highest of all offices,
directing the deliberations of the senate of the
East with a sure authority. Such is the bridegroom's
brilliance. The bride first saw the light in
the old city of Tomi by the mouth of the Danube.
She is descended on her mother's side from noble
ancestors famed in war and enriched by war's spoils
and derives especial glory from the renown of that
stalwart Celerinus who, when appointed to the
defence of Meroë and the Nile, and, after the death
by lightning of Carus 1 in Parthia, offered the throne
and dominion of the world by his soldiers, paid
no heed to their clamour and preferred repose to
an empire. Of his own will he refused when it was
offered that which men will use every sort of violence
and outrage every sort of right to acquire. For
the first time virtue was reckoned above a throne
and sovereignty, making offer of herself, met with
a refusal. Sadly did Fortune confess herself beaten
by a mortal. Great it is to deserve high office, still
greater to have despised it.
</p><p>Celerina's father has won every title that a
warrior may. Step by step he has reached the
highest of all ranks, that of commander-in-chief ; it is
he who dispenses titles of honour, settles the garrisons
of the provinces, unites the scattered forces of the
empire, and checks the disposition of its troops.
He decides the defences of Sarmatia and the legions
that are to face the wild Getae or keep Saxon and
Scot in subjection. He knows how many cohorts
fringe the shore of Ocean, how great an army
maintains peace along the banks of the Rhine.
In the family of Celerina is to be found unspotted
<pb id="v.2.p.213"/>
virtue, unfeigned loyalty, and diligence guided
by knowledge. She is Stilicho's choice ; to such
choice and judgement no praise can be added.
It were a shame, Venus, shouldst thou not be
present at the marriage of such a maid. Come,
bring all thy train. Fain would I shake the withering
wreaths, brandish the torches, and devote the
night to pleasure. Now even this my pipe gives
no dishonoured service answering the choirs' songs.</p></q>
</p><p>
Scarce had Hymen spoken and she bathes her in
the cool stream, gathers her flowing hair, and renews
her charms, taking from out the press the wondrous
garments spun by her mother Dione. Her chariot
is heaped with flowers and the yoke thereof is
fragrant with blossoms. Flowers entwine the reins
that fetter her bright doves. From all sides the birds
flock together, those that soothe with their song the
roar of Athesis, those whom Larius hears, Benacus
feeds, or Mincius welcomes with his quiet flood.
Quiet are those waters now that the birds' plaintive
notes resound there no more. The swans have flown
away and left the banks of Eridanus and the sounding
marshes of Padusa. Right glad are the wanton
Loves ; they catch and harness the birds and ride
them through the clouds before the eyes of Venus.
There they join in noisy battle, lean forward to strike
one another, and fall but suffer no hurt. Fallen they
overtake their steeds with flight swifter than theirs,
for the charioteer is fleeter than the chariot.
Soon as they reached the doors of the marriage-chamber
 they empty baskets full of red spring
flowers, pouring forth showers of roses and scattering
from their laden quivers violets gathered in Venus'
meadow, violets untouched e'en by the heat of the
<pb id="v.2.p.215"/>

Dog-star who had tempered for their frail beauty
his accustomed fires. Others throughout the palace
poured forth from jewelled caskets unguents gathered
by the banks of the Nile from trees whose bark,
when wounded by the cruel finger-nail, oozed with
rich gum. Cytherea approaches the bride, and,
despite her tears, drew her from her mother's arms.
Her swelling breast betokens maidenhood ripe for
marriage, her skin is whiter than lilies or than snow,
and her golden hair points to the Danube as her
birthplace. Then, taking the hand of the bridegroom,
Venus joins to it that of the bride and with
these words blesses their union : <q> Live as one and
fulfil all my rites. Give a thousand kisses, let arm
be bruised with enfolding arm, and lips so join that
soul may meet soul. And thou, husband, put not
thy confidence in rude love-making ; thy wife's
love cannot be won by threats, but must be gained
by entreaty. And do thou yield to thy husband
nor seek to show anger ; use not thy nails as
weapons like the women of Scythia. I beg thee
submit to conquest ; so shalt thou be indeed a
wife, so a mother. Why are there tears in thine
eyes ? Believe me, thou shalt love him whom now
thou fearest.</q>
So spake she, and chose from out her winged
attendants the two whose bows were strongest and
their aim most sure. At once Aethon and Pyrois
leaped forward, their bright wings tinged with purple.
Dipping their shafts in pure honey the one aims his at
the bride, the other his at the bridegroom. They draw
their bows ; the strings twang and the sure arrows
cleave the air with equal speed and implant themselves
at equal depths in the hearts of the twain.
<pb id="v.2.p.217"/>

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="26" id="poem.49"><head>Aponus. 1</head><p>

Fount that prolongest life for the dwellers in
Antenor's city, banishing by thy neighbouring waters
all harmful fates, seeing that thy marvels stir utterance
even in the dumb, that a people's love bids
poets to honour thee in song, and that there is
no hand whose fingers have not traced for thee
some lines in thankful witness of prayers granted,
shall I not be held guilty alike by the Muses and
the Nymphs if I alone sing not thy praises ? How
can a spot whose fame is on so many lips rightly
be passed over by me in slighting silence ?
Lower than a lofty hill yet higher than the level
plain rises a gentle eminence,, clear to see from all
around. Prolific is it in hot springs, for wherever
water penetrates its recesses encountering fires
drive it forth. The crumbling ground exhales
vapours, and the water, closed down in its prison of
burning rock, forces its way out by many a fissured
channel. 'Tis a region of liquid fire where Vulcan's
flames spring forth from earth's breast, a land of
burning and of sulphur. Who would not think it
barren ? Yet are those fiery fields green with
verdure ; grass grows o'er the burning marl and,
though the very rocks melt at the heat, plants,
mocking at the flames, boldly flourish.
Beyond this are vast furrows cut in the rock,
scarring and cleaving it in long lines. Traces are
<pb id="v.2.p.219"/>

they — so tradition tells — of Hercules' plough, or
else chance did the ploughshare's work. In the
middle of the hill is what seems a broad, steaming
sea, an azure lake of vast extent. Great is the
space it covers, still greater its depth where it
plunges down and loses itself beneath the rocky
caverns. A thick pall of steam hangs over it ;
its waters cannot be touched nor drunk though
they are transparent as crystal to the very bottom.
Nature took counsel for herself and lest that lake
should be entirely beyond our ken she let our eyes
penetrate what, because of its heat, our bodies
could not enter. When a breeze scatters the
thick clouds of steam and clears the grey surface
of the erstwhile vaporous water you can gaze with
wonder on the valley floor below that glassy flood
where glint old weapons, king's gifts 1 of bygone
days (between these a gulf of other hue, dark
with the eddyings of black sand, swallows the
hastening waters ; below there opens a cavern into
which the darkling flood pours, filling every nook
and cranny with its swirling eddies) ; then are
revealed the hidden places of the hill which, bent
round in a bow, encircles the surface of the water
with an overhanging rim. 2
A verdant amphitheatre surrounds this steaming
cauldron, and the ground floats lightly with slender
film 3 ; never will it give way beneath the visitor's
weight, upholding his timorous feet, trusty though
seeming so unsure. One would think it the work of
man's hand, so smoothly does its circuit enfold the
shore, slight and yet firm all the way. The water
<pb id="v.2.p.221"/>
in the lake stands motionless, filling it to the brim
and fearing to o'erstep its appointed limit. The
overflow runs in a stream down a sloping rock
and seeks the undulating plain below. A natural
but tortuous channel carries the water away and
thence it flows into an open conduit of lead. These
pipes, noiselessly impregnated with some powderous
mineral that the water carries down, produce a snowwhite
distillation of salt. The streams branch off in
all directions carrying with them this natural wealth
whithersoever art has directed their going, flexing
this way and that their errant courses, flowing in
swift torrent below aqueducts and warming the
arches with the heat of their rushing waters. Within
the arches, amid the roarings of the echoing rock,
issues forth fiercer steam and vapour as the water
rushes out. Then the sick, weak with sweating,
seek next the stagnant pools that long time has
made pleasantly cool.
Hail to thee, stream, generous giver of the waters
of healing, chief glory of the land of Italy, doctor
of all that come to thee, common helper of all
Aesculapius' sons ; a very present deity for whose
aid there is nought to pay. Whether it be
that hell's fiery streams have burst their banks and
that Phlegethon gone astray bestows his heat upon
the upper world, or that a river, originally of cold
water, sinks down into veins of sulphur and rises
thence afire (as one would think from the smell),
or that the mountain in arbitration summons the
two elements to a treaty, balancing a certain quantity
of fire against a similar amount of water that neither
yield to the other but under a just law of equipoise
each may withstand the other's might — whatsoever
<pb id="v.2.p.223"/>


shall prove to be the cause, whatever the origin,
of this we may be sure — that thou flowest not
without design. Who would dare to ascribe such
a miracle to chance ? Who could deny that the overruling
gods have so ordained ? Nature's lord, who
measures the centuries by the stars, has given thee a
place of honour among the works of his divinity, and,
pitying the feebleness of our human bodies, has
bidden pour forth healing waters for the earth, and
from the riven hills burst forth streams that should
win pardon from the Fates' relentless distaffs.
Happy ye whose lot it is to dwell by those banks
and to possess Aponus for your own ; you no plague
of earth, no pestilence-fraught winds of the south,
nor Sirius with his cruel fires can harm. Should
Lachesis' fatal thread threaten death men find in
thee a more propitious fate. If it chance that
noxious humours swell their limbs or that excess
of bile inflames their ailing bowels they need not
to open their veins nor to cure one wound with
another nor yet to drink medicine of bitter herbs.
By thy water's aid they renew their lost strength
without suffering ; 'mid luxury the sick find relief
from pain.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="27" id="poem.44"><head>The Phoenix. 1</head><p>

There is a leafy wood fringed by Ocean's farthest
marge beyond the Indes and the East where Dawn's
panting coursers first seek entrance ; it hears the
lash close by, what time the watery threshold echoes
to the dewy car ; and hence comes forth the rosy
<pb id="v.2.p.225"/>
morn while night, illumined by those far-shining
wheels of fire, casts off her sable cloak and broods less
darkly. This is the kingdom of the blessed bird of the
sun where it dwells in solitude defended by the inhospitable
nature of the land and immune from the
ills that befall other living creatures ; nor does it
suffer infection from the world of men. Equal to the
gods is that bird whose life rivals the stars and whose
renascent limbs weary the passing centuries. It
needs no food to satisfy hunger nor any drink to
quench thirst ; the sun's clear beam is its food, the
sea's rare spray its drink — exhalations such as these
form its simple nourishment. A mysterious fire
flashes from its eye, and a flaming aureole enriches
its head. Its crest shines with the sun's own light
and shatters the darkness with its calm brilliance.
Its legs are of Tyrian purple ; swifter than those of
the Zephyrs are its wings of flower-like blue dappled
with rich gold.
Never was this bird conceived nor springs it from
any mortal seed, itself is alike its own father and
son, and with none to recreate it, it renews its outworn
limbs with a rejuvenation of death, and at
each decease wins a fresh lease of life. For when a
thousand summers have passed far away, a thousand
winters gone by, a thousand springs in their course
given to the husbandmen that shade 1 of which autumn
robbed them, then at last, fordone by the number
of its years, it falls a victim to the burden of age ;
as a tall pine on the summit of Caucasus, wearied
with storms, heels over with its weight and threatens
at last to crash in ruin ; one portion falls by reason
of the unceasing winds, another breaks away rotted
by the rain, another consumed by the decay of years.
<pb id="v.2.p.227"/>
Now the Phoenix's bright eye grows dim and the
pupil becomes palsied by the frost of years, like
the moon when she is shrouded in clouds and her horn
begins to vanish in the mist. Now his wings, wont
to cleave the clouds of heaven, can scarce raise them
from the earth. Then, realizing that his span of life
is at an end and in preparation for a renewal of his
splendour, he gathers dry herbs from the sun-warmed
hills, and making an interwoven heap of the branches
of the precious tree of Saba he builds that pyre which
shall be at once his tomb and his cradle.
On this he takes his seat and as he grows weaker
greets the Sun with his sweet voice ; offering up
prayers and supplications he begs that those fires will
give him renewal of strength. Phoebus, on seeing
him afar, checks his reins and staying his course consoles
his loving child with these words : <q> Thou who
art about to leave thy years behind upon yon pyre,
who, by this pretence of death, art destined to rediscover
life ; thou whose decease means but the
renewal of existence and who by self-destruction
regainest thy lost youth, receive back thy life, quit
the body that must die, and by a change of form
come forth more beauteous than ever.</q>
So speaks he, and shaking his head casts one of his
golden hairs and smites willing Phoenix with its
life-giving effulgence. Now, to ensure his rebirth,
he suffers himself to be burned and in his eagerness
to be born again meets death with joy. Stricken
with the heavenly flame the fragrant pile catches
fire and burns the aged body. The moon in amaze
checks her milk-white heifers and heaven halts his
revolving spheres, while the pyre conceives the new
life ; Nature takes care that the deathless bird
<pb id="v.2.p.229"/>
perish not, and calls upon the sun, mindful of his
promise, to restore its immortal glory to the world.
Straightway the life spirit surges through his
scattered limbs ; the renovated blood floods his veins.
The ashes show signs of life ; they begin to move
though there is none to move them, and feathers
clothe the mass of cinders. He who was but now
the sire comes forth from the pyre the son and
successor ; between life and life lay but that brief
space wherein the pyre burned.
His first delight is to consecrate his father's spirit
by the banks of the Nile and to carry to the land of
Egypt the burned mass from which he was born.
With all speed he wings his way to that foreign
strand, carrying the remains in a covering of grass.
Birds innumerable accompany him, and whole flocks
thereof throng his airy flight. Their mighty host
shuts out the sky where'er it passes. But from
among so vast an assemblage none dares outstrip
the leader ; all follow respectfully in the balmy
wake of their king. Neither the fierce hawk nor
the eagle, Jove's own armour-bearer, fall to fighting ;
in honour of their common master a truce is observed
by all. Thus the Parthian monarch leads his
barbarous hosts by yellow Tigris' banks, all glorious
with jewels and rich ornament and decks his tiara
with royal garlands ; his horse's bridle is of gold,
Assyrian embroidery embellishes his scarlet robes,
and proud with sovereignty he lords it o'er his
numberless slaves.
There is in Egypt a well-known city celebrated
for its pious sacrifices and dedicated to the worship
of the Sun. Its temple rests on a hundred columns
hewn from the quarries of Thebes. Here, as the
<pb id="v.2.p.231"/>


story tells, the Phoenix is wont to store his father's
ashes and, adoring the image of the god, his master,
to entrust his precious burden to the flames. He
places on the altar that from which he is sprung
and that which remains of himself. Bright shines
the wondrous threshold ; the fragrant shrine is filled
with the holy smoke of the altar and the odour of
Indian incense, penetrating even as far as the
Pelusiac marshes, fills the nostrils of men, flooding
them with its kindly influence and with a scent
sweeter than that of nectar perfumes the seven
mouths of the dark Nile.
Happy bird, heir to thine own self ! Death which
proves our undoing restores thy strength. Thine
ashes give thee life and though thou perish not
thine old age dies. Thou hast beheld all that
has been, hast witnessed the passing of the ages.
Thou knowest when it was that the waves of the
sea rose and o'erflowed the rocks, what year it
was that Phaethon's error devoted to the flames.
Yet did no destruction overwhelm thee ; sole survivor
thou livest to see the earth subdued ; against thee
the Fates gather not up their threads, powerless to
do thee harm.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="28" id="poem.47"><head>The Nile. 1</head><p>

Blessèd is the man who cleaves the soil of Egypt
with his plough ; he need not hope for clouds to
shroud the heavens in darkness nor call upon the
storm-winds that bring the chilling rain or the
rainbow bright with its various colours
<pb id="v.2.p.233"/>
Fertile is Egypt without clouds ; here alone is
sunshine and yet rain. She regards not the sky,
needs not the wind ; enough for her the water
she herself contains, Nile's overflow. This swiftly-flowing
river rises in the mountainous country
of the south where it suffers the heats of the torrid
zone and of the scorching Crab and issues forth
from regions unknown into our world. Whence
it comes none knows, for vain has ever been the
search after its springing nor has any ever seen that
source. 'Tis said that, fashioned without witness, it
pours forth waters that have known a clime other than
ours. Thence with errant stream it stretches through
all Libya, and through Ethiopia's thousand dusky
kingdoms where it waters lands condemned to the
sun's unceasing fires, saviour of thirsting peoples, and
threads its course across Meroë and black Syene
and through the country of the wild Blemyae.
The unconquered Garamantes and the Gyrraei who
can tame wild animals drink of its waters, as do
those tribes who dwell in huge rocky caverns,
gathering the wood of ebony -trees and robbing
the elephant of his tusks of ivory, and the folk who
wear arrows in their hair.
Neither the cause nor yet the season of its overflow
is the same as that of other rivers. Its waters
rise neither because of melted snows nor by reason
of rains flooding its rocky marge ; for when dull
winter giveth increase to other rivers Nile keeps
within his banks ; when other rivers flow with
diminished stream, Nile, under other laws, rises.
For of a truth whatever toll summer has exacted
from all rivers Nature repays to the Nile, and waters
gathered together from the whole world meet thus
<pb id="v.2.p.235"/>


in one river. Then when the Dog-star increases
the heat of the sun and sucks up all moisture, drying
up earth's veins and filling heaven with its scorching
rays, winter comes upon the Nile, though elsewhere
all is summer. Then, bringing back to the fainting
husbandmen its accustomed waters, it overflows
ampler than the Aegean, fiercer than the deep
Ionian, and spreads itself over the low-lying country.
All the fields are aswim ; plough-land sounds to
the beat of the oar, and full often the shepherd,
o'ercome with summer's heat, wakes to see flocks
and fold carried away by the flood.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="29" id="poem.48"><head>The Magnet.</head><p>

Whosoever with anxious thought examines the
universe and searches out the origin of things — the
reason of the sun's and moon's eclipse, the causes of
comets' red and baneful fires, the source of the winds,
the motion that makes the earth to quake, the force
that splits the heavens in twain, the noise of the
thunder, the brilliance of the rainbow, let this man
(if man's mind has any power to conceive the truth)
explain to me something I would fain understand.
There is a stone called the loadstone ; black, dull,
and common. It does not adorn the braided hair
of kings nor the snowy necks of girls, nor yet shine
in the jewelled buckles of warriors' belts. But
consider the marvellous properties of this dull-looking
stone and you will see that it is of more
worth than lovely gems and any pearl sought of
<pb id="v.2.p.237"/>
Indian amid the seaweed on the Red Sea's shores.
It lives on iron and feeds on its inflexible nature ;
iron is its food and nourishment ; from iron it
recruits its strength. This seemingly inedible
food, circulating throughout its body, renews its
hidden powers. Without iron the loadstone dies ;
its bulk wastes away from lack of nourishment and
thirst parches its emptied veins.
Mars, who strikes cities with his bloody spear, and
Venus, who changes human cares to ease, share a
common shrine and temple built of gold. Each
deity has his own image ; Mars, a polished iron
statue, Venus, one fashioned of the loadstone. The
priest duly celebrates their union. The nuptial
torch precedes the choir ; myrtle wreaths adorn the
portals, the couches are piled with roses, while cloth
of scarlet dye, as befits a marriage, adorns the bridal
chamber. But, lo, a prodigy : Cytherea, without
quitting her station, attracts her husband to her,
and recalling the scene of which heaven was once
witness, clasps Mars to her bosom with amorous
breath. There she holds him suspended ; her arms
enfold the helmet of the god and clasp his whole
body in a lifelike embrace. He, stirred by the far-compelling
influence of her breath, is drawn towards
her by the secret chains of his jewel-bride Nature
presides over the divine marriage ; a binding breath
woos the steel to wedlock; suddenly two deities
are mated in secret union.
What hidden warmth infuses mutual sympathy
into these twin metals ? What harmony makes
one their stubborn souls ? The stone sighs and
burns, and smitten with love recognizes in the iron
the object of its desire, while the iron experiences a
<pb id="v.2.p.239"/>

gentle attraction for the stone. It is thus that Venus often holds the fierce god of war in check and softens his fiery glance when the angry blood boils within him and with drawn sword he whets his warmth. She alone can face his fierce steeds and appease the tumult of his heart, calming his anger with gentle flame. Peace and quiet are restored within his soul; he abjures the heat of battle and bends his head, helmed with ruddy plumes, to kiss the goddess.


Cruel boy, is aught beyond thy powers? Thou dost master the mighty thunderbolt; thou canst force the Thunderer to leave the sky and bellow amid the waves. Now thou showest that thou canst smite cold rocks and shapes not instinct with feeling or life, that stone can be wounded by thine arrows. Rocks are stirred by a passion of their own; iron is obedient to thy blandishments; thy flames exercise dominion over hardest marl. 

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="30" id="poem.29"><head>In Praise of Serena1</head><p>


Say, my muse, why tarriest thou so long to crown Serena's brows with the Pierian garland they so well deserve? Thinkest thou the gift too poor shouldst thou, a queen, deck but with flowers the head of a queen accustomed rather to wear a tiara bright with all the jewels of the Red Sea? Nay, those flowers of thine are such that neither Boreas' cold blast nor Sirius' scorching heat can hurt them; theirs is the bloom of everlasting spring for they
<pb id="v.2.p.241"/>
have grown by Permessus' fount and been watered
by Aganippe's wave. Those flowers have fed the
holy bees that skim the meadows and transmit
the honey of Helicon to coming generations.
Did ever the single theme of woman's worth more
fitly stir other bards ? The Greeks sing of Alcestis,
that chaste Thessalian, who, to win her husband from
death, freely offered herself in his stead, allowing
him to enjoy her own span of life. The Latin
Muse takes prophetic Tanaquil 1 for her theme
or Cloelia breasting Tiber's waves in her return to
Rome or the maiden Claudia dragging with her
own hair the ship which bore Cybele, what time it
stuck fast in that same stream. Does old Homer's
soaring soul essay aught else throughout his song ?
Dangers from Charybdis' gulf, from Scylla's dogs,
from Circe's cup, the escape of Ulysses from the greed
of Antiphates, the passage of the ship between
the rocks where sat the Sirens to whose alluring
voices the rowers were deaf, the blinding of Cyclops,
the desertion of Calypso — all these do but redound
to the glory of Penelope, and the whole scene is
set to display her chastity alone. Toils by land and
sea, ten years of war, ten years of wandering,
all do but illustrate the fidelity of a wife. Let
Claudia rejoice in the goddess' witness and with
heaven's help vindicate her claim to chastity,
freeing at the same moment the vessel's stern
and her own character from shame. Let Penelope
by artful delays deceive the madness of the suitors
and, ever faithful to Ulysses, delude their solicitations,
ever winding up again by night the warp of
her day-spun web. Yet shall not one of these
heroines dare to vie with Serena.
<pb id="v.2.p.243"/>
But if noble birth opens the first path to fame
and all its causes are to be traced to ancestry,
what blood more noble, what birth more gentle
than that of royalty ? Such majesty could not
have flourished within the house of a mere commoner
nor could glory so great have sprung from
any simple home. Thou art famous for that thine
uncle was an emperor, more famous by reason
of the warlike deeds of thy grandsire 1 who carried
the Roman eagles across the British Channel and
repulsed the armed bands of the Gaetulians.
Cornelia, daughter of the Scipios, must cease to
vaunt her high birth and to boast that she received
for dower the spoils of Carthage. Thou canst point
to ancestral triumphs in either hemisphere ; on
thy brow sit two crowns, the one won by thy
sires from Scotland, the other from the South.
Thou glory of the world, what time Lucina assisted at
the birth of thee, our new star, thy house had not yet
taken on itself the government of the whole earth ;
not till after Serena's birth did it know world-empire.
What human voice can worthily sing thy praises,
Spain ? Though India first bathes the new-born sun
in her ocean yet when the light dies thou waterest
his wearied steeds and in thy weaves the stars find
refreshment. Rich in horses, bounteous in crops,
dowered with mines, prolific in good emperors, to
thee the world owes Trajan, from thee sprang the
Aelian 2 race. From thy land came the brothers who
now govern us and their father. Other races whom
Rome has either received into alliance or subdued
by arms serve the varying needs of empire : the
corn of Egypt, the harvests of Africa go to feed
our armies ; Gaul recruits our powerful legions ;
<pb id="v.2.p.245"/>
Illyria produces stout horsemen for our cavalry. But Spain alone pays that rarest tribute — the gift of emperors. Corn, money, soldiers come from all the world over and are gathered together from every quarter of the globe; Spain gives us men to govern and direct all this. Nor was she content to be esteemed only for her famous heroes, did she not also excel in heroines, and, emulous to win glory from either sex, bestow upon us Flaccilla,5 Maria, and the fair Serena.

At thy6 birth they tell how swelling Tagus o'erflowed the rich fields with gold; Galicia laughed with flowers and on the rose-covered banks of Duria's fair stream the once white fleeces of the sheep were everywhere turned to purple grain. The Cantabrian main cast up jewels upon the shore, and the pale Asturian delves no more into the bowels of the mountain; on the day hallowed by thy birth earth poured forth gold as dross from her open veins. Beneath the caves of the Pyrenees the river Nymphs gather the fiery thunder-stones. The Nereids, yielding to the flowing tide, followed the flooding waves up the river's courses; there, in the sight of all, they acknowledged thee their queen by their applause and celebrated thy coming marriage in prophetic strains. And all the time beneath another sky grew the young Stilicho; he lived unwitting of his fortune, of the destined bride that awaited him afar, and in a distant world was the union of such destinies prepared.

No mortal nurse was worthy to watch over thy cradle. First the Nymphs gave thee suck at their fragrant breasts; the three Graces held thee in their arms and breathing upon thee taught thee to speak. Roses sprang where'er thou didst creep over the 

<pb id="v.2.p.247"/>
grass and white lilies blossomed there ; didst thou
close thine eyes in quiet sleep, there burgeoned the
purple violet to adorn thy grassy couch with her
imperial colour. Thy mother dared not tell of such
great omens and, knowing her own secret vow,
hides with eager hope the fulfilment she prays for.
Thy father Honorius held thee in a close embrace.
Whenever Theodosius — not emperor then — came
to his brother's house he covered thee with kisses
and loved to take thee with him to his own home.
Then turning to thy mother with gentle complaint,
<q>Why,</q> thou saidst, <q> take me from my own
home ? This man ever commands.</q> 1  Prophetic
was the sportive word and thine infant lips gave
augury of empire. At the death of thy sire
thine illustrious uncle adopted thee and to console
thee for the bitterness of that loss, bestowed upon
thee, his brother's child, more love than he could
have bestowed on any child of his own. Leda's
twin sons were not united with a bond of affection
more sure. He gave his own son the name his
brother had borne, hoping in some way to discover
in that son the image of the brother he had loved and
lost. Finally, when the people's choice had summoned
him to take up the reins of empire, Theodosius would
not vouchsafe his sons any proof of his affection for
them until he had summoned thee and thy faithful
sister from Spain to the lands of morning.
So now they leave Tagus' banks and the home of
the west winds and hasten towards the cities that
recognize the empery of the east. They come, the
maidens twain, his brother's children, on this side
Serena the younger, on that Thermantia 2 the elder
born, strange as yet to love ; nor has Hymen bent
<pb id="v.2.p.249"/>
their snowy necks to the yoke of Venus. Spirited
yet modest is the glance of each; of each the beauty
fires the hearts of men. Such as are Diana and her
sister, motherless child of Jove, when they visit the
realm of their uncle, lord of the sea (the foaming
waves grow smooth before them in honour of the
approach of the chaste goddesses ; Galatea ceases her
mad frolics, bold Triton dares not clasp Cymothoë in
his embrace ; o'er the whole ocean the dictates of
purity hold sway and Proteus prevents even Neptune's
flocks from indulging in their shameless amours)
— even such the daughters of Honorius enter the
palace and view the home of their royal parent.
Both did the prince embrace with a father's love
but justly did affection turn more readily to thee.
Often when, his heart troubled by the anxieties of
public business, he returned home depressed or
angered, when his own sons fled his presence and
even Flaccilla feared to approach her exasperated
husband, thou alone wert able to stay his wrath and
bring healing with sweet converse. On thy words
he would hang, to thee confess his secret thoughts.
Thy modesty, worthy of an earlier age, surpassed
even that of modest girlhood. Less chaste than thee
was that daughter of Alcinous whom Homer, in his
praises of her, compares to Diana ; she who spread
her clothes on the shore to dry and sported with her
attendant maids, throwing a golden ball from hand to
hand until she fled in alarm from Ulysses issuing forth
from the thicket where he had been enjoying sleep
after his shipwreck.
The study of the Muses and the songs of poets
of olden time were thy delight. Turning the
pages of Homer, bard of Smyrna, or those of Virgil,
<pb id="v.2.p.251"/>
poet of Mantua, thou findest fault with Helen nor
canst approve of Dido. Thy chaste mind fastens
upon examples more noble : Laodamia following
Protesilaus as he returned to the shades ; Euadne
who cast herself on the flaming P3rre whereon
her husband Capaneus perished, wishing to mingle
her ashes with his ; grave Lucrece who fell upon a
chaste sword, she who self-slain bore witness to the
tyrant's crime, aroused to war her country's righteous
wrath, drove Tarquin into exile and died gloriously,
having avenged by her one sacrifice both chastity and
freedom. Of such deeds thou dost read with joy, thyself
not less in virtue though more blessed of fortune.
Now that thou art of an age for marriage the
hopes of the young courtiers run high, but the
prince hesitates to select the happy man who is to
share thy couch and regal state.
The pages of the poets tell how ancient kings
bade suitors contend on the hard terms of purchasing
the bride at hazard of their lives, and rejoiced
that death should be the wooer of their daughters.
Pelops escaped the weapons of Pisa's king, thanks
to the chariot Neptune gave him, for it was Myrtilus
who tricked King Oenomaus by withdrawing the
lynch-pin from the chariot-wheel. Panting Hippomenes
got the better of Atalanta, daughter of
Schoeneus, who followed close on his traces, a sword
in her hand, by means of the golden apples. The
inhabitants of Calydon watched from their high
battlements the struggle of Hercules with the rivergod
when, Deianira being the prize of victory, the
panting hero shouted in triumph and Achelous paled
and shrank away, shorn of his horn, the wound
whereof the astonished river nymphs sought to heal.
<pb id="v.2.p.253"/>
But it is neither to the apples of the Hesperides
nor to victory over a river nor to treacherous
tampering with a chariot-wheel that Stilicho owes
the winning of thy hand ; the emperor himself
adjudged him worthy thereof, for that his valour
had been proved in countless wars ; his own courage
won him an empress to wife. Generals have often
bestowed decorations on those who have deserved
them in battle : one man wins the mural crown,
another the civic wreath, a third, for having defeated
an enemy's fleet, the naval decoration. Stilicho is
the only warrior who, as the reward for signal services
in war, has won from a grateful father's hand the
crown of marriage.
Thermantia owes her uncle no lesser debt of
gratitude : she too was married to a general. But
how far inferior to thine, Serena, was thy sister's
fortune ! For thee with fairer promise Rome's
guardian-angel kindles the torches, and glorious
are the garlands that thy marriage brings. First to
be set in his charge is the care of the horses reared in
the royal stables, whose dams were Phrygian mares,
or such as have pastured on Argos' plains, whose sires
were Cappadocians. Soon he exercises a double command
in the army 1 and fulfils his functions with such
energy and success that, howsoever great the honours
heaped upon him by the emperor, his deserts are ever
in excess of his reward. Whenever the cloud of war
threatened thou mightest have seen experienced
commanders of horse and foot give way to a leader
younger and of less exalted rank and without more
ado entrust to him the whole war. Neither rank nor
age stays older men through shame from ready
obedience to a youth. As when on a calm sea
<pb id="v.2.p.255"/>
every sailor maintains his right to manage the rudder,
but if the blustering south wind comes upon them
and the waves buffet them on either side, then
contention ceases and the sailors accepting a more
skilful hand admit their fear (for the storm has set
a term to their jealousy), even so Stilicho when the
storm of war broke out in Thrace was chosen as
commander-in-chief over the heads of all. Fear,
that surest of judges, won him the votes of all ;
regard for safety o'ermastered ambition and jealousy
was overthrown by dread.
How thou didst tremble and weep when the cruel
bugles summoned thy lord to arms ! With a countenance
wet with tears thou saw'st him leave thy
home praying for his safe return after snatching the
final hasty kiss from between the bars of his crested
helmet's visor. But again what joy when at length
he returned, preceded by the clarion of victory and
thou couldst hold his still mailed form in thy loving
arms once more ! How sweet the long hours of the
chaste night wherein thou badest him tell in safety the
story of his battles. Whilst he was at the wars thou
didst not comb thy shining hair nor wear the jewels
that were wont to adorn thee. Thy time is spent in
worship and in prayer as thy suppliant tresses sweep
the temple floor ; uncared for perishes the gracious
beauty that shall return with thine own lord.
But love languishes not in idleness and sloth ;
as far as it could a woman's watchful care seconds
his deeds of glory. While he warred with foreign
nations thou keepest guard lest mad envy or burning
calumny should dare aught against him while
far away, and lest, when war was ended abroad,
treachery should lie secretly in wait to injure him
<pb id="v.2.p.257"/>
at home. Thou didst indeed once show thy vigilance
what time Rufinus, hatching his plots, sought means
to destroy his master by traitorously stirring up the
Getae against Rome, for thou didst search out his
foul conspiracy and in fear for thy husband's safety,
didst send him warning by letters and messages.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="31" id="poem.40"><head>Letter to Serena.</head><p>

At the first kindling of Orpheus' marriage-torch
when festive Hymen filled the countryside of Thrace
the beasts and gay-plumaged birds strove among
themselves what best gifts they could bring their
poet. Mindful of the cave whose sounding rocks
had offered a wondrous theatre for his tuneful
lyre, the lynxes brought him crystal from the
summits of Caucasus ; griffins golden nuggets from
regions of the north ; doves wreaths of roses and
other flowers which they had flown to gather from
Venus' meadow ; the swan bore from the stream of
its native Padus amber broken from the boughs of
the famed sisters 1 ; while the cranes, after their war
with the pygmies, recrossed the Nile and gathered
in their mouths the precious pearls of the Red Sea.
There came, too, immortal Phoenix from the distant
East, bearing rare spices in his curved talons. No
bird nor beast was there but brought to that marriage-feast
tribute so richly deserved by Orpheus' lyre.
Busily Calliopea decked her son's bride with her
riches and all the treasures of Helicon, and, moreover,
<pb id="v.2.p.259"/>
with a mother's pride dared to invite to her son's
wedding the queen of starry heaven herself. The
queen of the gods spurned not her request either
out of respect for Calliopea herself or because she was
drawn by a just affection for the pious poet who had
so often in her honour chanted his songs before her
altars, hymning Juno's godhead with his sweet voice
and telling of the battles of her lord the Thunderer
waged on the plains of Phlegra, and of the menace
of Enceladus and the Titans there broken. Straightway,
counting the marriage - night worthy of her
presence, she brought heavenly gifts to deck the
bridal, gifts such as stoop not to adorn mortals,
gifts that the gods alone may possess. But as Juno
showed herself gracious to Thracian Orpheus, so wilt
thou, Serena, be favourable to my prayers. The
stars, her slaves, obey the nod of her head ; thee land
and sea, subdued beneath thy feet, obey. I did not,
as other suitors use, promise at my courtship fields
where graze unnumbered flocks nor hills covered
with countless vines, nor rich olive-trees waving in
the breeze their grey foliage, nor harvests reaped
by a thousand scythes, nor a lofty palace with golden
pillars. Enough was the mandate of a goddess ;
thy letter, Serena, stands me in stead of flocks,
of harvests, of palace. The shadow of thy name
has won over her parents and an imperial prayer
concealed my poverty. When Serena writes, what
with such words could not the empire's spirit or
duteous love accomplish ? 1
Would heaven had allowed me to solemnize the
longed-for day in the light of thy presence, in thy
<pb id="v.2.p.261"/>


lord's camp, before thy son-in-law's throne. The
royal purple would have been a good omen for our
union, the august assembly of the court would have
graced the ceremony and the hand which, by writing
that letter, promised me my bride would have
kindled the torch to light her to the altar. Now
that the envious sea deprives me of my fondest
hopes and stretches between thee and the coasts
of Libya, yet, though absent, be gracious unto me,
O queen, and of thy goodness grant me a safe return
as by a nod of thy head thou, a goddess, canst do.
Make straight the paths of earth ; bid but gentle
breezes blow and a calm sea prosper my voyage,
that the Muses and Aganippe's stream, the fount
of song, may hymn thy praises in gratitude for the
saving of their servant, the poet. 1

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="32" id="poem.95"><head></head><p>
of the Saviour

Christ, lord of the world, founder of a new age
of gold, voice and wisdom of the Most High, proceeding
from the Father's lofty mind and given by
that Father a share in the governance of this great
universe, thou hast overcome the sins of this our
mortal life, for thou hast suffered thy Godhead to
be clothed in human form and hath allowed mankind
to address thee face to face and confess thee man.
The swelling womb of the Virgin Mary conceived
thee after that she had been visited by the angel,
and the unwed mother, destined to give birth to
her own creator, was astonished at the unborn
<pb id="v.2.p.263"/>
child that grew within her body. A mortal womb
hid the artificer of the heavens : the creator of the
world became a part of human nature. In one
body was conceived the God who embraces the whole
wide world; and he whom nor earth nor sea nor sky
can contain was enclosed by the limbs of a little
child. Thou wert punished and didst suffer too,
for our sins, to save us from destruction, and didst
by thy death overcome Death. Then didst Thou
ascend into Heaven, returning to the Father who
rejoiced at the salvation of the world.
Bless Thou our Emperor that at holy seasons he
may for many years to come observe the fast-days
of the calendar.


</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="33" id="poem.56"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

This piece of ice still shows traces of its original
nature : part of it has become stone, part resisted
the cold. It is a freak of winter's, more precious by
reason of its incomplete crystallization, for that the
jewel contains within itself living water.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="34" id="poem.57"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

Ye waters, who confine waters in a prison akin
to them, ye that are liquid still and ye that were so,
what wit has united you ? By what trick of freezing
is the marvellous stone at once hard and wet ?
What contained heat has protected those enclosed
waters ? what warm wind melted that heart of
ice ? How comes it that the jewel in whose heart
the water ebbs and flows was either made solid
or liquid by frost ?
<pb id="v.2.p.265"/>



</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="35" id="poem.58"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

Alpine ice was becoming so hard that the sun
could not melt it, and this excess of cold was like
to make it precious as diamond. But it could not
imitate that stone in its entirety for at its heart
lay a drop of water which betrayed its nature. As
crystal its value is enhanced, for this liquid rock is
accounted a miracle and the water enclosed within
it increases its rarity.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="36" id="poem.59"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

See this vein which runs in a bright streak
through the translucent ice. This hidden water
fears not any blast of Boreas nor winter's chill but
runs this way and that. It is not frozen by
December's cold, nor dried up by July's sun, nor
wasted away by all-consuming time.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="37" id="poem.60"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

Safely hidden away in this round covering is a
stream, an errant spring, enclosed within frozen
waters. Mark you not how the crystal is all awash
in its cavernous heart where living waters surge this
way and that, and how, when the sun penetrates its
frozen depths, the hues of the rainbow are reflected
in it ? Wonderful stone, wonderful water : stranger
than all rivers and all stones because it is a stone
and yet fluid.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="38" id="poem.61"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

Children love to handle this shining crystal
and turn its chilly mass over and over in their little
hands ; they see imprisoned in the transparent rock
the water which alone winter forebore to freeze.
Placing the dry sphere against their thirsty lips
they press useless kisses on that which guards the
waters they desire.
<pb id="v.2.p.267"/>


</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="39" id="poem.62"><head>On a Crystal enclosing a Drop of Wafer.</head><p>

Do not despise this sphere of rock-crystal.
Kings' palaces contain no rarer jewel, nor are the
Red Sea's pearls of greater value. It may be shapeless
ice, unpolished rock, a rough, uncarven mass,
yet is it accounted among the most precious of riches.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="40" id="poem.41"><head>Letter to Olyhrius.</head><p>

What am I to think, that you send me no greeting,
that no <q>Good wishes</q> traced by your fingers come
back to me in turn ? Is writing so difficult ? Nay,
who so eloquent as thou whether thou dost compose
verses or, a second Cicero, thunder forth thy
speeches ? Greater even than thy riches is thy
genius, greater thine eloquence even than thy
wealth. Are the posts infrequent ? Nay, couriers'
feet never allow the dust to lie on the Flaminian
Way. If, then, thou hast the power to write
and messengers in plenty to carry thy letters what
reason hast thou for thy silence unless indeed
thou wish to slight me ? I take it thou hast
abandoned thy poet and wilt have none of him
(though I can scarce believe it) ; or distance has
made thy heart less fond. Dost thou forget me ?
Now shall Hydaspes lay the day to rest, and thou,
O sun, rise from out the seas of Spain ; now shall
Egypt change her nature and glisten with Getic
frost and the Bear bathe him in forbidden waters.
No, if Olybrius now disdains my love then 'tis sure
Orestes' loyalty availed nought. Nay come, banish
<pb id="v.2.p.269"/>
delay and to console thy friend speak to him from
far away with richer eloquence ; hither let many
a letter hasten with winged speech, to find its way
to my shelves and to my heart. Augustus disdained
not to write to poor Vergil and my muse shall never
bring thee shame. Farewell.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="41" id="poem.42"><head>Letter to Probinus.1</head><p>

How long, pray, shall there be silence between
us ? When shall a welcome letter win a dear
return ? Is it right to call me timid or rather thee
proud ? Surely each shares the other's fault. The
days slip away and while each is ashamed to be the
first to write our hesitation leads to an unbroken
silence. Yet what am I to do ? Respect forbids me
to write first ; love encourages me to do so. Let
love have his way. Fortune favours the brave, as
the old poet sang. Under her guidance I could not
hesitate to speak, though thou still keep silence. If
I shall seem overbold or guilty of some grave fault,
thou mayst blame but I shall not bear the burden
of ingratitude. 'Twas when thou wert consul that
I first drank of the stream of Latin song and that
my Muse, deserting Hellas, assumed the Roman
toga. 2 From thy consulship my youth drew its
omens and to thee I shall owe my future destiny.
Be moved by my importunity and after so long a
delay answer my letter. Farewell, Probinus ; be
thy father's fortune thine.
<pb id="v.2.p.271"/>

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="42" id="poem.53"><head>The Wild Boar and the Lion.</head><p>

A dark boar and a tawny lion met once in battle,
each exulting in his strength : the one shook his
cruel bristles, the other his dreadful mane. One
was Mars' favourite, the other Cybele's : both are
kings of the mountains, both engaged the labours
of Hercules.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="43" id="poem.75"><head>Against Curetius. 1</head><p>

Uranius, Curetius' father, could set deceptive stars
in a sphere of glass, gloomily shake his head over
the errant course of Saturn, or ensure for a trifle
the favourable influence of Jupiter. The father's
chicanery meets with its punishment, so long deferred,
in the son whose mouth needs must pay the just
penalty. For filthy are his delights and he wastes
all his substance in wantoning and debauchery.
And so the tongue of the son has squandered all
the riches which that of his lying father gathered
together.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="44" id="poem.76"><head>The Same.</head><p>

Wouldst thou, Curetius, have sure knowledge of
thy horoscope, I can give it thee better than even
thy father. Thy madness thou owest to the evil
influence of Mars ; thine ignorance of poetry to en-
<pb id="v.2.p.273"/>
feebling Mercury ; thy shameful disease and premature
decay to lady Moon and lady Venus ; Saturn
has robbed thee of thy property. But this one fact
is beyond me : — what causes thy filthy ways ?

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="45" id="poem.55"><head>The Shell</head><p>

Nymph, come from Helicon and pour herein thy
limpid waters ; fill all the vast extent of this wondrous
shell. Surely the water that has bathed the
face of the poetess Serena will have more virtue
than all the streams of Castalia.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="46" id="poem.72"><head>On a Cloak and a Bridle.</head><p>

His loving mother did not always fashion for her
dear son Achilles those round shields that did affright
the world ; she did not constantly approach the fiery
caverns of the god of Lemnos, begging a plumed
helmet for her son. She gave him, besides these,
garments of peace and unwarlike adornments wherewith,
after the toils of war, he might shine conspicuous
among the chiefs of the Achaeans. With her own
hand she wove him cloaks of purple and gold and with
patient care studded with ocean gems bridles to
adorn his fleet steeds, Xanthus and Balius.
On thee, most puissant emperor, thy wife's parents
bestow diverse presents. Stilicho gives thee warlike
gifts — slaughter of barbarians and victories on the
Rhine ; Serena, content to do such work as befits
a queen, plies her busy loom to weave thee raiment.
<pb id="v.2.p.275"/>

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="47" id="poem.73"><head>On a Gift to a Horse.</head><p>

Happy steed, whose good fortune it is to obey the
directing hand of a god and to be guided by a sacred
bit. Whether on the plains of Spain the wind tossed
thy mane in sport, or thou didst bathe in the melted
snows of Mount Argaeus, in some fertile valley of
Cappadocia, or thou didst scour the rich pasture-lands
of Thessaly in wind-swift course, receive this royal
harness and, tossing thy proud mane, fleck with foam
the bridle studded with emeralds. Arch thy haughty
neck beneath its collar of pearls ; let cloth of purple
and gold clothe thy shoulders and a belt of many
colours worked by Serena's chaste hands pass beneath
thy belly. 'Tis an ornament worthy the kings of
Persia. Such is her motherly love that to enhance
her son-in-law's glory she disdains not to embroider
the very harness of his horses.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="48" id="poem.70"><head>On a Strap embroidered by Serena for Honorius' Horse.</head><p>
Receive at a sister's hand a small gift, revered
prince, a gift embroidered by her own hand ; the
bridle of thy champing steed is of gold, his head-
harness studded with jewels; use now this strap to
pass beneath his belly. Whether his home was the
grassy plain of Armenia, or by the Halys, swollen
with the melted snows of Mount Argaeus wherein he
was wont to bathe, he well deserves an emeraldencrusted
bit to champ in his blood-flecked mouth
and cloth of Tyrian purple to adorn his back. How
<pb id="v.2.p.277"/>
conscious he is of his own beauty as he steps high
and shakes his flowing mane over his proud neck !
The slight nature of the present is dignified by the
affection of Serena who for her brothers decks even
their swift steeds.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="49" id="poem.46"><head>The Electric Ray</head><p>

Who has not heard of the invincible skill of the
dread torpedo and of the powers that win it its name ?
Its body is soft and its motion slow. Scarcely does
it mark the sand o'er which it crawls so sluggishly.
But nature has armed its flanks with a numbing
poison and mingled with its marrow chill to freeze all
living creatures, hiding as it were its own winter in
its heart. The fish seconds nature's efforts with its
own guilefulness ; knowing its own capabilities, it
employs cunning, and trusting to its power of touch
hes stretched full length among the seaweed and so
attacks its prey. It stays motionless ; all that have
touched it he benumbed. Then, when success has
crowned its efforts, it springs up and greedily devours
without fear the living limbs of its victim.
Should it carelessly swallow a piece of bait that
hides a hook of bronze and feel the pull of the jagged
barbs, it does not swim away nor seek to free itself
by vainly biting at the line ; but artfully approaches
the dark line and, though a prisoner, forgets not its
skill, emitting from its poisonous veins an effluence
which spreads far and wide through the water. The
poison's bane leaves the sea and creeps up the line ;
it will soon prove too much for the distant fisherman.
<pb id="v.2.p.279"/>


The dread paralysing force rises above the water's
level and climbing up the drooping line, passes down
the jointed rod, and congeals, e'er he is even aware
of it, the blood of the fisherman's victorious hand.
He casts away his dangerous burden and lets go his
rebel prey, returning home disarmed without his rod.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="50" id="poem.77"><head>Against James Commander of the Cavalry. 1</head><p>

By the ashes of S. Paul and the shrine of revered
S. Peter, do not pull my verses to pieces. General
James. So may S . Thomas prove a buckler to protect
thy breast and S. Bartholomew bear thee company to
the wars ; so may the blessed saints prevent the
barbarians from crossing the Alps and Suzanna 2 endow
thee with her strength ; so, should any savage foe
seek to swim across the Danube, let him be drowned
therein like the swift chariots of Pharaoh ; so may an
avenging javelin strike the Getic hordes and the
favour of Thecla 3 guide the armies of Rome ; so may
thy guests dying in their efforts to out-drink thee
assure thy board its triumph of hospitality and the
broached casks o'ercome thy thirst ; so may thy hand
ne'er be red with an enemy's blood — do not, I say,
pull my verses to pieces.

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="51" id="poem.68"><head>Archimedes' Sphere.</head><p>

When Jove looked down and saw the heavens
figured in a sphere of glass he laughed and said to
<pb id="v.2.p.281"/>
the other gods : <q> Has the power of mortal effort
gone so far ? Is my handiwork now mimicked
in a fragile globe ? An old man of Syracuse has
imitated on earth the laws of the heavens, the order
of nature, and the ordinances of the gods. Some
hidden influence within the sphere directs the
various courses of the stars and actuates the lifelike
mass with definite motions. A false zodiac runs
through a year of its own, and a toy moon waxes
and wanes month by month. Now bold invention
rejoices to make its own heaven revolve and sets
the stars in motion by human wit. Why should I
take umbrage at harmless Salmoneus and his mock
thunder ? Here the feeble hand of man has proved
Nature's rival.</q>

</p></div1>

<div1 type="poem" n="52" id="poem.37"><head>The Battle of the Giants.</head><p>

Once upon a time mother Earth, jealous of the
heavenly kingdoms and in pity for the ceaseless woes
of the Titans, filled all Tartarus with a monster brood,
thus giving birth to that which proved a very bane.
Her womb swollen with this monstrous birth she
opened Phlegra's side and brought forth foes against
heaven. With a noise as of thunder they burst forth
in profusion and, scarce born, prepare their hands for
war, as with twofold trail 1 they writhe their hissing
course. Suddenly the stars grow pale, Phoebus turns
his rosy steeds and, impelled by fear, retraces his
steps. The Bear takes refuge in the Ocean, and the
unsetting Triones learned to endure setting. Then
their angry mother stirred up her sons to war with
words such as these : <q> Children, ye shall conquer
<pb id="v.2.p.283"/>
heaven : all that ye see is the prize of victory ;
win, and the universe is yours. At last shall
Saturn's son feel the weight of my wrath ; shall
recognize Earth's power. What ! can any force
conquer me ? Has Cybele born sons superior to
mine ? Why has Earth no honour ? Why is she
ever condemned to bitter loss ? Has any form of
injury passed me by ? There hangs luckless Prometheus
in yon Scythian vale, feeding the vulture on
his living breast ; yonder, Atlas supports the weight
of the starry heavens upon his head, and his grey hair
is frozen stiff with cruel cold. What need to tell of
Tityus whose liver is ever renewed beneath the savage
vulture's beak, to contend with his heavy punishment ?
Up, army of avengers, the hour is come at
last, free the Titans from their chains ; defend your
mother. Here are seas and mountains, limbs of my
body, but care not for that. Use them as weapons.
Never would I hesitate to be a weapon for the destruction
of Jove. Go forth and conquer ; throw
heaven into confusion, tear down the towers of the
sky. Let Typhoeus seize the thunderbolt and the
sceptre ; Enceladus, rule the sea, and another in
place of the sun guide the reins of dawn's coursers.
Porphyrion, wreathe thou thy head with Delphi's
laurel and take Cirrha for thy sanctuary.</q>
This exhortation filled their minds with vain hopes.
They think themselves already victors o'er the gods,
imagine they have thrown Neptune into chains and
dragged him a prisoner from Ocean's bed. One
thinks to lay Mars low, one to tear Phoebus' locks
from his head ; one assigns Venus to himself, another
anticipates in thought his marriage with Diana, and
another is all aflame to do violence to chaste Minerva.
<pb id="v.2.p.285"/>
Meanwhile Iris, messenger of the gods, summons
the immortal council. There come the deities of
river and lake ; the very ghosts were there in heaven's
defence. Hell's shady portals could not hold Proserpine
afar ; the king of the silent himself advances in
his Lethaean chariot. His horses fear the light which
hitherto their astonished eyes have never looked
upon and, swerving this way and that, they breathe
forth thick vapour from their soot-black nostrils.
As, when an enemy's siege-engine affrights a town,
the citizens run together from all sides to defend
their citadel, so gods of all shapes and forms came
together to protect their father's home. Them Jove
thus addressed : <q> Deathless army, whose dwelling-place
is, and must ever be, the sky, ye whom no adverse
fortune can ever harm, mark ye how Earth with
her new children conspires against our kingdom
and undismayed has given birth to another brood ?
Wherefore, for all the sons she bore, let us give
back to their mother as many dead ; let her mourning
last through the ages as she weeps by as many
graves as she now has children.</q>
The clouds echo the blast of heaven's trumpets ;
on this side Heaven, on that Earth, sounds the
attack. Once more Nature is thrown into confusion
and fears for her lord. The puissant company of
the giants confounds all differences between things ;
islands abandon the deep ; mountains He hidden in
the sea. Many a river is left dry or has altered
its ancient course. One giant brandishes Thessalian
Oeta in his mighty hand, another gathers all his
strength and hurls Pangaeus at the foe, Athos with
his snows arms another ; this one roots up Ossa, that
tears out Rhodope and Hebrus' source, dividing the
<pb id="v.2.p.287"/>
waters that before were one ; Enipeus, gathered up
with its beetling crags, scatters its waters over yon
giant's shoulders : robbed of her mountains Earth
sank into level plains, parted among her own sons.
On all sides a horrid din resounds and only the air
divides the rival armies. First impetuous Mars urges
against the horrid band his Thracian steeds that oft
have driven in rout Getae or Geloni. Brighter than
flame shines his golden shield, high towers the
crest of his gleaming helmet. Dashing into the fray
he first encounters Pelorus and transfixes him with
his sword, where about the groin the two-bodied
serpent unites with his own giant form, and thus with
one blow puts an end to three lives. Exulting in his
victory he drives his chariot over the dying giant's
limbs till the wheels ran red with blood.
Mimas ran forward to avenge his brother. He
had torn Lemnos and with it Vulcan's fiery house
from out the foaming main, and was on the point of
hurling it when Mars' javelin prevented him, scattering
the brain from his shattered skull. What was
giant in him died, but the serpent legs still lived,
and, hissing vengeance, sought to attack the victor
after Mimas' death.
Minerva rushed forward presenting her breast
whereon glittered the Gorgon's head. The sight
of this, she knew, was enough : she needed not to
use a spear. One look sufficed. Pallas drew no
nearer, rage as he might, for he was the first to be
changed into a rock. When, at a distance from his
foe, without a wound, he found himself rooted to
the ground, and felt the murderous visage turn
him, little by little, to stone (and all but stone he was)
he called out, <q> What is happening to me ? What
<pb id="v.2.p.289"/>
is this ice that creeps o'er all my limbs ? What is
this numbness that holds me prisoner in these
marble fetters?</q> Scarce had he uttered these few
words when he was what he feared, and savage
Damastor, seeking a weapon wherewith to repel
the foe, hurled at them in place of a rock his brother's
stony corpse.
Then Echion, marvelling, all ignorant, at his
brother's death, even as he seeks to assail the author
of the deed, turned his gaze upon thee, goddess,
whom alone no man may see twice. Beaten audacity
well deserved its punishment and in death he learned
to know the goddess. But Palleneus, mad with
anger, turning his eyes aside, rushed at Minerva,
striking at her with undirected sword. Nigh at
hand the goddess smote him with her sword, and
at the same time the snakes froze at the Gorgon's
glance, so that of one body a part was killed by a
weapon and a part by a mere look. 
Impious Porphyrion, carried by his serpents into the
middle of the sea, tries to uproot trembling Delos,
wishing to hurl it at the sky. The Aegean was
affrighted ; Thetis and her agèd sire fled from their
watery caverns ; the palace of Neptune, regarded
with awe by all the denizens of the deep, lay deserted.
The summit of Cynthus rang with the cries of the
gentle nymphs who had taught Phoebus' unpractised
hand to shoot at the wandering beasts
with his bow, they who first had prepared the bed
for weeping Latona when, in labour with the lights
of heaven, she blessed the world with twin offspring.
Delos in terror called her lord Phoebus to help her
and begged him for aid. <q> In remembrance of the
<pb id="v.2.p.291"/>
time when Latona entrusted thine infant life to
my care, help me who thus call upon thee. Behold,
once more they seek to uproot me. . . .</q> 1
a final portion which has been lost. But it is more likely
that they come from some other poet's work and that the
abrupt end of Claudian's poem is due not to loss but to the
poet's sudden death.
</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>
