<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 33</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="book">
                <head>The Second Macedonian War</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The above-described events took place in
                        the winter. At the commencement of spring Quinctius, anxious to make the
                        Boeotians, who were uncertain which side to take, into a Roman dependency,
                        summoned Attalus to Elatia, and marching through Phocis fixed his camp at a
                        point five miles from Thebes, the Boeotian capital. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The following day, escorted by a single maniple and
                        accompanied by Attalus and the various deputations who had flocked to him
                        from all quarters, he proceeded to the city. The hastati of the legion,
                        numbering 2000 men, were ordered to follow him at a distance of one mile.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About half-way he was met by
                        Antiphilus, the captain-general of the Boeotians; the population of the city
                        were on the walls, anxiously watching the approach of the Roman general and
                        the king. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They saw few arms and few
                        soldiers with them, the hastati, who were following a mile behind, were
                        hidden by the windings of the road and the undulating nature of the terrain.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As he came nearer to the city he
                        slackened his pace, as though he were saluting the crowds who had come out
                        to meet him, but really to allow the hastati to catch him up. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> The townsfolk pushing along in a mass in front of
                        the lictor did not see the armed column which had hurried up until they
                        reached the general's quarters. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then they
                        were utterly dismayed, as they believed that the city had been betrayed and
                        captured through the treachery of Antiphilus. It was quite clear that the
                        Council of Boeotia which was summoned for the next day would have no chance
                        of unfettered deliberation. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They concealed
                        their vexation, since to have exhibited it would have been useless and
                        dangerous. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Attalus was the first to speak in the
                        council. He began by recounting the services which he had rendered to Greece
                        as a whole and in particular to the Boeotians. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> But he was too old and infirm to stand the strain of
                        public speaking, and suddenly became silent and fell down. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst they were removing the king, who had lost the
                        use of one side, the proceedings were suspended. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Aristaenus, the chief magistrate of the Achaeans, was
                        the next to speak, and he spoke with all the more weight because he gave the
                        Boeotians the same advice which he had given to the Achaeans. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Quinctius himself added a few remarks, in which
                        he dwelt more upon the good faith of the Romans and their sense of honour
                        than upon their arms and resources. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Dicaearchus of Plataea next brought forward a motion in favour of alliance
                        with Rome. When its terms had been recited no one ventured to oppose it,
                        consequently it was passed by the unanimous vote of the cities of Boeotia.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After the council broke up Quinctius
                        only stayed in <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> Thebes as long as
                        Attalus' sudden attack made it necessary, and as soon as he saw that there
                        was no immediate danger to life but only powerlessness in the limbs, he left
                        him to undergo the necessary treatment and returned to Elatia. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The Boeotians, like the Achaeans before them,
                        were thus admitted as allies, and as he was leaving everything behind in
                        peaceful security, he was able to devote all his thoughts to Philip and the
                        means of bringing the war to a close. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After his envoys had returned from their
                        fruitless mission to Rome, Philip decided to raise troops in every town in
                        his kingdom. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Owing to the perpetual wars
                        which had for so many generations drained the manhood of Macedonia there was
                        a serious lack of men of military age, and under Philip's own rule vast
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> numbers had perished in the naval
                        battles against the Rhodians and Attalus and in the campaigns against the
                        Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Under these circumstances he even
                        enrolled youths of sixteen and recalled to the colours men who had served
                        their time, provided they had any stamina left. After his army was brought
                        up to its proper strength he concentrated the whole of his forces at Dium
                        and <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> formed a standing camp there in
                        which he drilled and exercised his soldiers day by day whilst waiting for
                        the enemy. During this time Quinctius left Elatia and marched by way of
                        Thronium and Scarphea to Thermopylae. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        Aetolian Council had been summoned to meet at Heraclea to decide the
                        strength of the contingent which was to follow <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> the Roman general to war, and he waited at Thermopylae
                        for a couple of days to learn the result. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        When he had been informed of their decision he started, and marching past
                        Xyniae fixed his camp where the frontiers of Acarnania and Thessaly meet.
                        Here he waited for the Aetolian contingent, who came up without any loss of
                        time under the command of Phaeneas. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They
                        numbered 600 infantry and 400 cavalry. To remove any doubt as to why he had
                        waited he resumed his march as soon as they arrived. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> On his advance through Phthiotis he was joined by 500
                        Cretans from Gortynium and 300 Apollonians, armed like the Cretans, and not
                        long after by Amynander with 1200 Athamanian infantry. As soon as Philip
                        ascertained that the Romans had started from Elatia he realised that a
                        struggle lay before him which would decide the fate <milestone n="11??"
                            unit="section"/> of his kingdom, and he thought it well to address words
                        of encouragement to his soldiers. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> After
                        repeating the familiar phrases about the virtues of their ancestors and the
                        military reputation of the Macedonians, he dwelt more especially on the
                        considerations which tended to depress their courage and then on those from
                        which they ought to derive consolation and hope. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Against the three defeats sustained by the
                        Macedonian phalanx at the Aous he set the repulse of the Romans at Atrax.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the former occasion, when they
                        failed to maintain their hold on the pass leading into Epirus, he pointed
                        out that the fault lay, first, with those who had been careless in
                            <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> their outpost duties and then in the
                        behaviour of the light infantry and the mercenaries in the actual battle.
                        But the Macedonian phalanx stood its ground, and on favourable ground and in
                        a fair field would always remain unbeaten. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The phalanx consisted of 16,000 men, the flower of the military strength of
                        his dominions. There were in addition 2000 caetrati, whom they call "
                        peltasts," and contingents of the same strength were furnished by the
                        Thracians and by the Trallians, an Illyrian tribe. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Besides these there were about 1500 hired troops drawn
                        from various nationalities. and a body of cavalry numbering 2000 troopers.
                        With this force the king awaited his enemies. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Roman army was almost equal in numbers, in cavalry
                        alone were they superior, owing to the accession of the Aetolians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius had been led to hope that Thebes
                        in Phthiotis would be betrayed to him by Timon, the first man in the city,
                        and accordingly he marched thither. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                        rode up to the walls with a small body of cavalry and light infantry, but
                        his expectations were so far frustrated by a sortie from the city that he
                        would have been in imminent danger had not infantry and cavalry from the
                        camp come to his assistance in time. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When
                        he found that his hopes were illusory and that there was no prospect of
                        their being realised he desisted from any further attempt for the time.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Definite information having reached
                        him, however, that the king was now in Thessaly, though his exact
                        whereabouts was unknown, he sent his men into the fields round to cut down
                        and prepare stakes for a stockade. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both
                        the Macedonians and the Greeks made use of stockades, but they did not adapt
                        their materials either for convenience in carrying or for defensive
                        strength. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The trees they cut down were too
                        large and too branching for the soldiery to carry together with their arms,
                        and when they had put them in position and fenced their camp with them the
                        demolition of their rampart was an easy matter. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The large trunks stood up apart from one another and
                        the numerous stout branches afforded a good hold, so that two, or at the
                        most three, men by pulling together would bring a tree down, making at once
                        a gap as wide as a gate, and there was nothing at hand with which to block
                        the opening. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the other hand, the stakes
                        which the Romans cut were light and generally forked with <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> three, or at the most four, branches, so that, with his
                        arms slung at his back, the Roman soldier could carry several of them
                        together comfortably. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then again they fix
                        them so close together in the ground and interlace the branches in such a
                        way that it is impossible to discover to which particular tree any of the
                        outside branches belong, and these are made so sharp and so closely
                        intertwined that there is no room <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> left
                        for inserting the hand, nothing can be got hold of to be dragged away, nor
                        if there were would the enemy succeed in doing so because the branches are
                        hooked together like the links of a chain. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                        /> If one happens to be pulled out, it leaves only a small opening and it is
                        very easy to put another in its place. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius resumed his march on the
                        following day, but as the soldiers were carrying the timber for a stockade,
                        so that <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> they might be ready to form an
                        entrenched camp anywhere, the day's march was not a long one. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The position he selected was about six miles from
                        Pherae, and after fixing his camp he sent out reconnoitring parties to find
                        out in what part of Thessaly the enemy was, and what were his intentions.
                        Philip was in the neighbourhood of Larisa and had already received
                        information that the Romans had left Thebes for Pherae. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He, too, was anxious to bring matters to a decision and
                        determined to make straight for the enemy, and finally fixed his camp some
                        four miles from Pherae. The next day light infantry from both sides moved
                        out to seize some hills which commanded the city, but <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> when they caught sight of one another they halted and
                        sent to their respective camps for instructions as to what they were to do
                        now that they had come unexpectedly upon the enemy. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> As they awaited their return without moving the day
                        passed without any fighting and these detachments were recalled to camp. The
                        next day there was a cavalry action near those hills, in which Philip's
                        troops were routed and driven back to their camp; a success in which the
                        Aetolians had the greatest share. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Both
                        sides were greatly hampered in their movements by the nature of the ground,
                        which was thickly planted with trees, and by the gardens which are usually
                        found in suburban districts, the roads being enclosed between walls and in
                        some cases blocked. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Both commanders alike
                        determined to get out of the neighbourhood, and as though by mutual
                        agreement they both made for Scotusa: Philip, in the hope of obtaining a
                        supply of corn there; Quinctius, with the intention of forestalling his
                        adversary and destroying his corn. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                        armies marched the whole day without once getting sight of each other owing
                        to a continuous range of hills which lay between them. The Romans encamped
                        at Eretria in Phthiotis, Philip fixed his camp by the river Onchestus.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The next day Philip encamped at
                            <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> Melambium in the territory of
                        Scotusa and Quinctius at Thetideum in the neighbourhood of Pharsalia, but
                        not even then did either side know for certain where their enemy was.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The third day heavy clouds came up,
                        followed by a darkness as black as night which kept the Romans in their camp
                        for fear of a surprise attack. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Eager to press on, Philip was not in the
                        least deterred by the clouds which had descended to the earth after the
                        rain, and he ordered the standard-bearers to march out. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> But so thick a fog had blotted out the daylight that
                        the standard-bearers could not see their way, nor could the men see their
                        standards. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Misled by the confused shouts,
                        the column was thrown into as great disorder as if it had lost its way in a
                        night march. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When they had surmounted the
                        range of hills called Cynoscephalae, where they left a strong force of
                        infantry and cavalry in occupation, they formed their camp. The Roman
                        general was still in camp at Thetideum; he sent out, however, ten squadrons
                        of cavalry and a thousand velites to reconnoitre and warned them to be on
                        their guard against an ambuscade, which owing to the darkened daylight might
                        not be detected even in open country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When
                        they reached the heights where the enemy were posted both sides stood
                        stock-still as though paralysed by mutual fear. As soon as their alarm at
                        the unexpected sight subsided they sent messages to their generals in camp
                        and did not hesitate any longer to engage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        The action was begun by the advanced patrols, and then as the supports came
                        up the fighting became general. The Romans were by no means a match for
                        their opponents, and they sent message after message to their general to
                        inform him that they were being overpowered. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> A reinforcement of 500 cavalry and 2000 infantry, mostly Aetolians, under
                        two military tribunes, was hastily despatched and restored the battle, which
                        was going against the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This turn of
                        fortune threw the Macedonians into difficulties and they sent to their king
                        for help. But as owing to the darkness a battle was the last thing he had
                        looked for on that day, and as a large number of men of all ranks had been
                        sent out to forage, he was for a considerable time at a loss what to do.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The messages became more and more
                        importunate, and as the fog had now cleared away and revealed the situation
                        of the Macedonians who had been driven to the topmost height and were
                        finding more safety in their position than in their arms, Philip felt that
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> he ought to risk a general and
                        decisive engagement rather than let a part of his force be lost through want
                        of support. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly he sent
                        Athenagoras, the commander of the mercenaries, with the whole of the foreign
                        contingent, except the Thracians, and also the Macedonian and Thessalian
                        cavalry. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their appearance resulted in the
                        Romans being dislodged from the hill and compelled to retreat to lower
                        ground. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That they were not driven in
                        disorderly flight was mainly owing to the Aetolian cavalry, which at that
                        time was the best in Greece, though in infantry they were inferior to their
                        neighbours. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This affair was reported to the king as a
                        more important success than the facts warranted. Messenger after messenger
                        ran back from the field shouting that the Romans were in flight, and though
                            <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the king, reluctant and hesitating,
                        declared that the action had been begun rashly and that neither the time nor
                        the place suited him, he was at last driven into bringing the whole of his
                        forces into the field. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman commander
                        did the same, more because no other course was open to him than because he
                        wished to seize the opportunity of a battle. He posted the elephants in
                        front of his right wing, which he kept in reserve; the left, with the whole
                        of the light infantry, he led in person against the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> As they advanced he reminded them that they were going
                        to fight with the same Macedonians as those whom in spite of the difficult
                        ground they had driven out of the pass leading into Epirus, protected though
                        they were by the mountains and the river, and had thoroughly defeated;
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the same as those whom they had
                        vanquished under P. Sulpicius when they tried to stop their march on
                        Eordaea. The kingdom of Macedonia, he declared, stood by its prestige, not
                        by its strength, and even its prestige had at last disappeared. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> By this time he had come up to his detachments
                        who were standing at the bottom of the valley. They at once renewed the
                        fight and by a fierce attack compelled the enemy to give ground. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Philip with his caetrati and the infantry of his
                        right wing, the finest body in his army, which they call "the phalanx," went
                        at the enemy almost at a run; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nicanor, one
                        of his courtiers, was ordered to follow at once with the rest of his force.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As soon as he reached the top of the
                        hill and saw a few of the enemy's bodies and weapons lying about, he
                        concluded that there had been a battle there and that the Romans had been
                        repulsed, and when he further saw that fighting was going on near the
                        enemy's camp he was in a state of great exultation. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Soon, however, when his men came back in flight and it
                        was his turn to be alarmed, he was for a few moments anxiously debating
                        whether he ought not to recall his troops to camp. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Then, as the enemy were approaching, and especially as
                        his own men were being cut down as they fled and could not be saved unless
                        they were defended by fresh troops, and also as retreat was no <milestone
                            n="12??" unit="section"/> longer safe, he found himself compelled to
                        take the supreme risk, though half his force had not yet come up. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> The cavalry and light infantry who had been in
                        action he stationed on his right; the caetrati and the men of the phalanx
                        were ordered to lay aside their spears, the length of which only embarrassed
                        them, and make use of their swords. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> To
                        prevent his line from being quickly broken he halved the front and gave
                        twice the depth to the files, so that the depth might be greater than the
                        width. He also ordered the ranks to close up so that man might be in touch
                        with man and arms with arms. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the Roman troops who had been
                        engaged had retired through the intervals between the leading maniples,
                        Quinctius ordered the trumpets to sound the advance. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Seldom, it is said, has such a battle-shout been raised
                        at the beginning of an action, for both armies happened to shout at the same
                        moment, not only those actually engaged, but even the Roman reserves and the
                        Macedonians who were just then appearing on the field. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> On the right the king, aided mainly by the higher
                        ground on which he was fighting, had the advantage. On the left, where that
                        part of the phalanx which formed the rear was only just coming up, all was
                        confusion and disorder. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The centre stood
                        and looked on as though it were watching a fight in which it had no concern.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The newly-arrived part of the phalanx,
                        in column instead of in line of battle, in marching rather than in fighting
                        formation, had hardly reached the crest of the hill. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Though Quinctius saw that his men were giving ground on
                        the left he sent the elephants against these unformed troops and followed up
                        with a charge, rightly judging that the rout of a part would involve the
                        rest. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The result was not long in doubt;
                        the Macedonians in front, terrified by the animals, instantly turned tail,
                        and when these were repulsed the rest followed them. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> One of the military tribunes, seeing the position,
                        suddenly made up his mind what to do, and leaving that part of his line
                        which was undoubtedly winning, wheeled round with twenty maniples and
                        attacked the enemy's right from behind. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> No
                        army when attacked in the rear can fail to be shaken, but the inevitable
                        confusion was increased by the inability of the Macedonian phalanx, a heavy
                        and immobile formation, to face round on a new front. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> To make matters worse, they were at a serious
                        disadvantage from the ground, for in following their repulsed enemy down the
                        hill they had left the height for the enemy to make use of in his enveloping
                        movement. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Assailed on both sides they
                        lost heavily, and in a short time they flung away their arms and took to
                        flight. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With a small body of horse and foot Philip
                        occupied the highest point on the hills in order to see what fortune his
                        left wing had met with. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he became
                        aware of their disorderly flight and saw the Roman standards and arms
                        flashing on all the hills he too left the field. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Quinctius, who was pressing on the retiring foe, saw
                        the Macedonians suddenly holding their spears upright, and <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> as he was doubtful as to what they intended by
                        this unfamiliar maneuver he held up the pursuit for a few minutes. On
                        learning that it was the Macedonian signal of surrender, he made up his mind
                        to spare them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The soldiers, however,
                        unaware that the enemy were no longer resisting and ignorant of their
                        general's intention, commenced an attack upon them, and when those in front
                        had been cut down the rest scattered in flight. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Philip himself rode off at a hard gallop in the
                        direction of Tempe and drew rein at Gomphi, where he remained for a day to
                        pick up any survivors from the battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        Romans broke into the hostile camp in hopes of plunder, but they found that
                        it had to a large extent been cleared out by the Aetolians. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> 8000 of the enemy perished that day; 5000 were made
                        prisoners. Of the victors about 700 fell. If we are to believe Valerius, who
                        is given to boundless exaggeration, 40,000 of the enemy were killed and-here
                        his invention is not so wild-5700 made prisoners and 249 standards captured.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Claudius too writes that 32,000 of the
                        enemy were killed and 4300 made prisoners. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                        /> We have taken the smaller number, not because it is the smaller, but
                        because we have followed Polybius, who is no untrustworthy authority on
                        Roman history especially when the scene of it is in Greece. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After collecting together the fugitives
                        who had been scattered in the various stages of the battle and had followed
                        him in his flight, Philip despatched men to burn his papers at Larisa, that
                        they might not fall into the enemy's hands, and then retreated into
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Quinctius sold some of the
                        prisoners and a part of the booty and gave the rest to the soldiers, after
                        which he proceeded to Larisa, not knowing for certain in what direction the
                        king had gone or what movements he was contemplating. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst he was there a herald arrived from the king
                        ostensibly to ask for an armistice for the purpose of burying those who had
                        fallen in the battle, but really to ask for permission to open negotiations
                        for peace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Both requests were granted by
                        the Roman general, who also sent a message to the king bidding him not to
                        lose heart. This gave great offence to the Aetolians, who were intensely
                        mortified and said that the commander had been changed by his victory.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Before the battle, so they alleged, he
                        used to consult his allies on all matters great and small, but now they were
                        excluded from all his counsels; he was acting solely on his own judgment.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He was looking out for an opportunity
                        of ingratiating himself personally with Philip so that after the Aetolians
                        had borne the whole burden of the hardships and sufferings of the war the
                        Roman might secure for himself all the credit and advantages of peace.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As a matter of fact Quinctius
                        certainly did show the Aetolians less consideration, but they were quite
                        ignorant of his reason for treating them with neglect. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> They believed that he was looking for bribes from
                        Philip, though he was a man who never yielded to the temptation of money;
                        but it was not without good reason that he was disgusted with the Aetolians
                        for their insatiable appetite for plunder and their arrogance in claiming
                        for themselves the credit of the victory, a piece of vanity which offended
                        all men's ears. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Besides, if Philip were
                        out of the way and the kingdom of Macedonia hopelessly crushed he recognised
                        that the Aetolians must be regarded as the dominant power in Greece.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Dictated by these considerations his
                        conduct was deliberately designed to humiliate and belittle them in the eyes
                        of Greece. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The enemy were granted a fifteen days'
                        armistice and arrangements were made for a conference with Philip. Before
                        the date fixed for it Quinctius called his allies into consultation and laid
                        before them the conditions of peace which he thought ought to be imposed.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Amynander briefly stated his view,
                        which was that the terms should be such that Greece should be sufficiently
                        strong, even in the absence of the Romans, to protect her liberty and
                        prevent the peace from being broken. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        Aetolians spoke in a more vindictive tone. After a brief allusion to the
                        correctness of Quinctius' attitude in calling in those who <milestone
                            n="4??" unit="section"/> had been his allies in war to advise with him
                        on the question of peace, they went on to assure him that he was totally
                        mistaken if he supposed that he would leave either peace with Rome or
                        liberty for Greece on a sure basis unless Philip were either put to death or
                        expelled from his kingdom. Either of these alternatives was easy for him if
                        he chose to make full use of his victory. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Quinctius replied that in uttering these sentiments the Aetolians were
                        losing sight of the settled policy of Rome and convicting themselves of
                        inconsistency. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In all the former councils
                        and conferences when discussing the question of peace they had never
                        advocated the destruction <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> of Macedonia,
                        and the Romans, whose policy from the earliest times had been to show mercy
                        to the conquered, had furnished a conspicuous proof of this in the peace
                        which had been granted to Hannibal and the Carthaginians. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Leaving the Carthaginians, however, out of account, how
                        often had he himself had conferences with Philip? But never had the question
                        of his abdication been raised. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Had his
                        defeat in battle made the war one of extermination? "An enemy in arms one is
                        bound to meet with ruthless hostility; towards the conquered the greatest
                        minds show the greatest clemency. You think that kings of Macedon are a
                        danger to the liberties of Greece. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If
                        that nation and kingdom were swept away, Thracians, Illyrians, Gauls, savage
                        and barbarous tribes, would pour into Macedonia and then into Greece.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Do not, by removing the danger
                        closest to you, open the door to greater and more serious ones." Here he was
                        interrupted by Phaeneas, the president of the Aetolian league, who solemnly
                        declared amid great excitement that if Philip escaped then, he would soon
                        prove a still more dangerous enemy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        "Cease your uproar," said Quinctius, "when we have to deliberate. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> Peace will not be settled upon such terms as to
                        make it possible to recommence war." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The council broke up, and on the morrow
                        Philip went to the spot fixed for the conference, which was in the pass
                        leading into Tempe. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The day following a
                        meeting of the Romans and all their allies was convened, before which he
                        appeared. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He showed great prudence in
                        deliberately abstaining from any allusion to those conditions which were
                        regarded as essential, instead of letting them be forced from him in the
                        discussion. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All the concessions which in
                        the former conference the Romans had insisted upon or the allies had
                        demanded he said he would agree to, everything else he would leave to the
                        decision of the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This would seem to
                        have precluded any further demands even from those most hostile to him, and
                        yet Phaeneas broke the general silence by asking, "What? <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Philip! Do you at last restore to us Larisa, Cremaste,
                        Echinus and Phthiotic Thebes?" <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On Philip
                        replying that he placed no difficulty in the way of their resuming
                        possession of these places, a dispute arose between Quinctius and the
                        Aetolians over Thebes. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Quinctius asserted
                        that it belonged to Rome by the right of war, for before the war broke out
                        he marched there and invited the citizens to enter into friendly relations
                        with him, and whilst they were at full liberty to abandon Philip they
                        preferred his allegiance to that of the Romans. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Phaeneas retorted that it was only just and equitable,
                        considering the part they had taken in the war, that all which the Aetolians
                        possessed before the war should be restored to them. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> It was provided by treaty from the very first that the
                        spoils of war, including all movable goods and all livestock and prisoners,
                        should go to the Romans; the conquered cities and territories to the
                        Aetolians. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> "You yourselves," replied
                        Quinctius, "broke that treaty when you left us and made peace with Philip.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If it were still in force, it would
                        only apply to the cities which have been captured; the cities of Thessaly
                        have passed into our power of their own free will." <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> This declaration was approved by all the allies, but
                        created a bitter feeling amongst the Aetolians at the time, and soon led to
                        a war which proved most disastrous to them. It was agreed that Philip should
                        give up his son Demetrius and some of "the friends of the king" as hostages
                        and also pay an indemnity of 200 talents. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        With regard to the other matters, he was to send an embassy to Rome and a
                        four months' truce was granted him to enable him to do so. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> In case the senate declined to grant terms of peace the
                        agreement was to be cancelled and the hostages and money returned to Philip.
                        The main reason for Quinctius desiring an early peace is alleged to have
                        been the warlike designs of Antiochus and his threatened invasion of Europe.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this very time, and according to some
                        accounts on the very day on which the battle of Cynoscephalae was fought,
                        the Achaeans routed Androsthenes, one of Philip's generals, in a pitched
                        battle at Corinth. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Philip intended to hold
                        that city as a menace to the States of Greece, and after inviting the
                        leading citizens to a conference on the pretext of settling <milestone
                            n="3??" unit="section"/> what force of cavalry the Corinthians could
                        furnish for the war, he had detained them all as hostages. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The force in occupation consisted of 500 Macedonians
                        and 800 auxiliaries of various nationalities. In addition to these he had
                        sent 1000 Macedonians and 1200 Illyrians and also Thracian and Cretan
                        contingents (these tribes fought on both sides), amounting to 800 in all.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There were in addition 1000
                        heavy-armed troops, consisting of Boeotians, Thessalians and Acarnanians. A
                        draft from Corinth itself made up the whole force to 6000 men, and
                        Androsthenes felt himself strong enough to give battle. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Achaean captain-general, Nicostratus, was at Sicyon
                        with 2000 infantry and 200 cavalry, but seeing that he was inferior in both
                        the number and the quality of his troops, he did not venture outside the
                        walls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The king's troops overran and
                        ravaged the territories of Pellene, Phlius and Cleonae. At last, to show
                        their contempt for the timidity of their <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        enemy, they invaded the territory of Sicyon and, sailing along the Achaean
                        seaboard, harried and wasted the land. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Their confidence, as is usually the case, made them careless, and their
                        raids were conducted with an absence of all precautions. Seeing a
                        possibility of a successful surprise attack, Nicostratus sent secret
                        information to all the cities round as to what force each city should
                        contribute and on <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> what day they should
                        all muster at Apelaurus, a place in Stymphalia. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> All being in readiness on the appointed day he made a
                        night march through the district of Phlius to Cleonae, no one knowing what
                        his object was. He had with him 5000 infantry, of which . . . were
                        light-armed troops, and also 300 cavalry. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        With this force he waited for the return of the scouting patrols whom he had
                        sent out to ascertain in what direction the enemy had dispersed themselves.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Androsthenes, in perfect ignorance of all
                        this, marched out from Corinth and encamped by the Nemea, a stream which
                        divides the territory of Corinth from that of Sicyon. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Here, leaving half his army in camp, he formed the
                        other half and the whole of the cavalry into three divisions and ordered
                        them to make simultaneous raids in the territories of Pellene, Sicyon and
                        Phlius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The three divisions marched off on
                        their separate errands. As soon as intelligence of this was brought to
                        Nicostratus at Cleonae, he promptly sent a strong detachment of mercenaries
                        to seize the pass leading to Corinth. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He
                        followed with his army in two columns, the cavalry forming an advanced
                        guard. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In one column marched the
                        mercenaries and light infantry; in the other the hoplites, the main strength
                        of all Greek armies. When they were not far from the hostile camp some of
                        the Thracians began to attack the parties of the enemy scattered in the
                        fields. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The camp was filled with sudden
                        alarm and the commander was surprised and bewildered. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He had never seen the enemy, unless it were a few here
                        and there on the hills before Sicyon, as they did not venture on the lower
                        ground, and he never supposed that they would leave their position at
                        Cleonae and take the aggressive against him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> The dispersed parties were recalled to camp by sound of trumpet, and,
                        ordering the soldiers to seize their arms with all speed, he hurried out, of
                        the camp with a weak force and formed his line on the river bank. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> The other troops had hardly had time to collect
                        and form, and did not withstand the first charge, but the Macedonians, who
                        formed the bulk of the fighting line, made the victory for a long time
                        doubtful. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At length, with their flank
                        exposed by the flight of the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> rest of
                        the army and subjected to two separate attacks from the light infantry on
                        their flank and the hoplites and heavy armed on their front, they began to
                        give ground, and, as the pressure increased, turned and fled. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> The greater number flung away their arms and,
                        abandoning all hope of holding their camp, made for Corinth. Against these
                        Nicostratus sent his mercenaries in pursuit, and despatched the cavalry and
                        Thracian auxiliaries to attack the plundering parties round Sicyon.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Here too there was great slaughter,
                        almost more, in fact, than in the actual battle. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> Some who had been ravaging the country round Pellene
                        and Phlius were returning to camp, in no military formation and unaware of
                        all that had happened, when they fell in with the enemy patrols where they
                        had expected to find their own. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Others,
                        seeing men running in all directions, suspected what had happened and fled
                        with such precipitation that they lost themselves and even the peasantry
                        were able to cut them off. 1500 men fell on that day and 300 prisoners were
                        secured. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The whole of Achaia was
                        delivered from a great fear. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Acarnania was the only Greek State that
                        still adhered to the Macedonian alliance. Before the battle of Cynoscephalae
                        L. Quinctius had invited their chiefs to a conference at Corcyra, where he
                        induced them to take <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the first step
                        towards a change of policy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The two main
                        reasons for their fidelity were their innate sense of loyalty and their fear
                        and dislike of the Aetolians. A national council was convened at Leucas. It
                        was by no means generally attended, nor did those who were present agree as
                        to the course to be pursued. The leaders, however, including the presiding
                        magistrate, succeeded in getting a party motion carried in favour of an
                        alliance with Rome. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The cities which had
                        not sent representatives resented this strongly, and amidst the national
                        excitement two of their leading men, Androcles and Echedemus, emissaries of
                        Philip, had sufficient influence not only to obtain the cancelling of the
                        decree, but even to secure the <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                        condemnation of its authors, Archelaus and Bianor, on a charge of treason
                        and the dismissal from office of Zeuxidas, who as president had allowed the
                        motion to be put. The condemned men took a hazardous but, as events turned
                        out, a successful step. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their friends
                        advised them to bow to circumstances and go to the Romans at Corcyra, but
                        they resolved to present themselves before the people and either calm the
                        popular indignation or submit to whatever fortune might have in store for
                        them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When they entered the crowded
                        council chamber there were at first <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        murmurs of astonishment, but soon the respect inspired by the high position
                        they once held and the compassion felt for their present misfortunes evoked
                        silent sympathy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Permission having been
                        given them to speak, they at first adopted a suppliant tone, but when it
                        came to meeting the charges against them they defended themselves with all
                        the confidence of innocent men, and at last they ventured to complain mildly
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> of the treatment they had received
                        and remonstrated against the injustice and cruelty which had been meted out
                        to them. The feelings of their audience were so stirred that all the decrees
                        made against them were rescinded by a large majority. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Nevertheless it was decided to go back to the alliance
                        with Philip and renounce friendly relations with Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These decrees were passed at Leucas, the
                        capital of Acarnania and the seat of the national council. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When this sudden change of feeling was reported to
                        Flamininus at Corcyra, he at once set sail for Leucas and brought up at a
                        spot called the Heraeum. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then advanced
                        towards the city with every description of artillery and siege engines,
                        thinking that at the first shock of alarm the defenders would lose heart.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As soon as he saw that there were no
                        signs of their asking for peace he began to set up the vineae and towers and
                        bring the battering-rams up to the walls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Acarnania as a whole lies between Aetolia and Epirus and looks westward
                        towards the Sicilian Sea. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Leucadia, which
                        is now an island separated from Acarnania by a canal of moderate depth, was
                        then a peninsula, connected with the western shore of Acarnania by a narrow
                        isthmus half a mile long, and at no point more than 120 paces broad.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The city of Leucas is situated at the
                        head of this isthmus, resting on a hill which faces eastward towards
                        Acarnania; the lowest part of the city lies on the sea front and is level.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This makes it open to attack both by
                        land and sea, for the shallow waters are more like a lagoon than like the
                        sea, and the soil of the surrounding plain can easily be thrown up for lines
                        of investment and siege works. Many parts of the wall were in consequence
                        undermined or shaken down by the battering-rams. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> But the advantage which the situation of the city gave
                        to the assailants was counterbalanced by the indomitable spirit of the
                        defenders. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Ever on the alert, night and
                        day they repaired the shattered walls, barricaded the breaches, made
                        constant sorties and defended their walls by arms more than their walls
                        defended them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The siege would have been
                        protracted longer than the Romans anticipated had not some refugees of
                        Italian nationality who were living in Leucas admitted soldiers from the
                        citadel. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Once admitted, they ran down
                        with great tumult from the higher ground and found the Leucadians drawn up
                        in battle formation in the forum, who offered a stout resistance. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> In the meanwhile the walls had in many places
                        been successfully escaladed, and over the heaps of stones and debris a way
                        was made into the city. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> By this time the
                        general himself had enveloped the combatants with considerable force, and
                        whilst some perished between the two bodies of assailants others threw down
                        their arms and surrendered. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A few days
                        later, on hearing of the battle of Cynoscephalae; the whole of Acarnania
                        submitted to the Roman general. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In every direction alike Philip's fortunes
                        were sinking. Just at this time the Rhodians determined to win back from him
                        the district on the mainland known as Peraea, which had been held by their
                        forefathers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> An expedition was despatched
                        under the command of Pausistratus, consisting of 1300 Achaean infantry and
                        about 1800 miscellaneous troops drawn from various nations-Gauls and
                        Pisuetae; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nisuetae, Tamians and Trahi from
                        Africa, and Laudicenes from Asia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With
                        this force Pausistratus seized Tendeba, an extremely advantageous position
                        situated in the territory of Stratonice, the king's troops who had held it
                        being unaware of his advance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here he was
                        joined by a body of 1000 Achaean infantry and 400 cavalry specially raised
                        for this campaign. They were commanded by Theoxenus. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Dinocrates, one of the king's lieutenants, marched to
                        Tendeba with a view of recovering the place, and from there to Astragon,
                        another fortified position in the same district. All the scattered garrisons
                        were recalled, and with these and a contingent of Thessalians from
                        Stratonice itself he went on to Abanda where the enemy lay. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The Rhodians were quite ready for battle, and as the
                        camps lay near one another they at once took the field. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Dinocrates posted his 500 Macedonians on his right and
                        the Agrianians on his left, and formed his centre from the troops of
                            <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the various garrisons, mostly
                        Carians, whilst the flanks were covered by the Macedonian horse and the
                        Cretan and Thracian irregulars. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                        Rhodians had the Achaeans on their right and a picked force of mercenaries
                        on their left; the centre was held by a mixed force drawn from several
                        nationalities; their cavalry and such light infantry as they had protected
                        their flanks. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On that day the two armies only stood on
                        the banks of the stream, which was then running low, and after discharging a
                        few missiles at each other returned to camp. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The following day they were marshalled in the same
                        order, and the action which followed was a much more keenly contested one
                        than might have been expected from the numbers engaged. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> There were not more than 3000 infantry and about 100
                        cavalry on each side, but they were fairly matched not only in numbers and
                        equipment, but also in courage and tenacity. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The battle was begun by the Achaeans, who crossed the
                        rivulet and attacked the Agrianians, and they were followed by the whole
                        line, who went over the brook at the double. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> For a long time the struggle remained doubtful, till
                        the Achaeans, who numbered . . ., compelled the 400 to give ground.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> With the enemy's left pushed back,
                        they concentrated their attack on his right. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> As long as the Macedonian ranks were unbroken and the
                        phalanx kept its close formation they could not be moved, but when their
                        left was exposed and they tried to <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/>
                        bring their spears round to face the enemy who were making a flank attack,
                        they at once got into confusion and fell foul of one another, then they
                        turned and at last, flinging away their arms, broke into headlong flight.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The fugitives made for Bargyliae, and
                        Dinocrates also fled thither. The Rhodians kept up the pursuit for the
                        remainder of the day and then returned to camp. Had they gone on to
                        Stratonice straight from the battle-field the city would in all probability
                        have been taken, but they lost the <milestone n="20??" unit="section"/>
                        chance of doing this by wasting their time in recovering the fortified posts
                        and villages in Peraea. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> During this
                        interval those in command at Stratonice regained their courage, and before
                        long Dinocrates with the survivors from the battle entered the place.
                            <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> The city was subsequently besieged
                        and assaulted, but all to no purpose, nor could it be secured until some
                        years later, when it was made over to the Rhodians by Antiochus. These
                        incidents occurred almost simultaneously in Thessaly, Achaia and Asia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Emboldened by the successive Macedonian
                        defeats, the Dardanians began to lay waste the northern part of the realm.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Although Philip had almost the whole
                        world against him and Fortune was driving him and his people out of every
                        place in turn, he felt that to be expelled from Macedonia itself would be
                        worse than death. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> No sooner, therefore,
                        did he hear of the Dardanian invasion than he hurriedly levied troops in all
                        the cities of his kingdom and with a force of 6000 infantry and 500 cavalry
                        he came upon the enemy unexpectedly near Stobi in Paeonia. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> A great many men fell in the battle, a greater number
                        amongst the fields, where they were dispersed in the hope of plunder. Where
                        there was no obstacle to flight they were in no mood to risk the chance of a
                        battle, and so they retired within their own borders. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The success of this expedition, so different from the
                        state of things elsewhere, revived the spirits of his men. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> After this he returned to Thessalonica. The close of
                        the Punic War took place at a favourable moment, for it removed the danger
                        of having a second war on hand at the same time, namely the war against
                        Philip. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Still more opportune was the
                        victory over Philip at a time when Antiochus was already taking hostile
                        action from Syria. Not only was it easier to meet each singly than if they
                        had joined forces, but Spain was giving trouble at the same time and a
                        warlike movement on a large scale was taking place in that country.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During the previous summer Antiochus
                        had reduced all the cities in Coelo-Syria which had been under Ptolemy's
                        sway, and though he had now withdrawn into winter quarters he displayed as
                        great activity as he had done during the summer. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He had called up the whole strength of his kingdom and
                        had amassed enormous forces, both military and naval. At the commencement of
                        spring he had sent his two sons, Ardys and Mithridates, with an army to
                        Sardis with instructions to wait for him there <milestone n="10??"
                            unit="section"/> whilst he started by sea with a fleet of a hundred
                        decked ships and two hundred smaller vessels, including swift pinnaces and
                        Cyprian barques. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> His object was twofold:
                        to attempt the reduction of the cities along the whole coastline of Cilicia,
                        Lycia and Caria which owed allegiance to Ptolemy, and also to assist
                        Philip-the war with him was not over-both by land and sea. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Rhodians have given many splendid
                        proofs of their courage in maintaining their loyalty to Rome and in
                        defending the liberties of Greece, but never did they afford a finer
                        instance of it than at this time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Undismayed by the vastness of the impending war they sent a message to the
                        king forbidding him to sail beyond the promontory of Chelidonia in Cilicia,
                        a place rendered famous by its being mentioned in an ancient treaty between
                        the Athenians and the kings of Persia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If
                        he did not keep his fleet and his forces within that limit, they informed
                        him that they should oppose him, not because of any personal enmity to him,
                        but because they would not allow him to join forces with Philip and so
                        hinder the Romans in their work of liberating Greece. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Antiochus was at the time investing Coracesium. He had
                        so far secured Zephyrium, Soli, Aphrodisias and Corycus, and after rounding
                        Anemurium-another Cilician headland-had captured Selinus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> All these towns and other fortified places on this
                        coast had submitted to him either voluntarily or under the stress of fear,
                        but Coracesium unexpectedly shut its gates against him. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> During this delay the Rhodian envoys obtained an
                        audience of him. The tenor of their instructions was of a nature to rouse
                        the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> king's wrath, but he curbed his
                        anger and told them that he should send envoys to Rhodes with instructions
                        to renew the old ties which he and his ancestors had formed with that State,
                        and also to reassure them as to the object of his approach, which would
                        bring no injury or loss either to them or to their allies. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The embassy which he had sent to Rome had just
                        returned, and as the issue of the war with Philip was still uncertain the
                        senate had wisely given them a favourable reception. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Antiochus alleged the gracious reply of the senate and
                        the resolution they passed, so complimentary to him, as a proof that he had
                        no intention of breaking off his friendly relations with Rome. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Whilst the king's envoys were urging these
                        considerations in a meeting of the citizens of Rhodes, news came that the
                        war had been brought to a close at Cynoscephalae. On receipt of this
                        intelligence the Rhodians, having nothing more to fear from Philip,
                        abandoned their design of opposing Antiochus with their fleet. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> They did not, however, abandon the other object,
                        the defence of the liberties of the States in alliance with Ptolemy which
                        Antiochus was now threatening. To some they gave active assistance, others
                        they forewarned of the movements of the enemy; it was thus that Caunos,
                        Myndus, Halicarnassus and Samos owed their liberty to Rhodes. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> It is not worth while to go in detail into the
                        events which happened in this <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> part of
                        the world, seeing that it is almost beyond my powers to deal with those
                        especially connected with the war with Rome. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was at this time that Attalus, who
                        owing to his illness had been carried from Thebes to Pergamum, died there in
                        his seventy-second year after a reign of forty-four years. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Beyond his wealth Fortune had bestowed nothing on this
                        man which could lead him to hope that he would ever be king. But by making a
                        wise use of his riches and at the same time employing them on a magnificent
                        scale he gradually began to be regarded, first in his own estimation and
                        then in the eyes of his friends, as not unworthy of the crown. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> In one decisive battle he defeated the Gauls-a
                        nation all the more dreaded because they had migrated into Asia
                        comparatively recently-and after <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> this
                        victory he assumed the royal title and ever after justified it by a
                        corresponding greatness of soul. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He
                        governed his subjects with absolute justice and showed exceptional loyalty
                        to his allies; affectionate towards his wife and his children, four of whom
                        survived him, he was considerate and generous to his friends and left his
                        kingdom so settled and secure that the possession of it descended to the
                        third generation of his posterity. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This
                        was the state of things in Greece, Asia and Macedonia, when just as the
                        campaign against Philip was brought to a close and before peace had been
                        definitely established a serious war broke out in Further Spain. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> M. Helvius was administering the province, and he
                        wrote to the senate to inform them that the tribal chiefs Culchas and
                        Luxinius were in arms. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Fifteen fortified
                        towns were taking part with Culchas, whilst Luxinius was supported by the
                        strong cities of Carmo and Bardo, the Malacini and Sexetani on the coast and
                        the whole of Baeturia. In addition to these the tribes which had not yet
                        disclosed their intentions were prepared to rise as soon as their neighbours
                        moved. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After M. Sergius, the city praetor,
                        had read this despatch in the senate a decree was passed ordering that after
                        the new praetors were elected the one who obtained Spain as his province
                        should as soon as possible ask for the senate's instructions as to the
                        military operations there. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls arrived in Rome both at the
                        same time and convened the senate at the temple of Bellona. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> On their demanding a triumph for their military
                        successes, they were opposed by two of the tribunes of the plebs, who
                        insisted on the proposal being submitted to the House by each consul
                        separately. They would not permit a joint proposal to be made on the ground
                        that in that case equal honours would be conferred when the services were
                        far from equal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Q. Minucius replied that
                        Italy had been assigned to them both and he and his colleague had conducted
                        their operations with one mind and one policy. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> C. Cornelius added that when the Boii crossed the Po to
                        assist the Insubres and the Cenomanni it was through his colleague's action
                        in laying waste their fields and villages that they were compelled to return
                        and defend their own country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The tribunes
                        admitted that the achievements of C. Cethegus were such that there could be
                        no more hesitation about according him a triumph than about paying honours
                        to the immortal gods. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Neither Cethegus,
                        however, nor any other citizen possessed so much influence and power that he
                        could, after obtaining a well-deserved triumph for himself, grant the same
                        honour to a colleague who did not deserve it, and whose request for it was
                        an affront. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Q. Minucius, they declared,
                        had fought some insignificant actions, hardly worth talking about, amongst
                        the Ligurians and had lost a large number of men in Gaul. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Two military tribunes, T. Juventius and Cneius
                        Ligurius, both attached to the fourth legion, had fallen in an unsuccessful
                        battle in company with many other brave men, both citizens and allies. A few
                        towns and villages had ostensibly surrendered for the time being, without
                        giving any guarantee of good faith. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These
                        altercations between the consuls and the tribunes took up two days.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last the pertinacity of the
                        tribunes won the day and the consuls submitted their requests separately.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A triumph was unanimously decreed to C.
                        Cethegus. His popularity was still further enhanced by delegates from
                        Cremona and <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Placentia, who gratefully
                        described how he had delivered them from the horrors of a siege, and in the
                        case of most of those who had fallen into the enemy's hands from actual
                        slavery. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Q. Minucius put his motion merely
                        tentatively, and on finding the whole senate opposed to him gave out that by
                        virtue of his rights as consul, and in accordance with the precedent set by
                        many illustrious men, he should triumph on the Alban Mount. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> C. Cethegus celebrated his triumph while he was still
                        in office. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Many military standards were
                        carried in the procession, many spoils in captured wagons and many noble
                        Gauls were led before his chariot. Some authorities aver that the
                        Carthaginian general Hamilcar was amongst them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> But the eyes of all were turned chiefly to a crowd of
                        colonists from Cremona and Placentia who followed the consul's chariot
                        wearing the cap of liberty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The amount of
                        specie carried in the procession was 237,500 ases and 79,000 silver denarii.
                        Each of the soldiers received a bonus of 70 ases and double the amount was
                        given to each centurion and horseman. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Q.
                        Minucius celebrated his victories over the Ligurians and the Boii on the
                        Alban Mount. Though this triumph was less of a distinction than the other in
                        respect of the scene and glory of his achievements, and though everybody was
                        aware that its cost was not defrayed from the public treasury, still it
                        about equalled it in the number of standards and wagons and spoils.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Even the amount of money almost
                        reached the same figure; there were 254,000 ases and 53,200 silver denarii.
                        He gave to each of his soldiers the same sums as his colleague had given
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the triumph came the elections. The
                        new consuls were L. Furius Purpurio and M. Claudius Marcellus. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> The praetors elected the day following were Q.
                        Fabius Buteo, Tiberius Sempronius Longus, Q. Minucius Thermus, Manius
                        Acilius Glabrio, L. Apustius Fullo and C. Laelius. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> About the end of the year despatches arrived from T.
                        Quinctius stating that he had fought a pitched battle with Philip in
                        Thessaly, and that the enemy had been routed and put to flight. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> These despatches were read by Sergius first in
                        the senate and then, with the sanction of the senate, at a meeting of the
                        citizens. A five days' thanksgiving was appointed for this success. The
                        joint delegation from T. Quinctius and Philip arrived soon afterwards.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Macedonians were conducted to the
                        Government building in the Campus Martius, where they were accommodated as
                        guests of the State. The senate received them in audience in the temple of
                        Bellona; no long speeches were made, for the delegates simply stated that
                        the king was prepared to act in accordance with the wishes of the senate.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Following the traditional usage, ten
                        commissioners were appointed to advise with T. Quinctius as to the terms on
                        which peace was to be granted to <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Philip,
                        and a clause was added to the decree providing that among the members of the
                        commission should be included P. Sulpicius and P. Villius, to whom Macedonia
                        had been assigned as their province when they were consuls. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> On the same day a petition was presented by the
                        inhabitants of Cosa praying that their numbers might be enlarged, and an
                        order was made for a thousand fresh colonists to <milestone n="9??"
                            unit="section"/> be enrolled, no one to be included in the number who
                        had been an enemy alien since the consulship of P. Cornelius and Tiberius
                        Sempronius. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman Games in the Circus Maximus and
                        the scenic plays on the stage were exhibited by the curule aediles, P.
                        Cornelius Scipio and Cneius Manlius Vulso, on a more splendid scale than
                        usual, and amid greater hilarity on the part of the spectators owing to the
                        recent successes in the field. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Three times
                        they were repeated in every detail. The Plebeian Games were repeated seven
                        times. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The latter were exhibited by Manius
                        Acilius Glabrio and C. Laelius, and out of the proceeds of fines they set up
                        bronze statues of Ceres, Liber and Libera. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        The first business before the new consuls, L. Furius and M. Claudius
                        Marcellus, after taking office was the allotment of the provinces. The
                        senate was preparing to decree Italy as the province for both, but the
                        consuls tried hard to get Macedonia allotted as well as Italy. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Marcellus, who was the more anxious of the two to
                        obtain Macedonia, declared that the peace with Philip was illusory and that
                        if the Roman army were withdrawn he would resume hostilities. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> This made the senate hesitate in coming to a
                        decision, and the consul would probably have gained his point had not two
                        tribunes of the plebs, Q. Marcius Ralla and C. Atinius Labeo, threatened to
                        interpose their veto unless the plebs were first consulted as <milestone
                            n="7??" unit="section"/> to whether it was their will and pleasure that
                        peace should be made with Philip. The question was submitted to the plebs in
                        the Capitol, and the whole of the thirty-five tribes voted in the
                        affirmative. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The satisfaction felt at the
                        peaceful settlement with Macedonia was all the more welcome owing to the
                        gloomy news from Spain and the publication of a despatch stating that the
                        proconsul, C. Sempronius Tuditanus, acting in Hither Spain had been defeated
                        and his army routed and put to flight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Many men of high rank had fallen in the battle, and Tuditanus himself was
                        seriously wounded and died soon after being carried off the field.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Italy was assigned to both the
                        consuls as their province, together with the legions which the previous
                        consuls had had, and they were to raise four new legions, two to garrison
                        the City and two to be at the disposal of the senate. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> T. Quinctius Flamininus was to remain in his province
                        with the army which he had, and the previous extension of his command was
                        deemed sufficient. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The praetors next balloted for their
                        provinces. L. Apustius Fullo obtained the City jurisdiction, M. Acilius
                        Glabrio the jurisdiction in causes between citizens and aliens. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> Q. Fabius Buteo received Further Spain and Q.
                        Minucius Thermus, Hither Spain. C. Laelius was allotted Sicily and Tiberius
                        Sempronius Longus, Sardinia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consuls
                        were ordered to furnish the two praetors who were to proceed to Spain with
                        one legion each from the four new legions they were raising and also 4000
                        allied infantry and 300 cavalry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These two
                        praetors were ordered to proceed to their provinces at the earliest possible
                        moment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Spanish war, which was
                        practically a fresh war, because the natives had resorted to arms on their
                        own account without any Carthaginian army or general to support them, broke
                        out five years after the former war had been brought to a close
                        simultaneously with the Punic War. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Before
                        the praetors started for Spain, or the consuls left the City, they were
                        charged with the expiation of the various portents that had been announced.
                        P. Villius, a Roman knight who was on his way to the Sabine country, was
                        killed, together with his horse, by a flash of lightning. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The temple of Ferona near Capenae was similarly struck.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the temple of Moneta two
                        spear-heads burst into flame. A wolf entered the City through the Porta
                        Esquilina, the busiest part of the City, and ran down to the Forum; it then
                        ran through the Tuscan and Cermalian wards, and finally escaped through the
                        Porta Capena almost untouched. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These
                        portents were expiated by the sacrifice of full-grown victims. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this interval Cneius Cornelius
                        Blasio, who had administered Hither Spain before Tuditanus, was authorised
                        by the senate to enter the City in ovation. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Before him were borne 1515 pounds of gold and 20,000 of silver, and also
                        34,500 silver denarii. L. Stertinius, who made no effort to obtain a
                        triumph, brought away from Further Spain 50,000 <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> pounds of silver for the public treasury, and with the
                        proceeds from the sale of the spoil he erected two gateways in the Forum
                        Boarium in front of the temples of Fortuna and Mater Matuta, and one in the
                        Circus Maximus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On these three structures
                        he placed gilded statues. The above were the principal events during the
                        winter. T. Quinctius was in winter quarters at Elatia. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Amidst the numerous requests which he received from the
                        friendly States was one from the Boeotians begging that, those of their
                        countrymen who had been fighting for Philip might be restored to them.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Quinctius readily granted their
                        request, not because he thought that they deserved it, but because he was
                        anxious, in view of Antiochus' suspicious movements, to win the support and
                        sympathy of the Grecian States. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After they
                        had been restored it became at once apparent how little gratitude he had
                        evoked among the Boeotians, for they sent delegates to thank Philip for the
                        return of their countrymen, as though it were he who had made the concession
                        and not Quinctius and the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And at
                        the next election they chose a person called Brachylles as the Boeotarch,
                        for no other reason than because he had commanded the Boeotian contingent
                        which had served under Philip, thus passing over men like Zeuxippus and
                        Pisistratus and others who had brought about the alliance with Rome.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Annoyed as these men were at the time,
                        they were <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> still more apprehensive as to
                        the future, for if these things could go on while a Roman army was lying
                        almost at their gates, what would happen to them, they asked, when the
                        Romans had left for Italy and Philip was close at hand to help <milestone
                            n="11??" unit="section"/> his friends and take his revenge upon his
                        opponents? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As Brachylles was the main supporter of
                        the king they determined to get rid of him while the arms of Rome were in
                        their neighbourhood. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The hour chosen was
                        when he was returning from a State banquet in a state of intoxication,
                        escorted by an effeminate crew who had been carousing in the banquet hall.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was set upon by six armed men,
                        three of whom were Italians and three Aetolians, and killed on the spot. His
                        companions fled screaming for help, and the whole city was thrown into
                        uproar, men running in all directions with lanterns and torches. The
                        assassins had meanwhile escaped through the nearest gate. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> At daybreak the next morning the population gathered in
                        the theatre in such numbers as to give the appearance of a formal assembly
                        convened by edict or by the public crier. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Openly all men were saying that he had been murdered by his retinue and the
                        dissolute wretches who accompanied him, but in their hearts they fixed upon
                        Zeuxippus as the instigator of the crime. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        For the time being, however, it was decided that those who had been with him
                        should be arrested and examined under torture. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> While search was being made for them Zeuxippus,
                        determined to clear himself of any suspicion of complicity, came calm and
                        undismayed into the gathering and said that people were mistaken who
                        supposed that such an atrocious murder could have been committed by such
                        effeminate creatures. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He adduced many
                        strong arguments to support this view, and some who heard him were convinced
                        that if he were an accomplice he would never have appeared before the people
                        or made any allusion to the murder when no one had challenged him to do so.
                        Others were quite certain that by thus unblushingly meeting the charge he
                        was endeavouring to divert suspicion from himself. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> After a short time those who were really innocent were
                        put to the torture, and though they themselves knew nothing about it they
                        treated the universal opinion as though it amounted to proof and named
                        Zeuxippus and Pisistratus without alleging any evidence as to their actually
                        knowing what had happened. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Zeuxippus,
                        however, with a person called Stratonidas escaped by night to Tanagra,
                        fearing his own conscience more than the statements of men who were
                        unconscious of the true state of the case. Pisistratus paid no regard to the
                        informers and remained in Thebes. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Zeuxippus had a slave with him who had
                        acted as messenger and intermediary all through the affair. Pisistratus was
                        afraid that this man might turn informer, and it was through this very fear
                        that the slave was compelled to make the disclosure. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> He sent a letter to Zeuxippus warning him to do away
                        with the slave as he was privy to all they had done, and he did not believe
                        him to be so capable of concealing the thing as he had been of carrying it
                        out. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The bearer was ordered to give the
                        letter to Zeuxippus as soon as possible, and as he had no opportunity of
                        giving it at once he handed it to this very slave, whom he regarded as the
                        most faithful of all to his master, telling him at the same time that it was
                        from Pisistratus about a matter which greatly concerned Zeuxippus.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The slave assured the bearer that he
                        would deliver it forthwith, but being conscience stricken he opened it, and
                        after reading it through fled to Thebes and laid the evidence before the
                        magistrates. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Warned by the flight of the
                        slave, Zeuxippus withdrew to Anthedon, as he considered that a safer place
                        to live in. Pisistratus and the others were examined under torture and
                        afterwards executed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This murder roused Thebes and the whole of
                        Boeotia to an intensely bitter hatred against the Romans; they were quite
                        convinced that Zeuxippus, the foremost man amongst them, would not have been
                        a party to such a crime if he had not been countenanced by the Roman
                        general. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To go to war was impossible; they
                        had neither forces nor a leader, but they did the next thing to it, they
                        took to brigandage and assassination. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They
                        made away with soldiers who were billeted on them, and others on furlough
                        who were going about on various errands in their winter quarters. Some were
                        caught in the high roads by men who lay in wait for them, others were led on
                        false pretences to lonely inns and then seized and murdered. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> These crimes were committed from greed quite as
                        much as from hatred, because the men carried silver in their belts for
                        making purchases. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As more and more men
                        were amongst the missing every day, the whole of Boeotia acquired an evil
                        reputation, and the men were more afraid to go outside their camp than if
                        they had been in an enemy's country. On this, Quinctius sent officers to the
                        different cities to investigate the murders. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> Most of them were found to have been committed round Lake Copais; here
                        bodies were dug out of the mud and recovered from the shallows with stones
                        or amphorae fastened to them, to sink them deeper by their weight. Many
                        murders also took place at Acraephia and Coronea. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Quinctius issued orders for those who were guilty to be
                        given up to him, and he levied a fine of 500 talents upon the Boeotians for
                        the 500 soldiers who had been murdered. </p>
                    <p> Neither of these orders was complied with. The cities simply excused
                        themselves by saying that their government had not sanctioned any of these
                        deeds. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Quinctius thereupon sent a
                        deputation to visit Athens and Achaia and explain to them that it was in a
                        just and holy cause that he was going to punish the Boeotians by arms.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius received orders to
                        march to Acraephia with half the force, and he himself with the other half
                        invested Coronea after laving waste the country round. All the country
                        through which the two divisions advanced from Elatia was devastated.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Boeotians, completely cowed by
                        the losses they were sustaining and seeing fear and flight everywhere, sent
                        envoys, but as they were not admitted into the camp, the Athenian and
                        Achaean envoys came to their support. The mediation of the Achaeans was the
                        more effectual of the two, because in case they failed to obtain peace for
                        the Boeotians they were resolved to fight by the side of the Romans.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Through their representations, the
                        Boeotians were allowed to approach the Roman general and lay their case
                        before him. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Peace was granted them on
                        condition that they surrendered the guilty parties and paid a fine of 30
                        talents, and the siege was raised. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days later the ten commissioners
                        arrived from Rome. On their advice peace was granted to Philip on the
                        following terms: All the Greek communities in Europe and Asia were to be
                        free and independent; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Philip was to
                        withdraw his garrisons from those which had been under his rule and after
                        their evacuation hand them over to the Romans before the date fixed for the
                        Isthmian Games. He was also to withdraw his garrisons from the following
                        cities in Asia: Euromus, Pedasae, Bargyliae, Iasos, Myrina, Abydos, Thasos
                        and Perinthus, for it was decided that these too should be free. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> With regard to the freedom of Cios, Quinctius
                        undertook to communicate the decision of the senate and the commissioners to
                        Prusias, King of Bithynia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king was
                        also to restore all prisoners and deserters to the Romans, and all his
                        decked ships, save five, were to be surrendered, but he could retain his
                        royal galley, which was all but unmanageable owing to its size and was
                        propelled by sixteen banks of oars. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His
                        army was never to exceed 5000 men and he was not allowed to have a single
                        elephant, nor was he permitted to make war beyond his frontiers without the
                        express sanction of the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                        indemnity which he was required to pay amounted to 1000 talents, half of it
                        to be paid at once and the remainder in ten annual instalments. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias asserts that an annual tribute of
                        4000 lbs. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> of silver was imposed on the
                        king for ten years. Claudius says that the annual tribute amounted to 4200
                        lbs. of silver and extended over thirty years, with an immediate payment of
                        2000 lbs. He also says that an additional clause in the treaty expressly
                        provided that Philip should not make war upon Eumenes, who had succeeded his
                        father Attalus upon the throne. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As a
                        guarantee of the observance of these conditions hostages were taken by the
                        Romans, amongst whom was Philip's son, Demetrius. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Valerius Antias further states that the island of
                        Aegina and the elephants were given to Attalus, and that Stratonice and the
                        other cities in Caria which Philip had held were given to the <milestone
                            n="11??" unit="section"/> Rhodians, and the islands of Lemnos, Imbros,
                        Delos and Scyros to the Athenians. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Almost all the States of Greece welcomed
                        peace on these terms. The Aetolians formed a solitary exception. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> They did not venture upon open opposition, but
                        they criticised the commissioners' decision bitterly in private. It was,
                        they said, a mere form of words vaguely suggesting the delusive image of
                        pretended liberty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Why, they asked, were
                        some cities to be given to the Romans without being named, and others which
                        were named to retain their freedom, unless it was thought that the cities in
                        Asia might be safely left free because of their remoteness, whilst those in
                        Greece which are not even named might be appropriated, viz. Corinth,
                        Chalcis, Oreus, together with Eretria and Demetrias? <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Nor was this charge altogether groundless, for there
                        was much hesitation as to three of those cities. In the decree of the senate
                        which the commissioners had brought with them the rest of the cities in
                        Greece and Asia were unequivocally declared free, but in the case of
                        Corinth, Chalcis and Demetrias the commissioners were instructed to do and
                        determine <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> as the interests of the
                        commonwealth and the circumstances of the time and their own sense of duty
                        required. It was Antiochus they had in their minds; <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> they were convinced that as soon as he deemed his
                        strength adequate he would invade Europe, and they did not intend to leave
                        it open to him to occupy cities which would form such favourable bases of
                        operations. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quinctius proceeded with the
                        ten commissioners to Anticyra, and from there sailed across to Corinth. Here
                        the commissioners discussed for days the measures for securing the freedom
                        of Greece. Again and again Quinctius urged that the whole of Greece must be
                        declared free if they wanted to stop the tongues of the Achaeans and inspire
                        all <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> with a true affection for Rome and
                        an appreciation of her greatness-if, in fact, they desired to convince the
                        Greeks that they had crossed the seas with the sole purpose of winning their
                        freedom and not of transferring Philip's dominion over them to themselves.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The commissioners took no exception to
                        his insistence on making the cities free, but they argued that it would be
                        safer for the cities themselves <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> to
                        remain for a time under the protection of Roman garrisons rather than have
                        to accept Antiochus as their master in the place of Philip. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> At last they came to a decision; the city of
                        Corinth was to be restored to the Achaeans, but a garrison was to be placed
                        in Acrocorinthus, and Chalcis and Demetrias were to be retained until the
                        menace of Antiochus was removed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The date fixed for the Isthmian Games was
                        now close at hand. These Games always drew vast crowds, owing partly to the
                        innate love of the nation for a spectacle in which they watched contests of
                        every kind, competitions <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> of artistic
                        skill, and trials of strength and speed, and partly owing to the fact that
                        its situation between two seas made it the common emporium of Greece and
                        Asia, where supplies were to be obtained of everything necessary or useful
                        to man. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But on this occasion it was not
                        the usual attractions alone that drew the people from every part of Greece;
                        they were in a state of keen expectancy, wondering what would be the future
                        position of the country, and what fortune awaited themselves. All sorts of
                        conjectures were formed and openly expressed as to what the Romans would do,
                        but hardly anybody persuaded himself that they would withdraw from Greece
                        altogether. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the spectators had taken their seats,
                        a herald, accompanied by a trumpeter, stepped forward into the middle of the
                        arena, where the Games are usually opened by the customary formalities, and
                        after a blast from the trumpet had produced silence, made the following
                        announcement: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> "THE SENATE OF ROME AND T.
                        QUINCTIUS, THEIR GENERAL, HAVING CONQUERED KING PHILIP AND THE MACEDONIANS
                        DO NOW DECREE AND ORDAIN THAT THESE STATES SHALL BE FREE, SHALL BE RELEASED
                        FROM THE PAYMENT OF TRIBUTE, AND SHALL LIVE UNDER THEIR OWN LAWS, NAMELY THE
                        CORINTHIANS; <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> THE PHOCIANS; ALL THE
                        LOCRIANS TOGETHER WITH THE ISLAND OF EUBOEA; THE MAGNESIANS; THE
                        THESSALIANS; THE PERRHAEBIANS, AND THE ACHAEANS OF PHTHIOTIS." This list
                        comprised all those States which had been under the sway of Philip.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the herald had finished his
                        proclamation the feeling of joy was too great for men to take it all in.
                        They hardly ventured to trust their ears, and gazed wonderingly on one
                        another, as though it were an empty dream. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Not trusting their ears, they asked those nearest how their own interests
                        were affected, and as everyone was eager not only to hear but also to see
                        the man who had proclaimed their freedom, the herald was recalled and
                        repeated his message. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then they realised
                        that the joyful news was true, and from the applause and cheers which arose
                        it was perfectly evident that none of life's blessings was dearer to the
                        multitude than liberty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Games were
                        then hurried through; no man's eyes or ears were any longer fixed on them,
                        so completely had the one master joy supplanted all other pleasurable
                        sensations. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the close of the Games, almost the
                        entire assemblage ran to the spot where the <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> Roman general was seated, and the rush of the crowd who
                        were trying to touch his hand and throw garlands and ribbons became almost
                        dangerous. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was about thirty-three years
                        old at the time, and not only the robustness of his manhood but the delight
                        of reaping such a harvest of glory gave him strength. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The universal rejoicing was not simply a temporary
                        excitement; for many days it found expression in thoughts and words of
                        gratitude. "There is," people said, "one nation which at its own cost,
                        through its own exertions, at <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> its own
                        risk has gone to war on behalf of the liberty of others. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> It renders this service not to those across its
                        frontiers, or to the peoples of neighbouring States or to those who dwell on
                        the same mainland, but it crosses the seas in order that nowhere in the
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> wide world may injustice and tyranny
                        exist, but that right and equity and law may be everywhere supreme. By this
                        single proclamation of the herald all the cities in Greece and Asia recover
                        their liberty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To have formed this design
                        shows a daring spirit; to have brought it to fulfilment is a proof of
                        exceptional courage and extraordinary good fortune." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately after the Isthmian Games
                        Quinctius and the ten commissioners gave audience to the ambassadors from
                        the different monarchs and self-governing communities. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The first to be heard were those from Antiochus. They
                        spoke to very much the same effect as they had before spoken in Rome, making
                        insincere and empty professions of friendship, but they did not receive the
                        same ambiguous answer as on the former occasion, when the business with
                        Philip was not yet settled. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Antiochus was
                        openly and unequivocally warned to evacuate all the cities in Asia which had
                        belonged to either Philip or Ptolemy, to leave the free States alone, and
                        never to make aggressions on them, as all the cities through the length and
                        breadth of Greece must continue to enjoy peace and liberty. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He was especially warned not to lead his forces into
                        Europe or go there himself. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the
                        dismissal of the king's ambassadors a convention of those from the different
                        cities and States was held and the proceedings were expedited by the reading
                        out of the names in the decree of the ten commissioners. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The people of Orestis, a district in Macedonia, had
                        their old constitution restored to them as a reward for having been the
                        first to revolt from Philip. The Magnetes, the Perrhaebians and the
                        Dolopians were also declared free. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        Thessalians received their freedom and also a grant of the Achaean portion
                        of Phthiotis exclusive of Thebes and Pharsalus. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The demand of the Aetolians that Pharsalus and Leucas
                        should be restored to them in accordance with treaty rights was referred to
                        the senate, but the commissioners acting under the authority of their decree
                        united Phocis and Locris <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> thus reverting
                        to the former state of things. Corinth, Triphylia and Heraea-also in the
                        Peloponnesus-were restored to the Achaean league. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The commissioners intended to make a grant of Oreus and
                        Eretria to Eumenes, Attalus' son, but as Quinctius raised objections this
                        one point was left to the decision of the senate, and that body declared
                        these places and also Carystus to be free cities. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Lychnis and Parthus were given to Pleuratus; both these
                        Illyrian cities had been subject to Philip. Amynander was told to keep the
                        forts which he had taken from Philip during the war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the convention had broken up the
                        commissioners divided amongst themselves the work that lay before them and
                        separated, each proceeding to effect the liberty of the cities within his
                        own district. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> P. Lentulus went to
                        Bargyliae; L. Stertinius to Hephaestia, Thasos and the cities in Thrace; P.
                        Villius and L. Terentius went to interview Antiochus; and Cn. Cornelius
                        visited Philip. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After settling minor
                        points in accordance with his instructions, he asked the king whether he
                        would listen patiently to advice that might be not only useful to him but
                        salutary as well. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Philip replied that he
                        should be grateful for any suggestion he might make which would be to his
                        interest. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Cornelius then strongly urged
                        him, now that he had obtained peace, to send a mission to Rome to establish
                        relations of friendship and alliance. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By
                        doing this he would remove, in case of any hostile movement on the part of
                        Antiochus, the possibility of appearing to be waiting for an opportunity of
                        recommencing hostilities. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This meeting
                        with Philip took place at Tempe. He assured Cornelius that he would send
                        delegates forthwith, and Cornelius then went on to Thermopylae, where what
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> was called the Pylaic council-a
                        gathering from all parts of Greece-met on stated days. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He appeared before the council, and urged the Aetolians
                        especially to continue staunch and loyal friends to Rome. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Some of their leaders mildly remonstrated against the
                        change in the feelings of the Romans towards them since their victory;
                        others took a much stronger line and declared that without the aid of the
                        Aetolians Philip could not have been vanquished, nor could the Romans ever
                        have landed in Greece. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To prevent matters
                        from coming to an open quarrel, the Roman commander abstained from replying
                        to these charges and simply assured them that if they would send an embassy
                        to Rome they would gain everything that was fair and reasonable. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> On his authority, therefore, they passed a
                        resolution that a mission should be despatched. Such were the incidents that
                        marked the close of the war with Philip. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these events were happening in
                        Greece and Macedonia and Asia, Etruria very nearly became the scene of war
                        owing to a conspiracy of the slaves. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For
                        the purpose of investigating and crushing this movement, Manius Acilius
                        Glabrio, to whom as praetor the mixed jurisdiction over citizens and aliens
                        had been assigned, was sent into Etruria with one of the two legions
                        stationed in the City. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A body of the
                        conspirators was defeated in open battle and many of them were killed or
                        taken prisoners; the ringleaders were scourged and crucified; the others
                        sent back to their masters. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consuls
                        left for their provinces. Marcellus entered the territory of the Boii, and
                        whilst he was entrenching his camp on some rising ground, his men worn out
                        with marching all day long, Corolamus, one of the Boian chiefs, attacked him
                        with a large force and killed as many as 3000. Several men of high rank fell
                        in this tumultuary battle; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> amongst them
                        Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus and M. Junius Silanus, prefects of the allies,
                        and two military tribunes in the second legion-M. Ogulnius and P. Claudius.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Romans, however, succeeded by
                        great exertions in completing their lines and held the camp against the
                        attacks of the enemy, which his initial success rendered all the more
                        fierce. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus remained in his camp for
                        some time, in order that his wounded might be cured and that his men might
                        have time to recover their spirits after such heavy losses. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Boians, quite incapable of supporting
                        the weariness of delay, dispersed everywhere to their villages and
                        strongholds. Suddenly Marcellus crossed the Po and invaded the Comum
                        territory, where the Insubres had induced the natives to take up arms and
                        were now encamped. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Boian Gauls, full
                        of confidence after the recent fight, joined battle with him while he was
                        actually on the march, and at first attacked with such violence that they
                        forced the front ranks to give way. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Fearing that if they once began to give ground it might end in a complete
                        repulse, Marcellus brought up a cohort of Marsians and launched all the
                        troops of the Latin cavalry against the enemy. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> After they had by successive charges held up the
                        determined onset of the Gauls the rest of the Roman line recovered its
                        steadiness and resisted all attempts to break it. At last they took the
                        offensive in a furious charge which the Gauls were unable to stand; they
                        turned and fled in disorder. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> According to
                        Valerius Antias over 40,000 men were killed in that battle, 801 standards
                        captured, together with 732 wagons and a large number of gold chains.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Claudius tells us that one of these,
                        a very heavy one, was deposited as an offering in the temple of Jupiter on
                        the Capitol. The Gaulish camp was stormed and plundered on the same day as
                        the battle took place, and a few days later the town of Comum was captured.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Subsequently twenty-eight fortified
                        places went over to the consul. It is a question amongst the various
                        historians whether it was against the Boii or the Insubres that the consul
                        marched <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> in the first place, and whether
                        he wiped out his unsuccessful action by a successful one afterwards or
                        whether the victory at Comum was marred by his later disaster amongst the
                        Boii. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Soon after these instances of Fortune's
                        caprice, the other consul, L. Furius Purpurio, invaded the Boian territory
                        from the Sapinian canton in Umbria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He was
                        approaching the fortress of Mutelus, but fearing that he might be cut off by
                        the Boii and Ligurians, he led his army back over the way he had come, and
                        by making a wide detour through open and therefore safe country ultimately
                        joined his colleague. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> With their united
                        armies they traversed the Boian country as far as the town of Felsina,
                        systematically plundering as they advanced. That place, with all the
                        fortified positions in the country round, surrendered, as did most of the
                        tribe; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the younger men remained in arms
                        for the sake of plunder and had retreated into the depths of the forest.
                        Then the two armies advanced against the Ligurians. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Boii, who were still in arms, expected that as they
                        were supposed to be a long way off the Roman army would be more careless in
                        keeping its formation on the march, and they followed it through secret
                        paths in the forest with the intention of making a surprise attack.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As they did not catch it up, they
                        suddenly crossed the Po in ships and devastated the lands of the Laevi and
                        Libui. On their way back along the Ligurian frontier they fell in with the
                        Roman armies whilst they were loaded with plunder. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The battle began more quickly and more furiously than
                        if the time and place had previously been determined and all preparations
                        made for battle. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Here was a striking
                        instance of the way in which passion stimulates courage, for the Romans were
                        so determined to kill rather than simply to win a victory that they left
                        hardly a man alive to carry the news of the battle. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> When the despatch announcing this success reached Rome
                        a three days' thanksgiving was ordered for the victory. Marcellus arrived in
                        Rome soon afterwards and a triumph was unanimously accorded to him by the
                        senate. He celebrated his triumph over the Insubres and the Comensians while
                        still in office. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The anticipation of a
                        triumph over the Boii he resigned to his colleague, because he personally
                        had been unsuccessful against them, only in conjunction with his colleague
                        had he been victorious. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A large amount of
                        spoil was carried in the wagons taken from the enemy, including numerous
                        standards. The specie amounted to 320,000 ases and 234,000 silver denarii.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Each legionary received a gratuity of
                        80 ases; the cavalry and centurions each three times as much. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> .During this year Antiochus, who had spent
                        the winter in Ephesus, endeavoured to reduce all the cities in Asia to their
                        old condition of dependence. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With the
                        exception of Smyrna and Lampsacus, he thought that they would all accept the
                        yoke without difficulty, since they either lay in open level country or were
                        weakly defended by their walls and their soldiery. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Smyrna and Lampsacus asserted their right to be free
                        and there was danger, should their claim be allowed, of other cities in
                        Aeolis and Ionia following the example of Smyrna, and those on the
                        Hellespont the example of Lampsacus. Accordingly he despatched a force from
                        Ephesus to invest Smyrna and ordered the troops in Abydos to march to
                        Lampsacus, only a small detachment being left to hold the place. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> But it was not only the threat of arms that he
                        made use of, he sent envoys to make friendly overtures to the citizens, and
                        whilst gently rebuking <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> their rashness
                        and obstinacy lead them to hope that in a short time they would have what
                        they wanted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was, however, perfectly
                        clear to them and to all the world that they would enjoy their liberty as
                        the free gift of the king and not because they had seized a favourable
                        opportunity of winning it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They told the
                        envoys in reply that Antiochus must be neither surprised nor angry if they
                        did not patiently resign themselves to the indefinite postponement of their
                        hopes of liberty. </p>
                    <p> At the beginning of spring he set sail from Ephesus for the Hellespont and
                        ordered his land army to proceed from Abydos to the Chersonese. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> He united his naval and military powers at
                        Madytos, a city in the Chersonese, and as they had shut their gates against
                        him he completely invested the place, and was on the point of bringing up
                        his siege engines when the city surrendered. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                        /> The fear which Antiochus thus inspired led the inhabitants of Sestos and
                        the other cities in the Chersonese to make a voluntary surrender. His next
                        objective was Lysimachia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When he arrived
                        here with the whole of his land and sea forces he found the place deserted
                        and little more than a heap of ruins, for some years previously the
                        Thracians had captured and plundered the city and then burnt it. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Finding it in this condition, Antiochus was
                        seized by a desire to restore a city of such celebrity and so favourably
                        situated, and he at once set about the various tasks which this involved.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The houses and walls were rebuilt,
                        some of the former inhabitants who had been made slaves were ransomed,
                        others who were scattered as refugees throughout the Chersonese and the
                        shores of the Hellespont were discovered and brought together, and new
                        colonists were attracted by the prospect of the advantages they would
                        receive. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In fact every method was adopted
                        of repopulating the city. To remove at the same time all apprehensions of
                        trouble from the Thracians he proceeded with <milestone n="14??"
                            unit="section"/> one half of his army to devastate the neighbouring
                        districts of Thrace, the other half and all the ships' crews he left to go
                        on with the work of restoration. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Very shortly after this L. Cornelius, who
                        had been sent by the senate to settle the differences between Antiochus and
                        Ptolemy, made a halt at Selymbria, and three of the ten commissioners went
                        to Lysimachia: P. Lentulus from Bargyliae, P. Villius and L. Terentius from
                        Thasos. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were joined there by L.
                        Cornelius from Selymbria, and a few days later by Antiochus, who returned
                        from Thrace. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The first meeting with the
                        commissioners and the invitation which Antiochus gave them were kindly and
                        hospitable, but when it came to discussing their instructions and the
                        position of affairs in Asia a good deal of temper was shown on both sides.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans told Antiochus plainly that
                        everything he had done since his fleet set sail from Syria met with the
                        disapproval of the senate and they considered it right that all the cities
                        which had been subject to Ptolemy should be restored to him. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> With regard to those cities which had formed part
                        of Philip's possessions and which while <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        he was preoccupied with the war against Rome Antiochus had seized the
                        opportunity of appropriating himself, it was simply intolerable that after
                        the Romans had sustained such risks and hardships by sea and land for all
                        those years Antiochus should carry off the prizes of war. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Granting that it was possible for the Romans to take no
                        notice of his appearance in Asia as being no concern of theirs, what about
                        his entrance into Europe with the whole of his army and navy? What
                        difference was there between that and an open declaration of war against
                        Rome? Even if he had landed in Italy he would say that he did not mean war,
                        but the Romans were not going to wait until he was in a position to do that.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In his reply Antiochus expressed his
                        surprise that the Romans should go so carefully into the question as to what
                        Antiochus ought to do, whilst they never stopped to consider what limits
                        were to be set to their own advance by land and sea. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Asia was no concern of the senate, and they had no more
                        right to ask what Antiochus was doing in Asia than he had to ask what the
                        Roman people were doing in Italy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As for
                        Ptolemy and their complaint that he had appropriated his cities, he and
                        Ptolemy were on perfectly friendly terms and arrangements were being made
                        for them to be connected by marriage shortly. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> He had not sought to take advantage of Philip's
                        misfortunes nor had he come into Europe with any hostile intent against the
                        Romans. After the defeat of Lysimachus all that belonged to him passed by
                        the right of war to Seleucus, and therefore he counted it part of his
                        dominion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Ptolemy, and after him Philip,
                        alienated some of these places at a time when his (Antiochus') ancestors
                        were devoting their care and attention to other matters. Could there be a
                        shadow of doubt that the Chersonese and that part of Thrace which lies round
                        Lysimachia once belonged to Lysimachus? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To
                        recover the ancient right over these was the object of his coming and also
                        to rebuild from its foundations the city of Lysimachia, which had been
                        destroyed by the Thracians, in order that his son Seleucus might have it as
                        the seat of empire. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this discussion had been going on
                        for some days, an unauthenticated rumour reached them that Ptolemy was dead.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This prevented any decision from being
                        arrived at; both parties pretended that they had heard nothing about it, and
                        L. Cornelius, whose mission extended to both Antiochus and Ptolemy, asked
                        for a short adjournment to allow of his obtaining an interview with Ptolemy.
                        His object was to land in Egypt before the new occupant of the throne could
                        initiate any change of policy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Antiochus,
                        on the other hand, felt certain that if he took possession of Egypt at once
                        it would be his own, and so, taking his leave of the Roman commissioners and
                        leaving <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> his son to complete the
                        restoration of Lysimachia, he sailed with the whole of his fleet to Ephesus.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From there he despatched envoys to
                        Quinctius to lull his suspicion and to assure him that he was not
                        contemplating any new departure. Coasting along the Asiatic shores he
                        reached Patarae in Lycia and there he learnt that Ptolemy was alive. He now
                        abandoned all intention of sailing to Egypt, but continued his voyage as far
                        as Cyprus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When he had rounded the
                        promontory of Chelidoniae he was for some time delayed in Pamphylia near the
                        river Eurymedon by a mutiny amongst the crews. After continuing his voyage
                        as far as the co-called "heads" of the river Saros he was overtaken by a
                        terrible storm which engulfed nearly the whole of his fleet. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Many of the ships were wrecked, many ran aground,
                        a large number foundered so suddenly that none could swim to land. There was
                        a very great loss of life; not only nameless crowds of sailors and soldiers,
                        but many distinguished men, friends of the king, were amongst the victims.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Antiochus collected the remains of his
                        shattered fleet, but as he was in no condition to make an attempt on Cyprus
                        he returned to Seleucia, much poorer in men and material resources than when
                        he started on his expedition. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Here he had
                        the ships beached, for winter was close at hand, after which he went to
                        Antioch for the winter. Such was the position of affairs with regard to the
                        two monarchs. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year for the first time three
                        epulones were appointed, namely C. Licinius Lucullus, one of the tribunes of
                        the plebs who had got the law passed under which they were appointed, and
                        with him P. Manlius and P. Portius Laeca. They were allowed by law to wear
                        the toga praetexta like the priests. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But a
                        serious dispute broke out this year between the whole body of priests and
                        the City quaestors, Q. Fabius Labeo and P. Aurelius. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The senate had decided that the last repayment of the
                        money subscribed for the Punic War should be made to those who had
                        contributed and money was needed for the purpose. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> As the augurs and pontiffs had not made any
                        contribution during the war, the quaestors demanded payment from them.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They appealed in vain to the tribunes
                        of the plebs, and were compelled to pay their quota for every year of the
                        war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Two pontiffs died during the year;
                        they were succeeded by the consul, M. Marcellus, in place of C. Sempronius
                        Tuditanus, who had died while acting as praetor in Spain, and L. Valerius
                        Flaccus in place of M. Cornelius Cethegus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        The augur Q. Fabius Maximus also died while quite young, before he could
                        hold any magistracy; no successor was appointed during the year. </p>
                    <p> The consular elections were conducted by M. Marcellus; the new consuls were
                        L. Valerius Flaccus and M. Porcius Cato. The praetors elected were Cn.
                        Manlius Volso, Ap. Claudius Nero P. Porcius Laeca, C. Fabricius Luscinus, C.
                        Atinius Labeo and P. Manlius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The curule
                        aediles, M. Fulvius Nobilior and C. Flaminius, sold during the year a
                        million modii of wheat to the people at two ases the modius. This wheat was
                        sent by the Sicilians out of regard to C. Flaminius and in honour of his
                        father's memory. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Roman Games were
                        celebrated with great splendour and repeated on three different days. The
                        plebeian aediles, Cn. Domitius Ahenobarbus and C. Scribonius Curio, brought
                        several farmers of State lands before the popular tribunal; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> three of these were convicted, and out of the
                        fines imposed they built a temple to Faunus on the Island. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The Plebeian Games lasted two days and there was the
                        usual banquet. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On March 15, the day when they entered
                        upon office, the new consuls consulted the senate as to the allocation of
                        provinces. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate decided that since
                        the war in Spain was spreading to such a serious extent as to require the
                        presence of a consul and a consular army, Hither Spain should be one of the
                        two consular provinces. The consuls were instructed to come to a mutual
                        arrangement or else ballot for that province and Italy. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Whichever of them drew Spain was to take with him two
                        legions, 15,000 allied infantry and 800 cavalry and a fleet of 20 ships of
                        war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The other consul was to raise two
                        legions; that was looked upon as sufficient to hold Gaul after the crushing
                        blow dealt to the Insubres and the Boii the previous year. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Cato drew Spain, Valerius Italy. The praetors now
                        balloted for their provinces. C. Fabricius Luscinus received the City
                        jurisdiction; C. Atinius Labeo the jurisdiction over aliens; Cn. Manlius
                        Volso, Sicily; Ap. Claudius Nero, Further Spain; P. Porcius Laeca, Pisae, in
                        order to threaten the Ligurians from the rear. P. Manlius was assigned to
                        the consul to assist him in Hither Spain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Owing to the suspicious attitude of Antiochus and of the Aetolians, and also
                        of Nabis and the Lacedaemonians, T. Quinctius was continued in his command
                        with the two legions he had had before. Any reinforcements required to bring
                        them up to full strength were to be raised by the consuls and despatched to
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In addition to the legion which
                        Q. Fabius had had, Appius Claudius was authorised to raise 2000 infantry and
                        200 cavalry. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The same number of infantry
                        and cavalry were assigned to P. Manlius for employment in Hither Spain as
                        well as the legion which had served under the praetor Q. Minucius.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Out of the army in Gaul 10,000
                        infantry and 500 cavalry were decreed to P. Portius Laeca to operate in
                        Etruria round Pisae. Tiberius Sempronius Longus had his command in Sardinia
                        extended. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such was the distribution of the
                        provinces. Before the consuls left the City they were required, in
                        accordance with a decree of the pontiffs, to proclaim a Sacred Spring.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was in fulfilment of a vow made
                        by the praetor A. Cornelius Mammula at the desire of the senate and by order
                        of the people twenty-one years previously in the consulship of Cn. Servilius
                        and C. Flaminius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> C. Claudius Pulcher, the
                        son of Appius, was at the same time appointed augur in place of Q. Fabius
                        Maximus, who had died the year before. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Whilst general surprise was felt that nothing was being done about the war
                        which had broken out in Spain, a despatch arrived from Q. Minucius
                        announcing that he had successfully engaged the Spanish generals Budar and
                        Baesadines, and that the enemy had lost 12,000 men, Budar being made
                        prisoner and the rest routed and put to flight. When the despatch was read
                        less apprehension was felt about the two Spains, where a very serious war
                        had been anticipated. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The general anxiety
                        now centered on Antiochus, especially after the return of the ten
                        commissioners. After giving their report on the negotiations with Philip and
                        the terms on which peace had been made with him, they made it evident that a
                        war on at least as great a scale with Antiochus was imminent. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> He had, so they informed the senate, landed in
                        Europe with an enormous fleet and a splendid army, and if his attention had
                        not been diverted by a groundless hope based upon a still more groundless
                        rumour, to the invasion of Egypt, Greece would very soon have been in the
                        blaze of war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Even the Aetolians, a nation
                        naturally restless and now intensely embittered against the Romans, would no
                        longer remain quiet. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And there was another
                        most formidable mischief with its roots in the very vitals of Greece-Nabis,
                        who was for the time being tyrant of Lacedaemon, but who if he were allowed
                        would soon become tyrant of the whole of Greece, a man who in greed and
                        brutality rivalled the most notorious tyrants in history. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> If, after the Roman armies had been carried back to
                        Italy, he were allowed to hold Argos as a stronghold threatening the whole
                        of the Peloponnese, the deliverance of Greece from Philip would have been
                        effected in vain; in any case instead of a distant monarch as their lord
                        they would have a tyrant at their doors. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After listening to these statements made
                        by men of such weight and judgment, who, moreover, had made their report
                        after personal investigation, the senate were <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> of opinion that though the policy to be pursued towards
                        Antiochus was the more important question before them, still, as the king,
                        whatever his reason might be, had retired into Syria, it seemed better to
                        consider first what to do about the tyrant. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> After a lengthy discussion as to whether there were sufficient grounds
                        for a formal declaration of war or whether it would be enough to leave it to
                        T. Quinctius to act, as far as Nabis was concerned, in whatever way he
                        thought best in the interests of the State, the matter was finally left in
                        his hands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whether they took prompt steps
                        or whether they delayed action it did not seem to them to be of vital
                        importance to the commonwealth. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A much
                        more pressing question was what Hannibal and Carthage were likely to do in
                        case of war with Antiochus. The members of the party opposed to Hannibal
                        were constantly writing to their friends in Rome. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> According to their account, messengers and letters were
                        being sent by Hannibal to Antiochus and emissaries from the king were
                        holding secret conferences with him. Just as there were wild beasts which no
                        skill could tame, so this man was untamable and implacable. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He complained that his countrymen were becoming
                        enervated through ease and self-indulgence, and slumbering in indolence and
                        sloth, and said that nothing could rouse them but the clash of arms.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> People were all the more ready to
                        believe these assertions when they remembered that it was this man who was
                        responsible for the beginning quite as much as for the conduct of the late
                        war. His recent action had also called forth strong resentment amongst many
                        of the magnates. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The order of judges exercised supreme
                        power in Carthage at that time, owing mainly to the fact that they held
                        office for life. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The property, reputation
                        and life of everyone were in their power. Whoever offended one of the order
                        had an enemy in every member, and when the judges were hostile there was
                        always a prosecutor to be found amongst them. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Whilst these men were exercising this unbridled
                        despotism, for they used their power without any regard to the rights of
                        their fellow-citizens, Hannibal, who had been appointed one of the presiding
                        magistrates, ordered the quaestor to be summoned before him. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The quaestor paid no attention to the summons; he
                        belonged to the opposite party and, moreover, as the quaestors were
                        generally advanced to the all-powerful order of judges he gave himself the
                        airs of a man who was sure of promotion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Resenting this indignity Hannibal sent an officer to arrest the quaestor,
                        and after he was brought into the assembly Hannibal denounced not only the
                        quaestor but the whole of the judicial order, whose insolence and excessive
                        power utterly subverted the laws and the authority of the magistrates who
                        had to enforce them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When he saw that his
                        words were making a favourable impression and that the insolence and tyranny
                        of that order were recognised as dangerous to the liberty of the meanest
                        citizen, he at once proposed and carried a law enacting that the judges
                        should be elected annually and that none should hold office for two
                        consecutive years. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whatever popularity,
                        however, he gained amongst the masses by his action was counterbalanced by
                        the offence given to a large number of the aristocracy. A further step which
                        he took in the public interest aroused intense hostility to him personally.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The public revenues were being
                        frittered away, partly through careless management and partly through being
                        fraudulently appropriated by some of the political leaders and superior
                        magistrates. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The result was that there was
                        not money enough to meet the annual payment of the indemnity to Rome, and
                        there seemed every likelihood of a heavy tax being imposed upon the
                        individual citizens. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="47" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal had informed himself as to
                        the amount of the national income from all sources, the objects for which
                        calls upon it were made, what proportion was absorbed by the regular needs
                        of the State and <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> how much had been
                        embezzled, he stated publicly in the assembly that if the balance were
                        called up the government would be rich enough to meet the demands of Rome
                        without any tax falling on individual citizens. And he was as good as his
                        word. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Those who had for years been
                        battening on their pilferings from the national treasury were as furious as
                        if it was the seizure of their personal property and not the forcible
                        recovery of what they had stolen that was contemplated. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> In their rage they began to urge on the Romans, who
                        were on their own account looking out for an opportunity of visiting their
                        hate upon him. For a long time this policy found an opponent in P. Scipio
                        Africanus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He considered it quite beneath
                        the dignity of the Roman people to support the attacks of Hannibal's
                        accusers or to allow the authority of the government to be mixed up with the
                        party politics of Carthage, or not content with having defeated Hannibal in
                        open war to treat him as though he were a criminal against whom they were to
                        appear as prosecutors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At last, however,
                        his opponents carried their point and delegates were sent to Carthage to
                        point out to the senate there that Hannibal was concerting plans with
                        Antiochus for commencing war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Cn.
                        Servilius, M. Claudius Marcellus and Q. Terentius Culleo formed the
                        delegation. On their arrival in Carthage they were advised by Hannibal's
                        enemies to give out that people who asked the reason of their coming
                            <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> should be told that they had come to
                        adjust the differences between Masinissa and the government of Carthage.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This explanation was generally
                        believed. Hannibal alone was not deceived, he knew that he was the object at
                        which the Romans were aiming, and that the underlying motive of the peace
                        with Carthage was that he might be left as the sole victim of their undying
                        hostility. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He decided to bow before the
                        storm, and after making every preparation for flight he showed himself
                        during the day in the forum to allay suspicion and as soon as it was dark he
                        went in his official dress to the gate, accompanied by two attendants who
                        were unaware of his design. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="48" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the horses which he had ordered were
                        ready, he rode during the night to Byzacium-the name of a country
                        district-and the next day reached his castle on the coast between Acylla and
                        Thapsus. There a ship was awaiting him, prepared for immediate departure.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was in this way that Hannibal
                        withdrew from Africa, the country for whose misfortunes he had felt much
                        more pity than for his own. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That same day
                        he landed in the island of Cercina. Here he found some Phoenician merchant
                        ships lying in the harbour, and on his leaving his vessel there was a
                        general rush to greet him. In reply to inquiries he gave out that he was on
                        a mission to Tyre. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fearing, however, that
                        one or other of these ships might leave in the night for Thapsus or
                        Hadrumetum and report his appearance in Cercina, he ordered preparations for
                        a sacrifice to be prepared and the ships' captains to be invited to the
                        solemnity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He also gave directions for the
                        sails and yards to be collected from the ships that they might serve as
                        awnings to shade them at their feast, as it happened to be the middle of the
                        summer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The entertainment was as sumptuous
                        as time and circumstances permitted, and the conviviality was prolonged far
                        into the night, much wine being consumed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        As soon as he had an opportunity of escaping the observation of those in the
                        harbour Hannibal set sail. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The rest were
                        all asleep and it was not till late the next day that they rose from their
                        torpor, stupid with the effects of intoxication, and then had to spend
                        several hours in getting the tackle of their vessels back into its place. At
                        Hannibal's house in Carthage the usual crowd had collected in large numbers
                        in the vestibule. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When it became generally
                        known that he was not to be found, the <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                        crowd surged into the forum demanding the appearance of their foremost
                        citizen. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Some, guessing the truth,
                        suggested that he had fled, others-and these were the loudest and most
                        numerous-said that he had been put to death through Roman treachery, and you
                        might note the different expressions in their faces, as would be expected in
                        a city torn by violent political partisanship. Then came the news that he
                        had been seen in Cercina. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="49" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman delegates informed the council
                        of Carthage that the senate had definitely ascertained that it was mainly at
                        Hannibal's instigation that Philip had made war on Rome, and now letters and
                        messengers were being despatched to Antiochus and the Aetolians, and plans
                        had been formed for driving Carthage into revolt. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> It was to Antiochus that he had gone, and nowhere else,
                        and he would never rest until he had stirred up war throughout the whole
                        world. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> If the Carthaginians wanted to
                        satisfy the Roman people that none of his proceedings was in accordance with
                        their wishes or sanctioned by their government, they must see that he did
                        not go unpunished. The Carthaginians replied that they would do whatever the
                        Romans thought right. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After a fair voyage
                        Hannibal reached Tyre, and the founders of Carthage welcomed as from a
                        second fatherland the man who had achieved every possible distinction.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After a short stay here he continued
                        his voyage to Antiochia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here he heard
                        that the king had left for Asia, and he had an interview with his son, who
                        was at the time celebrating the Games at Daphne, and who gave him a most
                        friendly welcome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Anxious to lose no time
                        he at once resumed his voyage and found the king at Ephesus, still unable to
                        make up his mind on the question of war with Rome. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Hannibal's arrival was not the least important factor
                        in bringing him to a decision. The Aetolians, too, were now growing averse
                        from their alliance with Rome. They had sent a mission to Rome to demand the
                        restitution of Pharsalus, Leucas and certain other cities under the terms of
                        the former treaty, and the senate referred them to Quinctius. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
