<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to thirty-six -
                    33</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books twenty-seven to
                                thirty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">3</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XXXIII.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Titus Quinctius Flamininus, proconsul, gains a decisive victory over Philip
                        at Cynoscephalae. Caius Sempronius Tuditanus, praetor, cut off by the
                        Celtiberians. Death of Attalus, at Pergamus. Peace granted to Philip, and
                        liberty to Greece. Lucius Furius Purpureo and Marcus Claudius Marcellus,
                        consuls, subdue the Boian and Insubrian Gauls. Triumph of Marcellus.
                        Hannibal, alarmed at an embassy from Rome concerning him, flies to
                        Antiochus, king of Syria, who was preparing to make war on the Romans. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> SUCH were the occurrences of the winter. In
                    the beginning of spring, Quinctius, having summoned Attalus to Elatia, and being
                    anxious to bring under his authority the nation of the Bœotians, who had until
                    then been wavering in their dispositions, marched through Phocis, and pitched
                    his camp at the distance of five miles from Thebes, the capital of Bœotia.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Next day, attended by one company of
                    soldiers, and by Attalus, together with the ambassadors, who had come to him in
                    great numbers from all quarters, he proceeded towards the city, having ordered
                    the spearmen of two legions, being <pb n="1441" xml:id="p.1441"/> two thousand
                    men, to follow him at the distance of a mile. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    About midway, Antiphilus, praetor of the Bœotians, met him: the rest of the
                    people stood on the walls, watching the arrival of the king and the Roman
                    general. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Few arms and few soldiers appeared
                    around them —the hollow roads, and the valleys, concealing from view the
                    spearmen, who followed at a distance. When Quinctius drew near the city, he
                    slackened his pace, as if with intention to salute the multitude, who came out
                    to meet him; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> but the real motive of his
                    delaying was, that the spearmen might come up. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The townsmen pushed forward, in a crowd, before the lictors, not perceiving the
                    band of soldiers who were following them close, until they arrived at the
                    general's quarters. Then, supposing the city betrayed and taken, through the
                    treachery of Antiphilus, their praetor, they were all struck with astonishment
                    and dismay. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It was now evident that no room
                    was left to the Bœotians for a free discussion of measures in the assembly,
                    which was summoned for the following day. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    However, they concealed their grief, which it would have been both vain and
                    unsafe to have discovered. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the assembly met, Attalus first rose to
                    speak, and he began his discourse with a recital of the kindnesses conferred by
                    his ancestors and himself on the Greeks in general, and on the Bœotians in
                    particular. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But, being now too old and infirm
                    to bear the exertion of speaking in public, he lost his voice and fell;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and for some time, while they were
                    carrying him to his apartments, (for he was deprived of the use of one half of
                    his limbs,) the proceedings of the assembly were for a short time suspended.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then Aristaenus spoke on the part of the
                    Achaeans, and was listened to with the greater attention, because he recommended
                    to the Bœotians no other measures than those which he had recommended to the
                    Achaeans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A few words were added by Quinctius,
                    extolling the good faith rather than the arms and power of the Romans.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A resolution was then proposed, by
                    Dicaearchus of Plataea, for forming a treaty of friendship with the Roman
                    people, which was read; and no one daring to offer any opposition, it was
                    received and passed by the suffrages of all the states of Bœotia. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When the assembly broke up, Quinctius made no longer
                    stay at Thebes than the sudden accident to Attalus made necessary. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> When it appeared that the force of the disorder had
                    not <pb n="1442" xml:id="p.1442"/> brought the king's life into any immediate
                    danger, but had only occasioned a weakness in his limbs, he left him there, to
                    use the necessary means for recovery, and returned to Elatia, from whence he had
                    come. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having now brought the Bœotians, as
                    formerly the Achaeans, to join in the confederacy, while all places were left
                    behind him in a state of tranquillity and safety, he bent his whole attention
                    towards Philip, and the remaining business of the war. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, on his part, as his ambassadors had
                    brought no hopes of peace <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> from Rome,
                    resolved, as soon as spring began, to levy soldiers through every town in his
                    dominions: but he found a great scarcity of young men; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> for successive wars, through several generations, had very
                    much exhausted the Macedonians, and, even in the course of his own reign, great
                    numbers had fallen, in the <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> naval engagements
                    with the Rhodians and Attalus, and in those on land with the Romans. Mere
                    youths, therefore, from the age of sixteen, were enlisted; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and even those who had served out their time, provided they
                    had any remains of strength, were recalled to their standards. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Having, by these means, filled up the numbers of his army
                    about the vernal equinox, he drew together all his forces to Dius: he encamped
                    them there in a fixed post; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and, exercising
                    the soldiers every day, waited for the enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    About the same time Quinctius left Elatia, and came by Thronium and Scarphea to
                    Thermopylae. There he held an assembly of the Aetolians, which had been summoned
                    to meet at Heraclea, to determine with what number of auxiliaries they should
                    follow the Roman general to the war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On the
                    third day, having learned the determination of the allies, he proceeded from
                    Heraclea to Xyniae; and, pitching his camp on the confines between the Aenians
                    and Thessalians, waited for the Aetolian auxiliaries. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The Aetolians occasioned no delay. Six hundred foot and
                    four hundred horse, under the command of Phaeneas, speedily joined him; and then
                    Quinctius, to show plainly what he had waited for, immediately decamped.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On passing into the country of Phthiotis,
                    he was joined by five hundred <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> Cretans of
                    Gortynium, whose commander was Cydantes, with three hundred Apollonians, armed
                    nearly in the same manner; and not long after, by Amynander, with one thousand
                    two hundred Athamanian foot. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, being informed of the departure of the
                    Romans <pb n="1443" xml:id="p.1443"/> from Elatia, and considering that, on the
                    approaching contest, his kingdom was at hazard, thought it advisable to make an
                    encouraging speech to his soldiers; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> in which,
                    after he had expatiated on many topics often alluded to before, respecting the
                    virtues of their ancestors, and the military fame of the Macedonians, he touched
                    particularly on those considerations which at the time threw the greatest damp
                    on their spirits, and on those by which they might be animated to some degree of
                    confidence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To the defeat thrice suffered at
                    the narrow passes near the river Aous, by the phalanx of the Macedonians, he
                    opposed the repulse given by main force to the Romans at Atrax: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and even with respect to the former case, when they had not
                    maintained possession of the pass leading into Epirus, he said, <quote> the
                        first fault was to be imputed to those who had been negligent in keeping the
                        guards; and the second, to the light infantry and mercenaries in the time of
                        the engagement; but that, as to the phalanx of the Macedonians, it had stood
                        firm on that occasion; and would for ever remain invincible, on equal
                        ground, and in regular fight. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This body consisted of sixteen thousand men,
                    the prime strength of the army, and of the kingdom. Besides these, he had two
                    thousand targeteers, called Peltastae; of Thracians, and Illyrians of the tribe
                    called Trallians, the like number of two thousand; and of hired auxiliaries,
                    collected out of various nations, about one thousand; and two thousand horse.
                    With this force the king waited for the enemy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans had nearly an equal number; in cavalry alone they had a superiority,
                    by the addition of the Aetolians. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius, having decamped to Thebes in
                    Phthiotis, and having received encouragement to hope that the city would be
                    betrayed to him by Timon, a leading man in the state, came up close to the walls
                    with only a small number of cavalry and some light infantry. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> So entirely were his expectations disappointed, that he was
                    not only obliged to maintain a fight with the enemy who sallied out against him,
                    but would have incurred a fearful conflict had not both infantry <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> and cavalry been called out hastily from the camp,
                    and come up in time. Not meeting with that success which he had too
                    inconsiderately expected, he desisted from any further attempt to take the city
                    at present. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had received certain
                    information of the king being in Thessaly; but as he had not <pb n="1444"
                        xml:id="p.1444"/> yet discovered into what part of it he had come, he sent
                    his soldiers round the country, with orders to cut timber and prepare palisades.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both Macedonians and Greeks had palisades;
                    but the latter had not adopted the most convenient mode of using them, either
                    with respect to carriage, or for the purpose of strengthening their
                    fortifications. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They cut trees both too large
                    and too full of branches for a soldier to carry easily along with his arms: and
                    after they had fenced their camp with a line of these, the demolition of their
                    palisade was no difficult matter; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for the
                    trunks of large trees appearing to view, with great intervals between them, and
                    the numerous and strong shoots affording the hand a good hold, two, or at most
                    three young men, uniting their efforts, used to pull out one tree, which, being
                    removed, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> a breach was opened as wide as a
                    gate, and there was nothing at hand with which it could be stopped up.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the Romans cut light stakes, mostly of
                    one fork, with three, or at the most four branches; so that a soldier, with his
                    arms slung at his back, can conveniently carry several of them together;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and then they stick them down so closely,
                    and interweave the branches in such a manner, that it cannot be seen to what
                    main stem any branch belongs; besides which, the boughs are so sharp, and
                    wrought so intimately with each other, as to leave no room for a hand to be
                    thrust between; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> consequently an enemy cannot
                    lay hold of any thing capable of being dragged out, or, if that could be done,
                    could he draw out the branches thus intertwined, and which mutually bind each
                    other. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And even if, by accident, one should
                    be pulled out, it leaves but a small opening, which is very easily filled up. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Next day Quinctius, causing his men to carry
                    palisades with them, that they might be ready to encamp on any spot, marched
                    forward a short way, and took post about six miles from Pherae; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> whence he sent scouts to discover in what part of Thessaly
                    the king was, and what appeared to be his intention. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Philip was then near Larissa, and as soon as he learned
                    that the Roman general had removed from Thebes, being equally impatient for a
                    decisive engagement, he proceeded towards the enemy, and pitched his camp about
                    four miles from Pherae. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the day following,
                    some light troops went out from both camps, to seize on certain hills, which
                    overlooked the city. When, nearly at equal distance from the <pb n="1445"
                        xml:id="p.1445"/> summit which was intended to be seized, they came within
                    sight of each other, they halted; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and sending
                    messengers to their respective camps for directions, how they were to proceed on
                    this unexpected meeting with the enemy, waited their return in quiet. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> For that day, they were recalled to their camps,
                    without having commenced any engagement. On the following day, there was a
                    battle between the cavalry, near the same hills, in which the Aetolians bore no
                    small part; and in which the king's troops were defeated, and driven into their
                    camp. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Both parties were greatly impeded in the
                    action, by the ground being thickly planted with trees; by the gardens, of which
                    there were many in a place so near the city; and by the roads being enclosed
                    between walls, and in some places shut up. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    commanders, therefore, were equally desirous of removing out of that quarter;
                    and, as if by a preconcerted scheme, they both directed their route to Scotussa:
                    Philip with the hope of getting a supply of corn there; the Roman intending to
                    get before the enemy and destroy the crops. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The armies marched the whole day without having sight of each other in any
                    place, the view being intercepted by a continued range of hills between them.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Romans encamped at Eretria, in
                    Phthiotis; Philip, on the river Onchestus. But though Philip lay at Melambius,
                    in the territory of Scotussa, and Quinctius near Thetidium, in Pharsalia,
                    neither party knew with any certainty where his antagonist was. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> On the third day, there first fell a violent rain,
                    which was succeeded by darkness equal to that of night, and this confined the
                    Romans to <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> their camp, through fear of an
                    ambuscade. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, intent on hastening his march, and in
                    no degree deterred by the clouds, which after the rain lowered over the face of
                    the country, ordered his troops to march: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and
                    yet so thick a fog had obscured the day, that neither the standard-bearers could
                    see the road, nor the soldiers the standards; so that all, led blindly by the
                    shouts of uncertain guides, fell into disorder, like men wandering by night.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When they had passed over the hills called
                    Cynoscephalae, where they left a strong guard of foot and horse, they pitched
                    their camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Although the Roman general staid
                    at Thetidium, yet he detached ten troops of horse and one thousand foot, to find
                    out where the enemy lay; warning them, however, to beware of ambuscades, which
                    the darkness of the day would cover, even <pb n="1446" xml:id="p.1446"/> in an
                    open country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When these arrived at the hills,
                    where the enemy's guard was posted, struck with mutual fear, both parties stood,
                    as if deprived of the power of motion. They then sent back messengers to their
                    respective commanders; and when the first surprise subsided, they proceeded to
                    action without more delay. The fight was begun by small advanced parties; and
                    afterwards the numbers of the combatants were increased by reinforcements of
                    men, who supported those who gave way. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In this
                    contest the Romans, being far inferior to their adversaries, sent message after
                    message to the general, that they were being overpowered; on which he hastily
                    sent five hundred horse and two thousand foot, mostly Aetolians, under the
                    command of two military tribunes, who relieved them, and restored the fight.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Macedonians, distressed in turn by
                    this change of fortune, sent to beg succour from their king; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> but as, on account of the general darkness from the fog, he
                    had expected nothing less, on that day, than a battle, and had therefore sent a
                    great number of men, of every kind, to forage, he was, for a considerable time,
                    in great perplexity, and unable to form a resolution. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Subsequently, as the messengers still continued to urge
                    him, and the covering of clouds was now removed from the tops of the mountains,
                    and the Macedonian party was in view, having been driven up to the highest
                    summit, and trusting for safety rather to the nature of the ground than to their
                    arms, he thought it necessary, at all events, to <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> hazard the whole, in order to prevent the loss of a part,
                    for want of support; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and, accordingly, he
                    sent up Athenagoras, general of the mercenary soldiers, with all the
                    auxiliaries, except the Thracians, joined by the Macedonian and Thessalian
                    cavalry. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On their arrival, the Romans were
                    forced from the top of the hill, and did not face about until they came to the
                    level plain. The principal support which saved them from being driven down in
                    disorderly flight, was the Aetolian horsemen. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The Aetolians were then by far the best cavalry in Greece; in infantry, they
                    were surpassed by some of their neighbours. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This affair was represented as more successful
                    than the advantage gained in the battle could warrant; for people came, one
                    after another, and calling out that the Romans were flying in a panic;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> so that, though reluctant and hesitating,
                    declaring it a rash proceeding, and that he liked not either the <pb n="1447"
                        xml:id="p.1447"/> place or the time, yet he was prevailed upon to draw out
                    his whole force to battle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman general
                    did the same, induced by necessity, rather than by the favourableness of the
                    occasion. Leaving the right wing as a reserve, having the elephants posted in
                    front, he, with the left, and all the right infantry, advanced against the
                    enemy; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> at the same time reminding his men,
                    that <quote> they were going to fight the same Macedonians whom they had fought
                        in the passes of Epirus, fenced, as they were, with mountains and rivers,
                        and whom, after conquering the natural difficulties of the ground, they had
                        dislodged and vanquished; the same, whom they had before defeated under the
                        command of Publius Sulpicius, when they opposed their passage to Eordaea.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> That the kingdom of Macedonia had been
                        hitherto supported by its reputation, not by real strength; and that even
                        that reputation had, at length, vanished. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Quinctius soon reached his troops, who stood
                    in the bottom of the valley; and they, on the arrival of their general and the
                    army, renewed the fight, and, making a vigorous onset, compelled the enemy again
                    to turn their backs. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Philip, with the
                    targeteers, and the right wing of infantry, (the main strength of the Macedonian
                    army, called by them the phalanx,) advanced at a quick pace, having ordered
                    Nicanor, one of his courtiers, to bring up the rest of his forces with all
                    speed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At first, on reaching the top of the
                    hill, from a few arms and bodies lying there, he perceived that there had been
                    an engagement on the spot, and that the Romans had been repulsed from it.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When he likewise saw the fight now going
                    on close to the enemy's works, he was elated with excessive delight; <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> but presently, observing his men flying back, and
                    that the panic was on the other side, he was much embarrassed, and hesitated for
                    some time, whether he should cause his troops to retire into the camp.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then, as the enemy approached, he was
                    sensible that his party, besides the losses which they suffered as they fled,
                    must be entirely lost, if not speedily succoured; and as, by this time, even a
                    retreat would be unsafe, he found himself compelled to put all to hazard, before
                    he was joined by the other division of his forces. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> He placed the cavalry and light infantry that had been
                    engaged, on the right wing; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and ordered the
                    targeteers, and the phalanx of Macedonians, to lay aside their spears, which
                    their great length rendered unserviceable, and <pb n="1448" xml:id="p.1448"/> to
                    manage the business with their swords: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> at the
                    same time, that his line might not be easily broken, he lessened the extent of
                    the front one half, and doubled the files within so that it might be deeper than
                    it was broad. He ordered them also to close their files, so that man might join
                    with man and arms with arms. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius, having received among the standards
                    and ranks those who had been engaged with the enemy, gave the signal by sound of
                    trumpet. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It is said, that such a shout was
                    raised, as was seldom heard at the beginning of any battle; for it happened,
                    that both armies shouted at once; not only the troops then engaged, but also the
                    reserves, and those who were just then coming into the field. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The king, fighting from the higher ground, had the better
                    on the right wing, by means chiefly of the advantage of situation. On the left,
                    all was disorder and confusion; particularly when that division of the phalanx,
                    which had marched in the rear, was coming up. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The centre stood intent on the fight as on a spectacle which in no way concerned
                    them. The phalanx, just arrived, (a column rather than a line of battle, and
                    fitter for a march than for a fight,) had scarcely mounted the top of the hill:
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> before these could form, Quinctius, though
                    he saw his men in the left wing giving <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> way,
                    charged the enemy furiously, first driving on the elephants against them, for he
                    judged that one part being routed would draw the rest after. The affair was no
                    longer doubtful. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Macedonians, repelled by
                    the first shock of the elephants, instantly turned their backs; and the rest, as
                    had been foreseen, followed them in their retreat. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Then, one of the military tribunes, forming his design in
                    the instant, took with him twenty companies of men; left that part of the army
                    which was evidently victorious; and making a small circuit, fell on the rear of
                    the enemy's right wing. Any army whatever, thus charged from the rear, must have
                    been thrown into confusion. But to that confusion which under such circumstances
                    would be common to all armies, there was in this case an additional cause.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The phalanx of the Macedonians, being
                    heavy, could not readily face about; nor would they have been suffered to do it
                    by their adversaries in front, who, although they gave way to them a little
                    before, on this new occasion pressed them vigorously. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Besides, they lay under another inconvenience in respect of
                    the ground; for, by <pb n="1449" xml:id="p.1449"/> pursuing the retreating enemy
                    down the face of the hill, they had left the top to the party who came round on
                    their rear. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thus attacked on both sides, they
                    were exposed for some time to great slaughter, and then betook themselves to
                    flight, most of them throwing away their arms. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip, with a small party of horse and foot,
                    ascended a hill somewhat higher than the rest, to take a view of the situation
                    of his troops on the left. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then, when he saw
                    them flying in confusion, and all the hills around glittering with Roman
                    standards and arms, he withdrew from the field. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Quinctius, as he was pressing on the retreating enemy, observed the
                    Macedonians suddenly raising up their spears, and not knowing what they meant
                    thereby, he ordered the troops to halt. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then,
                    on being told that this was the practice of the Macedonians when surrendering
                    themselves prisoners, he was disposed to spare the vanquished; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> but the troops, not being apprized, either of the enemy
                    having ceased fighting, or of the general's intention, made a charge on them,
                    and the foremost having been cut down, the rest dispersed themselves and fled.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philip hastened in disorderly flight to
                    Tempè, and there halted one day at Gonni, to pick up any who might have survived
                    the battle. The victorious Romans rushed into the Macedonian camp with hopes of
                    spoil, but found it, for the most part, plundered already by the Aetolians.
                    Eight thousand of the enemy were killed on that day, five thousand taken.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of the victors, about seven hundred fell.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If any credit is to be attached to
                    Valerius Antias, who on every occasion exaggerates numbers enormously, the
                    killed of the enemy on that day amounted to forty thousand; the prisoners taken,
                    (in which article the deviation from truth is less extravagant,) to five
                    thousand seven hundred, with two hundred and forty-nine military standards.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Claudius also asserts that thirty-two
                    thousand of the enemy were slain, and four thousand three hundred taken.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> We have not given entire credit, even to
                    the smallest of those numbers, but have followed Polybius, a safe authority with
                    respect to all the Roman affairs, but especially those which were transacted in
                    Greece. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip having collected, after the flight,
                    such as, having been scattered by the various chances of the battle, had
                    followed his steps, and having sent people to Larissa to burn <pb n="1450"
                        xml:id="p.1450"/> the records of the kingdom, lest they should fall into the
                    hands of the enemy, retired into Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Quinctius set up to sale a part of the prisoners and booty, and part he bestowed
                    on the soldiers; and then proceeded to Larissa, without having yet received any
                    certain intelligence to what quarter Philip had betaken himself, or what were
                    his designs. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To this place came a herald from
                    the king, apparently to obtain a truce, until those who had fallen in battle
                    should be removed and buried, but in reality to request permission to send
                    ambassadors. Both were obtained from the Roman general; who, besides, added this
                    message to the king, <quote>not to be too much dejected.</quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This expression gave much offence,
                    particularly to the Aetolians, who were become very assuming, and who
                    complained, that <quote> the general was quite altered by success. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Before the battle, he was accustomed to transact
                        all business, whether great or small, in concert with the allies; but they
                        had, now, no share in any of his counsels; he conducted all affairs entirely
                        by his own judgment; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and was even seeking
                        an occasion of ingratiating himself personally with Philip, in order that,
                        after the Aetolians had laboured through all hardships and difficulties of
                        the war, the Roman might assume to himself all the merit and all the fruits
                        of a peace. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Certain it is, that he had treated them with
                    less respect than formerly, but they did not know why they were thus slighted.
                    They imagined that he was actuated by an expectation of presents from the king,
                    though he was of a spirit incapable of yielding to any such passion of the mind;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but he was, with good reason, displeased
                    at the Aetolians, on account of their insatiable greediness for plunder, and of
                    their arrogance in assuming to themselves the honour of the victory —a claim so
                    ill founded, as to offend the ears of all. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, he foresaw that, if Philip were removed out of the way, and the
                    strength of the kingdom of Macedonia entirely broken, the Aetolians would
                    necessarily be regarded as the masters of Greece. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> For these reasons, he intentionally did many things to
                    lessen their importance and reputation in the judgment of the other states. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A truce for fifteen days was granted to the
                    Macedonians, and a conference with the king himself appointed. Before the day
                    arrived on which this was to be held, the Roman general called a council of the
                    allies, and desired their opinions <pb n="1451" xml:id="p.1451"/> respecting the
                    terms of peace, proper to be prescribed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Amynander, king of Athamania, delivered his opinion in a few words; that <quote>
                        the conditions of peace ought to be adjusted in such a manner, as that
                        Greece might have sufficient power, even without the interference of the
                        Romans, to maintain the peace, and also its own liberty. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The address of the Aetolians was more harsh;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> for, after a few introductory observations
                    on the justice and propriety of the Roman general's conduct, in communicating
                    his plans of peace to those who had acted with him as allies in the war, they
                    insisted, that he was utterly mistaken, if he supposed that he could leave the
                    peace with the Romans, or the liberty of Greece, on a permanent footing, unless
                    Philip was either put to death or banished from his kingdom; both which he could
                    easily accomplish, if he chose to pursue his present success." <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Quinctius, in reply, said, that <quote> the Aetolians, in
                        giving such advice, attended not either to the maxims of the Roman policy,
                        or to the consistency of their own conduct. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> For, in all the former councils and conferences, wherein the conditions
                        of peace were discussed, they never once urged the pushing of the war to the
                        utter ruin of the Macedonian: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and, as to
                        the Romans, besides that they had, from the earliest periods, observed the
                        maxim of sparing the vanquished, they had lately given a signal proof of
                        their clemency in the peace granted to Hannibal and the Carthaginians.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But, not to insist on the case of the
                        Carthaginians, how often had the confederates met Philip himself in
                        conference, yet that it had never been urged that he should resign his
                        kingdom: and, because he had been defeated in battle, was that a reason that
                        their animosity should become implacable? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Against an armed foe, men ought to engage with hostile resentment; towards
                        the vanquished, the loftiest spirit was ever the most merciful. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> The kings of Macedonia were thought to be
                        dangerous to the liberty of Greece. Suppose that kingdom and nation
                        extirpated, the Thracians, Illyrians, and in time the Gauls, (nations
                        unsubjugated and savage,) would pour themselves into Macedonia first, and
                        then into Greece. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> That they should not,
                        by removing inconveniences which lay nearest, open a passage to others
                        greater and more grievous. </quote> Here he was interrupted by Phaeneas,
                    praetor of the Aetolians, who solemnly declared, that <quote> if Philip escaped
                        now, he would soon raise a new and more dangerous <pb n="1452"
                            xml:id="p.1452"/> war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On which Quinctius said, — <quote> Cease
                        wrangling, when you ought to deliberate. The king shall be bound down by
                        such conditions as will not leave it in his power to raise a war. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The convention was then adjourned; and next
                    day, the king came to the pass at the entrance of Tempè, the place appointed for
                    a conference; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and the third day following was
                    fixed for introducing him to a full assembly of the Romans and allies.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On this occasion Philip, with great
                    prudence, intentionally avoided the mention of any of those conditions, without
                    which peace could not be obtained, rather than suffer them to be extorted after
                    discussion; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and declared, that he was ready to
                    comply with all the articles which, in the former conference, were either
                    prescribed by the Romans or demanded by the allies; and to leave all other
                    matters to the determination of the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Although he seemed to have hereby precluded every objection, even from the most
                    inveterate of his enemies, yet, all the rest remaining silent, Phaeneas, the
                    Aetolian, said to him, — <quote> What! <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Philip,
                        do you at last restore to us Pharsalus and Larissa, with Cremaste, Echinus,
                        and Thebes in Phthiotis? </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On Philip answering, that <quote>he would give
                        no obstruction to their retaking the possession of them,</quote> a dispute
                    arose between the Roman general and the Aetolians about Thebes; for Quinctius
                    affirmed, that it became the property of the Roman people by the laws of war;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> because when, before the commencement of
                    hostilities, he marched his army thither, and invited the inhabitants to
                    friendship, they, although at full liberty to renounce the king's party, yet
                    preferred an alliance with Philip to one with Rome. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Phaeneas alleged, that, in consideration of their being
                    confederates in the war, it was reasonable, that whatever the Aetolians
                    possessed before it began, should be restored; and that, besides, there was, in
                    the first treaty, a provisional clause of that purport, by which the spoils of
                    war, <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> of every kind that could be carried or
                    driven, were to belong to the Romans; and that the lands and captured cities
                    should fall to the Aetolians. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Yourselves,</quote> replied Quinctius, <quote> annulled the conditions of
                        that treaty, at the time when ye deserted us, and made peace with Philip;
                        but supposing it still remained in force, yet that clause could affect only
                        captured cities. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Now, the states of
                        Thessaly submitted to us by a voluntary act of their own. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> — <pb n="1453" xml:id="p.1453"/> These words
                    were heard by their allies with universal approbation; but to the Aetolians they
                    were both highly displeasing at the present, and proved afterwards the cause of
                    a war, and of many great disasters attending it. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The terms settled with Philip were, that he should give his
                    son Demetrius, and some of his friends, as hostages; should pay two hundred
                    talents; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 38,750 <hi rend="italics"
                            >l.</hi>
                    </note> and send ambassadors to Rome, respecting the other articles: for which
                    purpose there should be a cessation of arms for four months. An engagement was
                    entered into, that, in case the senate should refuse to conclude a treaty, his
                    money and hostages should be returned to Philip. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> It is said, that one of the principal reasons which made
                    the Roman general wish to expedite the conclusion of a peace, was, that he had
                    received certain information of Antiochus intending to commence hostilities, and
                    to pass over into Europe. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time, and, as some writers say,
                    on the same day, the Achaeans defeated Androsthenes, the king's commander, in a
                    general engagement near Corinth. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Philip,
                    intending to use this city as a citadel, to awe the states of Greece, had
                    invited the principal inhabitants to a conference, under pretence of agreeing
                    with them as to the number of horsemen which the Corinthians could supply
                    towards the war, and these he detained as hostages. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Besides the force already there, consisting of five hundred
                    Macedonians and eight hundred auxiliaries of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    various kinds, he had sent thither one thousand Macedonians, one thousand two
                    hundred Illyrians, and of Thracians and Cretans (for these served in both the
                    opposite armies) eight hundred. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To these were
                    added Bœotians, Thessalians, and Acarnanians, to the amount of one thousand, all
                    carrying bucklers; with as many of the young Corinthians themselves, as filled
                    up the number of six thousand men under arms, —a force which inspired
                    Androsthenes with a confident wish to decide the matter in the field. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Nicostratus, praetor of the Achaeans, was at Sicyon,
                    with two thousand foot and one hundred horse; but seeing himself so inferior,
                    both in the number and kind of troops, he did not go outside the walls:
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the king's forces, in various excursions,
                    were ravaging the lands of Pellene, Phliasus, and Cleone. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> At last, reproaching the enemy with cowardice, they passed
                    over into the territory of Sicyon, and, sailing round Achaia, <pb n="1454"
                        xml:id="p.1454"/> laid waste the whole coast. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> As the enemy, while thus employed, spread themselves about
                    too widely and too carelessly, (the usual consequence of too much confidence,)
                    Nicostratus conceived hopes of attacking them by surprise. He therefore sent
                    secret directions to all the neighbouring states, as to what day, and what
                    number from each state, should assemble in arms at Apelaurus, a place in the
                    territory of Stymphalia. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All being in
                    readiness at the time appointed, he marched thence immediately; <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> and, without the knowledge of any one as to what he
                    was contemplating, came by night through the territory of the Phliasians to
                    Cleone. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He had with him five thousand foot,
                    of whom * * * * * * <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In the original,
                        the number is omitted, or lost.</note> were light-armed, and three hundred
                    horse; with this force he waited there, having despatched scouts to watch on
                    what quarter the enemy should make their irregular inroads. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Androsthenes, utterly ignorant of all these
                    proceedings, set out from Corinth, and encamped on the Nemea, a river running
                    between the confines of Corinth and Sicyon. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Here, dismissing one half of his troops, he divided the remainder into three
                    parts, and ordered all the cavalry of each part to march in separate divisions,
                    and ravage, at the same time, the territories of Pellene, Sicyon, and Phlius.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, the three divisions set out
                    by different roads. As soon as Nicostratus received intelligence of this at
                    Cleone, he instantly sent forward a numerous detachment of mercenaries, to seize
                    a pass at the entrance into the territory of Corinth; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and he himself quickly followed, with his troops in two
                    columns, the cavalry proceeding before the head of each, as advanced guards.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In one column marched the mercenary
                    soldiers and light infantry; in the other, the shield-bearers of the Achaeans
                    and other states, who composed the principal strength of the army. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Both infantry and cavalry were now within a small
                    distance of the camp, and some of the Thracians had attacked parties of the
                    enemy, who were straggling and scattered over the country, when the sudden alarm
                    reached their tents. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The commander was thrown
                    into the utmost perplexity; for, having never had a sight of the Achaeans,
                    except occasionally on the hills before Sicyon, when they did not venture to
                    come down into the plains, he had never imagined that they would come so far as
                    Cleone. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He ordered <pb n="1455"
                        xml:id="p.1455"/> the stragglers to be recalled by sound of trumpet;
                    commanded the soldiers to take arms with all haste; and, marching out of the
                    gate at the head of thin battalions, drew up his line on the bank of the river.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> His other troops, having scarcely had time
                    to be collected and formed, did not withstand the enemy's first onset;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the Macedonians had surrounded their
                    standards in by far the greatest numbers, and now kept the prospect of victory a
                    long time doubtful. At length, being left exposed by the flight of the rest,
                        <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> and pressed by two bodies of the enemy
                    on different sides, by the light infantry on their flank, and by the
                    shield-bearers and targeteers in front, and seeing victory declare against them,
                    they at first gave ground; soon after, being vigorously pushed, they turned
                    their backs; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and most of them, throwing away
                    their arms and having lost all hope of defending their camp, made the best of
                    their way to Corinth. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Nicostratus sent the
                    mercenaries in pursuit of these; and the auxiliary Thracians against the party
                    employed in ravaging the lands of Sicyon: occasioned great carnage in both
                    instances, greater almost than occurred in the battle itself. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Of those who had been ravaging Pellene and Phlius, some,
                    returning to their camp, ignorant of all that had happened, and without any
                    regular order, fell in with the advanced guards of the enemy, where they
                    expected their own. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Others, from the bustle
                    which they perceived, suspecting what was really the case, fled and dispersed
                    themselves in such a manner, that, as they wandered up and down, they were cut
                    off by the very peasants. There fell, on that day, one thousand five hundred:
                    three hundred were made prisoners. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> All Achaia
                    was thus relieved from their great alarm. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the battle at Cynoscephalae, Lucius
                    Quinctius had invited to Corcyra some chiefs of the Acarnanians, the only state
                    in Greece which had continued to maintain its alliance with the Macedonians; and
                    there made some kind of scheme for a change of measures. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Two causes, principally, had retained them in friendship
                    with the king: one was a principle of honour, natural to that nation; the other,
                    their fear and hatred of the Aetolians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A
                    general assembly was summoned to meet at Leucas; but neither did all the states
                    of Acarnania come thither, nor were those who did attend agreed in opinion.
                    However, the magistrates and leading men prevailed so far, as to get a decree
                    passed, thus privately, <pb n="1456" xml:id="p.1456"/> for joining in alliance
                    with the Romans. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This gave great offence to
                    those who had not been present; and, in this ferment of the nation, Androcles
                    and Echedemus, two men of distinction among the Acarnanians, being commissioned
                    by Philip, had influence enough in the assembly, not only to obtain the repeal
                    of the decree for an alliance <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> with Rome, but
                    also the condemnation, on a charge of treason, of Archesilaus and Bianor, both
                    men of the first rank in Acarnania, who had been the advisers of that measure;
                    and to deprive Zeuxidas, the praetor, of his office, for having put it to the
                    vote. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The persons condemned took a course
                    apparently desperate, but successful in the issue: for, while their friends
                    advised them to yield to the necessity of the occasion, and withdraw to Corcyra,
                    to the Romans, they resolved to present themselves to the multitude; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and either, by that act, to mollify their resentment,
                    or endure whatever might befall them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When
                    they had introduced themselves into a full assembly, at first, a murmur arose,
                    expressive of surprise; but presently silence took place, partly from respect to
                    their former dignity, partly from commiseration of their present situation.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Having been also permitted the liberty of
                    speaking, at first they addressed the assembly in a suppliant manner; but, in
                    the progress of their discourse, when they came to refute the charges made
                    against them, they spoke with that degree of confidence which innocence
                    inspires. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At last, they even ventured to
                    utter some complaints, and to charge the proceedings against them with injustice
                    and cruelty; and this had such an effect on the minds of all present, that, with
                    one consent, they annulled all the decrees passed against them. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, they came to a resolution, to renounce
                    the friendship of the Romans, and return to the alliance with Philip. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These decrees were passed at Leucas, the
                    capital of Acarnania, the place where all the states usually met in council.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> As soon, therefore, as the news of this
                    sudden change reached the lieutenant-general Flamininus, in Corcyra, he
                    instantly set sail with the fleet for Leucas; and coming to an anchor at a place
                    called Heraeus, advanced thence towards the walls with every kind of machine
                    used in the attacking of cities; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> supposing
                    that the first appearance of danger might bend the minds of the inhabitants to
                    submission. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But seeing no prospect of
                    effecting any thing, except by force, he began <pb n="1457" xml:id="p.1457"/> to
                    erect towers and sheds, and to bring up the battering-rams to the walls.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The whole of Acarnania, being situated
                    between Aetolia and Epirus, faces towards the west and the Sicilian sea.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Leucadia, now an island, separated from
                    Acarnania by a shallow strait which was dug by the hand, was then a peninsula,
                    united on its eastern side to Acarnania by a narrow isthmus: this isthmus was
                    about five hundred paces in length, and in breadth not above one hundred and
                    twenty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the entrance of this narrow neck
                    stands Leucas, stretching up part of a hill which faces the east and Acarnania:
                    the lower part of the town is level, lying along the sea, which divides Leucadia
                    from Acarnania. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thus it lies open to attacks,
                    both from the sea and from the land; for the channel is more like a marsh than a
                    sea, and all the adjacent ground is solid enough to render the construction of
                    works easy. In many places, therefore, at once the walls fell down, either
                    undermined, or demolished by the ram. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the
                    spirit of the besieged was as invincible as the town itself was favourably
                    situated for the besiegers: night and day they employed themselves busily in
                    repairing the shattered parts of the wall; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    and, stopping up the breaches that were made, fought the enemy with great
                    spirit, and showed a wish to defend the walls by their arms rather than
                    themselves by the walls. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And they would
                    certainly have protracted the siege to a length unexpected by the Romans, had
                    not some exiles of Italian birth, who resided in Leucas, admitted a band of
                    soldiers into the citadel: <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> notwithstanding
                    which, when those troops ran down from the higher ground with great tumult and
                    uproar, the Leucadians, drawing up in a body in the forum, withstood them for a
                    considerable time in regular fight. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Meanwhile
                    the walls were scaled in many places; and the besiegers, climbing over the
                    rubbish, entered the town through the breaches. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> And now the lieutenant-general himself surrounded the combatants with a
                    powerful force. Being thus hemmed in, many were slain, the rest laid down their
                    arms, and surrendered to the conqueror. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> In a
                    few days after, on hearing of the battle at Cynoscephalae, all the states of
                    Acarnania made their submission to the lieutenant-general. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time, fortune, depressing the same
                    party in every quarter at once, the Rhodians, in order to recover from Philip
                    the tract on the continent called Peraea, which <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> had <pb n="1458" xml:id="p.1458"/> been in possession of
                    their ancestors, sent thither their praetor, Pausistratus, with eight hundred
                    Achaean foot, and about one thousand nine hundred men, made up of auxiliaries of
                    various nations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These were Gauls, Nisuetans,
                    Pisuetans, Tamians, Areans from Africa, and Laodiceans from Asia. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> With this force Pausistratus seized by surprise
                    Tendeba, in the territory of Stratonice, a place exceedingly convenient for his
                    purpose, without the knowledge of the king's troops who had held it. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> A reinforcement of one thousand Achaean foot and one
                    hundred horse, called out for the same expedition, came up at the very time,
                    under a commander called Theoxenus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Dinocrates, the king's general, with design to recover the fort, marched his
                    army first to Tendeba, and then to another fort called Astragon, which also
                    stood in the territory of Stratonice. Then, calling in all the garrisons, which
                    were scattered in many different places, and the Thessalian auxiliaries from
                    Stratonice itself, he led them on to Alabanda, where the enemy lay. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The Rhodians were no way averse from a battle, and
                    the camps being pitched near each other, both parties immediately came into the
                    field. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Dinocrates placed five hundred
                    Macedonians on his right wing, and the Agrians on his left; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> the centre he formed of the troops which he had drawn
                    together out of the garrisons of the forts; these were mostly Carians; and he
                    covered the flanks with the cavalry, and the Cretan and Thracian auxiliaries.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Rhodians had on the right wing the
                    Achaeans; on the left, mercenary soldiers; and in the centre a chosen band of
                    infantry, a body of auxiliaries composed of troops of various nations.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The cavalry and what light infantry they
                    had, were posted on the wings. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> During that
                    day both armies remained on the banks of a rivulet, which ran between them, and,
                    after discharging a few javelins, they retired into their camps. Next day, being
                    drawn up in the same order, they fought a more important battle than could have
                    been expected, considering the numbers engaged; for there were not more than
                    three thousand infantry on each side, and about one hundred horse: <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> but they were not only on an equality with respect
                    to numbers, and the kind of arms which they used, but they also fought with
                    equal spirit and equal hopes. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> First, the
                    Achaeans, crossing the rivulet, made an attack on the Agrians; then the whole
                    line passed the river, almost at full speed. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    The <pb n="1459" xml:id="p.1459"/> fight continued doubtful a long time: the
                    Achaeans, one thousand in number, drove back the four hundred from their
                    position. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Then the left wing giving way, all
                    exerted themselves against the right. On the Macedonians no impression could be
                    made, so long as their phalanx preserved its order, each man clinging as it were
                    to another: <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> but when, in consequence of their
                    flank being left exposed, they endeavoured to turn their spears against the
                    enemy, who were advancing upon that side, they immediately broke their ranks.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> This first caused disorder among
                    themselves; they then turned their backs, and at last, throwing away their arms,
                    and flying with precipitation, made the best of their way to Bargylii. To the
                    same place Dinocrates also made his escape. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The Rhodians continued the pursuit as long as the day lasted, and then retired
                    to their camp. There is every reason to believe, that, if the victors had
                    proceeded with speed to Stratonice, that city would have been gained without a
                    contest; <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> but the opportunity for effecting
                    this was neglected, and the time wasted in taking possession of the forts and
                    villages in Peraea. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> In the mean time, the
                    courage of the troops in garrison at Stratonice revived; and shortly after,
                    Dinocrates, with the troops which had escaped from the battle, came into the
                    town, which, after that, was besieged and assaulted without effect; nor could it
                    be reduced until a long time after that, when Antiochus took it. <milestone
                        n="22" unit="section"/> Such were the events that took place in Thessaly, in
                    Achaia, and in Asia, all about the same time. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Philip was informed that the Dardanians, in
                    contempt of the power of his kingdom, shaken as at that time it was, <milestone
                        n="2??" unit="section"/> had passed the frontiers, and were spreading
                    devastation through the upper parts of Macedonia: <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> on which, though he was hard pressed in almost every
                    quarter of the globe, fortune on all occasions defeating his measures and those
                    of his friends, yet, thinking it more intolerable than death to be expelled from
                    the possession of Macedonia, he made hasty levies through the cities of his
                    dominions; and, with six thousand foot and five hundred horse, defeated the
                    enemy by a surprise near Stobi in Paeonia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Great numbers were killed in the fight, and greater numbers of those who were
                    scattered about in quest of plunder. As to such as found a road open for flight,
                    without having even tried the chance of an engagement, they <pb n="1460"
                        xml:id="p.1460"/> hastened back to their own country. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> After this enterprise, executed with a degree of success
                    beyond what he met in the rest of his attempts, and which raised the drooping
                    courage of his people, he retired to Thessalonica. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Seasonable as was the termination of the Punic war, in
                    extricating the Romans from the danger of a quarrel with Philip, the recent
                    triumph over Philip happened still more opportunely, when Antiochus, in Syria,
                    was already making preparations for hostilities. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> For besides that it was easier to wage war against them separately than if
                    both had combined their forces together, Spain had, a little before this time,
                    risen in arms in great commotion. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Antiochus,
                    though he had in the preceding summer reduced under his power all the states in
                    Cœle-Syria belonging to Ptolemy, and retired into winter quarters at Antioch,
                    yet allowed himself no relaxation from the exertions of the summer. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> For resolving to exert the whole strength of his
                    kingdom, he collected a most powerful force, both naval and military; and in the
                    beginning of spring, sending forward by land his two sons, Ardues and
                    Mithridates, at the head of the army, with orders to wait for him at Sardis, he
                    himself set out <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> by sea, with a fleet of one
                    hundred decked ships, besides two hundred lighter vessels, barks and fly-boats,
                    designing to attempt the reduction of all the cities under the dominion of
                    Ptolemy along the whole coast of Caria and Cilicia; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and, at the same time, to aid Philip with an army and
                    ships, for as yet that war had not been brought to a conclusion. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Rhodians, out of a faithful attachment to
                    the Roman people, and an affection for the whole race of the Greeks, have
                    performed many honourable exploits, both on land and sea: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> but never was their gallantry more eminently conspicuous
                    than on this occasion, when, nowise dismayed at the formidable magnitude of the
                    impending war, they sent ambassadors to tell the king, that he should not double
                    the point of Cheledoniae, which is a promontory of Cilicia, rendered famous by
                    an ancient treaty between the Athenians and the king of Persia; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> that if he did not confine his fleet and forces to that
                    boundary, they would meet him there and oppose him, not out of any ill will, but
                    because they would not suffer him to join Philip and obstruct the Romans, who
                    were restoring liberty to Greece. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At this time
                    Antiochus was pushing on the siege of Coracesium with his works; for, after he
                    had got <pb n="1461" xml:id="p.1461"/> possession of Zephyrium, Solae,
                    Aphrodisias, and Corycus; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and doubling
                    Anemurium, another promontory of Cilicia, had taken Selinus; when all these, and
                    the other fortresses on that coast, had, either through fear or inclination,
                    submitted without resistance, Coracesium shut its gates, and gave him a delay
                    which he did not expect. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here an audience was
                    given to the ambassadors of the Rhodians, and although the purport of their
                    embassy was such as might kindle passion in the breast of a king, yet he stifled
                    his resentment, and answered, that <quote> he would send ambassadors to Rhodes,
                        and would give them instructions to renew the old treaties, made by him and
                        his predecessors, with that state; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and to
                        assure them, that they need not be alarmed at his approach; that it would
                        involve no injury or fraud either to them or their allies; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> for that he was not about to violate the friendship
                        subsisting between himself and the Romans, both his own late embassy to that
                        people, and the senate's answers and decrees, so honourable to him, were a
                        sufficient evidence. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Just at that time his ambassadors happened to
                    have returned from Rome, where they had been heard and dismissed with courtesy,
                    as the juncture required; the event of the war with Philip being yet uncertain.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While the king's ambassadors were
                    haranguing to the above purpose, in an assembly of the people at Rhodes, a
                    courier arrived with an account of the battle at Cynoscephalae having finally
                    decided the fate of the war. Having received this intelligence, the Rhodians,
                    now freed from all apprehensions of danger from Philip, resolved to oppose
                    Antiochus with their fleet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Nor did they
                    neglect another object that required their attention; the protection of the
                    freedom of the cities in alliance with Ptolemy, which were threatened with war
                    by Antiochus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For, some they assisted with
                    men, others by forewarning them of the enemy's designs; by which means they
                    enabled the Cauneans, Mindians, Halicarnassians, and Samians to preserve their
                    liberty. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It were needless to attempt
                    enumerating all the transactions as they occurred in that quarter, when I am
                    scarcely equal to the task of recounting those which immediately concern the war
                    in which Rome was engaged. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At this time king Attalus, having fallen sick
                    at Thebes, and been carried thence to Pergamus, died at the age of seventy-one,
                    after he had reigned forty-four years. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To this
                    man for- <pb n="1462" xml:id="p.1462"/> tune had given nothing which could
                    inspire hopes of a throne except riches. By a prudent, and, at the same time, a
                    splendid use of these, he begat, in himself first, and then in others, an
                    opinion, that he was not undeserving of a crown. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> Afterwards, having in one battle utterly defeated the Gauls, which nation was
                    then the more terrible to Asia, as having but lately made its appearance there,
                    he assumed the title <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> of king, and ever after
                    exhibited a spirit equal to the dignity of that name. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He governed his subjects with the most perfect justice, and
                    observed an unvarying fidelity towards his allies; gentle and bountiful to his
                    friends; affectionate to his wife and four sons, who survived him; and he left
                    his government established on such solid and firm foundations, that the
                    possession of it descended to the third generation. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> While this was the posture of affairs in Asia, Greece, and
                    Macedonia, the war with Philip being scarcely ended, and the peace certainly not
                    yet perfected, a desperate insurrection took place in the Farther Spain.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcus Helvius was governor of that
                    province. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He informed the senate by letter,
                    that <quote> two chieftains, Colca and Luscinus, were in arms; that Colca was
                        joined by seventeen towns, and Luscinus by the powerful cities of Carmo and
                        Bardo; and that the people of the whole sea-coast, who had not yet
                        manifested their disposition, were ready to rise on the first motion of
                        their neighbours. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On this letter being read by Marcus Sergius,
                    city praetor, the senate decreed, that, as soon as the election of praetors
                    should be finished, the one to whose lot the government of Spain fell should,
                    without delay, consult the senate respecting the commotions in that province. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time the consuls came
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> home to Rome, and, on their holding a
                    meeting of the senate in the temple of Bellona, and demanding a triumph, in
                    consideration of their successes in the war, Caius Atinius Labeo, and Caius
                    Ursanius, plebeian tribunes, insisted that <quote> the consuls should propose
                        their claims of a triumph separately, for they would not suffer the question
                        to be put on both jointly, lest equal honours might be conferred where the
                        merits were unequal. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Minucius urged, that they had both been
                    appointed to the government of one province, Italy; and that, through the course
                    of their administration, his colleague and himself had been united in sentiments
                    and in counsels; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> to which Cornelius added,
                    that, when the Boians were passing the Po, to assist the <pb n="1463"
                        xml:id="p.1463"/> Insubrians and Caenomanians against him, they were forced
                    to return to defend their own country, from his colleague ravaging their towns
                    and lands. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In reply the tribunes ac-
                    knowledged, that the services performed in the war by Cor- nelius were so great,
                    that <quote> no more doubt could be entertained respecting his triumph than
                        respecting the ascribing of glory to the immortal gods. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nevertheless they insisted, that <quote>
                        neither he nor any other member of the community should possess such power
                        and influence as to be able, after obtaining the honour that was due to
                        himself, to bestow the same distinction on a colleague, who immodestly
                        demanded what he had not deserved. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                        exploits of Quintus Minucius in Liguria were trifling skirmishes, scarcely
                        deserving mention; and in Gaul he had lost great numbers of soldiers. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They mentioned even military tribunes, Titus
                    Juvencius and Cneius Labeo, of the fourth legion, the plebeian tribune's
                    brother, who had fallen in unsuccessful conflict, together with many other brave
                    men, both citizens and allies: and they asserted, that <quote> pretended
                        surrenders of a few towns and villages, fabricated for the occasion, had
                        been made, without any pledge of fidelity being taken. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These altercations between the consuls and
                    tribunes lasted two days: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> at last the
                    consuls, overcome by the obstinacy of the tribunes, proposed their claims
                    separately. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To Cneius Cornelius a triumph was unanimously
                    decreed: and the inhabitants of Placentia and Cremona added to the applause
                    bestowed on <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> the consul, by returning him
                    thanks, and mentioning, to his honour, that they had been delivered by him from
                    a siege; and that very many of them, when in the hands of the enemy, had been
                    rescued from captivity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Quintus Minucius just
                    tried how the proposal of his claim would be received, and finding the whole
                    senate averse from it, declared, that by the authority of his office of consul,
                    and pursuant to the example of many illustrious men, he would triumph on the
                    Alban mount. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Caius Cornelius, being yet in
                    office, triumphed over the Insubrian and Caenomanian Gauls. He produced a great
                    number of military standards, and carried in the procession abundance of Gallic
                    spoils in captured chariots. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Many Gauls of
                    distinction were led before his chariot, and along with them, some writers say,
                    Hamilcar, the Carthaginian general. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But what,
                    more than all, attracted the eyes of the public, was a crowd of Cremonian and
                    Placentian <pb n="1464" xml:id="p.1464"/> colonists, with caps of liberty on
                    their heads, following his chariot. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He carried
                    in his triumph two hundred and thirty-seven thousand five hundred <hi
                        rend="italics">asses,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 766 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and of silver denarii, stamped with a chariot, seventy-nine thousand.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 2551 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 0
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 10 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> He distributed to each of his soldiers seventy <hi rend="italics"
                        >asses,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 4 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 1/2
                            <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to a horseman and a centurion double that sum. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Minucius, consul, triumphed on the Alban mount,
                    over the Ligurian and Boian Gauls. Although this triumph was less respectable,
                    in regard to the place and the fame of his exploits, and because all knew the
                    expense was not issued from the treasury; yet, in regard of the number of
                    standards, chariots, and spoils, it was nearly equal to the other. The amount of
                    the money also was nearly equal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Two hundred
                    and fifty-four thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 820 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were conveyed to the treasury, and of silver denarii, stamped with a
                    chariot, fifty-three thousand two hundred. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 1717 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> He likewise gave to the soldiers, horsemen, and centurions, severally,
                    the same sums that his colleague had given. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the triumph, the election of consuls
                    came on. The persons chosen were Lucius Furius Purpureo and Marcus Claudius
                    Marcellus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Next day, the following were
                    elected praetors; Quintus Fabius Buteo, Tiberius Sempronius Longus, Quintus
                    Minucius Thermus, Manius Acilius Glabrio, Lucius Apustius Fullo, and Caius
                    Laelius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Toward the close of this year, a
                    letter came from Titus Quinctius, with information that he had fought a pitched
                    battle with Philip in Thessaly, and that the army of the enemy had been routed
                    and put to flight. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This letter was read by
                    Sergius, the praetor, first in the senate, and then, by the direction of the
                    fathers, in a general assembly; and supplications of five days' continuance were
                    decreed on account of those successes. Soon after arrived the ambassadors, both
                    from Titus Quinctius and from the king. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    Macedonians were conducted out of the city to the Villa Publica, where lodgings
                    and every other accommodation were provided for them, and an audience of the
                    senate was given them in the temple of Bellona. Not many words passed; for the
                    Macedonians declared, that whatever terms the senate should prescribe, the king
                    was ready to comply with them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was decreed,
                    that, conformably to ancient practice, ten ambassadors should be appointed, <pb
                        n="1465" xml:id="p.1465"/> and that, in council with them, the general,
                    Titus Quinctius, should grant terms of peace to Philip; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> and a clause was added, that, in the number of these
                    ambassadors, should be Publius Sulpicius and Publius Villius, who in their
                    consulships had held the province of Macedonia. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> On the same day the inhabitants of Oossa having presented a petition, praying
                    that the number of their colonists might be enlarged; an order was accordingly
                    passed, that one thousand should be added to the list, with a provision, that
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> no persons should be admitted into that
                    number who, at any time since the consulate of Publius Cornelius and Tiberius
                    Sempronius, had been partisans of the enemy. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year the Roman games were exhibited in
                    the circus, and on the stage, by the curule aediles, Publius Cornelius Scipio
                    and Cneius Manlius Vulso, with an unusual degree of splendour, and were beheld
                    with the greater delight, in consequence of the late successes in war. They were
                    thrice repeated entire, and the plebeian games seven times. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> These were exhibited by Manius Acilius Glabrio and Caius
                    Laelius, who also, out of the money arising from fines, erected three brazen
                    statues, to Ceres, Liber, and Libera. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Lucius
                    Furius and Marcus Claudius Marcellus, having entered on the consulship, when the
                    distribution of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the provinces came to be
                    agitated, and the senate appeared disposed to vote Italy the province of both,
                    exerted themselves to get that of Macedonia put to the lot along with Italy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Marcellus, who of the two was the more
                    eager for that province, by assertions that the peace was merely a feigned and
                    delusive one, and that, if the army were withdrawn thence, the king would renew
                    the war, caused some perplexity in the minds of the senate. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The consuls would probably have carried the point, had not
                    Quintus Marcius Rex and Caius Antinius Labeo, plebeian tribunes, declared, that
                    they would enter their protest, unless they were allowed, before any further
                    proceeding, to take the sense of the people, whether it was their will and order
                    that peace be concluded with Philip. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This
                    question was put to the people in the Capitol, and every one of the thirty-five
                    tribes voted on the affirmative side. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    public found the greater reason to rejoice at the ratification of the peace with
                    Macedonia, as melancholy news was brought from Spain; and a letter was made
                    public, announcing that <quote> the proconsul, Caius Sempro- <pb n="1466"
                            xml:id="p.1466"/> nius Tuditanus, had been defeated in battle in the
                        Hither Spain; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that his army had been
                        utterly routed and dispersed, and several men of distinction slain in the
                        fight. That Tuditanus, having been grievously wounded, and carried out of
                        the field, expired soon after. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Italy was decreed the province of both
                    consuls, in which they were to employ the same legions which the preceding
                    consuls had; and they were to raise four new legions, two for the city, and two
                    to be in readiness to be sent whithersoever the senate should direct. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius Flamininus was ordered to continue
                    in the government of his province, with the army of two legions, then on the
                    spot. The former prolongation of his command was deemed sufficient. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The praetors then cast lots for their
                    provinces. Lucius Apustius Fullo obtained the city jurisdiction; Manius Acilius
                    Glabrio, that between natives and foreigners; Quintus Fabius Buteo, Farther
                    Spain: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Quintus Minucius Thermus, Hither Spain;
                    Caius Laelius, Sicily; Tiberius Sempronius Longus, Sardinia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To Quintus Fabius Buteo and Quintus Minucius, to whom the
                    government of the two Spains had fallen, it was decreed, that the consuls, out
                    of the four legions raised by them, should give one each whichever they thought
                    fit, together with four thousand foot and three hundred horse of the allies and
                    Latin confederates; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and those praetors were
                    ordered to repair to their provinces at the earliest possible time. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> This war in Spain broke out in the fifth year after
                    the former had been ended, together with the Punic war. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Spaniards now, for the first time, had taken arms in
                    their own name, unconnected with any Carthaginian army or general. Before the
                    consuls stirred from the city, however, they were ordered, as usual, to expiate
                    the reported prodigies. Publius Villius, a Roman knight, on the road to Sabinia,
                    had been killed by lightning, together with his horse. The temple of Feronia, in
                    the Capenatian district, had been struck by lightning. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> At the temple of Moneta, the shafts of two spears had taken
                    fire and burned. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A wolf, coming in through the
                    Esquiline gate, and running through the most frequented part of the city, down
                    into the forum, passed thence through the Tuscan and Maelian streets; and
                    scarcely receiving a stroke, made its escape out of the Capenian gate.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These prodigies were expiated with victims
                    of the larger kinds. <pb n="1467" xml:id="p.1467"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time Cneius Cornelius Lentulus,
                    who had held the government of Hither Spain before Sempronius Tuditanus, entered
                    the city in ovation, pursuant to a decree of the senate, <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> and carried in the procession one thousand five hundred and
                    fifteen pounds' weight of gold, twenty thousand of silver; and in coin,
                    thirty-four thousand five hundred and fifty denarii. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 1115 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 13 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 3 1/2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Lucius Stretinius, from the Farther Spain,
                    without making any pretensions to a triumph, carried into the treasury fifty
                    thousand pounds' weight of silver; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and out of
                    the spoils taken, built two arches in the cattle-market, at the fronts of the
                    temple of Fortune and Mother Matuta, and one in the great Circus; and on these
                    arches placed gilded statues. These were the principal occurrences during the
                    winter. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At this time Quinctius was in winter
                    quarters at Elatia. Among many requests, made to him by the allies, was that of
                    the Bœotians, namely, that their countrymen, who had served in the army with
                    Philip, might be restored to them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With this
                    Quinctius readily complied; not because he thought them very deserving, but
                    that, as king Antiochus was already suspected, he judged it advisable to
                    conciliate every state in favour of the Roman interest. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> It quickly appeared how very little gratitude existed among
                    the Bœotians; for they not only sent persons to give thanks to Philip for the
                    restoration of their fellows, as if that favour had been conferred on them by
                    him, and not by Quinctius and the Romans; but, at the next election, raised to
                    the office of Bœotarch a man named Brachyllas, for no other reason than because
                    he had been commander of the Bœotians serving in the army of Philip; <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> passing by Zeuxippus, Pisistratus, and the others,
                    who had promoted the alliance with Rome. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These
                    men were both offended at the present and alarmed about the future consequences:
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> for if such things were done when a Roman
                    army lay almost at their gates, what would become of them when the Romans should
                    have gone away to Italy, and Philip, from a situation so near, should support
                    his own associates, and vent his resentment <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                    on those who had been of the opposite party? </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was resolved, while they had the Roman army
                    near at hand, to take off Brachyllas, who was the principal leader of the
                    faction which favoured the king; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and they
                    chose an opportunity for the deed, when, after having been at a public <pb
                        n="1468" xml:id="p.1468"/> feast, he was returning to his house inebriated,
                    and accompanied by some of his debauched companions, who, for the sake of
                    merriment, had been admitted to the crowded entertainment. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He was surrounded and assassinated by six men, of whom
                    three were Italians and three Aetolians. His companions fled, crying out for
                    help; and a great uproar ensued among the people, who ran up and down, through
                    all parts of the city, with lights: but the assassins made their escape through
                    the nearest gate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the first dawn, a full
                    assembly was called together in the theatre, by the voice of a crier, as if in
                    consequence of a previous appointment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Many
                    openly clamoured that Brachyllas was killed by those detestable wretches who
                    accompanied him; but their private conjectures pointed to Zeuxippus, as author
                    of the murder. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was resolved, however, that
                    those who had been in company with him should be seized and examined in their
                    presence. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While they were under examination,
                    Zeuxippus, with his usual composure, came into the assembly, for the purpose of
                    averting the charge from himself; yet said, that people were mistaken in
                    supposing that so daring a murder was the act of such effeminate wretches as
                    those who were charged with it, urging many plausible arguments to the same
                    purpose. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By which behaviour he led several to
                    believe, that, if he were conscious of guilt, he would never have presented
                    himself before the multitude, or, without being challenged by any, have made any
                    mention of the murder. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Others were convinced
                    that he intended, by thus unblushingly exposing himself to the charge, to throw
                    off all suspicion from himself. Soon after, those men who were innocent were put
                    to the torture; and, taking the universal opinion as having the effect of
                    evidence, they named Zeuxippus and Pisistratus; but they produced no proof to
                    show that they knew any thing of the matter. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Zeuxippus, however, accompanied by a man named Stratonidas, fled by night to
                    Tanagra; alarmed by his own conscience rather than by the assertion of men who
                    were privy to no one circumstance of the affair. Pisistratus, despising the
                    informers, remained at Thebes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> A slave of
                    Zeuxippus had carried messages backwards and forwards, and had been intrusted
                    with the management of the whole business. From this man Pisistratus dreaded a
                    discovery; and by that very dread forced him, against his will, to make one.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He sent a letter <pb n="1469"
                        xml:id="p.1469"/> to Zeuxippus, desiring him to <quote> put out of the way
                        the slave who was privy to their crime; for he did not believe him as well
                        qualified for the concealment of the fact as he was for the perpetration of
                        it. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He ordered the bearer of this letter to
                    deliver it to Zeuxippus as soon as possible; but he, not finding an opportunity
                    of meeting him, put it into the hands of the very slave in question, whom he
                    believed to be the most faithful to his master of any; and added, that it came
                    from Pisistratus respecting a matter of the utmost consequence to Zeuxippus.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Struck by consciousness of guilt, the
                    slave, after promising to deliver the letter, immediately opened it; and, on
                    reading the contents, fled in a fright to Thebes and laid the information before
                    the magistrate. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Zeuxippus, alarmed by the
                    flight of his slave, withdrew to Athens, where he thought he might live in exile
                    with greater safety. Pisistratus, after being examined several times by torture,
                    was put to death. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This murder exasperated the Thebans, and all
                    the Bœotians, to the most rancorous animosity against the Romans, for they
                    considered that Zeuxippus, one of the first men of the nation, had not been
                    party to such a crime without the instigation of the Roman general. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> To recommence a war, they had neither strength nor a
                    leader; but they had recourse to private massacres, as being next to war, and
                    cut off many of the soldiers, some as they came to lodge in their houses, others
                    as they wandered about their winter quarters, or were on leave of absence for
                    various purposes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some were killed on the
                    roads by parties lying in wait in lurking-places; others were seduced and
                    carried away to inns, which were left uninhabited, and there put to death.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At last they committed these crimes, not
                    merely out of hatred, but likewise from a desire of booty; for the soldiers on
                    furlough generally carried money in their purses for the purpose of trading.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At first a few at a time, afterwards
                    greater numbers used to be missed, until all Bœotia became notorious for those
                    practices, and a soldier went beyond the bounds of the camp with more timidity
                    than into an enemy's country. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Quinctius then
                    sent deputies round the states, to make inquiry concerning the murders
                    committed. The greatest number of murders were found to have been committed
                    about the lake called Copais; there the bodies were dug out of the mud, and
                    drawn up out <pb n="1470" xml:id="p.1470"/> of the marsh, having had earthen
                    jars or stones tied to them, so as to be dragged to the bottom by the weight.
                    Many deeds of this sort were discovered to have been perpetrated at Acrœphia and
                    Coronea. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quinctius at first insisted that the
                    persons guilty should be given up to him, and that, for five hundred soldiers,
                    (for so many had been cut off,) the Bœotians should pay five hundred talents.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 96,875 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Neither of these requisitions being complied
                    with, and the states only making verbal apologies, declaring, that none of those
                    acts had been authorized by the public; Quinctius first sent ambassadors to
                    Athens and Achaia, to satisfy the allies, that the war which he was about to
                    make on the Bœotians was conformable to justice and piety; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and then, ordering Publius Claudius to march with one-half
                    of the troops to Acrœphia, he himself, with the remainder, invested Coronea; and
                    these two bodies, marching by different roads from Elatia, laid waste all the
                    country through which they passed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    Bœotians, dismayed by these losses, while every place was filled with fugitives,
                    and while the terror became universal, sent ambassadors to the camp; and as
                    these were refused admittance, the Achaeans and Athenians came to their
                    assistance. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Achaeans had the greater
                    influence as intercessors; inasmuch as they were resolved, in case they could
                    not procure peace for the Bœotians, to join them in the war. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Through the mediation of the Achaeans, however, the
                    Bœotians obtained admission and an audience of the Roman general; who, ordering
                    them to deliver up the guilty, and to pay thirty talents <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 5821 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 10 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi>
                    </note> as a fine, granted them peace, and raised the siege. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A few days after this, the ten ambassadors
                    arrived from Rome, in pursuance of whose counsel, peace was granted to Philip on
                    the following conditions: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> That all the Grecian states, as well those in Asia as those in Europe,
                        should enjoy liberty, and their own laws: That from such of them as had been
                        in the possession of Philip, he should withdraw his garrisons, particularly
                        from the following places in Asia; Euromus, Pedasi, Bargylii, Iassus,
                        Myrina, Abydus; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and from Thasus and
                        Perinthus, for it was determined that these likewise should be free: That
                        with respect to the freedom of Cius, Quinctius should write to Prusias, king
                        of Bithynia, the resolutions of the senate, and of the ten ambassadors:
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That <pb n="1471" xml:id="p.1471"/>
                        Philip should return to the Romans the prisoners and deserters, and deliver
                        up all his decked ships, excepting five and the royal galley, —of <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> a size almost unmanageable, being moved by
                        sixteen banks of oars: That he should not keep more than five hundred
                        soldiers, nor any elephant: That he should not wage war beyond the bounds of
                        Macedonia without permission from the senate: <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That he should pay to the Roman people one thousand
                        talents: <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 193,750 <hi
                                rend="italics">l.</hi>
                        </note> one half at present, the other by instalments, within ten years. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias writes, that there was imposed
                    on him an annual tribute of four thousand pounds' weight of silver, for ten
                    years, and an immediate payment of twenty thousand pounds' weight. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The same author says, that an article was expressly
                    inserted, that he should not make war on Eumenes, Attalus's son, who had lately
                    come to the throne. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For the performance of
                    these conditions hostages were received, among whom was Demetrius, Philip's son.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias adds, that the island of
                    Aegina, and the elephants, were given as a present to Attalus, who was absent;
                    to the Rhodians, Stratonice, and other cities of Caria which had been in the
                    possession of Philip; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and to the Athenians,
                    the islands of Paros, Imbros, Delos, and Scyros. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While all the other states of Greece expressed
                    their approbation of these terms of peace, the Aetolians alone, in private
                    murmurs, made severe strictures on the determination of the ten ambassadors.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They said, <quote> it consisted merely of
                        an empty piece of writing varnished over with a fallacious appearance of
                        liberty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For why should some cities be put
                        into the hands of the Romans without being named, while others were
                        particularized, and ordered to be enfranchised without such consignment;
                        unless the intent was, that those in Asia, which, from their distant
                        situation, were more secure from danger, should be free; but those in
                        Greece, not being even mentioned by name, should be made their property:
                        Corinth, Chalcis, and Oreum; with Eretria, and Demetrias. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor was this charge entirely without
                    foundation: for there was some hesitation with respect to Corinth, Chalcis, and
                    Demetrias; because, in the decree of the senate in pursuance of which the ten
                    ambassadors had been sent from Rome, all Greece and Asia, except these three,
                    were expressly ordered to be set at liberty; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    but, with regard to these, ambassadors <pb n="1472" xml:id="p.1472"/> were
                    instructed, that, whatever measures the exigencies of the state might render
                    expedient, they should determine to pursue in conformity to the public good and
                    their own honour. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> King Antiochus was one of
                    whom they did not doubt that, so soon as he was satisfied that his forces were
                    adequate, he would cross over into Europe; and they were unwilling to let these
                    cities, the possession of which would be so advantageous to him, lie open to his
                    occupation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Quinctius, with the ten
                    ambassadors, sailed from Elatia to Anticyra, and thence to Corinth. Here the
                    plans they had laid down respecting the liberation of Greece were discussed for
                    about three days in a council of the ten ambassadors. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Quinctius frequently urged, that <quote> every part of
                        Greece ought to be set at liberty, if they wished to refute the cavils of
                        the Aetolians; if they wished, that sincere affection and respect for the
                        Roman nation should be universally entertained; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> or if they wished to convince the world that they had
                        crossed the sea with the design of liberating Greece, and not of
                        transferring the sovereignty of it from Philip to themselves. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Macedonians alleged nothing in opposition
                    to the arguments made use of in favour of the freedom of the cities; but <quote>
                        they thought it safer for those cities themselves that they should remain,
                        for a time, under the protection of Roman garrisons, than be obliged to
                        receive Antiochus for a master in the room of Philip. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Their final determination was, that <quote>
                        Corinth be restored to the Achaeans, but that a Roman garrison should
                        continue in the citadel; and that Chalcis and Demetrias be retained, until
                        their apprehensions respecting Antiochus should cease. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The stated solemnity of the Isthmian games was
                    at hand. These have ever been attended by very numerous meetings, as well on
                    account of the universal fondness entertained by this nation for exhibitions of
                    skill in arts of every kind, as well as of contests in strength and swiftness of
                    foot; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> as also, because of the convenience of
                    the locality, which furnishes commercial advantages of all kinds by its two
                    opposite seas, and by which it had obtained the character of a rendezvous for
                    all the population of Asia and Greece. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But on
                    this occasion, all were led thither not only for their ordinary purposes, but by
                    an eager curiosity to learn what was thenceforward to be the state of Greece,
                    and what their own condition; while many at the same time not only formed
                    opinions within themselves, <pb n="1473" xml:id="p.1473"/> but uttered their
                    conjectures in conversation. Scarcely any supposed that the Romans, victorious
                    as they were, would withdraw from the whole of Greece. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They took their seats, as spectators; and a herald,
                    preceded by a trumpeter, according to custom, advanced into the centre of the
                    theatre, where notice of the commencement of the games is usually made, in a
                    solemn form of words. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Silence being commanded
                    by sound of trumpet, he uttered aloud the following proclamation: THE SENATE AND
                    PEOPLE OF ROME, AND TITUS QUINCTIUS, THEIR GENERAL, HAVING SUBDUED KING PHILIP
                    AND THE MACEDONIANS, DO HEREBY ORDER, THAT THE FOLLOWING STATES BE FREE,
                    INDEPENDENT, AND RULED BY THEIR OWN LAWS: THE CORINTHIANS, PHOCIANS, AND ALL THE
                    LOCRIANS; THE IS- LAND OF EUBŒA, AND THE MAGNESIANS; THE THESSALIANS,
                    PERRHAeBIANS, <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> AND THE ACHAeANS OF PHTHIOTIS.
                    He then read a list of all the states which had been under subjection to king
                    Philip. The joy occasioned by hearing these words of the herald was so great,
                    that the people's minds were unable to conceive the matter at once. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Scarcely could they believe that they had heard them;
                    and they looked at each other, marvelling as at the empty illusion of a dream.
                    Each inquired of his neighbours about what immediately concerned himself,
                    altogether distrusting the evidence of his own ears. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> As every one desired not only to hear, but to see the
                    messenger of liberty, the herald was called out again; and he again repeated the
                    proclamation. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When they were thus assured of
                    the reality of the joyful tidings, they raised such a shout, and clapping of
                    hands, and repeated them so often, as clearly to show that of all blessings none
                    is more grateful to the multitude than liberty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> The games were then proceeded through with hurry; for neither the thoughts
                    nor eyes of any attended to the exhibitions, so entirely had the single passion
                    of joy pre-occupied their minds, as to exclude the sense of all other pleasures. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But, when the games were finished, every one
                    eagerly pressed towards the Roman general; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> so
                    that by the crowd rushing to one spot, all wishing to come near him, and to
                    touch his right hand, and throwing garlands and ribands, he was in some degree
                    of danger. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He was then about thirty-three
                    years of age; and besides the vigour of youth, the grateful sensations excited
                    by so eminent a harvest of glory, increased <pb n="1474" xml:id="p.1474"/> his
                    strength. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor was the general exultation
                    exhausted in the presence of all the assembly, but, through the space of many
                    days, was continually revived by sentiments and expressions of gratitude.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>There was a nation in the world,</quote> they said, <quote> which, at its
                        own expense, with its own labour, and at its own risk, waged wars for the
                        liberty of others. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And this was performed,
                        not merely for contiguous states, or near neighbours, or for countries that
                        made parts of the same continent; but they even crossed the seas for the
                        purpose, that no unlawful power should subsist on the face of the whole
                        earth; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but that justice, right, and law
                        should every where have sovereign sway. By one sentence, pronounced by a
                        herald, all the cities of Greece and Asia had been set at liberty.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To have conceived hopes of this,
                        argued a daring spirit; to have carried it into effect, was a proof of the
                        most consummate bravery and good fortune. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius and the ten ambassadors then gave
                    audience to the embassies of the several kings, nations, and states. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> First of all, the ambassadors of king Antiochus were
                    called. Their proceedings, here, were nearly the same as at Rome; a mere display
                    of words unsupported by facts. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the answer
                    given them was not ambiguous as formerly, during the uncertainty of affairs, and
                    while Philip was unsubdued; for the king was required in express terms to
                    evacuate the cities of Asia, which had been in possession either of Philip or
                    Ptolemy; not to meddle with the free cities, or ever take arms against them, and
                    to be in a state of peace and equality with all the cities of Greece wherever
                    they might be. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Above all it was insisted on,
                    that he should neither come himself into Europe, nor transport an army thither.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The king's ambassadors being dismissed, a
                    general convention of the nations and states was immediately held; and the
                    business was despatched with the greater expedition, because the resolutions of
                    the ten ambassadors mentioned the several states by name. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> To the people of Orestis, a district of Macedonia, in
                    consideration of their having been the first who came over from the side of the
                    king, their own laws were granted. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    Magnesians, Perrhaebians, and Dolopians were likewise declared free. To the
                    nation of the Thessalians, besides the enjoyment of liberty, the Achaean part of
                    Phthiotis was granted, excepting Phthiotian Thebes and Pharsalus. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The Aetolians, demanding that Pharsalus and <pb
                        n="1475" xml:id="p.1475"/> Leucas should be restored to them in conformity
                    to the treaty, were referred to the senate: but the council united to these, by
                    authority of a decree, Phocis and Locris, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    places which had formerly been annexed to them. Corinth, Triphylia, and Heraea,
                    another city of Peloponnesus, were restored to the Achaeans. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The ten ambassadors were inclined to give Oreum and Eretria
                    to king Eumenes, son of Attalus; but Quinctius dissenting, the matter came under
                    the determination of the senate, and the senate declared those cities free;
                    adding to them Carystus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Lycus and Parthinia,
                    Illyrian states, each of which had been under subjection to Philip, were given
                    to Pleuratus. Amynander was ordered to retain possession of the forts, which he
                    had taken from Philip during the war. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the convention broke up, the ten
                    ambassadors, dividing the business among them, set out by different routes to
                    give liberty to the several cities within their respective districts. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Publius Lentulus went to Bargylii; Lucius Stertinius,
                    to Hephaestia, Thasus, and the cities of Thrace; Publius Villius and Lucius
                    Terentius to king Antiochus; and Cneius Cornelius to Philip. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The last of these, after executing his commission with
                    respect to smaller matters, asked Philip, whether he was disposed to listen to
                    advice, not only useful but highly salutary. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    To which the king answered that he was, and would give him thanks besides, if he
                    mentioned any thing conducive to his advantage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> He then earnestly recommended to him, since he had obtained peace with the
                    Romans, to send ambassadors to Rome to solicit their alliance and friendship;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> lest, in case of Antiochus pursuing any
                    hostile measure, he might be suspected of having lain in wait and seized the
                    opportunity of the times for reviving hostilities. This meeting with Philip was
                    at Tempè in Thessaly; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and on his answering
                    that he would send ambassadors without delay, Cornelius proceeded to
                    Thermopylae, where all the states of Greece are accustomed to meet in general
                    assembly on certain stated days. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This is
                    called the Pylaic assembly. Here he admonished the Aetolians, in particular,
                    constantly and firmly to cultivate the friendship of the Roman people;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> but some of the principal of these
                    interrupted him with complaints, that the disposition of the <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> Romans towards their nation was not the same since the
                    victory, that it had been during the war; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    while others censured them with greater <pb n="1476" xml:id="p.1476"/> boldness,
                    and in a reproachful manner asserted, that <quote> without the aid of the
                        Aetolians, the Romans could neither have conquered Philip, nor even have
                        made good their passage into Greece. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To such discourses the Roman forbore giving
                    an answer, lest the matter might end in an altercation, and only said, that if
                    they sent ambassadors to Rome, every thing that was reasonable would be granted
                    to them. Accordingly, they passed a decree for such mission, agreeably to his
                    direction. — In this manner was the war with Philip concluded. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these transactions passed in Greece,
                    Macedonia, and Asia, a conspiracy among the slaves had well nigh made Etruria an
                    hostile province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To examine into and suppress
                    this, Manius Acilius the praetor, whose province was the administration of
                    justice between natives and foreigners, was sent at the head of one of the two
                    city legions. A number of them, who were by this time formed in a body, he
                    reduced by force of arms, killing and taking many. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Some, who had been the ringleaders of the conspiracy, he
                    scourged with rods, and then crucified; some he returned to their masters.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consuls repaired to their provinces.
                    Just as Marcellus entered the frontiers of the Boians, and while his men were
                    fatigued with marching the whole length of the day, and as he was pitching his
                    camp on a rising ground, Corolam, a chieftain of the Boians, attacked him with a
                    very numerous force, and slew three thousand of his men: <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> several persons of distinction fell in that tumultuary
                    engagement; amongst others, Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus and Marcus Junius
                    Silanus, praefects of the allies; and Aulus Ogulnius and Publius Claudius,
                    military tribunes in the second legion. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    Romans, notwithstanding, had courage enough to finish the fortification of their
                    camp, and to defend it, in spite of an assault made on it by the enemy, elated
                    by their success in the field. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marcellus
                    remained for some time in the same post, until he could tend the wounded, and
                    revive the spirits of his men, after such a disheartening blow. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The Boians, a nation remarkably impatient of delay, and
                    quickly disgusted at a state of inaction, separated, and withdrew to their
                    several forts and villages. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Marcellus then,
                    suddenly crossing the Po, led his lesions into the territory of Comum, where the
                    Insubrians, after rousing the people of the country to arms, lay encamped. The
                    fierce Boian Gauls attacked him on his march, and their <pb n="1477"
                        xml:id="p.1477"/> first onset was so vigorous, as to make a considerable
                    impression on his van. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On perceiving which,
                    and fearing lest, if his men once gave way, they would be dislodged, he brought
                    up a cohort of Marsians against the enemy, and ordered every troop of the Latin
                    cavalry to charge them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The first and second
                    charges of these having checked the enemy in their furious attack, the other
                    troops in the Roman line, resuming courage, advanced briskly on the foe. The
                    Gauls no longer maintained the contest, but turned their backs and fled in
                    confusion. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias relates, that in
                    that battle above forty thousand men were killed, <milestone n="13??"
                        unit="section"/> five hundred and seven military standards taken, with four
                    hundred and thirty-two chariots, and a great number of gold chains, one of
                    which, of great weight, Claudius says, was deposited as an offering to Jupiter,
                    in his temple in the Capitol. The camp of the Gauls was taken and plundered the
                    same day; and the town of Comum was reduced in a few days after. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> In a little time, twenty-eight forts came over to
                    the consul. There is a doubt among writers, whether the consul led his legions
                    first against the Boians, or against the Insubrians; <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> so as to determine, whether the successful battle
                    obliterated the disgrace of the defeat, or whether the victory obtained at Comum
                    was tarnished by the disaster incurred among the Boii. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Soon after those matters had passed with such
                    variety of fortune, Lucius Furius Purpureo, the other consul, came into the
                    country of the Boians, through the Sappinian tribe. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> He proceeded almost to the fort of Mutilus, when, beginning
                    to apprehend that he might be enclosed between the Boians and Ligurians, he
                    marched back by the road by which he came; and, making a long circuit, through
                    an open and therefore safe country, arrived at the camp of his colleague.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After this junction of their forces, they
                    overran the territory of the Boians, spreading devastation as far as the city of
                    Felsina. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This city, with the other fortresses,
                    and almost all the Boians, excepting only the young men who kept arms in their
                    hands for the sake of plunder, and had at that time withdrawn into remote woods,
                    made submission. The army was then led away against the Ligurians. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Boians thought that the Romans, as they were
                    supposed to be at a great distance, would be the more careless in keeping their
                    army together, and thereby afford an opportunity of attacking them un- <pb
                        n="1478" xml:id="p.1478"/> awares: with this expectation, they followed them
                    by secret paths through the forests. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They did
                    not overtake them: and therefore, passing the Po suddenly in ships, they ravaged
                    all the country of the Laevans and Libuans; whence, as they were returning with
                    the spoil of the country, they fell in with the Roman army on the borders of
                    Liguria. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A battle was begun with more speed,
                    and with greater fury, than if the parties had met with their minds prepared,
                    and at an appointed time and place. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On this
                    occasion it appeared to what degree of violence anger can stimulate men; for the
                    Romans fought with such a desire of slaughter, rather than of victory, that they
                    scarcely left one of the enemy to carry the news of their defeat. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> On account of these successes, when the letters of
                    the consuls were brought to Rome, a supplication for three days was decreed.
                    Soon after, Marcellus came to Rome, and had a triumph decreed him by an
                    unanimous vote of the senate. He triumphed, while in office, over the Insubrians
                    and Comans. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The prospect of a triumph over
                    the Boians he left to his colleague, because his own arms had been unfortunate
                    in that country; those of his colleague, successful. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Large quantities of spoils, taken from the enemy, were
                    carried in the procession in captured chariots, and many military standards;
                    also, three hundred and twenty thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> of brass,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1033 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 6
                            <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> two hundred and thirty-four thousand of silver denarii, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 2331 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 2 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> stamped with a chariot. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Eighty <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 5 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 2 1/4
                            <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were bestowed on each foot soldier, and thrice that value on each
                    horseman and centurion. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During that year, king Antiochus, after having
                    spent the winter at Ephesus, took measures for reducing, under his dominion, all
                    the cities of Asia, which had formerly been members of the empire. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> As to the rest, being either situated in plains, or
                    having neither walls, arms, nor men in whom they could confide, he supposed they
                    would, without difficulty, receive the yoke. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But Smyrna and Lampsacus openly asserted their independence: yet there was a
                    danger that if what they claimed were conceded to these, the rest of the cities
                    in Aetolia and Ionia would follow the example of Smyrna; and those on the
                    Hellespont that of Lampsacus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Wherefore he
                    sent an army from Ephesus to invest Smyrna; and ordered the troops, which were
                    at Abydos, to leave there only a small <pb n="1479" xml:id="p.1479"/> garrison,
                    and to go and lay siege to Lampsacus. Nor did he only alarm them by an
                    exhibition of force. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By sending ambassadors,
                    to make gentle remonstrances, and reprove the rashness and obstinacy of their
                    conduct, he endeavoured to give them hopes that they might soon obtain the
                    object of their wishes; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but not until it
                    should appear clearly, both to themselves and to all the world, that they had
                    gained their liberty through the kindness of the king, and not by any violent
                    efforts of their own. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In answer to which, they
                    said, that <quote> Antiochus ought neither to be surprised nor displeased, if
                        they did not very patiently suffer the establishment of their liberty to be
                        deferred to a distant period. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He himself, with his fleet, set sail from
                    Ephesus in the beginning of spring, and steered towards the Hellespont. His army
                    he transported to Madytus, a city in the Chersonese, and there joined his land
                    and sea forces together. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The inhabitants
                    having shut their gates, he surrounded the walls with his troops; and when he
                    was just bringing up his machines to the walls, a capitulation was entered into.
                    This diffused such fear through the inhabitants of Sestus and the other cities
                    of the Chersonese, as induced them to submit. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He then came, with the whole of his united forces, by land and sea, to
                    Lysimachia; which finding deserted, and almost buried in ruins, (for the
                    Thracians had, a few years before, taken, sacked, and burned it,) he conceived a
                    wish to rebuild a city so celebrated, and so commodiously situated. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly, extending his care to every object at
                    once, he set about repairing the walls and <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/>
                    houses, ransomed some of the Lysimachians who were in captivity, sought out and
                    brought home others, who had fled and dispersed themselves through the
                    Chersonese and Hellespontus, enrolled new colonists, whom he invited by
                    prospects of advantages, and used every means to repeople it fully. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> At the same time, that all fear of the Thracians
                    might be removed, he went, in person, with one half of the land forces, to lay
                    waste the nearest provinces of Thrace; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    leaving the other half, and all the crews of the ships, employed in the repairs
                    of the city. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About this time Lucius Cornelius, who had been
                    commissioned by the senate to accommodate the differences between the kings
                    Antiochus and Ptolemy, stopped at Selymbria; and, of the ten ambassadors,
                    Publius Lentulus from <pb n="1480" xml:id="p.1480"/> Bargylii, and Publius
                    Villius and Lucius Terentius from Thasus, came to Lysimachia. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Hither came, likewise, Lucius Cornelius from Selymbria, and
                    a few days after Antiochus from Thrace. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His
                    first meeting with the ambassadors, and an invitation which he afterwards gave
                    them, were friendly and hospitable; but when the business intrusted to them, and
                    the present state of Asia, came to be treated of, the minds of both parties were
                    exasperated. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans did not scruple to
                    declare, that every one of his proceedings, from the time when he set sail from
                    Syria, was displeasing to the senate; and they required restitution to be made,
                    to Ptolemy, of all the cities which had been under his dominion. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> For, as to what related to the cities which had been in the possession
                        of Philip, and which Antiochus, taking advantage of <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> a season when Philip's attention was turned to the war
                        with Rome, had seized into his own hands, it would surely be an intolerable
                        hardship, if the Romans were to have undergone such toils and dangers, on
                        land and sea, for so many years, and Antiochus to appropriate to himself the
                        prizes of the war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But, though his coming
                        into Asia might be passed over unnoticed by the Romans, as a matter not
                        pertaining to them, yet when he proceeded so far as to pass over into Europe
                        with all his land and naval forces, how much was this short of open war with
                        the Romans? Doubtless, had he even passed into Italy, he would deny that
                        intention. But the Romans would not wait to give him an opportunity of doing
                        so. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To this the king replied, that <quote> he
                        wondered how it was, that the Romans were in the habit of diligently
                        inquiring what ought to be done by king Antiochus; but never considered how
                        far they themselves ought to advance on land or sea. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Asia was no concernment of the Romans, in any shape;
                        nor had they any more right to inquire what Antiochus did in Asia, than
                        Antiochus had to inquire what the Roman people did in Italy. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> With respect to Ptolemy, from whom they
                        complained that cities had been taken, there was a friendly connexion
                        subsisting between him and Ptolemy, and he was taking measures to effect
                        speedily a connexion of affinity also; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        neither had he sought to acquire any spoils from the misfortunes of Philip,
                        nor had he come into Europe <pb n="1481" xml:id="p.1481"/> against the
                        Romans, <hi rend="italics"> but to recover the cities and lands of the
                            Chersonese, which, having been the property of Lysimachus, </hi>
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Here is a chasm in the original,
                            which is supplied from Polybius. </note> he considered as part of his
                        own dominion; because, when Lysimachus was subdued, all things belonging to
                        him became, by the right of conquest, the property of Seleucus. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> That, at times, when his predecessors were
                        occupied by cares of different kinds, Ptolemy first, and afterwards Philip,
                        usurping the rights of others, possessed themselves of several of these
                        places, but who could doubt that the Chersonese and the nearest parts of
                        Thrace belonged to Lysimachus? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To restore
                        these to their ancient state, was the intent of his coming, and to build
                        Lysimachia anew, (it having been destroyed by an inroad of the Thracians,)
                        in order that his son, Seleucus, might have it for the seat of his empire.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These disputes had been carried on for several
                    days, when a rumour reached them, but without any sufficiently certain
                    authority, that Ptolemy was dead; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> which
                    prevented the conferences coming to any issue: for both parties made a secret of
                    their having heard it; and Lucius Cornelius, who was charged with the embassy to
                    the two kings, Antiochus and Ptolemy, requested to be allowed a short space of
                    time, in which he could have a meeting with the latter; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> because he wished to arrive in Egypt before any change of
                    measures should take place in consequence of the new succession to the crown:
                    while Antiochus believed that Egypt would be his own, if at that time he should
                    take possession of it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Wherefore, having
                    dismissed the Romans, and left his son Seleucus, with the land forces, to finish
                    the rebuilding of Lysimachia, as he had intended to do, he sailed, with his
                    whole fleet, to Ephesus; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> sent ambassadors to
                    Quinctius to treat with him about an alliance, assuring him that the king would
                    attempt no innovations, and then, coasting along the shore of Asia, proceeded to
                    Lycia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having learned at Patarae that Ptolemy
                    was living, he dropped the design of sailing to Egypt, but nevertheless steered
                    towards Cyprus; and, when he had passed the promontory of Chelidonium, was
                    detained some little time in Pamphylia, near the river Eurymedon, by a mutiny
                    among his rowers. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When he had sailed thence as
                    far as the headlands, as they are called, of Sarus, such a dreadful storm arose
                    as almost buried him and his whole fleet in the deep. Many <pb n="1482"
                        xml:id="p.1482"/> ships were broken to pieces, and many cast on shore; many
                    swallowed so entirely in the sea, that not one man of their crews escaped to
                    land. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Great numbers of his men perished on
                    this occasion; not only persons of mean rank, rowers and soldiers, but even of
                    his particular friends in high stations. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    he had collected the relics of the general wreck, being in no capacity of making
                    an attempt on Cyprus, he returned to Seleucia, with a far less numerous force
                    than he had set out with. Here he ordered the ships to be hauled ashore, for the
                    winter was now at hand, and proceeded to Antioch, where he intended to pass the
                    winter. —In this posture stood the affairs of the kings. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome, in this year, for the first time,
                    were created offices called <hi rend="italics">triumviri epulones;</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">It was their office to regulate the
                        feasts of the gods.</note> these were Caius Licinius Lucullus, who, as
                    tribune, had proposed the law for their creation, Publius Manlius, and Publius
                    Porcius Laeca. These triumvirs, as well as the pontiffs, were allowed by law the
                    privilege of wearing the purple-bordered gown. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The body of the pontiffs had this year a warm dispute with the city quaestors,
                    Quintus Fabius Labeo and Lucius Aurelius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Money was wanted; an order having been passed for making the last payment to
                    private persons of that which had been raised for the support of the war;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and the quaestors demanded it from the
                    augurs and pontiffs, because they had not contributed their share while the war
                    subsisted. The priests in vain appealed to the tribunes; and the contribution
                    was exacted for every year in which they had not paid. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> During the same year two pontiffs died, and others were
                    substituted in their room: Marcus Marcellus, the consul, in the room of Caius
                    Sempronius Tuditanus, who had been a praetor in Spain; and Lucius Valerius, in
                    the room of Marcus Cornelius Cethegus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> An
                    augur also, Quintius Fabius Maximus, died very young, before he had attained to
                    any public office; but no augur was appointed in his place during that year.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consular election was then held by the
                    consul Marcellus. The persons chosen were, Lucius Valerius Flaccus and Marcus
                    Porcius Cato. Then were elected praetors, Caius Fabricius Luscinus, Caius
                    Atinius Labeo, Cneius Manlius Vulso, Appius Claudius Nero, Publius Manlius, and
                    Publius Porcius Laeca. The curule aediles, Marcus Fulvius Nobilior and Caius
                    Flaminius, made a distribution <pb n="1483" xml:id="p.1483"/> to the people of
                    one million pecks of wheat, at the price of two <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This corn the Sicilians had brought to Rome,
                    out of respect to Caius Flaminius and his father; and he gave share of the
                    credit to his colleague. The Roman games were solemnized with magnificence, and
                    exhibited thrice entire. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The plebeian aediles,
                    Cneius Domitius Aenobarbus and Caius Scribonius, chief curio, brought many
                    farmers of the public pastures to trial before the people. Three of these were
                    convicted; and out of the money accruing from fines imposed on them, they built
                    a temple of Faunus in the island. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The
                    plebeian games were exhibited for two days, and there was a <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> feast on occasion of the games. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lucius Valerius Flaccus and Marcus Porcius, on
                    the ides of March, the day of their entering into office, consulted the senate
                    respecting the provinces; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> who resolved, that
                        <quote> whereas the war in Spain was grown so formidable, as to require a
                        consular army and commander; it was their opinion, therefore, that the
                        consuls should either settle between themselves, or cast lots, for Hither
                        Spain and Italy as their provinces. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That
                        he to whom Spain fell should carry with him two legions, five thousand of
                        the Latin confederates, and five hundred horse; together with a fleet of
                        twenty ships of war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That the other consul
                        should raise two legions; for these would be sufficient to maintain
                        tranquillity in the province of Gaul, as the spirits of the Insubrians and
                        Boians had been broken the year before. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The lots gave Spain to Cato, and Italy to
                    Valerius. The praetors then cast lots for their provinces: to Caius Fabricius
                    Luscinus fell the city jurisdiction; Caius Atinius Labeo obtained the foreign;
                    Cneius Manlius Vulso, Sicily; Appius Claudius Nero, Farther Spain; Publius
                    Porcius Laeca, Pisa, in order that he might be at the back of the Ligurians; and
                    Publius Manlius was sent into Hither Spain, as an assistant to the consul.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Quinctius was continued in command for the
                    year, as apprehensions were entertained, not only of Antiochus and the
                    Aetolians, but likewise of Nabis, tyrant of Lacedaemon; and it was ordered that
                    he should have two legions, for which, if there was any necessity for a further
                    supply, the consuls were ordered to raise recruits, and send them into
                    Macedonia. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Appius Claudius was permitted to
                    raise, in addition to the legion which Quintius Fabius had commanded, two
                    thousand foot and two hundred horse. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The <pb
                        n="1484" xml:id="p.1484"/> like number of new-raised foot and horse was
                    assigned to Publius Manlius for Hither Spain; and the legion was given to him
                    which had been under the command of Minucius, the praetor. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> To Publius Porcius Laeca, for Etruria, near Pisa, were
                    decreed two thousand foot and five hundred horse, out of the army in Gaul.
                    Sempronius Longus was continued in command in Sardinia. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The provinces being thus distributed, the
                    consuls, before their departure from the city, were ordered, in accordance with
                    a decree of the pontiffs, to proclaim a <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    sacred spring, which Aulus Cornelius Mammula, praetor, had vowed in pursuance of
                    a vote of the senate, and an order of the people, in the consulate of Cneius
                    Servilius and Caius Flaminius. It was celebrated twenty-one years after the vow
                    had been made. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> About the same time, Caius
                    Claudius Pulcher, son of Appius, was chosen and inaugurated into the office of
                    augur, in the room of Quintus Fabius Maximus, who died the year before.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While people, in general, wondered that,
                    though Spain had arisen in arms, they were neglecting the war, a letter was
                    brought from Quintus Minucius, announcing that he had fought a pitched battle
                    with the Spanish generals, Budar and Besasis, near the town of Tura, and had
                    gained the victory: that twelve thousand of the enemy were slain; their general,
                    Budar, taken; and the rest routed and dispersed." After the reading of this
                    letter less alarm prevailed with respect to Spain, where a very formidable war
                    had been apprehended. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The whole anxiety of the
                    public was directed towards king Antiochus, especially after the arrival of the
                    ten ambassadors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These, after relating the
                    proceedings with Philip, and the conditions on which peace had been granted him,
                    gave information, that <quote> there still subsisted a war of no less magnitude
                        to be waged with Antiochus; that he had come over into Europe with a very
                        numerous fleet and a powerful army; that, had not a delusive prospect of an
                        opportunity of invading Egypt, raised by a more delusive rumour, diverted
                        him to another quarter, all Greece would have quickly been involved in the
                        flames of war. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nor would even the
                        Aetolians remain quiet, a race as well restless by nature as full of anger
                        against the Romans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That, besides, there
                        was another evil, of a most dangerous nature, lurking in the bowels of
                        Greece: Nabis, tyrant at present of Lacedaemon, but who would soon, <pb
                            n="1485" xml:id="p.1485"/> if suffered, become tyrant of all Greece,
                        equalling in avarice and cruelty all the tyrants most remarkable in history.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For, if he were allowed to keep
                        possession of Argos, which served as a citadel commanding the Peloponnesus,
                        when the Roman armies should be brought home to Italy, Greece would have
                        been in vain delivered out of bondage to Philip; because, instead of that
                        king, who, supposing no other difference, resided at a distance, she would
                        have for a master, a tyrant, close to her side. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On this intelligence being received from men
                    of such respectable authority, and who had, besides, examined into all the
                    matters which were reported, the senate, although <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> they deemed the business relating to Antiochus the more
                    important, yet, as the king had, for some reason or other, gone home into Syria,
                    they thought that the affair respecting the tyrant ought to be more promptly
                    attended to. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After debating, for a long time,
                    whether they should judge the grounds which they had at present sufficient
                    whereon a declaration of war should be decreed, or whether they should empower
                    Titus Quinctius to act, in the case respecting Nabis the Lacedaemonian, in such
                    manner as he should judge conducive to the public interest; they left it in his
                    hands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For they thought the business of such a
                    nature, that whether expedited or delayed, it could not very materially affect
                    the general interest of the Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It
                    was deemed more important to endeavour to discover what line of conduct Hannibal
                    and the Carthaginians would pursue, in case of a war breaking out with
                    Antiochus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Persons of the faction which
                    opposed Hannibal wrote continually to their several friends, among the principal
                    men in Rome, that <quote> messages and letters were sent by Hannibal to
                        Antiochus, and that envoys came secretly from the king to him. That, as some
                        wild beasts can never be tamed, so the disposition of this man was
                        irreclaimable and implacable. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That he
                        sometimes complained, that the state was debilitated by ease and indolence,
                        and lulled by sloth into a lethargy, from which nothing could rouse it but
                        the sound of arms. </quote> These accounts were deemed probable, when people
                    recollected the former war, which had not more been carried on than at first set
                    on foot by the efforts of that single man. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Besides, he had by a recent act provoked the resentment of many men in power.
                        <pb n="1486" xml:id="p.1486"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The order of judges possessed, at that time,
                    absolute power in Carthage; and this was owing chiefly to their holding the
                    office during life. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The property, character,
                    and life of every man was in their disposal. He who incurred the displeasure of
                    one of that order, found an enemy in every one of them; nor were accusers
                    wanting in a court where the justices were disposed to condemn. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> While they were in possession of this despotism, (for they
                    did not exercise their exorbitant power constitutionally,) Hannibal was elected
                    praetor; and he summoned the quaestor before him. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The quaestor disregarded the summons, for he was of the
                    opposite faction; and besides, as the practice was that, after the quaestorship
                    men were advanced into the order of judges, the most powerful of all, he already
                    assumed a spirit suited to the powers which he was shortly to possess.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal, highly offended hereat, sent an
                    officer to apprehend the quaestor; and, bringing him forth into an assembly of
                    the people, he made heavy charges not against him alone, but on the whole order
                    of judges; in consequence of whose arrogance and power, neither the magistracy
                    nor the laws availed any thing. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then,
                    perceiving that his discourse was with willing ears attended to, and that the
                    conduct of those men was incompatible with the freedom of the lowest classes, he
                    proposed a law, and procured it to be enacted, that the <quote> judges should be
                        elected annually; and that no person should hold the office two years
                        successively. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But, whatever degree of favour he acquired
                    among the commons by this proceeding, he roused, in a great part of the
                    nobility, an equal degree of resentment. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To
                    this he added another act, which, while it was for the advantage of the people,
                    provoked personal enmity against himself. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    public revenues were partly wasted through neglect, partly embezzled, and
                    divided among some leading men and magistrates; insomuch, that there was not
                    money sufficient for the regular annual payment of the tribute to the Romans, so
                    that private persons seemed to be threatened with a heavy tax. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Hannibal had informed himself of the
                    amount of the revenues arising from taxes and port duties, for what purposes
                    they were issued from the treasury, what proportion of them was consumed by the
                    ordinary expenses of the state, and how much was alienated by embezzlement;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> he asserted <pb n="1487" xml:id="p.1487"/>
                    in an assembly of the people, that if payment were enforced of the residuary
                    funds, the taxes might be remitted to the subjects; and that the state would
                    still be rich enough to pay the tribute to the Romans: which assertion he proved
                    to be true. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But now those persons who, for
                    several years past, had maintained themselves by plundering the public, were
                    greatly enraged; as if this were ravishing from them their own property, and not
                    as dragging out of their hands their ill-gotten spoil. Accordingly, they
                    instigated the Romans against Hannibal, who were seeking a pretext for indulging
                    their hatred against him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A strenuous
                    opposition was, however, for a long time made to this by Scipio Africanus, who
                    thought it highly unbecoming the dignity of the Roman people to make themselves
                    a party in the animosities and charges against Hannibal; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> to interpose the public authority among factions of the
                    Carthaginians, not deeming it sufficient to have conquered that commander in the
                    field, but to become as it were his prosecutors <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Subscribere actioni</hi> is to join the prosecutor as an
                        assistant; and <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the prosecutors were
                        obliged <hi rend="italics">calumniam jurare,</hi> to swear that they did not
                        carry on the prosecution through malice, or a vexatious design. Scipio,
                        therefore, means to reprobate the interference of the Roman state, which
                        would bring it into the situation of a common prosecutor in a court of
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> justice. </note> in a judicial
                    process, and preferring an action against him. Yet at length the point was
                    carried, that an embassy should be sent to Carthage to represent to the senate
                    there, that Hannibal, in concert with king Antiochus, was forming plans for
                    kindling a war. Three <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> ambassadors were sent,
                    Caius Servilius, Marcus Claudius Marcellus, and Quintus Terentius Culleo. These,
                    when they had arrived at Carthage, by the advice of Hannibal's enemies, ordered,
                    that any who inquired the cause of <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> their
                    coming should be told, that they came to determine the disputes subsisting
                    between the Carthaginians and Masinissa, king of Numidia; and this was generally
                    believed. But Hannibal was not ignorant that he was the sole object aimed at by
                    the Romans; and that, though they had granted peace to the Carthaginians, their
                    war against him, individually, remained irreconcilable. He <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> therefore determined to give way to fortune and the times;
                    and having already made every preparation for flight, he showed himself that day
                    in the forum, in order to guard against suspicion; and, as soon as it grew dark,
                    went in his common dress <pb n="1488" xml:id="p.1488"/> to one of the gates,
                    with his two attendants, who knew nothing of his intention. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Finding horses in readiness at a spot where he
                    had ordered, he traversed by night a district which the Africans denominated
                    Byzacium, and arrived, in the morning of the following day, at a castle of his
                    own between Acholla and Thapsus. There a ship, ready fitted out and furnished
                    with rowers, took him on board. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In this manner
                    did Hannibal leave Africa, lamenting the misfortunes of his country oftener than
                    his own. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He sailed over, the same day, to the
                    island of Cercina, where he found in the port a number of merchant ships,
                    belonging to the Phœnicians, with their cargoes; and on landing was surrounded
                    by a concourse of people, who came to pay their respects to him; on which he
                    gave orders, that, in answer to any inquiries, it should be said that he had
                    been sent as ambassador to Tyre. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Fearing,
                    however, lest some of these ships might sail in the night to Thapsus or
                    Adrumetum, and carry information of his having been seen at Cercina, he ordered
                    a sacrifice to be prepared, and the masters of the ships, with the merchants, to
                    be invited to the entertainment, and that the sails and yards should be
                    collected out of the ships to form a shade on shore <milestone n="5??"
                        unit="section"/> for the company at supper, as it happened to be the middle
                    of summer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The feast of the day was as
                    sumptuous, and well attended, as the time and circumstances allowed; and the
                    entertainment was prolonged, with plenty of wine, until late in the night.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as Hannibal saw an opportunity of
                    escaping the notice of those who were in the harbour, he set sail. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The rest were fast asleep, nor was it early, next
                    day, when they arose from their sleep, full of the illness of intoxication; and
                    then, when it was too late, they set about replacing the sails in the ships, and
                    fitting up the rigging, which employed several hours. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> At Carthage, those who were accustomed to visit Hannibal
                    met in a crowd, at the porch of his house; and when it was publicly known that
                    he was not to be found, the whole multitude assembled in <milestone n="10??"
                        unit="section"/> the forum, eager to gain intelligence of the man who was
                    considered as the first in the state. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Some
                    surmised that he had fled, as the case was; others, that he had been put to
                    death through the treachery of the Romans; and there was visible in the
                    expression of their countenances, that variety which might naturally be expected
                    in a state divided <pb n="1489" xml:id="p.1489"/> into factions, whereof each
                    supported a different interest. At length intelligence was brought, that he had
                    been seen at Cercina. </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman ambassadors represented to the
                    council, that <quote> proof had been laid before the senate at Rome, that
                        formerly king Philip had been moved, principally by the instigation of
                        Hannibal, to make war on the Roman people; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        and that lately, Hannibal had, besides, sent letters and messages to king
                        Antiochus, that he had entered into plans for driving Carthage to revolt,
                        and that he had now gone no whither but to king Antiochus. That he was a man
                        who would never be content, until he had excited war in every part of the
                        globe. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> That such conduct ought not to be
                        suffered to pass with impunity, if the Carthaginians wished to convince the
                        Roman people that none of those things were done with their consent, or with
                        the approbation of the state. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Carthaginians answered, that they were
                    ready to do whatever the Romans required them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Hannibal, after a prosperous voyage, arrived
                    at Tyre; where, as a man illustrated by every description of honours, he was
                    received by those founders of Carthage, as if in a se- cond native country, and
                    here he staid a few days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He then sailed to
                    Antioch; where, hearing that the king had already left the place, he procured an
                    interview with his son, who was celebrating the solemnity of the games at
                    Daphne, and who treated him with much kindness; after which, he set sail without
                    delay. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At Ephesus, he overtook the king, who
                    was still hesitating in his mind, and undetermined respecting a war with Rome:
                    but the arrival of Hannibal proved an incentive of no small efficacy to the
                    prosecution of that design. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At the same time,
                    the inclinations of the Aetolians also were alienated from the Roman alliance in
                    consequence of the senate having referred to Quinctius their ambassadors, who
                    demanded Pharsalus and Leucas, and some other cities, in conformity with the
                    first treaty. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
