<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Quintus Caecilius</title>
        <title>for Quintius, Sextus Roscius, Quintus Roscius, Against Quintus Caecilius, and against
          Verres</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
        <editor role="translator" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
            <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
              Yonge</title><idno type="OCLC">4709897</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons</publisher>
              <date>1903</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
          
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>

      <!--<refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:milestone[@n='$1']/tei:milestone[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:milestone[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="chapter" delim="."/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
      <!--
      <refsDecl n="text=Ver.">
        <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
        <refState delim=" " unit="actio"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="book"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="fre">French</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2016-02-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">Moved front matter for more uniform treatment within series.</change>
      <change when="2016-02-05" who="Lisa Cerrato">CTS structure</change>
      <change when="2016-02-02" who="Lisa Cerrato">reorganized change log; added three letter langs;
        revised refsDecl to make section canonical as chapter does not always contain sections (see
        chapter 6) creating conflicting hierarchies</change>
      <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and
        EpiDoc.</change>
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to
        unicode</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2010-09-03"> cleaned up log keyword</change>
      <change who="student" when="2010-07-08"> fixing place tags - AD</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-10-09">more reorganizing of texts module by
        collection</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
      <change who="rsingh04" when="2009-09-22">fixed chunking for cic. ver. to
        text:actio:book:section in order for bibls to work</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2009-06-03">fixed bad bibls</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2006-05-05">fixed date tags</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2006-02-10">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2005-08-01">removed stray item tags</change>
      <change who="packel" when="2005-07-25">Converted to XML</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2003-10-10">fixed four random typos</change>
      <change who="yorkc" when="2003-07-01">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor
        cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="2002-10-02">fixed typo you have not this to you have not heard
        this</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="2000-03-04">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="1996-11-30">revised and proofread again</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="1999-10-14">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
      <change who="lcerrato" when="1999-10-01">fixed valour for velour</change>
      <change who="dasmith" when="1999-08-12">Fixed refsDecl</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Minor tagging changes.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1999-08-04">Lisa's edits.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-09-01">Added sections.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Changed Quint. abbreviation to Quinct.</change>
      <change who="textgod" when="1997-03-26">Added to repository. Passes TEI parsing.</change>
      <change when="1997-03-19" who="DAS">ed.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="lat">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi004.perseus-eng2">
        <head>THE SPEECH AGAINST QUINTUS CAECILIUS.</head>
        
        <div type="commentary" resp="editor">
          <head>The Argument.</head>
        <p>The provinces of the quaestors being distributed to them by lot, the province of <placeName
          key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> fell to Cicero; Sextus Peducaeus being the praetor.
          In his discharge of the duties of his office he very much ingratiated himself with the
          Sicilians, and at his departure he assured them of his assistance in whatever business they
          might have at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. Three years after his return
          from <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> he was elected to the aedileship, being
          now in his thirty-seventh year the earliest age at which a man could be aedile. Before his
          entrance into this office he undertook the prosecution of Caius Verres, late praetor of
          <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, who was accused of having treated the
          Sicilians with the greatest rapacity and tyranny. All the cities of Sicily concurred in this
          prosecution except <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> and <placeName
            key="tgn,7003897">Messana</placeName>, as Verres had kept on good terms with them through
          fear of their riches and influence. The other towns all by a joint petition to Cicero
          entreated him to take the management of the prosecution, and he consented; Verres was
          supported by the Scipios, by the Metelli, and Hortensius. As soon as Cicero had agreed to
          undertake the management of the business, Quintus Caecilius Niger came forth, a Sicilian by
          birth, who had been quaestor to Verres, and (being in reality the tool of Verres, and making
          this demand in order to stifle the prosecution) demanded that the management of it should be
          entrusted to him; partly on the ground that he was a Sicilian, partly because he was, as he
          stated, a personal enemy of Verres, also he alleged, that having been his quaestor in
          <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, he knew better than Cicero could know the
          crimes which Verres really had committed. Cicero replies to this with many reasons why the
          conduct of the prosecution should be committed to him, especially because he did not
          volunteer to take it up, but is urged by a sense of duty, being begged to do so by all the
          Sicilians; and also because he is in ever, respect well able to conduct it, from his
          acquaintance with the count and with the Sicilians.</p>
        <p>There is some question why this speech is called <foreign xml:lang="lat"
          >Divinatio</foreign>, and different reasons have been alleged for it; some saying that it
          is because it refers to what is to be done, not to what has been done: others, that it is so
          called because no witnesses and no documents are produced, and the judges, having to decide
          on the arguments of the speakers alone, are forced to guess their way. Cicero carried his
          point, and the prosecution was entrusted to him. </p></div>
        

        <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>


        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus">
          <p>If any one of you, O judges, or of these who are present here, marvels perhaps at me,
            that I, who have for so many years been occupied in public causes and trials in such a
            manner that I have defended many men but have prosecuted no one could now on a sudden
            change my usual purpose, and descend to act as accuser;—he, if he becomes acquainted
            with the cause and reason of my present intention, will both approve of what I am doing,
            and will think, I am sure, that no one ought to be preferred to me as manager of this
            cause.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus">
          <p>As I had been quaestor in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, O judges,
            and had departed for that province so as to leave among all the Sicilians a pleasing and
            lasting recollection of my quaestorship and of my name, it happened, that while they
            thought their chief protection lay in many of their ancient patrons, they thought there
            was also some support for their fortunes secured in me, who, being now plundered and
            harassed, have all frequently come to me by the public authority, entreating me to
            undertake the cause and the defence of all their fortunes. They say that I repeatedly
            promised and repeatedly assured them, that, if any time should arrive when they wanted
            anything of me, I would not be wanting to their service.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus">
          <p>They said that the time had come for me to defend not only the advantages they enjoyed,
            but even the life and safety of the whole province, that they had now not even any gods
            in their cities to whom they could flee, because Caius Verres had carried off their most
            sacred images from the very holiest temples. That whatever luxury could accomplish in
            the way of vice, cruelty in the way of punishment, avarice in the way of plunder, or
            arrogance in the way of insult, had all been borne by them for the last three years,
            while this one man was praetor. That they begged and entreated that I would not reject
            them as suppliants, who, while I was in safety, ought to be suppliants to no one.</p>
        </div>

        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus">
          <p>I was vexed and distressed, O judges, at being brought into such a strait, as to be
            forced either to let those men's hopes deceive them who had entreated succour and
            assistance of me, or else, when I had from my very earliest youth devoted myself
            entirely to defending men, to be now, under the compulsion of the occasion and of my
            duty, transferred to the part of an accuser. I told them that they had an advocate in
            Quintus Caecilius, who had been quaestor in the same province after I was quaestor
            there. But the very thing which I thought would have been an assistance to me in getting
            rid of this difficulty, was above all things a hindrance to me; for they would have much
            more easily excused me if they had not known him, or if he had never been among them as
            quaestor.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus">
          <p>I was induced, O judges, by the considerations of duty, good faith, and pity; by the
            example of many good men; by the ancient customs and habits of our ancestors, to think
            that I ought to take upon myself this burden of labour and duty, not for any purpose of
            my own, but in the time of need to my friends. In which business, however, this fact
            consoles me, O judges, that this pleading of mine which seems to be an accusation is not
            to be considered an accusation, but rather a defence. For I am defending many men, many
            cities, the whole province of <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. So that,
            if one person is to be accused by me, I still almost appear to remain firm in my
            original purpose, and not entirely to have given up defending and assisting men.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus">
          <p>But if I had this cause so deserving, so illustrious, and so important; if either the
            Sicilians had not demanded this of me, or I had not had such an intimate connection with
            the Sicilians; and if I were to profess that what I am doing I am doing for the sake of
            the republic, in order that a man endowed with unprecedented covetousness, audacity, and
            wickedness,—whose thefts and crimes we have known to be most enormous and most infamous,
            not in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> alone, but in <placeName
              key="tgn,7002733">Achaia</placeName>, in <placeName key="tgn,1000004"
            >Asia</placeName>, in <placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, in <placeName
              key="tgn,7002611">Pamphylia</placeName>, and even at <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
              >Rome</placeName>, before the eyes of all men,—should be brought to trial by my
            instrumentality, still, who would there be who could find fault with my act or my
            intention?</p>
        </div>

        <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus">
          <p>What is there, in the name of gods and men! by which I can at the present moment confer
            a greater benefit on the republic? What is there which either ought to be more pleasing
            to the Roman people, or which can be more desirable in the eves of the allies and of
            foreign nations, or more adapted to secure the safety and fortunes of all men? The
            provinces depopulated, harassed, and utterly overturned; the allies and tributaries of
            the Roman people afflicted and miserable, are seeking now not for any hope of safety,
            but for comfort in their destruction.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus">
          <p>They who wish the administration of justice still to remain in the hands of the
            senatorial body, complain that they cannot procure proper accusers; those who are able
            to act as accusers, complain of the want of impartiality in the decisions. In the
            meantime the Roman people, although it suffers under many disadvantages and
            difficulties, yet desires nothing in the republic so much as the restoration of the
            ancient authority and importance to the courts of law. It is from a regret at the state
            of our courts of law that the restoration of the power of the tribunes <note
              anchored="true">Sulla in his reform of the constitution on the early aristocratic
              principles, left to the tribunes only the <foreign xml:lang="lat">jus
                auxiliandi</foreign>, but deprived them of the right of making legislative or other
              proposals either to the senate or to the comitia without having previously obtained
              the sanction of the Senate. But this arrangement did not last, for Pompeius restored
              them to their former rights. Smith, Dict. Ant. p. 990, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >Tribunis</foreign>.</note> is so eagerly demanded again. It is in consequence of
            the uncertainty of the courts of law, that another class <note anchored="true">Caius
              Gracchus had procured a law to be passed, that the Roman knights should be the judges;
              and they acted as such for forty years. After his victory over Marius, Sulla made a
              law that the judges should be selected from the senate. This arrangement had lasted
              ten years with the effect mentioned here by Cicero; and Aurelius Cotta was at this
              time proposing a law that the judges should be taken from the senators, knights, and
                <foreign xml:lang="lat">tribuni aerarii</foreign>, jointly.</note> is demanded to
            determine law-suits; owing to the crimes and infamy of the judges, even the office of
            censor, which formerly was used to be accounted too severe by the people, is now again
            demanded, and has become popular and praiseworthy.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus">
          <p>In a time of such licentiousness on the part of the wicked, of daily complaint on the
            part of the Roman people, of dishonour in the courts of law, of unpopularity of the
            whole senate, as I thought that this was the only remedy for these numerous evils, for
            men who were both capable and upright to undertake the cause of the republic and the
            laws, I confess that I, for the sake of promoting the universal safety, devoted myself
            to upholding that part of the republic which was in the greatest danger.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus">
          <p>Now that I have shown the motives by which I was influenced to undertake the cause, I
            must necessarily speak of our contention, that, in appointing an accuser, you may have
            some certain line of conduct to follow. I understand the matter thus, O judges:—when any
            man is accused of extortion, if there be a contest between any parties as to who may
            best be entrusted with the prosecution, these two points ought to be regarded most
            especially; first, whom they, to whom the injury is said to have been done, wish most to
            be their counsel; and secondly, whom he, who is accused of having done those injuries,
            would least wish to be so.</p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus">
          <p> In this cause, O judges, although I think both these points plain, yet I will dilate
            upon each, and first on that which ought to have the greatest influence with you, that
            is to say, on the inclination of those to whom the injuries have been done; of those for
            whose sake this trial for extortion has been instituted. Caius Verres is said for three
            years to have depopulated the province of <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
              >Sicily</placeName>, to have desolated the cities of the Sicilians, to have made the
            houses empty, to have plundered the temples. The whole nation of the Sicilians is
            present, and complains of this. They fly for protection to my good faith, which they
            have proved and long known; they entreat assistance for themselves from you and from the
            laws of the Roman people through my instrumentality; they desire me to be their defender
            in these their calamities; they desire me to be the avenger of their injuries, the
            advocate of their rights, and the pleader of their whole cause.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus">
          <p>Will you, O Quintus Caecilius, say this, that I have not approached the cause at the
            request of the Sicilians? or that the desire of those most excellent and most faithful
            allies ought not to be of great influence with these judges? If you dare to say that
            which Caius Verres, whose enemy you are pretending to be, wishes especially to be
            believed,—that the Sicilians did not make this request to me,—you will in the first
            place be supporting the cause of your enemy, against whom it is considered that no vague
            presumption, but that an actual decision has been come to, in the fact that has become
            notorious, that all the Sicilians have begged for me as their advocate against his
            injuries.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus">
          <p>If you, his enemy, deny that this is the case, which he himself to whom the fact is
            most injurious does not dare to deny, take care lest you seem to carry on your enmity in
            too friendly a manner. In the second place, there are witnesses, the most illustrious
            men of our state, all of whom it is not necessary that I should name, those who are
            present I will appeal to; while, if I were speaking falsely, they are the men whom I
            should least wish to be witnesses of my impudence. He, who is one of the assessors on
            this bid, Caius Marcellus, knows it; he, whom I see here present, Cnaeus Lentulus
            Marcellinus, knows it; on whose good faith and protection the Sicilians principally
            depend, because the whole of that province is inalienably connected with the name of the
            Marcelli.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus">
          <p>These men know that this request was not only made to me, but that it was made so
            frequently and with such earnestness, that I had no alternative except either to
            undertake the cause, or to repudiate the duty of friendship. But why do I cite these men
            as witnesses, as if the matter were doubtful or unknown? Most noble men are present here
            from the whole province, who being present, beg and entreat you, O judges, not to let
            your judgment differ from their judgment in selecting an advocate for their cause.
            Deputations from every city in the whole of <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
              >Sicily</placeName>, except two, <note anchored="true">Cicero means <placeName
                key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7003897"
                >Messana</placeName>, which did not join in the outcry against Verres, because
              Verres had resided at <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, and had
              enriched that city with some of the plunder which he had taken from other cities; and
              he had treated <placeName key="tgn,7003897">Messana</placeName> in the same way, which
              place he had made the repository of his plunder till he could export it to <placeName
                key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>.</note> are present; and if deputations from
            those two were present also, two of the very most serious of the crimes would be
            lessened in which these cities are implicated with Caius Verres.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus">
          <p>But why have they entreated this protection from me above all men? If it were doubtful
            whether they had entreated it from me or not, I could tell why they had entreated it;
            but now, when it is so evident that you can see it with your eyes, I know not why it
            should be any injury to me to have it imputed to me that I was selected above all
            men.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus">
          <p>But I do not arrogate any such thing to myself, and I not only do not say it, but I do
            not wish even to leave any one to believe that I have been preferred to every possible
            advocate. That is not the fact but a consideration of the opportunities of each
            individual and of his health, and of his aptitude for conducting this cause, has been
            taken into account. My desire and sentiments on this matter have always been these, that
            I would rather that any one of those who are fit for it should undertake it than I; but
            I had rather that I should undertake it myself than that no one should.</p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus">
          <p>The next thing is, since it is evident that the Sicilians have demanded this of me, for
            us to inquire whether it is right that this fact should have any influence on you and on
            your judgments; whether the allies of the Roman people, your suppliants, ought to have
            any weight with you in a matter of extortion committed on themselves. And why need I say
            much on such a point as this? as if there were any doubt that the whole law about
            extortion was established for the sake of the allies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus">
          <p>For when citizens have been robbed of their money, it is usually sought to be recovered
            by civil action and by a private suit. This is a law affecting the allies,—this is a
            right of foreign nations. They have this fortress somewhat less strongly fortified now
            than it was formerly, but still if there be any hope left which can console the minds of
            the allies, it is all placed in this law. And strict guardians of this law have long
            since been required, not only by the Roman people, but by the most distant nations.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus">
          <p>Who then is there who can deny that it is right that the trial should be conducted
            according to the wish of those men for whose sake the law has been established? All
              <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, if it could speak with one voice,
            would say this:—“All the gold, all the silver, all the ornaments which were in my
            cities, in my private houses, or in my temples,—all the rights which I had in any single
            thing by the kindness of the senate and Roman people,—all that you, O Caius Verres, have
            taken away and robbed me of, on which account I demand of you a hundred million of
              <foreign xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> according to the law.” If the whole
            province, as I have said, could speak, it would say this, and as it could not speak, it
            has of its own accord chosen an advocate to urge these points, whom it has thought
            suitable.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus">
          <p>In a matter of this sort, will any one be found so impudent as to dare to approach or
            to aspire to the conduct of the cause of others against the will of those very people
            whose affairs are involved in it? <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 If, O Quintus
            Caecilius, the Sicilians were to say this to you,—we do not know you—we know not who you
            are, we never saw you before; allow us to defend our fortunes through the
            instrumentality of that man whose good faith is known to us; would they not be saying
            what would appear reasonable to every one? But now they say this—that they know both the
            men, that they wish one of them to be the defender of their cause, that they are wholly
            unwilling that the other should be.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus">
          <p>Even if they were silent they would say plainly enough why they are unwilling. But they
            are not silent; and yet will you offer yourself, when they are most unwilling to accept
            you! Will you still persist in speaking in the cause of others? Will you still defend
            those men who would rather be deserted by every one than defended by you? Will you still
            promise your assistance to those men who do neither believe that you wish to give it for
            their sake, nor that, if you did wish it, you could do it? Why do you endeavour to take
            away from them by force the little hope for the remainder of their fortunes which they
            still retain, built upon the impartiality of the law and of this tribunal? Why do you
            interpose yourself expressly against the will of those whom the law directs to be
            especially consulted? Why do you now openly attempt to ruin the whole fortunes of those
            of whom you did not deserve very well when in the province? Why do you take away from
            them, not only the power of prosecuting their rights, but even of bewailing their
            calamities?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus">
          <p>If you are their counsel, whom do you expect to come forward of those men who are now
            striving, not to punish some one else by your means, but to avenge themselves on you
            yourself, through the instrumentality of some one or other? <milestone n="7"
              unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 But this is a well established fact, that the Sicilians especially
            desire to have me for their counsel; the other point, no doubt, is less clear,—namely,
            by whom Verres would least like to be prosecuted! Did any one ever strive so openly for
            any honour, or so earnestly for his own safety, as that man and his friends have striven
            to prevent this prosecution from being entrusted to me? There are many qualities which
            Verres believes to be in me, and which he knows, O Quintus Caecilius, do not exist in
            you: and what qualities each of us have I will mention presently;</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus">
          <p>at this moment I will only say this, which you must silently agree to, that there is no
            quality in me which he can despise, and none in you which he can fear. Therefore, that
            great defender <note anchored="true">Cicero alludes to Hortensius, indeed, the name of
              Hortensius appears in the text in some editions.</note> and friend of his votes for
            you and opposes me; he openly solicits the judges to have you preferred to me; and he
            says that he does this honestly, without any envy of me, and without any dislike to me.
            “For,” says he, “I am now asking for that which I usually obtain when I strive for it
            earnestly. I am not asking to have the defendant acquitted; but I am asking this, that
            he may be accused by the one man rather than by the other. Grant me this; grant that
            which is easy to grant, and honourable, and by no means invidious; and when you have
            granted that, you will, without any risk to yourself, and without any discredit, have
            granted that he shall be acquitted in whose cause I am labouring.”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus">
          <p>He says also, in order that some alarm may be mingled with the exertion of his
            influence, that there are certain men on the bench to whom he wishes their tablets to be
            shown, and that that is very easy, for that they do not give their votes separately, but
            that all vote together; and that a tablet, <note anchored="true">“The judges were
              provided with three <foreign xml:lang="lat">tabellae</foreign>, one of which was
              marked with A, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="lat">absolvo</foreign>, I acquit; the second
              with C, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="lat">condemno</foreign>, condemn; and the third with N
              L, i.e. <foreign xml:lang="lat">non liquet</foreign>. It is not clear to me, why
              Cicero (<bibl n="Cic. Mil. 6">pro Mil. 6</bibl>) calls the first <foreign
                xml:lang="lat">litera salutaris</foreign>, and the second <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >litera tristis</foreign>. It would seem that in some trials the tabellae were
              marked with the lettera L, <foreign xml:lang="lat">libero</foreign>, and D, <foreign
                xml:lang="lat">damno</foreign>, respectively.” Smith's Dict. Ant. v. <foreign
                xml:lang="lat">Tabella</foreign>. In trials like this between Cicero and Caecilius
              it is probable that the two tabellae had the names of the different candidates
              inscribed on them. The circumstance alluded to in the text was that a short time
              before this Terentius Varro had been accused of extortion and defended by Hortensius,
              who bribed the judges, and then in order to be sure that they voted as they had
              promised, caused tablets to be given to them smeared with coloured wax, so that he
              could easily recognize their votes in the balloting urn.</note> covered with the
            proper wax, and not with that illegal wax which has given so much scandal, is given to
            every one. And he does not give himself all this trouble so much for the sake of Verres,
            as because he disapproves of the whole affair. For he sees that, if the power of
            prosecuting is taken away from the high-born boys whom he has hitherto played with, and
            from the public informers, whom he has always despised and thought insignificant (not
            without good reason), and to be transferred to fearless men of well-proved constancy, he
            will no longer be able to domineer over the courts of law as he pleases.</p>
        </div>

        <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus">
          <p>I now beforehand give this man notice, that if you determine that this cause shall be
            conducted by me, his whole plan of defence must be altered, and must be altered in such
            a manner as to be carried on in a more honest and honourable way than he likes; that he
            must imitate those most illustrious men whom he himself has seen, Lucius Crassus and
            Marcus Antonius; who thought that they had no right to bring anything to the trials and
            causes in which their friends were concerned, except good faith and ability. He shall
            have no room for thinking, if I conduct the case, that the tribunal can be corrupted
            without great danger to many.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26" resp="perseus">
          <p>In this trial I think that the cause of the Sicilian nation,—that the cause of the
            whole Roman people, is undertaken by me; so that I have not to crush one worthless man
            alone, which is what the Sicilians have requested, but to extinguish and extirpate every
            sort of iniquity, which is what the Roman people has been long demanding. And how far I
            labour in this cause, or what I may be able to effect, I would rather leave to the
            expectations of others, than set forth in my own oration.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27" resp="perseus">
          <p>But as for you, O Caecilius, what can you do? On what occasion, or in what affair, have
            you, I will not say given proof to others of your powers! but even made trial of
            yourself to yourself? Has it never occurred to you how important a business it is to
            uphold a public cause? to lay bare the whole life of another? and to bring it palpably
            before, not only the minds of the judges, but before the very eyes and sight of all men;
            to defend the safety of the allies, the interests of the provinces, the authority of the
            laws, and the dignity of the judgment-seat? <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 Judge by
            me, since this is the first opportunity of learning it that you have ever had, how many
            qualities must meet in that man who is the accuser of another: and if you recognise any
            one of these in yourself, I will, of my own accord, yield up to you that which you are
            desirous of. First of all, he must have a singular integrity and innocence. For there is
            nothing which is less tolerable than for him to demand an account of his life from
            another who cannot give an account of his own. Here I will not say any more of yourself.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28" resp="perseus">
          <p>This one thing, I think, all may observe, that up to this time you had no opportunity
            of becoming known to any people except to the Sicilians; and that the Sicilians say
            this, that even though they are exasperated against the same man, whose enemy you say
            that you are, still, if you are the advocate, they will not appear on the trial. Why
            they refuse to, you will not hear from me. Allow these judges to suspect what it is
            inevitable that they must. The Sicilians, indeed, being a race of men over-acute, and
            too much inclined to suspiciousness, suspect that you do not wish to bring documents
            from <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> against Verres; but, as both his
            praetorship and your quaestorship are recorded in the same documents, they suspect that
            you wish to remove <note anchored="true">The Latin is <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >deportare</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="lat">asportare</foreign>, the former
              meaning to remove from one place to another, the latter to carry away; “but it seems
              by implication here, to carry them away with the intention of suppressing
              them.”—Long.</note> them out of <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29" resp="perseus">
          <p>In the second place, an accuser must be trustworthy and veracious. Even if I were to
            think that you were desirous of being so, I easily see that you are not able to be so.
            Nor do I speak of these things, which, if I were to mention, you would not be able to
            invalidate, namely that you, before you departed from <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
              >Sicily</placeName>, had become reconciled to Verres; that Potamo, your secretary and
            intimate friend, was retained by Verres in the province when you left it; that Marcus
            Caecilius, your brother, a most exemplary and accomplished young man, is not only not
            present here and does not stand by you while prosecuting your alleged injuries, but that
            he is with Verres, and is living on terms of the closest friendship and intimacy with
            him. These, and other things belonging to you, are many signs of a false accuser; but
            these I do not now avail myself of. I say this, that you, if you were to wish it ever so
            much, still cannot be a faithful accuser.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30" resp="perseus">
          <p>For I see that there are many charges in which you are so implicated with Verres, that
            in accusing him, you would not dare to touch upon them. 
            <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
            All Sicily complains that Caius Verres, when he had ordered corn to be brought into
            his granary for him, and when a bushel of wheat was two <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign>, demanded of the farmers twelve <foreign xml:lang="lat"
              >sesterces</foreign> a bushel for wheat. <note anchored="true">The praetor had the
              power to make an annual demand on the farmers for corn for be state, and the quaestor
              was to pay a fair market price for it; but in some cases the praetor allowed or
              compelled the farmer to pay a composition in money, instead of delivering corn, and
              Verres when the market price of wheat was only two <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >sesterces</foreign> a bushel compelled the farmers to pay twelve <foreign
                xml:lang="lat">sesterces</foreign> a bushel by way of composition</note> It was a
            great crime, an immense sum, an impudent theft, an intolerable injustice. I must
            inevitably convict him of this charge; what will you do, O Caecilius?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31" resp="perseus">
          <p>Will you pass over this serious accusation, or will you bring it forward? If you bring
            it forward, will you charge that as a crime against another, which you did yourself at
            the same time in the same province? Will you dare so to accuse another, that you cannot
            avoid at the same time condemning yourself? If you omit the charge, what sort of a
            prosecution will yours be, which from fear of danger to yourself, is afraid not only to
            create a suspicion of a most certain and enormous crime, but even to make the least
            mention of it? Corn was bought, on the authority of a decree of the senate, of the
            Sicilians while Verres was praetor; </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32" resp="perseus">
          <p>for which corn all the money was not paid. This is a grave charge against Verres; a
            grave one if I plead the cause, but, if you are the prosecutor, no charge at all. For
            you were the quaestor, you had the handling of the public money; and, even if the
            praetor desired it ever so much, yet it was to a great extent in your power to prevent
            anything being taken from it. Of this crime, therefore, if you are the prosecutor, no
            mention will be made. And so during the whole trial nothing will be said of his most
            enormous and most notorious thefts and injuries. Believe me, O Caecilius, he who is
            connected with the criminal in a partnership of iniquity, cannot really defend his
            associates while accusing him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33" resp="perseus">
          <p>The contractors exacted money from the cities instead of corn. Well! was this never
            done except in the praetorship of Verres? I do not say that, but it was done while
            Caecilius was quaestor. What then will you do? Will you urge against this man as a
            charge, what you both could and ought to have prevented from being done? or will you
            leave out the whole of it? Verres, then, at his trial will absolutely never hear at all
            of those things, which, when he was doing them, he did not know how he should be able to
            defend. <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 And I am mentioning those matters which lie
            on the surface. There are other acts of plunder more secret, which he, in order, I
            suppose, to check the courage and delay the attack of Caecilius, has very kindly
            participated in with his quaestor. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34" resp="perseus">
          <p>You know that information of these matters has been given to me; and if I were to
            choose to mention them, all men would easily perceive that there was not only a perfect
            harmony of will subsisting between you both, but that you did not pursue even your
            plunder separately. So that if you demand to be allowed to give information of the
            crimes which Verres has committed in conjunction with you, I have no objection, if it is
            allowed by the law. But if we are speaking of conducting the prosecution, that you must
            yield ta those who are hindered by no crimes of their own from being able to prove the
            offences of another.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35" resp="perseus">
          <p>And see how much difference there will be between my accusation and yours. I intend to
            charge Verres with all the crimes that you committed, though he had no share in them,
            because he did not prevent you from committing them, though he had the supreme power;
            you, on the other hand, will not allege against him even the crimes which he committed
            himself, lest you should be found to be in any particular connected with him. What shall
            I say of these other points, O Caecilius? Do these things appear contemptible to you,
            without which no cause, especially no cause of such importance, can by any means be
            supported? Have you any talent for pleading? any practice in speaking? Have you paid any
            attention or acquired any acquaintance with the forum, the courts, and the laws?</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36" resp="perseus">
          <p>I know in what a rocky and difficult path I am now treading; for as all arrogance is
            odious, so a conceit of one's abilities and eloquence is by far the most disagreeable of
            all. On which account I say nothing of my own abilities; for I have none worth speaking
            of, and if I had I would not speak of them. For either the opinion formed of me is quite
            sufficient for me, such as it is; or if it be too low an opinion to please me, still I
            cannot make it higher by talking about them.</p>
        </div>

        <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37" resp="perseus">
          <p>I will just, O Caecilius, say this much familiarly to you about yourself, forgetting
            for a moment this rivalry and contest of ours. Consider again and again what your own
            sentiments are, and recollect yourself; and consider who you are, and what you are able
            to effect. Do you think that, when you have taken upon yourself the cause of the allies,
            and the fortunes of the province, and the rights of the Roman people, and the dignity of
            the judgment-seat and of the law, in a discussion of the most important and serious
            matters, you are able to support so many affairs and those so weighty and so various
            with your voice, your memory, your counsel, and your ability?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38" resp="perseus">
          <p>Do you think that you are able to distinguish in separate charges, and in a
            well-arranged speech, all that Caius Verres has done in his quaestorship, and in his
            lieutenancy, and in his praetorship, at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>,
            or in <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, or in <placeName key="tgn,7002733"
              >Achaia</placeName>, or in <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>, or in
              <placeName key="tgn,7002611">Pamphylia</placeName>, as the actions themselves are
            divided by place and time? Do you think that you are able (and this is especially
            necessary against a defendant of this sort) to cause the things which he has done
            licentiously, or wickedly, or tyrannically, to appear just as bitter and scandalous to
            those who hear of them, as they did appear to those who felt them?</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39" resp="perseus">
          <p>Those things which I am speaking of are very important, believe me. Do not you despise
            this either; everything must be related, and demonstrated, and explained; the cause must
            be not merely stated, but it must also be gravely and copiously dilated on. You must
            cause, if you wish really to do and to effect anything, men not only to hear you, but
            also to hear you willingly and eagerly. And if nature kind been bountiful to you in such
            qualities, and if from your childhood you had studied the best arts and systems, and
            worked hard at them;—if you had learnt Greek literature at <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, not at <placeName key="tgn,7003850"
              >Lilybaeum</placeName>, and Latin literature at <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
              >Rome</placeName>, and not in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>; still
            it would be a great undertaking to approach so important a cause, and one about which
            there is such great expectation, and having approached it, to follow it up with the
            requisite diligence; to have all the particulars always fresh in your memory; to discuss
            it properly in your speech, and to support it adequately with your voice and your
            faculties.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40" resp="perseus">
          <p>Perhaps you may say, What then? Are you then endowed with all these qualifications?—I
            wish indeed that I were; but at all events I have laboured with great industry from my
            very childhood to attain them. And if I, on account of the importance and difficulty of
            such a study have not been able to attain them, who have done nothing else all my life,
            how far do you think that you must be distant from these qualities, which you have not
            only never thought of before, but which even now, when you are entering on a stage that
            requires them all, you can form no proper idea of, either as for their nature or as to
            their importance? </p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41" resp="perseus">
          <p>I, who as all men know, am so much concerned in the forum and the courts of justice,
            that there is no one of the same age, or very few, who have defended more causes, and
            who spend all my time which can be spared from the business of my friends in these
            studies and labours, in order that I may be more prepared for forensic practice and more
            ready at it, yet, (may the gods be favourable to me as I am saying what is true!)
            whenever the thought occurs to me of the day when the defendant having been summoned, I
            have to speak, I am not only agitated in my mind, but a shudder runs over my whole
            body.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42" resp="perseus">
          <p>Even now I am surveying in my mind and thoughts what party spirit will be shown by men;
            what throngs of men will meet; how great an expectation the importance of the trial will
            excite; how greet a multitude of hearers the infamy of Caius Verres will collect; how
            great an audience for my speech his wickedness will draw together And when I think of
            these things, even now I am afraid as to what I shall be able to say suitable to the
            hatred men bear him who are inimical and hostile to him, and worthy of the expectation
            which all men will form, and of the importance of the case.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43" resp="perseus">
          <p>Do you fear nothing, do you think of nothing are you anxious about nothing of all this?
            Or if from some old speech you have been able to learn, “I entreat the mighty and
            beneficent <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>,” or, “I wish it were
            possible, O judges,” or something of the sort, do you think that you shall come before
            the court in an admirable state of preparation? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44" resp="perseus">
          <p>And, even if no one were to answer you, yet you would not, as I think, be able to state
            and prove even the cause itself. Do you now never give it a thought, that you will have
            a contest with a most eloquent man, and one in a perfect state of preparation for
            speaking, with whom you will at one time have to argue, and at another time to strive
            and contend against him with all your might? Whose abilities indeed I praise greatly,
            but not so as to be afraid of them, and think highly of, thinking however at the same
            time that I am more easily to be pleased by them than cajoled by them. <milestone n="14"
              unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 He will never put me down by his acuteness; he will never put me out
            of countenance by any artifice; he will never attempt to upset and dispirit me by
            displays of his genius. I know all the modes of attack and every system of speaking the
            man has. We have often been employed on the same, often on opposite sides. Ingenious as
            he is, he will plead against me as if he were aware that his own ability is to same
            extent put on its trial.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45" resp="perseus">
          <p>But as for you, O Caecilius, I think that I see already how he will play with you, how
            he will bandy you about; how often he will give you power and option of choosing which
            alternative you please,—whether a thing were done or not, whether a thing be true or
            false; and whichever side you take will be contrary to your interest. What a heat you
            will be in, what bewilderment! what darkness, O ye immortal gods! will overwhelm the
            man, free from malice as he is. What will you do when he begins to divide the different
            counts of your accusation, and to arrange on his fingers each separate division of the
            cause? What will you do when he begins to deal with each argument, to disentangle it, to
            get rid of it? You yourself in truth will begin to be afraid lest you have brought an
            innocent man into danger. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46" resp="perseus">
          <p>What will you do when he begins to pity his client, to complain, and to take off some
            of his unpopularity from him and transfer it to you? to speak of the close connection
            necessarily subsisting between the quaestor and the praetor? of the custom of the
            ancients? of the holy nature of the connection between those to whom the same province
            was by lot appointed? Will you be able to encounter the odium such a speech will excite
            against you? Think a moment; consider again and again. For there seems to me to be
            danger of his overwhelming you not with words only, but of his blunting the edge of your
            genius by the mere gestures and motions of his body, and so distracting you and leading
            you away from every previous thought and purpose. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47" resp="perseus">
          <p>And I see that the trial of this will be immediate; for if you are able today to answer
            me and these things which I am saying; if you even depart one word from that book which
            some elocution-master or other has given you, made up of other men's speeches; I shall
            think that you are able to speak, and that you are not unequal to that trial also, and
            that you will be able to do justice to the cause and to the duty you undertake. But if
            in this preliminary skirmish with me you turn out nothing, what can we suppose you will
            be in the contest itself against a most active adversary? <milestone n="15"
              unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 Be it so; he is nothing himself, he has no ability; but he comes
            prepared with well-trained and eloquent supporters. And this too is something, though it
            is not enough; for in all things he who is the chief person to act, ought to be the most
            accomplished and the best prepared. But I see that Lucius Appuleius is the next counsel
            on the list, a mere beginner, not as to his age indeed, but as to his practice and
            training in forensic contests. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48" resp="perseus">
          <p>Next to him he has, as I think, Allienus; he indeed does belong to the bar, but
            however, I never took any particular notice of what he could do in speaking; in raising
            an outcry, indeed, I see that he is very vigorous and practiced. In this man all your
            hopes are placed; he, if you are appointed prosecutor, will sustain the whole trial. But
            even he will not put forth his whole strength in speaking, but will consult your credit
            and reputation; and will abstain from putting forth the whole power of eloquence which
            he himself possesses, in order that you may still appear of some importance As we see is
            done by the Greek pleaders; that he to whom the second or third part belongs, though he
            may be able to speak somewhat better than his leader, often restrains himself a good
            deal, in order that the chief may appear to the greatest possible advantage, so will
            Allienus act; he will be subservient to you, he will pander to your interest, he will
            put forth somewhat less strength than he might. </p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49" resp="perseus">
          <p>Now consider this, O judges, what sort of accusers we shall have in this most important
            trial; when Allienus himself will somewhat abstain from displaying all his abilities, if
            he has any, and Caecilius will only be able to think himself of any use, because
            Allienus is not so vigorous as he might be, and voluntarily allows him the chief share
            in the display. What fourth counsel he is to have with him I do not know, unless it be
            one of that crowd of losers of time who have entreated to be allowed an inferior part in
            this prosecution, whoever he might be to whom you gave the lead. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50" resp="perseus">
          <p>And you are to appear in just this state of preparation, that you have to make friends
            of those men who are utter strangers to you, for the purpose of obtaining their
            assistance. But I will not do these men so much honour as to answer what they have said
            in any regular order, or to give a separate answer to each; but since I have come to
            mention them not intentionally, but by chance, I will briefly, as I pass, satisfy them
            all in a few words. <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 Do I seem to you to be in such
            exceeding want of friends that I must have an assistant given me, chosen not out of the
            men whom I have brought down to court with me, but out of the people at large? And are
            you suffering under such a dearth of defendants, that you endeavour to filch this cause
            from me rather than look for some defendants of your own class at the pillar of Maenius?
              <note anchored="true">Maenius had sold his house to Cato and Valerius Flaccus when
              they were censors, and they had built the Porcian Piazza on the spot, but he had
              reserved for himself one pillar for him and his heirs to have a view of the
              gladiatorial contests from it; and near this column the <foreign xml:lang="lat"
                >triumviricapitates</foreign> held their court, before whose tribunal it was chiefly
              the lower sort of criminals who were brought, and as a general rule the advocates who
              practised in these courts were of a lower class than those who confined themselves to
              more respectable clients, and to civil actions.</note></p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51" resp="perseus">
          <p>Appoint me, says he, to watch Tullius. What? How many watchers shall I have need of, if
            I once allow you to meddle with my bag? as you will have to be watched not only to
            prevent your betraying anything, but to prevent your removing anything. But for the
            whole matter of that watchman I will answer you thus in the briefest manner possible;
            that these honest judges will never permit any assistant to force himself against my
            consent into so important a cause, when it has been undertaken by me, and is entrusted
            to me.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52" resp="perseus">
          <p>In truth, my integrity rejects an overlooker; my diligence is afraid of a spy. But to
            return to you, O Caecilius, you see how many qualities are wanting to you; how many
            belong to you which a guilty defendant would wish to belong to his prosecutor, you are
            well aware. What can be said to this? For I do not ask what you will say yourself, I see
            that it is not you who will answer me, but this book which your prompter has in his
            hand; who, if he be inclined to prompt you rightly, will advise you to depart from this
            place and not to answer me one word. For what can you say? That which you are constantly
            repeating, that Verres has done you an injury? I have no doubt he has, for it would not
            be probable, when he was doing injuries to all the Sicilians, that you alone should be
            so important in his eyes that he should take care of your interests. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53" resp="perseus">
          <p> But the rest of the Sicilians have found an avenger of their injuries; you, while you
            are endeavouring to exact vengeance for your injuries by your own means, (which you will
            not be able to effect,) are acting in a way to leave the injuries of all the rest
            unpunished and unavenged. And you do not see that it ought not alone to be considered
            who is a proper person to exact vengeance, but also who is a person capable of doing
            so,—that if there be a man in whom both these qualifications exist, he is the best man.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54" resp="perseus">
          <p> But if a man has only one of them, then the question usually asked is, not what he is
            inclined to do, but what he is able to do. And if you think that the office of
            prosecutor ought to be entrusted to him above all other men, to whom Caius Verres has
            done the greatest injury, which do you think the judges ought to be most indignant
            at,—at your having been injured by him, or at the whole province of <placeName
              key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> having been harassed and ruined by him? I think
            you must grant that this both is the worst thing of the two, and that it ought to be
            considered the worst by every one. A flow, therefore, that the province ought to be
            preferred to you as the prosecutor. For the province is prosecuting when he is pleading
            the cause whom the province has adopted as the defender of her rights, the avenger of
            her injuries, and the pleader of the whole cause. </p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55" resp="perseus">
          <p>Oh, but Caius Verres has done you such an injury as might afflict the minds of all the
            rest of the Sicilians also, though the grievance was felt only by another. Nothing of
            the sort. For I think it is material also to this argument to consider what sort of
            injury is alleged and brought forward as the cause of your enmity. Allow me to relate
            it. For he indeed, unless he is wholly destitute of sense, will never say what it is.
            There is a woman of the name of Agonis, a Lilybaean, a freedwoman of Venus Erycina; a
            woman who before this man was quaestor was notoriously well off and rich. From her some
            prefect of Antonius's <note anchored="true">Antonius had been appointed as naval
              commander-in-chief along the whole coast; in which capacity it was that he made his
              unauthorized attack on <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, which gave rise
              to the war in which the island was reduced by Metellus Creticus.</note> carried off
            some musical slaves whom he said he wished to use in his fleet. Then she, as is the
            custom in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> for all the slaves of
                <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName>, and all those who have procured their
            emancipation from her, in order to hinder the designs of the prefect, by the scruples
            which the name of <persName><surname>Venus</surname></persName> would raise, said that
            she and all her property belonged to Venus. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56" resp="perseus">
          <p> When this was reported to Caecilius, that most excellent and upright man, he ordered
            Agonis to be summoned before him; he immediately orders a trial to ascertain “if it
            appeared that she had said that she and all her property belonged to Venus.” The
            recuperators <note anchored="true">“In many cases a single judex was appointed, in
              others several were appointed, and they seem sometimes to have been called <foreign
                xml:lang="lat">recuperatores</foreign>, as opposed to the single judex.”—Smith,
              Dict. Ant. p. 529, v. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Judex</foreign>.</note> decide all that
            was necessary, and indeed there was no doubt at all that she had said so. He sends men
            to take possession of the woman's property. He adjudges her herself to be again a slave
            of Venus; then he sells her property and confiscates the money. So while Agonis wishes
            to keep a few slaves under the name and religious protection of Venus, she loses all her
            fortunes and her own liberty by the wrong doing of that man. After that, Verres comes to
              <placeName key="tgn,7003850">Lilybaeum</placeName>; he takes cognisance of the affair;
            he disapproves of the act; he compels his quaestor to pay back and restore to its owner
            all the money which he had confiscated, having been received for the property of
            Agonis.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57" resp="perseus">
          <p> He is here, and you may well admire it, no longer Verres, but Quintus Mucius. <note
              anchored="true">“Quintus Mucius Scaevola is spoken of here, who in be year A.U.C. 660
              was sent as proconsul to <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName>, where he
              governed with such justice and strictness that the senate afterwards by formal decree
              reminded magistrates about to depart for that province of his
              example.”—Hottoman.</note> For what could he do more delicate to obtain a high
            character among men? what more just to relieve the distress of the women? what more
            severe to repress the licentiousness of his quaestor? All this appears to me most
            exceedingly praiseworthy. But at the very next step, in a moment, as if he had drank of
            some Circaean cup, having been a man, he becomes Verres again; he returns to himself and
            to his old habits. For of that money he appropriated a great share to himself, and
            restored to the woman only as much as he chose. </p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58" resp="perseus">
          <p>Here now if you say that you were offended with Verres, I will grant you that and allow
            it; if you complain that he did you any injury, I will defend him and deny it. Secondly,
            I say that of the injury which was done to you no one of us ought to be a more severe
            avenger than you yourself, to whom it is said to have been done. If you afterwards
            became reconciled to him, if you were often at his house, if he after that supped with
            you, do you prefer to be considered as acting with treachery or by collusion with him? I
            see that one of these alternatives is inevitable, but in this matter I will have no
            contention with you to prevent your adopting which you please. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59" resp="perseus">
          <p> What shall I say if even the pretext of that injury which was done to you by him no
            longer remains? What have you then to say why you should be preferred, I will not say to
            me, but to any one? except that which I hear you intend to say, that you were his
            quaestor: which indeed would be an important allegation if you were contending with me
            as to which of us ought to be the most friendly to him; but in a contention as to which
            is to take up a quarrel against him, it is ridiculous to suppose that an intimate
            connection with him can be a just reason for bringing him into danger.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60" resp="perseus">
          <p> In truth, if you had received ever so many injuries from your praetor, still you would
            deserve greater credit by bearing them than by revenging them; but when nothing in his
            life was ever done more rightly than that which you call an injury, shall these judges
            determine that this cause, which they would not even tolerate in any one else, shall
            appear in your case to be a reasonable one to justify the violation of your ancient
            connection? When even if you had received the greatest injury from him, still, since you
            have been his quaestor, you cannot accuse him and remain blameless yourself. But if no
            injury has been done you at all, you cannot accuse him without wickedness; and as it is
            very uncertain whether any injury has been done you, do you think that there is any one
            of these men who would not prefer that you should depart without incurring blame rather
            than after having committed wickedness?</p>
        </div>

        <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61" resp="perseus">
          <p>And just think how great is the difference between my opinion and yours. You, though
            you are in every respect inferior to me, still think that you ought to be preferred to
            me for this one reason, because you were his quaestor. I think, that if you were my
            superior in every other qualification, still that for this one cause alone you ought to
            be rejected as the prosecutor. For this is the principle which has been handed down to
            us from our ancestors, that a praetor ought to be in the place of a parent to his
            quaestor; that no more reasonable nor more important cause of intimate friendship can be
            imagined than a connection arising from drawing the same lot, having the same province,
            and being associated in the discharge of the same public duty and office. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62" resp="perseus">
          <p> Wherefore, even if you could accuse him without violating strict right, still, as he
            had been in the place of a parent to you, you could not do so without violating every
            principle of piety. But as you have not received any injury, and would yet be creating
            danger for your praetor, you must admit that you are endeavouring to wage an unjust and
            impious war against him. In truth, your quaestorship is an argument of so strong a
            nature, that you would have to take a great deal of pains to find an excuse for accusing
            him to whom you had acted as quaestor, and can never be a reason why you should claim on
            that account to have the office of prosecuting him entrusted to you above all men. Nor
            indeed, did any one who had acted as quaestor to another, ever contest the point of
            being allowed to accuse him without being rejected.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63" resp="perseus">
          <p> And therefore, neither was permission given to Lucius Philo to bring forward an
            accusation against Caius Servilius, nor to Marcus Aurelius Scaurus to prosecute Lucius
            Flaccus, nor to Cnaeus Pompeius to accuse Titus Albucius; not one of whom was refused
            this, permission because of any personal unworthiness, but in order that the desire to
            violate such an intimate connection might not be sanctioned by the authority of the
            judges. And that great man Cnaeus Pompeius contended about that matter with Caius
                <persName><surname>Julius</surname></persName>, just as you are contending with me.
            For he had been the quaestor of Albucius, just as you were of Verres: Julius had on his
            side this reason for conducting the prosecution, that, just as we have now been
            entreated by the Sicilians, so he had then been entreated by the Sardinians, to espouse
            their cause. And this argument has always had the greatest influence; this has always
            been the most honourable cause for acting as accuser, that by so doing one is bringing
            enmity on oneself in behalf of allies, for the sake of the safety of a province, for the
            advantage of foreign nations—that one is for their sakes incurring danger, and spending
            much care and anxiety and labour. </p>
        </div>
        <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64" resp="perseus">
          <p>Even if the cause of those men who wish to revenge their own injuries be ever so
            strong, in which matter they are only obeying their own feelings of indignation, not
            consulting the advantage of the republic: how much more honourable is that cause, which
            is not only reasonable, but which ought to be acceptable to all,—that a man, without
            having received any private injury to himself, should be influenced by the sufferings
            and injuries of the allies and friends of the Roman people! When lately that most brave
            and upright man Lucius <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName> demanded to be
            allowed to prefer an accusation against Publius Gabinius, and when Quintus Caecilius
            claimed the same permission in opposition to
              <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName>, and said that in so doing he was
            following up an old quarrel which he had long had with Gabinius; it was not only the
            authority and dignity of Piso which had great weight, but also the superior justice of
            his cause, because the Achaeans had adopted him as their patron. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65" resp="perseus">
          <p> In truth, when the very law itself about extortion is the protectress of the allies
            and friends of the Roman people, it is an iniquitous thing that he should not, above all
            others, he thought the fittest advocate of the law and conductor of the trial, whom the
            allies wish, above all men, to be the pleader of their cause, and the defender of their
            fortunes. Or ought not that which is the more honourable to mention, to appear also far
            the most reasonable to approve of? Which then is the more splendid, which is the more
            honourable allegation—“I have prosecuted this man to whom I had acted as quaestor, with
            whom the lot cast for the provinces, and the custom of our ancestors, and the judgment
            of gods and men had connected me,” or, “I have prosecuted this man at the request of the
            allies and friends of the Roman people, I have been selected by the whole province to
            defend its rights and fortunes?” Can any one doubt that it is more honourable to act as
            prosecutor in behalf of those men among whom you have been quaestor, than as prosecutor
            of him whose quaestor you have been? </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66" resp="perseus">
          <p> The most illustrious men of our state, in the best of times, used to think this most
            honourable and glorious for them to ward off injuries from their hereditary friends, and
            from their clients, and from foreign nations which were either friends or subjects of
            the Roman people, and to defend their fortunes. We learn from tradition that Marcus
            Cato, that wise man, that most illustrious and most prudent man, brought upon himself
            great enmity from many men, on account of the injuries of the Spaniards among whom he
            had been when consul. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67" resp="perseus">
          <p> We know that lately Cnaeus Domitius prosecuted Marcus Silanus on account of the
            injuries of one man, Egritomarus, his father's friend and comrade. <milestone n="21"
              unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>
 Nor indeed has anything ever had more influence over the minds of
            guilty men than this principle of our ancestors, now re-adopted and brought back among
            us after a long interval, namely, that the complaints of the allies should be brought to
            a man who is not very inactive, and their advocacy undertaken by him who appeared able
            to defend their fortunes with integrity and diligence. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68" resp="perseus">
          <p> Men are afraid of this; they endeavour to prevent this; they are disquieted at such a
            principle having ever been adopted, and after it has been adopted at its now being
            resuscitated and brought into play again. They think that, if this custom begins
            gradually to creep on and advance, the laws will be put in execution, and actions will
            be conducted by honourable and fearless men, and not by unskillful youths, or informers
            of this sort.</p>
        </div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69" resp="perseus">
          <p> Of which custom and principle our fathers and ancestors did not repent when Publius
            Lentulus, he who was chief of the Senate, prosecuted Marcus Aquillius, having Caius
            Rutilius Rufus backing the accusation; or when Publius Africanus, a man most eminent for
            valour, for good fortune, for renown, and for exploits, after he had been twice consul
            and had been censor brought Lucius Cotta to trial Then the name of the Roman people was
            rightly held in high honour; rightly was the authority of this empire and the majesty of
            the state considered illustrious. Nobody marveled in the case of that great man
            Africanus, as they now pretend to marvel with respect to me, a man endowed with but
            moderate influence and moderate talents, just because they are annoyed at me; </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70" resp="perseus">
          <p> “What can he be meaning? does he want to be considered a prosecutor who hitherto has
            been accustomed to defend people? and especially now at the age when he is seeking the
            aedileship?” But I think it becomes not my age only, but even a much greater age, and I
            think it an action consistent with the highest dignity to accuse the wicked, and to
            defend the miserable and distressed. And in truth, either this is a remedy for a
            republic diseased and in an almost desperate condition, and for tribunals corrupted and
            contaminated by the vices and baseness of a few, for men of the greatest possible honour
            and uprightness and modesty to undertake to uphold the stability of the laws, and the
            authority of the courts of justice; or else, if this is of no advantage, no medicine
            whatever will ever be found for such terrible and numerous evils as these. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71" resp="perseus">
          <p> There is no greater safety for a republic, than for those who accuse another to be no
            less alarmed for their own credit, and honour, and reputation, than they who are accused
            are for their lives and fortunes. And therefore, those men have always conducted
            prosecutions with the greatest care and with the greatest pains, who have considered
            that they themselves had their reputations at stake. <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/><milestone unit="Para"/>

            You, therefore, O judges ought to come to this decision, that Quintus Caecilius of whom
            no one has ever had any opinion, and from whom even in this very trial nothing could be
            expected—who takes no trouble either to preserve a reputation previously acquired, or to
            give grounds for hope of himself in future times—will not be likely to conduct this
            cause with too much severity, with too much accuracy, or with too much diligence. For he
            has nothing which he can lose by disappointing public expectation; even if he were to
            come off ever so shamefully, or ever so infamously, he will lose no credit which he at
            present enjoys. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72" resp="perseus">
          <p> From us the Roman people has many hostages which we must labour with all our might and
            by every possible means to preserve uninjured, to defend, to keep in safety, and to
            redeem; it has honour which we are desirous of; it has hope, which we constantly keep
            before our eyes; it has reputation, acquired with much sweat and labour day and night;
            so that if we prove our duty and industry in this cause, we may be able to preserve all
            those things which I have mentioned safe and unimpaired by the favour of the Roman
            people; but if we trip and stumble ever so little, we may at one moment lose the whole
            of those things which have been collected one by one and by slow degrees. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73" resp="perseus">
          <p> On which account it is your business, O judges, to select him who you think can most
            easily sustain this great cause and trial with integrity, with diligence, with wisdom,
            and with authority. If you prefer Quintus Caecilius to me, I shall not think that I am
            surpassed in dignity; but take you care that the Roman people do not think that a
            prosecution as honest, as severe, as diligent as this would have been in my hands, was
            neither pleasing to yourselves nor to your body. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
