<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight books - 5</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, the first eight Books</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1857</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/4/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="322" xml:id="p.322"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="book">
                <head>BOOK V.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> During the siege of Veii winter dwellings erected for the soldiers. This
                        being a novelty, affords the tribunes of the people a pretext for exciting
                        discontent. The cavalry for the first time serve on horses of their own.
                        Furius Camillus, dictator, takes Veii after a siege of ten years. In the
                        character of military tribune, whilst laying siege to Falisci, he sends back
                        the children of the enemy, who were betrayed into his hands. Furius
                        Camillus, on a day being appointed for his trial, goes into exile. The
                        Senonian Gauls lay siege to Clusium. Roman ambassadors, sent to mediate
                        peace between the Clusians and Gauls, are found to take part with the
                        former; in consequence of which the Gauls march directly against Rome, and
                        after defeating the Romans at Allia take possession of the city with the
                        exception of the Capitol. They scaled the Capitol by night, but are
                        discovered by the cackling of geese, and repulsed, chiefly by the exertions
                        of Marcus Manlius. The Romans, compelled by famine, agree to ransom
                        themselves. Whilst the gold is being weighed to them, Camillus, who had been
                        appointed dictator, arrives with an army, expels the Gauls, and destroys
                        their army. He successfully opposes the design of removing to Veii. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> PEACE being established in every other
                    quarter, the Romans and Veientians were still in arms with such rancour and
                    animosity, that it was evident that ruin awaited the vanquished party. The
                    elections in the two states were conducted in very different methods. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans augmented the number of military tribunes
                    with consular power. Eight, a number greater than on any previous occasion, were
                    appointed, Manius Aemilius Mamercinus a second time, Lucius Valerius Potitus a
                    third time, Appius Claudius Crassus, Marcus Quintilius Varus, Lucius Julius
                    Iulus, Marcus Postumius, Marcus Furius Camillus, Marcus Postumius Albinus. The
                    Veientians, on the contrary, through disgust at the annual intriguing which was
                    sometimes the cause of dissensions, elected a king. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> That step gave offence to the feelings of the states of
                    Etruria, not more from their hatred of kingly government than of the <pb n="323"
                        xml:id="p.323"/> king himself. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He had
                    before this become obnoxious to the nation by reason of his wealth and
                    arrogance, because he had violently broken off the performance of some annual
                    games, the omission of which was deemed an impiety: <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> when through resentment of a repulse, because another had
                    been preferred to him as a priest by the suffrages of the twelve states, he
                    suddenly carried off, in the middle of the performance, the performers, of whom
                    a great part were his own slaves. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The nation,
                    therefore, devoted beyond all others to religious performances, because they
                    excelled in the method of conducting them, passed a decree that aid should be
                    refused to the Veientians, as long as they should be subject to a king.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All allusion to this decree was suppressed
                    at Veii through fear of the king, who would have considered the person by whom
                    any such matter might be mentioned as a leader of sedition, not as the author of
                    an idle rumour. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Although matters were
                    announced to the Romans as being quiet in Etruria, yet because it was stayed
                    that this matter was being agitated in all their meetings, they so managed their
                    fortifications, that there should be security on both sides; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> some were directed towards the city and the sallies of the
                    townsmen; by means of others a front looting towards Etruria was opposed to such
                    auxiliaries as might happen to come from thence. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Roman generals conceived greater
                    hopes from a blockade than from an assault, winter huts also, a thing quite new
                    to the Roman soldier, began to be built; and their determination was to continue
                    the war by wintering there. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After an account
                    of this was brought to Rome to the tribunes of the people, who for a long time
                    past <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> had found no pretext for exciting
                    disturbances, they run forward into the assembly, stir up the minds of the
                    commons, saying that <quote> this was the motive for which pay had been
                        established for the soldiers, nor had it escaped their knowledge, that such
                        a present from the enemies was tainted with poison. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> That the liberty of the commons had been sold; that
                        their youth removed for ever, and exiled from the city and the republic, did
                        not now even yield to the winter and to the season of the year, and visit
                        their homes and private affairs. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> What
                        could they suppose was the cause for continuing the service without
                        intermission? That undoubtedly they should find none other than [the fear]
                        lest any thing might be done in furtherance of their interests by <pb
                            n="324" xml:id="p.324"/> the attendance of those youths in whom the
                        entire strength of the commons lay. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Besides that they were harassed and worked much more severely than the
                        Veientians. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For the latter spent the
                        winter beneath their own roofs, defending their city by strong walls and its
                        natural situation, whilst the Roman soldier, in the midst of toil and
                        hardship, continued beneath the covering of skins, overwhelmed with snow and
                        frost, not laying aside his arms even during the period of winter, which is
                        a respite from all wars by land and sea. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        Neither kings, nor those consuls, tyrannical as they were before the
                        institution of the tribunitian office, nor the stern authority of the
                        dictator, nor the overbearing decemvirs, ever imposed such slavery as that
                        they should perform unremitting military service, which degree of regal
                        power the military tribunes now exercised over the Roman commons. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> What would these men have done as consuls or
                        dictators, who have exhibited the picture of the proconsular office so
                        implacable and menacing? but that all this happened justly. Among eight
                        military tribunes there was no room even for one plebeian. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Formerly the patricians filled up three places with the
                        utmost difficulty; now they went in file eight deep to take possession of
                        the various offices; and not even in such a crowd is any plebeian
                        intermixed; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> who, if he did no other good,
                        might remind his colleagues, that it was freemen and fellow citizens, and
                        not slaves, that constituted the army, who ought to be brought back during
                        winter at least to their homes and roofs; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        and to come and see at some part of the year their parents, children, and
                        wives, and to exercise the rights of freedom, and to take part in electing
                        magistrates. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> While they exclaimed in these and such terms,
                    they found in Appius Claudius an opponent not unequal to them, who had been left
                    behind by his colleagues to check the turbulence of the tribunes; a man trained
                    even from his youth in contests with the plebeians; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> who several years before, as has been mentioned,
                    recommended the dissolution of the tribunitian power by means of the protests of
                    their colleagues. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> He, not only endowed with good natural powers,
                    but well trained also by experience, on that particular occasion, delivered the
                    following address: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "If, Romans, there was ever
                    reason to doubt, whether the tribunes of the people have ever promoted sedition
                    for your sake or their own, I am certain <pb n="325" xml:id="p.325"/> that in
                    the course of this year that doubt must have ceased to exist; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and while I rejoice that an end has at length come of a
                    mistake of such long continuance, I in the next place congratulate you, and on
                    your account the republic, that this delusion has been removed during a course
                    of prosperous events. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Is there any person who
                    can feel a doubt that the tribunes of the commons were never so highly
                    displeased and provoked by any wrongs done to you, if ever such did happen, as
                    by the munificence of the patricians to the commons, when pay was established
                    for those serving in the army. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> What else do
                    you suppose that they either then dreaded, or now wish to disturb, except the
                    union between the orders, which they think contributes most to the dissolution
                    of the tribunitian power? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thus, by Jove, like
                    workers in iniquity, they are seeking for work, who also wish that there should
                    be always some diseased part in the republic, that there may be something for
                    the cure of which they may be employed by you. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For, [tribunes,] whether do you defend or attack the commons? whether are you
                    the enemies of those in the service, or do you plead their cause? <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Unless perhaps you say, whatever the patricians do,
                    displeases us; whether it is for the commons, or against the commons; and just
                    as masters forbid their slaves to have any dealing with those belonging to
                    others, and deem it right that they should equally refrain from having any
                    commerce with them, either for kindness or unkindness; ye, in like manner,
                    interdict us the patricians from all intercourse with the people, lest by our
                    courteousness and munificence we may challenge their regard, and they become
                    tractable and obedient to our direction. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And
                    if there were in you any thing of the feeling, I say not of fellow-citizens, but
                    of human beings, how much more ought you to favour, and, as far as in you lay,
                    to promote rather the kindly demeanour of the patricians and the tractability of
                    the commons! <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And if such concord were once
                    permanent, who would not venture to engage, that this empire would in a short
                    time become the highest among the neighbouring states? </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "I shall hereafter explain to you how not only
                    expedient, but even necessary has been this plan of my colleagues, according to
                    which they would not draw off the army from Veii until the business has been
                    completed. For the present I am disposed to speak concerning the condition of
                    the soldiers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="326" xml:id="p.326"/> Which observations of mine I think would appear
                    reasonable not only before you, but even, if they were delivered in the camp, in
                    the opinion of the soldiers themselves; on which subject if nothing could
                    suggest itself to my own mind to say, I certainly should be satisfied with that
                    which is suggested by the arguments of my adversaries. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> They lately said, that pay should not be given to the
                    soldiers because it had never been given. How then can they now feel displeased,
                    that additional labour should be imposed in due proportion on those to whom some
                    addition of profit has been added? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In no case
                    is there either labour without emolument, nor emolument in general without the
                    expense of labour. Toil and pleasure, in their natures most unlike, are yet
                    linked together by a sort of natural connexion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> Formerly the soldier thought it a hardship that he gave his labour to the
                    commonwealth at his own expense; at the same time he was glad for a part of the
                    year to till his own ground; to acquire that means whence he might support
                    himself and family at home and in war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now he
                    feels a pleasure that the republic is a source of advantage to him, and gladly
                    receives his pay. Let him therefore bear with patience that he is a little
                    longer absent from home and his family affairs, to which no heavy expense is now
                    attached. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whether if the commonwealth should
                    call him to a settlement of accounts, would it not justly say, You have pay by
                    the year, perform labour by the year? do you think it just to receive a whole
                    year's pay for six months' service? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Romans,
                    with reluctance do I dwell on this topic; for so ought those persons proceed who
                    employ mercenary troops. But we wish to treat as with fellow-citizens, and we
                    think it only just that you treat with us as with the country. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Either the war should not have been undertaken, or it ought
                    to be conducted suitably to the dignity of the Roman people, and brought to a
                    close as soon as possible. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But it will be
                    brought to a conclusion if we press on the besieged; if we do not retire until
                    we have consummated our hopes by the capture of Veii. In truth, if there were no
                    other motive, the very discredit of the thing should impose on us perseverance.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In former times a city was kept besieged
                    for ten years, on account of one woman, by all Greece. At what a distance from
                    their homes! <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> how many lands, how many seas
                    distant! We grumble at enduring a siege of a year's duration within twenty <pb
                        n="327" xml:id="p.327"/> miles of us, almost within sight of our own city;
                    because, I suppose, the cause of the war is trifling, nor is there resentment
                    sufficiently just to stimulate us to persevere. Seven times they have rebelled:
                    in peace they never acted faithfully. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They
                    have laid waste our lands a thousand times: the Fidenatians they forced to
                    revolt from us: they have put to death our colonists there: contrary to the law
                    of nations, they have been the instigators of the impious murder of our
                    ambassadors: <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> they wished to excite all
                    Etruria against us, and are at this day busily employed at it; and they scarcely
                    refrained from violating our ambassadors when demanding restitution. With such
                    people ought war to be conducted in a remiss and dilatory manner? </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If such just resentment have no influence
                    with us, will not, I entreat you, the following considerations influence you?
                    Their city has been enclosed with immense works, by which the enemy is confined
                    within their walls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They have not tilled their
                    land, and what was previously tilled has been laid waste in the war. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> If we withdraw our army, who is there who can doubt
                    that they will invade our territory not only from a desire of revenge, but from
                    the necessity also imposed on them of plundering from the property of others,
                    since they have lost their own? By such measures then we do not put off the war,
                    but admit it within our own frontiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What
                    shall I say of that which properly interests the soldiers, for whose interests
                    those worthy tribunes of the commons, all on a sudden, are now so anxious to
                    provide, after they have endeavoured to wrest their pay front them? How does it
                    stand? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They have formed a rampart and a
                    trench, both works of great labour, through so great an extent of ground; they
                    have erected forts, at first only a few, afterwards very many, when the army
                    became increased; they have raised defenders not only towards the city, but
                    towards Etruria also, against any succours which may come from thence.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What need I mention towers, vineae, and
                    testudines, and the other apparatus used in attacking towns? When so much labour
                    has been expended, and they have now at length reached the end of the work, do
                    you think that all these preparations should be abandoned that, next summer, the
                    same course of toil may have to be undergone again in forming them anew?
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> How much less trouble to support the works
                    already <pb n="328" xml:id="p.328"/> done, and to press on and persevere, and to
                    get rid of our task! For certainly the matter is of short duration, if it be
                    conducted with a uniform course of exertions; nor do we by these intermissions
                    and interruptions expedite the attainment of our hopes. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> I am now speaking of labour and of loss of time. What? do
                    these such frequent meetings in Etruria on the subject of sending aid to Veii
                    suffer us to disregard the danger which we encounter by procrastinating the war?
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As matters stand now, they are incensed,
                    they dislike them, they refuse to send any; as far as they are concerned, we are
                    at liberty to take Veii. Who can promise that their temper will be the same
                    hereafter, if the war is suspended? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> when, if
                    you suffer any relaxation, more respectable and more frequent embassies will go;
                    when that which now displeases the Etrurians, the establishment of a king at
                    Veii, may, after an interval, be done away with, either by the joint
                    determination of the state that they may recover the good will of the Etrurians,
                    or by a voluntary act of the king, who may be unwilling that his reign should
                    stand in the way of the welfare of his countrymen. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> See how many circumstances, and how detrimental, follow
                    that line of conduct: the loss of works formed with so great labour; the
                    threatening devastation of our frontiers; an Etruscan excited instead of a
                    Veientian war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These, tribunes, are your
                    measures, pretty much the same, in truth, as if a person should render a disease
                    tedious, and perhaps incurable, for the sake of present meat or drink, in a
                    patient who, by resolutely suffering himself to be treated, might soon recover
                    his health. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> If, by Jove, it were of no consequence with respect to the present war,
                        yet it certainly would be of the utmost importance to military discipline,
                        that our soldiers should be accustomed not only to enjoy the victory
                        obtained by them; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but even though matters
                        should proceed more slowly than was anticipated, to brook the tediousness
                        and await the issue of their hopes, however tardy; and if the war be not
                        finished in the summer, to wait for the winter, and not, like summer birds,
                        in the very commencement of autumn look out for shelter and a retreat.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I pray you, the eagerness and pleasure
                        of hunting hurries men into snow and frost, over mountains and woods; shall
                        we not employ that patience on the exigencies of war, which even sport and
                        pleasure are wont to call forth? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Are we to
                        suppose that the bodies of our soldiers are so effeminate, their <pb n="329"
                            xml:id="p.329"/> minds so feeble, that they cannot hold out for one
                        winter in a camp, and be absent from home? that, like persons who wage a
                        naval war, by taking advantage of the weather, and observing the season of
                        the year, they are able to endure neither heat nor cold? <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> They would certainly blush, should any one lay these
                        things to their charge; and would maintain that both their minds and their
                        bodies were possessed of manly endurance, and that they were able to conduct
                        war equally well in winter and in summer; and that they had not consigned to
                        the tribunes the patronage of indolence and sloth, and that they remembered
                        that their ancestors had created this very power, neither in the shade nor
                        beneath their roofs. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Such sentiments are
                        worthy of the valour of your soldiers, such sentiments are worthy of the
                        Roman name, not to consider merely Veii, nor this war which is now pressing
                        us, but to seek a reputation for hereafter for other wars and for other
                        states. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Do you consider the difference of
                        opinion likely to result from this matter as trivial? Whether, pray are the
                        neighbouring states to suppose that the Roman people is such, that if any
                        one shall sustain their first assault, and that of very short continuance,
                        they have nothing afterwards to fear? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> or
                        whether such should be the terror of our name, that neither the tediousness
                        of a distant siege, nor the inclemency of winter, can dislodge the Roman
                        army from a city once invested, and that they know no other termination of
                        war than victory, and that they carry on wars not more by briskness than by
                        perseverance; which is necessary no doubt in every kind of war, but more
                        especially in besieging cities; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> most of
                        which, impregnable both by their works and by natural situation, time itself
                        overpowers and reduces by famine and thirst; as it will reduce Veii, unless
                        the tribunes of the commons shall afford aid to the enemy, and the
                        Veientians find in Rome reinforcements which they seek in vain in Etruria.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Is there any thing which can happen
                        so much in accordance with the wishes of the Veientians, as that <milestone
                            n="11??" unit="section"/> first the Roman city, then the camp, as it
                        were by contagion, should be filled with sedition? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> But, by Jove, among the enemy so forbearing a state of
                        mind prevails, that not a single change has taken place among them, either
                        through disgust at the length of the siege nor even of the kingly form of
                        government; nor has the refusal of aid by the Etrurians aroused their
                        tempers. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For <pb n="330" xml:id="p.330"/>
                        whoever will be the abettor of sedition, will be instantly put to death; nor
                        will it be permitted to any one to utter those sentiments which amongst you
                        are expressed with impunity. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He is sure
                        to receive the bastinade, who forsakes his colours or quits his post.
                        Persons advising not one or two soldiers, but whole armies to relinquish
                        their colours or to forsake their camp, are openly listened to in your
                        public assemblies. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Accordingly whatever a
                        tribune of the people says, although it tends to the ruin of the country or
                        the dissolution of the commonwealth, you are accustomed to listen to with
                        partiality; and captivated with the charms of that authority, you suffer all
                        sorts of crimes to lie concealed beneath it. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> The only thing that remains is, that what they
                        vociferate here, the same projects do they realize in the camp and among the
                        soldiers, and seduce the armies, and not suffer them to obey their officers;
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> since that and that only is liberty
                        in Rome, to show no deference to the senate, nor to magistrates, nor laws,
                        nor the usages of ancestors, nor the institutions of our fathers, nor
                        military discipline. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Even already Appius was a match for the
                    tribunes of the people in the popular assemblies; when suddenly a misfortune
                    sustained before Veii, from a quarter whence no one could expect it, both gave
                    Appius the superiority in the dispute, produced also a greater harmony between
                    the different orders, and greater ardour to carry on the siege of Veii with more
                    pertinacity. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For when the trenches were now
                    advanced to the very city, and the machines were almost about to be applied to
                    the walls, whilst the works are carried on with greater assiduity by day, than
                    they are guarded by night, a gate was thrown open on a sudden, and a vast
                    multitude, armed chiefly with torches, cast fire about on all sides; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> and after the lapse of an hour the flames destroyed
                    both the rampart and the machines, the work of so long a time, and great numbers
                    of men, bearing assistance in vain, were destroyed by the sword and by fire.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the account of this circumstance was
                    brought to Rome, it inspired sadness into all ranks; into the senate anxiety and
                    apprehension, lest the sedition could no longer be withstood either in the city
                    or in the camp, and lest the tribunes of the commons should insult over the
                    commonwealth, as if vanquished by them; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> when
                    on a sudden, those who possessed an equestrian fortune, <pb n="331"
                        xml:id="p.331"/> but to whom horses had not been assigned by the public,
                    having previously held a meeting together, went to the senate; and having
                    obtained permission to speak, promise that they will serve on their own horses.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And when thanks were returned to them by
                    the senate in the most complimentary terms, and the report of this proceeding
                    spread through the forum and the city, there suddenly ensues a concourse of the
                    commons to the senate-house. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They say that
                        <quote> they are now of the pedestrian order, and the preferred their
                        services to the commonwealth, though not compelled to serve, whether they
                        wished to march them to Veii, or to any other place. If they were led to
                        Veii, they affirm, that they would not return from thence, until the city of
                        the enemy was taken. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then indeed they with difficulty set bounds to
                    the joy which now poured in upon them; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for
                    they were not ordered, as in the case of the horsemen, to be publicly eulogized,
                    the order for so doing being consigned to the magistrates, nor were they
                    summoned into the senate-house to receive an answer; nor did the senate confine
                    themselves within the threshold of their house, but every one of them
                    individually with their voice and hands testified from the elevated ground the
                    public joy to the multitude standing in the assembly; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> they declared that by that unanimity the Roman city would
                    be happy, and invincible and eternal; praised the horsemen, praised the commons;
                    extolled the day itself by their praises; they acknowledged that the courtesy
                    and kindness of the senate was outdone. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Tears
                    flowed in abundance through joy both from the patricians and commons; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> until the senators being called back into the house,
                    a decree of the senate was passed, "that the military tribunes, summoning an
                    assembly, should return thanks to the infantry and cavalry; and should state
                    that the senate would be mindful of their affectionate attachment to their
                    country. But that it was their wish that their pa should go on for those who
                    had, out of their turn, undertaken voluntary service. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> To the horsemen also a certain stipend was assigned. Then
                    for the first time the cavalry began to serve on their own horses. This army of
                    volunteers being led to Veii, not only restored the works which had been lost,
                    but also erected new ones. Supplies were conveyed from the city with greater
                    care than before; lest any thing <pb n="332" xml:id="p.332"/> should be wanting
                    for the accommodation of an army who deserved so well. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The following year had military tribunes with
                    consular authority, Caius Servilius Ahala a third time, Quintus Servilius,
                    Lucius Virginius, Quintus Sulpicius, Aulus Manlius a second time, Manius Sergius
                    a second time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> During their tribuneship,
                    whilst the solicitude of all was directed to the Veientian war, the garrison at
                    Anxur was neglected in consequence of the absence of the soldiers on leave, and
                    from the indiscriminate admission of Volscian traders was overpowered, the
                    guards at the gates being suddenly betrayed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Less of the soldiers perished, because they were all trafficking through the
                    country and city like suttlers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nor were
                    matters conducted more successfully at Veii, which was then the chief object of
                    all public solicitude. For both the Roman commanders had more quarrels among
                    themselves, than spirit against the enemy; and the severity of the war was
                    exaggerated by the sudden arrival of the Capenatians and the Faliscians.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These two states of Etruria, because they
                    were contiguous in situation, judging that in case Veii was conquered, they
                    should be next to the attacks of the Romans in war; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> the Faliscians also, incensed from a cause affecting
                    themselves, because they had already on a former occasion mixed themselves up in
                    a Fidenatian war, being bound together by an oath by reciprocal embassies,
                    marched unexpectedly with their armies to Veii. It so happened, they attacked
                    the camp in that quarter where Manius Sergius, military tribune, commanded, and
                    occasioned great alarm; because the Romans imagined that all Etruria was aroused
                    and were advancing in a great mass. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same
                    opinion aroused the Veientians in the city. Thus the Roman camp was attacked on
                    both sides; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and crowding together, whilst they
                    wheeled round their battalions from one post to another, they were unable either
                    to confine the Veientians within their fortifications, or repel the assault from
                    their own works, and to defend themselves from the enemy on the outside. The
                    only hope was, if succour could be brought from the greater camp, that the
                    different legions should fight, some against the Capenatians and Faliscians,
                    others against the sallies of the townsmen. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But Virginius had the command of that camp, who, from personal grounds, was
                    hateful to and incensed <pb n="333" xml:id="p.333"/> against Sergius. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> This man, when word was brought that most of the
                    forts were attacked, the fortifications sealed, and that the enemy were pouring
                    in on both sides, kept his men under arms, saying that if there was need of
                    assistance, his colleague would send to him. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    His arrogance was equalled by the obstinacy of the other; who, that he might not
                    appear to have sought any aid from an adversary, preferred being defeated by an
                    enemy to conquering through a fellow-citizen. His men were for a long time cut
                    down between both: at length, abandoning their works, a very small number made
                    their way to the principal camp; the greater number, with Sergius himself, made
                    their way to Rome. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Where, when he threw the
                    entire blame on his colleague, it was resolved that Virginius should be sent for
                    from the camp, and that lieutenant-generals should take the command in the mean
                    time. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The affair was then discussed in the
                    senate, and the dispute was carried on between the colleagues with (mutual)
                    recriminations. But few took up the interests of the republic, (the greater
                    number) favoured the one or the other, according as private regard or interest
                    prejudiced each. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The principal senators were of opinion, that
                    whether so ignominious a defeat had been sustained through the misconduct or the
                    misfortune of the commanders, <quote> the regular time of the elections should
                        not be waited for, but that new military tribunes should be created
                        immediately, who should enter into office on the calends of October. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whilst they were proceeding to intimate their
                    assent to this opinion, the other military tribunes offered no opposition.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But Sergius and Virginius, on whose
                    account it was evident that the senate were dissatisfied with the magistrate of
                    that year, at first deprecated the ignominy, then protested against the decree
                    of the senate; they declared that they would not retire from office before the
                    ides of December, the usual day for persons entering on magisterial duties.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Upon this the tribunes of the plebeians,
                    whilst in the general harmony and in the prosperous state of public affairs they
                    had unwillingly kept silence, suddenly becoming confident, began to threaten the
                    military tribunes, that unless they conformed to the order of the senate, they
                    would order them to be thrown into prison. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Then Caius Servilius Ahala, a military tribune, observed, <quote> With respect
                        to you, tribunes of the commons, and your threats, <pb n="334"
                            xml:id="p.334"/> I would with pleasure put it to the test, how there is
                        not more of authority in the latter than of spirit in yourselves. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> But it is impious to strive against the authority
                        of the senate. Wherefore do you cease to seek amid our quarrels for an
                        opportunity of doing mischief; and my colleagues will either do that which
                        the senate thinks fit, or if they shall persist with too much pertinacity, I
                        will immediately nominate a dictator, who will oblige them to retire from
                        office. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When this speech was approved with general
                    consent, and the patricians rejoiced, that without the terrors of the
                    tribunitian office, another and a superior power had been discovered to coerce
                    the magistrates, overcome <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> by the universal
                    consent, they held the elections of military tribunes, who were to commence
                    their office on the calends of October, and before that day they retired from
                    office. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the military tribuneship of Lucius
                    Valerius Potitus for the fourth time, Marcus Furius Camillus for the second
                    time, Manius Aemilius Mamercinus a third time, Cneius Cornelius Cossus a second
                    time, Kaeso Fabius Ambustus, Lucius Julius Iulus, much business was transacted
                    at home and abroad. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For there was both a
                    complex war at the same time, at Veii, at Capena, at Falerii, and among the
                    Volscians, that Anxur might be recovered from the enemy; and at the same time
                    there was some difficulty experienced both in consequence of the levy, and of
                    the contribution of the tax: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> there was also a
                    contention about the appointment of plebeian tribunes; and the two trials of
                    those, who a little before had been invested with consular authority, excited no
                    trifling commotion. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> First of all the tribunes
                    of the soldiers took care that the levy should be held; and not only the juniors
                    were enlisted, but the seniors also were compelled to give in their names, to
                    serve as a garrison to the city. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But in
                    proportion as the number of the soldiers was augmented, so much the greater sum
                    of money was required for pay; and this was collected by a tax, those who
                    remained at home contributing against their will, because those who guarded the
                    city had to perform military service also, and to serve the commonwealth.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the commons, by their
                    seditious harangues, caused these things, grievous in themselves, to seem more
                    exasperating, by their asserting, " that pay was established for the soldiers
                    with this view, that they might wear out one half of the commons by <pb n="335"
                        xml:id="p.335"/> military service, the other half by the tax. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> That a single war was being waged now for the third
                    year, on purpose hat they may have a longer time to wage it. That armies ad been
                    raised at one levy for four different wars, and that boys even and old men were
                    dragged from home. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> That neither summer nor
                    winter now made any difference, so that there may never be any respite for the
                    unfortunate commons, who were now even at last made to pay a tax; <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> so that after they brought home their bodies wasted
                    by hardship, wounds, and eventually by age, and found their properties at home
                    neglected by the absence of the proprietors, had to pay a tax out of their
                    impaired fortunes, and to refund to the state in a manifold proportion the
                    military pay which had been as it were received on interest. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Between the levy and the tax, and their minds being taken
                    up by more important concerns, the number of plebeian tribunes could not be
                    filled up at the elections. A struggle was afterwards made that patricians
                    should be elected into the vacant places. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    When this could not be carried, still, for the purpose of weakening the
                    Trebonian law, it was managed that Caius Lacerius and Marcus Acutius should be
                    admitted as tribunes of the commons, no doubt through the influence of the
                    patricians. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Chance so directed it, that this year Cneius
                    Trebonius was tribune of the commons, and he considered that he undertook the
                    patronage of the Trebonian law as a debt due to his name and family. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> He crying out aloud, <quote> that a point which some
                        patricians had aimed at, though baffled in their first attempt, had yet been
                        carried by the military tribunes that the Trebonian law had been subverted,
                        and tribunes of the commons had been elected not by the suffrages of the
                        people but by the mandate of the patricians; and that the thing was now come
                        to this, that either patricians or dependants of patricians were to be had
                        for tribunes of the commons; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that the
                        devoting laws were taken away, the tribunitian power wrested from them; he
                        alleged that this was effected by some artifice of the patricians, by the
                        villany and treachery of his colleagues. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> While not only the patricians, but the
                    tribunes of the commons also became objects of public resentment; as well those
                    who were elected, as those who had elected them; then three of the college,
                    Publius Curiatius, Marcus Metilius, and Marcus Minucius, alarmed for their
                    interests, make an attack <pb n="336" xml:id="p.336"/> on Sergius and Virginius,
                    military tribunes of the former year; they turn away the resentment of the
                    commons, and public odium from themselves on them, by appointing a day of trial
                    for them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They observe that <quote> those
                        persons by whom the levy, the tribute, the long service, and the distant
                        seat of the war was felt as a grievance, those who lamented the calamity
                        sustained at Veii; such as had their houses in mourning through the loss of
                        children, brothers, relatives, and kinsmen, had now through their means the
                        right and power of avenging the public and private sorrow on the two guilty
                        causes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For that the sources of all their
                        sufferings were centred in Sergius and Virginius: nor did the prosecutor
                        advance that charge more satisfactorily than the accused acknowledged it;
                        who, both guilty, threw the blame from one to the other, Virginius charging
                        Sergius with running away, Sergius charging Virginius with treachery.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The folly of whose conduct was so
                        incredible, that it is much more probable that the affair had been contrived
                        by concert, and by the common artifice of the patricians. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> That by them also an opportunity was formerly given to
                        the Veientians to burn the works for the sake of protracting the war; and
                        that now the army was betrayed, and the Roman camp delivered up to the
                        Faliscians. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> That every thing was done that
                        the young men should grow old before Veii, and that the tribunes should not
                        be able to consult the people either regarding the lands or the other
                        interests of <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the commons, and to give
                        weight to their measures by a numerous attendance [of citizens], and to make
                        head against the conspiracy of the patricians. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> That a previous judgment had been already passed on the
                        accused both by the senate and the Roman people and by their own colleagues.
                        For that by a decree of the senate they had been removed from the
                        administration of affairs, and when they refused to resign their office they
                        had been forced into it by their colleagues; and that the Roman people had
                        elected tribunes, who were to enter on their office not on the ides of
                        December, the usual day, but instantly on the calends of October, because
                        the republic could no longer subsist, these persons remaining in office.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And yet these individuals,
                        overwhelmed and already condemned by so many decisions against them,
                        presented themselves for trial before the people; <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> and thought that they were done with the matter, and
                        had suffered sufficient punish- <pb n="337" xml:id="p.337"/> ment, because
                        they were reduced to the state of private citizens two months sooner [than
                        ordinary]: and did not consider that the power of doing mischief any longer
                        was then taken from them, that punishment was not inflicted; for that the
                        official power of their colleagues also had been taken from them who
                        certainly had committed no fault. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> That
                        the Roman citizens should resume those sentiments which they had when the
                        recent disaster was sustained, when they beheld the army flying in
                        consternation, covered with wounds, and in dismay pouring into the gates,
                        accusing not fortune nor any of the gods, but these their commanders.
                            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They were cert in, that there was not
                        a man present in the assembly who did not execrate and detest the persons,
                        families, and fortunes of Lucius Virginius and Manius Sergius. <milestone
                            n="16" unit="section"/> That it was by no means consistent that now,
                        when it was lawful and their duty, they should not exert their power against
                        persons, on whom they had severally imprecated the vengeance of the gods.
                        That the gods themselves never laid hands on the guilty it was enough if
                        they armed the injured with the means of taking revenge. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Urged on by these discourses the commons
                    condemn the accused [in a fine] of ten thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> in
                    weight, Sergius in vain throwing the blame on fortune and the common chance of
                    war, Virginius entreating that he might not be more unfortunate at home than he
                    had been in the field. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Their resentment of the
                    people being turned against them, obliterated the remembrance of the assumption
                    of the tribunes and of the fraud committed against the Trebonian law. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The victorious tribunes, in order that the people
                    might reap an immediate benefit from the trial, publish a form <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> of an agrarian law, and prevent the tax from being
                    contributed, since there was need of pay for so great a number of troops, and
                    the enterprises of the service were conducted with success in such a manner,
                    that in none of the wars did they reach the consummation of their hope. At Veii
                    the camp which had been lost was recovered and strengthened with forts and a
                    garrison. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here M. Aemilius and Kaeso Fabius,
                    military tribunes, commanded. None of the enemy were found outside the walls by
                    Marcus Furius in the Faliscan territory, and Cneius Cornelius in the Capenatian
                    district: spoil was driven off, and the country laid waste by burning of the
                    houses and the fruits of the earth: <pb n="338" xml:id="p.338"/> the towns were
                    neither assaulted nor besieged. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But among the
                    Volscians, their territory being depopulated, Anxur, which was situate on an
                    eminence, was assaulted, but to no purpose; and when force was ineffectual, they
                    commenced to surround it with a rampart and a trench. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The province of the Volscians had fallen [to the lot of]
                    Valerius Potitus. In this state of military affairs an intestine disturbance
                    broke out with greater violence than the wars were proceeded with. And when it
                    was rendered impossible by the tribunes to have the tax paid, and the payment
                    [of the army] was not remitted to the generals, and the soldiers became
                    importunate for their pay, the camp also was well nigh being involved in the
                    contagion of the sedition in the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Amid
                    this resentment of the commons against the patricians, though the tribunes
                    asserted that now was the time for establishing liberty, and transferring the
                    sovereign dignity from the Sergii and <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    Virginii to plebeians, men of fortitude and energy, still they proceeded no
                    further than the election of one of the commons, Publius Licinius Calvus,
                    military tribune with consular power for the purpose of establishing their right
                    by precedent: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the others elected were
                    patricians, Publius Maenius, Lucius Titinius, Publius Maelius, Lucius Furius
                    Medullinus, Lucius Publius Volscus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    commons themselves were surprised at having gained so important a point, and not
                    merely he who had been elected, being a person who had filled no post of honour
                    before, being only a senator of long standing, and now weighed down with years.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Nor does it sufficiently appear, why he
                    was elected first and in preference to any one else to taste the sweets of the
                    new dignity. Some think that he was raised to so high a dignity through the
                    influence of his brother, Cneius Cornelius, who had been military tribune on the
                    preceding year, and had given triple pay to the cavalry. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Others [say] that he had himself delivered a seasonable
                    address equally acceptable to the patricians and commons, concerning the harmony
                    of the several orders [of the state]. The tribunes of the commons, exulting in
                    this victory at the election, relaxed in their opposition regarding the tax, a
                    matter which very much impeded the progress of public business. It was paid in
                    with submission, and sent to the army. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the country of the Volscians Anxur was soon
                    retaken, the guarding of the city having been neglected during a fes- <pb
                        n="339" xml:id="p.339"/> tival day. This year was remarkable for a cold and
                    snowy winter, so that the roads were impassable, and the Tiber not navigable.
                    The price of provisions underwent no change, in consequence of the abundance
                    previously laid in. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And because Publius
                    Licinius, as he obtained his office without any rioting, to the greater joy of
                    the commons than annoyance of the patricians, so also did he administer it; a
                    rapturous desire of electing plebeians at the next election took possession of
                    them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Of the patricians Marcus Veturius alone
                    obtained a place: almost all the centuries appointed the other plebeian
                    candidates as military tribunes with consular authority. Marcus Pomponius, Caius
                    Duilius, Volero Publilius, Caeius Genucius, Lucius Atilius. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The severe winter, whether from the ill temperature of the
                    air [arising] from the abrupt transition to the contrary state, or from
                    whatsoever other cause, was followed by an unhealthy summer, destructive to all
                    species of animals; and when neither the cause nor termination of this
                    intractable pestilence could be discovered, the Sibylline books were consulted
                    according to a decree of the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    duumvirs for the direction of religious matters, the lectisternium being then
                    for the first time introduced into the city <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    of Rome for eight days implored the favour of Apollo and Latona, Diana and
                    Hercules, Mercury and Neptune, three couches being laid out with the greatest
                    magnificence that was then possible. The same solemn rite was observed also by
                    private individuals. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The doors lying open
                    throughout the entire city, and the use of every thing lying out in common, they
                    say that all passengers, both those known and those unknown indiscriminately,
                    were invited to lodgings, and that conversation was adopted between persons at
                    variance with complaisance and kindness, and that they refrained from disputes
                    and quarrels; their chains were also taken off those who were in confinement
                    during those days; that afterward a scruple was felt in imprisoning those to
                    whom the gods had brought such aid. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the
                    mean while the alarm was multiplied at Veii, three wars being concentred in the
                    one place. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For as the Capenatians and
                    Faliscians had suddenly come with succour [to the Veientians], they had to fight
                    against three armies on different sides in the same manner as formerly, through
                    the whole extent of their works. The recollection of the sentence passed on
                    Sergius and Virginius aided them above every <pb n="340" xml:id="p.340"/> thing
                    else. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly some forces being led
                    around in a short time from the principal camp, where some delay had been made
                    on the former occasion, attack the Capenatians on their rear, whilst they were
                    engaged in front against the Roman rampart. The fight commencing in this quarter
                    struck terror into the Faliscians also, and a sally from the camp opportunely
                    made put them to flight, thrown into disorder as they now were. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The victors, having then pursued them in their
                    retreat, made great slaughter amongst them. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    And soon after those who had been devastating the territory of Capena, having
                    met them as it were by chance, entirely cut off the survivors of the fight as
                    they were straggling through the country: <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and
                    many of the Veientians in their retreat to the city were slain before the gates;
                    whilst, through fear lest the Romans should force in along with them, they
                    excluded the hindmost of their men by closing the gates. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These were the transactions of that year. And
                    now the election of military tribunes approached; about which the patricians
                    felt more intense solicitude than about the war, inasmuch as they saw that the
                    supreme authority was not only shared with the commons, but almost lost to
                    themselves. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Wherefore the most distinguished
                    individuals being, by concert, prepared to stand candidates, whom they thought
                    [the people] would feel ashamed to pass by, they themselves, nevertheless, as if
                    they were all candidates, trying every expedient, strove to gain over not only
                    men, but the gods also, raising religious scruples about the elections held the
                    two preceding years; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that, in the former of
                    those years, a winter set in intolerably severe, and like to a prodigy from the
                    gods; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> on the next year [they had] not
                    prodigies, but events, a pestilence inflicted on both city and country through
                    the manifest resentment of the gods: whom, as was discovered in the books of the
                    fates, it was necessary to appease, for the purpose of warding off that plague.
                    That it seemed to the gods an affront that honours should be prostituted, and
                    the distinctions of birth confounded, in an election which was held under proper
                    auspices. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The people, overawed as well by the
                    dignity of the candidates as by a sense of religion, elected all the military
                    tribunes with consular power from among the patricians, the greater part being
                    men who had been most highly distinguished by honour; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Valerius <pb n="341" xml:id="p.341"/> Potitus a
                    fifth time, Marcus Valerius Maximus, Marcus Furius Camillus a third time, Lucius
                    Furius Medullinus a third time, Quintus Servilius Fidenas a second time, Quintus
                    Sulpicius Camerinus a second time. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> During this
                    tribunate, nothing very memorable was performed at Veii. All their force was
                    employed in depopulating the country. Two consummate commanders, Potitus from
                    Falerii, Camillus from Capena, carried off great booty, nothing being left
                    undestroyed which could be injured by sword or by fire. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the mean time many prodigies were
                    announced; the greater part of which were little credited or even slighted,
                    because individuals were the reporters of them, and also because, the Etrurians
                    being now at war with them, they had no aruspices through whom they might attend
                    to them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The attention of all was turned to a
                    particular one: the lake in the Alban grove swelled to an unusual height without
                    any rain, or any other cause which could account for the matter independently of
                    a miracle. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Commissioners were sent to the
                    Delphic oracle to inquire what the gods portended by this prodigy; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> but an interpreter of the fates was presented to them
                    nearer home in a certain aged Veientian, who, amid the scoffs thrown out by the
                    Roman and Etrurian soldiers from the out-posts and guards, declared, after the
                    manner of one delivering a prophecy, that until the water should be discharged
                    from the Alban lake, the Romans should never become masters of Veii. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> This was disregarded at first as having been thrown
                    out at random, afterwards it began to be canvassed in conversation; until one of
                    the Roman soldiers on guard asked one of the townsmen who was nearest him (a
                    conversational intercourse having now taken place in consequence of the long
                    continuance of the war) who he was, who threw out those dark expressions
                    concerning the Alban lake? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After he heard that
                    he was an aruspex, being a man whose mind was not without a tincture of
                    religion, pretending that he wished to consult him on the expiation of a private
                    portent, if he could aid him, he enticed the prophet to a conference. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> And when, being unarmed, they had proceeded a
                    considerable distance from their respective parties without any apprehension,
                    the Roman youth having the advantage in strength, took up the feeble old man in
                    the sight of all, and amid the ineffectual bustle made by the Etrurians, carried
                    him away to <pb n="342" xml:id="p.342"/> his own party. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> When he was conducted before the general, and sent from
                    thence to Rome to the senate, to those who asked him what that was which he had
                    stated <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> concerning the Alban lake, he
                    replied, <quote> that undoubtedly the gods were angry with the Veientian people
                        on that day, on which they had inspired him with the resolve to disclose the
                        ruin of his country as destined by the fates. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Wherefore what he then declared urged by divine
                        inspiration, he neither could recall so that it may be unsaid; and perhaps
                        by concealing what the immortal gods wished to be published, no less guilt
                        was contracted than by openly declaring what ought to be concealed.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Thus therefore it was recorded in the
                        books of the fates, thus in the Etrurian doctrine, that whensoever the Alban
                        water should rise to a great height, then, if the Romans should discharge it
                        in a proper manner, victory was granted them over the Veientians: before
                        that occurred, that the gods would not desert the walls of Veii. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He then detailed what would be the legitimate
                    method of draining. But the senate deeming his authority as but of little
                    weight, and not to be entirely depended on in so important a matter, determined
                    to wait for the deputies and the responses of the Pythian oracle. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before the commissioners returned from
                    Delphos, or an expiation of the Alban prodigy was discovered, the new military
                    tribunes with consular power entered on their office, Lucius Julius Iulus,
                    Lucius Furius Medullinus for the fourth time, Lucius Sergius Fidenas, Aulus
                    Postumius Regillensis, Publius Cornelius Maluginensis, and Aulus Manlius. This
                    year a new enemy, the Tarquinians, started up. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Because they saw the Romans engaged in many wars together, that of the Volscians
                    at Anxur, where the garrison was besieged, that of the Aequans at Lavici, who
                    were attacking the Roman colony there, moreover in the Veientian, Faliscan, and
                    Capenatian war, and that matters were not more tranquil within the walls, by
                    reason of the dissensions between the patricians and commons; considering that
                    amid these [troubles] there was an opportunity for an attack, they send their
                    light-armed cohorts to commit depredations on the Roman territory. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> For [they concluded] either that the Romans would
                    suffer that injury to pass off unavenged, that they might not encumber
                    themselves with an additional war, or that they would resent it with a scanty
                    army, and one by no means strong. The <pb n="343" xml:id="p.343"/> Romans [felt]
                    greater indignation, than alarm, at the inroads of the Tarquinians. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> On this account the matter was neither taken up with
                    great preparation, nor was it delayed for any length of time. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Aulus Postumius and Lucius Julius, having raised a body of
                    men, not by a regular levy, (for they were prevented by the tribunes of the
                    commons,) but [a body consisting] mostly of volunteers, whom they had arouse by
                    exhortations, having proceeded by cross marches through the territory of Caere,
                    fell unexpectedly on the Tarquinians, as they were returning from their
                    depredations and laden with booty; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> they slew
                    great numbers, stripped them all of their baggage, and, having recovered the
                    spoils of their own lands, they return to Rome. Two days were allowed to the
                    owners to reclaim their effects. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the third
                    day, that portion not owned (for most of it belonged to the enemies themselves)
                    was sold by public auction; and what was produced from thence, was distributed
                    among the soldiers. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The other wars, and more
                    especially the Veientian, were of doubtful issue. And now the Romans, despairing
                    of human aid, began to look to the fates and the gods, when the deputies
                    returned from Delphos, bringing with them an answer of the oracle, corresponding
                    with the response of the captive prophet: <quote> Roman, beware lest the Alban
                        water be confined in the lake, beware of suffering it to flow into the sea
                        in its own stream. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thou shalt let it out
                        and form a passage for it through the fields, and by dispersing it in
                        channels thou shalt consume it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then
                        press boldly on the walls of the enemy, mindful that the victory is granted
                        to you by these fates which are now revealed over that city which thou art
                        besieging for so many years. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The war
                        being ended, do thou, as victorious, bring ample offerings to my temples,
                        and having renewed the religious institutions of your country, the care of
                        which has been given up, perform them in the usual manner. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Upon this the captive prophet began to be held
                    in high esteem, and Cornelius and Postumius, the military tribunes, began to
                    employ him for the expiation of the Alban prodigy, and to appease the gods in
                    due form. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And it was at length discovered
                    wherein the gods found fault with the neglect of the ceremonies and the omission
                    of the customary rites; that it was undoubtedly nothing else, than that the
                    magistrates, having been appointed under some defect [in their election], <pb
                        n="344" xml:id="p.344"/> had not directed the Latin festival and the
                    solemnities on the Alban mount with due regularity. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The only mode of expiation in the case was, that the
                    military tribunes should resign their office, the auspices be taken anew, and an
                    interregnum be adopted. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All these things were
                    performed according to a decree of the senate. There were three interreges in
                    succession, Lucius Valerius, Quintus Servilius Fidenas, Marcus Furius Camillus.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In the mean time disturbances never ceased
                    to exist, the tribunes of the commons impeding the elections until it was
                    previously stipulated, that the greater number of the military tribunes should
                    be elected out of the commons. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Whilst these
                    things are going on, assemblies of Etruria were held at the temple of Voltumna,
                    and the Capenatians and Faliscians demanding that all the states of Etruria
                    should by common consent and resolve aid in raising the siege of Veii, the
                    answer given was: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> that on a former occasion they had refused that to the Veientians,
                        because they had no right to demand aid from those from whom they had not
                        solicited advice on so important a matter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        That for the present their own condition instead of themselves <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> So I have rendered <hi
                                rend="italics">pro se</hi> or it may be rendered,
                                <quote>considering their circumstances,</quote> scil. the external
                            circumstances in which they were placed. </note> denied it to them, more
                        especially in that part of Etruria. That a <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        strange nation, the Gauls, were become new neighbours, with whom they
                        neither had a sufficiently secure peace, nor a certainty of war: to the
                        blood, however, and the name and the present dangers of their kinsmen this
                        [mark of respect] was paid, that if any of their youth were disposed to go
                        to that war, they would not prevent them. </quote> Hence there was a report
                    at Rome, that a great number <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> of enemies had
                    arrived, and in consequence the intestine dissensions began to subside, as is
                    usual, through alarm for the general safety. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Without opposition on the part of the
                    patricians, the prerogative tribe elect Publius Licinius Calvus military tribune
                    without his suing for it, a man of tried moderation in his former tribunate, but
                    now of extreme old age; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and it was observed
                    that all were re-elected in regular succession out of the college of the same
                    year, Lucius Titinius, Publius Maenius, Publius Maelius, Cneius Genucius, Lucius
                    Atilius: before these were proclaimed, the tribes being summoned in the ordi-
                        <pb n="345" xml:id="p.345"/> nary course, Publius Licinius Calvus, by
                    permission of the interrex, spoke as follows: <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Romans, I perceive that from the recollection of our administration you
                        are seeking an omen of concord, a thing most important at the present time
                        for the ensuing year. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If you re-elect the
                        same colleagues, improved also by experience, in me you no longer behold the
                        same person, but the shadow and name of Publius Licinius now left. The
                        powers of my body are decayed, my senses of sight and hearing are grown
                        dull, my memory falters, the vigour of my mind is blunted. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Behold here a youth, </quote> says he, holding his son,
                        <quote> the representation and image of him whom ye formerly made a military
                        tribune, the first from among the commons. This youth, formed under my own
                        discipline, I present and dedicate to the commonwealth as a substitute for
                        myself. And I beseech you, Romans, that the honour readily offered by
                        yourselves to me, you would grant to his suit, and to my prayers added in
                        his behalf. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The favour was granted to the request of the
                    father, and his son, Publius Licinius, was declared military tribune with
                    consular power along with those whom I have mentioned above. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Titinius and Genucius, military tribunes, proceeded against
                    the Faliscians and Capenatians, and whilst they conduct the war with more
                    courage than conduct, they fall into an ambush. Genucius, atoning for his
                    temerity by an honourable death, fell among the foremost in front of the
                    standards. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Titinius, having collected his men
                    from the great confusion [into which they were thrown] on a rising ground,
                    restored their order of battle; nor did he, however, venture to engage the enemy
                    on even ground. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> More of disgrace than of loss
                    was sustained; which was well nigh proving a great calamity; so much alarm was
                    excited not only at Rome, whither an exaggerated account of it had reached, but
                    in the camp also at Veii. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There the soldiers
                    were with difficulty restrained from flight, as a report had spread through the
                    camp that, the generals and army having been cut to pieces, the victorious
                    Capenatians and Faliscians and all the youth of Etruria were not far off.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At Rome they gave credit to accounts
                    still more alarming than these, that the camp at Veii was now attacked, that a
                    part of the enemy was now advancing to the city prepared for an attack: they
                    crowded to the walls, and supplications of the matrons, which the public panic
                    had called forth from their houses, were offered up in the <pb n="346"
                        xml:id="p.346"/> temples; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and the gods
                    were petitioned by prayers, that they would repel destruction from the houses
                    and temples of the city and from the walls of Rome, and that they would avert
                    that terror to Veii, if the sacred rites had been duly renewed, if the prodigies
                    had been expiated. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The games and the Latin festival had now been
                    performed anew; now the water from the Alban lake had been discharged upon the
                    fields, and the fates were demanding [the ruin of] Veii. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly a general destined for the destruction of that
                    city and the preservation of his country, Marcus Furius Camillus, being
                    nominated dictator, appointed Publius Cornelius Scipio his master of the horse.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The change of the general suddenly
                    produced a change in every thing. Their hopes seemed different, the spirits of
                    the people were different, the fortune also of the city seemed changed.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> First of all, he punished according to
                    military discipline those who had fled from Veii in that panic, and took
                    measures that the enemy should not be the most formidable object to the soldier.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then a levy being proclaimed for a certain
                    day, he himself in the mean while makes an excursion to Veii to strengthen the
                    spirits of the soldiers: thence he returns to Rome to enlist the new army, not a
                    single man declining the service. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Youth from
                    foreign states also, Latins and Hernicians, came, promising their service for
                    the war: after the dictator returned them thanks in the senate, all preparations
                    being now completed for the war, he vowed, according to a decree of the senate,
                    that he would, on the capture of Veii, celebrate the great games, and that he
                    would repair and dedicate the temple of Mother Matuta, which had been formerly
                    consecrated by King Servius Tullius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having
                    set out from the city with his army amid the high expectation <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Expectatione, $c.</hi> With confident expectations on the
                        part of his countrymen, rather than simple hope. </note> rather than mere
                    hopes <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> of persons, he first encountered the
                    Faliscians and Capenatians in the district of Nepote. Every thing there being
                    managed with consummate prudence and skill, was attended, as is usual, with
                    success. He not only routed the enemy in battle, but he stripped them also of
                    their camp, and obtained a great quantity of spoil, the principal part of
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> which was handed over to the quaestor; not
                    much was given to the soldiers. From thence the army was marched to Veii, and
                    additional forts close to each other were <pb n="347" xml:id="p.347"/> erected;
                    and by a proclamation being issued, that no one should fight without orders, the
                    soldiers were takes off from those skirmishes, which frequently took place
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> at random between the wall and rampart,
                    [so as to apply] to the work. Of all the works, far the greatest and <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> more laborious was a mine which they commenced to
                    carry into the enemies' citadel. And that the work might not be interrupted, and
                    that the continued labour under ground might not exhaust the same individuals,
                    he divided the number of pioneers into six companies; six hours were allotted
                    for the work in rotation; nor by night or day did they give up, until they made
                    a passage into the citadel. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the dictator now saw that the victory was
                    in his hands, that a most opulent city was on the point of being taken, and that
                    there would be more spoil than had been obtained in all previous wars taken
                    together, that he might not incur either the resentment of the soldiers from a
                    parsimonious <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> partition of the plunder, or
                    displeasure among the patricians from a prodigal lavishing of it, he sent a
                    letter to the senate, <quote> that by the kindness of the immortal gods, his own
                        measures, and the perseverance of the soldiers, Veii would be soon in the
                        power of the Roman people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> What did they thinly should be done with
                    respect to the spoil? Two opinions divided the senate; the one that of the elder
                    Publius Licinius, who on being first asked by his son, as they say, proposed it
                    as his opinion, that a proclamation should be openly sent forth to the people,
                    that whoever wished to share in the plunder, should proceed to the camp before
                    Veii; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the other that of Appius Claudius, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Niebuhr, (vol. ii. p.
                        233,) this fear put into the mouth of Claudius, is attributable to ignorance
                        or forgetfulness on the part of Livy, of the early usage in the dividing of
                        spoils, which had ceased to be observed in the time of Augustus. According
                        to former Roman usage, half of the conquering army was employed, under the
                        sanction <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> of a solemn oath, to subtract
                        nothing, in collecting the spoil, which was then partly divided by lot,
                        partly sold, and the proceeds, if promised to the soldiers, disbursed to
                        them man by man, if otherwise, it was brought into the treasury. Both
                        schemes mentioned here by Livy, it will be observed. contemplated
                        compensation to the people for the war-tax which they had so long paid; but
                        that of Licinius was more <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> favourable,
                        especially to the poor, as the ordinary citizens would receive equal shares,
                        and the compensation would be direct and immediate. Gunne. </note> who,
                    censuring such profusion as unprecedented, extravagant, partial, and one that
                    was unadvisable, <pb n="348" xml:id="p.348"/> if they should once judge it
                    criminal, that money taken from the enemy should be [deposited] in the treasury
                    when exhausted by wars, advised their pay to be paid to the soldiers out of that
                    money, so that the commons might thereby have to pay less tax. For that <quote>
                        the families of all would feel their share of <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> such a bounty in equal proportion; that the hands of
                        the idlers in the city, ever greedy for plunder, would not then carry off
                        the prizes due to brave warriors, as it generally so happens that <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> according as each individual is wont to seek the
                        principal part of the toil and danger, so is he the least active as a
                        plunderer. </quote> Licinius, on the other hand, argued that the money in
                    that case would ever prove the source of jealousy and animosity, and that it
                    would afford grounds for charges before the commons, and thence for seditions
                    and new laws. "That it was more advisable therefore that the feelings of the
                    commons should be conciliated by that bounty; that succour should be afforded
                    them, exhausted and drained <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> by a tax of so
                    many years, and that they should feel the fruits arising from a war, in which
                    they had in a manner grown old. What each took from the enemy with his own hand
                    and brought home with him would be more gratifying and delightful, than if he
                    were to receive a much larger share at the will of another. That the dictator
                    himself wished to shun the odium and recriminations arising from the matter; for
                    that reason he transferred it to the senate. The senate, too, ought to hand the
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> matter thus referred to them over to
                    the commons, and suffer every man to have what the fortune of war gave to to
                    him. This proposition appeared to be the safer, as it would make the senate
                    popular. A proclamation was therefore issued, that those who chose should
                    proceed to the camp to the dictator for the plunder of Veii. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The vast multitude who went filled the camp.
                    Then the dictator, going forth after taking the auspices, having issued orders
                    that the soldiers should take arms, says, <quote> Under thy guidance, O Pythian
                        Apollo, and inspired by thy divinity, I proceed to destroy the city of Veii,
                        and I vow to thee the tenth part of the spoil. <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified">
                            <quote> This <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> vow frequently occurs in
                                Grecian history, like that made of the Persian booty, but this is
                                the only instance in the history of Rome. </quote>  <hi
                                rend="italics">Niebuhr,</hi> vol. ii. 239. </note> Thee also, queen
                        Juno, who <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> inhabitest Veii, I beseech, that
                        thou wilt accompany us, when <pb n="349" xml:id="p.349"/> victors, into our
                        city, soon to be thine, where a temple worthy of thy majesty shall receive
                        thee. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Evocatos.</hi> When the Romans besieged a town, and
                        thought themselves <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> sure of taking it, they
                        used solemnly to call out of it the gods in whose protection the place was
                        supposed to be. </note> Having offered up these prayers, there being more
                    than a sufficient number of men, he assaults the city on every quarter, in order
                    that the perception of the danger threatening them from the mine might be
                    diminished. The Veientians, ignorant that they had already been doomed by
                        <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> their own prophets, already by foreign
                    oracles, that the gods had been already invited to a share in their plunder,
                    that some, called out by vows from their city, were looking towards the temple
                    of the enemy and new habitations, and that they were spending that the last day
                    [of heir existence], fearing nothing less than that, their walls being
                    undermined, the citadel was now filled with enemies, briskly run to the walls in
                    arms, wondering what could be the reason that, when no one had stirred from the
                    Roman posts for so many days, then, as if struck with sudden fury, they should
                    run heedlessly to the walls. A fabulous narrative <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> is introduced here, that, when the king of the Veientians
                    was offering sacrifice, the voice of the aruspex, declaring that the victory was
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> given to him who should cut up the
                    entrails of that victim, having been heard in the mine, incited the Roman
                    soldiers to burst open the mine, carry off the entrails, and bring them to the
                    dictator. But in matters of such remote antiquity, I should deem it sufficient,
                    if matters bearing a resemblance to truth <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> be
                    admitted as true. Such stories as this, more suited to display on the stage,
                    which delights in the marvellous, than to historic authenticity, it is not worth
                    while either to affirm or refute. The mine, at this time full of chosen men,
                    suddenly discharged the armed troops in the temple of Juno which was in the
                    citadel of Veii. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The idea of the
                        Romans working a mine, even through the soil of Veii, so as to be sure of
                        reaching not only the town and the citadel, and even the temple, is
                        considered by Niebuhr as extremely ridiculous. He deems the circumstance
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> a clear proof of the fiction that
                        attaches to the entire story of the capture of Veii. The whole seems to be
                        an imitation of the siege of Troy.  <hi rend="italics">Gunne.</hi>
                    </note> Some of them attack the rear of the enemy on the walls; some tore open
                    the bars of the gates; some set fire to <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the
                    houses, while stones and tiles were thrown down from the roofs by the women and
                    slaves. Clamour, consisting of the various voices of the assailants and <pb
                        n="350" xml:id="p.350"/> the terrified, mixed with the crying of women and
                    children, fills every place. The soldiers being in an instant beaten off from
                    the walls, and the gates being thrown open, some entering in bodies, others
                    scaling the deserted walls, the city become filled with enemies, fighting takes
                    place in every quarter. Then, much slaughter being now made, the ardour of the
                    fight abates; and the dictator commands the heralds to proclaim that the unarmed
                    should be spared. This put an end to bloodshed. Then laying down their arms,
                    they commenced to surrender; and, by permission of the dictator, the soldiers
                    disperse in quest <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> of plunder. And when this
                    was collected before his eyes, greater in quantity and in the value of the
                    effects than he had hoped or expected, the dictator, raising his hands to
                    heaven, is said <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> to have prayed, <quote>
                        that, if his success and that of the Roman people seemed excessive to any of
                        the gods and men, it might be permitted to the Roman people to appease that
                        jealousy with as little detriment as possible to himself and the Roman
                        people. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The passage in the original, in the
                        generality of editions, <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> is read as
                        follows: <hi rend="italics">ut eam invidiam lenire, qum minimo suo private
                            incommodo</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">publicoque, populo Romano liceret:</hi> i. e. that both
                        himself and the Roman people may get over the evil consequences of the
                        jealousy of the gods with as little detriment as possible to either: <hi
                            rend="italics">populi Romani</hi> seems preferable here: i. e. <quote>
                            that <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> it might be allowed to lighten
                            that jealousy, by the least possible injury to his own private interest,
                            and to the public interests of the Roman people. </quote> There were
                        certainly two persons concerned in the <hi rend="italics">invidia</hi> and
                            <hi rend="italics">incommodum</hi> here, Camillus himself, and the Roman
                        people; to whom respectively the <hi rend="italics">damnatio,</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italics">clades captae urbis,</hi> afterwards mentioned, obviously
                        refer. Some editions read, <hi rend="italics">invidiam lenire suo privato
                            incommodo, qum minimo publico populi Romani liceret.</hi> This is the
                        reading <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> adopted by Crevier; i. e.
                            <quote>to appease the jealousy by his own private loss, rather than the
                            least public loss.</quote> This is more in accordance with the account
                        given of Camillus by Plutarch, and contains a sentiment certainly more
                        worthy both of Livy and of Camillus. Sentiments ascribed by Plutarch to
                        Camillus, will have suo private incommodo, quam minimo publico P. R., giving
                        him the patriotic wish to render light the odium by his own private loss,
                            <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/>
                        <hi rend="italics">rather than</hi> the least public loss; or, by his own
                        private loss, but if not, <hi rend="italics">by</hi> as small a public loss
                        as possible. Pop- <hi rend="italics">li</hi> R- <hi rend="italics">i</hi> ,
                        better than <hi rend="italics">o, o,</hi> as <hi rend="italics">liceret</hi>
                        would, in the latter case, apply only to one of the parties; in the former
                        both are understood. </note> It is recorded that, when turning about during
                    this prayer, he stumbled and fell; and to persons judging of the matter by
                    subsequent events, that seemed to refer as an omen to Camillus' own
                    condemnation, and the disaster <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> of the city
                    of Rome being akin, which happened a few years after. And that day was consumed
                    in <pb n="351" xml:id="p.351"/> slaughtering the enemy and in the plunder of
                    this most opulent city. </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following day the dictator sold the
                    inhabitants of free condition by auction: that was the only money applied to
                    public use, not without resentment on the part of the people: <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and for the spoil they brought home with them, they felt no
                    obligation either to their commander, who in his search for abettors of his own
                    parsimony, had referred to the senate a matter within his own jurisdiction, or
                    to the senate, but to the Licinian family, of which the son had laid he matter
                    before the senate, and the father had been the proposer of so popular a
                    resolution. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When all human wealth had been
                    carried away from Veii, they then began to remove the offerings to their gods
                    and the gods themselves, but more after the manner of worshippers than of
                    plunderers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For youths selected from the
                    entire army, to whom the charge of conveying queen Juno to Rome was assigned,
                    after having thoroughly washed their bodies and arrayed themselves in white
                    garments, entered her temple <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> with profound
                    adoration, applying their hands at first with religious awe, because, according
                    to the Etrurian usage, no one but a priest of a certain family had been
                    accustomed to touch that statue. Then when some one, moved either by divine
                    inspiration, or in youthful jocularity, said, <quote>Juno, art thou willing to
                        go to Rome,</quote> the rest joined in shouting that the goddess had nodded
                    assent. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To the story an addition was
                    afterwards made, that her voice was heard, declaring that <quote>she was
                        willing.</quote> Certain it is, we are informed that, having been raised
                    from her pace by machines of trifling power, she was light and easily removed,
                    like as if she [willingly] followed; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and that
                    she was conveyed safe to the Aventine, her eternal seat, whither the vows of the
                    dictator had invited her; where the same Camillus who had vowed it, afterwards
                    dedicated a temple to her. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Such was the fall
                    of Veii, the wealthiest city of the Etrurian nation, which even in its final
                    overthrow demonstrated its greatness; for having been besieged for ten summers
                    and winters without intermission, after it had inflicted considerably greater
                    losses than it had sustained, eventually, fat now at length urging [its
                    destruction], it was carried after all by the contrivances of art, not by force. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When news was brought to Rome that Veii was
                    taken <pb n="352" xml:id="p.352"/> although both the prodigies had been
                    expiated, and the answers of the prophets and the Pythian responses were well
                    known, and though they had selected as their commander Marcus Furius, the
                    greatest general of the day, which was doing as much to promote success as could
                    be done by human prudence; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> yet because the war
                    had been carried on there for so many years with various success, and many
                    losses had been sustained, their joy was unbounded, as if for an event not
                    expected; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and before the senate could pass any
                    decree, all the temples were crowded with Roman matrons returning thanks to the
                    gods. The senate decrees supplications for the space of four days, a number of
                    days greater than [was prescribed] in any former war. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator's arrival also, all ranks pouring out to meet
                    him, was better attended than that of any general before, and his triumph
                    considerably surpassed all the ordinary style of honouring such a day.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The most conspicuous of all was himself,
                    riding through the city in a chariot drawn by white horses; and that appeared
                    unbecoming, not to say a citizen, but even a human being. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The people considered it an outrage on religion that the
                    dictator's equipage should emulate that of Jupiter and Apollo; and for that
                    single reason his triumph was rather splendid than pleasing. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He then contracted for a temple for queen Juno on Mount
                    Aventine, and consecrated that of Mother Matuta: and, after having performed
                    these services to the gods and to mankind, he laid down his dictatorship.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They then began to consider regarding the
                    offering to Apollo; and when Camillus stated that he had vowed the tenth part of
                    the spoil to him, and the pontiff declared that the people ought to discharge
                    their own <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> obligation, a plan was not readily
                    struck out of ordering the people to refund the spoil, so that the due
                    proportion might be set aside out of it for sacred purposes. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At length they had recourse to this which seemed the
                    easiest course, that, whoever wished to acquit himself and his family of the
                    religious obligation, after he had made his own estimate of his portion of the
                    plunder, should pay into the treasury the value <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> of the tenth part, so that out of it a golden offering
                    worthy of the grandeur of the temple and the divinity of the god might be made,
                    suitable to the dignity of the Roman people. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    This contribution also tended to alienate the affections of the commons from
                    Camillus. During these transactions ambassadors came from <pb n="353"
                        xml:id="p.353"/> the Volscians and Aequans to sue for peace; and peace was
                    obtained, rather that the state wearied by so tedious a war might obtain repose,
                    than that the petitioners were deserving of it. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the capture of Veii, the following year
                    had six military tribunes with consular power, the two Publii Cornelii, Cossus
                    and Scipio, Marcus Valerius Maximus a second time, Kaeso Fabius Ambustus a third
                    time, Lucius Furius Medullinus a fifth time, Quintus Servilius a third time. To
                    the Cornelii the Faliscian war, to Valerius and Servilius the Capenatian war,
                    fell by lot. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By them no cities were attempted
                    by storm or by siege, but the country was laid waste, and the plunder of the
                    effects on the lands was driven off; not a single fruit tree, not a vegetable
                    was left on the land. These losses reduced the people of Capena; peace was
                    granted to them on their suing for it. The war among the Faliscians still
                    continued. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Rome in the mean time sedition
                    became multiplied; and for the purpose of assuaging this they resolved that a
                    colony should be sent off to the Volscian country, for which three thousand
                    Roman citizens should be enrolled; and the triumvirs appointed for the purpose,
                    distributed three acres and seven-twelfths to each man. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This donation began to be scorned, because they thought
                    that it was offered as a solace for the disappointment of higher hopes. For why
                    were the commons to be sent into exile to the Volscians, when the magnificent
                    city of Veii was still in view, and the Veientian territory, more fertile and
                    extensive than the Roman territory? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The city
                    also they extolled as preferable to the city of Rome, both in situation, in the
                    grandeur of its enclosures, and buildings, both public and private. Nay, even
                    that scheme was proposed, which after the taking of Rome by the Gauls was still
                    more strongly urged, of removing to Veii. But they destined Veii to be inhabited
                    by half the commons and half the senate; and that two cities of one common
                    republic might be inhabited by the Roman people. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote> A <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> proposal so absurd would have
                            justified the most vehement opposition of the senate. But it is much
                            more probable, that the scope of the proposition was, that on this
                            occasion the whole of the conquered land should <milestone n="7"
                                unit="section"/> be divided, but amongst the whole nation, so that
                            the patricians also and their clients should receive <milestone n="8"
                                unit="section"/> a share as absolute property. </quote>  <hi
                            rend="italics">Neibuhr,</hi> vol. ii. p. 248. </note> When the nobles
                    strove against these measures so strenuously, as to de- <pb n="354"
                        xml:id="p.354"/> dare "that they would sooner die in the sight of the Roman
                    people, than that any <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> of these things should
                    be put to the vote; for that now in one city there were so many dissensions;
                    what would there be in two? Would any one prefer a vanquished to a victorious
                    city; and suffer Veii now after being captured to enjoy greater prosperity than
                    it had before its <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> capture? Lastly, that they
                    may be forsaken in their country by their fellow-citizens; that no power should
                    ever oblige them to forsake their country and fellow-citizens, and follow Titus
                    Licinius (for he was the tribune of the commons who proposed the measure) as a
                    founder to Veii, abandoning the divine Romulus, the son of a god, the parent and
                    founder of the city of Rome. When these proceedings were going on with shameful
                    contentions, (for the <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> patricians had drawn
                    over one half of the tribunes of the commons to their sentiments,) nothing else
                    obliged the commons to refrain from violence, but that whenever a clamour was
                    set up for the purpose of commencing a riot, the principal members of the
                    senate, presenting themselves among the foremost to the crowd, ordered that they
                    themselves should be attacked, struck, and put to death. Whilst they abstained
                    from violating their age, dignity, and honourable station, their respect for
                    them checked their rage even with respect to similar attempts on others. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Camillus, at every opportunity and in all
                    places, stated publicly, <quote> that this was not at all surprising; <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> that the state was gone mad; which, though bound
                        by a vow, yet felt greater concern in all other matters than in acquitting
                        itself of its religious obligations. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He
                        would say nothing of the contribution of an alms more strictly speaking than
                        of a tenth; since each man bound himself in his private capacity by it, the
                        public was set free. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However, that his
                        conscience would not permit him to pass this over in silence, that out of
                        that spoil only which consisted of movable effects, a tenth was set apart;
                        that no mention was made of the city and captured land, which were also
                        included in the vow. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As the discussion of this point seemed
                    difficult to the senate, it was referred to the pontiffs; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Camillus being invited [to the council], the college
                    decided, that whatever had belonged to the Veientians before the uttering of the
                    vow, and had come into the power of the Roman people after the vow was made, of
                    that a tenth part was sacred to Apollo. Thus the city and land <pb n="355"
                        xml:id="p.355"/> were brought into the estimate. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The money was issued from the treasury, and the consular
                    tribunes of the soldier were commissioned to purchase gold with it. And when
                    there was not a sufficient quantity of this [metal], the matrons having held
                    meetings to deliberate on the subject, and by a general resolution having
                    promised the military tribunes <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> their gold
                    and all their ornaments, brought them into the treasury This circumstance was
                    peculiarly grateful to the senate, and they say that in return for this
                    generosity the honour was conferred on the matrons, that they might use covered
                    chariots [when going] to public worship and the games, and open chaises on
                    festival and common days. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A certain weight of
                    gold being received from each and valued, in order that the price might be paid
                    for it, it was resolved that a golden bowl should be made of it, which was to be
                    carried to Delphos as an offering to Apollo. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    As soon as they disengaged their minds from the religious obligation, the
                    tribunes of the commons renew their seditious practices; the populace are
                    excited against all the nobles, but above all against Camillus: <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> that <quote>he by confiscating and consecrating the
                        plunder of Veii had reduced it to nothing.</quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The absent [nobles] they abuse in violent
                    terms: they evince a respect for them in their presence, when they voluntarily
                    presented themselves to their fury. As soon as they perceived that the business
                    would be protracted beyond that year, they re-elect as tribunes of the commons
                    for the following year the same abettors of the law; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> and the patricians strove to accomplish the same thing with
                    respect to those who were opponents of the law. Thus the same persons in a great
                    measure were re-elected tribunes of the commons. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the election of military tribunes the
                    patricians succeeded by their utmost exertions in having Marcus Furius Camillus
                    elected. They pretended that he was wanted as a commander on account of the
                    wars; but he was intended as an opponent to the tribunes in their profusion.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The military tribunes with consular
                    authority elected with Camillus were, Lucius Furius Medullinus a sixth time,
                    Caius Aemilius, Lucius Valerius Publicola, Spurius Postumius, Publius Cornelius
                    a second time. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the commencement of the year
                    the tribunes of the commons took not a step until Marcus Furius Camillus should
                    set out to the Faliscians, as that war had been assigned to him. Then by
                    delaying the project cooled; and <pb n="356" xml:id="p.356"/> Camillus, whom
                    they chiefly dreaded as an antagonist, acquired an increase of glory among the
                    Faliscians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For when the enemy at first
                    confined themselves within the walls, considering it the safest plan, by laying
                    waste their lands and burning their houses, he compelled them to come forth from
                    the city; but their fears prevented them from proceeding to any considerable
                    length. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At about a mile from the town they
                    pitch their camp; trusting that it was sufficiently secure from no other cause,
                    than the difficulty of the approaches, the roads around being rough and craggy,
                    in some parts narrow, in others steep. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But
                    Camillus having followed the direction of a prisoner belonging to the country as
                    his guide, decamping at an advanced hour of the night, at break of day shows
                    himself on ground considerably higher [than theirs]. The Romans worked at the
                    fortifications in three divisions: the rest of the army stood prepared for
                    battle. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There he routs and puts to flight the
                    enemy when they attempted to interrupt his works; and such terror was struck
                    into the Faliscians in consequence, that, in their precipitate flight passing by
                    their own camp which lay in their way, they made for the city. Many were slain
                    and wounded, before that in their panic they could make their way through the
                    gates. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Their camp was taken; the spoil was
                    given up to the quaestors, to the great dissatisfaction of the soldiers; but
                    overcome by the strictness of his authority, they both hated and admired the
                    same firmness of conduct. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then a regular siege
                    of the city took place, and the lines of circumvallation were carried on, and
                    sometimes occasional attacks were made by the townsmen on the Roman posts, and
                    slight skirmishes took place: and the time was spent, no hope [of success]
                    inclining to either side, whilst corn and other provisions were possessed in
                    much greater abundance by the besieged than the besiegers from [the store] which
                    had been previously laid in. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And their toil
                    appeared likely to prove just as tedious as it had at Veii, had not fortune
                    presented to the Roman general at once both an opportunity for displaying his
                    virtuous firmness of mind already tested in warlike affairs, and a speedy
                    victory. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was the custom among the Faliscians to
                    employ the same person as preceptor and private tutor for their children; and,
                    as continues the usage to this day in Greece, several youths were intrusted to
                    the care of one man. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The person <pb n="357"
                        xml:id="p.357"/> who appeared to excel in knowledge, instructed, as t is
                    natural to suppose, the children of the leading men. A he had established it as
                    a custom during peace to carry the boys out beyond the city for the sake of play
                    and of exercise; that custom not having been discontinued during the existence
                    of the war; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> then drawing them away from the
                    gate, sometimes in shorter, sometimes in longer excursions, advancing farther
                    than usual, when an opportunity offered, by varying their play and conversation,
                    he led them on between the enemy's guards, and thence to the Roman camp into his
                    tent to Camillus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There to the atrocious act
                    he added a still more atrocious speech: that <quote> he had delivered Falerii
                        into the hands of the Romans, when he put into their power those children;
                        whose parents are there at the head of affairs. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When Camillus heard this, he says, <quote>
                        Wicked as thou art, thou hast come with thy villanous offering neither to a
                        people nor a commander like thyself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Between us and the Faliscians there exists rot that form of society which is
                        established by human compact; but between both there does exist, and ever
                        will exist, that which nature has implanted. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                        /> There are laws of war as well of peace; and we have learned to wage them
                        justly not less than bravely. We carry arms not against that age which is
                        spared even when towns are taken, but against men who are themselves armed,
                        and who, not having been injured or provoked by us, attacked the Roman camp
                        at Veii. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those thou hast surpassed, as far
                        as lay in you, by an unprecedented act of villany: I shall conquer them, as
                        I did Veii, by Roman arts, by bravery, labour, and by arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then having stripped him naked, and tied his
                    hands behind his back, he delivered him up to the boys to be brought back to
                    Falerii; and supplied them with rods to scourge the traitor and drive him into
                    the city. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At which spectacle, a crowd of
                    people being assembled, afterwards the senate being convened by the magistrates
                    on the extraordinary circumstance, so great a change was produced in their
                    sentiments, that the entire state earnestly demanded peace at the hands of
                    those, who lately, outrageous by hatred and anger, almost preferred the fate of
                    the Veientians to the peace of the Capenatians. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> The Roman faith, the justice of the commander, are cried up in the forum and
                    in the senate-house; and by universal consent ambassadors set out to the camp to
                    Camillus, and thence by permission of Camillus to Rome to <pb n="358"
                        xml:id="p.358"/> the senate, in order to deliver up Falerii. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> When introduced before the senate, they are
                    represented as having spoken thus: <quote> Conscript fathers, overcome by you
                        and your commander by a victory at which neither god nor man can feel
                        displeasure, we surrender ourselves to you, considering that we shall live
                        more happily under your rule than under our own law, than which nothing can
                        be more glorious for a conqueror. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In the
                        result of this war two salutary examples have been exhibited to mankind. You
                        preferred faith in war to present victory: we, challenged by your good
                        faith, have voluntarily given up to you the victory. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> We are under your sovereignty. Send men to receive our
                        arms, our hostages, our city with its gates thrown open. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> You shall never have to repent of our fidelity, nor we
                        of your dominion. </quote> Thanks were returned to Camillus both by the
                    enemy and by his own countrymen. Money was required of the Faliscians to pay off
                    the soldiers for that year, that the Roman people might be relieved from the
                    tribute. Peace being granted, the army was led back to Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Camillus returned home, signalized by
                    much more solid glory than when white horses had drawn him through the city,
                    having vanquished the enemy by justice and good faith, the senate did not
                    conceal their sense of respect for him, but immediately set about acquitting him
                    of his vow; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and Lucius Valerius, Lucius
                    Sergius, Aulus Manlius, being sent in a ship of war as ambassadors to carry the
                    golden bowl to Delphos as an offering to Apollo, were intercepted by the pirates
                    of the Liparenses not far from the Sicilian Strait, and carried to Liparae. It
                    was the custom of the state to make a division of all booty which was acquired,
                    as it were, by public piracy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On that year it
                    so happened that one Timasitheus filled the office of chief magistrate, a man
                    more like the Romans than his own countrymen. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Who, himself reverencing the name of ambassadors, and the offering, and the god
                    to whom it was sent, and the cause of the offering, impressed the multitude
                    also, who almost on all occasions resemble their ruler, with [a sense] of
                    religious justice; and after having brought the ambassadors to a public
                    entertainment, escorted them with the protection of some ships to Delphos, and
                    from thence brought them back in safety to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> By a decree of the senate a league of hospitality was formed with him, and
                    presents were conferred on him by the state. During the same <pb n="359"
                        xml:id="p.359"/> year the war with the Aequans was conducted with varying
                    success; so that it was a matter of doubt both among the troops themselves and
                    at Rome, whether they had been victorious or were vanquished. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman commanders were Caius Aemilius and Spurius
                    Postumius, two of the military tribunes. At first they acted in conjunction;
                    then, after the enemy were routed in the field, it was agreed that Aemilius
                    should take possession of Verrugo with a certain force, and that Postumius
                    should devastate the country. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There, as the
                    latter proceeded rather negligently, and with his troops irregularly drawn up,
                    he was attacked by the Aequans, and an alarm being occasioned, he was driven to
                    the nearest hill; and the panic spread from thence to Verrugo to the other
                    detachment of the army. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When Postumius, having
                    withdrawn his men to a place of safety, summoned an assembly and upbraided them
                    with their fright and flight; with having been beaten by a most cowardly and
                    dastardly enemy; the entire army shout aloud that they deserved to hear all
                    this, and admitted the disgrace they had incurred; but [they promised] that they
                    would make amends, and that the enemy's joy should not be of long duration.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Demanding that he would instantly lead
                    them from thence to the camp of the enemy, (this lay in the plain within their
                    view,) they submitted to any punishment, if they did not take it before night.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Having praised them, he orders them to
                    take refreshment, and to be in readiness at the fourth watch. And the enemy, in
                    order to prevent the flight of the Romans from the hill through the road which
                    led to Verrugo, were posted to meet them; and the battle commenced before
                    daylight, (but the moon was up all the night,) and was not more confused than a
                    battle fought by day. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But the shout having
                    reached Verrugo, when they thought that the Roman camp was attacked, occasioned
                    such a panic, that in spite of the entreaties of Aemilius and his efforts to
                    stop them they fled to Tusculum in great disorder. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> From thence a report was carried to Rome that
                        <quote>Postumius and his army were cut to pieces.</quote> When the dawn of
                    day had removed all apprehension of an ambuscade in case of a hasty pursuit,
                    after riding through the ranks, by demanding [the performance of] their promises
                    he infused such ardour into them, that the Aequans could no longer withstand
                    their impetuosity. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then the slaughter of them
                    in their flight, such as takes place when matters are <pb n="360" xml:id="p.360"
                    /> conducted more under the influence of anger than of courage, was continued
                    even to the total destruction of the enemy, and the melancholy news from
                    Tusculum, the state having been alarmed without cause, was followed by a letter
                    from Postumius decked with laurel, (announcing) that <quote>the victory belonged
                        to the Roman people; that the army of the Aequans was destroyed.</quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the proceedings of the plebeian tribunes
                    had not yet attained a termination, both the commons exerted themselves to
                    continue their office for the promoters of the law, and the patricians to
                    re-elect the opponents of the law; but the commons were more successful in the
                    election of their own magistrates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Which
                    annoyance the patricians avenged by passing a decree of the senate that consuls
                    should be elected, magistrates detested by the commons. After an interval of
                    fifteen years, Lucius Lucretius Flavus and Servius Sulpicius Camerinus were
                    appointed consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the beginning of this
                    year, whilst the tribunes of the commons united their efforts to pass the law,
                    because none of their college were likely to oppose them, and the consuls
                    resisted them with no less energy, the Aequans storm Vitellia, a Roman colony in
                    their territory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The chief part of the
                    colonists made their way in safety to Rome, because the town, having been taken
                    by treachery in the night, afforded an unimpeded mode of escape by the remote
                    side of the city. That province fell to the lot of Lucius Lucretius the consul.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He having set out with his army,
                    vanquished the enemy in the field; and returned victorious to Rome to a much
                    more serious contest. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A day of trial had been
                    appointed for Aulus Virginius and Quintus Pomponius, plebeian tribunes of the
                    two preceding years, in whose defence by the combined power of the patricians,
                    the honour of the senate was involved. For no one laid against them any other
                    impeachment, either of their mode of life or of their conduct in office, save
                    that, to gratify the patricians, they had protested against the tribunitian law.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The resentment of the commons, however,
                    prevailed over the influence of the senate; and by a most pernicious precedent
                    these men, though innocent, were condemned [to pay a fine of] ten thousand <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi> in weight. At this the patricians were very much
                    incensed. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Camillus openly charged the commons
                    with gross violation of duty, <quote> who, now turning their venom against their
                        own body, <pb n="361" xml:id="p.361"/> did not feel that by their iniquitous
                        sentence on the tribune they abolished the right of protesting; that
                        abolishing this right of protesting, they had upset the tribunitian
                        authority. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For they were mistaken in
                        expecting that the patricians would tolerate the unbridled licentiousness of
                        that office. If tribunitian violence could not be repelled by tribunitian
                        aid, that the patricians would find out some other weapon. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The consuls he also blamed, because they had
                    in silence suffered those tribunes who had followed the authority of the senate
                    to be deceived by [their reliance] on the public faith. By openly expressing
                    these sentiments, he every day still further exasperated the angry feelings of
                    the people. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But he ceased not to urge the senate to oppose
                    the law; <quote> that when the day for proposing the law had arrived they should
                        go down to the forum with no other feeling than as men who remembered that
                        they had to contend for their altars and homes, and the temples of the gods,
                        and the soil in which they had been born. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        For that as far as he himself individually was concerned, if during this
                        contest [to be sustained] by his country it were allowable for him to think
                        of his own glory, it would even reflect honour on himself, that a city
                        captured by him should be densely inhabited, that he would daily enjoy the
                        monument of his glory, and that he would have before his eyes a city borne
                        by him in his triumph, that all would tread in the footsteps of his renown.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But that he deemed it an impiety that
                        a city deserted and forsaken by the immortal gods should be inhabited; that
                        the Roman people should reside in a captive soil, and that a vanquished
                        should be taken in exchange for a victorious country. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Stimulated by these exhortations of their
                    leader, the patricians, both young and old, entered the forum in a body, when
                    the law was about to be proposed: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and
                    dispersing the selves through the tribes, each earnestly appealing to the
                    members of their own tribe, began to entreat them with tears <quote> not to
                        desert that country for which they themselves and their fathers had fought
                        most valiantly and successfully, </quote> pointing to the Capitol, the
                    temple of Vesta, and the other temples of the gods around; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote> not to drive the Roman people, exiles and outcasts, from their native
                        soil and household gods into the city of the enemy; and not to bring matters
                        to such a state, that it was better that Veii were not taken, lest Rome
                        should be <pb n="362" xml:id="p.362"/> deserted. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Because they proceeded not by violence, but by
                    entreaties, and in the midst of these entreaties frequent mention was [made] of
                    the gods, the greatest part [of the people] were influenced by religious
                    scruples: and more tribes by one rejected the law than voted for it. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> And so gratifying was this victory to the patricians,
                    that on the following day, on a motion made by the consuls, a decree of the
                    senate was passed, that seven acres a man of Veientian territory should be
                    distributed to the commons; and not only to the fathers of families, but so that
                    all persons in their house in a state of freedom should be considered, and that
                    they might be willing to rear up their children with that prospect. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The commons being won over by such a boon, no
                    opposition was made to holding the elections for consuls. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Valerius Potitus, and Marcus Manlius, who afterwards
                    obtained the surname of Capitolinus, were elected consuls. These consuls
                    celebrated the great games which Marcus Furius, when dictator, had vowed in the
                    Veientian war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the same year the temple of
                    imperial Juno, vowed by the same dictator and during the same war, is dedicated;
                    and they state that the dedication was attended with great zeal by the matrons.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A war scarcely worth mentioning was waged
                    with the Aequans at Algidum, the enemies taking to flight almost before they
                    commenced the fight. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> To Valerius, because he
                    was more persevering in slaughtering them in their flight, a triumph was
                    granted; it was decreed that Manlius should enter the city with an ovation. The
                    same year a new war broke out with the Volsinians; whither an army could not be
                    led, on account of a famine and pestilence in the Roman territories, which arose
                    from drought and excessive heat; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> on account of
                    which the Volsinians forming a junction with the Salpinians, being elated with
                    pride, made an unprovoked incursion into the Roman territories. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> War was then proclaimed against the two states. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Caius Julius died during his censorship; Marcus
                    Cornelius was substituted in his room; a proceeding which was afterwards
                    considered as offensive to religion; because during that lustrum Rome was taken.
                    Nor since that time has a censor ever been substituted in the room of one
                    deceased. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And the consuls being seized by the
                    distemper, it was determined that the auspices should be taken anew during an
                    interregnum. <pb n="363" xml:id="p.363"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Therefore when in pursuance of a decree of the
                    senate the consuls resigned their office, Marcus Furius Camillus is created
                    interrex, who appointed Publius Cornelius Scipio interrex, and he afterwards
                    Lucius Valerius Potitus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By him were appointed
                    six military tribunes with consular power; so that, though any one of them
                    should be incommoded by bad health, the state might have a sufficient number of
                    magistrates. On the calends of July, the following entered on their office,
                    Lucius Lucretius, Servius Sulpicius, Marcus Aemilius, Lucius Furius Medullinus a
                    seventh time, Agrippa Furius, Caius Aemilius a second time. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Of these, Lucius Lucretius and Caius Aemilius got the
                    Volsinians as their province; the Salpinians fell to the lot of Agrippa Furius
                    and Servius Sulpicius. The first engagement was with the Volsinians. The war,
                    important from the number of the enemy, was without difficulty brought to a
                    close. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At the first onset, their army was put
                    to flight. Eight thousand soldiers, hemmed in by the cavalry, laid down their
                    arms and surrendered. The account received of that war had the effect of
                    preventing the Salpinians from hazarding an engagement; the troops secured
                    themselves within their towns. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans
                    drove spoil in every direction, both from the Salpinian and Volsinian territory,
                    there being no one to repel that aggression; until a truce for twenty years was
                    granted to the Volsinians, exhausted by the war, on this condition, that they
                    should make restitution to the Roman people, and furnish the pay of the army for
                    that year. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> During the same year, Marcus
                    Caedicius, a plebeian, announced to the tribunes that in the New Street, where
                    the chapel now stands, above the temple of Vesta, he had heard in the silence of
                    the night a voice louder than that of a human being, which ordered the
                    magistrates to be told, that the Gauls were approaching. This, as is usual, was
                    disregarded, on account of the humble station of the author, and also because
                    the nation was a remote one, and therefore the less known. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And not only were the warnings of the gods disregarded,
                    fate now impending; but further, the only human aid which was left them, Marcus
                    Furius, they drove away from the city; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> who, on
                    a day [of trial] being appointed for him by Lucius Appuleius, a tribune of the
                    people, in reference to the Veientian spoil, he having also lost his son, a
                    young man, about the same time, when he summoned to his house the members of <pb
                        n="364" xml:id="p.364"/> his tribe and his dependents, (they constituted a
                    considerable portion of the commons,) and having sounded their sentiments, he
                    received for answer, <quote> that they would contribute whatever fine he should
                        be condemned to pay; that to acquit him they were unable, </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Niebuhr and Arnold understand these
                        words to signify, that these persons had already made up their minds not to
                        acquit him, or assist him by voting in favour of him in fact, that they
                        could not conscientiously do <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> so. It may,
                        however, signify simply, that the people were so incensed against him, that
                        there existed not a rational prospect of acquittal for him. </note> retired
                    into exile; after praying to the immortal gods, "that if that outrage was done
                    to him without his deserving it, they would at the earliest opportunity give
                    cause to his ungrateful country to regret his absence. In his absence he was
                    fined fifteen thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> in weight. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> That citizen being driven away, who being
                    present, Rome could not be captured, if any thing is certain regarding human
                    affairs; the destined ruin now approaching the city, ambassadors came from the
                    Clusinians, soliciting aid against the Gauls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    A report is current that that nation, allured by the delightfulness of the
                    crops, and more especially of the wine, an enjoyment then new to them, crossed
                    the Alps, and took possession of the lands formerly cultivated by the Etrurians;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that Aruns, a native of Clusium,
                    introduced wine into Gaul for the purpose of enticing the nation, through
                    resentment for his wife's having been debauched by Lucumo, whose guardian he
                    himself had been, a very influential young man, and on whom vengeance could not
                    be taken, unless foreign aid were resorted to; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    that this person served as a guide to them when crossing the Alps, and advised
                    them to lay siege to Clusium. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I would not
                    indeed deny that the Gauls were brought to Clusium by Aruns or any other native
                    of Clusium; but that those persons who laid siege to Clusium were not they who
                    first crossed the Alps, is sufficiently certain. For two hundred years before
                    they laid siege to Clusium and captured the city of Rome, the Gauls passed over
                    into Italy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nor were these the first of the
                    Etrurians with whom the Gauls fought, but long before that they frequently
                    fought with those who dwelt between the Apennines and the Alps. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Before the Roman empire the sway of the Tuscans was much
                    extended by land and by sea; how very powerful <pb n="365" xml:id="p.365"/> they
                    were in the upper and lower seas, by which Italy is encompassed like an island,
                    the names [of these seas] is a proof; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> the one
                    of which the Italian nations have called the Tuscan sea, the general appellation
                    of the people; the other the Hadriatic, from Hadria, a colony of Tuscans.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Greeks call these same seas the
                    Tyrrhenian and Hadriatic. This people inhabited the country extending to both
                    seas in twelve cities, colonies equal in number to the mother cities having been
                    sent, first on this side the Apennines towards the lower sea, afterwards to the
                    other side of the Apennines; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> who obtained
                    possession of all the district beyond the Po, even as far as the Alps, except
                    the corner of the Venetians, who dwell round the extreme point of the
                    [Hadriatic] sea. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Alpine nations also have
                    this origin, more especially the Rhaetians; whom their very situation has
                    rendered savage, so as to retain nothing of their original, except the accent of
                    their language, and not even that without corruption. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Concerning the passage of the Gauls into Italy
                    we have heard as follows. In the reign of Tarquinius Priscus at Rome, the
                    supreme government of the Celts, who compose the third part of Gaul, was in the
                    hands of the Biturigians: they gave a king to the Celtic nation. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> This was Ambigatus, one very much distinguished by
                    his merit, and both his great prosperity in his own concerns and in those of the
                    public; for under his administration Gaul was so fruitful and so well peopled,
                    that so very great a population appeared scarcely capable of being restrained by
                    any government. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He being now advanced in
                    years, and anxious to relieve his kingdom of so oppressive a crowd, declares his
                    intention to bend his sister's sons, Bellovesus and Sigovesus, two enterprising
                    youths, into whatever settlements the gods should grant them by augury:
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that they should take out with them as
                    great a number of men as they pleased, so that no nation might be able to
                    obstruct them in their progress. Then to Sigovesus the Hercynian forest was
                    assigned by the oracle: to Bellovesus the gods marked out a much more cheering
                    route into Italy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He carried out with him from
                    the Biturigians, the Arvernians, the Senonians, the Aeduans, the Ambarrians, the
                    Carnutians, and the Aulercians, all that was superfluous in their population.
                    Having set out with an immense force of horse and foot, he arrived in the
                    country of the Tricastinians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="366" xml:id="p.366"/> Next the Alps were opposed [to their progress], and
                    I am not surprised that they should seem impassable, as they had never been
                    climbed over through any path as yet, as far at least as tradition can extend,
                    unless we are disposed to believe the stories regarding Hercules. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> When the height of the mountains kept the Gauls there
                    penned up as it were, and they were looking around [to discover] by what path
                    they might pass into another world between the summits, which joined the sky, a
                    religious scruple detained them, it having been announced to them that strangers
                    in search of lands were attacked by the nation of the Salyans. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> These were the Massilians, who had come by sea from
                    Phocaea. The Gauls considering this an omen of their own fortune, assisted them
                    in fortifying the ground which they had taken possession of on their first
                    landing, covered with spacious woods. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They
                    themselves crossed the Alps through the Taurinian and pathless forests; and
                    having defeated the Etrurians not far from the Ticinus, on hearing that the land
                    in which they had posted themselves was called Insubria, the same name as the
                    Insubres, a canton of the Aedui: embracing the omen of the place, they built a
                    city there, and called it Mediolanum. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Some time after another body, consisting of
                    Cenomanians, having followed the tracks of the former under the conduct of
                    Elitovius, crossed the Alps through the same forest, with the aid of Bellovesus,
                    and settle themselves where the cities of Brixia and Verona now stand (the
                    Libuans then possessed these places). After these came the Salluvians, who fix
                    themselves near the ancient canton of the Ligurians called Laevi, inhabiting the
                    banks of the Ticinus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Next the Boians and
                    Lingonians, having made their way over through the Penine pass, all the tract
                    between the Po and the Alps being occupied, crossed the Po on rafts, and drove
                    out of the country not only the Etrurians, but the Umbrians also: they confined
                    themselves however within the Apennines. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then
                    the Senonians, the latest of these emigrants, took possession of the track
                    [extending] from the Utens to the Aesis. I find that it was this nation that
                    came to Clusium, and thence to Rome; whether alone, or aided by all the nations
                    of the Cisalpine Gauls, is not duly ascertained. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> The Clusians, terrified at their strange enemy, on beholding their great
                    numbers, the forms of the men such as they had never seen, and the kind <pb
                        n="367" xml:id="p.367"/> of arms [they carried], and on hearing that the
                    troops of the Etrurians had been frequently defeated by them on both sides of
                    the Po, sent ambassadors to Rome to solicit aid from the senate, though they had
                    no claim on the Roman people, in respect either of alliance or friendship,
                    except that the had not defended their relations the Veientians against the
                    Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No aid was obtained: three
                    ambassadors were sent, sons of Marcus Fabius Ambustus, to treat with the Gauls
                    in the name of the senate and Roman people; that they should not attack the
                    allies and friends of the Roman people from whom they had received no wrong.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That they should be supported by the
                    Romans even by force of arms, if circumstances obliged them; but it seemed
                    better that war itself should be kept aloof, if possible; and that the Gauls, a
                    nation strangers to them, should be known by peace, rather than by arms. </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The embassy was a mild one, had it not been
                    consigned to ambassadors too hot in temper, and who resembled Gauls more than
                    Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> To whom, after they delivered their
                    commission in the assembly of the Gauls, the following answer is returned:
                    Though the name of the Romans was new to their ears, yet they believed them to
                    be brave men, whose aid was implored by the Clusians in their perilous
                    conjuncture. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And since they chose to defend
                    their allies against them by negociation rather than by arms, that they on their
                    part would not reject the pacific terms which they propose, if the Clusians
                    would give up to the Gauls in want of land, a portion of their territories which
                    they possessed to a greater extent than they could cultivate; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> otherwise peace could not be obtained: that they wished to
                    receive an answer in presence of he Romans; and if the land were refused them,
                    that the would decide the matter with the sword in presence of the sane Romans;
                    that they might have an opportunity of carrying home an account how much the
                    Gauls excelled all other mortals in bravery. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On the Romans asking what right they had to demand land from the possessors, or
                    to threaten war [in case of refusal], and what business the Gauls had in
                    Etruria, and on their fiercely replying, that they carried their right in their
                    swords, that all things were the property of the brave, with minds inflamed on
                    both sides they severally have recourse to arms, and the battle is commenced.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Here, fate now pressing <pb n="368"
                        xml:id="p.368"/> hard on the Roman city, the ambassadors, contrary to the
                    law of nations, take up arms; nor could this be done in secret, as three of the
                    noblest and bravest of the Roman youth fought in the van of the Etrurians; so
                    conspicuous was the valour of the foreigners. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover Quintus Fabius, riding out beyond the line, slew a general of the Gauls
                    who was furiously charging the very standards of the Etrurians, having run him
                    through the side with his spear: and the Gauls recognised him when stripping him
                    of his spoils; and a signal was given throughout the entire line that he was a
                    Roman ambassador. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Giving up therefore their
                    resentment against the Clusians, they sound a retreat, threatening the Romans.
                    Some gave it as their opinion that they should proceed forthwith to Rome.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The seniors prevailed, that ambassadors
                    should be sent to complain of the injuries done them, and to demand that the
                    Fabii should be given up to them in satisfaction for having violated the law of
                    nations. When the ambassadors had stated matters, according to the instructions
                    given to them, the conduct of the Fabii was neither approved by the senate, and
                    the barbarians seemed to them to demand what was just: but in the case of men of
                    such station party favour prevented them from decreeing that which they felt to
                    be right. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Wherefore lest the blame of any
                    misfortune, which might happen to be received in a war with the Gauls, should
                    lie with them, they refer the consideration of the demands of the Gauls to the
                    people, where influence and wealth were so predominant, that those persons,
                    whose punishment was under consideration, were elected military tribunes with
                    consular power for the ensuing year. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At which
                    proceeding the Gauls being enraged, as was very natural, openly menacing war,
                    return to their own party. With the three Fabii the military tribunes elected
                    were Quintus Sulpicius Longus, Quintus Servilius a fourth time, Servius
                    Cornelius Maluginensis. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Though danger of such magnitude was impending
                    (so completely does Fortune blind the minds of men when she wishes not her
                    threatening stroke to be foiled) a state, which against the Fidenatian and
                    Veientian enemies, and other neighbouring states, had recourse to aid even from
                    the most extreme quarters, and had appointed a dictator on <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> many trying occasions, that same state now, when an enemy,
                    never before seen or heard of, from the ocean and remotest regions <pb n="369"
                        xml:id="p.369"/> of the earth, was advancing in arms against them, looked
                    not for any extraordinary command or aid. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Tribunes, by whose temerity the war had been brought on them, were appointed to
                    the chief direction of affairs, and even making less of the war than fame had
                    represented it, held the levy with no greater diligence than used to be
                    exercised for ordinary wars. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the mean while
                    the Gauls, on hearing that honour was even conferred on the violators of human
                    law, and that their embassy was slighted, inflamed with resentment, over which
                    that nation has no control, immediately snatched up their standards, and enter
                    on their march with the utmost expedition. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    When the cities, alarmed at the tumult occasioned by them as they passed
                    precipitately along, began to run to arms, and the peasants took to flight, they
                    indicated by a load shout that they were proceeding to Rome, taking up an
                    immense space of ground, wherever they passed, with their horses and men, their
                    troops spreading widely in every direction. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But fame and the messengers of the Clusians, and then of the other states one
                    after another, preceding them, the rapid advance of the enemy brought the
                    greatest consternation to Rome; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for, with
                    their tumultuary troops hastily led on, they met them within the distance of the
                    eleventh mile-stone, where the river Allia, descending from the Crustuminian
                    mountains in a very deep channel, joins the river Tiber not far below the road.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Already all places in front and on each
                    side were crowded with the enemy, and this nation, which has a natural turn for
                    causeless confusion, by their harsh music and discordant clamours, filled all
                    places with a horrible din. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There the military tribunes, without having
                    previously selected a place for their camp, without having previously raised a
                    rampart to which they might have a retreat, unmindful of their duty to the gods,
                    to say nothing of that to man, without taking auspices or offering sacrifices,
                    draw up their line, which was extended towards the flanks, lest they should be
                    surrounded by the great numbers of the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Still their front could not be made equal to that of the enemy, though by
                    thinning their line they rendered their centre weak and scarcely connected.
                    There was on the right a small eminence, which it was determined to fill with
                    bodies of reserve; and that circumstance, as it was the first cause of their
                    dismay and flight, so it proved their only means of safety in <pb n="370"
                        xml:id="p.370"/> their flight. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For
                    Brennus, the chieftain of the Gauls, being chiefly apprehensive of some design
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In my translation of this passage
                        I have differed from Baker, who thus renders: <quote> thinking, that as his
                            enemies were few in number, their skill was what he had chiefly to guard
                            against. </quote> Dureau De Lamalle thus translates: <quote>supposant de
                            la ruse aux ennemis, a raison de leur petit nombre.</quote> This is
                        obviously the <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> correct version. </note>
                    being intended in the small number. of the enemy, thinking that the high ground
                    had been seized for this purpose, that, when the Gauls had been engaged in front
                    with the line of the legions, the reserve was to make an attack on their rear
                    and flank, directed his troops against the reserve; certain, that if he had
                    dislodged them <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> from their ground, the victory
                    would be easy in the plain for a force which had so much the advantage in point
                    of numbers: thus not only fortune, but judgment also stood on the side of the
                    barbarians. In the opposite army there appeared nothing like Romans, either in
                    the <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> commanders, or in the soldiers. Terror and
                    dismay had taken possession of their minds, and such a forgetfulness of every
                    thing, that a far greater number of them fled to Veii, a city of their enemy,
                    though the Tiber stood in their way, than by the direct road to Rome, to their
                    wives and children. Their situation defended the reserve for some time;
                    throughout the remainder of the line as soon as the shout was heard, by those
                    who stood nearest on their flank, and by those at a distance on their rear,
                    almost before they could look <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> at the enemy as
                    yet untried, not only without attempting to fight, but without even returning
                    the shout, fresh and unhurt they took to flight. Nor was there any slaughter of
                    them in the act of fighting; but their rear was cut to pieces, whilst they
                    obstructed their flight by their struggling one <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> with another. Great slaughter was made on the bank of the Tiber, whither the
                    entire left wing, having thrown down their arms, directed their flight;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and many who did not know how to swim, or
                    were exhausted, being weighed down by their coats of mail and other defensive
                    armour, were swallowed up in the current. The greatest part however escaped safe
                    to <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Veii; whence not only no reinforcement,
                    but not even an account of their defeat, was forwarded to Rome. Those on the
                    right wing which had been posted at a distance from the river, and rather near
                    the foot of the mountain, all made for Rome, and, without even shutting the
                    gates, fled into the citadel. <pb n="371" xml:id="p.371"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The miraculous attainment of so sudden a
                    victory held even the Gauls in a state of stupefaction. And at first they stood
                    motionless with panic, as if not knowing what had happened; then they
                    apprehended a stratagem; at length they began to collect the spoils of the
                    slain, and to pile up the arms in heaps, as is their custom. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Then, at length, where no appearance of any thing hostile
                    was any where observed having proceeded on their journey, they reach the city of
                    Rome not long before sun-set: where when some horsemen, who had advanced before,
                    brought back word that the gates were not shut, that no guard was posted before
                    the gates, no armed troops on the walls, another cause of amazement similar to
                    the former made them halt; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and dreading the
                    night and ignorance of the situation of the city, they posted themselves between
                    Rome and the Anio, after sending scouts about the walls and the several gates to
                    ascertain what plans the enemy would adopt in their desperate circumstances.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> With respect to the Romans, as the greater
                    part had gone to Veii from the field of battle, and no one supposed that any
                    survived except those who had fled back to Rome, being all lamented as lost,
                    both those living and those dead, they caused the entire city to be filled with
                    wailings. The alarm for the public interest stifled private sorrow, as soon as
                    it was announced that the enemy were at hand. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Presently the barbarians patrolling around the walls in troops, they heard their
                    yells and the dissonant clangour of their arms. All the interval up to the next
                    day kept their minds in such a state of suspense, that an assault seemed every
                    moment about to be made on the city: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> on their
                    first approach, when they arrived at the city, [it was expected;] for if this
                    were not their design, that they would have remained at the Allia; then towards
                    sunset, because there was not much of the day remaining, they imagined that
                    there would attack them before night; then that the design was deferred until
                    night, in order to strike the greater terror. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    At length the approach of light struck them with dismay; and the calamity itself
                    followed closely upon their continued apprehension of it, when the troops
                    entered the gates in hostile array. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> During
                    that night, however, and the following day, the state by no means bore any
                    resemblance to that which which had fled in so dastardly a manner at the Allia.
                    For as there was not a hope that the city could be defended, so small a number
                        <pb n="372" xml:id="p.372"/> of troops now remaining, it was determined that
                    the youth fit for military service, and the abler part of the senate with their
                    wives and children, should retire into the citadel and Capitol; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> and having collected stores of arms and corn, and thence
                    from a fortified post, that they should defend the deities, and the inhabitants,
                    and the Roman name: that the flamen [Quirinalis] and the vestal priestesses
                    should carry away far from slaughter and conflagration the objects appertaining
                    to the religion of the state: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and that their
                    worship should not be intermitted, until there remained no one who should
                    continue it. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If the citadel and Capitol, the
                    mansion of the gods, if the senate, the source of public counsel, if the youth
                    of military age, should survive the impending ruin of the city, the loss would
                    be light of the aged, the crowd left behind in the city, and who were sure to
                    perish <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The aged were doomed
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> to perish under any circumstances, (
                            <hi rend="italics">utique,</hi> ) from scarcity of provisions, whether
                        they retired into the Capitol with the military youth, or were left behind
                        in the city. </note> under any circumstances. And in order that the plebeian
                    portion of the multitude might bear the thing with greater resignation, the aged
                    men, who had enjoyed triumphs and consulships, openly declared that they would
                    die along with them, <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and that they would not
                    burden the scanty stores of the armed men with those bodies, with which they
                    were now unable to bear arms, or to defend their country. Such was the
                    consolation addressed to each other by the aged now destined to death. </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Their exhortations were then turned to the
                    band of young men, whom they escorted to the Capitol and citadel, commending to
                    their valour and youth whatever might be the remaining fortune of a city, which
                    for three hundred and sixty years had been victorious in all its wars.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When those who carried with them all their
                    hope and resources, parted with the others, who had determined not to survive
                    the ruin of their captured city; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> both the
                    circumstance itself and the appearance [it exhibited] was really distressing,
                    and also the weeping of the women, and their undecided running together,
                    following now these, now those, and asking their husbands and children what was
                    to become of them, [all together] left nothing that could be added to human
                    misery. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A great many of them, however,
                    escorted their friends into the citadel, no one either preventing or inviting
                    them; because the measure <pb n="373" xml:id="p.373"/> which was advantageous to
                    the besieged, that of reducing the number of useless persons, was but little in
                    accordance with humanity. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The rest of the
                    crowd, chiefly plebeians, whom so small a hill could not contain, nor could they
                    be supported amid such a scarcity of corn, pouring out of the city as if in one
                    continued train, repaired to the Janiculum. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Frog thence some were dispersed through the country, some made for the
                    neighbouring cities, without any leader or concert, following each his own
                    hopes, his own plans, those of the public being given up as lost. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> In the mean time the Flamen Quirinalis and the vestal
                    virgins, laying aside all concern for their own affairs, consulting which of the
                    sacred deposits should be carried with them, which should be left behind, for
                    they had not strength to carry them all, or what place would best preserve them
                    in safe custody, consider it best to put them into casks and to bury them in the
                    chapel adjoining to the residence of the Flamen Quirinalis, where now it is
                    profane to spit out. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The rest they carry away
                    with them, after dividing the burden among themselves, by the road which leads
                    by the Sublician bridge to the Janiculum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When
                    Lucius Albinius, a Roman plebeian, who was conveying his wife and children in a
                    waggon, beheld them on that ascent among the rest of the crowd which was leaving
                    the city as unfit to carry arms; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> even then
                    the distinction of things divine and human being preserved, considering it an
                    outrage on religion, that the public priests and sacred utensils of the Roman
                    people should go on foot and be carried, that he and his family should be seen
                    in a carriage, he commanded his wife and children to alight, placed the virgins
                    and sacred utensils in the vehicle, and carried them on to Caere, whither the
                    priests had intended to go. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile at Rome all arrangements being now
                    made, as far as was possible in such an emergency, for the defence of the
                    citadel, the crowd of aged persons having returned to their houses, awaited the
                    enemy's coming with minds firmly prepared for death. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Such of them as had borne curule offices, in order that
                    they may die in the insignia of their former station, honours, and merit,
                    arraying themselves in the most magnificent garments worn by those drawing the
                    chariots of the gods in procession, or by persons riding in triumph, seated
                    themselves in their ivory chairs, in the middle of their halls. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Some say that they devoted themselves for their coun- <pb
                        n="374" xml:id="p.374"/> try and the citizens of Rome, Marcus Fabius, the
                    chief pontiff, dictating the form of words. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The Gauls, both because by the intervention of the night they had abated all
                    angry feelings arising from the irritation of battle, and because they had on no
                    occasion fought a well-disputed fight, and were then not taking the city by
                    storm or violence, entering the city the next day, free from resentment or heat
                    of passion, through the Colline gate which lay open, advance into the forum,
                    casting their eyes around on the temples of the gods, and on the citadel, which
                    alone exhibited any appearance of war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> From
                    thence, after leaving a small guard, lest any attack should be made on them
                    whilst scattered, from the citadel or Capitol, they dispersed in quest of
                    plunder; the streets being entirely desolate, rush some of them in a body into
                    the houses that were nearest; some repair to those which were most distant,
                    considering these to be untouched and abounding with spoil. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Afterwards being terrified by the very solitude, lest any
                    stratagem of the enemy should surprise them whilst being dispersed, they
                    returned in bodies into the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> forum and the
                    parts adjoining to the forum, where the houses of the commons being shut, and
                    the halls of the leading men lying open, almost greater backwardness was felt to
                    attack the open than the shut houses; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> so
                    completely did they behold with a sort of veneration men sitting in the porches
                    of the palaces, who besides their ornaments and apparel more august than human,
                    bore a striking resemblance to gods, in the majesty which their looks and the
                    gravity of their countenance displayed. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst
                    they stood gazing on these as on statues, it is said that Marcus Papirius, one
                    of them, roused the anger of a Gaul by striking him on the head with his ivory,
                    while he was stroking his beard, which was then universally worn long; and that
                    the commencement of the bloodshed began with him, that the rest were slain in
                    their seats. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> After the slaughter of the
                    nobles, no person whatever was spared; the houses were plundered, and when
                    emptied were set on fire. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But whether it was that all were not possessed
                    with a desire of destroying the city, or it had been so determined by the
                    leading men of the Gauls, both that some fires should be presented to their
                    view, [to see] if the besieged could be forced into <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> a surrender through affection for their dwellings, and that
                    all the houses should not be burned down, so that what- <pb n="375"
                        xml:id="p.375"/> ever portion should remain of the city, they might hold as
                    a pledge to work upon the minds of the enemy; the fire by no means spread either
                    indiscriminately or extensively on the first day, as is usual in a captured
                    city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans beholding from the citadel
                    the city filled with the enemy, and their running to and fro through all the
                    streets, some new calamity presenting itself in every different quarter, were
                    neither able to preserve their presence of mind, nor even to have perfect
                    command of their ears and eyes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To whatever
                    direction the shouts of the enemy, the cries of women and children, the
                    crackling of the flames, and the crash of falling houses, had called their
                    attention, thither, terrified at every incident, they turned their thoughts,
                    faces, and eyes, as if placed by fortune to be spectators of their falling
                    country, and as if left as protectors of no other of their effects, except their
                    own persons: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> so much more to be commiserated
                    than any others who were ever besieged, because, shut out from their country,
                    they were besieged, beholding all their effects in the power of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nor was the night, which succeeded so
                    shockingly spent a day, more tranquil; daylight then followed a restless night;
                    nor was there any time which failed to produce the sight of some new disaster.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Loaded and overwhelmed by so many evils,
                    they did not at all abate their determination, [resolved,] though they should
                    see every thing in flames and levelled to the dust, to defend by their bravery
                    the hill which they occupied, small and ill provided as it was, being left [as a
                    refuge] for liberty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And now, as the same
                    events recurred every day, as if habituated to misfortunes, they abstracted
                    their thoughts from all feeling of their circumstances, regarding their arms
                    only, and the swords in their right hands, as the sole remnants of their hopes. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls also, after having for several days
                    waged an ineffectual war against the buildings of the city, when they saw that
                    among the fires and ruins of the captured city nothing now remained except armed
                    enemies, neither terrified by so many disasters, nor likely to turn their
                    thoughts to a surrender, unless force were employed, determine to have recourse
                    to extremities, and to make an attack on the citadel. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> A signal being given at break of day, their entire
                    multitude is marshalled in the forum; thence, after raising the shout and
                    forming a testudo, they advance to the attack. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Against <pb n="376" xml:id="p.376"/> whom the Romans, acting neither rashly nor
                    precipitately, having strengthened the guards at every approach, and opposing
                    the main strength of their men in that quarter where they saw the battalions
                    advancing, suffer the enemy to ascend, judging that the higher they ascended,
                    the more easily would they be driven back down the steep. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> About the middle of the ascent they met them: and making a
                    charge thence from the higher ground, which of itself bore them against the
                    enemy, they routed the Gauls with slaughter and destruction, so that never
                    after, either <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> in parties or with their whole
                    force, did they try that kind of fighting. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Laying aside all hope of succeeding by force of arms, they prepare for a
                    blockade; of which having had no idea up to <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    that time, they had, whilst burning the city, destroyed whatever corn had been
                    therein, and during those very days all the provisions had been carried off from
                    the land to Veii. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Accordingly, dividing their
                    army, they resolved that one part should plunder through the neighbouring
                    states, that the other part should carry on the siege of the citadel, so that
                    the ravagers of the country might supply the besiegers with corn. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls, who marched from the city, were led
                    by fortune herself, to make trial of Roman valour, to Ardea, where Camillus was
                    in exile: who, more distressed by the fortune of the public than his own, whilst
                    he now pined away arraigning gods and men, fired with indignation, and wondering
                    where were now those men who with him had taken Veii and Falerii, who had
                    conducted other wars rather by their own valour than by the favour of fortune,
                    hears on a sudden that the army of the Gauls was approaching, and that the
                    people of Ardea in consternation were met in council on the subject. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And as if moved by divine inspiration, after he
                    advanced into the midst of the assembly, having hitherto been accustomed to
                    absent himself from such meetings, he says, "People of Ardea, my friends of old,
                    of late my fellow-citizens also, since your kindness so ordered it, and my good
                    fortune achieved it, let no one of you suppose that I have come forward here
                    forgetful of my condition; but the [present] case and the common danger obliges
                    every one to contribute to the common good whatever service he can in our
                    present alarming situation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And when shall I
                    repay you for your so very important services to me, if I now be remiss? or
                    where will <pb n="377" xml:id="p.377"/> you derive benefit from me, if not in
                    war? By this accomplishment I maintained my rank in my native country: and,
                    unconquered in war, I was banished during peace by my ungrateful
                    fellow-citizens. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To you, men of Ardea, a
                    favourable opportunity has been presented of making a return for all the former
                    favours conferred by the Roman people, such as you yourselves remember, (for
                    which reason, as being mindful of them, you are not to be upbraided with them,)
                    and of obtaining great military renown for this your city over the common enemy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The nation, which now approaches in
                    disorderly march, is one to which nature has given great spirits and bodies
                    rather huge than firm. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Let the disaster of Ron
                    e serve as a proof. They captured the city when lying open to them; a small
                    handful of men from the citadel and Capitol withstand them. Already tired out by
                    the slow process of a siege, they retire and spread themselves through the
                    country. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Gorged with food and wine hastily
                    swallowed, when night comes on they stretch themselves indiscriminately, like
                    brutes, near streams of water, without entrenchment, without guards or advanced
                    posts; more incautious even now than usual in consequence of success. If you
                    then are disposed to defend your own walls, and not to suffer all these places
                    to become Gaul, take up arms in a full body at the first watch: follow me to
                    slaughter, not to battle. If I do not deliver them up to you fettered by sleep,
                    to be butchered like cattle, I decline not the same issue of my affairs at Ardea
                    as I had at Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Both friends and enemies were satisfied that
                    there existed no where at that time a man of equal military talent. The assembly
                    being dismissed, they refresh themselves, carefully watching the moment the
                    signal should be given which being given, during the silence of the beginning of
                    the night they attended Camillus at the gates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Having gone forth to no great distance from the city, they found the camp of the
                    Gauls, as had been foretold, unprotected and neglected on every side, and attack
                    it with a shout. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> No fight any where, but
                    slaughter every where; their bodies, naked and relaxed with sleep, are cut to
                    pieces. Those most remote, however, being roused from their beds, not knowing
                    what the tumult was, or whence it came, were directed to flight, and some of
                    them, without perceiving it, into the midst of the enemy. A great number flying
                    into the territory of Antium, an attack <pb n="378" xml:id="p.378"/> being made
                    on them in their straggling march by the townspeople, were surrounded and cut
                    off. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A like carnage was made of the Tuscans in
                    the Veientian territory; who were so far from compassionating the city which had
                    now been its neighbour for nearly four hundred years, overpowered as it now was
                    by a strange and unheard-of enemy, that at that very time they made incursions
                    on the Roman territory; and laden with plunder, had it in contemplation to lay
                    siege to Veii, the bulwark and last hope of the Roman race. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman soldiers had seen them straggling over the
                    country, and collected in a body, driving the spoil before them, and they
                    perceived their camp pitched at no great distance from Veii. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Upon this, first self-commiseration, then indignation, and
                    after that resentment, took possession of their minds: <quote> Were their
                        calamities to be a subject of mockery to the Etrurians, from whom they had
                        turned off the Gallic war on themselves? </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Scarce could they curb their passions, so as
                    to refrain from attacking them at the moment; and being restrained by Quintus
                    Cadicius, the centurion, whom they had appointed their commander, they deferred
                    the matter until night. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A leader equal to
                    Camillus was all that was wanted; in other respects matters were conducted in
                    the same order and with the same fortunate result. And further, under the
                    guidance of some prisoners, who had survived the nightly slaughter, they set out
                    to Salinae against another body of Tuscans, they suddenly made on the following
                    night still greater havoc, and returned to Veil exulting in their double
                    victory. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, at Rome, the siege, in general, was
                    slow, and there was quiet on both sides, the Gauls being intent only on this,
                    that none of the enemy should escape from between their posts; when, on a
                    sudden, a Roman youth drew on himself the admiration both of his countrymen and
                    the enemy. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was a sacrifice solemnized at
                    stated times by the Fabian family on the Quirinal hill. To perform this Caius
                    Fabius Dorso having descended from the Capitol, in the Gabine cincture, carrying
                    in his hands the sacred utensils, passed out through the midst of the enemy's
                    post, without being at all moved by the calls or threats of any of them, and
                    reached the Quirinal hill; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and after duly
                    performing there the solemn rites, coming back by the same way with the same
                    firm countenance and gait, confident that the gods <pb n="379" xml:id="p.379"/>
                    were propitious, whose worship he had not even neglected when prohibited by the
                    fear of death, he returned to the Capitol to his friends, the Gauls being either
                    astounded at such an extraordinary manifestation of boldness, or moved even by
                    religious considerations, of which the nation is by no means regardless.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In the mean time, not only the courage,
                    but the strength of those at Veii increased daily, not only those Romans
                    repairing thither from the country who had strayed away after the unsuccessful
                    battle, or the disaster of the city being taken, but volunteers also flowing in
                    from Latium, to come in for share of the spoil. It now seemed high time that
                    their country should be recovered and rescued from the hands of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But a head was wanting to this strong
                    body. The very spot put them in mind of Camillus, and a considerable part
                    consisted of soldiers who had fought successfully under his guidance and
                    auspices: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and Caedicius declared that he would
                    not give occasion that any one, whether god or man, should terminate his command
                    rather than that, mindful of his own rank, he would himself call (for the
                    appointment of) a general. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With universal
                    consent it was resolved that Camillus should be sent for from Ardea, but not
                    until the senate at Rome were first consulted: so far did a sense of propriety
                    regulate every proceeding, and so carefully did they observe the distinctions of
                    things in their almost desperate circumstances. They had to pass at great risk
                    through the enemy's guards. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For this purpose a
                    spirited youth, Pontius Cominius, offered his services, and supporting himself
                    on cork was carried down the Tiber to the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> From thence, where the distance from the bank was shortest, he makes his way
                    into the Capitol over a portion of the rock that was craggy, and therefore
                    neglected by the enemy's guard: and being conducted to the magistrates, he
                    delivers the instructions received from the army. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Then having received a decree of the senate, both that
                    Camillus should be recalled from exile at the comitia curiata, and be forthwith
                    appointed dictator by order of the people, and that the soldiers should have the
                    general whom they wished, he passed out the same way and proceeded with his
                    despatches to Veii; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and deputies being sent
                    to Camillus to Ardea, conducted him to Veii: or else the law was passed by the
                    curiae, and he was nominated dictator in his absence; for I am more inclined to
                    believe that he did not set out <pb n="380" xml:id="p.380"/> from Ardea until he
                    found that the law was passed; because he could neither change his residence
                    without an order of the people, nor hold the privilege of the auspices in the
                    army until he was nominated dictator. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these things were going on at Veii, in
                    the mean while the citadel and Capitol of Rome were in great danger. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> For the Gauls either having perceived the track of a
                    human foot where the messenger from Veii had passed, or having of themselves
                    remarked the easy ascent by the rock at the temple of Carmentis, on a moonlight
                    night, after they had at first sent forward an unarmed person, to make trial of
                    the way, delivering their arms, whenever any difficulty occurred, alternately
                    supported and supporting each other, and drawing each other up, according as the
                    ground required, they reached the summit in such silence, that they <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> not only escaped the notice of the sentinels, but
                    of the dogs also, an animal extremely wakeful with respect to noises by night.
                    The notice of the geese they did not escape, which, as being sacred to Juno,
                    were spared though they were in the greatest scarcity of food. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Which circumstance was the cause of their preservation. For
                    Marcus Manlius, who three years before had been consul, a man distinguished in
                    war, being aroused from sleep by their cackling and the clapping of their wings,
                    snatched up his arms, and at the same time calling the others to do the same,
                    proceeds to the spot; and whilst the others are thrown into confusion, he struck
                    with the boss of his shield and tumbles down a Gaul, who had already got footing
                    on the summit; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and when the fall of this man
                    as he tumbled threw down those who were next him, he slew others, who in their
                    consternation had thrown away their arms, and caught hold of the rocks to which
                    they clung. And now the others also having assembled beat down the enemy by
                    javelins and stones, and the entire band, having lost their footing, were hurled
                    down the precipice in promiscuous ruin. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    alarm then subsiding, the remainder of the night was given up to repose, (as far
                    as could be done considering the disturbed state of their minds,) when the
                    danger, even though past, still kept them in a state of anxiety. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Day having appeared, the soldiers were summoned by
                    sound of trumpet to attend the tribunes in assembly, when recompence was to be
                    made both to merit and to demerit; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Manlius was
                    first of all commended for his bravery and presented with <pb n="381"
                        xml:id="p.381"/> gifts, not only by the military tribunes, but with the
                    consent of the soldiers, for they all carried to his house, which was in the
                    citadel, a contribution of half a pound of corn an half a pint of wine: a matter
                    trifling in the relation, but the [prevailing] scarcity had rendered it a strong
                    proof of esteem, when each man, depriving himself of his own food, contributed
                    in honour of one man a portion subtracted from his body and from his necessary
                    requirements. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then the guards of that place
                    where the enemy had climbed up unobserved, we e summoned; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and when Quintus Sulpicius declared openly that he would
                    punish all according to the usage of military discipline, being deterred by the
                    consentient shout of the soldiers who threw the blame on one sentinel, he spared
                    the rest. The man, who was manifestly guilty of the crime, he threw down from
                    the rock, with the approbation of all. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> From
                    this time forth the guards on both sides became more vigilant on the part of the
                    Gauls, because a rumour spread that messengers passed between Veii and Rome, and
                    on that of the Romans, from the recollection of the danger which occurred during
                    the night. </p>
                <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But beyond all the evils of siege and war,
                    famine distressed both armies; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> pestilence,
                    moreover, [oppressed] the Gauls, both as being encamped in a place lying between
                    hills, as well as heated by the burning of the houses, and full of exhalations,
                    and sending up not only ashes but embers also, whenever the wind rose to any
                    degree; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and as the nation, accustomed to
                    moisture and cold, is most intolerant of these annoyances, and, suffering
                    severely from the heat and suffocation, they were dying, the diseases spreading
                    as among cattle, now becoming weary of burying separately, they heaped up the
                    bodies promiscuously and burned them; and rendered the place remarkable by the
                    name of Gallic piles. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A truce was now made
                    with the Romans, and conferences were held with the permission of the
                    commanders; in which when the Gauls frequently alluded to the famine, and
                    referred to the urgency of that as a further motive for their surrendering, for
                    the purpose of removing that opinion, bread is said to have been thrown in many
                    places from the Capitol, into the advanced posts of the enemy. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> But the famine could neither be dissembled nor endured any
                    longer. Accordingly, whilst the dictator is engaged in person in holding a levy,
                    in ordering his <pb n="382" xml:id="p.382"/> master of the horse, Lucius
                    Valerius, to bring up the troops from Veii, in making preparations and
                    arrangements, so that he may attack the enemy on equal terms, in the mean time
                    the army <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> of the Capitol, wearied out with
                    keeping guard and with watches, having surmounted all human sufferings, whilst
                    nature would not suffer famine alone to be overcome, looking forward from day to
                    day, to see whether any succour would come from the dictator, <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> at length not only food but hope also failing, and their
                    arms weighing down their debilitated bodies, whilst the guards were being
                    relieved, insisted that there should be either a surrender, or that they should
                    be bought off, on whatever terms were possible, the Gauls intimating in rather
                    plain terms, that they could be induced for no very great compensation to
                    relinquish the siege. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then the senate was held
                    and instructions were given to the military tribunes to capitulate. Upon this
                    the matter was settled between Quintus Sulpicius, a military tribune, and
                    Brennus, the chieftain of the Gauls, and one thousand pounds' weight of gold was
                    agreed on as the ransom of a people, who were soon after to be the rulers of the
                    world. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To a transaction very humiliating in
                    itself, insult was added. False weights were brought by the Gauls, and on the
                    tribune objecting, his sword was thrown in in addition to the weight by the
                    insolent Gaul, and an expression was heard intolerable to the Romans, <quote>Woe
                        to the vanquished!</quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But both gods and men interfered to prevent
                    the Romans from living on the condition of being ransomed; for by some chance,
                    before the execrable price was completed, all the gold being not yet weighed in
                    consequence of the altercation, the dictator comes up, and orders the gold to be
                    removed, and the Gauls to clear away. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When
                    they, holding out against him, affirmed that they had concluded a bargain, he
                    denied that the agreement was a valid one, which had been entered into with a
                    magistrate of inferior authority without his orders, after he had been nominated
                    dictator; and he gives notice to the Gauls to get ready for battle. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> He orders his men to throw their baggage in a heap,
                    and to get ready their arms, and to recover their country with steel, not with
                    gold, having before their eyes the temples of the gods, and their wives and
                    children, and the soil of their country disfigured by the calamities of war, and
                    all those objects which they were solemnly bound <pb n="383" xml:id="p.383"/> to
                    defend, to recover, and to revenge. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then
                    draws up his army, as the nature of the place admitted, on the site of the
                    half-demolished city, and which was uneven by nature, and he secured all those
                    advantages for his own men, which could be prepared or selected by military
                    skill. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Gauls, thrown into confusion by the
                    unexpected event, take up arms, and with rage, rather than good judgment, rushed
                    upon the Romans. Fortune had now changed; now the aid of the gods and human
                    prudence assisted the Roman cause. At the first encounter, therefore, the Gauls
                    were routed with no greater difficulty than they had found in gaining the
                    victory at Allia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were afterwards beaten
                    under the conduct and auspices of the same Camillus, in a more regular
                    engagement, at the eighth stone on the Gabine road, whither they had betaken
                    themselves after their defeat. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There the
                    slaughter was universal: their camp was taken, and not even one person was left
                    to carry news of the defeat. The dictator, after having recovered his country
                    from the enemy, returns into the city in triumph; and among the rough military
                    jests which they throw out [on such occasions] he is styled, with praises by no
                    means undeserved, Romulus, and parent of his country, and a second founder of
                    the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His country, thus preserved by arms,
                    he unquestionably saved a second time in peace, when he hindered the people from
                    removing to Veii, both the tribunes pressing the matter with greater earnestness
                    after the burning of the city, and the commons of themselves being more inclined
                    to that measure; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and that was the cause of his
                    not resigning his dictatorship after the triumph, the senate entreating him not
                    to leave the commonwealth in so unsettled a state. </p>
                <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> First of all, he proposed matters appertaining
                    to the immortal gods; for he was a most scrupulous observer of religious duties;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and he procures a decree of the senate,
                        <quote> that all the temples, as the enemy had possessed them, should be
                        restored, their bounds traced, and expiations made for them, and that the
                        form of expiation should be sought in the books by the decemvirs; <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> that a league of hospitality should be entered
                        into by public authority with the people of Caere, because they had afforded
                        a reception to the sacred utensils of the Roman people and to their priests;
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and because, by the kindness of that
                        people, the worship of the immortal gods had not been <pb n="384"
                            xml:id="p.384"/> intermitted; that Capitoline games should be exhibited,
                        for that Jupiter, supremely good and great, had protected his own mansion
                        and the citadel of the Roman people when in danger; and that Marcus Furius,
                        the dictator, should establish a college for that purpose, out of those who
                        should inhabit the Capitol and citadel. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Mention was also introduced of expiating the
                    voice heard by night, which had been heard announcing the calamity before the
                    Gallic war, and neglected, and a temple was ordered in the New Street to Aius
                    Locutius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The gold which had been rescued from
                    the Gauls, and that also which during the alarm had been collected from the
                    other temples into the recess of Jupiter's temple, the recollection being
                    confused as to the temples to which it should be carried back, was all judged to
                    be sacred, and ordered to be placed under the throne of Jupiter. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Already the religious scruples of the state had
                    appeared in this, that when gold was wanting for public uses, to make up for the
                    Gauls the amount of the ransom agreed upon, they had accepted that which was
                    contributed by the matrons, so that they might not touch the sacred gold. Thanks
                    were returned to the matrons, and to this was added the honour of their having
                    funeral orations pronounced on them after death, in the same manner as the men.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Those things being finished which
                    appertained to the gods, and such measures as could be transacted through the
                    senate, then, at length, as the tribunes were teasing the commons by their
                    unceasing harangues, to leave the ruins, to remove to Veii, a city ready
                    prepared for them, being escorted by the entire senate, he ascends the tribunal,
                    and spoke as follows: </p>
                <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Romans, so disagreeable to me are contentions
                    with the tribunes of the people, that in my most melancholy exile, whilst I
                    resided at Ardea, I had. no other consolation than that I was removed from these
                    contests; and for this same reason I would never have returned, even though you
                    recalled me by a decree of the senate, and by order of the people. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Nor has it been any change in my own sentiments, but
                    in your fortune, that has persuaded me to return now. For the question was that
                    my country should remain in its own established seat, not that I should reside
                    in my country. And on the present occasion I would gladly remain quiet and
                    silent, were not the present struggle also appertaining to my country's
                    interests, to be wanting to which, as long as life lasts, were <pb n="385"
                        xml:id="p.385"/> base in others, in Camillus impious. For why have we
                    recovered it? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Why have we rescued it when
                    besieged out of the hands of the enemy, if we ourselves desert it when
                    recovered? And when, the Gauls being victorious, the entire city captured, both
                    the gods and the natives of Rome still retained and inhabited the Capitol and
                    citadel, shall even the citadel and the Capitol be deserted, now when the Romans
                    are victorious and the city has been recovered? And s all our prosperous fortune
                    cause more desolation to this city than our adverse caused? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Truly if we had no religious institutions established
                    together with the city, and regularly transmitted down to us, still the divine
                    power has so manifestly interested itself in behalf of the Roman state on the
                    present trying occasion, that I should think that all neglect of the divine
                    worship was removed from the minds of men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For
                    consider the events of these latter years one after the other, whether
                    prosperous or adverse; you will find that all things succeeded favourably with
                    us whilst we followed the gods, and unfavourably when we neglected them.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Now, first of all the Veientian war of
                    how many years' duration, with what immense labour waged! was not brought to a
                    termination, until the water was discharged from the Alban lake by the
                    admonition of the gods. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What, in the name of
                    heaven, regarding this recent calamity of our city? did it arise, until the
                    voice sent from heaven concerning the approach of the Gauls was treated with
                    slight? until the law of nations was violated by our ambassadors, and until such
                    violation was passed over by us with the same indifference towards the gods,
                    when it should have been punished by us? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly vanquished, made captives and ransomed, we have suffered such
                    punishments at the hands of gods and men, as that we are now a warning to the
                    whole world. Afterwards our misfortunes reminded us of our religious duties.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> We fled for refuge to the gods, to the
                    seat of Jupiter supremely good and great; amid the ruin of all our effects our
                    sacred utensils we partly concealed in the earth; part of them we carried away
                    to the neighbouring cities and removed from the eyes of the enemy. Though
                    deserted by gods and men, still we intermitted not the worship of the gods.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Accordingly they have restored to us our
                    country, and victory, our ancient renown in war which had been lost, and on our
                    enemies, who, blinded by avarice, have violated <pb n="386" xml:id="p.386"/> the
                    faith of a treaty with respect to the weight of gold, they have turned dismay,
                    and flight, and slaughter. </p>
                <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "When you behold such striking instances of
                    the effects of honouring or neglecting the deity, do you perceive what an act of
                    impiety we are about to perpetrate, scarcely emerging from the wreck of our
                    former misconduct and calamity? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> We possess a
                    city founded under auspices and auguries; not a spot is there in it that is not
                    full of religious rites and of the gods: the days for the anniversary sacrifices
                    are not more definitely stated, than are the places in which they are to be
                    performed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All these gods, both public and
                    private, do ye, Romans, pretend to forsake. What similarity does your conduct
                    bear [to that] which lately during the siege was beheld with no less admiration
                    by the enemy than by yourselves in that excellent Caius Fabius, when he
                    descended from the citadel amid the Gallic weapons, and performed on the
                    Quirinal hill the solemn rites of the Fabian family? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Is it your wish that the family religious rites should not
                    be intermitted even during war, but that the public rites and the Roman gods
                    should be deserted even in time of peace, and that the pontiffs and flamens
                    should be more negligent of public religious ceremonies, than a private
                    individual in the anniversary rite of a particular family? <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Perhaps some one may say, that we will either perform these
                    duties at Veii, or that we will send our priests hither from thence in order to
                    perform them; neither of which can be done, without infringing on the
                    established forms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For not to enumerate all
                    the sacred rites severally and all the gods, whether in the banquet of Jupiter
                    can the lectisternium be performed in any other place, save in the Capitol?
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What shall I say of the eternal fire of
                    Vesta, and of the statue, which, as the pledge of empire, is kept under the
                    safeguard of her temple? What, O Mars Gradivus, and you, father Quirinus, of
                    your Ancilia? Is it right that these sacred things, coeval with the city, some
                    of them more ancient than the origin of the city, should be abandoned to
                    profanation? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And, observe the difference
                    existing between us and our ancestors. They handed down to us certain sacred
                    rites to be performed by us on the Alban and on the Lavinian mounts. Was it in
                    conformity with religion that these sacred rites were transferred to us to Rome
                    from the cities of our enemies? shall we transfer them hence <pb n="387"
                        xml:id="p.387"/> to Veii, an enemy's city, without impiety? <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Come, recollect how often sacred rites are performed anew,
                    because some ceremony of our country had been omitted through negligence or
                    accident. On a late occasion, what circumstance, after the prodigy of the Alban
                    lake, proved a remedy to the state distressed by the Veientian war, but the
                    repetition of the sacred rites and the renewal of the auspices? <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> But further, as if duly mindful of ancient religious
                    usages, we have both transferred foreign deities to Rome, and have established
                    new ones. Very recently, imperial Juno was transferred from Veii, and had her
                    dedication performed on a day how distinguished for the extraordinary zeal of
                    the matrons, and with what a full attendance! <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    We have directed a temple to be erected to Aius Locutius, in consequence of the
                    heavenly voice heard in the New Street. To our other solemnities we have added
                    the Capitoline games, and, by direction of the senate, we have founded a new
                    college for that purpose. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Which of these
                    things need we have done, if we were to leave the Roman city together with the
                    Gauls? if it was not voluntarily we remained in the Capitol for so many months
                    of siege; if we were retained by the enemy through motives of fear? <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> We are speaking of the sacred rites and of the
                    temples; what, pray, of the priests? Does it not occur to you, what a degree of
                    profaneness would be committed in respect of them. The Vestals, forsooth, have
                    but that one settlement, from which nothing ever disturbed them, except the
                    capture of the city. It is an act of impiety for the flamen Dialis to remain for
                    a single night without the city. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Do ye mean
                    to make them Veientian instead of Roman priests? And shall the virgins forsake
                    thee, O Vesta? And shall the flamen by living abroad draw on himself and on his
                    country such a weight of guilt every night? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    What of the other things, all of which we transact under auspices within the
                    Pomaerium, to what oblivion, to what neglect do we consign them? <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> The assemblies of the Curias, which comprise
                    military affairs; the assemblies of the Centuries, at which you elect consuls
                    and military tribunes, when can they be held under auspices, unless where they
                    are wont [to be held]? Shall we transfer them to Veii? <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> or whether for the purpose of holding their elections shall
                    the people assemble at so great inconvenience into a city deserted by gods and
                    men? <pb n="388" xml:id="p.388"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "But the case itself forces us to leave a city
                    desolated by fire and ruin, and remove to Veii, where all things are entire, and
                    not to distress the needy commons by building here. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But that this is only held out as a pretext, rather than
                    that it is the real motive, I think is evident to you, though I should say
                    nothing on the subject; for you remember that before the arrival of the Gauls,
                    when the buildings, both public and private, were still unhurt, and the city
                    still stood in safety, this same question was agitated, that we should remove to
                    Veii. Observe then, tribunes, what a difference there is between my way of
                    thinking and yours. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Ye think that though it
                    may not have been advisable to do it then, still that now it ought certainly to
                    be done; I, on the contrary, (and be not surprised until you shall have heard
                    the state of the case,) admitting it were advisable to remove when the entire
                    city was safe, would not vote for relinquishing these ruins now. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> For then victory would be the cause of our removing
                    into a captured city, one that would be glorious to ourselves and our posterity;
                    whilst now this same removal would be wretched and disgraceful to us, and
                    glorious to the Gauls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For we shall appear not
                    to have left our country as conquerors, but to have lost it from having been
                    vanquished; the flight at Allia, the capture of the city, the blockading of the
                    Capitol, [will seem] to have imposed this necessity on us of forsaking our
                    household gods, of having recourse to exile and flight from that place which we
                    were unable to defend. And have the Gauls been able to demolish Rome, which the
                    Romans shall be deemed to have been unable to restore? <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> What remains, but that if they should now come with new
                    forces, (for it is evident that their number is scarcely credible,) and should
                    they feel disposed to dwell in this city, captured by them, and deserted by you,
                    would you suffer them? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What, if not the Gauls,
                    but your old enemies, the Aequans and Volscians, should form the design of
                    removing to Rome; would you be willing that they should become Romans, you
                    Veientians? Would ye prefer that this should be a desert in your possession, or
                    a city of the enemy? For my part I can see nothing more impious. Is it because
                    ye are averse to building, ye are prepared to incur this guilt, this disgrace?
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Even though no better, no more ample
                    structure could be erected throughout the entire city than that cottage of our
                    founder, is it not bet- <pb n="389" xml:id="p.389"/> ter to dwell in cottages,
                    like shepherds and rustics, amid your sacred places and your household gods,
                    than to go publicly into exile? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Our
                    forefathers, strangers and shepherds, when there was nothing in these places but
                    woods and marshes, erected a new city in a very short time; do we, with a
                    Capitol and citadel safe, and the temples of the gods still standing, feel it
                    irksome to build up what has been burnt? and what we individually would have
                    done, if our private residence had been burned down, shall we as a body refuse
                    to do in the case of a public conflagration? </p>
                <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> What, if by some evil design or accident a file should break out at
                        Veii, and the flames spread by the wind, as may happen, should consume a
                        considerable portion of the city; are we then to seek Fidenae, or Gabii, or
                        any other city to remove to? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Has our
                        native soil so slight a hold on us, or this earth which we call mother; or
                        does our love of country lie merely in the surface and in the timber of the
                        houses? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For my part, I will acknowledge to
                        you, whilst I was absent, though I am less disposed to remember this as the
                        effect of tour injustice than of my own misfortune, as often as my country
                        came into my mind, all these circumstances occurred to me, the hills, the
                        plains, the Tiber, the face of the country familiar to my eyes, and this
                        sky, beneath which I had been born and educated; may these now induce you,
                        by their endearing hold on you, to remain in your present settlement, rather
                        than they should cause you to pine away through regret, after having left
                        them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Not without good reason did gods and
                        men select this place for founding a city: these most healthful hills; a
                        commodious river, by means of which the produce of the soil may be conveyed
                        from the inland countries, by which maritime supplies may be obtained; close
                        enough to the sea for all purposes of convenience, and not exposed by too
                        much proximity to the dangers of foreign fleets; a situation in the centre
                        of the regions of Italy, singularly adapted by nature for the increase of a
                        city. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The very size of so new a city is a
                        proof. Romans, the present year is the three hundred and sixty-fifth year of
                        the city; for so long a time are you waging war amid nations of such long
                        standing; yet not to mention single cities, neither the Volscians combined
                        with the Aequans, so many and such strong towns, nor all Etruria, so potent
                        by land and sea, occupying the breadth of Italy between the two seas, can
                            <pb n="390" xml:id="p.390"/> cope with you in war. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> And as the case is so, where, in the name of goodness,
                        is the wisdom in you who have tried [this situation] to make trial now of
                        some other, when, though your own valour may be removed elsewhere, the
                        fortune of this place certainly cannot be transferred? <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Here is the Capitol, where, a human head being found,
                        it was foretold that in that place would be the head of the world, and the
                        chief seat of empire. Here, when the Capitol was to be freed by the rites of
                        augury, Juventas and Terminus, to the very great joy of our fathers,
                        suffered not themselves to be moved. Here is the fire of Vesta, here the
                        Ancilia sent down from heaven, here are all the gods propitious to you if
                        you stay. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Camillus is said to have moved them as well by
                    other parts of his speech, but chiefly by that which related to religious
                    matters. But an expression seasonably uttered determined the matter whilst still
                    undecided; for when a meeting of the senate, a little after this, was being held
                    in the Curia Hostilia regarding these questions, and some troops returning from
                    relieving guard passed through the forum in their march, a centurion in the
                    comitium cried out, <quote> Standard-bearer, fix your standard! <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> it is best for us to remain here. </quote> Which
                    expression being heard, both the senate came out from the senate-house, and all
                    cried out that <quote>they embraced the omen,</quote> and the commons, who were
                    collected around, joined their approbation. The law [under discussion] being
                    rejected, the building of the city commenced in several parts at once.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Tiles were supplied at the public expense.
                    The privilege of hewing stone and felling timber wherever each person wished was
                    granted, security being taken that they would finish the buildings on that year.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Their haste took away all attention to the
                    regulating the course of the streets, whilst, setting aside all distinction of
                    property, they build on any part that was vacant. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> That is the reason why the ancient sewers, at first
                    conducted through the public streets, now in many places pass under private
                    houses, and why the form of the city appears more like one taken up by
                    individuals, than regularly portioned out [by commissioners]. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
