<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 5-7 - 5</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books V, VI and VII With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1924: no copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.3"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="book">
                <head>Book V</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Peace was now established elsewhere, but <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> Romans and
                    Veientes were at war, and their rage and animosity were such that the end was
                    clearly at hand for those that should be vanquished. Each people held an
                    election very different from that of the other. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> The Romans enlarged the number of their military tribunes with consular
                    authority, and elected eight, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy
                        seems to have erred through including the names of the censors, Camillus and
                        Albinus, in his list of tribunes, of whom there were at this time but six.
                        See chap. x. § 1 and chap. xiv. § 5 and notes there. </note> a greater
                    number than ever before, to wit, Manius Aemilius Mamercus (for the second time),
                    Lucius Valerius Potitus (for the third), Appius Claudius Crassus, Marcus
                    Quinctilius Varus, Lucius Julius lulus, Marcus Postumius, Marcus Furius
                    Camillus, Marcus Postumius Albinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But the
                    Veientes, weary of annual canvassing, which was sometimes the cause of brawls,
                    chose a king. This gave offence to the feelings of the Etruscan peoples, who
                    loathed not more the institution of kings than the King himself. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> He had for some time been hateful to the nation by
                    reason of his wealth and arrogance, since he had violently broken up a solemn
                        <pb n="p.5"/> festival, which it is impious to interrupt, in his <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> resentment
                    of a political rebuff; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and because the
                    suffrages of the Twelve Peoples had returned another man as priest in preference
                    to him, he had suddenly carried off the actors, most of whom were his own
                    slaves, in the middle of the games. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And so the
                    nation which was devoted beyond all others to religious rites (and all the more
                    because it excelled in the art of observing them) voted to refuse its help to
                    the men of Veil, so long as they should obey a king. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> This vote the Veientes would not suffer to be mentioned, in
                    their fear of the King, who had a way of treating the man by whom any such
                    saying was reported as a leader in sedition, not as the bearer of an idle tale.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Although the Romans got word that things
                    were quiet in Etruria, still, because they <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    heard that this question came up at all their meetings, they so constructed
                    their works as to have a double fortification, one facing Veii, to oppose the
                    sallies of the townsfolk, the other confronting Etruria, to shut off any
                    assistance that might come from thence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the Roman generals hoped more from a siege
                    than from an assault, they even began the erection of winter quarters —a new
                    thing to the Roman soldier —and planned to carry the campaign on, straight
                    through the winter. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When news of this came to
                    Rome, to the plebeian tribunes, who had now for a long time been unable to
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> hit upon any pretext for agitation, they
                    hurried before the assembly and set to work upon the passions of the commons: So
                    this was the reason that the soldiers had been granted pay! <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> They had not been mistaken in thinking that this gift of
                    their opponents would be smeared with poison. The liberty of the <pb n="p.7"/>
                    commons had been sold; the young men, having <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> been permanently removed and
                    banished from the City and from the state, were no longer free, even in winter
                    and the stormy season, to see to their homes and their affairs. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> What, they asked, did their hearers suppose to be the
                    reason for making the service continuous? They would assuredly find no other
                    motive than this: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> lest, through the presence
                    in large numbers of the young men in whom lay all the vigour of the commons,
                    something might be accomplished for the people's good. Moreover, they were far
                    more ruthlessly abused and trodden down than <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    were the Veientes, who, for their part, spent the winter in their houses,
                    safeguarding their city by means of strong walls and natural defences, whilst
                    the Roman soldiers were enduring toil and danger, overwhelmed with snows and
                    frosts, in tents, not even laying aside their weapons in the winter time, a
                    season of respite from all wars both by land and by sea. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Such slavery as this neither kings, nor the proud consuls
                    who came before the establishment of the tribunician power, nor the stern
                    authority of a dictator, nor harsh decemvirs, had laid upon them, — that they
                    should wage perennial war. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Pray what would
                    those men do if they should become consuls or dictators, who had made the
                    semblance of consular authority so savage and truculent? But the commons were
                    only getting their deserts. There had been no room even amongst eight military
                    tribunes for a single plebeian. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Heretofore
                    the patricians had been wont with the utmost exertion to fill three places in a
                    year: now they were advancing eight abreast to make good their authority, and
                    there was never a commoner hanging on to the crowd, were it <pb n="p.9"/> only
                    to remind his colleagues that their soldiers were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B c. 403</note> not slaves but freemen and
                    fellow citizens; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> whom, at least in winter,
                    they were bound to bring back to the shelter of their houses, and to leave them
                    some portion of the year to <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> look after
                    their parents, their children, and their wives, and to use their liberty and
                    elect magistrates. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> As they shouted forth these and suchlike
                    arguments, they found an opponent not unequal to them in Appius Claudius, whom
                    his colleagues had left behind to repress sedition on the part of the tribunes.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> He was a man experienced from his youth
                    up in contentions with the plebs, and I have related how, some years before, he
                    had advised that the intervention of their colleagues be used to break the power
                    of the tribunes. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See Book IV, chap.
                        xlviii. The Appius Claudius here mentioned was a grandson of the decemvir.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The man not only had a nimble wit but was
                    already a practised orator, and he delivered on this occasion a speech to the
                    following effect: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> "If it has ever been a
                    question, Quirites, whether it was for your sake or their own that the tribunes
                    of the commons have always encouraged sedition, I am certain that the doubt has
                    this year been resolved; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and not only do I
                    rejoice that you have at length cleared up a long misunderstanding, but I
                    congratulate both you, - and on your account the state as well, that it has:
                    happened at a time, of all others, when your affairs are prospering. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Or is there anyone who doubts that no wrongs which
                    you have suffered, if haply such there have sometimes been, have ever so
                    offended and stirred up the plebeian tribunes as has the boon which the Fathers
                    bestowed upon the commons, when they granted pay for military service?
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> What else do you believe they <pb n="p.11"
                    /> were afraid of then, or are seeking now to shatter, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 403</note> but the harmony of the
                    orders, which they regard as very apt to overthrow the tribunician authority?
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Indeed they are like quack-salvers seeking
                    employment, since they desire that there should always be some disease in the
                    body politic, that there may be something which you may call them in to cure.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Pray, are you tribunes defending the
                    commons, or attacking them? Are you adversaries of the soldiers, or their
                    advocates? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Or perhaps this is your plea:
                    'Whatever the Fathers do displeases us, be it in behalf of the commons or
                    against them'; and just as masters forbid outsiders to have aught to do with
                    their slaves, and think it right that they should abstain alike from benefiting
                    and from harming them, so you deny the Fathers intercourse with the commons,
                    lest we by our friendliness and liberality encourage them, or they become
                    dutiful and obedient to us. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> How much more, if
                    you had in you the slightest —I say not patriotism, but —humanity, ought you
                    rather to have favoured, and, so far as in you lay, to have encouraged the
                    kindly spirit of the Fathers and the complaisance of the plebs? <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> And if this harmony should last, who would not make
                    bold to warrant that our empire would soon be the greatest among the
                    neighbouring peoples? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "I shall presently explain, in regard to this
                    plan of my colleagues, who have not been willing to withdraw the army from Veii
                    with its task unaccomplished, —how not merely profitable but even necessary it
                    was. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But first I wish to speak about the
                    actual condition of the soldiers; and I think that if I should express my
                    meaning not in your presence only but also in the camp, the army itself <pb
                        n="p.13"/> would judge it reasonable. Indeed, though I were <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> unable to
                    think of anything to urge myself, I could be quite content with the speeches of
                    my opponents. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were lately insisting that
                    pay ought not to be given to the men, because it never had been given. How then
                    can they object, if to those who have gained some new advantage be allotted new
                    labour also, in proportion. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nowhere, as a
                    rule, is service given without recompense, nor recompense except for service;
                    toil and pleasure, most unlike in nature, have been linked together in a sort of
                    natural bond. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Formerly the soldier was vexed
                    that he must serve the state at his own cost; yet he was happy to be able, for a
                    half of the year, to till his own field and gain the means of keeping himself
                    and his family, whether he were at home or with the army. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Now he is happy that the state affords him gain, and is
                    glad to receive his pay. Let him therefore be resigned to remaining away a
                    little longer from his home and his property, which is now under no heavy
                    charges. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Why, if the commonwealth should call
                    him to a reckoning, would it not justly say, 'You have a year's stipend, render
                    a year's service; do you think it right that for a campaign of six months you
                    should receive the pay of twelve?' <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I dislike
                    to dwell upon this point, Quirites; for it is thus that men who employ
                    mercenaries ought to argue; we would deal as though with fellow citizens, and we
                    think it only right that you deal with us as with your native country.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Either we ought not to have undertaken the
                    war, or we ought to conduct it as befits the Roman People, and end it as quickly
                    as possible. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And we shall end it, if we press
                    our beleaguered foes, and quit them not till we have fulfilled our <pb n="p.15"
                    /> hopes and captured Veii. Truly, if there were no <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> other reason, the very
                    indignity of the thing should compel us to persist! <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Did all Greece once, for one woman's sake, war ten years
                    against a city so far from home, with all those lands and seas between?
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And does it irk us, being less than
                    twenty miles away and almost within sight of Rome, to maintain a siege for a
                    single year? Doubtless our reason for fighting is a trivial one, and we have no
                    proper and sufficient grievance to incite us to persevere! <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Seven times have they renewed the war; never have they kept
                    faith in peace; our fields they have pillaged a thousand times; they forced the
                    Fidenates to forsake us; our settlers there they put to death; <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> it was they who instigated, in violation of the law of
                    nations, the impious murder of our envoys; they sought to raise up all Etruria
                    against us, and they are striving to this end to-day; when our ambassadors
                    sought redress they well-nigh did them bodily injury. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "With such enemies ought we to wage a
                    fainthearted and dilatory war? If so just grounds of resentment have no power to
                    move us, pray have the following considerations none? <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The city is hemmed in with vast siege-works, which confine
                    the enemy within his walls; he has not cultivated his land, and what was
                    cultivated has been laid waste in the war; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> if
                    we bring our army back, who can doubt that not only a desire for revenge, but
                    also necessity, constraining them to plunder others since they have lost their
                    own possessions, will cause them to invade our territory? So we are not
                    postponing the war, if we act on your advice, but are receiving it within our
                    own borders. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> And what of that matter which <pb
                        n="p.17"/> specially concerns the soldiers, whom the worthy <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 403</note> plebeian
                    tribunes formerly wished to rob of their pay, but are now desirous of
                    protecting? How does it stand with them? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    rampart and the trench, each involving prodigious toil, they have carried all
                    that distance; forts they erected only a few at first, but since then, with the
                    growth of the army, they have built very many; they have thrown up earthworks,
                    not only against the city, but also facing Etruria, if any aid should come from
                    that side; what need to speak of towers, mantlets, penthouses, and the rest of
                    the equipment for storming towns? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When they
                    have expended all this labour, and the end of their task is at last in sight, do
                    you: vote for abandoning these things, that when summer comes they may sweat and
                    toil again to produce them afresh? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> How much
                    less effort it requires to guard what is already made, and to press on and
                    persevere and put an end to our anxiety! For surely it is- a thing soon done, if
                    we carry it through without stopping, and do not ourselves drag out our hopes
                    with these interruptions and delays. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I talk of
                    the loss of time and labour; what of the danger that we run by putting off the
                    war? Do -the frequent debates in Etruria about the dispatch of succours to Veii
                    allow us to forget it? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Just now they are angry
                    and resentful, and declare that they will send none; for all they care, we may
                    capture Veii. But who is to guarantee that if we postpone the campaign they will
                    hereafter feel the same: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> since if you
                    slacken, a greater and more numerous embassy will set out, <pb n="p.19"/> and
                    since what now offends the Etruscans —the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> setting up of a king at Veii
                    —may be altered with the lapse of time or by agreement of the citizens, to the
                    end that thereby they may regain the goodwill of Etruria; or with the consent of
                    the King himself, who would not wish his sovereignty to hurt the safety of his
                    people? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> See how many undesirable consequences
                    attend that line of policy: the loss of works constructed with such effort; the
                    imminent devastation of our fields; the Etruscans, instead of the Veientes only,
                    aroused to war with us. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It is thus, tribunes,
                    that you would manage matters, much as though in dealing with a sick man, who if
                    he would undergo a strict regimen might begin at once to recover, you should
                    protract his illness and perhaps render it incurable, by .indulging his
                    immediate desire for meat and drink. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "If it were of no moment to this war, it was
                    yet, I assure you, of the utmost importance for military discipline that our
                    soldiers become accustomed not only to pluck a victory within their grasp, but
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> if a campaign should be even more
                    protracted, to put up with the tedium and await the outcome of their hopes,
                    however long-deferred; and if a war be not finished in a summer, to stay for
                    winter, nor, like birds of passage, cast about at once, on the approach of
                    autumn, for shelter and covert. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Do the
                    eagerness, pray, and delight that men have in hunting carry them through snow
                    and frost into the mountains and the forests; and shall not we use in the stress
                    of war the same resolution which even sport and pleasure are wont to call out?
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Do we think the bodies of our soldiers so
                    effeminate, their hearts so faint, that they cannot endure to be one <pb
                        n="p.21"/> winter in camp, away from home; that like sailors <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note> they must
                    wage war with an eye on the weather, observing the seasons, incapable of
                    withstanding heat or cold? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They would
                    certainly blush if anyone should charge them with this, and would maintain that
                    manly endurance was in their souls and bodies, and that they could campaign as
                    well in winter as in summer; that they had given the tribunes no commission to
                    protect softness and idleness; and that they were mindful that their grandsires
                    had not founded the tribunician power in the shade or under roofs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "It is due to the valour of your soldiers, it
                    is due to the Roman name, that you should look not merely to Veii and this
                    present war that is upon us, but should seek for the years to come a reputation
                    that will serve you in other wars and amongst all other nations. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Do you suppose there will be no great difference in
                    men's opinion of us, whether our neighbours conclude the Roman People to be
                    such, that if a city withstand the brunt of their first assault for a very brief
                    time, it need thenceforward have no fears; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> or
                    whether our name inspire such dread, that men believe that once a Roman army has
                    sat down before a town, it will never budge, either from the weariness of a
                    protracted siege or from the rigours of winter, that it knows no other end of
                    war but victory, and relies in its campaigns not more on swiftness than on
                    perseverance? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For perseverance, needful in
                    every kind of warfare, is especially so in besieging cities, since
                    fortifications and natural advantages make most of them impregnable, and time
                    itself subdues them, with hunger and thirst, and captures them, as it <milestone
                        n="10??" unit="section"/> shall capture Veii, unless <pb n="p.23"/> the
                    plebeian tribunes help our enemies, and the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 403</note> Veientes find in Rome those
                    succours which they are seeking to no purpose in Etruria. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Could anything happen which would so please the Veientes as that
                        factions should spring up, first in the City of Rome, and then, as though by
                        contagion, in the camp? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But our enemies,
                        by Heaven, are so well disciplined that no weariness of the blockade nor
                        even of kingly rule has occasioned the smallest revolt among them; neither
                        has the Etruscans' denial of help provoked their spirit; for whosoever
                        prompts sedition shall forthwith die the death; <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> nor shall any man there have licence to say what is
                        said with impunity to you. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Death by
                        cudgelling is the wage of him who forsakes the standards or quits his post;
                        but those who advise the men to abandon their standards and desert the camp
                        gain a hearing, not with one or two soldiers, but with whole armies, openly,
                        in public meetings; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> so accustomed are you
                        to hear with complacency whatever a tribune says, even if it tends to betray
                        the City and to undo the state; and captivated by the charm of that
                        authority, you suffer any wickedness whatsoever to lurk beneath it.
                            <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It only remains for them to utter in
                        camp and in the presence of the soldiers the view which they noisily publish
                        here, and to corrupt the armies and not to suffer them to obey their
                        leaders. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> For in the upshot liberty has
                        come to mean at Rome, that a man respect neither senate nor magistrates, nor
                        laws, nor ancestral customs, nor institutions of the fathers, nor military
                        discipline. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Appius was already holding his own with the
                    tribunes of the plebs, even in public meetings, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy implies that the speech which he has reported
                        above was delivered in the Senate. </note> when a sudden disaster, from a
                    source which could <pb n="p.25"/> least have been anticipated, befell the army
                    before <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 403</note>
                    Veii, giving Appius the advantage in the argument, while it increased the mutual
                    good-will of the orders and their ardour for a more vigorous prosecution of the
                    siege. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For when they had pushed forward the
                    terrace towards the town, and had all but brought the mantlets into contact with
                    the walls, —more intent upon erecting their works by day than on guarding them
                    by night, —the <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> gate was suddenly flung open,
                    and a vast horde, most of them armed with torches, hurled fire on the works, and
                    in an hour's time terrace and mantlets, that had taken so long to make, were
                    consumed in the flames; and many men perished by the sword or the fire, in vain
                    efforts to save them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the news of this
                    came to Rome, it filled the City with sadness, the senate with anxiety and
                    apprehension, lest they might now indeed be unable to check the disaffection,
                    either in the City or the camp, and the tribunes might crow over the
                    commonwealth as though they had overthrown it; when lo! <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> those who were of equestrian rating, but had not received
                    horses from the state, having first taken counsel together, came to the senate,
                    and being granted a hearing, volunteered to serve on their own horses.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These men had no sooner received a vote of
                    thanks from the senate, in the most honourable terms, and the report of it had
                    spread to the Forum and the City, than the plebeians suddenly ran together to
                    the Curia, and: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> declared that it was now the
                    turn of the foot-soldiers to proffer extraordinary service to the state, whether
                    it would have them march to Veii, or anywhere else; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> if they should be led to Veii, they promised that they
                    would not quit their ground <pb n="p.27"/> until they had taken the enemy's
                    city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 403</note> indeed the senate could
                    scarce control its already overflowing joy; for they did not, as with the
                    knights, issue an order to the magistrates to thank them, nor did they call them
                    into the Curia to receive an answer, neither did the senate keep within the
                    House; but each for himself cried out from above, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> from the steps that led down to the Comitium.
                    </note> to the multitude standing in the Comitium, and by speech and gesture
                    signified the general joy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Rome was blest,
                    they said, and invincible and eternal, by reason of this noble harmony; they
                    praised the knights, they praised the plebeians, they extolled the very day
                    itself, and confessed that the courtesy and good-will of the senate had been
                    surpassed. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Fathers and commoners mingled
                    their tears of joy, till the Fathers were recalled into the senate-house, and
                        <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> decreed that the military tribunes
                    should hold an assembly and thank the infantry and the knights, and say to them
                    that the senate would remember their loyalty to their country, and that it was
                    voted that all who had volunteered to serve out of their due order should
                    receive pay. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The knights, too, were granted a
                    definite money allowance. Then for the first time cavalry-men began to serve on
                    their own horses. The volunteer army, having marched to Veii, not only replaced
                    the works that had been lost, but added new ones. The city dispatched provisions
                    with more than its former zeal, that nothing might be lacking to an army that
                    had deserved so well. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The ensuing year had for consular tribunes
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 402</note> Gaius
                    Servilius Ahala (for the third time), Quintus Servilius, Lucius Verginius,
                    Quintus Sulpicius, Aulus Manlius (for the second time), and Manius Sergius <pb
                        n="p.29"/> (for the second time). In their term of office, while <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 402</note> everyone was
                    intent on the war with Veii, the garrison at Anxur was neglected; <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> soldiers were given furlough, Volscian traders were
                    admitted without discrimination, and, the sentinels at the gates being suddenly
                    overpowered, the town was taken. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Not many
                    soldiers perished, because they were all, except the sick, occupied, like
                    sutlers, with trafficking in the country-side and the towns near by. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Nor were things any better at Veii, which was at that
                    time the nation's chief concern; for the Roman commanders showed more jealousy
                    of one another than spirit in dealing with the enemy, whose forces moreover were
                    enlarged by the unexpected accession of the Capenates and the Faliscans.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These two Etruscan peoples, being nearest
                    in situation, believed that if the Veientes were conquered it would be their
                    turn next to face a Roman invasion. The Faliscans, besides, had incurred
                    hostility on their own account, because they had been mixed up before in the war
                    with Fidenae. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See IV. xvii. 11.</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So they exchanged embassies, bound themselves
                    by an oath, and their armies suddenly appeared before Veii. It happened that
                    they attacked the camp at that point where the tribune Manius Sergius was in
                    command, and great was the terror they inspired, since the Romans thought that
                    all Etruria had risen and was come with a mighty array against them. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The same belief roused up the Veientes in the town.
                    Thus a two-fold attack was directed against the camp. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The soldiers rallied into groups, facing now this way and
                    now that, yet were unable either quite to confine the Veientes within the
                    siege-lines, or to ward off the attack upon their own defences and protect <pb
                        n="p.31"/> themselves from the enemy outside. Their only <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 402</note> hope was if
                    help should come from the larger camp, so that the legions might face different
                    ways, some of them confronting the Capenates and Faliscans, and others the
                    sortie of the townsfolk. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But that camp was
                    under the command of Verginius, who was privately hated by Sergius and returned
                    his enmity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This man, though word was brought
                    that many bastions had been stormed and the ramparts scaled, and that the enemy
                    were attacking on both sides, held his troops under arms, saying that if his
                    colleague needed help he would let him know. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    His pride found a match in the other's obstinacy, and Sergius, lest he should
                    seem to have required any aid of his rival, preferred defeat at the hands of the
                    enemy to victory gained through a fellow citizen. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> For a long time the Romans were slaughtered between the two
                    attacking armies; finally they abandoned their works, and a very few escaped
                    into the larger camp, while Sergius himself, with the chief part of his men,
                    kept on to Rome. It was there decided, on his throwing all the blame upon his
                    colleague, to summon Verginius from camp, and in the meanwhile put lieutenants
                    in command of it. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The affair was then debated
                    in the senate and the colleagues heaped abuse on one another. There were but few
                    who spoke for the commonwealth: most of them argued for one or the other
                    disputant, according as each was swayed by private interest or favour. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The leading senators held, that whether the:
                    fault or the misfortune of the commanders were the cause of this shameful
                    disaster, they ought not to await the regular time for elections, but proceed at
                    once to choose new military tribunes, to begin <pb n="p.33"/> their magistracy
                    on the first of October. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 402</note> members were
                    voting for this proposal, the other military tribunes raised no objection;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but of all people Sergius and Verginius,
                    the very men on account of whom it was evident that the senate was disgusted
                    with the magistrates of that year, first begged to be spared the humiliation,
                    then vetoed the senate's decree, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                            <hi rend="italics">senatus consultum</hi> was no more than a
                        'resolution' which the presiding magistrate might, if he chose, refuse to
                        carry out. </note> declaring that they would not resign their authority
                    before the thirteenth of December, the accustomed day for entering upon office.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Whereupon the tribunes of the plebs, who
                    so long as harmony prevailed and the affairs of the City prospered, had
                    reluctantly held their tongues, suddenly broke out and threatened the tribunes
                    of the soldiers, that unless they submitted to the senate they would send them
                    to prison. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Then Gaius Servilius Ahala, a
                    military tribune, said: <quote> So far as concerns you, tribunes of the commons,
                        and your menaces, I should indeed willingly put it to the proof how you have
                        in your threats as little legality as courage; but it is impious to oppose
                        the authority of the senate. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Accordingly
                        do you give over seeking in our quarrels occasion for working mischief, and
                        my colleagues shall either do as the senate decrees, or if they persist in
                        stubborn opposition, I will forthwith name a dictator, to compel them to lay
                        down their authority. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This speech was universally approved, and the
                    Fathers rejoiced that they needed not the trumpery threats of the tribunician
                    power, but had found another and a greater force to coerce the magistrates;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and the latter, overborne by the unanimity
                    of feeling, held an election of military tribunes, to begin service on October
                    the first, and before that date resigned their office. </p>
                <pb n="p.35"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consular tribuneship of Lucius Valerius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 401</note>
                    Potitus (for the fourth term), Marcus Furius Camillus (for the second <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Really the first term of Camillus. The
                        error here and in chap. i. § 2 (see note) is tacitly corrected in chap. xiv.
                        § 5. </note> ), Manius Aemilius Mamercus (for the third), Gnaeus Cornelius
                    Cossus (for the second), Caeso Fabius Ambustus, and Lucius Julius lulus, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Not the same man as mentioned in chap.
                        i. § 2.</note> was a time of great activity both at home and in the field.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For they made war at many points
                    simultaneously, before Veii, at Capena, at Falerii, and in the Volscian country
                    —to recover Anxur from the enemy; —and <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> in Rome
                    both the levy and the payment of the war-tax occasioned difficulties, a quarrel
                    sprang up over the co-optation of plebeian tribunes, and the trials: of the two
                    who had lately exercised consular powers aroused no small commotion. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The first concern of the military tribunes was to
                    levy troops, and they not only enrolled the younger men, but also compelled the
                    seniors to enlist for service in guarding the City. But the more they increased
                    the number of the soldiers, the more money they required for pay. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> This they tried to collect by taxation; but those who
                    remained at home contributed with reluctance, because they had also in defence
                    of the City to perform the labour of soldiers and serve the commonwealth.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To make this obligation, heavy in itself,
                    seem yet more grievous, the tribunes of the plebs delivered seditious speeches,
                    in which they alleged that the senators had established pay for the troops for
                    this reason, that they might ruin one half of the plebs with fighting and the
                    other half with taxation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They were now
                    drawing out a single war into its third year, and were purposely misconducting
                    it, that they might conduct it the longer. Again, with one levy they had
                    enrolled armies for four wars, and <pb n="p.37"/> had haled away even boys and
                    old men. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Now they <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 401</note> were confounding winter with
                    summer, to allow no rest ever to the unhappy commons, on whom finally they had
                    even imposed a tax; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that when they should drag
                    home their bodies spent with toil, with wounds, and at last with old age, and
                    should then find all things gone to waste in the long absence of the owners,
                    they might pay tribute out of their diminished property, and return to the state
                    many times, as it were with usury, the wages they had received as soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> What with the levy and the tax and the
                    weightier cares that preoccupied men's minds, they were unable on the day of
                    election to return the full number of plebeian tribunes. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> An effort was then made to obtain the co-optation of
                    patricians for the vacant places. When this failed, nevertheless, in order to
                    invalidate the law, it was brought about that Gaius Lacerius and Marcus Acutius
                    should be chosen tribunes, without doubt through patrician influence. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> From the beginning no patrician might
                        become a tribune of the plebs (II. xxxiii. 1) and in 448 the Trebonian law
                        forbade co-optation to that office (III. lxv. 4). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It so happened that in that year one of the
                    tribunes was Gnaeus Trebonius, whose name and family seemed to make it his duty
                    to defend the Trebonian law. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This man said
                    that what the Fathers had formerly aimed at (and had been foiled on their first
                    attempting), the tribunes of the soldiers had finally extorted; he asseverated
                    that the Trebonian law had been done away with, and that the tribunes of the
                    plebs had been appointed not by the votes of the people but at the dictation of
                    the nobles; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> that things had come to such a
                    pass, that they must perforce have either patricians or the satellites of
                    patricians for tribunes of the plebs; their sacred laws were being taken <pb
                        n="p.39"/> away, the tribunician power wrested from them. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 401</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This was done, he declared, by the knavery of
                    the patricians, the rascality and the treason of his colleagues. </p>
                <p> Men were burning with resentment, not only against the patricians, but also
                    against the tribunes of the plebs, both those who had been co-opted and those
                    who had co-opted them, when three of the college, Publius Curatius, Marcus
                    Metilius, and Marcus Minucius, being alarmed at their own situation, I fell
                    violently upon Sergius and Verginius, the military tribunes of the previous
                    year, and by appointing them a day for trial turned against them the anger and
                    displeasure which the plebs had evinced towards themselves. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> They reminded their hearers, that those who were aggrieved
                    by the levy, or the tax, or the protracted service and the long duration of the
                    war, those who sorrowed for the calamity that befell at Veii, those whose houses
                    were in mourning for the loss of sons, brothers, kinsmen or connexions, —that
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> all those now had the right and the power,
                    thanks to the speakers, of avenging the nation's grief and their own private
                    sorrow on the two culprits; for of all their sufferings Sergius and Verginius
                    were the cause; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and this their accusers were
                    not more forward to maintain than the defendants to confess, who, equally
                    guilty, threw the blame on one another, Verginius taxing Sergius with his
                    flight, while Sergius complained of Verginius's treachery. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Their madness had been so incredible, that it was much more
                    probable that they had done the thing upon agreement, with the collusion of the
                    senators; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> who having before given opportunity
                    to the Veientes to set fire to their works, in order to <pb n="p.41"/> prolong
                    the war, had now betrayed the army and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 401</note> delivered up a Roman camp to the Faliscans.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They were doing everything to wear out
                    the young men before Veii, and prevent the tribunes from bringing before the
                    people the question of land and other advantages to the plebs, and from pushing
                    their measures in well-attended assemblies and thwarting the conspiracy of the
                    patricians. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Judgment was already given
                    against the accused both by the senate and by the Roman People, and also by
                    their own college; for the senate had by its decree removed them from authority,
                    and when they refused to abdicate their office, their colleagues had coerced
                    them by threatening to appoint a dictator, and the Roman People had elected
                    tribunes to assume their duties, not on the thirteenth of December, the usual
                    date, but immediately, on October the first, believing that the state could
                    endure no longer if the incumbents should remain in place; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> yet, in spite of all, these men, stigmatized and
                    fore-judged by so many adverse verdicts, presented themselves for trial by the
                    people, and fancied that they were quit and sufficiently mulcted because they
                    were made private citizens two months before their time; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> not perceiving that they had then merely been deprived of
                    the power to do further mischief, not punished, since their colleagues, too,
                    were turned out of office, though they had certainly done no wrong. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Let the Quirites call back the spirit they had shown
                    when the recent calamity had occurred, when they had beheld the flight and
                    confusion of their troops, as they stumbled, wounded and dismayed, through the
                    City gates, accusing neither fortune nor any of the gods, but these their <pb
                        n="p.43"/> leaders. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> They were sure that
                    there was not a man <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        401</note> present in the assembly who had not on that day cursed and
                    execrated the lives, the houses, and the fortunes of Lucius Verginius and Manius
                    Sergius. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It was not reasonable that their
                    hearers, having a legal and moral right in the matter, should not use their
                    power against those upon whom each one of them had invoked the wrath of Heaven.
                    The gods themselves never laid hands upon the guilty; it was enough if they
                    armed with an opportunity for vengeance those who had been wronged. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Incited by these speeches, the plebs <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 400</note> condemned
                    the accused to pay each a fine of 10,000 pounds of bronze. It was in vain that
                    Sergius blamed Fortune and the common chance of war, while Verginius begged that
                    he might <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> not be more unlucky at home than he
                    had been in the campaign. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On them the wrath of
                    the people was poured out, and the co-optation of the tribunes and the evasion
                    of the Trebonian law were almost forgotten. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The victorious tribunes, that the plebs might
                    have an immediate reward for its judgment, proposed a land-law and forbade the
                    gathering of the war-tax, notwithstanding that pay was needed for so many
                    armies, whose campaigning, though successful, yet failed to realize the desired
                    end in any war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Thus, at Veii, they recovered
                    the lost camp and strengthened it with fortresses and garrisons, led by the
                    military tribunes Manius Aemilius and Caeso Fabius; Marcus Furius in the
                    Faliscan country, and Gnaeus Cornelius in the territory of Capena, meeting no
                    enemies afield, drove off booty, and burning farmhouses and crops, laid waste
                    the land, but the towns they neither assaulted nor besieged; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> in the Volscian <pb n="p.45"/> country, however, after
                    ravaging the fields, they <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B. c. 400</note> made a futile attack on Anxur, which was seated on an
                    eminence, and finding force to be unavailing, began to invest it with a stockade
                    and trench, under Valerius Potitus, who had got the command against the Volsci. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While military affairs were in this posture, a
                    quarrel that broke out at home aroused more energy than went to their making of
                    wars; and since the tax could not be taken up, on account of the tribunes, and
                    the generals were sent no money, while the soldiers were clamouring for their
                    pay, the camp, too, was like to have been disrupted by the contagion of mutiny
                    in the City. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the midst of this hostility
                    which the plebs felt towards the patricians, though the plebeian tribunes said
                    that the time was now come to establish liberty, and to transfer the highest
                    office from such as Sergius and Verginius to <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                    stout and courageous commoners, yet they got no further than the election of one
                    plebeian (by way of asserting their right), namely, Publius Licinius Calvus, to
                    be military tribune with consular powers; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the
                    others chosen were patricians: Publius Manlius, Lucius Titinius, Publius
                    Maelius, Lucius Furius Medullinus, Lucius Publilius Volscus. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The plebeians themselves were amazed that they had gained
                    so important a point, and not alone the man who had been chosen, one that had
                    held no offices before, but was only a senator of long standing, now well on in
                    years. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> There is no unanimity of opinion why
                    he was selected as the first and fittest to taste of the new honours. Some think
                    it was the favour of his cousin <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Or,
                        perhaps, step-brother.</note> Gnaeus Cornelius, who as tribune of the
                    soldiers the year before had granted triple pay <pb n="p.47"/> to the
                    cavalrymen, ' that got him his promotion to so <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 399</note> great an office; others,
                    that he himself made a timely speech on the harmony of the orders, which pleased
                    both patricians and plebeians. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Overjoyed at
                    their victory in this election, the tribunes of the plebs withdrew that
                    opposition to the tax which was the greatest obstacle to the business of the
                    state, and it was obediently paid in and dispatched to the army. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Anxur of the Volsci was speedily recaptured, a
                    holiday having relaxed the vigilance of their guard. This year was remarkable
                    for so cold and snowy a winter, that the roads were blocked and the Tiber became
                    unnavigable. The price of corn, owing to the supply which they had brought in
                    before, did not go up. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Publius Licinius had
                    obtained his magistracy without any disorders, rejoicing the commons more than
                    he offended the patricians, and in the same spirit he conducted it; the people
                    therefore became desirous of returning plebeians at the next election of
                    consular tribunes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Marcus Veturius was the
                    sole patrician candidate to get in; all the other military tribunes with
                    consular authority were commoners, as the result of an all but unanimous vote of
                    the centuries. Their names were Marcus Pomponius, Gnaeus Duillius, Volero
                    Publilius, Gnaeus Genucius, Lucius Atilius </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The severe winter was succeeded, whether in
                    consequence of the sudden change from such inclement weather to the opposite
                    extreme, or for some other reason, by a summer that was noxious and baleful to
                    all living creatures. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Unable to discover what
                    caused the incurable ravages of this distemper, or would put an end to them, the
                    senate voted to consult the Sibylline Books. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The duumvirs <pb n="p.49"/> in charge of the sacred rites then celebrated the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 399</note> first
                    lectisternium <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> From <hi rend="italics"
                            >lectus,</hi>
                        <quote>couch</quote> and <hi rend="italics">sternere,</hi>
                        <quote>to spread.</quote> The images of the gods were placed on banqueting
                        couches and served with food. </note> ever held in Rome, and for the space
                    of eight days sacrificed to Apollo, to Latona and Diana, to Hercules, to Mercury
                    and to Neptune, spreading three couches for them with all the splendour then
                    attainable. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They also observed the rite in
                    their homes. All through the City, they say, doors stood wide open, all kinds of
                    viands were set out for general consumption, all comers were welcomed, whether
                    known or not, and men even exchanged kind and courteous words with personal
                    enemies; there was a truce to quarrelling and litigation; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> even prisoners were loosed from their chains for those
                    days, and they scrupled thenceforth to imprison men whom the gods had thus
                    befriended. </p>
                <p> Meantime alarms were multiplied at Veii, where three wars were rolled into one.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For, precisely as before, the Capenates
                    and the Faliscans came suddenly to raise the siege, and the Romans fought about
                    their works against three armies, which attacked them on both sides. What helped
                    them most, was the recollection how Sergius and Verginius had been condemned.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And so from the principal camp, where the
                    delay had occurred on the former occasion, troops were dispatched by a short
                    circuit and fell upon the Capenates in the rear, as they faced the rampart of
                    the Romans. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Beginning there, the battle
                    carried terror even among the Faliscans, who were wavering, when a timely sally
                    from the camp put them to flight. Then, as they retreated, the victors pursued
                    them with great slaughter; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and not long after
                    a party that was raiding the territory of the Capenates happened to fall in with
                    them and destroyed such as had survived the battle. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Of the <pb n="p.51"/> Veientes likewise, many, as they fled
                    back to the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        399</note> town, were slain before the gates, when their friends, fearing
                    lest the Romans should burst in along with them, had closed the portals, and
                    barred out the hindmost of their own people. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the events of this year. And <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 398</note> now the time
                    drew near for choosing military tribunes and the Fathers were almost more
                    concerned about the election than about the war, perceiving that the highest
                    authority had been not merely shared with the plebs, but well-nigh lost to
                    themselves. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They therefore arranged that their
                    most distinguished members should stand, —men whom they believed the electors
                    would be ashamed to pass over, —and at the same time they themselves, as if they
                    had all been candidates, left no stone unturned, and called to their aid not
                    only men, but the gods as well, by raising a religious scruple anent the
                    election held two -years before. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the year
                    before the last, they said, there had been an intolerable winter, like a warning
                    from Heaven. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Last year had come not prodigies
                    but actual realities: a pestilence had descended upon the fields and the City,
                    clearly proceeding from the anger of the gods, whom they must propitiate in
                    order to avert the plague, as the fateful Books had indicated; it had seemed to
                    the gods an affront that an election held under their auspices should prostitute
                    honours and confound family distinctions. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    people were awed not only by the dignity of the candidates, but by the fear of
                    Heaven, and to be military tribunes with consular powers chose all patricians,
                    and chiefly the most illustrious among them, as follows: <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Lucius Valerius Potitus (for the fifth time), Marcus
                    Valerius Maximus, Marcus Furius Camillus (for the second <pb n="p.53"/> time),
                    Lucius Furius Medullinus (for the third), Q. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 398</note> Servilius Fidenas (for the
                    second), Quintus Sulpicius Camerinus (for the second). These tribunes achieved
                    absolutely nothing noteworthy at Veii, but employed all their strength in
                    pillaging. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The two chief commanders, Potitus
                    and Camillus, —one at Falerii, the other at Capena, —carried off huge spoils and
                    left nothing untouched that iron or fire could destroy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile many portents were reported, most of
                    which, because they had only one witness each to vouch for them, obtained no
                    credence and were slighted; and, besides, when the Etruscans, whose services
                    they employed to avert evil omens, were at war with them, they had no
                    soothsayers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> One thing occasioned universal
                    anxiety, namely that the lake in the Alban Wood, without any rains or other
                    cause to make it less than a miracle, rose to an unwonted height. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> To inquire what the gods could possibly foretell by
                    that prodigy, envoys were sent to the Delphic oracle. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But a nearer interpreter of the fates presented himself, an
                    old man of Veii, who, while the Roman and Etruscan soldiers were scoffing at one
                    another as they stood guard at the outposts, declared in a prophetic strain that
                    until the water should be drawn off from the Alban Lake the Romans never could
                    take Veii. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At first they made light of this as
                    an idle taunt; then they began to talk it over; presently one of the Roman
                    outpost inquired of the townsman nearest him (for owing to the long continuance
                    of the war they had now got into the way of conversing together) who that man
                    was who threw out mysterious hints regarding the Alban Lake. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When he heard that he was a soothsayer, being himself not
                    without a touch of <pb n="p.55"/> superstition, he alleged a desire to consult
                    him <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 398</note> about
                    the averting of a domestic portent, if he could spare the time, and so enticed
                    the seer to a conference. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And when they had
                    walked a little way apart from the friends of both, unarmed and fearing nothing,
                    the stalwart young Roman laid hold of the feeble old man in the sight of them
                    all, and despite an unavailing hubbub raised by the Etruscans, bore him off to
                    his own fellows. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There they had him before the
                    general, who sent him on to Rome, to the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> When the Fathers questioned him what it was he had meant about the Alban
                    Lake, he answered that the gods must surely have been incensed at the people of
                    Veii on the day when they put it into his: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    mind to reveal the destruction destined to befall his native city; and so what
                    he had then uttered under divine inspiration, he could not now unsay and recall;
                    and perhaps in concealing what the immortal gods wished to be published guilt
                    was incurred no less than by disclosing what should be hid. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Thus then it was written in the books of fate, thus handed
                    down in the lore of the Etruscans, that when the Alban water should overflow, if
                    then the Romans should duly draw it off, they would be given the victory over
                    the Veientes; until that should come, to pass, the gods would not abandon the
                    walls of Veii. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He then went on to explain the
                    appointed method of draining it. But the senators, making slight account of his
                    authority, as not sufficiently trustworthy in so grave a matter, determined to
                    wait for their deputies with the response of the Pythian oracle. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A tunnel to drain the flood-waters of
                        the Alban Lake, 1300 yards long and from seven to ten feet high, was
                        actually cut through the solid rock, not to bring about the capture of Veil,
                        but to save a few hundred acres of arable land on the sloping edge within
                        the crater (Tenney Frank, <hi rend="italics">Economic</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">History of Rome,</hi> p. 7). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But before these envoys could return from
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 397</note> Delphi
                    or an expiation be devised for the Alban <pb n="p.57"/> portent, new military
                    tribunes with consular authority <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 397</note> came in; these were Lucius Julius lulus, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the second time ( <hi
                            rend="italics">cf.</hi> chap. x. § 1). </note> Lucius Furius Medullinus
                    (for the fourth time), Lucius Sergius Fidenas, Aulus Postumius Regillensis,
                    Publius Cornelius Maluginensis, and Aulus Manlius. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For the third time ( <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> chap.
                        viii. § 1). </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In that year a new enemy arose in the
                    Tarquinienses, who seeing the Romans beset with many wars at once, —against the
                    Volsci, who were laying siege to the garrison at Anxur, against the Aequi, who
                    were attacking the Roman colony at Labici, and also against the men of Veii, of
                    Falerii, and of Capena, — and perceiving that affairs within the City were no
                    less troubled, owing to contentions betwixt the patricians and the plebs,
                    believed that in these circumstances they had an opportunity to do the Romans a
                    hurt, and sent out light-armed detachments to raid their territory; <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> for they thought that either the Romans would put up
                    with the wrong, to avoid the burden of another war, or would take the field with
                    a small and therefore inadequate army. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    indignation of the Romans was greater than their concern for the damage wrought
                    by the Tarquinienses; so they neither made strenuous efforts to prepare, nor
                    deferred taking action to a distant date. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Aulus Postumius and Lucius Iulus, without holding a regular levy —for this the
                    plebeian tribunes hindered —but with a company consisting almost solely of
                    volunteers whom they had induced to join by their exhortations, marched out by
                    cross-country ways through the territory of Caere, and surprised the
                    Tarquinienses as they were returning from their depradations laden with booty.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Many men they slew, all they stripped of
                    their baggage; and having recovered the spoils of their own fields, <pb n="p.59"
                    /> returned to Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two days were allowed the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 397</note> owners
                    to identify their property; on the third all that had not been recognized
                    —chiefly things belonging to the enemy themselves —was sold under the spear
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> at public auction, the spear being set up to
                        advertise such a sale. </note> and the proceeds divided amongst the
                    soldiers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The other campaigns, especially the one at
                    Veii, were indecisive. And now the Romans, despairing of human aid, were looking
                    to destiny and the gods, when the deputies returned from Delphi, bringing the
                    oracle's response, which corresponded with the utterance of the captive seer:
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Roman, see that thou suffer not the Alban water to be confined within
                        the lake, nor to fret its own channel to the sea; thou shalt draw it forth
                        and water the fields withal, and spread it abroad till it be lost in
                        rivulets; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> after that press boldly on
                        against the walls of the foe, and know that over that city which thou dost
                        beleaguer for so many years, the fates now disclosed have given thee the
                        victory. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When thou hast ended the war
                        with conquest, bring to my temple an ample gift, and repeat and accomplish
                        in customary wise the ancestral rites thou hast neglected. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The captive soothsayer began from that moment
                    to be held in great repute, and the military tribunes, Cornelius and Postumius,
                    set out to employ him about the expiation of the Alban prodigy and the due
                    appeasement of the gods. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At length it was
                    discovered wherein the gods taxed them with neglecting ceremonies or omitting a
                    festival: it was assuredly nothing else than that magistrates in whose election
                    there had been a flaw had improperly proclaimed the Latin games <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> and the sacrifice on the <pb n="p.61"/> Alban Mount
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Latin Festival (in honour of
                        Jupiter Latiaris, who presided over the Latin League) was held each year,
                        and was followed by a sacrifice, on the date proclaimed by the new consuls,
                        or consular tribunes. </note> ; only one atonement for these errors <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.397</note> was open to
                    them, to make the tribunes of the soldiers resign their office, to take the
                    auspices afresh, and to begin an interregnum. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    By decree of the senate these things were done. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> There were three successive interreges, Lucius Valerius, Quintus Servilius
                    Fidenas, Marcus Furius Camillus, In the meantime there were continuous
                    disturbances, and the plebeian tribunes blocked the election, until it had first
                    been agreed that the majority of the military tribunes should be chosen out of
                    the commons. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> While this was going on, the Etruscans met in
                    council at the Fane of Voltumna; where the Capenates and Faliscans proposed that
                    all the nations of Etruria should unite in a common resolution 'and design to
                    raise the siege of Veii. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The council made
                    answer that they had before refused the Veientes this request, on the ground
                    that they had no right to ask help from those whom they had not cared to look to
                    for advice in so weighty a matter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Just then,
                    however, the plight of their country itself denied the petition. There was now
                    in the greatest part of Etruria a strange race, new settlers, with whom they
                    were neither securely at peace nor yet certain to have war. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Nevertheless, out of regard for the blood and the name and
                    the present perils of their kinsmen, they would grant that if any of their young
                    men wished to serve in that war, they might do so without let or hindrance.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Of such recruits it was said at Rome that
                    a great number had come in; and so domestic differences began to subside, as
                    generally happens, in the face of a common danger. </p>
                <pb n="p.63"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It occasioned the Fathers no displeasure <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> when the
                    prerogative centuries <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi
                            rend="italics">praerogatives</hi> were the eighteen centuries of
                        knights, which voted first; if they agreed, the other centuries were not
                        called. See I. xliii. 11. </note> chose Publius Licinius Calvus tribune of
                    the soldiers, without his seeking office; he was a man whose moderation had been
                    proven in his former term, but was now become superannuated. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> It was clear that all who had been his colleagues in that
                    same year would also be returned, one after the other, to wit: Lucius Titinius,
                    Publius Maenius, Gnaeus Genucius, Lucius Atilius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> But before they were declared to the duly assembled tribes,
                    Licinius spoke as follows, having obtained permission of the interrex: <quote>
                        It is an omen of harmony, as I perceive, Quirites, a thing most needful at
                        this juncture, that you seek for the ensuing year, when in your voting you
                        remember our former magistracy; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but
                        whereas in my colleagues you are choosing again the same men, and all the
                        better for experience, in me you see no longer the same Publius Licinius, of
                        whom but the shadow and the name are left. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        My strength of body is decayed, my sight and hearing dulled, memory fails
                        me, and the vigour of my mind is impaired. Here, </quote> he cried, laying
                    hold of his son, <quote> here is a young man, the effigy and likeness of him you
                        formerly chose for military tribune first of all plebeians. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Him have I bred up in my own principles, and in my
                        stead I give and dedicate him to the state, and I pray you, Quirites, who
                        without my seeking have offered me the office, that you grant it to him, who
                        seeks it, and to the prayers I have added in his behalf. </quote> The father
                    was granted his request, and the son, Publius Licinius, was declared military
                    tribune with consular powers, together with those I have named above. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Titinius and Genucius, tribunes of the soldiers, <pb
                        n="p.65"/> having marched against the Faliscans and Capenates, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> brought more
                    spirit than generalship to their conduct of the war, and plunged into an ambush.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Genucius, atoning for his rashness by an
                    honourable death, fell fighting among the foremost, in front of the standards;
                    Titinius rallied his men, who had been thrown into great confusion, on a little
                    eminence, and made a stand, yet he would not risk an engagement on level ground.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The disgrace outweighed the defeat, which
                    had almost proved disastrous, so great was the panic which it caused, not only
                    in Rome, where a greatly exaggerated report of the affair had been received, but
                    also in the camp before Veii. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There the
                    soldiers could hardly be restrained from flight, for a rumour had run through
                    the camp that the victorious Capenates and Faliscans, having slaughtered the
                    Roman commanders and their army, were close at hand, with all the manhood of
                    Etruria. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accounts even more alarming had been
                    credited at Rome: that the camp at Veii was already under attack; that already a
                    division of the enemy was marching to assail the City. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> There was a rush to the walls, and the women, drawn from
                    their houses by the general consternation, betook themselves to prayer in the
                    temples, and besought the gods to ward off destruction from the houses and
                    shrines of the City and from the walls of Rome, and to turn that panic against
                    Veii, if the sacred rites had been duly renewed and the portents expiated. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> And now the games and the Latin Festival had
                    been repeated, now the water had been let out from the Alban Lake upon the
                    fields, and the doom of Veii drew on apace. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly the commander destined to destroy that city and to save his country,
                        <pb n="p.67"/> Marcus Furius Camillus, was appointed dictator, and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> named
                    Publius Cornelius Scipio as his master of the horse. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The change in the command at once made a change in all
                    things else; there was new hope and a new spirit, and even the fortune of the
                    City seemed to be renewed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The dictator's
                    first act was to visit military punishment upon those who had fled from Veil in
                    the panic there, and to teach his men that the enemy was not the worst thing
                    they had to fear. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then fixed the levy for a
                    certain day, and in the interval hastened to Veii to encourage his soldiers;
                    thence he returned to Rome to enroll the new army, and found no one who refused
                    to serve. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Even foreign troops, Latins and
                    Hernicans, came with promises to help in this war, and the dictator thanked them
                    in the senate. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy's brevity here
                        makes the sentence a little obscure. No doubt the Latins and Hernicans first
                        sent envoys, and these were introduced into the senate and there thanked by
                        the dictator. </note> All things being now in readiness for the campaign,
                    Camillus vowed, in pursuance of a senatorial decree, to celebrate the great
                    games, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> votive games in recognition of some special
                        favour of the gods. </note> if he should capture Veii, and to restore and
                    dedicate anew the temple of Mater Matuta, which in time gone by had been
                    consecrated by King Servius Tullius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Marching
                    out from the City, where he left a greater feeling of suspense than of
                    confidence, he first engaged the Faliscans and Capenates, in the Nepesine
                    country. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There all his measures, being
                    executed with consummate skill and prudence, were attended, as generally
                    happens, with good fortune. Not only did he rout the enemy in battle, but he
                    also deprived them of their camp and got possession of enormous booty, the chief
                    part of which was made over to the quaestor, and no great quantity given to the
                    soldiers. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then led his army to Veii, where
                    he increased the number of redoubts, and withdrawing the troops from the <pb
                        n="p.69"/> skirmishes which frequently took place, on the spur <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 398</note> of the
                    moment, in the space between the town wall and the stockade, by an edict
                    forbidding <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> any man to fight without orders,
                    he employed them in digging. Of all the works, much the greatest and most
                    laborious was a mine they began to drive into the enemy's citadel. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> That this work might not be interrupted nor the same
                    men become exhausted by perpetually toiling under ground, he divided the workers
                    into six parties and assigned them six-hour shifts in rotation; night and day
                    the work went on unceasingly, till they had made a way into the citadel. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator saw that victory was at last
                    within his grasp, and that a city of great wealth was on the point of being
                    taken, with booty more than if all previous wars had been put together.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Lest, therefore, he might incur either the
                    resentment of the soldiers, in consequence of a niggardly division of the
                    spoils, or the ill-will of the Fathers, if he were lavish in sharing them out,
                    he wrote to the senate, that thanks to the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    favour of the immortal gods, his own direction, and the patient efforts of his
                    troops, Veii would presently be in the power of the Roman People, and asked what
                    disposition they proposed making of the plunder. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> The senate was divided between two opinions; the aged Publius Licinius, who
                    was the first, they say, that his son called upon to speak, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy is perhaps following Licinius
                        Macer (Introd. Vol. I, p. xxix), in recording the very irregular procedure
                        by which the tribune passed over the patrician senators to honour his
                        plebeian father. </note> advised making public proclamation that the people
                    decreed that whoso desired a share in the spoils should proceed to the camp at
                    Veii; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> the other plan was that of Appius
                    Claudius, who declared that such largess was without example, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The booty was regularly sold and the
                        proceeds placed in the treasury. </note> reckless, unfair, and ill-advised;
                    if they were <pb n="p.71"/> persuaded once for all that it was wicked that money
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note>
                    captured from the enemy should lie in the treasury, which had been exhausted by
                    the wars, he urged them to pay the soldiers out of it, that <milestone n="6??"
                        unit="section"/> the plebs might have so much the less war-tax to contribute
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The patricians also paid the tax;
                        but it bore harder upon the plebeians, owing to their poverty. </note> ;
                    this was a boon of which all families alike would feel the benefit, nor would
                    the hands of idle city-folk, greedy of pillage, pluck away the rewards of
                    valiant fighting men —since it commonly turned out that in proportion as a man
                    was prone to seek a leading share of toil and danger, he was slow in plundering.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Licinius argued, on the other hand, that
                    this money would breed endless suspicion and hate, and would furnish grounds for
                    accusations before the plebs, and so for agitation and revolutionary laws;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> it was better, therefore, to win over by
                    this gift the sympathies of the commons, to succour them, exhausted and
                    impoverished as they were by so' many years' taxation, and to let them enjoy the
                    spoils and fruits of that war in which they had well-nigh grown old men; there
                    would in every instance be more satisfaction and pleasure in what a man took
                    with his own hand from the enemy and brought home, than if he received many
                    times its value at the discretion of another; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    the dictator himself would fain avoid the enmity and charges arising from this
                    business, and therefore had handed it over to the senate; the senate, likewise,
                    in its turn, should refer the question to the plebs, and let every man keep what
                    the fortune of war might give him. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This
                    policy seemed the safer, since it would make the senate popular. Accordingly,
                    proclamation was made that all who liked might go to the dictator in camp, to
                    share in the plunder of Veii. </p>
                <pb n="p.73"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A vast throng went out, and filled the camp.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> Then
                    the dictator, after taking the auspices, came forth and commanded the troops to
                    arm. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Under thy leadership,</quote> he cried, <quote> Pythian Apollo, and
                        inspired by thy will, I advance to destroy the city of Veii, and to thee I
                        promise a tithe of its spoils. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the same
                        time I beseech thee, Queen Juno, that dwellest now in Veii, to come with us,
                        when we have gotten the victory, to our City —soon to be thine, too —that a
                        temple meet for thy majesty may there receive thee. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These prayers uttered, he set forward with
                    overwhelming numbers to assault the town on every side, that the inhabitants
                    might not perceive the danger pressing upon them from the mine. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The Veientes, unconscious that they were already given up
                    by their own soothsayers, and by foreign oracles, that some of the gods had
                    already been invited to share in their despoiling, while others having been
                    entreated to quit their city were beginning to look to new homes in the temples
                    of their enemies, and that this was the <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> last
                    day they were themselves to live, feared nothing less than that their defences
                    were undermined and their citadel already filled with foemen, and, each for
                    himself, took up arms and ran out to the ramparts; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> marvelling what it meant that whereas for so many days not
                    a Roman had stirred from his post, they should now, as though they had suddenly
                    gone mad, be rushing blindly against the walls. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At this point men introduce a tale, how, as
                    the King of the Veientes was sacrificing, the Roman soldiers in the mine
                    overheard the soothsayer declare that to him who should cut up <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Latin word is a technical term
                        which is used of carving up, in a specified way, the entrails ( <hi
                            rend="italics">prosiciae</hi> ) which were to be burnt on the altar.
                    </note> the inwards of that victim would be given the victory, and were <pb
                        n="p.75"/> moved to open the mine and seize the entrails, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> which they
                    bore off to the dictator. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But in matters of so
                    great antiquity I should be content if things probable were to be received as
                    true: this story, more fit to be displayed on the stage, that delights in
                    wonders, than to be believed, it is worth while neither to affirm nor to refute.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">With this sentence compare Livy's
                        Preface, § 6.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The mine, which was then filled with picked
                    troops, suddenly discharged its armed men into the temple of Juno, on the
                    Veientine citadel; some of them assailed the backs of their enemies, who were on
                    the walls; others wrenched off the bars that made fast the gates; others, when
                    the women and slaves cast down stones and tiles from roofs, fetched fire against
                    them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The air resounded with shouts;
                    discordant threats of the attackers and despairing shrieks of the defenders were
                    blended with the wailing of women and children. <milestone n="12" unit="section"
                    /> In a moment the armed soldiers were everywhere hurled from the walls, and the
                    gates thrown open. A part of the Romans poured through them in a body, others
                    scaled the deserted walls; the city was overrun with enemies; the battle raged
                    in every quarter; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> then, when there had
                    already been great carnage, the fighting began to flag, and the dictator bade
                    the heralds proclaim that those without arms should be spared. This ended the
                    slaughter. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The unarmed began to give
                    themselves up, and the Romans scattered, with the dictator's permission, in
                    quest of booty. When this was brought before him, and he saw that it was
                    considerably larger and comprised effects of greater value than he had hoped or
                    thought, it is said that he raised his <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/>
                    hands to heaven and prayed that if any god or man deemed his good fortune and
                    that of the Roman People to be excessive, it might be granted <pb n="p.77"/> him
                    to appease that envy with the least harm to his <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> own private interests and to
                    the public welfare of the Roman People. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> As he
                    turned, while making this prayer, tradition states that he slipped and fell, and
                    that this omen was seen (when men came later to gather its meaning from the
                    event) to point to the condemnation of Camillus himself, and in the second
                    place, to the capture of Rome, a disaster which befell a few years afterwards.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> So that day was spent in the slaughter of
                    enemies and the sack of a most opulent city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following day the dictator sold the
                    free-born inhabitants into slavery. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Literally, <quote>under the chaplet,</quote> alluding to the garlands worn
                        by captives when they were put up for sale (Aulus Gellius, VI. iv.). </note>
                    This was the only money that went into the state treasury, but the commons were
                    angry about it; as for the booty they brought back themselves, they gave the
                    credit not to their commander, who had referred to the Fathers, that they might
                    support his niggardliness, a matter which had lain <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> within his own discretion, nor yet to the senators, but- to
                    the house of the Licinii, whose son had brought to a vote in the senate that
                    popular measure which his father had proposed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When the wealth that belonged to men had now been carried away out of Veii, they
                    began to remove the possessions of the gods and the gods themselves, but more in
                    the manner of worshippers than of pillagers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For out of all the army youths were chosen, and made to cleanse their bodies and
                    to put on white garments, and to them the duty was assigned of conveying Queen
                    Juno to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Reverently entering her temple,
                    they scrupled at first to approach her with their hands, because this image was
                    one that according to Etruscan practice none but a priest of a certain family
                    was wont to <pb n="p.79"/> touch; when one of them, whether divinely inspired
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> or out
                    of youthful jocularity, asked, <quote>Wilt thou go, Juno, to Rome?</quote>
                    —whereat the others all cried out that the goddess had nodded assent. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> It was afterwards added to the story that she had
                    also been heard to say that she was willing. At all events we are told that she
                    was moved from her place with contrivances of little power, as though she
                    accompanied them voluntarily, and <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> was
                    lightly and easily transferred and carried safe and sound to the Aventine, the
                    eternal home to which the prayers of the Roman dictator had called her; and
                    there Camillus afterwards dedicated to her the temple which he himself had
                    vowed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Such was the fall of Veii, the wealthiest city
                    of the Etruscan race, which gave evidence of its greatness even in its final
                    overthrow; since after a blockade of ten continuous summers and winters, during
                    which time it had inflicted considerably heavier losses than it had sustained,
                    it yet was ultimately taken, when at last even destiny fought against it, by
                    siege-works and not by force. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When word came to Rome that Veii was taken,
                    although the portents had been averted and the answers of the soothsayers and
                    the Pythian oracle were known; and though they had done all that human wisdom
                    could do to help, in choosing Marcus Furius Camillus, greatest of all generals,
                    to lead them; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> nevertheless, because they had
                    warred there so many years with varying fortune and had suffered many a reverse,
                    their joy, as though unexpected, knew no bounds; and ere the senate could act,
                    the temples were all thronged with Roman matrons giving thanks to the gods.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The <pb n="p.81"/> senate decreed
                    supplications for four days, a longer <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 396</note> period than in any former war. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Moreover, as the dictator drew near, all sorts and
                    conditions of men ran forth to meet him in such numbers as had never welcomed a
                    general before, and the triumph far exceeded the measure of honour usual on that
                    day. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He was himself the most conspicuous
                    object in it, as he rode into the City on a chariot drawn by white horses; an
                    act which struck men as being not only undemocratic, but irreverent, for they
                    were troubled at the thought that in respect to his steeds the dictator was made
                    equal to Jupiter and the sun-god; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> and the
                    triumph, chiefly for this one reason, was more brilliant than popular. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy is probably mistaken in ascribing
                        the unpopularity of the triumph to the supposed presumption of Camillus,
                        since it was traditional for the triumphator to suggest a likeness to
                        Jupiter, both in his chariot and in his costume. Resentment over the
                        disposal of the booty is more likely to have been the reason. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He then let the contract for the temple of
                    Queen Juno on the Aventine, and dedicated one to Mater Matuta; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">This temple was in the cattle-market,
                        the Forum Boarium.</note> and having fulfilled these obligations to gods and
                    men, laid down the dictatorship. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The next thing to be discussed was the gift to
                    Apollo, to whom Camillus said that he had solemnly promised a tenth part of the
                    spoils. The pontiffs ruled that the people must discharge this obligation, but
                    it was not easy to devise a method <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> for
                    compelling them to return the booty, that out of it the due proportion might be
                    set apart for the sacred object. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They finally
                    resorted to what seemed the least oppressive plan, namely, that whosoever wished
                    to acquit himself and his household of obligation on the score of the vow,
                    should appraise his own share of the spoils, and pay in a tenth part of its
                    value to the public treasury, to the <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> end
                    that it might be converted into an offering of gold befitting the grandeur of
                    the temple and the power of the god and corresponding to the majesty of the
                    Roman <pb n="p.83"/> People. This contribution still further alienated <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> the
                    affections of the commons from Camillus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See chap. xxii. § 1 and chap. xxiii. § 5.</note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> In the midst of these affairs came envoys
                    from the Volsci and the Aequi seeking peace, and their suit was granted, more
                    that the state, worn out with so long a war, might be at rest, than because the
                    petitioners deserved it. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year which followed the capture of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 395</note> Veii had six
                    consular tribunes, to wit, the two Publii Cornelii, Cossus and Scipio, Marcus
                    Valerius Maximus (for the second time), Caeso Fabius Ambustus (for the third),
                    Lucius Furius Medullinus (for the fifth), Quintus Servilius (for the third). To
                    the Cornelii was allotted the Faliscan war, to Valerius and Servilius the war
                    with Capena. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They attempted no cities, either
                    by assault or by siege, but wasted the countryside and despoiled the farmers of
                    their possessions, leaving not one fruit-tree in the land nor any productive
                    plant. This devastation overcame the resistance of the Capenates; they begged
                    for peace and it was granted. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the Faliscan
                    country the war went on. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Rome, meanwhile, there were disturbances of
                    many sorts, to quiet which the senate had voted to plant a colony on the
                    Volscian frontier, and to enroll for that destination three thousand Roman
                    citizens, to each of whom a board of three, appointed for the purpose, had
                    proposed to assign three iugera <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                            <hi rend="italics">iugerum</hi> contained 28,800 square feet, while the
                        English acre contains 43,560. </note> and seven-twelfths. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This donation men were disposed to spurn, regarding it as a
                    sop intended to divert their hopes from greater things: for why should the plebs
                    be banished to the Volscian country, when the fair city of Veii and the
                    Veientine lands (more fertile and extensive than those of Rome) were there <pb
                        n="p.85"/> in plain sight? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The city, too,
                    they preferred to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        395</note> the City of Rome, whether for situation, or for the splendour of
                    its public and private buildings and its places. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Nay, they even mooted the plan which certainly had a great following later,
                    when the Gauls had captured Rome, of migrating to Veii. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See chap. xlix.</note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> For the rest, they intended that half of the
                    plebs and half of the senate should dwell in Veii, regarding it as possible for
                    the Roman people to inhabit two cities with a common polity. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This proposal the patricians opposed with such
                    vehemence as to declare that they would sooner die in the sight of the Roman
                    People than suffer anything of the sort to come to a vote; for when there was
                    already so much dissension in a single city, what would it be in two? <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Was it possible that any man should prefer a
                    vanquished to a victorious city, and suffer Veii captured to enjoy a greater
                    fortune than Veii free? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In fine, it was
                    conceivable that they should be left behind in their native city by their fellow
                    Romans; but to forsake their country and their fellow-citizens no violence
                    should ever force them; they had no mind to follow Titus Sicinius —the tribune
                    of the plebs who had proposed the bill —to Veii, as their founder, abandoning
                    the god Romulus, the son of a god, the Father and Author of the Roman City. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These differences gave rise to disgraceful
                    contentions —for the Fathers had won over some of the plebeian tribunes <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Only two, in fact, according to chap.
                        xxix. § 6, but one was enough to veto the motion. </note> to their opinion
                    —and <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the only thing that compelled the plebs
                    to stay their hands was this, that as often as they raised a shout, in order to
                    begin a riot, the leaders of the senate were the first to confront the mob,
                    bidding them visit blows, <pb n="p.87"/> wounds, and death on them. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The grey hairs of <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 395</note> these men, their
                    distinctions, and their honours, they shrank from outraging, and shame thwarted
                    their rage in all similar attempts. </p>
                <p> Camillus harangued the people constantly, and in all places. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> It was no wonder, he said, that the citizens had gone mad,
                    since, bound though they were to carry out their vow, they were more concerned
                    about everything else than about the discharge of their obligation. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> He would say nothing of their penny contribution —a
                    truer name for it than tithe —since in this regard each man had bound himself as
                    an individual, and the state was freed; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but
                    there was one thing his conscience would not suffer him to pass over in silence;
                    to wit, that the tithe should be defined as consisting of that part only of the
                    booty which was movable; and that nothing should be said of the captured city
                    and its territory, which were likewise included in the vow. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Unable to agree on this point, the senate
                    referred it to the pontiffs, who decided, after consulting with Camillus, that
                    so far as these things had belonged to the Veientes before the vow was made, and
                    had subsequently come into the possession of the Roman People, a tithe thereof
                    was sacred to Apollo. Thus the city and the land came into the estimate.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Money was drawn from the treasury, and the
                    tribunes of the soldiers with consular rank were directed to purchase gold with
                    it; and there being not enough of this metal, the matrons held meetings to
                    consider the need, and binding themselves by a common resolution to supply the
                    tribunes with gold, brought in all their ornaments to the treasury. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> No act was ever more acceptable to the senate, and to
                        <pb n="p.89"/> honour the matrons for their generosity, it is said to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 395</note> have voted
                    that they might drive in four-wheeled carriages to festivals and games, and in
                    two-wheeled cars on holy and working days. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    When the gold received from each had been appraised, in order that the moneys
                    might be repaid, it was determined to make a golden bowl and carry it to Delphi
                    as an offering to Apollo. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No sooner had they eased their minds of the
                    vow, than the tribunes of the commons began again their agitation, inflaming the
                    populace against all the nobles, but especially against Camillus, whom they
                    charged with having reduced to naught the spoils of Veii, by devoting them to
                    the state and to religion. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If any of the
                    leaders were absent, they were fiercely denounced; being present they outfaced
                    their angry critics and shamed them into silence. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> As soon as the people saw that the question would be
                    carried over from that year, they worked for the re-election of the tribunes of
                    the plebs who were backing the measure; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The proposed law mentioned in chap. xxiv. § 7.</note>
                    and the patricians exerted themselves to do the same for its opponents. So, for
                    the most part, the same tribunes were returned to office. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the voting for military tribunes, the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 394</note> senators
                    with much ado obtained the election of Marcus Furius Camillus. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">For the third time. See chap. xiv. §
                        5.</note> The need of a commander for the wars was their pretext, but what
                    they really wanted was a man who would combat the lavishness of the tribunes.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> , their proposal to divide up the lands of
                        Veii. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> With Camillus were elected to that office,
                    Lucius Furius Medullinus (for the sixth time), Gaius Aemilius, Lucius Valerius
                    Publicola, Spurius Postumius, and (for the second time) Publius Cornelius. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Either Scipio or Cossus (chap. xxiv. §
                        1), or possibly Maluginensis (chap. xiv. § 1). </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the outset of the year the tribunes of the
                    commons made no move, until Marcus Furius <pb n="p.91"/> Camillus should march
                    against the Faliscans, for to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 394</note> him this war had been committed. Then came
                    delays, and men's enthusiasm waned, while Camillus, the opponent whom they
                    chiefly feared, won fresh renown in the Faliscan country. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> For though at first the enemy kept within their walls,
                    deeming this their safest course, he compelled them, by ravaging their fields
                    and burning their farm-houses, to come out of their city. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Still, they were afraid to advance very far, and pitched
                    their camp about a mile from the town, trusting that it was quite safe, without
                    other reason than the difficulty of approaching it; for the ground about it was
                    rough and broken, and the roads were either narrow or steep. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But Camillus, employing a prisoner taken in that very
                    region for his guide, broke camp in the dead of night, and showed himself at
                    earliest dawn in a considerably superior position. The Romans, divided into
                    three shifts, began to build a rampart, the soldiers who were not working
                    standing by in readiness to fight. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There, when
                    the enemy sought to hinder the work, he defeated and routed them; and so great
                    was the panic that came over the Faliscans, that they fled in disorder past
                    their camp, which was the nearer refuge, and made for the town; and many were
                    slain or wounded, before, in their terror, they could rush in through the gates.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The camp was taken, and the booty was paid
                    over to the quaestors. This incensed the troops, but they were overborne by the
                    strictness of the discipline, and admired, while they detested, their general's
                    probity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Then came a blockade of the town, and
                    the construction of siege works; and sometimes, when opportunity offered, the
                    townsfolk would raid the Roman outposts and <pb n="p.93"/> skirmishes would
                    ensue. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Time wore on, without <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 394</note> bringing
                    hope to either side; the besieged had corn and other supplies, which they had
                    laid up beforehand in greater abundance than the besiegers; and it began to seem
                    as though the struggle would be as long drawn out as at Veii, had not Fortune,
                    at one stroke, given the Roman general an opportunity to display the magnanimity
                    already familiar from his exploits in war, and an early victory. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was customary amongst the Faliscans to
                    employ the same person as teacher and attendant of their children, and they used
                    to intrust a number of lads at the same time to the care of one man, a practice
                    which still obtains in Greece. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The children of
                    the chief men, as is commonly the case, were under the tuition of one who was
                    regarded as their foremost scholar. This man had in time of peace got into the
                    way of leading the boys out in front of the city for play and exercise, and
                    during the war made no change in his routine, but would draw them sometimes a
                    shorter, sometimes a longer distance from the gate, with this and that game and
                    story, until being farther away one day than usual, he seized the opportunity
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> to bring them amongst the enemy's
                    outposts, and then into the Roman camp, to the headquarters of Camillus.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then followed up his villainous act
                    with an even more villainous speech, saying that he had given Falerii into the
                    hands <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> of the Romans, having delivered up to
                    them the children of those whose fathers were in power there. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> On hearing this Camillus answered: <quote> Neither the
                        people nor the captain to whom you are come, you scoundrel, with your
                        scoundrel's gift, is like yourself. Between us and the Faliscans is no <pb
                            n="p.95"/> fellowship founded on men's covenants; but the fellowship
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 394</note>
                        which nature has implanted in both sides is there and will abide. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> There are rights of war as well as of peace, and
                        we have learnt to use them justly no less than bravely. We bear no weapons
                        against those tender years which find mercy even in the storming of a city,
                        but against those who are armed themselves, who, without wrong or
                        provocation at our hands, attacked the Roman camp at Veii. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Those people you have done your best to conquer by an
                        unheard-of crime. I shall conquer them, as I conquered Veii, in the Roman
                        way, by dint of courage, toil, and arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then had the fellow stripped, his hands
                    bound behind his back, and gave him up to the boys to lead back to Falerii,
                    providing them with rods to scourge the traitor as they drove him into town.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To behold this spectacle, there was at
                    first a great gathering together of the people, and presently the magistrates
                    called a meeting of the senate about the strange affair, and men underwent such
                    a revulsion of feeling, that those who a short time before, in the fury of their
                    hate and resentment would almost have preferred the doom of Veii to the peace of
                    Capena, were now calling for peace, with the voice of an entire city. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The honesty of the Romans, and the justice of their
                    general, were praised in market-place and senate-house, and, with the consent of
                    all, envoys proceeded to Camillus in his camp, and thence, by his permission, to
                    the Roman senate, to surrender Falerii. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Being
                    introduced into the Curia they are said to have spoken as follows: <quote>
                        Conscript Fathers, you and your general have won a victory over us which no
                        one, whether God or man, could begrudge you, and we <pb n="p.97"/> give
                        ourselves into your hands, believing (than which <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 394</note> nothing can be more
                        honourable to a victor) that we shall be better off under your government
                        than under our own laws. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The outcome of
                        this war has afforded the human race two wholesome precedents: you have set
                        fair-dealing in war above immediate victory; and we, challenged by your
                        fair-dealing, have freely granted you that victory. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> We are under your sway; send men to receive our arms
                        and hostages, and our city, the gates of which stand open. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Neither shall you be disappointed in our fidelity nor
                        we in your rule. </quote> Camillus was thanked both by his enemies and by
                    his fellow citizens. The Faliscans were commanded to pay the soldiers for that
                    year, that the Roman People might be exempted from the war tax. Peace being
                    granted, the Roman army was led home. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Camillus, having returned to the City
                    distinguished by a far better kind of glory than when he had entered it in
                    triumph drawn by white horses —for he had conquered his enemies by justice and
                    fair-dealing —uttered no reproaches, but the senators were ill-at-ease till they
                    should free him, without delay, from the obligation of his vow. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> And so, to carry the golden bowl as a gift to Apollo at
                    Delphi, they appointed Lucius Valerius, Lucius Sergius, and Aulus Manlius, who,
                    being dispatched in a single warship, were captured by Liparaean pirates not far
                    from the Sicilian Straits and carried to Liparae. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> It was the manner of that people to divide up the booty
                    which they had obtained by a kind of public piracy, but it chanced that year
                    that one Timasitheus was chief magistrate, a man more resembling the Romans than
                    his own countrymen; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.99"/> who, himself revering the title of the envoys and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 394</note> their gift,
                    as well as the god to whom it was being sent and the cause of the oblation,
                    imbued also the people, who are almost always like their ruler, with a due sense
                    of religious awe; and after entertaining the ambassadors in the guest-house of
                    the state, even sent ships to convoy them to Delphi, and thence brought them
                    safely back to Rome. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A covenant of hospitality
                    was made with him by decree of the senate, and gifts were presented him in the
                    name of the state. </p>
                <p> The same year there was a war with the Aequi, of so varied fortune that it was
                    not clear, either at the front itself or in Rome, whether the upshot had been
                    victory or defeat. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman generals were two
                    of the military tribunes, Gaius Aemilius and Spurius Postumius. At first they
                    exercised the command conjointly; afterwards, when they had routed the enemy in
                    battle, they arranged that Aemilius should hold Verrugo with a garrison, while
                    Postumius should lay waste the country. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As he
                    was leading his troops in irregular formation, somewhat carelessly in
                    consequence of his success, the Aequi fell upon them and throwing them into
                    confusion drove them to the nearest hills, whence the panic spread even to
                    Verrugo, to the other army. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Postumius having
                    rallied his men in a position of safety, called them together and chid them for
                    their alarm and flight, telling them they had been discomfited by the most
                    craven and fugitive of foes. Whereat the army cried out as one man, that they
                    deserved his reproaches, and confessed the enormity of their misconduct, but
                    promised that they would themselves mend it, and that their <pb n="p.101"/>
                    enemies' joy should be short-lived. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Demanding
                    to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 394</note> be led
                    forthwith against the camp of the Aequi — which was in full sight in the plain
                    where they had pitched it —they professed themselves willing to undergo any
                    punishment if they should not have stormed it before nightfall. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Postumius commended them and bade them sup and be
                    ready at the fourth watch. The enemy, too, that they might cut off any retreat
                    by night along the road to Verrugo, from the hill where the Romans lay, were
                    afield and met them, and the battle began before daylight, but there was a moon
                    all night. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They could see to fight as well as
                    in the daytime; but the shouts were heard in Verrugo, the soldiers believed the
                    Roman camp was being attacked, and so great was their consternation that,
                    despite the efforts of Aemilius to check them and despite his appeals, they fled
                    in a scattered rout to Tusculum. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> From thence
                    a rumour was carried to Rome that Postumius and the army were destroyed. But
                    Postumius, as soon as the first rays of light had removed all fear of ambuscades
                    in case of a wide-spread pursuit, rode down the line, reminding his men of the
                    promises they had given him, and inspired such ardour that the Aequi could no
                    longer withstand their charge, and were slaughtered while they fled (as happens
                    when rage is more concerned than valour), till their army was clean destroyed;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and the gloomy tidings from Tusculum
                    which had thrown the City into a needless fright, were succeeded by a
                    laurel-wreathed letter from Postumius, announcing the victory of the Roman
                    People and the annihilation of the Aequian army. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The measures introduced by the tribunes <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 393</note>
                    <pb n="p.103"/> of the plebs being still undecided, the commons <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 393</note> strove to
                    prolong the tenure of the supporters of the bill, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Providing for the division of the Roman People between
                        Rome and Veii. See chap. xxiv. § 7. </note> and the patricians to re-elect
                    the tribunes who had vetoed it; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> but in the
                    election of their own magistrates the plebeians proved the stronger, a
                    disappointment which the Fathers avenged by passing a resolution in the senate
                    providing for the election of consuls —a magistracy odious to the plebs. There
                    had been no consuls for fifteen years, when they elected Lucius Lucretius
                    Flavus, and Servius Sulpicius Camerinus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In
                    the beginning of this year, the tribunes united in a spirited attempt —for none
                    of the college was disposed to object —to carry the bill; and the consuls, for
                    that very reason, were quite as active in opposing them. While the whole body
                    politic was absorbed in this one concern, Vitellia, a Roman colony, was captured
                    by the Aequi, in whose territory it was situated. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The greatest part of the settlers escaped, for the place
                    was taken by treachery at night and their flight through the opposite quarter of
                    the town was unopposed, and made their way to Rome in safety. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> To Lucius Lucretius the consul fell the command in this
                    affair. Marching out with his army, he defeated the enemy in a battle and
                    returned victorious to the City, where he found a far more serious struggle
                    impending. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A day of trial had been appointed
                    for the plebeian tribunes of two years before, namely Aulus Verginius and
                    Quintus Pomponius, to defend whom the senate, as the patricians all agreed, was
                    in honour bound; for no man brought any charge against their lives or the
                    conduct of their office, except their having, out of complaisance to the
                    Fathers, opposed the tribunician law. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But the
                        <pb n="p.105"/> influence of the senators was out-weighed by the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 393</note> resentment
                    of the plebs, and a shameful precedent was set, when the innocent men were
                    condemned each to pay a fine of 10,000 asses. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    This roused the indignation of the senate. Camillus frankly denounced the
                    depravity of the commons, who having turned against their own representatives,
                    failed to perceive that they had by their wicked judgment of the tribunes done
                    away with the veto, and that in doing away with the veto they had overthrown the
                    tribunician power. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For if they supposed that
                    the unbridled licence of that office would be tolerated by the Fathers, they
                    were mistaken; if tribunician violence could not be resisted by the help of
                    tribunes, the senators must find some other weapon. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> He rebuked the consuls also, because they had, without
                    protesting, allowed those tribunes who had followed the guidance of the senate
                    to suffer for their reliance on the guarantee of state protection. By such
                    sentiments, publicly expressed in speeches, he angered the people more and more
                    from day to day. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As to the senate, he ceased not to encourage
                    it in opposing the law: they must go down into the Forum, when the day should
                    arrive for voting on it, in no other spirit than that of men who realized that
                    they had to fight for hearth and home, for the temples of their gods, and for
                    the soil of their birth. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> So far, indeed, as
                    the question touched his private interest, it would actually be an honour to
                    him, if it were not sinful to be thinking of his own renown while his country
                    was struggling for life, that the city he had, won should be thronged with
                    people; that he should <pb n="p.107"/> daily be reminded of his glory, and have
                    before his <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 393</note>
                    eyes the town which had figured in his triumph; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy is thinking of the custom which grew up later of
                        exhibiting in the triumphal procession models or pictures of towns, rivers,
                        and mountains, belonging to the conquered nation. </note> that all men
                    should tread in the footsteps of his fame. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But
                    he thought it an offence against Heaven that a city deserted and forsaken by the
                    immortal gods should be inhabited, and that the Roman People should dwell on
                    conquered soil, exchanging their victorious City for a vanquished one. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These earnest words of their leading member so
                    stirred the senators, old men as well as young, that on the day the law was
                    proposed they formed in a body and came into the Forum, where they dispersed
                    among the tribes, and canvassing every man <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/>
                    his own tribesmen, began with tears to beseech them, that they would not forsake
                    that City for which both they and their fathers had fought with the greatest
                    courage and good fortune. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They pointed to the
                    Capitol, to the shrine of Vesta, and to the other temples standing all about
                    them; they begged them not to drive the Roman People, an exile, and a wanderer
                    from its native land and its household gods, to the city of its enemies, nor to
                    carry things so far that it would be better that Veii had not been taken, so
                    that Rome might not be deserted. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Since the
                    patricians used not force but entreaties, and in their entreaties made many a
                    reference to the gods, the greater part felt the prick of conscience, and the
                    law was rejected by one more tribe than voted in its favour. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">There were at this time twenty-one
                        tribes.</note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> And so greatly did this victory rejoice the
                    Fathers, that next day, at the instance of the consuls, a decree was passed by
                    the senate, that seven <hi rend="italics">iugera</hi> of the Veientine land
                    should be apportioned to every plebeian, and not alone to the heads of families,
                    but so as to reckon in all the free-born members of the <pb n="p.109"/>
                    household, that with such a prospect before them <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 393</note> men might be willing to
                    rear children. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Appeased by this largess, the plebs made <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 392</note> no
                    objection to an assembly for the election of consuls, and the choice fell on
                    Lucius Valerius Potitus and Marcus Manlius, afterwards surnamed Capitolinus.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> At vi. xvii. 5 Livy implies that
                        Manlius was given the cognomen because of his defence of the Capitol (chap.
                        xlvii.), but at IV. xlii. 2 a L. Manlius Capitolinus had been mentioned, and
                        the surname was probably due to the family's residing on the Capitoline. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These consuls celebrated the Great Games,
                    which Marcus Furius the dictator had vowed in the war with Veii. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> This year saw also the dedication of a temple to
                    Queen Juno, vowed by the same dictator in the same war; and tradition relates
                    that the ceremony was attended by throngs of enthusiastic matrons. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A campaign in no way memorable was fought with
                    the Aequi on Mount Algidus, the enemy being routed before they had well begun to
                    fight. Valerius was the more persistent in cutting them down as they fled, and
                    to him was decreed a triumph; Manlius was allowed to enter the City in an
                    ovation. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A lesser triumph, in which
                        the victorious general entered the City on foot. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In this year also a new war broke out, namely
                    with the people of Volsinii. Owing to a famine and pestilence which arose in the
                    Roman territories on account of drought and excessive heat, it was impossible to
                    send an army against them; and in consequence of this the Volsinienses, having
                    added the Sappinates <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Sappinum, a town
                        otherwise unknown, is presumed to have been situated near Volsinii. </note>
                    to their forces, were puffed up with pride and made an incursion themselves into
                    the fields of the Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> War was then
                    declared against both nations. </p>
                <p> Gaius Julius, the censor, died, and Marcus Cornelius was substituted in his
                    place, a circumstance <pb n="p.111"/> which was afterwards thought to have
                    offended the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        392</note> gods, because in this lustrum Rome was captured; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> nor from that day has a censor ever been appointed in the
                    room of one who has died. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Thereafter
                        the survivor resigned and two new censors were appointed (ix. xxxiv. 21). </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The consuls, too, caught the plague, and it
                    was voted that fresh auspices should be obtained by means of an interregnum.
                    Accordingly, when the consuls, in obedience to the senate's decree, had
                    abdicated, Marcus Furius Camillus was appointed interrex, and named as his
                    successor Publius Cornelius Scipio, who, in turn, named Lucius Valerius Potitus
                    interrex; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> under whom they elected six military
                    tribunes of consular rank, so that even if any of them should fall ill the state
                    might still have magistrates. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the first day of July they entered <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 391</note> office, to
                    wit, Lucius Lucretius, Servius Sulpicius, Marcus Aemilius, Lucius Furius
                    Medullinus (for the seventh time), Furius Agrippa, and (for the second time)
                    Gaius Aemilius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of these, Lucius Lucretius and
                    Gaius Aemilius were assigned the war with Volsinii as their province, while the
                    Sappinates fell to Agrippa Furius and Servius Sulpicius. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The Volsinienses were encountered first, in a campaign of
                    great magnitude in respect to the enemy's numbers, though the engagement with
                    them was no very sharp affair. Their line broke at the first assault, and in the
                    rout eight thousand soldiers were cut off by the cavalry, and laying down their
                    arms, surrendered. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the Sappinates heard
                    of this campaign, they refused to risk a battle, but retired within their walls
                    and prepared to defend themselves. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans
                    plundered right and left, both the lands of Sappinum and those of Volsinii,
                    without finding any to resist their force, until the <pb n="p.113"/>
                    Volsinienses wearied of the war; and upon their agreeing <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 391</note> to restore the goods of the
                    Roman People and furnish pay for the army for that campaign, they were granted a
                    truce of twenty years. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The same year Marcus Caedicius, a plebeian,
                    reported to the tribunes, that in the Nova Via, where the chapel now stands
                    above the temple of Vesta, he had heard in the silence of the night a voice more
                    distinct than a man's, which bade him tell the magistrates that the Gauls were
                    approaching. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This portent was neglected, as
                    often happens, because of the informant's humble station, and because that race
                    was remote and therefore not well known. And not only did they reject the
                    warnings of Heaven, as their doom drew nearer, but they even sent away from the
                    City the only human assistance present with them, in the person of Marcus
                    Furius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He had been indicted by Lucius
                    Apuleius, tribune of the plebs, on account of the spoils of Veii, just at the
                    time of losing his youthful son. Summoning to his house his fellow tribesmen and
                    his clients (who formed a good part of the plebs), he sounded their feelings,
                    and having been answered that they would make up such an amount as he might be
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> fined, but that they could not acquit
                    him, he departed into exile, beseeching the immortal gods that if he were an
                    innocent man to whom that wrong was done they would speedily make his thankless
                    fellow citizens wish to have him back. He was fined in his absence in the sum of
                    15,000 asses. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the expulsion of that citizen whose
                    presence, if anything in this life is certain, would have made the capture of
                    Rome impossible, disaster approached the ill-fated City with the arrival of <pb
                        n="p.115"/> envoys from the men of Clusium seeking help <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 391</note> against the
                    Gauls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The story runs that this race, allured
                    by the delicious fruits and especially the wine —then a novel luxury —had
                    crossed the Alps and possessed themselves of lands that had before been tilled
                    by the Etruscans; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and that wine had been
                    imported into Gaul expressly to entice them, by Arruns of Clusium, in his anger
                    at the seduction of his wife by Lucumo. This youth, whose guardian he had been,
                    was so powerful that he could not have chastised him without calling in a
                    foreign force. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He it was who is said to have
                    guided the Gauls across the Alps, and to have suggested the attack on Clusium.
                    Now I would not deny that Arruns or some other citizen brought the Gauls to
                    Clusium, but that those who besieged Clusium were not the first who had passed
                    the Alps is generally agreed. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Indeed it was
                    two hundred years before the attack on Clusium and the capture of Rome, that the
                    Gauls first crossed over into Italy; neither were the Clusini the first of the
                    Etruscans with whom they fought; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but long
                    before that the Gallic armies had often given battle to those who dwelt between
                    the Apennines and the Alps. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The Tuscan sway, down to the rise of the Roman
                    domination, stretched over a wide expanse of land and sea. How great their power
                    was on the upper and the lower seas, by which Italy is surrounded like an
                    island, is apparent from the names, since the Italian races have called one of
                    them Tuscan, the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> general designation of the
                    race, and the other Hadriatic, from Hatria, an Etruscan colony; and the Greeks
                    know the same seas as Tyrrhenian and Adriatic. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    In the lands which slope on either side <pb n="p.117"/> towards one of these
                    seas, they had twice twelve <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 391</note> cities; first the twelve on this side the
                    Apennines, towards the lower sea; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> to which
                    afterwards they added the same number beyond the Apennines, sending over as many
                    colonies as there were original cities, and taking possession of all the
                    transpadane region (except the angle belonging to the Veneti who dwell about the
                    gulf) as far as the Alps. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Alpine tribes
                    have also, no doubt, the same origin, especially the Raetians; who have been
                    rendered so savage by the very nature of the country as to retain nothing of
                    their ancient character save the sound of their speech, and even that is
                    corrupted. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Concerning the migration of the Gauls into
                    Italy we are told as follows: While Tarquinius Priscus reigned at Rome, the
                    Celts, who make up one of the three divisions of Gaul, were under the domination
                    of the Bituriges, and this tribe supplied the Celtic nation with a king.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ambigatus was then the man, and his
                    talents, together with his own and the general good fortune, had brought him
                    great distinction; for Gaul under his sway grew so rich in corn and so populous,
                    that it seemed hardly possible to govern so great a multitude. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The king, who was now an old man and wished to relieve his
                    kingdom of a burdensome throng, announced that he meant to send Bellovesus and
                    Segovesus, his sister's sons, two enterprising young men, to find such homes as
                    the gods might assign to them by augury; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and
                    promised them that they should head as large a number of emigrants as they
                    themselves desired, so that no tribe might be able to prevent their settlement.
                    Whereupon to Segovesus were by lot assigned the Hercynian highlands <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">Hercynei
                            saltus</hi> were the upland districts of South Germany (including the
                        Black Forest, Bohemia, and the Hartz) where both Caesar and Tacitus intimate
                        that Celts had formerly established settlements ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >B.G.</hi> VI. xxiv.; <hi rend="italics">Germ.</hi> xxviii.). </note> ;
                    but to <pb n="p.119"/> Bellovesus the gods proposed a far pleasanter road, into
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 391</note> Italy.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Taking out with him the surplus population
                    of his tribes, the Bituriges, Arverni, Senones, Haedui, Ambarri, Carnutes, and
                    Aulerci, he marched with vast numbers of infantry and cavalry into the country
                    of the Tricastini. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Tribes in central
                        Gaul some of whose names survive in the modern Bourges, Auvergne, Sens, and
                        Chartres. The Tricastini were in the Roman province (Provence). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There the Alps stood over against them; and I
                    for one do not wonder that they seemed insuperable, for as yet no road had led
                    across them —as far back at all events as tradition reaches —unless one chooses
                    to believe the stories about Hercules. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While
                    they were there fenced in as it were by the lofty mountains, and were looking
                    about to discover where they might cross, over heights that reached the sky,
                    into another world, superstition also held them back, because it had been
                    reported to them that some strangers seeking lands were beset by the Salui.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> These were the Massilians, who had come in
                    ships from Phocaea. The Gauls, regarding this as a good omen of their own
                    success, lent them assistance, so that they fortified, without opposition from
                    the Salui, the spot which they had first seized after landing. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> They themselves crossed the Alps through the Taurine passes
                    and the pass of the Duria; routed the Etruscans in battle not far from the river
                    Ticinus, and learning that they were encamped in what was called the country of
                    the Insubres, who bore the same name as an Haeduan canton, they regarded it as a
                    place of good omen, and founded a city there which they called Mediolanium.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Now Milan.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Presently another band, consisting of Cenomani
                    led by Etitovius, followed in the tracks <pb n="p.121"/> of the earlier
                    emigrants; and having, with the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 391</note> approval of Bellovesus, crossed the Alps by the
                    same pass, established themselves where the cities of Brixia and Verona are-now.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After these the Libui came and settled,
                    and the Salluvii —taking up their abode hard by the ancient tribe of the Laevi
                    Ligures, about the river Ticinus. Then, over the Poenine Pass, came the Boii and
                    Lingones, who finding everything taken up between the Po and the Alps, crossed
                    the Po on rafts, and drove out not only the Etruscans, but also the Umbrians
                    from their lands; nevertheless, they kept on the further side of the Apennines.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then the Senones, the latest to come, had
                    their holdings from the river Utens all the way to the Aesis. This was the
                    tribe, I find, which came to Clusium and from thence to Rome, but whether alone
                    or assisted by all the peoples of Cisalpine Gaul, is uncertain. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The men of Clusium, alarmed by this strange
                    invasion, when they beheld the numbers and the unfamiliar figures of the men and
                    their novel weapons, and heard that on many afield, this side the Po and beyond
                    it, they had put to flight the levies of Etruria; though they had no rights of
                    alliance or of friendship with the Romans, except that they had refused to
                    defend their kinsmen the Veientes against the Roman People; did yet dispatch
                    envoys to Rome to ask help of the senate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As
                    for the help, they were unsuccessful; but the three sons of Marcus Fabius
                    Ambustus were sent as ambassadors to remonstrate with the Gauls, in the name of
                    the senate and the Roman People, against their attack on those who had done them
                    no wrong, and were the Roman People's allies and friends. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans, <pb n="p.123"/> they said, would be obliged to
                    defend them, even <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        391</note> going to war, if circumstances should make it necessary; but it
                    had seemed preferable that the war itself should, if possible, be avoided, and
                    that they should make the acquaintance of the Gauls — a new race to them —in a
                    friendly rather than in a hostile manner. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was a peaceful embassy, had it not <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> been for the
                    violence of the ambassadors, who were more like Gauls than Romans. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> To them, when they had made known their mission in
                    the council, the Gauls replied, that although they then heard for the first time
                    the name of Roman, they could yet believe them to be stout-hearted men, since
                    the Clusini had sought their aid in time of danger; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and inasmuch as they had chosen to defend their allies by
                    negotiation rather than by the sword, they would not, for their own part, spurn
                    the peace which the Romans proposed, if the men of Clusium, who possessed more
                    land than they could till, would surrender to the Gauls, who needed land, a
                    portion of their territory; on no other terms could they consider granting
                    peace. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They added that they desired to be
                    answered in the presence of the Romans, and that if land were refused them, it
                    was under the eyes of these same Romans that they meant to fight, that they
                    might be able to tell their friends how greatly the Gauls excelled all other men
                    in prowess. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When the Romans asked what
                    conceivable right they had to demand land of its occupants under threat of war,
                    and what business Gauls had in Etruria, they were truculently informed, that the
                    new-comers carried their right at the point of the sword and that all things
                    belonged to the brave. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So, angry passions <pb
                        n="p.125"/> being kindled on both sides, they ran to their <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C. 390</note> weapons and
                    joined battle; and the envoys, impelled by the fate which was even then urging
                    Rome to its doom, took up arms, in defiance of the law of nations. Nor could it
                    pass unnoticed, when in the very fore-front of the Tuscan line there were
                    fighting three of the noblest and most valiant of the Roman youth, so
                    conspicuous was the strangers' bravery. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nay,
                    Quintus Fabius even rode out in front of the line, and meeting the Gallic leader
                    as he charged boldly at the very standards of the Etruscans, ran his spear
                    through his side and killed him. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As he was
                    engaged in despoiling his man, the Gauls recognized him, and the word passed
                    through all the army that it was the Roman envoy. Thereupon, they gave over
                    their anger at the Clusini and sounded the retreat, uttering threats against the
                    Romans. Some were for marching at once on Rome; but the older men brought them
                    over to send envoys first to complain of their wrongs, and to demand the
                    surrender of the Fabii, in satisfaction for their violation of the law of
                    nations. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the Gallic emissaries had stated
                    their mission according to instructions, the senate disapproved of the conduct
                    of the Fabii and felt the demands of the barbarians to be just; but private
                    interest could not suffer them, in the case of men of such exalted station, to
                    decree what they approved. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And so, that the
                    blame might not rest with the senate, if a Gallic war should chance to bring
                    disaster, they referred the demands of the Gauls to the people for
                    consideration; and with them wealth and influence carried so much more weight,
                    that the men whose punishment was under discussion were elected consular
                    tribunes for <pb n="p.127"/> the ensuing year. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> At this the Gauls were enraged, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 390</note> as they had every right to be, and returned to
                    their people with open threats of war. The tribunes of the soldiers chosen with
                    the three Fabii were Quintus Sulpicius Longus, Quintus Servilius (for his fourth
                    term), and Publius Cornelius Maluginensis. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now that so heavy a calamity drew
                    towards,-such is the blindness Fortune visits on men's minds when she would have
                    her gathering might meet with no check, —that state which against the Fidenates
                    and Veientes and other neighbouring tribes had on many occasions resorted to the
                    last expedient and named a dictator —that <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    state, I say, though now an enemy never yet seen or heard of was rousing up war
                    from the ocean and the remotest corners of the world, had recourse to no unusual
                    authority or help. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes whose rashness
                    had brought on the war were in supreme command; they conducted the levy with no
                    greater care than had usually been employed in preparing for ordinary campaigns,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Dionysius of
                        Halicarnassus (XII. xix) four legions were embodied, and so many allies and
                        auxiliary troops that at the Allia the Roman army numbered 40,000 ( <hi
                            rend="italics">cf.</hi> Plut. <hi rend="italics">Cam.</hi> XVIII).
                    </note> and even disparaged the rumoured seriousness of the danger. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Gauls, meanwhile, on learning that honours had
                    actually been conferred on men who had violated the rights of mankind and that
                    their embassy had been made light of, were consumed with wrath (a passion which
                    their race is powerless to control), an straightway catching up their standards,
                    set their column in rapid motion. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As they
                    marched swiftly and noisily on, the terrified cities armed in haste, and the
                    peasants fled; but they signified with loud cries, wherever they came, that Rome
                    was their goal, and their horse and foot in an extended line covered a vast
                    tract of ground. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Yet, though rumour and the
                    report of the Clusini preceded them, and <pb n="p.129"/> after that successive
                    messages from other peoples, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 390</note> the utmost consternation was wrought in Rome by
                    the enemy's swiftness, which was <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> such that
                    the army, albeit levied as it were <hi rend="italics">en masse</hi> and
                    hurriedly led out, barely covered eleven miles before confronting him, at the
                    point where the river Allia descends in a very deep channel from the
                    Crustuminian mountains, and mingles, not far south of the highway, with the
                    waters of the Tiber. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The exact
                        position of the battlefield is uncertain, as the town Crustumerium has
                        disappeared and left no trace. A brook called <hi rend="italics">Fosso
                            Aaecstro,</hi> which empties into the Tiber about eleven miles from
                        Rome, has been thought to be the ancient Allia. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Gauls had already overrun all the ground
                    in front and on both sides, and —the race being naturally given to vainglorious
                    outbursts —their wild songs and discordant shouts filled all the air with a
                    hideous noise. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There the tribunes of the soldiers, without
                    having selected a place for a camp or fortified a position to which they might
                    retreat, and, forgetting even the gods, to say nothing of men, without auspices
                    or sacrificial omens, drew up their line with the wings extended to prevent
                    being outflanked by the numbers of the enemy; yet could not stretch their front
                    as wide as his, though they thinned it till the centre was weak and scarce held
                    together. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was a little eminence on the
                    right which they decided to occupy with their reserves, a measure which, though
                    it was the beginning of their panic and flight, was also the sole salvation of
                    the fugitives. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For Brennus, the Gallic
                    chieftain, seeing the Romans to be so few, was especially apprehensive of a
                    stratagem. He supposed that they had seized the higher ground' for this purpose,
                    that when the Gauls had made a frontal attack on the battle-line of the legions,
                    the reserves might assail them in the flank and rear. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> He therefore directed his assault against the reserves, not
                    doubting that, if he could <pb n="p.131"/> dislodge them, it would be easy for
                    his greatly <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        390</note> superior numbers to obtain a victory in the plain. Thus not only
                    luck but generalship as well were on the side of the barbarians. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> In the other army there was no resemblance to Romans,
                    either amongst officers or private soldiers. Terror and dismay had got hold of
                    their spirits, and such complete forgetfulness of everything that a much greater
                    number fled to Veii, a hostile city, though the Tiber was across their way, than
                    by the straight road to Rome, to their wives and children. For a little while
                    the reserves were protected by their position. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    In the rest of the field, no sooner had those who were nearest heard the
                    shouting on their flank, and those who were farthest the outcry in their rear,
                    than — fresh and unhurt —they ran away from their strange enemies, almost before
                    they had caught sight of them; and so far were they from risking a combat, that
                    they did not even return their battle-cry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    None were slain in fight; but they were cut down from behind as they blocked
                    their escape by their own struggles in the disordered rout. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> On the bank of the Tiber, whither the whole left wing had
                    fled, after throwing away their arms, there was great slaughter, and many who
                    could not swim, or lacked the strength, weighed down by their corslets and other
                    armour, sank beneath the flood. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nevertheless,
                    the chief part got safely to Veii, whence they not only sent no succours to
                    Rome, but dispatched not even a messenger to tell of the defeat. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> From the right wing, which had stood at a distance
                    from the river and closer to the foot of the mountain, the fugitives all made
                    for Rome, and without stopping even to shut the city gates, sought refuge in the
                    Citadel. </p>
                <pb n="p.133"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The very Gauls themselves, stunned by <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> the
                    marvellous victory they had so suddenly gained, at first stood rooted to the
                    spot with amazement, like men that knew not what had happened; then they feared
                    an ambush; after that they fell to collecting the spoils of the slain and
                    erecting piles of arms, as their custom is; then at last having discovered no
                    hostile movement anywhere, they began their march, and a little before sunset
                    reached the environs of Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There, when the
                    cavalry had reconnoitred and had reported that the gates were not closed, that
                    no out-guards were watching before the gates, that no armed men were on the
                    walls, astonishment held them spell-bound as before; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> and fearful of the night and the lie of the unknown : City,
                    they went into camp between Rome and the Anio, after sending off patrols about
                    the walls and the rest of the gates, to find out what the enemy in their
                    desperate case could possibly be at. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As for
                    the Romans, inasmuch as more, on escaping from the battle, had fled to Veii than
                    to Rome, and no one supposed that any were left alive except those who had found
                    refuge in the City, they mourned for all alike, both the living and the dead,
                    and well nigh filled the City with lamentation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> But presently their personal griefs were overwhelmed in a general panic, with
                    the announcement that the enemy was at hand; and soon they could hear the
                    dissonant howls and songs of the barbarians, as their squadrons roamed about the
                    walls. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> During all the time that intervened
                    before the following morning their hearts were. in, such. suspense, that each
                    moment they anticipated an immediate attack:. on the first arrival of the enemy,
                    because they had come close to the <pb n="p.135"/> City —for they would have
                    stopped at the Allia, had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B.C. 390</note> this not been their design; —again, <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> towards sundown, because there was little daylight left,
                    they thought that they would enter the City before nightfall; then they
                    concluded that they had put it off till night, to strike more fear into them.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Finally the approach of dawn put them
                    beside themselves, and close upon these restless apprehensions came the evil
                    they were dreading, when the hostile forces entered the city gates. Yet neither
                    that night nor the following day did the citizens at all resemble those who had
                    fled in such consternation at the Allia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For
                    having no hopes that they could protect the City with so small a force as
                    remained to them, they resolved that the men of military age and the able-bodied
                    senators should retire into the Citadel and the Capitol, with their wives and
                    children; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and, having laid in arms and
                    provisions, should from that stronghold defend the gods, the men, and the name
                    of Rome; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> that the flamen and the priestesses
                    of Vesta should remove the sacred objects pertaining to the State far from the
                    bloodshed and the flames, nor should their cult be abandoned till none should be
                    left to cherish it. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If the Citadel and the
                    Capitol, where dwelt the gods; if the senate, the source of public wisdom; if
                    the young men capable of bearing arms survived the impending destruction of the
                    City, they could easily bear to lose the crowd of old men left behind them, who
                    were bound to die in any case. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> And in order
                    that the multitude of commoners might endure it with the more composure, the old
                    men who had triumphed and those who had been consuls declared publicly that they
                    would perish with those others, nor burden with bodies <pb n="p.137"/> incapable
                    of bearing arms in defence of the country <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> the scanty stores of the
                    fighting men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Such were the consolations which the old men
                    appointed to die exchanged among themselves; then, directing their encouragement
                    to the band of youths whom they were escorting to the Capitol and the Citadel,
                    they committed to their valour and their young strength whatever fortune might
                    yet be in store for a City that for three hundred and sixty years had been
                    victorious in every war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On the departure of
                    those who carried with them all hope and help, from those who had resolved not
                    to <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> survive the capture and destruction of
                    their City, though the separation was a pitiful thing to see, yet the tears of
                    the women, as they, ran distractedly up and down, and following now these, -now
                    those, demanded of husbands and sons to what fate they were consigning them,
                    supplied the final touch of human wretchedness. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Still, the greater part of them followed their sons into the Citadel, though
                    none either forbade or encouraged it, since what would have helped the besieged
                    to lessen the number of non-combatants would have been inhuman. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Another host —consisting chiefly of plebeians —too large
                    for so small a hill to receive, or to support with so meagre a supply of corn,
                    streamed out of the City as though forming at last one continuous line, and took
                    their way towards Janiculum. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Thence some of
                    them scattered through the country-side, and others made for the towns near by.
                    They had neither leader nor concerted plan; each followed the promptings of his
                    own hopes and his own counsels, in despair of the: commonwealth. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the flamen of Quirinus and the
                    Vestal <pb n="p.139"/> virgins, with no thought for their own belongings, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> were
                    consulting which of the sacred things they should carry with them, and which,
                    because they were not strong enough to carry them all, they must leave behind,
                    and, finally, where these objects would be safe. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> They judged it best to place them in jars and bury them in the shrine
                    adjoining the flamen's house, where it is now forbidden to spit; the rest of the
                    things they carried, sharing the burden amongst them, along the road which leads
                    by the Sublician Bridge to Janiculum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As they
                    mounted the hill they were perceived by a plebeian named Lucius Albinius, who
                    had a waggon in which he was conveying his wife and children, amidst the throng
                    of those who, unfit for war, were leaving the City. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Preserving even then the distinction between divine and
                    human, and holding it sacrilege that the priestesses of his country should go
                    afoot, bearing the sacred objects of the Roman People, while his family were
                    seen in a vehicle, he commanded his wife and children to get down, placed the
                    virgins and their relics in the waggon, and brought them to Caere, whither the
                    priestesses were bound. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome meantime such arrangements for
                    defending the Citadel as the case admitted of were now fairly complete, and the
                    old men returned to their homes to await the coming of their enemies with hearts
                    that were steeled to die. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Such of them as had
                    held curule magistracies, that they might face death in the trappings of their
                    ancient rank and office, as beseemed their worth, put on the stately robes which
                    are worn by those who conduct the <hi rend="italics">tensae</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cars used in the games of the Circus
                        to carry the images of the Gods. </note> or celebrate a triumph, and, thus
                    habited, seated themselves on ivory chairs <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The curule chair was inlaid with ivory. At this period
                        the only curule magistrates were dictators, masters of the horse, consuls,
                        and censors. </note> in the middle of <pb n="p.141"/> their houses.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some historians record that Marcus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> Folius, the
                    pontifex maximus, led in the recitation of a solemn vow, by which they devoted
                    themselves to death, in behalf of their country and the Roman Quirites. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Gauls found their lust for combat cooled
                    by the night which had intervened. At no point in the battle had they been
                    pushed to desperate exertions, nor had they now to carry the City by assault. It
                    was therefore without rancour or excitement that they entered Rome, on the
                    following day, by the Colline Gate (which lay wide open), and made their way to
                    the Forum, gazing about them at the temples of the gods and at the Citadel,
                    which alone presented some show of war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Thence, after leaving a moderate guard to prevent any attack upon their
                    scattered forces from Citadel or Capitol, they dispersed in quest of booty
                    through streets where there was none to meet them, some rushing in a body into
                    whatever houses were nearest, while others sought out the most remote, as though
                    supposing that only such would be intact and full- of plunder. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But being frightened out of these by their very solitude,
                    lest the enemy should by some ruse entrap them as they wandered apart, they came
                    trooping back to the Forum and the places near it. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> There they found the dwellings of the plebeians fastened
                    up, but the halls of the nobles open; and they hesitated almost more to enter
                    the open houses than the shut, —so <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> nearly akin
                    to religious awe was their feeling as they beheld seated in the vestibules,
                    beings who, besides that their ornaments and apparel were more splendid than
                    belonged to man, seemed also, in their majesty of countenance and in the gravity
                    of their expression, most like to gods. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.143"/>
                <p> While they stood reverentially before them, as <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> if they had been images, it
                    is related that a Gaul stroked the beard of one of them, Marcus Papirius, —
                    which he wore long, as they all did then, —whereat the Roman struck him over the
                    head with his ivory mace, and, provoking his anger, was the first to be slain;
                    after that the rest were massacred where they sat; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> and when the nobles had been murdered, there was no mercy
                    then shown to anyone; the houses were ransacked, and after being emptied were
                    given to the flames. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But whether it was that not all the Gauls
                    desired to destroy the City, or that their leaders had resolved to make a
                    certain show of burning, to inspire alarm, in hopes that the besieged might be
                    driven to capitulate by affection for their homes, but not to <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> burn up all the houses, in order that they might hold
                    whatever remained of the City as a pledge to work on the feelings of their
                    enemies — however this may have been, the fire spread by no means so freely or
                    extensively on the first day as is commonly the case in a captured town.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As the Romans looked down from their
                    fastness and saw the City full of enemies running up and down in all the
                    streets, while first in one quarter and then in another some new calamity would
                    be occurring, they were unable, I do not say to keep their heads, but even to be
                    sure of their ears and eyes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Wherever the
                    shouting of the invaders, the lamentations of the women and children, the
                    crackling of the flames, and the crash of falling buildings drew their
                    attention, trembling at each sound, they turned their thoughts and their gaze
                    that way, as though Fortune had placed them there to witness the <pb n="p.145"/>
                    pageant of their dying country. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Of all their
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note>
                    possessions nothing was left them to defend save their persons alone; and so
                    much more wretched was their plight than that of all others who have ever been
                    beleaguered, that they were cut off from their native City and confined where
                    they could see all that belonged to them in the power of their enemies.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nor was the night more tranquil, after a
                    day of such distress; and the night was followed by a restless day, with never a
                    moment that had not still some fresh calamity to unfold. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Yet, oppressed as they were, or rather overwhelmed, by so
                    many misfortunes, nothing could alter their resolve; though they should see
                    everything laid low in flames and ruins, they would stoutly defend the hill they
                    held, however small and naked, which was all that Liberty had left. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> And now that the same events were occurring every
                    day, like men grown used to grief, they had ceased to feel their own
                    misfortunes, looking solely to their shields and the swords in their right hands
                    as their only remaining hope. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Gauls likewise, having vainly for some
                    days waged war against only the buildings of Rome, when they saw that there was
                    nothing left amidst the smouldering ruins of the captured City but armed
                    enemies, who for all their disasters were not a jot appalled nor likely to yield
                    to anything but force, took a desperate resolution to attack the Citadel.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At daybreak the signal was made; and the
                    entire host, having formed up in the Forum, gave a cheer, and raising their
                    shields above their heads and locking them, began the ascent. The defenders on
                    the other hand did nothing rashly <pb n="p.147"/> or in confusion. At all the
                    approaches they had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        390</note> strengthened the guard-posts, and where they saw the enemy
                    advancing they stationed their best soldiers, and suffered them to come up,
                    persuaded that the higher they mounted up the steep the easier it would be to
                    drive them down. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They made their stand about
                    the middle of the declivity, and there, launching their attack from the higher
                    ground, which seemed of itself to hurl them against the foe, dislodged the
                    Gauls, with such havoc and destruction that they never attempted to attack in
                    that manner again, with either a part or the whole of their strength. So,
                    relinquishing all hope of getting up by force of arms, they prepared for a
                    blockade. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Having never till that moment
                    considered such a thing, they had destroyed all the corn in the City with their
                    conflagrations, and what was in the fields had all been hurriedly carried off,
                    within the last few days, to Veil. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They
                    therefore arranged to divide their army, and employ part of it to pillage the
                    neighbouring nations and part to invest the Citadel, in order that those who
                    held the lines might be provisioned by the foragers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the Gauls departed from the City,
                    Fortune's own hand guided them to Ardea, that they might make trial of Roman
                    manhood. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Camillus was languishing there in
                    exile, more grieved by the nation's calamity than by his own; and as he
                    sorrowfully inveighed against gods and men, and asked, with wonder and
                    humiliation, where those heroes were who had shared with him in the capture of
                    Veii and Falerii, and whose gallantry in other wars had ever outrun their
                    success, <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> of a sudden he heard that the army
                    of the Gauls was coming, and that the Ardeates <pb n="p.149"/> in alarm were
                    deliberating what to do about it. With <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 390</note> an inspiration nothing less than divine, he
                    pushed into the midst of their conference, —though before accustomed to avoid
                    these councils —and there, <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <quote>Men of Ardea,</quote> he said, <quote> my ancient friends, and of late my
                        fellow citizens, —since your goodness would have it so and my own fortune
                        has made it necessary, —let none of you suppose me to have come forward in
                        forgetfulness of my condition; but circumstances and our common peril oblige
                        every man at this crisis to contribute what he can to the general defence.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And when shall I show gratitude for
                        your great kindnesses to me, if I am backward now? Or when shall you have
                        need of me, if not in war? 'Twas by this art that I stood secure in my
                        native City: unbeaten in war, I was driven out in time of peace by the
                        thankless citizens. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But you, men of Ardea,
                        have now an opportunity of requiting the Roman People for such great
                        benefits as you yourselves are mindful of, —nor need I cast upto you things
                        which you remember; —and your city has an opportunity to win from our common
                        enemy great renown in war. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That people now
                        drawing near in loose array has been endowed by nature with bodily size and
                        courage, great indeed but vacillating; which is the reason that to every
                        conflict they bring more terror than strength. This may be seen in their
                        defeat of the Romans. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They captured the
                        City, which lay wide open; but a handful of men in the Citadel and the
                        Capitol are holding them at bay; already, oppressed by the tedium of the
                        siege, they are departing and roaming aimlessly through the country-side.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They greedily gorge themselves with
                        food and wine, and when <pb n="p.151"/> night approaches they erect no
                        rampart, and without <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                            >B. C. 390</note> pickets or sentries, throw themselves down anywhere
                        beside a stream, in the manner of wild beasts. Just now success has rendered
                        them even more careless than they are wont to be. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> If you have a mind to protect your city and not to
                        suffer all this country to become Gaul, arm yourselves in the first watch,
                        and follow me in force, not to a battle but a massacre. If I do not deliver
                        them up to you fast asleep, to be butchered like cattle, I am ready to
                        submit at Ardea to the same fate that I endured at Rome. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Well-wishers and opponents were alike
                    persuaded that there was no such warrior in those days anywhere. Breaking up the
                    council, they supped, and waited intently for the signal. On its being given, in
                    the silence of the early night, they presented themselves before Camillus at the
                    gates. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They had not left the city very far
                    behind them, when they came to the camp of the Gauls, unguarded, just as he had
                    prophesied, and open on every side, and, giving a loud cheer, rushed upon it.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was no resistance anywhere: the
                    whole place was a shambles, where unarmed men, relaxed in sleep, were
                    slaughtered. Those, however, who were farthest off were frightened from the
                    places where they lay, and ignorant of the nature of the attack or its source,
                    fled panic-stricken, and some ran unawares straight into the enemy. The most of
                    them were carried into the territory of Antium, where they wandered about until
                    the townspeople sallied out and cut them off. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A similar overthrow was experienced, in the
                    region of Veii, by the Etruscans. So far were they from <pb n="p.153"/> pitying
                    a City that had been their neighbour for <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> close upon four hundred
                    years, and was now overwhelmed by an enemy never seen or heard of before, that
                    they chose that time to make incursions into the lands of the Romans; and laden
                    with spoils, even meditated an attack on Veii and its garrison, the last hope of
                    the Roman name. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman soldiers had seen
                    them, as they ranged through the fields and afterwards, gathering in a body,
                    drove the booty off before them, and could descry their camp, which was pitched
                    not far from Veii. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This made them at first to
                    compassionate themselves; then they were seized with resentment, which soon gave
                    way to rage: were even the Etruscans, whom they had saved from the Gauls by
                    incurring war themselves, to make sport of their calamities? <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They could hardly curb an impulse to assail them on the
                    instant; but being restrained by the centurion Quintus Caedicius, whom they had
                    chosen to be their commander, they postponed the affair till dark. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The only thing wanting was a leader like Camillus; in
                    all else the order followed was the same, and the same success was achieved.
                    Indeed, under the guidance of captives who had survived the nocturnal massacre,
                    they set out on the following night and came to another band of Etruscans, at
                    the salt-works, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Established according
                        to tradition, by King Ancus (I. xxxiii. 9), on the right bank of the Tiber,
                        not far from Ostia. </note> whom they surprised and defeated with even
                    greater carnage; and so, rejoicing in their double victory, returned to Veii. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome meanwhile the siege was for the most
                    part languishing and all was quiet on both sides, the Gauls being solely
                    concerned with preventing the escape of any enemy through their lines, when
                    suddenly a young Roman attracted the <pb n="p.155"/> wondering admiration of
                    fellow citizens and foes. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B.C. 390</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was an annual sacrifice to be made on
                    the Quirinal Hill by the family of the Fabii. To celebrate it Gaius Fabius
                    Dorsuo, in the Gabinian cincture, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        This was a mode of girding up the toga traditional in religious ceremonies.
                    </note> with the sacred vessels in his hands, descended from the Capitol, passed
                    out through the midst of the enemy's pickets, and regardless of any words or
                    threats, proceeded to the Quirinal, where he duly accomplished all the rites.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He then returned by the same way, with the
                    like resolute countenance and gait, in the full assurance of the favour of the
                    gods whose service not even the fear of death could cause him to neglect, and
                    rejoined his friends on the Capitol, leaving the Gauls dumbfounded by his
                    astonishing audacity, or perhaps even moved by religious awe, a sentiment to
                    which that race is far from indifferent. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Veii, all this while, they were gathering
                    from day to day, not courage merely, but strength as well. Not only were Romans
                    coming in from the country-side, —men who had been wanderers since the defeat,
                    or the capture of the City, —but volunteers were also pouring in from Latium,
                    that they might share in the spoils. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It seemed
                    therefore that the time was now ripe to return to their native City and wrest it
                    from the hands of the enemy; but their strong body lacked a head. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The place itself reminded men of Camillus, and there
                    were many of the soldiers who had fought successfully under his leadership and
                    auspices. Moreover, Caedicius declared that he would suffer neither god nor man
                    to put an end to his authority, but, remembering his station, would himself
                    demand the appointment of a general. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With the
                    consent of all they resolved <pb n="p.157"/> to send for Camillus from Ardea,
                    but not till the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        390</note> senate at Rome had been consulted; so modest were they in their
                    conduct of everything, preserving the proper distinctions even in their
                    well-nigh desperate case. It was necessary at enormous risk to pass the enemy's
                    outposts. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This an active youth named Pontius
                    Cominus undertook to do, and supporting himself on a strip of cork, floated down
                    the Tiber to the City. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Once there, he passed
                    by the shortest way from the bank up a cliff so steep that the enemy had
                    neglected to guard it, to the Capitol, and being brought before the magistrates
                    delivered to them the message from the army. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Then, on the senate's resolving that the <hi rend="italics">curiate</hi>
                    <hi rend="italics">comitia</hi> should recall Camillus from exile, and that,
                    even as the people commanded he should straightway be appointed dictator, and
                    the soldiers have the general they desired, the messenger returned by the same
                    route and came in haste to Veii; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> whence
                    envoys were despatched to Ardea for Camillus, and fetched him to Veii; or rather
                    —as I prefer to believe that he did not quit Ardea until he had learnt that the
                    law was passed, since he could not change his residence without the People's
                    command, nor take the auspices in the army till he had been appointed
                    dictator-the curiate law was passed and Camillus declared dictator, in his
                    absence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While this was going on at Veii, the Citadel
                    of Rome and the Capitol were in very great danger. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For the Gauls had noticed the tracks of a man, where the
                    messenger from Veii had got through, or perhaps had observed for themselves that
                    the cliff near the shrine of Carmentis <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > The mother of Evander, whose name appears in I. vii. 8 in the form
                        Carmenta. </note> afforded an easy ascent. So on a starlit night they first
                    sent <pb n="p.159"/> forward an unarmed man to try the way; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> then <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B.C. 390</note> handing up their weapons when there was a steep place, and
                    supporting themselves by their fellows or affording support in their turn, they
                    pulled one another up, as the ground required, and reached- the summit, in such
                    silence that not only the sentries but even the dogs —creatures easily troubled
                    by noises in the night —were not aroused. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But
                    they could not elude the vigilance of the geese, which, being sacred to Juno,
                    had, notwithstanding the dearth of provisions, not been killed. This was the
                    salvation of them all; for the geese with their gabbling and clapping of their
                    wings woke Marcus Manlius, —consul of three years before and a distinguished
                    soldier, —who, catching up his weapons and at the same time calling the rest to
                    arms, strode past his bewildered comrades to a Gaul who had already got a
                    foothold on the crest and dislodged him with a blow from the boss of his shield.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As he slipped and fell, he overturned
                    those who were next to him, and the others in alarm let go their weapons and
                    grasping the rocks to which they had been clinging, were slain by Manlius.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And by now the rest had come together and
                    were assailing the invaders with javelins and stones, and presently the whole
                    company lost their footing and were flung down headlong to destruction.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then after the din was hushed, the rest of
                    the night —so far as their excitement would permit, when even a past peril made
                    them nervous —was given up to sleep. At dawn the trumpet summoned the soldiers
                    to assemble before the tribunes. Good conduct and bad had both to be requited.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> First Manlius was praised for his courage
                    and presented with gifts, not only by <pb n="p.161"/> the tribunes of the
                    soldiers, but by agreement <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                        >B. C. 390</note> amongst the troops, who brought each half a pound of spelt
                    and a gill of wine to his house, which stood in the Citadel. It is a little
                    thing to tell, but the scarcity made it a great token of affection, since
                    everyone robbed himself of his own sustenance and bestowed what he had
                    subtracted from his physical necessities to do honour to one man. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Then the watchmen of the cliff which the enemy had
                    scaled without being discovered were called up. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> Quintus Sulpicius, the tribune, announced his intention to punish them all in
                    the military fashion; but deterred by the cries of the soldiers, who united in
                    throwing the blame upon a single sentinel, he spared the others. This man was
                    guilty beyond a doubt, and was flung from the rock with the approval of all.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> From that time the guards on both sides
                    were more alert: the Gauls, because it had been put about that messengers were
                    passing between Veii and Rome, the Romans, from their recollection of the peril
                    of the night. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But worse than all the evils of the blockade
                    and the war was the famine with which both armies were afflicted. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The Gauls suffered also from a pestilence, being
                    encamped between hills on low ground, parched and heated by the conflagration,
                    where the air was filled with ashes, as well as dust, whenever a breeze sprang
                    up. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> These annoyances were intolerable to a
                    race accustomed to damp and cold, and when, distressed by the suffocating heat,
                    they began to sicken of diseases that spread as though the victims had been
                    cattle, they were soon too slothful to bury their dead singly, and piling the
                    bodies up in promiscuous heaps, they burned them, <pb n="p.163"/> causing the
                    place to be known from that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B. C. 390</note> circumstance as the Gallic Pyres. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy tells us in xxii. xiv. 11, that
                        the <hi rend="italics">Busta Gallica</hi> were in the middle of the City,
                        but the exact site cannot be determined. </note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A truce was afterwards made with the Romans,
                    and the commanders allowed their soldiers to talk together. Since in these
                    conversations the Gauls used frequently to taunt their enemies with their
                    famished state, and call on them to yield to that necessity and surrender, the
                    Romans are said, in order to do away with this opinion, to have cast bread down
                    from the Capitol in many places, into the outposts of the enemy. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Yet at last they could neither dissemble their hunger
                    nor endure it any longer. The dictator was now holding a levy of his own at
                    Ardea, and having ordered the master of the horse, Lucius Valerius, to bring up
                    his army from Veii, was mustering and drilling a force with which he might cope
                    with the Gauls on equal terms. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But the army on
                    the Capitol was worn out with picket duty and mounting guard; and though they
                    had got the better of all human ills, yet was there one, and that was famine,
                    which nature would not suffer to be overcome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Day after day they looked out to see if any relief from the dictator was at
                    hand; but at last even hope, as well as food, beginning to fail them, and their
                    bodies growing almost too weak to sustain their armour when they went out on
                    picket duty, they declared that they must either surrender or ransom themselves,
                    on whatever conditions they could make; for the Gauls were hinting very plainly
                    that no great price would be required to induce them to raise the siege.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thereupon the senate met, and instructed
                    the tribunes of the soldiers to arrange the terms. Then, at a conference between
                    Quintus Sulpicius the tribune and the Gallic chieftain Brennus, the affair <pb
                        n="p.165"/> was settled, and a thousand pounds of gold was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> agreed on as
                    the price of a people that was destined presently to rule the nations.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The transaction was a foul disgrace in
                    itself, but an insult was added thereto: the weights brought by the Gauls were
                    dishonest, and on the tribune's objecting, the insolent Gaul added his sword to
                    the weight, and a saying intolerable to Roman ears was heard, —Woe to the
                    conquered! </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But neither gods nor men would suffer the
                    Romans to live ransomed. For, by some chance, before the infamous payment had
                    been consummated, and when the gold had not yet, owing to the dispute, been all
                    weighed out, the dictator appeared and commanded the gold to be cleared away and
                    the Gauls to leave. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They objected vehemently,
                    and insisted on the compact; but Camillus denied the validity of that compact
                    which, subsequently to his own appointment as dictator, an inferior magistrate
                    had made without his authorization, and warned them to prepare for battle.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> His own men he ordered to throw their
                    packs in a heap, make ready their weapons, and win their country back with iron
                    instead of gold; having before their eyes the temples of the gods, their wives
                    and their children, the soil of their native land, with the hideous marks of war
                    upon it, and all that religion called upon them to defend, recover, or avenge.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then drew up his line, as well as the
                    ground permitted, on the naturally uneven surface of the half-ruined City, and
                    saw to it that his soldiers had every advantage in choice of position and in
                    preparation which the art of war suggested. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The Gauls were taken aback; they armed, and, with more rage than judgment, <pb
                        n="p.167"/> charged the Romans. But now fortune had turned; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> now the
                    might of Heaven and human wisdom were engaged in the cause of Rome. Accordingly,
                    at the first shock the Gauls were routed with as little effort as they had
                    themselves put forth to conquer on the Allia. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    They afterwards fought a second, more regular engagement, eight miles out on the
                    Gabinian Way, where they had rallied from their flight, and again the
                    generalship and auspices of Camillus overcame them. Here the carnage was
                    universal; their camp was taken; and not a man survived to tell of the disaster.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The dictator, having recovered his country
                    from her enemies, returned in triumph to the city; and between the rough jests
                    uttered by the soldiers, was hailed in no unmeaning terms of praise as a Romulus
                    and Father of his Country and a second Founder of the City. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> His native City, which he had saved in war, he
                    then indubitably saved a second time, now that peace was won, by preventing the
                    migration to Veil: though the tribunes were more zealous for the plan than ever,
                    now that the City lay in ashes, and the plebs were of themselves more inclined
                    to favour it. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This was the reason of his not
                    resigning the dictatorship after his triumph, for the senate besought him not to
                    desert the state in its hour of uncertainty. <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> His first act, in conformity with his
                    scrupulous attention to religion, was to lay before the senate such matters as
                    pertained to the immortal gods, and to obtain the <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> passage of a decree that all shrines, in so far as they had
                    been in the enemy's possession, should be restored, their boundaries
                    established, and rites of purification celebrated, and that the duumvirs should
                        <pb n="p.169"/> search the Books <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >The Sybilline Books.</note> for the proper rites; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> that a covenant <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="marg">B.C. 390</note> of hospitality should be entered into by the
                    state with the people of Caere, because they had received the holy things of the
                    Roman People and its priests, and thanks to their good offices worship of the
                    immortal gods had not been interrupted; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> that
                    Capitoline Games should be held, because Jupiter Optimus Maximus had protected
                    his own abode and the Citadel of the Roman People in its time of danger; and
                    that Marcus Furius the dictator should to that end constitute a board consisting
                    of men who lived on the Capitol and the Citadel. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> A proposal was made, too, for propitiating the voice which was heard in the
                    night to foretell disaster before the Gallic War, and was disregarded, and a
                    temple was ordered to be built in the Nova Via to Aius Locutius. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The god of Utterance. This
                            <quote>temple</quote> is evidently the <quote>chapel</quote> spoken of
                        at chap. xxxii. § 6. </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The gold which had been carried away from the
                    Gauls and that which had been collected from other temples during the alarm and
                    carried into the shrine of Jupiter, since there was no clear recollection where
                    it ought to be returned, was all adjudged to be sacred and ordered to be
                    deposited under the throne of Jupiter. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Even
                    before this the scrupulousness of the citizens had been apparent in this
                    connexion, for when the gold in the public coffers was insufficient to make up
                    to the Gauls the stipulated sum, they had accepted what the matrons got
                    together, that they might not touch the sacred gold. For this a vote of thanks
                    was given to the matrons, and they were granted the honour of having eulogies
                    pronounced at their funerals, as in the case of the men. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> After these measures, which related to the gods and lay
                    within the competence of the senate, had been enacted, then, and only then,
                    heeding the importunity of the <pb n="p.171"/> tribunes, who were urging the
                    plebs unceasingly to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B. C.
                        390</note> quit their ruins and emigrate to a city ready to their hand at
                    Veii, Camillus went up into the assembly, attended by the entire senate, and
                    discoursed as follows: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "So painful to me, Quirites, are these
                    controversies with the tribunes of the plebs, that my most bitter exile knew no
                    other solace but this, all the time that I lived at Ardea, that I was far away
                    from these contentions. And they are likewise the cause that though you had a
                    thousand times recalled me by resolution of the senate and the people's vote, I
                    intended never to return. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Nor have I now been
                    induced to do so by any change in my desires, but by the alteration in your
                    fortunes. For the issue was this, that my countrymen should abide in their own
                    home, not that I, at any or all costs, should be with my countrymen. Even now I
                    would gladly stop and hold my peace, were not this too the quarrel of my
                    country; whom to fail while life endures is in other men disgraceful, but in
                    Camillus impious. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For why did we seek to win
                    her back, why rescue her, when besieged, from the hands of the enemy, if, now
                    that she is recovered, we voluntarily abandon her? And although, while the Gauls
                    were victorious and in possession of the entire City, the Capitol nevertheless
                    and the Citadel were held by the gods and men of Rome, shall we now, when the
                    Romans are victorious and the City is regained, desert even Citadel and Capitol?
                    Shall our prosperity make Rome more desolate than our adversity has done?
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Indeed, if we had no religious rites
                    established with the founding of the City and by tradition handed down, <pb
                        n="p.173"/> yet so manifest has at this time the divine purpose <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> been in the
                    affairs of Rome, that I for one should suppose it no longer possible for men to
                    neglect the worship of the gods. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For consider
                    these past few years in order, with their successes and reverses; you will find
                    that all things turned out well when we obeyed the gods, and ill when we spurned
                    them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First of all, the war with Veii. How
                    many years we fought, and with what painful exertion! And the end came not,
                    until, admonished by Heaven, we drew the water off from the Alban Lake.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What, I beseech you, of this strange
                    disaster that lately overwhelmed our City? Did it come before we disregarded the
                    voice from Heaven that announced the approach of the Gauls? before the law of
                    nations was violated by our envoys? before we, that ought to have punished their
                    fault, had passed it by, with the same indifference towards the gods? <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Therefore were we conquered, led captive, and put to
                    ransom; and suffered such punishments at the hands of gods and men as to be a
                    warning to all the world. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Adversity then
                    turned our thoughts upon religion. We fled for refuge to the Capitol and its
                    gods, to the seat of Jupiter Optimus Maximus; of our holy things, some, in the
                    ruin of our fortunes, we concealed in the earth, others we removed to
                    neighbouring cities out of sight of our enemies; in the worship of the gods,
                    albeit forsaken of gods and men, yet were we unceasing. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Therefore have they given us our native land again, and
                    victory, and our ancient renown in war that we had forfeited; and against our
                    enemies, who, blinded with greed, broke treaty and troth in the weighing of the
                    gold, have they turned dismay and rout and slaughter. </p>
                <pb n="p.175"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "As you consider these momentous effects <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> upon the
                    affairs of men, of serving the deity and of neglecting him, do you begin,
                    Quirites, to perceive how, though yet scarce clear of the wreckage of our former
                    guilt and calamity, we are headed towards a grievous sin? <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> We have a City founded with due observance of auspice and
                    augury; no corner of it is not permeated by ideas of religion and the gods; for
                    our annual sacrifices, the days are no more fixed than are the places where they
                    may be performed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Do you intend, Quirites, to
                    abandon all these gods, both of state and of family? How squares your conduct
                    with that of the noble young man Gaius Fabius in the recent siege, which the
                    enemy beheld with no less astonishment and admiration than yourselves, when he
                    descended from the Citadel through the missiles of the Gauls and offered the
                    annual sacrifice of the Fabian clan on the Quirinal Hill? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> What? Would you suffer no interruption, even in war, of
                    family rites, but desert the national worship and the gods of Rome in time of
                    peace? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Would you have the pontiffs and the
                    flamens less careful of the ceremonies of the state religion than a private
                    citizen has been of the anniversary of his clan? Perhaps someone may say that we
                    shall either do these things at Veii, or thence dispatch our priests to Rome to
                    do them; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> but of these courses neither can be
                    followed without violation of the sacred usages. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> For, not to enumerate all the kinds of rites and all the gods, is it possible
                    at the feast of Jupiter <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On the 15th
                        of November the senate held a stately banquet at which a couch was placed
                        for Jupiter, and Juno and Minerva occupied stools on either side of the god.
                    </note> that the couch should be spread elsewhere than in the Capitol? Why need
                    I speak of Vesta's eternal fires, and the image <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The image of Pallas (Palladium), fabled to have bee
                        brought to Italy by Aeneas. </note> which is preserved as a pledge of empire
                    in her temple? or of your sacred <pb n="p.177"/> shields, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See I. xx. 4, and note.</note> O Mars Gradivus and
                    Quirinus our Father? <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C.
                        390</note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All these holy things would you leave behind
                    on unconsecrated ground —things coeval with the City, and some more ancient than
                    its origin? </p>
                <p> "And mark what a difference between us and our forefathers! They handed down to
                    us certain rites to be solemnized on the Alban Mount and in Lavinium. But if we
                    scrupled to transfer sacred rites from hostile cities to ourselves in Rome, can
                    we shift them without sin from Rome to Veii, city of our enemies? <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> Recollect, I beg you, how often sacrifices are
                    renewed because some point of antique ritual has been, through carelessness or
                    accident, omitted. What was it, a while ago, after the portent of the Alban
                    Lake, that brought relief to the commonwealth —then in the throes of war with
                    Veii —if not a renewal of the sacred rites and auspices? <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> But, more than that, like men mindful of their old
                    religious fervour, we have both brought in foreign deities to Rome and
                    established new ones. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Queen Juno was lately
                    conveyed from Veii and enshrined on the Aventine, and how notable was that day,
                    for the zeal of the matrons and the throng! We have ordered a temple to be built
                    for Aius Locutius because of the voice from heaven, clearly heard in the Nova
                    Via. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> We have added Capitoline Games to the
                    other annual festivals, and by authority of the senate have established a new
                    college for this purpose. Was there any of these things we needed to have
                    undertaken, if we meant to retire from Rome along with the Gauls; if we remained
                    not voluntarily in the Capitol, through so many months of siege, but constrained
                    by fear of the enemy? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> We talk of sacred rites
                    and temples; <pb n="p.179"/> pray, what about the priests? Do you never think
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> what a
                    sacrilege you are about? The Vestals surely have but that one dwelling-place,
                    from which nothing ever caused them to remove but the capture of the City; the
                    Flamen Dialis may not lie for a single night outside the City, without sin.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Will you make these priests Veientine
                    instead of Roman? Shall thy Virgins forsake thee, Vesta, and the Flamen, as he
                    dwells abroad, bring, night after night, such guilt upon himself and the
                    republic? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> What about the other matters nearly
                    all of which <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy has in mind one
                        important exception: the centuriate comitia met outside the pomerium,
                        usually in the Campus Martius. </note> we transact, after taking auspices,
                    within the pomerium? To what oblivion and neglect do we consign them? <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> The curiate comitia which deals with the business of
                    war, the centuriate comitia, where you elect the consuls and military tribunes
                    —where can these be held, with due observance of the auspices, save in the
                    customary places? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Shall we transfer them to
                    Veii? Or shall the people, for the sake of the comitia assemble with enormous
                    inconvenience in this City, forsaken of god and man? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "'But,' you will say, 'while it is obvious
                    that everything will be polluted beyond all possibility of purification, yet the
                    situation itself compels us to leave a City which fires and falling buildings
                    have made a wilderness, and emigrate to Veii, where everything is untouched, nor
                    vex the helpless commons with building here.' <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But that this is rather a pretext than a true reason is, I think, apparent to
                    you, Quirites, without my saying so; for you remember how, before the coming of
                    the Gauls, when our roof-trees, public and private, were unharmed and our City
                    stood uninjured, that this same proposal was <pb n="p.181"/> urged, of migrating
                    to Veii. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Chap. xxiv. § 7.</note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And consider, tribunes, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 396</note> how wide is the difference
                    between my view and yours. You think that even if then it ought not to have been
                    done, yet now at any rate it ought; I on the contrary —and be not astonished at
                    this, till you have heard what my meaning is, —even if it had been right to
                    migrate then, with the City all intact, should not think it right to abandon
                    these ruins now. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For then our victory would
                    have been a reason for migrating to a captured city —a reason glorious to
                    ourselves and our posterity; but now such a removal is for us a wretched and
                    humiliating course, and a glory to the Gauls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    For we shall not seem to have left our country as victors, but to have lost it
                    as men vanquished. It will be thought that the rout on the Allia, the capture of
                    the City, the blockade of the Capitol, have compelled us to forsake our family
                    gods, and sentence ourselves to banishment and exile from that place which we
                    were powerless to defend. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Have Gauls then been
                    able to cast Rome down; and must Romans appear unable to have raised her up?
                    What remains, if they should presently come with fresh forces —for all agree
                    that their numbers are scarce to be believed, — and should wish to dwell in this
                    City which they have captured and you have abandoned, but that you should suffer
                    them? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What if not the Gauls but your ancient
                    foes the Volsci and Aequi should migrate to Rome? Should you like them to be
                    Romans, and yourselves Veientes? Or should you not prefer this to be your
                    wilderness, rather than the city of your enemies? For my part I do not see what
                    could be more abominable. Are you ready to stomach these outrages, these
                    infamies, because it <pb n="p.183"/> irks you to build? <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> If in all the City no house could <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> be put up better or bigger
                    than is the famous Hut of our Founder, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > The <hi rend="italics">casa Romuli</hi> stood on the Palatine, on the side
                        next the Circus Maximus, and a hut which went by this name was preserved and
                        venerated as late as Livy's own time. </note> would it not be better to live
                    in huts, as shepherds and rustics do, amongst our sacred monuments and our
                    household gods, than to go forth as a nation into exile? <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Our ancestors refugees and herdsmen, at a time when there
                    was nothing in this region but forests and marshes, built quickly a new City;
                    and are we loath, though Capitol and Citadel are untouched and the temples of
                    the gods are standing, to rebuild what has been destroyed by fire? And what each
                    would have done for himself, if his house had been burned, shall we refuse to do
                    together after this common conflagration? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Or suppose that by crime or chance a fire should break out at Veii, and
                        that the wind should spread the flames, as may easily happen, until they
                        consume a great part of the city; are we to quit it, and seek out Fidenae,
                        or Gabii, or any other town you like, and migrate thither? <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Have the soil of our native City and this land which we
                        call our mother so slight a hold on us? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Is
                        our love of country confined to buildings and rafters? And in truth I will
                        confess to you —though: like not to recall the wrong you did me —that as
                        often, during my absence, as I thought of my native place, all these objects
                        came into my mind: the hills and the fields and the Tiber and the region
                        familiar to my eyes, and this sky beneath which I had been born and reared.
                        And I wish these things may rather move you now with love, Quirites, to make
                        you abide in your own home, than afterwards, when you have left it, torment
                        you with vain regrets. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Not without cause
                        did gods and men select this <pb n="p.185"/> place for establishing our City
                        —with its healthful <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg"
                            >B.C. 390</note> hills; its convenient river, by which crops may be
                        floated down from the midland regions and foreign commodities brought up;
                        its sea, near enough for use, yet not exposing us, by too great propinquity,
                        to peril from foreign fleets; a situation in the heart of Italy —a spot, in
                        short, of a nature uniquely adapted for the expansion of a city. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> This is proved by the very greatness of so new a
                        place. It is now, Quirites, in its three hundred and sixty-fifth year.
                        Amongst all these ancient nations you have for so long a time been waging
                        wars; and all this while — to say nothing of single cities —neither the
                        Volsci joined with the Aequi, and all their powerful towns, nor all Etruria,
                        with its enormous strength on land and water, and its occupancy of the
                        entire breadth of Italy from sea to sea, has been a match for you in war.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Since this is so, what a plague is the
                        reason why you that have experienced these things should experiment with
                        others? Granting that your valour may go elsewhere, yet surely the fortune
                        of this place could not be taken along! <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Here is the Capitol, where men were told, when of old they discovered there
                        a human head, that in that place should be the head of the world and the
                        seat of empire; here, when the Capitol was being cleared with augural rites,
                        Juvent as and Terminus, to the vast joy of your fathers, refused to be
                        removed; here are Vesta's fires, here the shields that were sent down from
                        heaven, here are all the gods propitious, if you remain. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The speech of Camillus is said to have moved
                    them, particularly where he touched upon religion; but the doubtful issue was
                    resolved by a word <pb n="p.187"/> that was let fall in the nick of time. It was
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="marg">B.C. 390</note> while
                    the senate, a little later, was deliberating about these matters in the Curia
                    Hostilia; some cohorts returning from guard-duty were marching through the
                    Forum, and as they came to the Comitium a centurion cried out,
                        <quote>Standard-bearer, fix your ensign; here will be our best place to
                        remain.</quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hearing this sentence the senators came out
                    from the Curia and shouted their acceptance of the omen, and the commons
                    gathering round them signified approval. The bill was then rejected, and people
                    began in a random fashion to rebuild the City. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The state supplied tiles, and granted everybody the right to quarry stone and to
                    hew timber where he liked, after giving security for the completion of the
                    structures within that year. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In their haste
                    men were careless about making straight the streets, and paying no attention to
                    their own and others' rights, built on the vacant spaces. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> This is the reason that the ancient sewers, which were at
                    first conducted through the public ways, at present frequently run under private
                    dwellings, and the appearance of the City is like one where the ground has been
                    appropriated rather than divided. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
