<?xml version="1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Letters to Brutus</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
        <editor role="editor" n="Shuckburgh">Evelyn Shuckburgh</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:NEH">NEH</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Cicero</author>
            <title>The Letters of Cicero; the whole extant correspondence in chronological order, in
              four volumes</title><idno type="OCLC">7046222</idno>
            <editor role="editor">Evelyn S. Shuckburgh</editor>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>George Bell and Sons</publisher>
              <date>1908-1909</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <bibl>
          
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim="." unit="volume"/>
        <refState unit="page"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="year"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="volume"/>
        <refState unit="year"/>
        <refState unit="letter"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="la">Latin </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
        <language ident="fr">French </language>
        <language ident="de">German </language>
        <language ident="it">Italian </language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
                        <change>
                                <date>9 August 1999</date>
                                <respStmt>
                                        <name>David Smith</name>
                                        <resp>ed.</resp>
                                </respStmt>
                                <item> 
$Log: cic.shuck_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.6  2013-09-13 11:20:02  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.4  2012-01-05 16:08:00  lcerrato
fixed A IV 10 where much of the letter had been put into a footnote

Revision 1.3  2010-07-09 14:48:01  rsingh04
fixed CVS log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:12 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection
                                        
Revision 1.26 2009/09/22 16:21:36 rsingh04 
fixed references to Cic. Ver. 

Revision 1.25 2009/09/18 20:18:24 lcerrato
renumbered letters which were marked as errata in print
version intro pages (we had duplicates so certain letters
were not visible) 

Revision 1.24 2009/07/02 20:20:11 lcerrato
fixed references to Aristot. Pol. up through book 4 

Revision 1.23 2009/06/24 16:52:01 student 
fixed Ter. Hec. and Ph. references - zr 

Revision 1.22 2009/06/24 15:15:03 student
fixed Ter. Hau. references - zr 

Revision 1.21 2009/06/24 02:59:14 student 
fixed Ter. Eu. references - zr 

Revision 1.20 2009/06/24 01:16:40 student 
fixed Ter. An. references -  zr 

Revision 1.19 2009/06/23 22:08:31 student 
fixed Ter. Ad. references - zr 

Revision 1.18 2009/06/23 13:36:54 student
fixed Pl. Trin. references - zr 

Revision 1.17 2009/06/22 17:04:28 student 
fixed Pl. Ps. references - zr 

Revision 1.16 2009/06/03 20:04:28 lcerrato 
fixed bad bibls 

Revision 1.15 2009/05/19 20:52:13 lcerrato 
fixed bad bibls 

Revision 1.14 2008/05/09 15:34:23 lcerrato 
fixed some table cells 

Revision 1.13 2008/05/08 18:59:24 lcerrato 
added table found in front of volume 4 

Revision 1.12 2008/05/01 19:35:51 rsingh04
changed text=Q. Cic. Pet. back to text=Pet. 

Revision 1.11 2008/05/01 16:17:41 rsingh04 
moved head tags at the beginning of each year to a margin note tag 

Revision 1.10 2008/05/01 15:57:09 lcerrato 
added info on the source of the text, and corrected OCLC number 

Revision 1.9 2008/05/01 14:54:24 rsingh04 
fixed chunking schemes 

Revision 1.8 2008/04/30 20:40:27 lcerrato 
fixed conflicts with some letter names which were causing the letters not to appear

Revision 1.7 2008/04/30 19:04:01 rsingh04 
removed bad chunking schemes and updated others. moved all of the intros before a year or appendix into an epigraph before the first letter in that year/appendix 

Revision 1.6 2008/04/29 20:54:28 rsingh04 
structural fixes so that it actually chunks and displays the texts. have not yet fixed collisions
(where multiple chunks have the same type and value. have
not yet tidied up what is displayed either. need to work on
getting the translations to map with the latin version
                                        
Revision 1.5 2006/05/05 17:38:11 packel 
fixed date tags
                                        
Revision 1.4 2006/02/10 20:50:20 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.3 2005/10/18 15:44:36 lcerrato
fixed typo fam. 11.28 "not" missing per Latin and user
report 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:20 packel 
removed stray item tags 

Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:35 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.15 2005/03/30 17:19:13 mimno 
P4 version                                        

Revision 1.14 2004/05/24 14:08:30 amahoney 
fix some broken dates, digits outside tags 

Revision 1.13 2002/06/10 14:12:35 amahoney 
mark refrences to Plautus 

Revision 1.12 2001/02/05 18:23:49 gcrane 
typo 

Revision 1.11 2000/09/25 19:30:47 amahoney 
fix date values (negative for BC, add values where
omitted) 

Revision 1.10 2000/09/13 13:39:08 gcrane 
typo
                                        
Revision 1.9 2000/03/05 01:16:07 dasmith 
Allow proper chunking of introductions. Broke introductions of vols. 3
and 4 into sections. 

Revision 1.8 2000/03/04 20:34:12 dasmith 
Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.7 2000/03/01 22:52:05 dasmith 
Fixed typo in MILESTONE tag name. 

Revision 1.6 2000/03/01 22:50:51 dasmith 
Added volume milestones. Took volume numbers out of PBs. Removed repeated
"Cicero's Letters" headers. 

Revision 1.5 2000/02/25 05:09:32 dasmith 
Not entirely satisfied, but decided just to chunk on
parts for front matter. 

Revision 1.4 2000/02/22 18:16:49 amahoney 
fix some broken bibl refs 

Revision 1.3 2000/01/31 22:37:30 dasmith 
Tweaks to refsDecl to get chunking right.
                                        
Revision 1.2 1999/08/11 14:19:55 dasmith 
Normalized appendix
names. 

Revision 1.1 1999/08/09 22:19:17 dasmith 
Combined into single file. 
                                </item>
                        </change>
                <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite file and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=2:letter=1" type="letter" xml:id="s833">
        <head>DCCCXXXIII (BRUT. II, 1)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO MARCUS IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (MARCH-APRIL)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> AT the time of my writing this it is thought that the decisive hour has arrived. For
          melancholy despatches and messages are arriving about our friend Decimus Brutus. For my
          part I am not excessively alarmed by them, for I cannot possibly distrust such armies and
          leaders as we now have. Nor do I agree with the majority of people: for I do not think ill
          of the loyalty of the consuls, which has been the subject of great suspicion. In certain
          particulars I do find them wanting in prudence and promptitude. If they had displayed
          those qualities we should long ago have recovered the constitution. For you are not
          ignorant of the importance of times and seasons in public affairs, and what a difference
          it makes whether the same thing is settled, undertaken, carried out before or after a
          particular period. If all the decrees expressed in severe language during this civil
          disturbance had been passed on the day on which I spoke in their favour, and had not been
          postponed from day to day, or not been delayed and put off from the moment that their
          execution was undertaken, we should not now be at war. I have made good, Brutus, every
          duty to the state, to which a man was bound, who occupied the station in which I have been
          placed by the judgment of the senate and people. And I am not speaking now of those duties
          which alone, of course, can be positively demanded of every human being—good faith,
          vigilance, patriotism. Such duties there is no one who is not bound to make good. But I
          think that a man who speaks among the leading members of the senate is bound to display
          wisdom also. And since I have involved myself in the heavy responsibility of taking the
          helm of state, I should think myself no less deserving of reproach, if it was against its
          true interests that I advised the senate, than if I did so with insincerity. All things
          actually <pb n="204"/> transacted, or which are in the Course of being transacted, I know
          are carefully written out for your benefit. But there is one thing I should like you to
          learn from me—that my heart is at the seat of war, and seeks no means of retreat, unless
          it chance that the interest of the state compels me to do so. The feelings of the
          majority, however, look to you and Cassius. wherefore, my dear Brutus, prepare yourself to
          believe that, if at this time a success is achieved, you will have to reform the
          constitution; if a reverse is sustained, your task will be its restoration. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=2:letter=3" type="letter" xml:id="s834">
        <head>DCCCXXXIV (BRUT. II, 3)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>DYRRACHIUM, I APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I am anxiously expecting the letter which you wrote after you received the news of my
          movements and of the death of Trebonius. <note n="1" anchored="true">The murder of
            Trebonius by <foreign xml:lang="la">Dolabella</foreign>. See pp.189, 210. </note> For I
          feel certain that you will expound your plan of action. By a shocking crime we have at
          once lost a most loyal citizen and have been driven from the possession of a province, the
          recovery of which is easy. But its subsequent recovery will not relieve the scandal and
          crime. Antonius <note n="2" anchored="true">Gaius Antonius, to whom his brother had caused
            the senate to transfer the province of Macedonia from himself, having previously
            transferred it from M. <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>, who had been nominated
            by Caesar. <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> had seized him and was keeping him
            prisoner. </note> is still in my camp; but, on my honour, I am much affected by the
          man's entreaties, and I fear a violent outbreak in some quarter may carry him off. I am
          really distracted with indecision. But if I knew your opinion, I should cease to be
          anxious: for I should be persuaded that it was the best thing to be done. Wherefore at the
          earliest possible moment let me know what your opinion is. Our friend Cassius holds Syria
          and the legions stationed in it, having indeed been actually invited <pb n="205"/> to come
          by Murcus, Marcius, and the army itself. I have written to my sister Tertia and my mother,
          not to publish this most admirable and fortunate achievement of Cassius before they knew
          what your advice was and you thought it right. I have read two of your speeches, one
          delivered on the 1st of January, the other against Calenus. You are, of course, waiting
          for my praise of them at this time of day! I cannot decide whether it is your courage or
          your genius that is the more admirably displayed in these pamphlets. I quite agree in
          their having even the title of Philippics by which you jestingly described them in one of
          your letters. <note n="1" anchored="true">The letter containing this jest of Cicero's is
            lost. The title Philippics was the current one by the time of Iuvenal at any rate (x.
            125), and Plutarch (Cic. 24) says that Cicero himself placed that title on the copies.
            Against this the authority of Aulus Gellius (vii. II; xiii. I, 21), who calls them
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Orationes Antonianae</foreign>, is not worth much. </note>
          <milestone unit="para"/>The two things which I want are money and more men. The latter—the
          sending some part of the soldiers now in Italy to me—you can accomplish either by a secret
          arrangement with Pansa or by bringing the matter before the senate. The former can be got
          from the senate direct. This is still more necessary, and not more so for my army than for
          that of the other commanders. This makes me the more regret that we have lost Asia: which
          I am told is being so harassed by Dolabella that his murder of Trebonius no longer appears
          the most cruel thing he has done. Antistius Vetus, <note n="2" anchored="true">Vetus
            apparently brought the money sent by Appuleius the quaestor from Asia. See pp.190, 224.
          </note> however, has come to my aid with money. Your son Cicero is giving me such ion by
          his industry, endurance, hard work, and high courage, in short, by every kind of service,
          that he seems to me never to forget for a moment whose son he is. Therefore, as I cannot
          by any possibility think more highly than I already do of one who is the dearest object of
          your affection, pay my sagacity the compliment of believing that he will not have to trade
          upon your reputation for the attainment of the same offices as his father held before him.
            <milestone unit="para"/>1 April, Dyrrachium. <pb n="206"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=2:letter=2" type="letter" xml:id="s836">
        <head>DCCCXXXVI (BRUT. II, 2)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO MARCUS IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 11 APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> YOU have had the opportunity of learning Plancus's splendid loyalty to the Republic, his
          legions, auxiliaries, and forces from his own letter, a copy of which I think has been
          sent to you. The fickleness and inconstancy of your relative Lepidus, who, next to his own
          brother, <note n="2" anchored="true">L. Aemilius Paullus, who was afterwards put on the
            proscription lists by the triumvirs with at any rate the consent of his brother. </note>
          holds his relations by marriage <note n="3" anchored="true">Lepidus was married to
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Iunia</foreign>, half-sister to <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus;</foreign> Cassius to <foreign xml:lang="la">Tertia</foreign>, her sister.
          </note> as his deadliest foes, and his feelings perpetually hostile to the constitution, I
          think you have clearly perceived from the letters of your family. As for me, I am
          restlessly waiting for news. The decisive hour is upon us: for our whole hope depends on
          relieving Decimus Brutus, for whom I am greatly alarmed. Here in Rome I have my tribune
          Titius. Cicero wishes to make Plancus look upon it as unimportant. It probably, however,
          contributed to confirm his intention of joining Antony, as he eventually did. <pb n="209"
          /> hands full with that madman Servilius. <note n="1" anchored="true">See p.207. </note> I
          have endured him longer than is consistent with my position, but I have done so for the
          sake of the Republic, for fear of giving unprincipled citizens some one—who, lunatic as he
          is, is yet a man of rank-round whom to rally. They are doing so none the less, and I do
          not think that he is a man who ought to be wholly alienated from the Republic. But I have
          come to the end of my tolerance of him. For he has begun giving himself such airs, that he
          regards no one as free. In the case of Plancus, however, he flamed up with extraordinary
          anger, and for two days maintained so fierce a controversy with me, and was so crushed by
          me, that I hope I have permanently brought him to a more reasonable frame of mind. In the
          midst of this controversy too, on the 9th of April, a letter was handed to me in the
          senate from our friend Lentulus, <note n="2" anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Quaestor</foreign> of Trebonius in Asia. See pp.272-280. </note>
          telling me about Cassius, about his legions, and about Syria. I immediately read it aloud,
          whereupon Servilius and several besides looked somewhat small. For there are a good many
          distinguished men who cherish the most disloyal sentiments: but what annoyed Servilius
          most bitterly was that the senate agreed to my motion about Plancus. It is a portentous
          thing in the Republic, but to what end... <note n="3" anchored="true">The rest of the
            letter has been lost. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=2:letter=4" type="letter" xml:id="s837">
        <head>DCCCXXXVII (BRUT. II, 4)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (AT DYRRACHIUM)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 12 APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> AFTER I had given Scaptius a letter for you on the morning of the 11th of April, I
          received one from you in the evening of the same day, dated from Dyracchium on the 1st of
          April. Accordingly, on the morning of the 12th, having been informed by Scaptius that the
          men to whom I had <pb n="210"/> given the letter the day before had not started and were
          going at once, I have dashed off this brief note in the midst of the turmoil of my morning
          levée. I am delighted with the news about Cassius, and I congratulate the Republic, and
          also myself, for having proposed in the senate, in spite of Pansa's opposition and anger,
          that Cassius should make war upon Dolabella. <note n="1" anchored="true">Trebonius, who
            had gone as governor of Asia soon after the murder of Caesar, was avowedly collecting
            troops and money and fortifying towns with a view of supporting the tyrannicides. When
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Dolabella</foreign> arrived at Smyrna on his way to Syria he
            was still <foreign xml:lang="la">consul</foreign>, but Trebonius declined to admit him
            there or at Pergamus. <foreign xml:lang="la">Dolabella</foreign> went on his way to
            Ephesus, followed by a body of men whom Trebonius sent to watch him. He, however, laid a
            trap for them, captured or killed them, and, hurrying back to Smyrna, surprised and
            captured Trebonius, who according to one story was at once put to death, and according
            to another was tortured for two days first. On news of this reaching Rome, <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Dolabella</foreign> was on the motion of Cicero declared a <foreign
              xml:lang="la">hostis</foreign>, and Cassius was authorized to wage war against him
              (<bibl n="Cic. Phil. 11.29">Phil. 11.29</bibl>, sq.; <bibl n="TLG551.17 3.26">Appian,
              B.C. 3.26</bibl>). </note> And indeed I boldly maintained that he was already engaged
          in that war without any decree of ours. About you also I said on that occasion what I
          thought ought to be said. This speech <note n="2" anchored="true">The eleventh Philippic.
          </note> shall be transmitted to you, since I perceive that you like my "Philippics." You
          ask my advice as to Gaius Antonius: my opinion is that he should be kept under arrest till
          we know the fate of Decimus Brutus. From the letter you addressed to me it appears that
          Dolabella is harassing Asia and behaving in a most abominable manner there. You have
          mentioned also to several people that Dolabella has been prevented from landing by the
          Rhodians. But if he has approached Rhodes, I think he must have abandoned Asia. If that is
          so, I think you should stay where you are. But if he once gets a hold of that province,
          believe me it will not be right for you to do so, but I think you will have to go to Asia
          to attack him. As to your saying that you are in want of two necessary things-money and
          more men—it is difficult to see what to suggest. For I can't think of any resources upon
          which you can draw, except those which the senate has assigned to you by its decree—that
          you should raise loans from the cities. As to more men also, I do not see what can
          possibly be done. For so far from Pansa <pb n="211"/> sparing you any of his own army or
          levy, he is even annoyed that so many are going to you as volunteers: because, as I
          believe, he thinks that he cannot have too great a force; but, as many suspect, because he
          doesn't wish you to be too strong either. But this is a suspicion which I do not share.
          You say in your letter that you have written to Tertia and your mother not to disclose the
          achievements of Cassius until I think it right. <note n="1" anchored="true">See p.205.
          </note> I understand your motive to be a fear lest the feelings of Caesar's party—as that
          party is still called-should be violently affected. But before your letter was received,
          the facts had been heard and were quite public property. Your letter-carriers also had
          brought letters to many of your intimate friends. Therefore there is no need to suppress
          the truth, especially as it is impossible to do so. Besides, even if it had been possible,
          I should have thought that it should be spread broadcast rather than be kept concealed. As
          to my son, if he has all the good in him which you describe, I am of course as delighted
          as I am bound to be, and if you exaggerate it from affection for him, the mere fact of
          your being attached to him rejoices me more than I can say. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=2:letter=5" type="letter" xml:id="s839">
        <head>DCCCXXXIX (BRUT. II, 5)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (AT DYRRACHIUM)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 16 APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I BELIEVE that your friends—to not one of whom do I yield in affection to you—have
          written to tell you what despatches were read in the senate on the 13th of April from you,
          and at the same time from Antony. But though there was no need for us all to repeat the
          same story, yet it is necessary that I should write and tell you my feeling, deliberate
          opinion, and sentiments as to the nature of this war generally. My object, Brutus, in
          imperial politics has always been the same as your own: my policy in certain points-not in
          all-has perhaps been somewhat more drastic. You know that it was always my opinion that
          the Republic should be delivered not only from a tyrant but from a tyranny also. <note
            n="1" anchored="true">That is, that Antony should have shared the fate of Caesar. See
            pp.174, 214, etc. </note> You took a more indulgent view-to <pb n="214"/> your own
          undying honour, no doubt. But which was the better course we have felt to our bitter
          sorrow, and are still feeling to our grave peril. More recently you have directed all your
          efforts to secure peace—which could not be brought about by mere words—I to secure
          liberty, which is impossible without peace. <note n="1" anchored="true">Cicero puts the
            converse in <bibl n="Cic. Phil. 2.113">Phil. 2.113</bibl>, when he says that "peace is
            liberty without war," pax <foreign xml:lang="la">est tranquilla libertas</foreign>.
          </note> But my view was that peace itself could be brought about by war and arms. There
          was no want of enthusiasts who were eager to fight, but we checked their enthusiasm and
          damped their ardour. And so it had come to such a pass that, had not some god inspired
          Caesar Octavianus with that resolution, we must necessarily have fallen under the power of
          Marcus Antonius, the most abandoned and depraved of men, with whom you see at this very
          moment in what a desperate contest we are engaged. Now that, of course, would never have
          occurred if Antony had not been spared at that time. <note n="2" anchored="true">That is,
            when Caesar was murdered. Cicero still labours under the delusion that the revolution
            all depended on one man. If Antony had been murdered on the Ides of March, were there no
            others ready to play his part, and still more ably? Augustus is the best answer. It is
            well to observe how little mere assassination has ever been able to effect in political
            movements. </note> But I pass over these reflexions: for the deed which you
          performed-ever memorable and all but divine-disarms all criticism, for it is one which can
          never be even praised in terms adequate to its merit. <milestone unit="para"/>You lately
          came to the front again with a look of stern resolve. In a brief time you collected by
          your unaided exertions an army, forces, sufficient legions. Great heavens! What a message,
          what a despatch! <note n="3" anchored="true">The despatch in which <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus</foreign> announced that he had taken possession of Macedonia, and was
            beleaguering Gaius Antonius in <foreign xml:lang="la">Apollonia</foreign> (see <bibl
              n="Cic. Phil. 10.26">Phil. 10.26</bibl>). A second despatch announced his capture.
          </note> What exultation was there in the senate, what an outburst of cheerfulness in the
          city! I never saw anything praised with such complete unanimity. There was some anxiety
          about the remnants of Antony's forces, whom you had deprived for the most part of his
          cavalry and legions. But that was happily relieved. For your next despatch, which was read
          in the senate, clearly sets forth the excellence both of com <pb n="215"/> mander and
          soldiers, and the good service done by your staff-among others, by my son. <note n="1"
            anchored="true">Young Cicero is said to have defeated Gaius Antonius in an engagement at
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Byllis</foreign>, near <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Apollonia</foreign> (<bibl n="Plut. Brut. 26">Plutarch, Brut. 26</bibl>). </note> And
          if your friends here had thought it right that a motion should be brought before the
          senate in consequence of its despatch, and had it not come at a time of great confusion,
          just after the departure of the consul Pansa, a regular vote of thanks and one due to the
          immortal gods would have been passed. <milestone unit="para"/>Lo and behold, on the 13th
          of April, early in the morning comes Pilius Celer in hot haste—what a man, good heavens!
          How trustworthy and consistent! What an honest politician! He brings two letters, one in
          your name, a second in that of Antony. He hands them to the tribune Sevilius. Sevilius
          passed them on to Cornutus. <note n="2" anchored="true">Who was praetor <foreign
              xml:lang="la">urbanus</foreign> (p.207), and therefore presided in the senate in the
            absence of the consuls. </note> They are read in the senate. "ANTONIUS PROCONSUL !
          "-There was as much surprise expressed as though the words read had been "DOLABELLA
          IMPERATOR"; from whom indeed letter-carriers have arrived, but no one of the position of
          Pilius to venture to produce a despatch and to hand it to the magistrates. <note n="3"
            anchored="true">The province of Macedonia had been assigned during Caesar's life to
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>, probably by a <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >lex</foreign>. After his death Antony induced the senate to nominate himself (<bibl
              n="TLG551.17 3.24">App. B.C. 3.24</bibl>). Later on in <date when="-0044">B.C.
              44</date>, by a <foreign xml:lang="la">lex</foreign> proposed by a tribune, Cisalpine
            Gaul was transferred to Antony (App. 3.30). Macedonia was therefore vacant, and a
              <foreign xml:lang="la">sortitio</foreign> held in the senate on the 28th of November
            gave it to Gaius Antonius (<bibl n="Cic. Phil. 3.26">Phil. 3.26</bibl>). As a matter of
            fact, however, the outgoing proconsul Q. Hortensius had handed over his province and
            army to <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> (Plut Brut. 25), and the senate, now
            under Cicero's influence, would only acknowledge <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>
            as proconsul. For <foreign xml:lang="la">Dolabella</foreign>, see p.210. </note> Your
          despatch is read. It was short indeed, but very indulgent in its reference to Antonius.
          The senate was greatly astonished. And I could not see my way clearly as to what I ought
          to do. Was I to declare it a forgery? What if you had acknowledged it? Was I to assert its
          genuineness? That will be a reflexion on your official position. So I let that day pass
          without saying anything. But next day, when there had begun to be much talk about it, and
          Pilius had made himself offensively conspicuous, the first step was after all taken by me.
          I said a great deal about "the proconsul" Antonius. Sestius backed me up. <pb n="216"/>
          Afterwards, in private conversation with me, he dwelt on the danger he inferred for his
          own son and mine if they bore arms against "a proconsul." You know the sort of man he is.
          However, he did not shrink from supporting the contention. <note n="1" anchored="true"
            >That is, the contention (<foreign xml:lang="la">causa</foreign>) that M. <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> was the legal proconsul in Macedonia. </note> Others
          also spoke. Our friend Labeo, for instance, remarked that there was neither any seal of
          yours on the despatch, nor any date affixed, and that you had not written to your friends,
          as was your custom. <note n="2" anchored="true">That is, that the bearer of the public
            despatch brought no private letters at the same time, as we have seen was the almost
            invariable custom. For as there was no postal services, such messengers were always used
            for this purpose. It was a good argument against the genuineness of the letter. </note>
          By this he meant to argue that the despatch was a forgery, and, if you would know the
          truth, he was thought to be convincing. <milestone unit="para"/>Now, Brutus, you must take
          into consideration the whole question of the war. I notice that you take pleasure in
          lenient measures, and think that the most advantageous line to take. It is an admirable
          sentiment: but it is for other circumstances and other times that a place for clemency
          generally is and ought to be reserved. As things are now, Brutus, what is actually being
          done? The hope of the needy and the ruined is the plunder of the temples of the immortal
          gods; and what depends upon the issue of this war is neither more nor less than our bare
          existence. Who is it that we are sparing, or what is our object? Are we then consulting
          for the interests of those, whose victory means that not a trace of us will be left? For
          what difference is there between Dolabella and any one of the three Antonies? If we spare
          any of the latter, we have been harsh in the case of Dolabella. That the senate and Roman
          people take this view is partly the result of the mere facts of the case, but for the most
          part has been brought about by my advice and influence. If you disapprove this policy, I
          will speak up for your opinion, but I shall not abandon my own. From you men expect
          neither weakness nor cruelty. An obvious mean between these is that you should be stern to
          the leaders, placable to the soldiers. I should like my son, my dear Brutus, to be as much
          as possible by your side <pb n="217"/> He will find no better school of virtue than the
          contemplation and imitation of you. <milestone unit="para"/>16 April. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=2.3-6" type="letter" xml:id="s840">
        <head>DCCCXL (BRUT. I, 2, §§ 3-6)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (AT DYRRACHIUM)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 17 APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I rejoice that you have found the army and cavalry well affected to you. About
          Dolabella, as you remark, you will inform me' if you hear any news. In regard to this, I
          am pleased to think that I foresaw how independent your judgment would be as to making war
          on Dolabella. That, as I saw clearly at the time, was of great importance to the state,
          and, as I now am of opinion, of great importance to your own position. <milestone
            unit="para"/>You say in your letter that I have not hurried myself <note n="1"
            anchored="true">Me <foreign xml:lang="la">maximo otio egisse</foreign>. I doubt the
            soundness of the text, and the meaning of it as it stands. Whatever compliments Cicero
            may deserve, mildness in regard to the Antonies can scarcely he one of them. </note> at
          all in making attacks on the Antonies; and you go on to commend me for it. I have no doubt
          that you think so; but I can in no sense admit the justice of the distinction you draw,
          when you say that more vigour should be used in preventing civil wars, than in wreaking
          vengeance upon the vanquished. I strongly differ from you, Brutus, and I do not admit your
          clemency doctrine. A salutary sternness is superior to the empty show of clemency. But if
          we choose the rôle of clemency we shall never have any lack of civil wars. However, that
          is more your concern than mine. For myself I can say, like the father in the Trinummus of
          Plautus, <note n="2" anchored="true">
            <bibl n="Pl. Trin. 2.2">Plaut. Trin. ii. 2, 42.</bibl>
          </note>
          <quote>My time is all but past: 'tis you this most concerns.</quote>
          <milestone unit="para"/>You will be crushed, believe me, Brutus, unless you take <pb
            n="218"/> proper precautions. For you won't always have the same people, nor the same
          senate, nor the same leader of the senate. Regard these words as uttered by the oracle of
          the Pythian Apollo. Nothing can be truer. <milestone unit="para"/>17 April. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=3.1-3" type="letter" xml:id="s841">
        <head>DCCCXLI (BRUT. I, 3, §§ 1-3)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (AT DYRRACHIUM)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 21 APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> OUR cause seems in a better position: for I feel sure that you have had letters telling
          you what has happened. <note n="1" anchored="true">The victory of Forum <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Gallorum</foreign> See p.211 sq. </note> The consuls have shewn
          themselves to be the sort of men I have often described them in my letters. In the
          youthful Caesar indeed there is a surprising natural strain of virtue. Pray heaven we may
          govern him in the flush of honours and popularity as easily as we have held him up to this
          time I That is certainly a more difficult thing, but nevertheless I have no mistrust. For
          the young man has been convinced, and chiefly by my arguments, that our safety is his
          work, and that at least, if he had not diverted Antony from the city, all would have been
          lost. <note n="2" anchored="true">Cicero argues that Octavian's consciousness of having
            done the loyalists a good service will attach him the more to them. He will be unwilling
            to forfeit the good opinion he has earned. He little knew Octavian and his secret
            purposes. </note> Three or four days indeed before this glorious news, the city, struck
          by a sudden panic, <note n="3" anchored="true">This appears to have been caused by the
            action of the praetor Ventidius Bassus, who enrolled two legions of veterans, and was
            supposed to be coming to Rome to seize Cicero and the leading opponents of Antony. He,
            however, marched to <foreign xml:lang="la">Ariminum</foreign>, and succeeded in joining
            Antony after the battle by a splendid march across country to <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Vado</foreign> (<bibl n="TLG551.17 3.66">Appian, B.C. 3.66</bibl>). </note> was for
          pouring out with wives and children to seek you. The same city on the 20th of April, with
          its fears all dispelled, would rather that you came here than go to you. On that day in
          very truth I reaped the most abundant <pb n="219"/> harvest of my great labours and my
          many sleepless nights—that is, at least, if there is a harvest in genuine and
          well-grounded glory. For I was surrounded by a concourse of people as great as our city
          can contain, by whom I was escorted to the Capitol and placed upon the rostra <note n="1"
            anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign> of course was not on the
            Capitol, and this has been put forward as an argument against the genuineness of the
            letter. I think Cicero may be putting the story shortly. The procession first went to
            the Capitol to offer thanks to Iupiter, and then came down to the forum to be addressed
            from the <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign>. </note> amidst the loudest cheers and
          applause. I have no vanity in me—and indeed I ought to have none: yet after all a
          unanimous feeling of all orders, thanks, and congratulations do move my heart, because it
          is a thing to be proud of that in the hour of the people's preservation I should be the
          people's hero. But these things I would rather you heard from others. Pray inform me of
          your own doings and plans with the greatest exactness; and do be careful that your
          generosity does not bear the appearance of weakness. <note n="2" anchored="true">That is,
            in sparing Gaius Antonius. See p.215. </note> This is the sentiment of the senate, and
          of the people, that no enemies ever more richly deserved condign punishment than those
          citizens who have taken up arms against their country in this war. Indeed in every speech
          I make in the senate I call for vengeance upon them and attack them amidst the applause of
          all loyal citizens. What your view of this is I must leave you to judge for yourself: my
          opinion is that all three brothers stand on one and the same ground. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=3.4" type="letter" xml:id="s843">
        <head>DCCCXLIII (BRUT. 1, 3, § 4)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (AT DYRRACHIUM)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 27 APRIL</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> WE have lost two consuls-good men enough; yes, at any rate good men. As for Hirtius, he
          fell in the moment of <pb n="221"/> victory, <note n="1" anchored="true">In storming
            Antony's camp a week after the battle of Forum <foreign xml:lang="la">Gallorum</foreign>
            (21st April). </note> having also won a great battle only a few days before. For Pansa
          had retreated, after receiving wounds which put him out of action. <note n="2"
            anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Pansa</foreign> appears to have retired wounded to <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Bononia</foreign> after the battle. It is rather remarkable that
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Galba</foreign> says nothing of his being wounded in Letter
            DCCCXXXVIII. </note> Decimus Brutus and Caesar are in pursuit of the remnants of the
          enemy. <note n="3" anchored="true">It turned out that Caesar had refused to join Decimus
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> in the pursuit of Antony. </note> All,
          moreover, have been declared "enemies," who followed the party of Antony: and that decree
          of the senate most people interpret as applying also to those whom you have captured or
          who have surrendered to you. For my part I refrained from urging any severity, though I
          proposed a decree referring to Gaius Antonius by name: for I had made up my mind that the
          senate ought to be informed by you of the merits of his case. <milestone unit="para"/>27
          April. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=11" type="letter" xml:id="s846">
        <head>DCCCXLVI (BRUT. I, II)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>DYRRACHIUM (MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> ANTISTIUS VETUS is so devoted to the Republic that I feel no doubt of his shewing
          himself in the case both of Caesar and Antony a most determined champion of the common
          liberty, if he ever gets the opportunity. For the man who, meeting P. Dolabella in Achaia
          in possession of infantry and cavalry, preferred incurring any danger from the treachery
          of an utterly unscrupulous outlaw to being thought either to have been compelled to give
          money, or to have given it voluntarily to a most abandoned and unprincipled man-he, I say,
          has not only promised but has paid us 2,000 Sestertia out of his own pocket, and, what is
          much more valuable, has presented himself in person and has joined us. <note n="1"
            anchored="true">Vetus had evidently brought to <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>
            what was properly public money. It may be the C. Antistius Vetus who in the previous
            year was in Syria engaged in attacking Caecilius Bassus. See p. 15. </note> I have been
          desirous to persuade him to remain in my camp in military command and to support the
          Republic. But he has made up his mind that he is bound to go home after having dismissed
          his army. He assured us, however, that he would return promptly in the position of
          legatus, <note n="2" anchored="true">I do not think this can mean a <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >libera legatio</foreign>. Vetus was going home apparently to stand for the
            praetorship. If he could not get that, owing to the elections being suspended in the
            absence of the consuls, he would accept the office of <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >legatus</foreign> under <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>. </note> unless the
          consuls intended holding the praetorian <pb n="225"/> elections; for with a man of his
          political views, I was urgent that he should not postpone the time of his canvass. What
          this man has done ought to be approved by everybody, at any rate by those who believe that
          this army is of great moment to the state, by you all the more so in proportion as you
          defend our liberty with greater spirit and fame, and are sure to enjoy a higher position
          if the result of our plans is what we desire it to be. I also ask you, my dear Cicero, as
          a personal favour, and with the confidence of a friend, to love Vetus and to desire the
          highest promotion for him. For though nothing can turn him from his purpose, he will yet
          be capable of being incited by your praises and kindness still more to embrace and hold
          fast your principles. I shall be very grateful if it is so. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=5" type="letter" xml:id="s848">
        <head>DCCCXLVIII (BRUT. 1,5)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (AT DYRRACHIUM)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (5 MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> ON the 27th of April, when the speeches were being delivered in the senate as to the
          proceedings to be taken against the men who had been adjudged public enemies, Servilius
          referred among others to the case of Ventidius, <note n="1" anchored="true">Ventidius
            Bassus, the praetor, who had marched from <foreign xml:lang="la">Ariminum</foreign> and
            joined Antony at <foreign xml:lang="la">Vada</foreign> Sabata. See pp.218, 221, 230.
          </note> and also advised that Cassius should conduct the war against Dolabella. I spoke in
          support of this, and added to the motion that you, if you thought it expedient and to the
          public advantage, should direct your attack upon Dolabella: and that if you could not do
          so with advantage to the public service, or if you thought that it was to the interests of
          the state, you should keep your army in the district in which it now is. The senate could
          not have paid you a greater compliment than leaving you to decide what you thought to be
          for the benefit of the state. For my own part my feeling is that, if Dolabella has a body
          of troops, if he has a camp, if he has any footing anywhere, it concerns your honour and
          position that you should go against him. As to the forces in the hands of our friend
          Cassius we know nothing, for we have had no despatch from him personally, nor has any news
          reached us upon which we can rely. But how important it is that Dolabella should be
          crushed you certainly fully appreciate, both that he may be punished for his crime, and
          that there may be no place of refuge for the ringleaders of the outlaws after their rout
          at Mutina. And indeed that this has all along been my opinion you may recollect from my
          previous letter—though at that time our only harbour of refuge was in your camp, and we
          were looking to your army to save us from destruction. Much more, now that we have been
          freed as I hope from absolute danger, ought we to <pb n="227"/> devote ourselves to
          crushing Dolabella. <note n="1" anchored="true">Cicero means that he had thought <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> ought to pursue <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Dolabella</foreign>, though before the success at <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Mutina</foreign> it was important for the <foreign xml:lang="la">Optimates</foreign>
            at Rome to have <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> near at hand in case of danger.
            Now that the battle of <foreign xml:lang="la">Mutina</foreign> had relieved them of that
            fear, there can be no reason why <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> should not go
            to Asia, or anywhere else that was necessary. </note> But think the matter over
          carefully, decide it wisely, and—if you deem it right-let me know what you have resolved
          and what you are actually doing. I wish my son Cicero to be co-opted into your college.
            <note n="2" anchored="true">The college of the pontifices. Two vacancies had occurred by
            the death of Iulius Caesar and P. Servilius Isauricus. They were filled up later in the
            year by Ventidius Bassus and <foreign xml:lang="la">Cornelius</foreign> Balbus. </note>
          I think in the circumstances that in the election of sacerdotes candidates might be voted
          for in their absence : for it has been done even before this. For instance, Gaius Marius,
          though he was in Cappadocia, was created an augur under the lex Domitia; <note n="3"
            anchored="true">Marius went to <foreign xml:lang="la">Cappadocia</foreign> in <date>B.C.
                <date to="-0098" from="-0099">99</date>-98</date> on a <foreign xml:lang="la">votiva
              legatio</foreign> to the mother of the gods, really with a view to see the state of
            things in regard to the encroachments of Mithradates, against whom he wished to be
            appointed to command. The <foreign xml:lang="la">lex Domitia</foreign>, <date
              when="-0104">B.C. 104</date>, left the right of co-optatio in a modified form to the
            sacred colleges. Two of the existing members nominated a man, who was next elected by
            seventeen of the tribes in the <foreign xml:lang="la">sacerdotum comitia</foreign>, and
            was then—as though by a congé d' élire-co-opted by the whole college. This had since
            that time been again modified by <foreign xml:lang="la">Sulla</foreign>, the
            intermediate process of election by the seventeen tribes being omitted or in some way
            reduced to a mere form; but after <foreign xml:lang="la">Sulla</foreign> the old
            practice was resumed. </note> nor has any law since made that illegal. There is even a
          clause in the lex Julia—the most recent legislation on the subject of the priesthoods—in
          these words: "the candidate and anyone for whom votes shall be taken." This clearly
          indicates that votes can be taken for one who does not act as a candidate. I have written
          to my son on this subject telling him to follow your advice, as in all other things. It is
          for you again to decide about Domitius and our friend Cato. <note n="4" anchored="true"
            >That is, whether you wish them to be candidates. L. Domitius Ahenobarbus (who fell at
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Pharsalia</foreign>) married <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Porcia</foreign>, a sister of <foreign xml:lang="la">Cato Uticensis</foreign>, and
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> was married to <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Porcia</foreign>, a daughter of the same <foreign xml:lang="la">Cato</foreign>.
            Therefore the son of Domitius—Cn. Domitius Ahenobarbus and young <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Cato</foreign>, the son of <foreign xml:lang="la">Cato Uticensis</foreign>, were
            connexions of <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>, and he might wish to back them.
          </note> But however legal it may be for votes to be taken for a man in his absence, yet it
          is easier in every way for those who are on the spot. While if you have <pb n="228"/>
          resolved that you must go to Asia, we shall have no means of summoning our friends to the
          comitia. Certainly I think that everything would have been more expeditiously done if
          Pansa were alive: for he would have at once held the election of his colleague, and then
          the comitia of the sacerdotes would have been held before those of the praetors. As it is,
          I foresee a long delay on account of the auspicia; for as long as there is a single
          patrician magistrate left the auspicia cannot revert to the senate. It is certainly a
          serious complication. <note n="1" anchored="true">The same difficulty had occurred in
              <date when="-0049">B.C. 49</date>, when both consuls were abroad (see vol. ii.,
            pp.331, 349). The lesser magistrate cannot "create," i.e., hold the election for, the
            greater. In old times, when the consuls were the only curule magistrates, in case of
            their disappearance by death or otherwise, the auspicia—the right of taking the
            auspices, without which there could be no valid election-were said to revert to the
              <foreign xml:lang="la">patres</foreign> of the senate. The senate then nominated
              <foreign xml:lang="la">interreges</foreign>, who held the election. But the question
            is now complicated by the fact that there are other curule magistrates who possess the
              <foreign xml:lang="la">auspicia</foreign>, which therefore cannot revert to the
              <foreign xml:lang="la">patres</foreign> unless they abdicate. In <date when="-0052"
              >B.C. 52</date> the question did not arise, for the elections having been all
            prevented till after the 1st of January, all curule magistrates had vacated their
            offices, and therefore the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspicia</foreign> had reverted to the
              <foreign xml:lang="la">patres</foreign>. By a "patrician magistrate," Cicero
            practically means a curule magistrate, originally confined to the patricians: the term
            is still used, though the old "patrician" monopoly of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >auspicia</foreign> had long disappeared. </note> Pray write and tell me your views on
          the whole question. <milestone unit="para"/>5 May. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=4.1-3" type="letter" xml:id="s853">
        <head>DCCCLIII (BRUT. I, 4, §§ 1-3)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>DYRRACHIUM (7 MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> MY joy at hearing of the success of our friend Decimus Brutus and the Consuls it is
          easier for you to imagine than for me to write. <note n="1" anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> could not have known of the death of the
            consuls, which indeed was not known at first even at Rome. Galba's letter (pp.211-213)
            says nothing even of Pansa's wound, and as <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>
            refers below to the last words of Letter DCCCXLI (p.219), he could not have as yet
            received DCCCXLIII. </note> I have nothing but praise and pleasure for everything that
          has occurred, but especially for the fact that the sortie of Brutus not only proved his
          own salvation, but also a very great assistance to the victory. <note n="2"
            anchored="true">According to Dio (46, 40), Decimus <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus</foreign> and his besieged garrison made no sortie during the battle, nor took
            any part in it. But there is nothing surprising in M. <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus</foreign> having heard that he did. The inaccuracy of the reports during the
            war has again and again been apparent. </note>
          <milestone unit="para"/>You remark that all the three Antonies stand on one and the same
          ground, and that it rests with me to decide what view I take. Well, my only conclusion is
          that the decision in regard to those citizens who have fought and not been killed rests
          with the senate or the Roman people. "Ah, but," you will say, "you are wrong to begin with
          in calling men citizens whose feelings to the state are those of enemies." On the
          contrary, I am acting with the strictest justice. For that which the senate has not yet
          voted, nor the Roman people ordained—that I do not take upon myself to prejudge, nor do I
          claim to decide it on my own authority. From this position I do not budge-from the man,
          whom circumstances did not compel me to put to death, I have not wrested anything in a
          spirit of cruelty, nor have I given him any indulgence from mere weakness; but I have
          retained him in my power until the end of the war. I consider it much the more honourable
          course, and one which the <pb n="235"/> Republic can with more safety concede, not to
          press heavily on the unfortunate, rather than to indulge men of influence in what is
          calculated to inflame their ambition and arrogance. <note n="1" anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> seems to be referring to those members of the
            party who were in favour of severities to the opposition, partly from desire for
            vengeance, and partly with an eye to confiscations and other personal advantages. We
            heard much of this in the early times of the civil war. See vol. ii., pp.294, 310, etc.
          </note> In this matter, Cicero, you—who have done the most splendid and gallant services,
          and are most deeply beloved by all on private and public grounds alike-seem to me too
          ready to believe what you hope; and the moment anyone has done anything well, to be ready
          to give and concede everything to him. As though it were not quite possible that a mind
          should be corrupted by bribery and perverted to evil. You are so good-natured that you
          won't be angry at receiving this hint, especially as it concerns the common safety. You
          will act, however, as it may seem best to you. Even I, when you have admonished me...
            <note n="2" anchored="true">The end of the letter is lost. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=16" type="letter" xml:id="s860">
        <head>DCCCLX (BRUT. I, 16)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>MACEDONIA (MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I<note n="1" anchored="true">The textual history of this and the following letter (to
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Atticus</foreign>) is strong enough, and the references in
            Plutarch's <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> (ch. xxii) are sufficient to prove
            that they, or documents exceedingly like them, existed in his time and were believed to
            be genuine. To my mind the letter to <foreign xml:lang="la">Atticus</foreign> has much
            the stronger internal signs of genuineness of the two. For in spite of every attestation
            one is loath to think that the present letter was really written by a man who enjoyed as
            high a reputation among his contemporaries as <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>
            did. It is so querulous, poor, ill-expressed, and tautological—so entirely unworthy of
            the subject and the writer and the recipient—that we should be glad to know of a dull
            pupil in a rhetorical school being discovered to be its author. To read arguments in
            favour of its being Brutus's usual style reminds one of a criticism of Charles Lamb,
            who, being told that somebody's sonnets were like those of Petrarch, replied, "Yes, they
            are like Petrarch's, if we could suppose Petrarch to have been born a fool." I have left
            these letters in the place assigned them in Messrs. Tyrrell and Purser's edition; but
            one of the gravest objections to them is the difficulty of deciding to what particular
            juncture they can refer: and for some reasons it seems to me to be most natural to put
            at any rate the first of them before the battle of <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Mutina</foreign>. </note> have read an extract from your letter to Octavius which was
          sent me by Atticus. Your zeal and care for my safety gave me no novel pleasure; for it is
          not merely a matter of habit, but of daily habit, to be told of you that you have said or
          done something in defence of my position which displayed your fidelity and complimentary
          opinion of me. But that same extract of your letter to Octavius about us caused me a
          distress as great as my heart is capable of feeling. For you thank him in the name of the
          Republic in such terms! With such abject and whispering humbleness-why must I write the
          word? I blush to think of my position and high estate, yet I must write it-you commend our
          safety to him! Could any death be worse disaster? You, in fact,. avow that the slavery is
          not abolished, only the master changed! Recall your words and dare to say that those
          prayers are not <pb n="244"/> the prayers of an enslaved subject to a tyrant. The one and
          only thing-you say—that is demanded and expected of him is that he consent to the safety
          of those citizens, of whom the loyalists and the people have a good opinion. What? If he
          doesn't consent, shall we not be safe? And yet it is better not to be than to be by his
          favour. <note n="1" anchored="true">This of course recalls Shakespeare, and may have
            suggested, <quote>
              <l>I had as lief not be as live to be</l>
              <l>In awe of such a thing as I myself.</l>
            </quote> Jul. Caes. i. 2, 95. </note> Upon my honour I do not think that all the gods
          are so hostile to the safety of the Roman people, that we need entreat Octavius for the
          safety of any citizen, not to say for "the liberators of the world"—for there is a certain
          advantage in using strong language, and at any rate there is a propriety in doing so to
          people who do not know what every man ought to fear or to aim at. <milestone unit="para"
          />Do you confess, Cicero, that Octavius has this power, and are you his friend? Or, if you
          regard me with affection, do you wish me to appear at Rome, when in order to do so safely
          I have had to be recommended to that boy? Why do you thank him, if you think he has to be
          asked to allow and suffer us to keep our lives? Is it to be regarded as a favour that he
          has preferred to be himself rather than a second Antony, to whom we had to make petitions
          like that? Does anyone address to the destroyer of another's tyranny, and not rather to
          its successor, a prayer that those who have done the most splendid services to their
          country may be allowed their lives? This is mere weakness and a counsel of despair. And
          the fault is not yours more than everyone else's. It was this that egged on Caesar to
          desire royalty, and induced Antony after his death to aim at occupying the place of the
          dead man, and has at the present moment put that boy of yours on such a pedestal, as to
          make you think that he must be absolutely entreated to grant life to such men as us, and
          that we shall even now be able to enjoy a bare safety from the pity of one man, and by
          nothing else whatever. But if we had remembered that we were Romans, these dregs of
          mankind would not have conceived the ambition of playing the tyrant with more boldness
          than we should have forbidden it: nor would Antony have had his ambition <pb n="245"/>
          more roused by Caesar's royalty, than his fears excited by Caesar's death. For yourself; a
          consular and the avenger of such abominable crimes—and I fear that by their suppression
          the mischief was only postponed by you for a short time—how can you contemplate your own
          achievements, and at the same time countenance, or at any rate endure these things with
          such abject humbleness as to have the air of countenancing them? Again, what was your
          private and personal quarrel with Antony? Why, it was just because he made this very
          claim—that our safety should be asked as a favour from him; that we should hold our civil
          rights on sufferance—we from whom he had himself received his freedom; that he should be
          absolute in the Republic—it was for these reasons that you thought we must take up arms to
          prevent his playing the tyrant. Was the object of doing so that, when he had been
          prevented, we should have to petition another man to allow himself to be put in his place?
          Or was it that the Republic should be its own master and at its own disposal? Surely:
          unless we are to suppose that our objection was not to slavery but to the terms of our
          slavery! And yet, not only had we the opportunity of supporting our high estate with
          Antony as a liberal master, but even of enjoying rewards and honours as his partners to
          the top of our ambition: for what would he have refused to men, whose submissiveness he
          saw would be the greatest bulwark of his tyranny? But nothing seemed sufficient to make us
          barter our honour and freedom. <milestone unit="para"/>This very boy, whom the name of
          Caesar appears to instigate against the slayers of Caesar, what would he give, if there
          were a chance of such traffic, to be as powerful with our support, as he certainly will be
          when we choose life for its own sake, and the possession of money, and the title of
          consulars! But Caesar will have perished in vain: for why did we rejoice at his death, if
          we were to become none the less slaves when he is dead? No one else cares about these
          things, but may the gods and goddesses take from me every. thing sooner than the
          resolution of never conceding what I would not endure in Caesar—I won't say to the heir of
          the man I killed, but even to my father himself if he were to come to life again-namely,
          that he should, without a protest from me, be more powerful than the laws and the senate.
            <pb n="246"/> Are you so deluded as to think that the rest of the world will be' free
          from one without whose consent there is no footing for us in Rome? Moreover, how can you
          possibly get what you ask? For you ask that he would consent to our safety: do we
          therefore appear likely to accept safety, since we have accepted life? But how can we
          accept it, if we previously give up position and liberty? Do you count the fact of living
          at Rome as complete citizenship? It is circumstance, not the particular place of
          residence, that must secure me that. I was neither properly a full citizen while Caesar
          was alive, except when I had resolved upon doing that deed; nor can I ever be anywhere an
          exile so long as I abhor servitude and submission to insult worse than every other evil.
          To ask a man who has adopted a tyrant's name as his own <note n="1" anchored="true"
            >Octavius by adoption in Caesar's will was now C. Iulius Caesar Octavianus. <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> never calls him Octavianus, as that would acknowledge
            the adoption, and only Caesar ironically. </note> for the safety of the avengers and
          destroyers of the tyranny—is not this to fall back into the very dungeon from which you
          have just escaped? Why, in Greek states when tyrants are put down their sons are included
          under the same punishment. <note n="2" anchored="true">A verse of Stasimus is quoted by
            Polybius (23, 10) on the policy of killing sons as well as fathers <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">nh/pios o(\s pate/ra ktei/nas ui(ou\s katalei/pei</foreign>, "Oh fool!
            to slay the sire and leave the sons!" </note> Am I to desire to see a state, or to
          regard it as a state at all, which is incapable of recovering even a freedom handed down
          by its ancestors and rooted in its very being, and which is more afraid of the name of a
          slain tyrant in the person of a mere boy, than confident in itself; though seeing the very
          man who possessed the most over-weening power removed by the valour of a few? For
          myself—do not henceforth recommend me to your Caesar, nor yourself either, if you will
          listen to me. You must have a great value for the few years that your time of life allows
          you, if for their sake you are going to be a suppliant to that boy of yours. Again, take
          care that those very splendid attacks which you have made and are still making upon
          Antony, instead of getting you credit for courage, are not misinterpreted into a belief
          that you are afraid. For if you think Octavius the sort of person from whom to make
          petitions for our safety, you will be thought <pb n="247"/> not to have fled from a
          master, but to have looked out for a more agreeable master. Of your praising him for his
          conduct up to this time I quite approve, for it deserves to be praised, provided that he
          adopted these measures against the tyrannical power of another and not in support of his
          own. But when you shew your opinion that he is not only to be allowed so much power, but
          is even to have so much tendered to him by yourself; as to be petitioned not to refuse us
          our lives, you are making a very bad bargain with him, for you are giving away to him the
          very thing of which the Republic seemed to be in possession through him. And it does not
          occur to you that, if Octavius deserves those honours for waging war on Antony, to those
          who have cut up that mischief by the roots—of which the present position is but the last
          trace—the Roman people will never give what is an adequate reward of their service, though
          it should heap everything it had to give upon them at once. See too how much more awake
          people are to actual fear than to the memory of past terrors. Because Antony is still
          alive and in arms, while in regard to Caesar what could and was bound to be done is all
          over and cannot be undone, Octavius is the man whose decision as to us is awaited by the
          Roman people; we are in such a position that one man has to be petitioned to enable us to
          live. I however—to return to your policy—so far from being the sort of man to supplicate,
          am one forcibly to coerce those who demand that supplications should be addressed to them.
          If I can't do that, I will withdraw far from the servile herd and will for myself regard
          as Rome wherever I am able to be free. I shall feel only pity for men like yourself; if
          neither age nor honours nor the example of other men's courage has been able to lessen
          your clinging to life. For my part I shall only think myself happy if I abide with
          firmness and persistency in the idea that my patriotism has had its reward: for what is
          there better than the memory of good actions, and for a man-wanting nothing except
          liberty—to disregard the vicissitudes of human life? But at any rate I will not yield to
          the yielders, nor be conquered by those who are willing to be conquered themselves. I will
          try every expedient, every plan: and I will never desist from the attempt to rescue our
          country from slavery. If the luck follows <pb n="248"/> which ought to follow, I shall
          rejoice: if not, I shall rejoice all the same, for on what better deeds or thoughts can my
          life be spent than on those which are directed to the liberation of my fellow citizens?
          For you, Cicero, I beg and entreat you not to give in to fatigue or despair. In warding
          off actually existing evils ever seek to discover those that will occur if they are not
          prevented, and so prevent their creeping in upon us. Consider that the brave and
          independent spirit, with which as consul and now as a consular you have vindicated the
          freedom of the state, ceases to exist if a consistent and even tenor of conduct is not
          preserved. For I confess that tried virtue is in a harder position than virtue that is
          unknown. We exact good deeds as a debt: we assail the reverse with anger in our hearts, as
          though we were cheated by such men. So, for instance, though it is a most laudable thing
          that Cicero should resist Antony, yet because the consul of that time is thought naturally
          to guarantee the consular of today, no one admires him. And if this same Cicero when
          dealing with others has distorted his judgment, which he kept unshaken with such
          steadiness and high spirit in routing Antony, he will not only snatch the glory of future
          action from his own grasp, but will even force his past career to fade from sight (for
          there is nothing which is truly great in itself; unless it is deliberate and systematic),
          because no one is under a greater obligation to love the Republic and to be the champion
          of liberty, whether we regard his ability or his great past or the eager demands upon him
          from all the world. Wherefore Octavius ought not to be petitioned to consent to our
          safety. Rather do you rouse yourself to the fixed belief that the state in which you have
          performed the most splendid services will be free and honoured, if only the people have
          leaders in their resistance to the plots of traitors. <pb n="249"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=17" type="letter" xml:id="s861">
        <head>DCCCLXI (BRUT. I, 17)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO ATTICUS (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>MACEDONIA (MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> YOU say in your letter that Cicero wonders at my never making any remark about his
          political actions. Since you ask me, under compulsion from you I will set down my
          sentiments. I know that Cicero does everything with the best intentions—for what could be
          clearer to me than his devotion to the Republic? But he, the acutest of men, appears to me
          in certain things to have acted with a want of—shall I call it tact or disinterestedness
          ?-in spite of the fact that he has not scrupled to incur the enmity of Antony at the
          height of his power on behalf of the Republic. I don't know what to set down on paper for
          you except the one thing: that the boy's ambition and unscrupulousness have been rather
          provoked than repressed by Cicero: and that he carries this indulgence to such a pitch
          that he does not abstain from abusive remarks-remarks which recoil upon himself with
          double force, because he put more than a single person to death, and ought rather to
          confess himself a murderer than to taunt Casca as he does, and because he imitates in
          Casca's case the conduct of Bestia. <note n="1" anchored="true">That is, he is as bitter
            to <foreign xml:lang="la">Casca</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="la">Bestia</foreign> was
            formerly to himself. L. Calpurnius <foreign xml:lang="la">Bestia</foreign> had been a
            partisan of <foreign xml:lang="la">Catiline (pro</foreign> Sest. § 11). Yet Cicero
            defended him on a charge of <foreign xml:lang="la">ambitus</foreign> in <date
              when="-0056">B.C. 56</date> (see vol. i., p.216). There were two brothers Casca—C.
            Servilius <foreign xml:lang="la">Casca</foreign> and P. Servilius Casca—engaged in the
            assassination. Publius was tribune in <date>B.C. <date to="-0043" from="-0044"
              >44</date>-43</date>. From <foreign xml:lang="la">ad</foreign>
            <bibl n="Cic. Att. 16.159">Att. 16.159</bibl>, p.159, it would seem that Octavian had
            protested against his tribuneship (cp. <bibl n="Cic. Phil. 13.31">Phil. 13.31</bibl>,
            p.189). It seems almost too great an inconsistency to be believed that Cicero should
            ever have reproached any man with the death of Caesar. </note> Pray, because we are not
          always bragging of the Ides of March, as he always has his Nones of December on his lips,
          is Cicero in any better position for vilifying a most glorious deed than Bestia and
          Clodius were for their habitual attacks upon his consulship? Our friend Cicero boasts to
          me that he has, though a <pb n="250"/> civilian, successfully faced the war of Antony.
          What good is that to me, if as a price for crushing Antony succession into Antony's
          position is demanded, and if the avenger of that evil comes forward as the supporter of
          another destined to have a deeper foundation and to strike deeper roots, unless we prevent
          it? Granted that his present policy proceeds from fear-shall we say of tyranny, or of a
          tyrant, or of Antony? Well, but I feel no gratitude to one who, to avoid being the slave
          of a bad-tempered master, does not deprecate slavery itself-nay, rather proposes to give
          him a triumph and pay for his men, and by all manner of decrees instigates him not to
          shrink from coveting the high position of the man whose name he has adopted. Is this
          worthy of a consular or of a Cicero? Since I have not been allowed to be silent, you will
          have to read what must necessarily give you annoyance, for I am conscious myself of the
          pain with which I have written this to you; nor am I ignorant what your sentiments as to
          the situation are, and how desperate also you think the possibility of its cure. <note
            n="1" anchored="true">It seems necessary in the context that this sentence should mean
            that <foreign xml:lang="la">Atticus</foreign> despaired of remedial measures. Various
            emendations have been proposed. I have simply changed <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >desperatam</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="la">desperatum</foreign>, and regarded
              <foreign xml:lang="la">posse sanari</foreign> as a substantive, "the possibility of a
            cure," which is a rather characteristic usage in these letters. </note> Nor, by heaven,
          do I blame you, Atticus. For your age, your habits, and your children <note n="2"
            anchored="true">Atticus—we should observe—had only one child, a daughter. But perhaps we
            may pass <foreign xml:lang="la">liberi</foreign> as a facon <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >de</foreign> parler. </note> make you unenterprising—a fact which I gathered also
          from our friend Flavius. But I return to Cicero. What is the difference between
          Salvidienus <note n="3" anchored="true">Salvidienus Rufus, an early friend of Octavian's,
            who had been with him at <foreign xml:lang="la">Apollonia</foreign>. He was a man of
            obscure origin (<foreign xml:lang="la">ex</foreign> infima <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >fortuna</foreign>, <bibl n="Suet. Aug. 66">Suet. Aug. 66</bibl>), but was employed on
            confidential matters for some time by Augustus. He has now apparently been sent to Rome
            with Octavian's demand for the consulship. In <date when="-0042">B.C. 42</date> and 41
            he was employed against Sextus Pompeius in Sicily, and from thence was despatched to
            secure Gaul and Spain: and returned to take part in the siege of <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Perusia</foreign>. After the fall of <foreign xml:lang="la">Perusia</foreign> (<date
              when="-0040">B.C. 40</date>), he went with Augustus to Gaul, where he was left in
            command, and designated <foreign xml:lang="la">consul</foreign> for <date when="-0039"
              >B.C. 39</date>. But in the autumn of <date when="-0040">B.C. 40</date>, when Antony
            came to <foreign xml:lang="la">Brundisium</foreign>, he seems to have told Augustus that
            Salvidienus had been tampering with the loyalty of the Gauls, and he was convicted of
              <foreign xml:lang="la">maiestas</foreign> and declared a <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >hostis</foreign> by the senate; and thereupon put to death (<bibl n="TLG551.17 5.52"
              >App. B.C. 5.52</bibl>-56; Dio, 48, 13-33). </note> and him? What <pb n="251"/>
          greater honour could he have proposed in the senate? Cicero is afraid," you will say,
          "even now of the remnant of the civil war." Does anyone then, while fearing a war nearly
          concluded, think that neither the tyrannical power of 'the victorious army's commander nor
          the rashness of the boy is at all alarming? Or is his motive for this very action the idea
          that now, owing to the greatness of his power, every kind of honour must be spontaneously
          offered to him? How strange is the blindness of fear! While taking precautions against
          what you dread, actually to invite danger and to bring it upon you, though you might
          perhaps have avoided it altogether! We are over-fearful of death, exile, and poverty: I
          think that these things are the worst of evils in Cicero's eyes, and that while he has
          people from whom to get what he wants, and by whom to be made much of and flattered, he
          has no aversion to servitude, if it be but tempered by a show of respect—if there can be
          any respect in what is the last and most wretched degradation. Therefore, though Octavius
          call Cicero "father," consult him in everything, praise and thank him, nevertheless the
          truth will come out that words do not agree with deeds. For what can be more contrary to
          common sense than to regard a man as a father, who is not even reckoned as free? For my
          part, I set no store by those accomplishments with which I know Cicero to be better
          furnished than anyone else: for what good to him are the speeches on behalf of his
          country's liberty, the essays on dignity, death, exile, poverty, which he has composed
          with the utmost wealth of language? What a much truer view Philippus seems to have of
          those things, when he refused all compliments to his own stepson, <note n="1"
            anchored="true">For Philippus would not address him as Caesar, at any rate when he first
            came to Italy. See p.21. </note> than Cicero has, who pays them to one who has no
          connexion with him! Let him cease then from absolutely insulting our misfortunes by his
          boastful language; for what does it profit us that Antony has been conquered, if the only
          result of his defeat is to leave his place open to another? However, even now there is a
          note of uncertainty in your letter. Long live Cicero—as he may well do—to cringe and
          serve! if he is not ashamed to think of his age nor his honour, nor his great <pb n="252"
          /> past. For myself, at any rate, there is no condition of servitude, however favourable,
          which will deter me from waging war on the principle: that is, on royalty,
          unconstitutional magistracies, absolutism, and power that aims at being above the laws.
          Though Antony may be a good man, as you say in your letter-which, however, has never been
          my opinion—yet the law of our ancestors was that no one, not even a father, should be an
          absolute master. Unless I had been as deeply attached to you as Cicero believes that
          Octavius is devoted to him, I should not have written this to you. I am grieved to think
          that as you read this you are getting angry—for you are most affectionate to all your
          friends, and especially to Cicero: but assure yourself of this, that my personal goodwill
          to Cicero is in no way modified, though my opinion is largely so, for you cannot ask a man
          to judge except from what seems to him to be truth in each case. I could have wished that
          you had mentioned in your letter what arrangements were being made for the betrothal of
          our dear Attica: I might have said something to you of what I felt about the matter. I am
          not surprised that you are anxious about Porcia's health. <note n="1" anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Porcia</foreign>, if we are to accept the <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >consolatio</foreign> (Letter DCCCXCVII) as genuine, seems to have died soon after
            this. </note> Lastly, I will gladly do what you ask, for my sisters <note n="2"
            anchored="true">Half-sisters: <foreign xml:lang="la">Iunia</foreign> married to Lepidus,
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Tertia</foreign> to Cassius. We have no means of knowing to
            whom <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> is referring-perhaps to Lepidus, to whom
            Cicero may have asked him to write. </note> ask me the same, and I know the man and his
          views. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=4.3-6" type="letter" xml:id="s862">
        <head>DCCCLXII (BRUT. I, 4, §§ 3-6)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>CAMP IN EPIRUS, 15 MAY</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> ... <note n="3" anchored="true">This letter-forming in the MSS. the latter part of
            DCCCLIII-is imperfect. The first part of it appears to have been lost. </note> Now,
          Cicero, now is the time for action, lest we turn out to have rejoiced in vain at the
          defeat of Antony, and lest <pb n="253"/> it is always to be a case of cutting out one
          mischief for another to grow worse than the former. No reverse can now find us unprepared
          or otiose, in which everyone will not be to blame, and especially yourself, whose
          influence the senate and Roman people not only allow to be so great, but even desire to be
          the very greatest that one man's can be in a free state. And this influence you ought to
          maintain not only by good intentions but also by prudent conduct. Now the prudence, with
          which you are richly endowed, does not fail you in any respect except as to moderation in
          bestowing honours. <note n="1" anchored="true">The honours proposed to Octavian after the
            battles at <foreign xml:lang="la">Mutina</foreign>. </note> All other endowments you
          possess in such profusion, that your excellences will stand comparison with any of the
          heroes of old. The only outcome of your grateful and generous heart that people feel to be
          wanting is a more cautious and better regulated liberality. For the senate ought to grant
          nothing to anybody which may serve as a precedent or justification to the ill-disposed.
          For instance, I am afraid in regard to the consulship that your friend Caesar will think
          that he has mounted to a higher position by means of your decrees than he will be willing
          to descend from, if he is once made consul. <note n="2" anchored="true">We have already
            heard of the constitutional difficulty as to the election of consuls in the places of
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Pansa</foreign> and Hirtius (p. 228). Octavian sent to Rome
            soon after the battles of <foreign xml:lang="la">Mutina</foreign>, demanding to be
            allowed to stand for the consulship, and Cicero had already on the 1st of January
            proposed that, whenever he was a candidate for it, he should be assumed to have held the
            quaestorship (<bibl n="Cic. Phil. 5.47">Phil. 5.47</bibl>). According to Appian (<bibl
              n="TLG551.17 3.82">B.C. 3.82</bibl>; cp. Dio, 46; 42; <bibl n="Plut. Cic. 46"
              >Plutarch, Cic. 46</bibl>), Octavian proposed to Cicero to be his colleague, promising
            to leave the administration to him, and Cicero agreed to the proposal, and tried to
            induce the senate therefore to admit his candidature—as it had to do afterwards under
            compulsion of his army. This story is rejected by Cicero's admirers as a Caesarian
            invention, I don't quite know why. It seems not highly improbable in itself; and this
            letter of Brutus—especially the last sentence—seems to shew that there were at any rate
            rumours afloat at the time to that effect. </note> But if Antony regarded the working
          machinery of kingly power left by another as an opportunity for seizing kingly power for
          himself, what do you suppose a man's feelings will be who shall conceive himself justified
          in aspiring to any kind of office, not on the authority of a slain tyrant, but on that of
          the senate itself? Wherefore I shall reserve my compliments <pb n="254"/> to your good
          nature and foresight till I begin to have proof that Caesar will be content with the
          extra-constitutional honours that he has already received. <note n="1" anchored="true">He
            had by two separate <foreign xml:lang="la">senatus consulta</foreign> been invested
            first with the rank of propraeter and the <foreign xml:lang="la">consularia
              ornamenta</foreign> (the honorary rank of <foreign xml:lang="la">consul</foreign>),
            and with imperium. This last was on the 5th of January. </note> "Do you mean, then," you
          will say, "to make me liable for another man's misconduct?" Yes, certainly for another's,
          if its occurrence might have been prevented by foresight. And oh that you may clearly see
          the depth of my alarm in regard to him! <milestone unit="para"/>P.S.-After writing the
          above I have been informed that you have been elected consul. <note n="2" anchored="true"
            >See note p.233. This rumour of course was false; but it may have been connected with
            the belief that Cicero had listened to Octavian's suggestion. </note> I shall indeed
          begin to imagine that I have before my eyes a complete and self-sustained Republic, when I
          see that. Your son is well, and has been sent in advance into Macedonia with the cavalry.
            <milestone unit="para"/>15 May, in camp. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=6" type="letter" xml:id="s863">
        <head>DCCCLXIII (BRUT. I, 6)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>IMA CANDAVIA,</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p>
          <note n="3" anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Candavia</foreign> is a mountain across which the Egnatian Way
            went, about eighty miles from <foreign xml:lang="la">Dyrrachium. Ima Candavia</foreign>
            seems to mean the district at the foot of the mountain. <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus</foreign> is therefore marching down the <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Egnatia</foreign> into Macedonia proper. </note> 19 MAY Don't expect me to thank you.
          From the closeness of our intimacy, which has now reached the highest possible point of
          friendship, that ought long ago to have become superfluous. Your son is not in my
          quarters; we shall meet in Macedonia. His orders were to lead the cavalry from Ambracia by
          way of Thessaly, and I have written to him to meet me at Heraclea. When I see him; as you
          consent, I will settle with him about his return for his candidature, or rather his recom
            <pb n="255"/> mendation to the office. <note n="1" anchored="true">In the college of
            pontifices, for which Cicero asked his son to stand (see p. 227). I think by <foreign
              xml:lang="la">aut commendationem, Brutus</foreign> means politely to hint that he is
            sure of getting it, though of course there will be the form of election. </note> I
          commend to your protection with the utmost warmth Pansa's physician Glyco, who is married
          to the sister of my freedman Achilles. I am told that he is suspected by Torquatus in
          regard to Pansa's death, and is in custody as a murderer. Nothing could be more
          incredible: for who lost more than he did by Pansa's death? Besides he is a well-conducted
          moral man, whom even personal advantage would seem unlikely to tempt to crime. I beg you,
          and that with great earnestness—for my Achilles is as anxious about it as he is bound to
          be—to rescue him from prison and be his preserver. This I regard as affecting my duty as a
          private man as nearly as anything else could do. <note n="2" anchored="true">Glyco was
            said to have poisoned Pansa's wounds, and Octavian's enemies asserted that he did so at
            his instigation—a scandal that took a long time dying out (see <bibl n="Suet. Aug. 11"
              >Suet. Aug. 11</bibl>; Tacitus, A. i. io). Torquatus was Pansa's quaestor. </note>
          <milestone unit="para"/>While I was actually writing this letter to you a despatch was
          delivered to me from Satrius, a legate of Gaius Trebonius, saying that Dolabella had been
          defeated and put to flight by Tillius <note n="3" anchored="true">L. Tillius <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Cimber</foreign>, who struck the first blow in the assassination of
            Caesar (<bibl n="Suet. Jul. 82">Suet. Iul. 82</bibl>). He went afterwards—in virtue of
            Caesar's nomination—to the governorship of <foreign xml:lang="la">Bithynia</foreign>. In
            the course of the next year (<date when="-0042">B.C. 42</date>) he came to Macedonia
            with a fleet to aid <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> and Cassius. He fell at
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Philippi</foreign>, or immediately afterwards. </note> and
          Deiotarus. I am sending you a Greek letter of a certain Cicereius to Satrius. Our friend
          Flavius <note n="4" anchored="true">Praefectus <foreign xml:lang="la">fabrum</foreign> of
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>. See p.250. </note> in a dispute that he has
          with the people of Dyrrachium about an inheritance has named you as arbitrator: I beg you,
          Cicero, as does Flavius also, to settle this business. There is no doubt that the town
          owed money to the man who made Flavius his heir, nor do the Dyrrachini deny it, but they
          allege that they received from Caesar a remission of their debt. Don't allow your friends
            <note n="5" anchored="true">The people of <foreign xml:lang="la">Dyrrachium</foreign>
            had for some years had some special connexion with Cicero. He may have acted for them in
            some way. See vol. i., p.575. </note> to do a wrong to a friend of mine. <milestone
            unit="para"/>19 May, in camp at Ima Candavia. <pb n="256"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=7" type="letter" xml:id="s864">
        <head>DCCCLXIV (BRUT. I, 7)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>(MACEDONIA, LATTER PART OF MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> No one can better judge than you how dear Lucius Bibulus ought to be to me, considering
          his great struggles and anxieties on behalf of the Republic. Accordingly, his own
          excellence as well as our intimacy ought to make him your friend. I think myself therefore
          obliged to write at the less length: for a wish of mine ought to influence you, provided
          that it is equitable and is conceived in fulfilment of a necessary duty. He has resolved
          to stand for the place of Pansa. <note n="1" anchored="true">Two of the sons of Bibulus
            perished in a mutiny at Alexandria, and in <date when="-0050">B.C. 50</date> we find him
            trying in vain to get a third surviving son elected augur. This L. Calpurnius Bibulus
            may be a son of <foreign xml:lang="la">Porcia</foreign>, and therefore stepson to
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>, of whom he lived to write a memoir (vol. ii.,
            p.184). </note> I beg you therefore to nominate him. <note n="2" anchored="true">To the
            augurship. </note> You cannot do a favour to any man more closely attached than we are
          to you, nor can you nominate a more deserving man than Bibulus. What need to write about
          Domitius and Appuleius, seeing that they are most warmly recommended to you by their own
          merits? To Appuleius certainly you are bound to lend the protection of your influence—but
          Appuleius's praises shall be sung in the special letter he brings with him. Do not fail to
          take Bibulus to your bosom—a man, believe me, who may develop into the sort of character
          to deserve your most select praises. <pb n="257"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=1" type="letter" xml:id="s869">
        <head>DCCCLXIX (BRUT. I, I)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (LATE IN MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> L. Clodius, <note n="1" anchored="true">Vol. ii., p 19; vol. iii., p.224. </note>
          tribune-designate, is much attached to me, or, to speak with more empressement, loves me
          dearly. And when I am assured of that I feel certain—for you know me—that you will
          conclude that I love him: for nothing seems to me less human than not to give an answering
          affection to those by whom one's love is challenged. He seemed to me to suspect, much to
          his chagrin, that some unfavourable report had reached you from his friends, or rather
          through his enemies, by which your feelings were alienated from him. It is not my habit,
          my dear Brutus, as I think you know, to make rash statements about another man. It is a
          risky thing to do, owing to the secret feelings and complicated natures of mankind But I
          have seen to the bottom of Clodius's heart: I know it, and have formed my judgment of it.
          There are many proofs of it, but such as I need not write down, for I want you to regard
          this as a solemn deposition rather than a letter. He has been promoted by Antony—though a
          large share even of that very favour has its origin in you—and accordingly he would wish
          his safety so long as it is compatible with ours. But he fully understands—for he is no
          fool, as you are aware—that matters have come to such a point that both cannot be
          preserved; accordingly he prefers us. As to yourself, indeed, he both speaks and feels in
          the most affectionate manner. <pb n="263"/> Wherefore, if anyone has written to you or
          spoken to you by word of mouth disparagingly of him, I beg you again and again to believe
          me rather than them. I have greater opportunity of judging than any such casual observer,
          and I am more devoted to you. Make up your mind that Clodius is most warmly attached to
          you, and is such a citizen as a man of the greatest sense and most ample fortune is bound
          to be. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=2.1-3" type="letter" xml:id="s870">
        <head>DCCCLXX (BRUT. I, 2, §§ 1-3)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (LATE IN MAY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> WHEN I had already written and sealed a despatch to you, a letter from you was delivered
          to me full of startling intelligence. But the most surprising of all was that Dolabella
          had sent five cohorts <note n="1" anchored="true">That is, half a legion. </note> into the
          Chersonese. <note n="2" anchored="true">The Thracian <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Chersonese</foreign>. </note> Is he so flush of troops that a man who was said to be
          in flight from Asia is now attempting to get a foothold in Europe? With five cohorts,
          moreover, what did he think that he could do when you had five legions, <note n="3"
            anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> seems to have had five legions originally. He
            added one when he took Gaius Antonius, and enlisted two more in the province (<bibl
              n="TLG551.17 3.79">App. B.C. 3.79</bibl>). </note> a splendid body of cavalry, and
          very large auxiliary forces? These same cohorts, I hope, by this time are in your hands,
          since that outlaw has been so insensate. I strongly commend your policy in not having
          moved your army from Apollonia and Dyrrachium, until you heard of the flight of Antony, of
          Decimus Brutus having broken out of Mutina, and of the victory of the Roman people.
          Accordingly, in saying that you had afterwards resolved to lead your army into the
          Chersonese, and not to suffer the government of the Roman people to be a laughingstock to
          an enemy stained with the worst of crimes, you are acting in the interests of your own
          position and of the <pb n="264"/> Republic. You speak of an outbreak in the fourteenth
          legion on account of Gaius Antonius; you will excuse my saying that I am in sympathy with
          the severity of the soldiers rather than with yours. <note n="1" anchored="true">Reading,
            with Mueller, <foreign xml:lang="la">quarta decima Antoni</foreign>. .. magis <foreign
              xml:lang="la">mihi probatur militum severitas quam tua</foreign>. If this is right,
            what seems to have happened is that the fourteenth legion were guilty of a riotous
            demonstration against Gaius Antonius, which <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>
            punished as a breach of military discipline. Appian (<bibl n="TLG551.17 3.79">B.C.
              3.79</bibl>) says that Antonius was eventually put to death for tampering with the
            legions; Plutarch (Brut. 28) that he was put to death by <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus</foreign> in retaliation for the murder of Cicero. In that case it was not
            till December; but Cicero evidently shews that he was in favour of getting rid of him in
            any way. According to Dio (47, 24), <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> left him at
            Apollonia—when he went to Asia—under the charge of Gaius Clodius, who put him to death
            to prevent his being rescued by his brother Marcus. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=8" type="letter" xml:id="s883">
        <head>DCCCLXXXIII (BRUT. I, 8)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (MAY-JUNE)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I SHALL recommend many to you, and it is inevitable that I should do so—for it is always
          the best men and best citizens that are most inclined to follow your judgment; and it is
          for your approval that all brave men desire to work and study with activity; and finally
          everyone thinks that my influence and favour have very great weight with you. But I
          recommend to you Gaius Nasidienus—a burgher of Suessa—with an earnestness beyond which I
          cannot go about anyone. In the war in Crete under Metellus <note n="3" anchored="true">Q.
            Metellus Creticus conquered the Cretans in <date>B.C. <date to="-0066" from="-0068"
                >68</date>-66</date>. </note> he led the eighth "first line": <note n="4"
            anchored="true">That is, he was the centurion of the first <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >ordo</foreign> in the eighth cohort of a legion: there were ten cohorts in a legion,
            and each cohort had six <foreign xml:lang="la">ordines</foreign> with a centurion to
            each. </note> afterwards he was employed in the management of his property. At this
          period, influenced by the party divisions in the state, and by your pre-eminent position,
          he wishes to gain some distinction by your means. I am recommending to you, Brutus, a man
          of courage, a man of good character, and— <pb n="284"/> if that is at all to the point—of
          wealth also. <note n="1" anchored="true">See vol. iii., p.64. Mr. Tyrrell sees in this a
            reflexion on the disinterestedness of <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>. No doubt
            money was sorely needed (see p.224), and rich men were welcome at the camp. </note> I
          shall be very much obliged if you treat him so as to enable him to thank me for favours
          received from you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=10" type="letter" xml:id="s892">
        <head>DCCCXCII (BRUT. I, 10)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (JUNE)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I have no letter as yet from you—not so much as a rumour—to shew that you are aware of
          the resolution of the senate and are bringing your army into Italy. That you should do so,
          and with all speed, the Republic urgently requires: for <pb n="298"/> the internal
          mischief daily grows more serious, and we are in difficulties from enemies at home no less
          than from those abroad. The former have, it is true, always existed from the beginning of
          the war, but they were then more easily crushed. The senate was then in a more resolute
          frame of mind, roused to action not only by the motions which I brought forward, but also
          by my earnest exhortations. Pansa was then in the senate very strenuous and bold in his
          attacks upon all men of that sort, and especially his father-in-law. <note n="1"
            anchored="true">Fufius Calenus, who desired terms made with Antony (<bibl
              n="Cic. Phil. 8.11">Phil. 8.11</bibl>). </note> As consul his courage never failed him
          from the beginning, nor his loyalty at the end. The conduct of the war at Mutina left
          nothing to complain of in Caesar, though some few points in Hirtius. The fortune of this
          war is <quote>For happy though but ill, for ill not worst.</quote>
          <note n="2" anchored="true">Twice quoted before. See vol. i., p.189. </note> The Republic
          was victorious: Antony's forces were cut to pieces, and he himself driven out of the
          country. Then came so many mistakes on the part of Decimus Brutus, that in a certain sense
          the victory slipped through our fingers. <note n="3" anchored="true">Very different froni
            the language which Cicero employs to Decimus himself. The fact is that Decimus could not
            possibly pursue Antony effectively. His garrison had suffered greatly from want of food
            in <foreign xml:lang="la">Mutina</foreign>, and from natural excess after the siege was
            raised. He had no transport. Octavius refused ahsolutely to assist him, or to have
            anything to do with him. And the fourth and Martian legions stuck to Octavius, as did
            most of the veterans with Hirtius and <foreign xml:lang="la">Pansa</foreign>. Antony had
            two days' start at least, and was not—as Cicero fondly imagined-leading away a
            demoralized army. His cavalry was intact, and the splendid march by Acqui to <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Vado</foreign>, and then by the Riviera to Frejus, shews that the rest
            of his forces was in no desperate case. </note> Our generals did not pursue the
          demoralized, unarmed, wounded enemy, and time was granted to Lepidus to give us a taste of
          that fickleness, which we had had many occasions to know before, in a more disastrous
          field. The armies of Brutus and Plancus are good but raw; their auxiliary forces of Gauls
          are very numerous and very loyal. But certain persons by most unprincipled letters and
          misleading agents and messages induced Caesar—up to that time wholly governed by my
          advice, and personally possessed of brilliant ability and admirable firmness of
          character—to entertain <pb n="299"/> a very confident hope of the consulship. As soon as I
          discovered that, I never ceased offering him advice by letter in his absence, and
          remonstrating with his connexions who were in town, and who seemed to be supporting his
          ambition; nor in the senate did I hesitate to lay bare the sources of a most criminal
          plot. Nor indeed do I remember a better disposition on the part of senate or magistrates.
          For in the case of voting an extra-constitutional office to a man of power, or rather of
          super-eminent power—since power now depends on force and arms—it never yet happened that
          no tribune, no one in any other office, no private senator was found to support it. But in
          spite of this firmness and manly spirit, the city was after all in a state of anxiety. For
          we are flouted, Brutus, both by the airs assumed by the soldiers and the arrogance of
          their commander. Each man claims to be powerful in the Republic in proportion to his
          physical force. Reason, moderation, law, custom, duty—all go for nothing: as do the
          judgment and opinion of their fellow citizens, and their respect for the verdict of
          posterity. It was because I foresaw all this long ago that I was on the point of flying
          from Italy at the time when the report of the edicts issued by you and Cassius recalled
          me. You also roused my spirits, Brutus, at Velia. For though it vexed me to be going to a
          city from which you who freed it were an exile—which had also happened to me formerly in a
          similar danger, though with more melancholy result-yet I continued my journey and reached
          Rome, and without any guard to protect me I shook the power of Antony, and encouraged by
          my influence and advice the protecting force offered by Caesar against his treasonable
          arms. And if Caesar keeps his word and follows my counsel, I think we shall have
          protection enough. But if the counsels of the disloyal have greater weight than mine, or
          if the weakness of his time of life proves unequal to the strain of the business, our
          whole hope is in you. Wherefore fly hither, I beseech you, and put the last touch to the
          freedom of a state, which you liberated by courage and high spirit rather than by any
          fortunate coincidence. Men of all sorts will crowd round you. Write and urge Cassius to do
          the same. Hope of liberty is nowhere to be found except in the headquarters of your two
          camps. We have, it is true, <pb n="300"/> generals and armies in the west on which we Can
          rely. The protecting force of the young Caesar, for instance, I regard at present as
          trustworthy: but so many are trying to shake his loyalty that at times I am mortally
          afraid of his giving way. <milestone unit="para"/>That is a complete view of the political
          situation, as it exists at the moment at which I write. I could wish that it might improve
          as we go on: but if otherwise—which God forbid! I shall grieve for the sake of the
          Republic, which ought to have been immortal: but for myself—what a brief span of life is
          left! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=9" type="letter" xml:id="s897">
        <head>DCCCXCVII (BRUT. I, 9)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (8 JUNE)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> I would have performed the function, which you performed in my own time of mourning, and
          have written you a letter of consolation, had I not known that you did not stand in need
          of those remedies in your sorrow with which you relieved mine. And I should hope that you
          will now more easily heal your own wound than you then could mine. <note n="1"
            anchored="true">See vol. iii., pp.197, 201. Cicero there says that Brutus's letter gave
            him no consolation. This letter is to <foreign xml:lang="la">condole</foreign> with
              <foreign xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign> on the death of his wife <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Porcia</foreign>. The ordinary story—told by Plutarch and others—is that
            she committed suicide by swallowing burning charcoal after the death of <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Brutus</foreign>. But there was another account that she died a natural
            death. Her illness is alluded to p. 252. If this letter is genuine the latter account
            must be the true one. </note> It is, moreover, quite unlike a man as great as you are
          not to be able to do himself what be has enjoined on another. For myself, the arguments
          which you had collected, as well as your personal influence, deterred me from excessive
          indulgence in grief: for when I seemed to you to be bearing my sorrow with less firmness
          than was becoming to a man, and especially one accustomed to console others, you wrote
          upbraiding me in sharper terms than were usual with you. Accordingly, putting a high value
          on your opinion, and having a wholesome awe of it, I pulled myself together and regarded
          what I had learnt, read, and been taught as being the weightier by the addition of your
          authority. And at that time, Brutus, I owed nothing except to duty and nature: you now
          have to regard the people and the stage—to use a common expression. For since the eyes not
          only of your army, but of all the citizens, and I ought almost to say of all the world,
          are fixed on you, it is not at all seemly that the man who makes us all braver should
          himself seem weakened in mind. To sum up: you have met with a sorrow—for you <pb n="308"/>
          have lost a thing unparalleled in the world—and you must needs suffer from so severe a
          wound, lest the fact of having no sense of sorrow should be a greater misfortune than
          sorrow itself: but that you should do so in moderation is advantageous to others,
          necessary for yourself. I would have written at greater length, had not even this been
          already too much. We are expecting you and your army, without which-even if everything
          else succeeds to our wishes—we seem likely to be scarcely as free as we could desire. On
          the whole political situation I will write at greater length, and perhaps with more
          certainty, in the letter which I think of handing to our friend Vetus. <note n="1"
            anchored="true">See pp.205, 313. </note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=13" type="letter" xml:id="s903">
        <head>CMIII (BRUT. I, 13)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>M. IUNIUS BRUTUS TO CICERO (AT ROME)</salute>
          <dateline>MACEDONIA, I JULY</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> The fear which others entertain makes me nervous about M. Lepidus. If he has wrenched
          himself from us—which I hope it will turn out that people have suspected about him
          hurriedly and without good grounds—I beg and beseech you, Cicero, appealing to our close
          friendship and your kindness to me, to forget that my sister's children are the sons of
          Lepidus, and to consider that I have succeeded to the place of their father. If I can
          induce you to do that, there is certainly nothing that you will hesitate to undertake for
          them. Some people live on one sort of terms with their relations, others on another, but I
          cannot do enough for my sister's children to satisfy my affection or duty. What
          consideration is there, moreover, which either the loyalists can shew me—if I am but
          worthy of some consideration from them—or what can I promise my mother and sister and
          these children, if Brutus being their uncle has no weight with you and the senate against
          the fact of Lepidus being their father? I am neither able for anxiety and vexation to
          write at great length to you, nor ought I to do so. For in a matter of so much importance
          and so vitally affecting me, if I need words in order to move your interest and confirm
          your resolution, there is no hope that you will do what I wish or what you <pb n="313"/>
          are in duty bound to do. Therefore don't expect a lengthy petition from me. Only fix your
          eyes on me, who have a good right to obtain this service from you, either on private
          grounds from Cicero the man—and the closest of my friends—or from the consular, all
          private ties put aside. What you mean to do please write and tell me as soon as possible.
            <milestone unit="para"/>1 July, in camp. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=12" type="letter" xml:id="s904">
        <head>CMIV (BRUT. I, 12)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (BEGINNING OF JULY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> Though I am immediately about to give a letter to Messalla Corvinus, <note n="1"
            anchored="true">The celebrated M. Valerius <foreign xml:lang="la">Messalla</foreign>
            Corvinus, the protector of Tibullus. See p.76. For Vetus see p.308. </note> yet I could
          not let our friend Vetus reach you without a letter from me. The Republic, Brutus, is in
          the most imminent peril, and though victorious we are forced to begin the struggle once
          more. This is the result of the crime and infatuation of M. Lepidus. At such a time, while
          many things afflict me owing to the anxiety I feel for the Republic, yet nothing has given
          me greater vexation than to be unable to grant the petitions of your mother and sister:
          for as to yourself—which is of the greatest importance in my eyes—I think that I shall
          have no difficulty in satisfying you. The fact is that the position of Lepidus cannot on
          any consideration be separated from that of Antony, and in the judgment of all is even a
          worse one, both because he had been complimented by the senate with the most splendid
          honours, and had even sent an excellent despatch to the senate a few days before. Suddenly
          he not only receives the remnants of the enemy, but begins a war by land and sea with the
          greatest ferocity, the result of which is still in the balance. Therefore, while we are
          asked to shew consideration to his children, no guarantee is offered that we shall not
          undergo the most extreme penalties, if their father— <pb n="314"/> which God forbid—is
          victorious. Not indeed that I fail to consider how cruel it is that the crimes of parents
          should be expiated by the punishment of sons. But it is an excellent doctrine in law that
          affection for children should make parents more loyal to the Republic: therefore it is
          Lepidus that is Cruel to his children, not he who declares Lepidus a public enemy. Nay,
          even if he laid down his arms and was condemned for vis—a prosecution in which he would
          have no defence to offer-his sons would have met with the same disaster by the
          confiscation of his property. However, what your mother and sister deprecate in the case
          of his children, that very thing and measures more cruel still are what Lepidus, Antony,
          and the rest denounce against us. Therefore our chief hope at this time is in you and your
          army. It is of very great importance both to the highest interests of the Republic and to
          your own glory and political position that—as I wrote to say before-you should come to
          Italy at the earliest possible Opportunity: for the Republic stands sorely in need both of
          your material forces and of your counsel. I have gladly, in pursuance of what you said in
          your letter, opened my arms to Vetus as his affection and his extreme loyalty to you
          deserved, and I have found him most zealous and devoted both to yourself and the Republic.
          My son I hope shortly to see: for I feel confident that he will promptly come to Italy in
          your train. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=14" type="letter" xml:id="s908">
        <head>CMVIII (BRUT. I, 14)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, II JULY</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> YOURS was a very short letter. "Short" do I say? Rather it was not a letter at all.
          Brutus write to me in three lines at such a crisis as this? I would rather have written
          nothing at all. And you talk of not hearing from me! Which of your men ever came to you
          without a letter from me? And what epistle of mine had not something of weight in it? And
          if they have not reached you, I think that your family letters cannot have done So either.
          You say that you will give a longer letter to my son. So far, so good: but even this one
          ought to have had more matter in it. Now upon your writing to me about my son's quitting
          you, I immediately bustled my letter-carriers off with a letter to my son telling him
          that, even if he came to Italy, he should return to you: for nothing could be more
          gratifying to me and nothing more honourable to him. However, I had several times written
          to tell him that <pb n="318"/> the election to the sacred colleges had by great exertions
          on my part been put off to another year. This I had taken pains to do for the sake of my
          son, and also for that of Domitius, Cato, Lentulus, and the Bibuli—as I wrote to tell you.
          But of course when you sent me that stingy little note this was not yet known to you.
          Wherefore I urge you, my dear Brutus, with all my might not to send my son from your side,
          and to bring him home with you in person, which if you have any regard for the Republic,
          for which you were born, you ought to do at once. For the war has revived—and a very
          serious one—owing to the crime of Lepidus: while Caesar's army, which was in an excellent
          state, is not only of no service, but even makes it necessary for your army to be
          summoned. If that once reaches Italy there will not be a single citizen, deserving to be
          called such, who will not find his way to your camp. It is true that Decimus Brutus has
          effected a splendid junction with Plancus, yet you are not ignorant how uncertain are
          men's feelings when infected with party spirit, how uncertain the results of battles. Nay,
          even if we conquer, as I hope, nevertheless the public service will require a great deal
          of guidance from your wisdom and your influence. Come to our help, therefore, in God's
          name, and that as soon as possible: and assure yourself that you did not do better service
          to your country by the Ides of March, on which you shook the yoke of slavery from your
          fellow citizens, than you will do if you now arrive in good time. <milestone unit="para"
          />11 July. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=15" type="letter" xml:id="s909">
        <head>CMIX (BRUT. I, 15)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME (MIDDLE OF JULY)</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> You have Messalla with you. What letter, therefore, can I write with such minute care as
          to enable me to explain to you what is being done and what is occurring in public affairs,
          more thoroughly than he will describe them to you, who has at once the most intimate
          knowledge of everything, <pb n="319"/> and the talent for unfolding and conveying it to
          you in the best possible manner? For beware of thinking, Brutus—for though it is
          unnecessary for me to write to you what you know already, yet I cannot pass over in
          silence such eminence in every kind of greatness-beware of thinking, I say, that he has
          any parallel in honesty and firmness, care and zeal for the Republic. So much so that in
          him eloquence—in which he is extraordinarily eminent-scarcely seems to offer any
          opportunity for praise. Yet in this accomplishment itself his wisdom is made more evident;
          with such excellent judgement and with so much acuteness has he practised himself in the
          most genuine style of rhetoric. Such also is his industry, and so great the amount of
          midnight labour that he bestows on this study, that the chief thanks would not seem to be
          due to natural genius, great as it is in his case. <note n="1" anchored="true">According
            to Eusebius,<foreign xml:lang="la">Messalla</foreign> was born in <date when="-0059"
              >B.C. 59</date>. He would in that case be now only between fifteen and sixteen, and
            could not possibly have done anything to justify this panegyric or to account for it.
            Accordingly, it has been argued that he was born in <date when="-0070">B.C. 70</date>,
            one of the many expedients that have had to be resorted to to prove the genuineness of
            these letters. He survived to make the motion in the senate (<date when="-0002">B.C.
              2</date>) conferring on Augustus the title of <foreign xml:lang="la">pater
              patriae</foreign> (<bibl n="Suet. Aug. 58">Suet. Aug. 58</bibl>). As, however, he was
            contemporary with young Marcus at Athens, he was probably born about <date when="-0065"
              >B.C. 65</date>. See vol. iii., p.225. </note> But my affection carries me away: for
          it is not the purpose of this letter to praise Messalla, especially to Brutus; to whom his
          excellence is not less known than it is to me, and these particular accomplishments of his
          which I am praising even better. Grieved as I was to let him go from my side, my one
          consolation was that in going to you who are to me a second self; he was performing a duty
          and following the path of the truest glory. But enough of this I now come, after a long
          interval of time, to a certain letter of yours, in which, while paying me many
          compliments, you find one fault with me—that I was excessive and, as it were, extravagant
          in proposing votes of honour. That is your criticism: another's, perhaps, might be that I
          was too stern in inflicting punishment and exacting penalties, unless by chance you blame
          me for both. If that is so, I desire that my principle in both these things should be very
          clearly known to you. And I do not rely solely on the dictum of Solon, who was at once the
          wisest of the Seven and the only <pb n="320"/> lawgiver among them. He said that a state
          was kept together by two things-reward and punishment. Of course there is a certain
          moderation to be observed in both, as in everything else, and what we may call a golden
          mean in both these things. But I have no intention to dilate on such an important subject
          in this place. <milestone unit="para"/>But what has been my aim during this war in the
          motions I have made in the senate I think it will not be out of place to explain. After
          the death of Caesar and your ever memorable Ides of March, Brutus, you have not forgotten
          what I said had been omitted by you and your colleagues, and what a heavy cloud I declared
          to be hanging over the Republic. A great pest had been removed by your means, a great blot
          on the Roman people wiped out, immense glory in truth acquired by yourselves: but an
          engine for exercising king. y power had been put into the hands of Lepidus and Antony, of
          whom the former was the more fickle of the two, the latter the more corrupt, but both of
          whom dreaded peace and were enemies to quiet. Against these men, inflamed with the
          ambition of revolutionizing the state, we had no protecting force to oppose. For the fact
          of the matter was this: the state had become roused as one man to maintain its liberty; I
          at the time was even excessively warlike; you, perhaps with more wisdom, quitted the city
          which you had liberated, and when Italy offered you her services declined them.
          Accordingly, when I saw the city in the possession of parricides, and that neither you nor
          Cassius could remain in it with safety, and that it was held down by Antony's armed
          guards, I thought that I too ought to leave it: for a city held down by traitors, with all
          opportunity of giving aid cut off, was a shocking spectacle. But the same spirit as always
          had animated me, staunch to the love of country, did not admit the thought of a departure
          from its dangers. Accordingly, in the very midst of my voyage to Achaia, when in the
          period of the Etesian gales a south wind—as though remonstrating against my design—had
          brought me back to Italy, I saw you at Velia and was much distressed: for you were on the
          point of leaving the country, Brutus—leaving it, I say, for our friends the Stoics deny
          that wise men ever "flee." As soon as I reached Rome I at once threw myself in opposition
          to Antony's treason and insane policy: and having roused his wrath against me, I <pb
            n="321"/> began entering upon a policy truly Brutus-like—for this is the distinctive
          mark of your family—that of freeing my country. The rest of the story is too long to tell,
          and must be passed over by me, for it is about myself. I will only say this much: that
          this young Caesar, thanks to whom we still exist, if we would confess the truth, was a
          stream from the fountain-head of my policy. To him I voted honours, none indeed, Brutus,
          that were not his due, none that were not inevitable. For directly we began the recovery
          of liberty, when the divine excellence of even Decimus Brutus had not yet bestirred itself
          sufficiently to give us an indication of the truth, and when our sole protection depended
          on the boy who had shaken Antony from our shoulders, what honour was there that he did not
          deserve to have decreed to him? However, all I then proposed for him was a complimentary
          vote. of thanks, and that too expressed with moderation. I also proposed a decree
          conferring imperium on him, which, although it seemed too great a compliment for one of
          his age, was yet necessary for one commanding an army—for what is an army without a
          commander with imperium ? <note n="1" anchored="true">This is founded on <bibl
              n="Cic. Phil. 5.45">Phil. 5.45</bibl>
          </note> Philippus proposed a statue; Servius at first proposed a licence to stand for
          office before the regular time. Servilius afterwards proposed that the time should be
          still farther curtailed. At that time nothing was thought too good for him. <milestone
            unit="para"/>But somehow men are more easily found who are liberal at a time of alarm,
          than grateful when victory has been won. For when that most joyful day of Decimus Brutus's
          relief from blockade had dawned on the Republic and happened also to be his birthday, I
          proposed that the name of Brutus should be entered in the fasti under that date. And in
          that I followed the example of our ancestors, who paid this honour to the woman Laurentia,
          at whose altar in the Velabrum you pontiffs are accustomed to offer sacrifice. And when I
          proposed this honour to Brutus I wished that there should be in the fasti an eternal
          memorial of a most welcome victory: and yet on that very day I discovered that the
          ill-disposed in the senate were somewhat in a majority over the grateful. In the course of
          those same days I lavished honours—if you like that word-upon the dead Hirtius, Pansa, and
            <pb n="322"/> even Aquila. And who has any fault to find with that, unless he be one
          who, no sooner an alarm is over, forgets the past danger? There was added to this grateful
          memorial of a benefit received some consideration of what would be for the good of
          posterity also; for I wished that there should exist some perpetual record of the popular
          execration of our most ruthless enemies. I suspect that the next step does not meet with
          your approbation. It was disapproved by your friends, who are indeed most excellent
          citizens, but inexperienced in public business. I mean my proposing an ovation for Caesar.
          For myself; however—though I am perhaps wrong, and I am not a man who believes his own way
          necessarily right—I think that in the course of this war I never took a more prudent step.
          The reason for this I must not reveal, lest I should seem to have a sense of favours to
          come rather than to be grateful for those received. I have said too much already: let us
          look at other points. I proposed honours to Decimus Brutus, and also to Lucius Plancus.
          Those indeed are noble spirits whose spur to action is glory but the senate also is wise
          to avail itself of any means-provided that they are honourable—by which it thinks that a
          particular man can be induced to support the Republic. But—you say—I am blamed in regard
          to Lepidus: for, having placed his statue on the rostra, I also voted for its removal.
            <note n="1" anchored="true">When Lepidus was declared a public enemy. See p.300. </note>
          I tried by paying him a compliment to recall him from his insane policy. The infatuation
          of that most unstable of men rendered my prudence futile. Yet all the same more good was
          done by demolishing the statue of Lepidus, than harm by putting it up. <milestone
            unit="para"/>Enough about honours; now I must say a few words about penalties. For I
          have gathered from frequent expressions in your letters that in regard to those whom you
          have conquered in war, you desire that your clemency should be praised. <note n="2"
            anchored="true">See p. 216. </note> I hold, indeed, that you do and say nothing but what
          becomes a philosopher. But to omit the punishment of a crime—for that is what "pardoning"
          amounts to-even if it is endurable in other cases, is mischievous in a war like this. For
          there has been no civil war, of all that have <pb n="323"/> occurred in the state within
          my memory, in which there was not certain to be some form of constitution remaining,
          whichever of the two sides prevailed. In this war, if we are victorious, I should not find
          it easy to affirm what kind of constitution we are likely to have; if we are conquered,
          there will certainly never be any. I therefore proposed severe measures against Antony,
          and severe ones also against Lepidus, and not so much out of revenge as in order that I
          might for the present prevent unprincipled men by this terror from attacking their
          country, and might for the future establish a warning for all who were minded to imitate
          their infatuation. However, this proposal was not mine more than it was everybody's. The
          point in it which had the appearance of cruelty was that the penalty extended to the
          children who did not deserve any. But that is a thing of long standing and characteristic
          of all states. For instance, the children of Themistocles were in poverty. And if the same
          penalty attaches to citizens legally condemned in court, how could we be more indulgent to
          public enemies? What, moreover, can anyone say against me when he must confess that, had
          that man conquered, he would have been still more revengeful towards me? <milestone
            unit="para"/>Here you have the principles which dictated my senatorial proposals, at any
          rate in regard to this class of honours and penalties. For, in regard to other matters, I
          think you have been told what opinions I have expressed and what votes I have given. But
          all this is not so very pressing What is really pressing, Brutus, is that you should come
          to Italy with your army as soon as possible. There is the greatest anxiety for your
          arrival. Directly you reach Italy all classes will flock to you. For whether we win the
          victory—and we had in fact won a most glorious one, only that Lepidus set his heart on
          ruining everything and perishing himself with all his friends-there will be need of your
          counsel in establishing some form of constitution. And even if there is still some
          fighting left to be done, our greatest hope is both in your personal influence and in the
          material strength of your army. But make haste, in ,God's name! You know the importance of
          seizing the right moment, and of rapidity What pains I am taking in the interests of your
          sister's children, I hope you know from the letters of your mother <pb n="324"/> and
          sister. <note n="1" anchored="true">
            <foreign xml:lang="la">Servilia</foreign> and his half-sister <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Iunia</foreign>, wife of Lepidus. </note> In undertaking their Cause I shew more
          regard to your affection, which is very precious to me, than, as some think, to my own
          consistency. But there is nothing in which I more wish to be and to seem consistent than
          in loving you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="text=BRUT.:book=1:letter=18" type="letter" xml:id="s910">
        <head>CMX (BRUT. I, 18)</head>

        <opener>
          <salute>TO M. IUNIUS BRUTUS (IN MACEDONIA)</salute>
          <dateline>ROME, 27 JULY</dateline>
        </opener>
        <p> AFTER I had often urged you by letter to come as soon as possible to the aid of the
          state, and to bring your army into Italy, and when I thought that your relatives had no
          doubt on that subject, I was asked by that most prudent and careful lady your mother—whose
          every thought and care are directed and devoted to you—to call on her on the 24th of July,
          which, as in duty bound, I at once did. On my arrival, I found Casca, Labeo, and Scaptius
            <note n="2" anchored="true">Q. Antistius Labeo—one of the assassins—caused a slave to
            kill him in his tent after the battle at <foreign xml:lang="la">Philippi</foreign>
              (<bibl n="TLG551.17 4.135">App. B.C. 4.135</bibl>). For <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Casca</foreign> see p.249. M. Scaptius had carried on a banking business in <foreign
              xml:lang="la">Cilicia</foreign>, and was the agent of <foreign xml:lang="la"
              >Brutus</foreign> there. See vol. ii., pp.128, 135 sq. </note> there. Well, she opened
          the subject and asked me my opinion, whether we should ask you to come to Italy, and
          whether we thought that to your advantage, or whether it were better that you should put
          it off and stay where you were. I answered—as was my real opinion—that it was of the
          highest advantage to your position and reputation to bring help at the first possible
          moment to the tottering and almost prostrate Republic. For what disaster do you think is
          wanting in a war, in which the victorious armies refuse to pursue a flying enemy, and in
          which an officer with imperium in full possession of his rights, enjoying the most
          splendid honours and the most ample fortune, with wife and children, with you and Cassius
          related to him by marriage, has yet proclaimed war on the Republic? How can I use the
          words "in such <pb n="325"/> unanimity of senate and people," when such fatal mischief
          abides within our very walls? But the bitterest sorrow which is affecting me as I write
          this is that, whereas the Republic accepted me as a surety for that youth, or, I might
          almost say, that boy, I seem scarcely able to make my promise good. Truly, a guarantee for
          another's feeling and sentiment, especially in affairs of the greatest importance, is more
          onerous and difficult than one for money. For money can be paid, and a loss of property is
          bearable. But how are you to make good what you have guaranteed to the state, unless he
          for whom you undertook the obligation is willing that it should be fulfilled? <note n="1"
            anchored="true">That is, in the case of a guarantee of conduct, which necessarily
            depends on the persons for whom the guarantee is given being willing to conform to a
            certain standard of behaviour. The allusion is to Octavian. </note> However, I shall
          retain even him, I hope, in spite of many adverse influences. For he seems to have a
          character of his own, though he is at the pliable time of life, and there are many
          prepared to corrupt him, who hope that, by holding out before him the glamour of false
          honour, the sight of a naturally good intelligence may be blinded. Accordingly, to my
          other labours has been added the task of applying every engine to the keeping of a hold
          upon the young man, that I may not incur a reputation for rashness. However, where is the
          rashness? I bound the man, for whom I gave the guarantee, more tightly than I did myself;
          nor can the state regret my having given a guarantee for one who in the actual campaign
          was rendered more resolute by my promise, as well as from his own disposition. But, unless
          I am mistaken, the greatest difficulty in the Republic is the want of money. For the
          loyalists grow daily more callous to the call for property tax. All that was collected by
          the one per cent. income tax, owing to the shameless returns made by the wealthy, is
          exhausted by the bounties given to two legions: whereas endless expenses are hanging over
          us, both for the armies now protecting us, and for yours—for our friend Cassius seems able
          to come home very well provided. But of this and many other things I desire to talk to you
          when we meet, and that as soon as possible. About your sister's sons, <note n="2"
            anchored="true">The sons of Lepidus and <foreign xml:lang="la">Iunia</foreign>. </note>
          Brutus, I did not wait for you to write. As a matter of fact, the state of the <pb n="326"
          /> times itself—for the war will be protracted-guarantees that the case will be left for
          you to decide. But from the very first, though I could not divine the long continuance of
          the war, I pleaded the cause of the boys in the senate, as I think you Can have learnt
          from your mother's letter. <note n="1" anchored="true">This and the assertion in the
            previous letter seem directly contradictory to Letter DCCCCIV, p.314. </note> Nor will
          there ever arise any circumstance in which I shall not, even at the risk of my life, say
          and do whatever I think is your wish and to your interest. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
