<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five - 44</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol. A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>
                                History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end, with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books
                            </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change> </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="2057" xml:id="p.2057"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XLIV.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p>
                        Quintus Marcius Philippus, the consul, penetrates into Macedonia through
the rugged passes, and takes several cities. The Rhodians send an em-
bassy to Rome, threatening to aid Perseus, unless the Romans made
peace with him. This act was received with general indignation. Lucius
Aemilius Paullus, the consul, sent against Perseus, defeats him, and re-
duces all Macedonia to subjection. Before the engagement, Caius Sul-
picius Gallus, a military tribune, foretells an eclipse of the moon, and
warns the soldiers not to be alarmed at that phenomenon. Gentius, king
of Illyria, vanquished by Anicius the praetor, and sent prisoner, together
with his wife and children, to Rome. Ambassadors from Ptolemy and
Cleopatra, king and queen of Egypt, complain of Antiochus making war
upon them. Perseus, not paying Eumenes, king of Pergamus, and Gen-
tius, king of Illyria, the money he had promised them for their assistance,
is deserted by them.
                    </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    EARLY in the spring which succeeded the winter in which these transactions took place, the consul, Quintus Marcius Philippus, set out from Rome, with five thousand men, whom he was to carry over to reinforce his legions, and arrived at Brundusium. Marcus Popilius, of consular rank, and other young men of equal dignity, accompanied him, in the capacity of military tribunes for the legions in Macedonia.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Nearly at the same time, Caius Marcius Figulus, the praetor, whose province was the fleet, came to Brundusium; and, both sailing from Italy, made Corcyra on the second day, and Actium, a port of Acarnania, on the third.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, then, disembarking at Ambracia, proceeded towards Thessaly by land. The praetor, doubling Cape Leucate, sailed into the gulf of Corinth; then, leaving his ships at Creusa, he went by land also through the middle of Bœotia, and, by a quick journey of one day, came to the fleet at Chalcis.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Aulus Hostilius at that time lay encamped in Thessaly, near Palaepharsalus; and though he had performed no warlike act of any consequence, yet he had reformed his troops from a state of dissolute licentiousness, and brought them to exact military discipline; had
                    <pb n="2058" xml:id="p.2058"/>
                    faithfully consulted the interest of the allies, and defended them from every kind of injury.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On hearing of his successor's approach, he carefully inspected the arms, men, and horses; and then, with the army in complete order, he marched out to meet the consul. Their first meeting was such as became their own dignity and the Roman character; and in transacting business afterwards,
                    <hi rend="italics">they preserved the greatest harmony and propriety.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        words in Italics are introduced conjecturally, to supply chasms in the original.
                    </note>
                    The proconsul, addressing himself to the troops,
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        exhorted them to behave with courage, and with due respect to the orders of their commander. He then recommended them, in warm terms, to the consul, and, as
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        soon as he had despatched the necessary affairs, set off for Rome.
                    </hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The words in Italics are introduced conjecturally, to supply chasms in the original.
                    </note>
                    A few days after, the consul
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    made a speech to his soldiers, which began with the unnatural
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    murder which Perseus had perpetrated on his brother, and meditated against his father; he then mentioned
                    <quote>
                        his acquisition of the kingdom by nefarious practices; his poisonings and murders; his abominable attempt to
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        assassinate Eumenes; the injuries he had committed against the Roman people; and his plundering the cities of their allies, in violation of the treaty.
                    </quote>
                    <quote>How detestable such proceedings were in the sight of the gods, Perseus would feel,</quote>
                    he said,
                    <quote>
                        in the issue of his
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        affairs; for the gods always favoured righteous and honourable dealings; by means of which the Roman people had risen to so great an exaltation.
                    </quote>
                    He next compared the strength of the Roman people, which now embraced the whole world, with that of Macedonia, and the armies of the one with those of the
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    other; and then added,
                    <quote>
                        How much more powerful armies of Philip and Antiochus had been conquered by forces not more numerous than the present!
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Having animated the minds of his soldiers by such exhortations, he began to consult on a general plan of operations for the campaign; being joined by the praetor, Caius Marcius, who, after receiving the command of the fleet, came thither from Chalcis.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    It was resolved not to waste time by delaying longer in Thessaly; but to decamp immediately, and advance thence into Macedonia;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    and that the praetor should exert himself to the utmost, that the fleet might appear, at the same time, on the enemy's coasts.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The praetor then having been
                    <pb n="2059" xml:id="p.2059"/>
                    sent away, the consul, having ordered the soldiers to carry with them a month's provisions, struck his tents, on the tenth day after he received the command of the army, and proceeded one day's march.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He then called together his guides, and ordered them to explain, in the presence of the council, by what road each of them proposed to lead him; then, having dismissed them, he asked the opinion of the council, as to what route he should prefer.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Some advised the road through Pythium; others, that over the Cambunian mountains, by which the consul Hostilius had marched the year before; while others, again, preferred that which passed by the side of the Lake Ascuris.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    There was yet before him a considerable length of road common to each of these routes; the further consideration of this matter was therefore postponed until they should encamp near the place where the roads diverged.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He then marched into Perrhaebia, and posted himself between Azorus and Doliche, in order to consider again which was the preferable road.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    In the mean time, Perseus, understanding that the enemy was marching towards him, but unable to guess what route he might take, resolved to secure all the passes by guards.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    To the top of the Cambunian mountains, called by the natives Volustana, he sent ten thousand light infantry, under the command of Asclepiodotus; ordering Hippias, with a detachment of twelve thousand Macedonians, to guard the pass called Lapathus, near a fort which stood over the Lake Ascuris.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He himself, with the rest of his forces, lay for some time in camp at Dium;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    but afterwards, as if he had lost the use of his judgment, and was incapable of forming any plan, he used to gallop along the coast, with a party of light horse, sometimes to Heracleum, sometimes to Phila, and then return with the same speed to Dium.
                </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    By this time the consul had determined to march through the pass near Octolophus, where, as we have mentioned, the camp of the king formerly stood.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But he deemed it prudent to despatch before him four thousand men, to secure such places as might be useful: the command of this party was given to Marcus Claudius, and Quintus Marcius the consul's son.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The main body followed close after; but the road was so steep, rough, and craggy, that the advanced party of light troops, with great difficulty, effected in two days a march of fifteen miles; and then encamped. They call the place
                    <pb n="2060" xml:id="p.2060"/>
                    which they took, the tower of Eudieru.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Next day they advanced seven miles; and, having seized on a hill at a small distance from the enemy's camp, sent back a message to the consul, that
                    <quote>
                        they had come up with the enemy; and had taken post in a place which was safe and convenient in every respect; urging him to join them with all possible speed.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    This message came to the consul at the Lake Ascuris, at a time when he was full of anxiety, on account of the badness of the road on which he had entered, and for the fate of the small force he had sent forward into the midst of the posts of the enemy.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    His spirits were therefore greatly revived; and, soon effecting a junction of all his forces, he pitched his camp on the side of the hill that had been seized, where the ground was the most commodious.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This hill was so high as to afford a wide-extended prospect, presenting to their eyes, at one view, not only the enemy's camp, which was little more than a mile distant, but the whole extent of territory to Dium and Phila, together with a large tract of the sea-coast;
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    circumstances which greatly enlivened the courage of the soldiers, giving them so near a view of the grand theatre of the war, of all the king's forces, and of the country of the enemy.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    So eager were they, that they pressed the consul to lead them on directly to the enemy's camp; but, after the fatigue that they had suffered on the road, one day was set apart for repose.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    On the third day, the consul, leaving one half of his troops to guard the camp, drew out his forces against the enemy.
                </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Hippias had been sent by the king, a short time before, to maintain that pass; and having employed himself, since he first saw the Roman camp on the hill, in preparing his men's minds for a battle, he now went forth to meet the consul's army as it advanced.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans came out to battle with light armour, as did the enemy; light troops being the fittest to commence the engagement.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    As soon as they met, therefore, they instantly discharged their javelins, and many wounds were given and received on both sides in a disorderly kind of conflict; but few of either party were killed.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This only roused their courage for the following day, when they would have engaged with more numerous forces, and with greater animosity, had there been room to form a line; but the summit of the mountain was contracted into a ridge so
                    <pb n="2061" xml:id="p.2061"/>
                    narrow, as scarcely to allow space for three files in front;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    so that, while but few were fighting, the greater part, especially such as carried heavy arms, stood mere spectators of the fight. The light troops even ran through the hollows of the hill, and attacked the flanks of the light-armed troops of the enemy; and alike through even and uneven places, sought to come to action.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    That day, greater numbers were wounded than killed, and night put a stop to the dispute.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The Roman general was greatly at a loss how to proceed on the third day; for to remain on that naked hill was impossible, and he could not return without disgrace, and even danger, if the enemy with the advantage of the ground, should press on his troops in their retreat:
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    he had therefore no other plan left than to improve his bold attempt, by persevering resolution, which sometimes, in the issue, proves the wiser course.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    He had, in fact, brought himself into such a situation, that if he had had to deal with an enemy like the ancient kings of Macedon, he might have suffered a severe defeat. But while the king, with his horsemen, ran up and down the shore at Dium; and though at a distance of twelve miles, he was almost within hearing of the shout and noise of his forces who were engaged, neither strengthened his forces by sending up fresh men to relieve the weary, nor, what was most material, appeared himself in the action;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    the Roman general, notwithstanding that he was above sixty years old, and unwieldy through corpulency, performed actively every duty of a commander.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He persisted with extraordinary resolution in his bold undertaking; and, leaving Popilius to guard the summit, marched across, through trackless places, having sent forward a party to open a road. Attalus and Misagenes, with the auxiliary troops of their own nations, were ordered to protect them, while clearing the way through the forests.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    He himself, keeping the cavalry and baggage before him, closed the rear with the legions.
                </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    In descending the mountain, the men suffered inexpressible fatigue, besides the frequent falling of the cattle and their loads, so that, before they had advanced quite four miles, they began to think that their most eligible plan would be to return, if they could, by the way they had come.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The elephants caused almost as much confusion among the troops as an enemy could; for, when they came to impassable steeps, they threw off their riders, and set up such a hideous roar, as spread terror through all, especially among the horses, until a method
                    <pb n="2062" xml:id="p.2062"/>
                    was contrived for bringing them down.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    They fastened in the earth, in the line of descent, some way from the top, two long, strong posts, distant from each other a little more
                    <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/>
                    than the breadth of the animal, on which were fastened beams thirty feet long, so as to form a kind of bridge, and covered it with earth;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    after a little intermediate space, a second and similar bridge was formed; then a third bridge, with several others one after another, where the rocks were precipitous.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The elephant walked forward on solid footing upon the bridge; but, before he came to the end, the posts underneath were cut, and the bridge falling, obliged him to slide down gently to the beginning of the next bridge, which some of them performed standing, others on their haunches.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    When they arrived at the level of another bridge, they were again carried down, by its falling in like manner; and so on until they came to more level ground. The Romans advanced that day scarcely more than seven miles; and even of this journey little was performed on foot.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Their method of proceeding in general was rolling themselves down, together with their arms and other encumbrances, with every kind of discomfort; insomuch, that even their commander, who led them such a march, did not deny, but that the whole army might have been cut off by a small party.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    During the night, they arrived at a small plain; but, as it was hemmed in on every side, there was no opportunity of discover- ing whether it was a position of danger or not. However, as they had, beyond their expectation, at length found good footing, they judged it necessary to wait, during the next day, in that deep valley for Popilius, and the forces left behind with him;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    who, though the enemy gave them no disturbance from any quarter, suffered severely from the difficulties of the ground, — as if they had been harassed by an enemy.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    These having joined the main body, the whole proceeded, on the third day, through a pass called by the natives Callipeuce.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    On the fourth day they marched down through places equally trackless, but more cleverly in consequence of their experience, and with more comfortable hopes, as they saw no enemy any where, and as they were coming nearer to the sea, into the plains, where they pitched their camp of infantry between Heracleum and Libethrus, the greater part being posted on hills, the rest occupying a valley and part of the plain where
                    <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    the cavalry encamped.
                    <pb n="2063" xml:id="p.2063"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The king, it is said, was bathing, when he was informed of the enemy's approach; on hearing which, he started up from his seat, and rushed out in a fright, crying out, that he was conquered without a battle;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and afterwards, in a state of great perturbation, amidst plans and orders dictated by fear, he recalled two most intimate friends from his garrisons, and sent one to Pella, where his treasure was lodged, and the other to Parthus, and opened all the passes to the invasion of the enemy.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    He himself, having suddenly removed from Dium all the gilded statues, that they might not fall a prey to the enemy, ordered all the inhabitants to remove to Pydna; and thus made the conduct of the consul, in venturing into a situation out of which he could not retreat without the enemy's permission, although it might have been deemed rash and inconsiderate, to wear the appearance of judicious boldness.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For there were only two passes through which the Romans could remove from their present situation; one through Tempe into Thessaly, the other by Dium into Macedonia; and both these were occupied by parties of the king's troops.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    So that if an intrepid commander had, only for ten days, maintained his ground, without yielding to the first appearance of an approaching terror, the Romans could neither have retreated by Tempe into Thessaly, nor have had any road open for the conveyance of provisions to their position.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    For Tempe is a pass of such a nature, that even supposing no obstruction was given by an enemy, it is difficult to get through it;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    being so narrow for the distance of five miles, that there is barely room for a loaded horse to pass:
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    the precipices, also, on both sides, are so abrupt, that it is scarcely possible to look down from them, without a dizziness alike of the eyes and the mind; while the roaring and depth of the river Peneus, flowing through the middle of the glen, increases the terrific effect.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    This defile, in its nature so dangerous, was guarded by parties of the king's troops, stationed in four different places: one near Gonnus, at the first entrance; another in an impregnable fortress at Condylos; a third near Lapathus, in a place called Charax; and the fourth on the road itself about midway, where the valley is narrowest, and might have been easily defended even by half a score men.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    All possibility either of retreating, or of receiving provisions through Tempe, being cut off, the Romans, in order to return, must have crossed
                    <pb n="2064" xml:id="p.2064"/>
                    over the same mountains from which they came down;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    but even though they might have been able to effect this by passing unobserved, they never could have accomplished it openly, and while the enemy kept possession of the heights;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    and besides, the difficulties which they had already experienced would have precluded every hope of the kind.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    In this rash enterprise they would have no other plan left than to force their way into Macedonia, through the midst of the enemy posted at Dium; and if the gods had not deprived the king of his understanding, this would have been extremely difficult.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    For the space between the foot of Mount Olympus and the sea is not much more than a mile in breadth;
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    one half of which is taken up by the mouth of the river Baphirus, which forms a large morass, and, of the remaining plain, a great share is occupied by the town and the temple of Jupiter: the rest, being a very small space, might have been shut up with a trench and rampart of no great length; or, so great was the plenty of stones and timber on the spot, that a wall might have been drawn across, and towers erected.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But the king's judgment was so entirely blinded by the sudden fright, that he reflected not upon any one of these circumstances;
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    on the contrary, he evacuated all his strong posts, and leaving them open to the enemy, fled back to Pydna.
                </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, perceiving in the folly and sloth of the enemy a most favourable prospect, not only of safety, but of success, sent back a messenger to Larissa, with orders to Spurius Lucretius to seize on the deserted forts about Tempe;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    then, sending forward Popilius, to examine all the passes round Dium, and learning that all was clear, he marched in two days to that town, ordering the camp to be fixed under the walls of the temple, that no violation might be offered to that sacred place.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    He went himself into the city; and seeing it, though not large, yet highly ornamented with public buildings and abundance of statues, and remarkably well fortified, he could scarcely believe that there was not some stratagem concealed in the abandonment of such important advantages without cause.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He waited therefore one day to examine all the country round; then he decamped; and supposing that he should find plenty of corn in Pieria, advanced to a river called the Mytis.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On the day following, continuing his march, he received the voluntary surrender of the city of Agasse; whereupon, in order
                    <pb n="2065" xml:id="p.2065"/>
                    to gain the good opinion of the rest of the Macedonians, he contented himself with receiving hostages, assuring the inhabitants, that he would leave them their city without a garrison, and that they should live free from taxes, and under their own laws.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Proceeding thence one day's march, he encamped at the river Ascordus; but, finding that the farther he removed from Thessaly, the greater was the scarcity of every thing, he returned to Dium;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    which clearly demonstrated how much he must have suffered if he had been cut off from Thes- saly, since he found it unsafe to go to any great distance from it.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus, having drawn all his forces into one body, and assembled all his generals, reprimanded severely the commanders of the garrisons, and particularly Hippias, and Asclepiodotus;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    asserting that they had betrayed to the Romans the keys of Macedonia; of which charge no one was more truly guilty than himself.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, on seeing the fleet at sea, conceived hopes that they were coming with provisions, for every article had now become very dear and very scarce; but when the ships came into harbour, he was informed that the transports had been left behind at Magnesia.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He was then under great perplexity to determine what measures to take; so hard did he find it to struggle with the difficulties of his situation, though not aggravated by any effort of the enemy;
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    when, very seasonably, a letter arrived from Lucretius, acquainting him that he was in possession of all the forts about Tempe and Phila, and had found in them great plenty of corn and other necessaries.
                </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, highly delighted with this intelligence, removed his quarters from Dium to Phila, in order to strengthen that post, and, at the same time, to distribute corn to the soldiers, on the spot, as the carriage of it thence would be tedious.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    That march gave rise to opinions not at all favourable to his reputation: some said that he retired from the enemy through fear; because if he had staid in Pieria he must have risked a battle:
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    others, that, not considering the daily changes produced by fortune in the affairs of war, he had let slip out of his hands advantages which threw themselves in his way, and which, in all probability, he could never regain.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For, by giving up the possession of Dium, he at once roused the enemy to action; who at length saw the necessity of endeavouring to recover what he had lost before, through his own fault.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    On
                    <pb n="2066" xml:id="p.2066"/>
                    hearing of the consul's departure, therefore, Perseus marched back to Dium, repaired whatever had been destroyed and laid waste by the Romans, rebuilt the battlements which they had thrown down, strengthened the fortifications all round, and then pitched his camp within five miles of the city, on the hither bank of the Enipeus, in order to have the river itself, the passage of which was extremely difficult, as a defence to his post.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Enipeus, which rises in a valley of Mount Olympus, is a small stream during the summer, but is raised by the winter rains to a violent torrent, when, as it runs over the rocks, it forms furious eddies, and, by sweeping away the earth at the bottom into the sea, makes very deep gulfs, while the sinking of the middle of the channel renders the banks both high and steep.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus, thinking that the advance of the enemy was sufficiently obstructed by this river, contemplated spending there the remainder of the summer.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    In the mean time, the consul sent Popilius, with two thousand men, from Phila to Heracleum.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    It is distant about five miles from Phila, midway between Dium and Tempe, and stands on a steep rock hanging over the river.
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Popilius, before he brought his troops up to the walls, sent to recommend to the magistrates and principal men, rather to try the honour and clemency of the Romans than their power;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    but this advice produced no effect, the fires in the king's camp on the Enipeus being now within their sight The attack was then commenced by assaults, and with works and machines, as well on the side facing the sea, (for the ships had been brought up close to the shore,) as on land.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    A party of Roman youths actually gained possession of the lowest part of the wall, by turning to the purposes of war a kind of sport which they were accustomed to practise in the circus.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    In those times, when the present extravagant fashion of filling the area with beasts of every kind was yet unknown, it was customary to contrive various kinds of amusements; for when one chariot race and one equestrian performer were exhibited, both the performances scarcely filled up the space of an hour.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Among other diversions, in the more elaborate games, about sixty young men in arms, sometimes more, used to be introduced, whose performances were partly a representation of troops going through the military exercise, and partly a display of more accurate skill than appeared in the practice of
                    <pb n="2067" xml:id="p.2067"/>
                    soldiers, and which approached nearer to the mode of fighting used by gladiators.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    After performing various evolutions, they formed in a square body with their shields raised over their heads, and closed together, the foremost standing upright, the next stooping a little, the third and fourth lines more and more, and so on, until the hindmost rested on their knees, thus composing a covering in the shape of a tortoise-shell, and sloping, like the roof of a house.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Then two armed men, who stood at the distance of about fifty feet, ran forward, and after some menacing flourishes of their arms, mounted over the closed shields, from the bottom to the top of this roof; and, treading as steadily as if on solid ground, sometimes paraded along the extreme edges of it, as if repelling an enemy, and sometimes encountered each other on the middle of it.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    A body similar to this was brought up against the lowest part of the wall, and the soldiers, standing thereon, mounted until they were as high as the defendants on the battlements; and these having been beaten off, the soldiers of two companies climbed over into the town.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The only difference was, that here the outside men in the front and in the two flanks alone did not raise their shields over their heads, lest they should expose their bodies, but held them before them, as in battle; so that the weapons thrown at them from the walls, as they advanced, did them no injury, while those that were poured like a shower on the roof glided down the smooth slope to the bottom, without doing any mischief.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    When Heracleum was taken, the consul removed his quarters thither, as if he intended to besiege Dium; and, after driving the king thence, to advance to Pieria. But as he was now preparing his quarters for the winter, he ordered roads to be made for the conveyance of provisions from Thessaly, and proper places to be chosen for store-houses;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    also huts to be built, where the people employed in bringing the provisions might lodge.
                </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus, having at length recovered his spirits, after the panic with which he had been seized, began to wish that obedience had not been paid to the orders which he had given in his fright, to throw the treasures at Pella into the sea, and to burn the naval arsenals at Thessalonica.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Andronicus, indeed, whom he had sent to Thessalonica, had spun out the
                    <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    time, leaving him time for repentance, which actually took place; but Nicias, less provident, threw into the sea
                    <pb n="2068" xml:id="p.2068"/>
                    what money he found at Pella.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He seems, however, to have fallen into a mistake which was not without remedy, inasmuch as the greatest part of that treasure was brought up again by divers. Nevertheless, such shame did the king feel for his terror on the occasion, that he caused the divers to be privately put to death, together with Andronicus and Nicias, that there might be no living witnesses of so preposterous an order.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the mean time, Caius Marcius, with the fleet, sailed from Heracleum to Thessalonica. Landing his men, he made wide depredations on the country; and when the troops from the city came out against him, he defeated them in several actions, and drove them back in dismay within their walls.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    He even alarmed the city itself; but the townsmen, erecting engines of every kind, wounded, with stones thrown from them, not only such as straggled carelessly near the walls, but even those who were on board the ships.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore re-embarked his troops; and giving up the design of besieging Thessalonica, proceeded thence to Aenia, fifteen miles distant, situated opposite to Pydna, in a fertile country. After ravaging the lands in that quarter, he coasted along the shore until he arrived at Antigonea.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Here his troops landed, and for some time carried their depredations through all the country round, putting a great deal of booty on board the ships;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    but afterwards a party of Macedonians, consisting of foot and horse intermixed, fell upon them as they straggled, and, pursuing them as they fled to the shore, killed near five hundred, and took as many prisoners.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Extreme necessity, on finding themselves hindered from safely regaining their vessels, roused the courage of the Roman soldiers, at once with despair of any other means of safety, (than by resistance,) and also with indignation.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    They renewed the fight on the shore, and those who were on board assisted them; and here about two hundred Macedonians were killed, and a like number taken. From Antigonea the fleet sailed on to the district of Pallene, where a descent was made for the purpose of plundering.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    This district belonged to the territory of Cassandrea, and was by far the most plentiful of any at which they had yet touched on the coast. There they were met by king Eumenes, who came from Elea with twenty decked ships; and king Prusias also sent thither five ships of war.
                </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    By this accession of strength the praetor was encouraged
                    <pb n="2069" xml:id="p.2069"/>
                    to lay siege to Cassandrea.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This city was built by king Cassander, in the pass which connects the territory of Pallene with the rest of Macedonia.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It is bounded on one side by the Toronaean, on another by the Macedonian Sea; for it stands on a neck of land which stretches into the ocean, and rises in the part opposite Magnesia to a height equal to that of Mount Athos, forming two unequal promontories, the larger called Posideum, the smaller Canastraeum.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The besiegers formed their attacks on two different sides; the Roman general, at a place called Clitae, drew a trench from the Macedonian to the Toronaean Sea, to which he added pointed palisades, to cut off the communication; while on the other side is the Euripus, where Eumenes carried on his attack.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans underwent a vast deal of labour in filling up a trench, which Perseus had recently dug in the way; and on the praetor inquiring where the earth that had been taken out of it was thrown, as he saw no heaps of it any where, some arches were shown him that were closed up with it, not of equal thickness with the old wall, but with a single row of brick.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    On this, he formed the design of opening a way into the city, by breaking through that wall; and he hoped to be able to escape observation, if, by assaulting another part by scalade, and raising a tumult there, he could divert the attention of the besieged to the defence of the place attacked.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    There were in garrison at Cassandrea, besides the younger inhabitants, who formed no contemptible body, eight hundred Agrians and two thousand Illyrians from Penestia, sent thither by Pleuratus, each being a warlike race. While these were busy in defending the walls, and the Romans using their utmost efforts to scale them, in an instant of time the arches were broken through, and the city laid open;
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    and if those who made this irruption had been armed, they must have immediately become masters of the town.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    When the soldiers were told that this work was accomplished, they were so elated with joy, that they raised a sudden shout, expecting to force their way in, some in one part, and others in another.
                </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    At first the enemy was seized with wonder at to what this sudden shout could mean;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    but when Pytho and Philip, the commanders of the garrison, were told that the city was laid open, they concluded that every advantage resulting from that event would be in favour of whichever party should make
                    <pb n="2070" xml:id="p.2070"/>
                    the first charge; and, therefore, they sallied out, with a strong body of Agrians and Illyrians, who, while the Romans were coming together and being congregated from various parts that they might march in order into the city, routed them while thus disordered and irregular, and drove them to the trench, into which they tumbled them, in heaps, one over another.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    About six hundred were killed in this action, and almost every one that was found between the wall and the trench was wounded.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The blow meditated by the praetor having thus recoiled on himself, made him slower to form any other attempts; and as Eumenes made little or no progress, though he carried on his operations both by land and sea, they concurred in a resolution to strengthen their guards, in order to prevent the introduction of any reinforcement from Macedonia:
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and, since they had not succeeded by assault, to carry on the siege by regular approaches.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    While they were making preparations for this, ten barks, belonging to the king, sent from Thessalonica, with a chosen body of Gallic auxiliaries, observing the enemy's ships lying at anchor in the road, and keeping as close to the shore as possible, amidst the darkness of the night, in a single line, effected their entrance to the city. Intelligence of this new addition of force obliged both the Romans and Eumenes to raise the siege.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They then sailed round the promontory, and brought the fleet into the harbour of Torone. This town also they attempted to besiege; but, perceiving that it was defended by a strong garrison, they dropped the design, and proceeded to Demetrias.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    When they approached this place, they saw the walls fully manned with armed troops; they therefore sailed on, and brought the fleet into harbour at Iolcos, intending, after ravaging the country there, to proceed to the siege of Demetrias.
                </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    In the mean time, the consul, not to lie inactive in the enemies' country, sent Marcus Popilius, with five thousand men, to reduce the city of Melibœa.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This city stands at the foot of the Mount Ossa, where it stretches out into Thessaly, and is very advantageously situated for commanding Demetrias.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The first approach of the enemy struck terror into the inhabitants of the place; but soon recovering from the fright occasioned by the unexpectedness of the event, they ran hastily in arms to the gates and walls, where an entrance was apprehended, and at once put a stop to all hope of taking the
                    <pb n="2071" xml:id="p.2071"/>
                    place by the first assault.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Preparations were therefore made for a siege, and the works commenced for making the approaches. When Perseus was informed that both Melibœa was being besieged by the consul's army, and that the fleet at the same time was lying at Iolcos, intending to proceed thence to attack Demetrias, he sent Euphranor, one of his generals, with two thousand chosen men, to Melibœa.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    His orders were, that, if he could compel the Romans to retire from before Melibœa, he should then march secretly into Demetrias, before the enemy should bring up their troops from Iolcos to that city.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    As soon as he suddenly became visible on the high grounds to the besiegers of Melibœa, they abandoned their numerous works in great consternation, and set them on fire.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Thus they withdrew from Melibœa, and Euphranor, having raised the siege of one city, marched instantly to Demetrias. Then the townsmen felt confident that they should be able, not only to defend their walls, but to protect their lands also from depredations; and they made several irruptions on the straggling parties of the plunderers, not without injury to the enemy.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    However, the praetor and the king rode round the walls to view the situation of the city, and try whether they might attempt it on any side, either by storm or works.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    It was reported, that some overtures of friendship between Eumenes and Perseus were here agitated, through Cydas, a Cretan, and Antimachus, governor of Demetrias.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    It is certain, that the armies retired from Demetrias. Eumenes sailed to the consul; and, after congratulating him on his success in penetrating into Macedonia, went home to Pergamus.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Marcius Figulus, the praetor, having sent part of his fleet to winter at Sciathus, with the remainder repaired to Oreum in Eubœa; judging that the most convenient city from which he could send supplies to the armies in Macedonia and Thessaly.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    There are very different accounts given respecting king Eumenes: if Valerius Antias is to be believed, he neither gave any assistance with his fleet to the praetor, though often solicited by letters; nor did he depart from the consul for Asia in good humour, being offended at not being permitted to lie in the same camp with him; he says too, that he could not be prevailed on even to leave the Gallic horsemen that he had brought with him.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    But his brother Attalus remained with the consul, and in the con-
                    <pb n="2072" xml:id="p.2072"/>
                    stant tenor of his conduct
                    <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                    evinced a sincere attachment, and an extraordinary degree of zeal and activity in the service.
                </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    While the war was being carried on in Macedonia, ambassadors came to Rome, from a chieftain of the Gauls beyond the Alps, whose name is said to have been Balanos, but of what tribe is not mentioned. They brought an offer of assistance towards the war in Macedonia.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The senate returned him thanks, and sent him presents, —a golden chain of two pounds weight, golden bowls to the amount of four pounds, a horse completely caparisoned, and a suit of horseman's armour.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    After the Gauls, ambassadors from Pamphylia, brought into the senate-house a golden crown, of the value of twenty thousand Philippeans, and requested permission to deposit it, as an offering, in the shrine of Jupiter supremely good and great, and to offer sacrifice in the Capitol, which was granted.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The said ambassadors having expressed a wish to renew the treaty of friendship, a gracious answer was given, and a present was made to each of two thousand
                    <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        6
                        <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                        9
                        <hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
                        2
                        <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Then audience was given to the ambassadors of king Prusias; and, a little after, to those of the Rhodians, who discoursed on the same subject, but in a widely different manner.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The purpose of both embassies was, to effect a peace with king Perseus. The address of Prusias consisted of entreaties rather than demands; for he declared, that
                    <quote>
                        he had hitherto supported the cause of the Romans, and would continue to support it as long as the war should continue.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        But, on Perseus sending ambassadors to him, on the subject of putting an end to the war with Rome, he had promised them to become a mediator with the senate:
                    </quote>
                    and he requested that,
                    <quote>
                        if they could prevail on themselves to lay aside their resentment, they would place him in the favourable position of mediator of the peace.
                    </quote>
                    Such was the discourse of the king's ambassadors.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The Rhodians, after ostentatiously recounting their many services to the Roman people, and arrogating to themselves rather the greater share of its successes, particularly in the case of king Antiochus, proceeded in this manner;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    that,
                    <quote>
                        at a time when peace subsisted between the Macedonians and Romans, they likewise commenced a friendship with king Perseus, which they had, since, unwillingly broken, without having any reason to com-
                        <pb n="2073" xml:id="p.2073"/>
                        plain of him, but merely because it was the desire of the Romans to draw them into a confederacy in the war, that for three years past they had felt many inconveniences from that war.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        In consequence of the interruption of commerce, and the loss of their port duties and provisions, their island was distressed by a general scarcity.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        When their countrymen could no longer suffer this, they had sent other ambassadors into Macedonia, to Perseus, to announce to him that it was the wish of the Rhodians that he should conclude a peace with the Romans, and had sent them to Rome with the same message.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        The Rhodians would afterwards consider what measures they should judge proper to be taken against either party that should prevent an end being put to the war.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    I am convinced that no person, even at the present time, can hear or read such expressions without indignation; we may, then, easily judge what was the state of mind of the senators when they listened to them.
                </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    According to the account of Claudius, no answer was given; and a decree of the senate only was read, by which the Roman people ordered, that the Carians and Lycians should enjoy independence; and that a letter should be sent immediately to each of those nations, acquainting them therewith.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    On hearing which the principal ambassador, whose arrogant demeanour, just before, the senate could scarce contain, fell down insensible.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Other writers say, that an answer was given to this effect:
                    <quote>
                        That, at the commencement of the present war, the Roman people had learned, from unquestionable authority, that the Rhodians, in concert with king Perseus, had formed secret machinations against their commonwealth;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        and that, if that matter had been doubtful hitherto, the words of their ambassadors, just now, had reduced it to a certainty; as, in general, treachery, though at first sufficiently cautious, yet, in the end, betrays itself. Were the Rhodians now to act the part of arbiters of war and peace throughout the world?
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        were the Romans at their nod to take up arms and lay them down? and henceforth to appeal, not to the gods, but to the Rhodians, for their sanction of treaties?
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        And was this indeed the case, that, unless their orders were obeyed, and the armies withdrawn from Macedonia, they would consider what measures they should take?
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        What the Rhodians might determine, they themselves knew best; but the
                        <pb n="2074" xml:id="p.2074"/>
                        Roman people, as soon as the conquest of Perseus should be completed, an event which they hoped was at no great distance, would most certainly consider how to make due retribution to each state, according to its deserts in the course of the war.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Nevertheless the usual presents of two thousand
                    <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    each were sent to the ambassadors, which they did not accept.
                </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Then was read a letter from the consul, Quintus Marcius, informing the senate, that
                    <quote>
                        he had passed the mountains, and penetrated into Macedonia;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        that the praetor had collected there, and procured from other places, stores of provisions for the approaching winter; and that he had brought from the Epirots twenty thousand measures of wheat, ten thousand of barley, the price of which he desired might be paid to their ambassadors in Rome:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        that clothing for the troops must be sent from Rome; and that he wanted about two hundred horses, above all Numidian horses; where he was, he could procure none.
                    </quote>
                    The senate decreed, that every thing should be done in accordance with the consul's letter.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The praetor, Caius Sulpicius, agreed with contractors for conveying into Macedonia six thousand gowns, thirty thousand tunics, and the horses, all to be left to the approbation of the consul; and he paid the Epirot ambassadors the price of the corn. He then introduced to the senate, Onesimus, son of Pytho, a Macedonian of distinction.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    He had always advised the king to peaceable measures, and recommended to him, that, as his father Philip had, to the last day of his life, made it an established rule to read over twice every day the treaty concluded with the Romans, so he should, if not daily, yet frequently, observe the same practice. When he could not dissuade him from war, he at first began to absent himself on various pretences, that he might not be present at proceedings which he could not approve.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But at last, having discovered that suspicions were harboured against him, and that he was tacitly accused of the crime of treason, he went over to the Romans, and was of great service to the consul.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    When he was introduced into the senate-house, he mentioned these circumstances, and the senate thereupon decreed that he should be enrolled in the number of their allies; that a house and accommodations should be provided for him; also a grant of two hundred acres of land, in that part of the Tarentine territory which was the public property of the Roman people;
                    <pb n="2075" xml:id="p.2075"/>
                    and a house in Tarentum to be bought for him; the charge of executing all which was committed to Caius Decimius, the praetor.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    On the ides of December, the censors performed the general survey with more severity than formerly. A great many were deprived of their horses, among whom was Publius Rutilius, who, when tribune of the people, had carried on a violent prosecution against them; he was, besides, degraded from his tribe, and disfranchised.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    In pursuance of a decree of the senate, one-half of the taxes of that year was paid by the quaestors into the hands of the censors, to defray the expenses of public works.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Tiberius Sempronius, out of the money assigned to him, purchased for the public the house of Publius Africanus, behind the old house, near the statue of Vertumnus, with the butchers' stalls and shops adjoining;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    where he built the public court-house, afterwards called the Sempronian.
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The end of the year was now approaching, and people chiefly canvassed in their conversation, through their concern about the war in Macedonia, what consuls they should choose, to bring that war, at length, to a conclusion.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The senate therefore passed an order, that Cneius Servilius should come home, at the very first opportunity, to hold the elections.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Sulpicius, the praetor, sent the order of the senate to the consul; and, in a few days after, read his answer in public, wherein he promised to be in the city before the * * day of * * *. The consul came in due time, and the election was finished on the day appointed. The consuls chosen were, Lucius Aemilius Paullus, a second time, fourteen years after his first consulship, and Caius Licinius Crassus.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Next day, the following were appointed praetors: Cneius Baebius Tamphilus, Lucius Anicius Gallus, Cneius Octavius, Publius Fonteius Balbus, Marcus Aebutius Elva, and Caius Papirius Corbo.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The senate's anxiety about the Macedonian war stimulated them to more than ordinary expedition in all their proceedings;
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    they therefore ordered, that the magistrates elect should immediately cast lots for their provinces, that it might be known which consul was to have the command in Macedonia, and which praetor that of the fleet;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    in order that they might, without loss of time, consider and prepare whatever was requisite for the service, and consult the senate on any point where their direction was necessary, they voted, that,
                    <quote>
                        on the magistrates
                        <pb n="2076" xml:id="p.2076"/>
                        coming into office, the Latin festival should be celebrated as early as the rules of religion permitted;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        and that the consul who was to go into Macedonia should not be detained on account of it.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    When these orders were passed, Italy and Macedonia were named as the provinces for the consuls; and for the praetors, besides the two jurisdictions in the city, the fleet, Spain, Sicily, and Sardinia. As to the consuls, Macedonia fell to Aemilius, Italy to Licinius.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Of the praetors, Cneius Baebius got the city jurisdiction; Lucius Anicius the foreign, under a rule to go wherever the senate should direct; Cneius Octavius, the fleet; Publius Fonteius, Spain; Marcus Aebutius, Sicily; and Caius Papirius, Sardinia.
                </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    It immediately became evident to all, that Lucius Aemilius would prosecute the war with vigour; for, besides that he was a different kind of man (from his predecessors), his thoughts were intently employed night and day solely on the business relative to that war.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In the first place, he requested the senate to send commissioners into Macedonia, to review the armies and the fleet, and to bring authentic information as to what might be necessary both for the land and sea forces; to make what discoveries they could respecting the state of the king's forces;
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    and to learn how much of the country was in our power, how much in that of the enemy; whether the Romans were still encamped among the woods and mountains, or had got clear of all the difficult passes, and were come down into the plains;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    who appeared to be faithful allies to us, who were doubtful and suspended their fidelity on fortune, and who avowed enemies; what store of provisions was prepared, and whence new supplies might be brought by land-carriage, whence by the fleet; and what had been achieved during the last campaign, either on land or sea. For he thought that, by gaining a thorough knowledge of all these particulars, decisive plans might be taken for future proceedings.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The senate directed the consul Cneius Servilius to send as commissioners, into Macedonia, such persons as should be approved of by Lucius Aemilius. Cneius Domitius Ahenobarbus, Aulus Licinius Nerva, and Lucius Baebius, accordingly, began their journey two days after.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Towards the close of this year it was reported that two showers of stones had fallen, one in the territory of Rome, the other in that of Veii; and the nine days' solemnity was performed.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Of the priests,
                    <pb n="2077" xml:id="p.2077"/>
                    died this year, Publius Quintilius Varus, flamen of Mars, and Marcus Claudius Marcellus, decemvir, in whose room was substituted Cneius Octavius.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It has been remarked as an instance of the increasing munificence of the times, that in the Circensian games, exhibited by Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica and Publius Lentulus, curule aediles, sixty-three panthers, with forty bears and elephants, made a part of the show.
                </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    At the beginning of the following year, Lucius Aemilius Paullus and Caius Licinius, the consuls, having commenced their administration on the ides of March, the senators were impatient to hear what propositions were to be laid before them, particularly with respect to Macedonia, by the consul to whose lot that province had fallen;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    but Paullus said, that he had as yet nothing to propose to them, the commissioners not being returned: that
                    <quote>
                        they were then at Brundusium, after having been twice driven back to Dyrrachium in attempting the passage:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        that he intended, shortly, to propose something to their consideration, when he should have obtained the information which was previously necessary, and which he expected within very few days.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He added, that,
                    <quote>
                        in order that nothing should delay his setting out, the day before the ides of April had been fixed for the Latin festival;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        after finishing which solemnity, he and Cneius Octavius would begin their journey as soon as the senate should direct: that, in his absence, his colleague Caius Licinius would take care that every thing necessary to be provided, or sent for the war, should be provided and sent;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        and that, in the mean time, audience might be given to the embassies of foreign nations.
                    </quote>
                    The first introduced were ambassadors from Alexandria, sent by king Ptolemy and queen Cleopatra.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They came into the senate-house dressed in mourning, with their hair and beard neglected, holding in their hands branches of olive; there they prostrated themselves, and their discourse was even more piteous than their dress.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Antiochus, king of Syria, who had formerly been a hostage at Rome, had lately, under the honourable pretext of restoring the elder Ptolemy to the throne, made war on his younger brother, who was then in possession of Alexandria;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    and having gained the victory in a sea-fight off Pelusium, and thrown a temporary bridge across the Nile, he led over his army, and was terrifying Alexandria itself, by laying siege to it; so that he seemed
                    <pb n="2078" xml:id="p.2078"/>
                    almost on the point of taking possession of that very opulent kingdom.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The ambassadors, after complaining of these proceedings, besought the senate to succour those princes, the faithful friends of their empire.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    They said, that
                    <quote>
                        such had been the kindness of the Roman people to Antiochus, such its influence over all kings and nations, that if they only sent ambassadors, to give him notice that the senate were displeased at war being made with princes in alliance with them, he would instantly retire from the walls of Alexandria, and lead his army home into Syria.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        But if they hesitated to do this, Ptolemy and Cleopatra would soon come to Rome as exiles from their kingdom, which must excite some degree of shame in the Roman people, for not having brought them assistance in their extreme distress.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The senate, affected by the supplications of the Alexandrians, immediately sent Caius Popilius Laenas, Caius Decimius, and Caius Hostilius, ambassadors, to put an end to the dispute between those kings.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Their instructions were, to go first to Antiochus, then to Ptolemy; and to acquaint them, that, unless hostilities were stopped, whichever party persisted, must expect to be considered by the senate as neither a friend nor an ally.
                </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    These ambassadors set out, within three days, in company with those of Alexandria; and, on the last day of the feast of Minerva, the commissioners arrived from Macedonia. Their coming had been so impatiently wished for, that, if it had not been very late in the day, the consuls would have assembled the senate immediately.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Next day the senate met, and the commissioners had an audience.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    They stated, that "the army had been led through pathless and difficult wilds into Macedonia, with more risk than advantage: that Pieria, to which its march had been directed, was then possessed by the king; and the two camps so close to each other, as to be separated only by the river Enipeus:
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    that the king offered no opportunity to fight, nor were our men strong enough to compel him; and, besides, that the winter had unexpectedly interrupted all military operations: that the soldiers were maintained in idleness, and had not corn sufficient for more than six
                    <hi rend="italics">days:</hi>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    that the force of the Macedonians was said to amount to thirty thousand effective men: that if Appius Claudius had a sufficient force at Lychnidus, the king might be perplexed by a two-fold hostile array; but that, as the case stood,
                    <pb n="2079" xml:id="p.2079"/>
                    both Appius, and the troops under his command, were in the utmost danger, unless either a regular army were speedily sent thither, or they were removed thence.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>From the camp,</quote>
                    they stated that
                    <quote>
                        they had gone to the fleet; where they learned, that part of the seamen had perished by sickness; that others, particularly such as came from Sicily, had gone off to their own homes; and that the ships were in want of men, while those who were on board had neither received pay nor had clothing:
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        that Eumenes and his fleet, as if driven thither by the wind, had both come and gone away, without any apparent reason; nor did the intentions of that king seem to be thoroughly settled.
                    </quote>
                    While they reported every particular in the conduct of Eumenes as suspicious, they represented the fidelity of Attalus as stedfast in the highest degree.
                </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    After the commissioners were heard, Lucius Aemilius said, that he then proposed for consideration the business of the war:
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and the senate decreed, that
                    <quote>
                        tribunes for eight legions should be appointed, half by the consuls, and half by the people; but that none should be named for that year who had not held some magisterial office:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        that, out of all the military tribunes, Lucius Aemilius should select such as he chose for the two legions that were to serve in Macedonia; and that, as soon as the Latin festival should be finished, the said consul, with the praetor Cneius Octavius, to whose lot the fleet had fallen, should repair to that province.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    To these was added a third, Lucius Anicius, the praetor who had the foreign jurisdiction; for it was resolved that he should succeed Appius Claudius in the province of Illyria, near Lychnidus.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The charge of raising recruits was laid on the consul Caius Licinius, who was ordered to enlist, of Roman citizens, seven thousand foot and two hundred horse, and to demand, from the Latin confederates, seven thousand foot and four hundred horse;
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and also to write to Cneius Servilius, governor of Gaul, to raise there six hundred horse.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This force he was ordered to send, with all expedition, into Macedonia, to his colleague.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It was resolved, that there should be no more than two legions in that province, but that their numbers should be filled up so as that each should contain six thousand foot and three hundred horse; and that the rest of the foot and horse should be placed in the different garrisons;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    that such men as were unfit for service should be discharged, and
                    <pb n="2080" xml:id="p.2080"/>
                    that the allies should be obliged to raise another body of ten thousand foot and eight hundred horse.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    These were assigned as a reinforcement to Anicius, in addition to the two legions which he was ordered to carry into Illyria, consisting each of five thousand two hundred foot and three hundred horse; and five thousand seamen were raised for the fleet.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The consul Licinius was ordered to employ two legions in the service of his province, and to add to them ten thousand foot and six hundred horse of the allies.
                </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    When the senate had passed these decrees, the consul Lucius Aemilius went out from the senate-house into the assembly of the people, whom he addressed in a discourse to this effect:
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        Romans, I think I have perceived that your congratulations, on my obtaining, by lot, the province of Macedonia, were warmer than either when I was saluted consul, or on the day when I entered on office; and that for no other reason, than your having conceived an opinion, that by me the war with Perseus, which has been long protracted, may be brought to a conclusion becoming the majesty of the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        I trust that the gods also have favoured this disposal of the lots, and will give me their aid in the conduct of affairs.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        Some of these consequences I can prognosticate; others I can hope for. One thing I regard as certain, and venture to affirm; that I will endeavour, by every exertion in my power, that this hope which you have conceived of me may not be frustrated.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Every thing necessary for the service, the senate has ordered; and as it has been resolved, that I am to go abroad immediately, and I do not wish to delay, my colleague, Caius Licinius, an admirable man, will make the preparations with as much zeal, as if he himself were to carry on that war.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Do you give full credit to whatever I shall write to you, or to the senate; but do not by your credulity encourage mere rumours, of which no man shall appear as the responsible author.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        For, no man is so entirely regardless of reputation, as that his spirits cannot be damped; which I have observed has commonly occurred, especially in this war.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        In every circle, and, truly, at every table, there are people who lead armies into Macedonia; who know where the camp ought to be placed; what posts ought to be occupied by troops; when and through what pass Macedonia should be entered; where magazines should be formed; how provisions
                        <pb n="2081" xml:id="p.2081"/>
                        should be conveyed by land and sea; and when it is proper to engage the enemy, when to lie quiet.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        And they not only determine what is best to be done, but if any thing is done in any other manner than what they have pointed out, they arraign the consul, as if he were on his trial.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        These are great impediments to those who have the management of affairs; for every one cannot encounter injurious reports with the same constancy and firmness of mind as Fabius did, who chose to let his own authority be diminished through the folly of the people, rather than to mismanage the public business with a high reputation.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        I am not one of those who think that commanders ought never to receive advice; on the contrary, I should deem that man more proud than wise, who did every thing of his own single judgment. What then is my opinion?
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                        That commanders should be counselled, chiefly, by persons of known talent; by those, especially, who are skilled in the art of war, and who have been taught by experience; and next, by those who are present at the scene of action, who see the country, who see the enemy; who see the advantages that occasions offer, and who, embarked, as it were, in the same ship, are sharers of the danger.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        If, therefore, any one thinks himself qualified to give advice respecting the war which I am to conduct, which may prove advantageous to the public, let him not refuse his assistance to the state, but let him come with me into Macedonia. He shall be furnished by me with a ship, a horse, a tent; and even with his travelling charges.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        But if he thinks this too much trouble, and prefers the repose of a city life to the toils of war, let him not, on land, assume the office of a pilot. The city, in itself, furnishes abundance of topics for conversation;
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        let it confine its passion for talking, and rest assured, that we shall be content with such councils as shall be framed within our camp.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Soon after this speech, the Latin festival having been celebrated on the day before the calends of April, and the sacrifice on the mount affording favourable omens, the consul, and Cneius Octavius, the prae- tor, set out directly for Macedonia.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    There is a tradition that the consul, at his departure, was escorted by multitudes unusually numerous; and that people, with confident hope, presaged a conclusion of the Macedonian war, and the speedy return of the consul, to a glorious triumph.
                </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    During these occurrences in Italy, Perseus, though he
                    <pb n="2082" xml:id="p.2082"/>
                    could not, at first, prevail on himself to complete the design which he had projected, of attaching to himself Gentius, king of Illyria, on account of the money which would be demanded for it;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    yet, when he found that the Romans had penetrated the passes, and that the final crisis of the war drew near, resolved to defer it no longer, and having, by his ambassador Hippias, consented to pay three thousand talents of silver,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        58,125
                        <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note>
                    provided hostages were given on both sides; he now sent Pantauchus, one of his most trusty friends, to conclude the business.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Pantauchus met the Illyrian king at Meteo, in the province of Labeas, and there received from the king his oath and the hostages. Gentius likewise sent an ambassador, named Olympio, to require an oath and hostages from Perseus.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Together with him, were sent persons to receive the money; and by the advice of Pantauchus, to go to Rhodes, with ambassadors from Macedonia. Parmenio and Morcus were appointed.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Their instructions were, first, to receive the king's oath, the hostages, and money; and then to proceed to Rhodes; and it was hoped, that, by the name of the two kings, the Rhodians might be incited to a war against Rome, and that the union of that state, which alone at
                    <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    that time possessed naval glory, would leave the Romans no prospect of success, either on land or sea.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    As the Illyrians approached, Perseus marched with all his cavalry, from his camp on the Enipeus, and met them at Dium. There the articles agreed on were executed;
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    a body of cavalry having been drawn up around, whom the king chose should be witness to the treaty of alliance made with Gentius, supposing that this event would add greatly to their confidence.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The hostages were given and taken in the sight of all; those who were to receive the money were sent to Pella, where the king's treasure lay; and the persons who were to go to Rhodes, with the Illyrian ambassadors, were ordered to take ship at Thessalonica.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    There was present one Metrodorus, who had lately come from Rhodes, and who, on the authority of Dinon and Polyaratus, two principal members of that state, affirmed, that the Rhodians were prepared for the war; he was appointed head of the joint embassy with the Illyrians.
                </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    At this time Perseus sent to Eumenes and Antiochus, a common message, which the state of affairs seemed to suggest;
                    <pb n="2083" xml:id="p.2083"/>
                    that
                    <quote>
                        a free state, and a king, were, in their natures, hostile to each other.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        That the Roman people were accustomed to attack kings singly; and, what was more shameful, to conquer them, by the power of other kings.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        Thus, his father was overpowered by the aid of Attalus; and by the assistance of Eumenes, and of his father Philip, in part, Antiochus had been vanquished; and now, both Eumenes and Prusias were armed against himself.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        If the regal power should be abolished in Macedonia, the next, in their way, would be Asia, which they had already rendered, in part, their own, under the pretence of liberating the states; and next to that Syria.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Already Prusias was honoured by them, far beyond Eumenes; and already Antiochus, though victorious, was debarred from Egypt, the prize of his arms.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    He desired that each of them,
                    <quote>
                        considering these matters seriously, should see that he either compelled the Romans to make peace with him, or, if they should persist in such an unjust war, he should regard them as the common enemies of all kings.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The message to Antiochus was sent openly; the ambassador to Eumenes went under the pretence of ransoming prisoners. But some more secret business was transacted between them, which, in addition to the jealousy and distrust already conceived by the Romans against Eumenes,
                    <hi rend="italics">brought on him charges</hi>
                    of a heavier nature.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For they considered him as a traitor, and nearly as an enemy, while the two kings laboured to overreach each other in schemes of fraud and avarice.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    There was a Cretan, called Cydas, an intimate of Eumenes; this man had formerly conferred, at Amphipolis, with one Chimarus, a countryman of his own, serving in the army of Perseus; and he, afterwards, had had one interview with Menecrates, and another with Archidamus, officers of the king, at Demetrias, close under the wall of the town.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Herophon, too, who was sent on that business, had, before that, executed two embassies to the same Eumenes.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    These furtive conferences and embassies were notorious; but what the subject of them was, or what agreement had taken place between the kings, remained a secret.
                </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Now the truth of the matter was this: Eumenes neither wished success to Perseus nor intended to make war upon him; and his ill-will arose not so much from the enmity which they inherited from their fathers, as from the personal quarrels which had broken out between themselves.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The
                    <pb n="2084" xml:id="p.2084"/>
                    jealousy of the two kings was not so moderate, that Eumenes could, with patience, have seen Perseus acquiring such vast power and glory as awaited him, if he conquered the Romans.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Besides which, he saw that Perseus, from the commencement of the war, by every mean, sought a prospect of peace; and that every day, as the danger approached nearer, he was contriving and contemplating no other object.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He considered, too, that as the war had been protracted beyond the expectations of the Romans, their commanders and senate would not be averse from putting an end to a contest so inconvenient and difficult. Having discovered this inclination in both parties, he concluded, that, from the disgust of the stronger party, and the fears of the weaker, this might take place spontaneously;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and therefore he the more wished, for the sake of conciliating favour to himself, to make his own efforts available in the business.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore, sometimes, laboured to stipulate for a consideration for not affording assistance to the Romans, either on sea or land; at other times, for bringing about a peace with them. He demanded for not interfering in the war, one thousand talents;
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        193,750
                        <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note>
                    for effecting a peace, one thousand five hundred;
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        290,625
                        <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note>
                    and for his sincerity in either case, he professed himself prepared, not only to make oath, but to give hostages also.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus, stimulated by his fears, showed the greatest readiness in the beginning of the negotiation, and treated without delay about receiving the hostages; when it was agreed, that, on their being received, they should be sent to Crete.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But when they came to the mention of money, there he hesitated;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    remarking that, in the case of kings of their high character, a pecuniary consideration was mean and sordid, both with respect to the giver, and still more so with respect to the receiver.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He preferred not to decline the payment in the hope of a peace with Rome, but said that he would pay the money when the business should be concluded; and that he would lodge it in the mean time in the temple of Samothrace.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    As that island was under his own dominion, Eumenes said, that it was all the same as if the money were at Pella; and he struggled hard to obtain some part of it at the present.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Thus, having manœuvred with each other to no purpose, they gained nothing but disgrace.
                </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    This was not the only business which Perseus left
                    <pb n="2085" xml:id="p.2085"/>
                    unfinished from motives of avarice, since for a small sum of money he might have procured, through Eumenes, a secure peace, well purchased even with half of his kingdom; while, if defrauded, he might have exposed him to public view, as an enemy laden with his pelf, and made the Romans deservedly his enemies.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Through this avaricious spirit the prompt alliance of king Gentius, with the assistance of a large
                    <hi rend="italics">army</hi>
                    of Gauls, who had spread themselves through Illyria, and offered themselves to him, was lost.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    There came ten thousand horsemen, and the same number of footmen, who themselves kept pace with the horses, and in place of the riders who had fallen, took on the horses to the fight.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    They had stipulated that each horseman should receive in immediate payment, ten golden Philippics, each footman five, and their commander one thousand.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus went from his camp on the Enipeus with half of his forces to meet them as they approached; and issued orders through the towns and villages near the road, to prepare provisions, so that they might have plenty of corn, wine, and cattle.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    He brought with him some horses, trappings, and cloaks, for presents to the chiefs; and a small quantity of gold to be divided among a few; for the multitude, he supposed, might be amused with hopes.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He advanced as far as the city of Almana, and encamped on the bank of the river Axius, at which time the army of the Gauls lay near Desudaba, in Maedica, waiting for the promised hire.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Thither he sent Antigonus, one of his nobles, with directions, that the said army should remove their camp to Bylazor, a place in Paeonia, and that their chiefs should come to him in a body. They were at this time seventy-five miles distant from the river Axius and the king's camp.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Antigonus, in his message, told them what great plenty of every thing was provided on the road by the king's directions, and what presents of apparel, money, and horses he intended for them on their arrival. They answered, that they would judge of those things when they saw them;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    at the same time asking him, whether, according to their stipulation for immediate payment, he had brought with him the gold which was to be distributed to each footman and horseman? When to this no direct answer was given, Clondicus, their prince, said,
                    <quote>
                        Go back,
                        <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                        then, and tell your king, that, unless they should have received the gold and the host-
                        <pb n="2086" xml:id="p.2086"/>
                        ages, the Gauls would never move one step farther.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    When this message was brought to the king, he called a council: and, as it was very plain what advice all the members would give; he, being a better guardian of his money than of his kingdom, began to descant on the perfidy and savage behaviour of the Gauls.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>The disasters,</quote>
                    he said,
                    <quote>
                        of many states demonstrated, that it would be dangerous to admit such a multitude into Macedonia, lest they might feel such allies more troublesome than their Roman enemies. Five thousand horsemen would be enough for them to employ in the war, and
                        <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/>
                        that number they need not be afraid to receive.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    It was sufficiently clear to all that what he feared was the paying of such a multitude, and nothing else; but as none had the courage to declare their opinion, when asked, Antigonus was sent again, with a message; that the king chose to employ only five thousand horsemen, but that he could not receive the rest of their number.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    When the barbarians heard this, they began to murmur, and show a great deal of anger at being brought so far from home for no purpose; but Clondicus again asked him, whether he would pay even the five thousand the hire agreed on.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    When he perceived that an evasive answer was given to this question also, the Gauls, dismissing the insidious envoy unhurt, which was what he himself had scarcely hoped could be his fate, returned home to the Danube, after utterly wasting such lands of Thrace as lay near their road.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Now had this body of troops, while the king lay quiet on the Enipeus, been led against the Romans through the passes of Perrhaebia, into Thessaly, it might not only have stripped that country so bare, that the Romans could not expect supplies from thence;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    but might even have destroyed the cities themselves, while Perseus, by detaining his enemy at the Enipeus, would have put it out of their power to succour their allies.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Romans, indeed, would have been obliged to look out for their own safety, since they could neither stay where they were, after losing Thessaly, whence their army drew sustenance, nor move forward, as the camp of the Macedonians
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        stood in their way.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        By this error, Perseus enlivened the hopes of the Romans,
                    </hi>
                    and damped not a little
                    <hi rend="italics">those of the Macedonians,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The passages in Italics are only conjectural, and
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        introduced to supply an hiatus in the original.
                    </note>
                    who had depended much on that project. Through the same
                    <pb n="2087" xml:id="p.2087"/>
                    avarice, he alienated from him king Gentius. When he paid, at Pella, three hundred talents to the persons sent by Gentius, he allowed them to seal up the money. He then ordered ten talents to
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    be carried to Pantauchus, and these he desired should be given immediately to the king. He ordered his people, who were carrying the rest
                    <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                    of the money, sealed with the seals of the Illyrians, to convey it by short journeys, and when they should come
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    to the bounds of Macedonia, to halt there, and wait for a message from him. Gentius, having received this small portion of the money, and being incessantly urged by Pantauchus to provoke the Romans by some hostile act, threw into
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    custody Marcus Perperna and Lucius Petilius, who happened to come at that time as ambassadors. Having heard this, Perseus, thinking that the Illyrian had now laid himself under a necessity of waging war with the Romans at least, sent to recall those who were conveying the money, as if for no other object, than that the greatest possible booty might be reserved for the Romans on his defeat. Herophon,
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    too, returned from Eumenes, without any one knowing what had been secretly negotiated between them. The parties themselves had mentioned publicly that the business of the prisoners had been concluded, and Eumenes, for the sake of avoiding suspicion, acquainted the consul with it.
                </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Upon the return of Herophon from Eumenes, Perseus, disappointed in his hope, sent Antenor and Callippus, the commanders of his fleet, with forty barks, to which were added five heavy galleys, to Tenedos, that they might protect the
                    <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    vessels sailing to Macedonia with corn, and scattered among the Cyclades.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    This squadron, setting sail from Cassandrea, steered, first, to the harbour at the foot of Mount Athos, and crossing over thence, with mild weather, to Tenedos, found lying in the harbour a number of Rhodian undecked ships, and their commander Eudamus; these they did not offer to molest, but, after having spoken them in a friendly manner, suffered them to pursue their course.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Then, learning that, on the other side of the island, fifty transports of their own were shut up by a squadron of Eumenes, commanded by Damius, which lay in the mouth of the harbour, they sailed round with all haste;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    and the enemy's ships retiring, through fear, they sent on the transports to Macedonia, ten
                    <pb n="2088" xml:id="p.2088"/>
                    barks having been appointed to accompany them, which were to return to Tenedos as soon as they had convoyed them to a place of safety.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly, on the ninth day after, they rejoined the fleet, then lying at Sigeum. From thence they sailed over to Subota, an island between Elea and Athos.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    The next day after the fleet had reached Subota, it happened that thirty-five vessels, of the kind called horse-transports, sent by Eumenes to Attalus, and which had sailed from Elea, with Gallic horsemen and their horses, were steering towards Phanae, a promontory of Chios, from whence they might cross over to Macedonia, A signal having been given to Antenor,
                    <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    from a post of observation, that these ships were passing along the main, he left Subota, and met them between Cape Erythrae and Chios, where the strait is narrowest.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    The officers of Eumenes believed nothing less probable than that a Macedonian fleet was cruising in that sea; they imagined that they were Romans, or that Attalus, or some people sent home by him from the Roman camp, were on their way to Pergamus.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    But when, on their nearer approach, the shape of the vessels was plainly perceived, and when the briskness of their rowing, and their prows being directed straight against themselves, proved that enemies were approaching, a panic was struck into them; for they had no hope of being able to make resistance, their ships being of an unwieldy kind, and the Gauls scarcely able to bear a state of quiet when at sea.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Some, who were nearest to the shore of the continent, swam to Erythrae; some, crowding all their sail, ran the ships aground near Chios; and, leaving their horses behind, made for the city in disorderly flight.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    When the barks, however, had landed their troops nearer to the city, where the
                    <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    access was more convenient, the Macedonians overtook and put to the sword the flying Gauls, some on the road, and some who had been shut out before the gate, for the Chians had shut their gates, not knowing who they were that fled, or who that pursued. About eight hundred Gauls were killed, and two hundred made prisoners.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Of the horses, some were lost in the sea, by the ships being wrecked, and others the Macedonians hamstrung on the shore.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Antenor ordered the same ten barks, which he had employed before, to carry twenty horses of extraordinary beauty, with the prisoners, to Thessalonica, and to return to the fleet as speedily as possible; saying, that he
                    <pb n="2089" xml:id="p.2089"/>
                    would wait for them at Phanae.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    The fleet staid about three days off the city, and then proceeded to Phanae, and the ten barks having returned sooner than was expected, they set sail, and crossed the Aegean Sea to Delos.
                </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    While these things were taking place, the Roman ambassadors, Caius Popilius, Caius Decimius, and Caius Hostilius, having sailed from Chalcis with three quinqueremes, arrived at Delos, and found there forty Macedonian barks, and five quinqueremes belonging to king Eumenes.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The sacred character of the temple and the island secured all parties from injury; so that the Roman and Macedonian seamen, and those of Eumenes, used to meet promiscuously in the temple, a truce being imposed by the religious feeling which the place inspired.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Antenor, the commander of Perseus's fleet, having learned, by signals from his watch-posts, that several transport ships were passing by at sea, went himself in pursuit, with one half of his barks, (distributing the other half among the Cyclades,) and sunk or plundered every ship he met with, except such as were bound for Macedonia.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Popilius and the ships of Eumenes assisted as many as they were able;
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    but, in the night, the Macedonians sailing out, generally with two or three vessels, passed unseen.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    About this time, ambassadors from Macedonia and Illyria came together to Rhodes. Their influence was the greater, in consequence of their squadron cruising freely among the Cyclades, and over all the Aegean Sea, and likewise on account of the junc- tion of Perseus and Gentius, and of the report of the Gauls approaching with a great force both of horse and foot.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Dinon and Polyaratus, the partisans of Perseus, now took fresh courage, and the Rhodians not only gave a favourable answer to the ambassadors, but declared publicly, that
                    <quote>
                        they would put an end to the war by their own influence;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        and therefore desired the kings to dispose themselves to accede to a peace.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    It was now the beginning of spring, and the new commanders had arrived in their provinces; the consul Aemilius in Macedonia, Octavius at Oreum, where the fleet lay, and Anicius in Illyria, to carry on the war against Gentius.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This prince, who was the son of Pleuratus, king of Illyria, and his queen Eurydice, had two brothers, one called Plator, by both parents, the other Caravantius, by the same mother only. The latter, as descended of ignoble ancestors on his father's
                    <pb n="2090" xml:id="p.2090"/>
                    side, was but little suspected; but, that his reign might be more secure, he had put to death Plator, and two active men his friends, Ettritus and Epicadus.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It was rumoured, that he was actuated by jealousy towards his brother, who had engaged himself to Etuta, the daughter of Hononus, prince of the Dardanians, as if, by that match, engaging that nation in his interest;
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    and this supposition was rendered the more probable by Gentius marrying her, after the death of Plator. From this time, when he was delivered from the fear of his brother, he began to be oppressive to his subjects, and the natural violence of his temper was inflamed by an immoderate use of wine.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Having been incited, as was mentioned above, to a war with the Romans, he collected all his forces, amounting to fifteen thousand men, at Lissus.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    From thence, detaching his brother with one thousand foot and fifty horse, to reduce, either by force or terror, the nation of the Cavians, he marched himself to Bassania, a city five miles distant from Lissus. The inhabitants were in alliance with Rome.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, having been first solicited by emissaries sent in advance, they determined rather to endure a siege than surrender themselves. In Cavia, the people of the town of Durnium cheerfully opened their gates to Caravantius, on his arrival; but another town, called Caravantis, refused him admittance; and whilst he was carelessly ravaging their lands, many of his straggling soldiers were killed by a muster of the peasants.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    By this time Appius Claudius, having joined to the army he had in command some bodies of auxiliaries, composed of Bulinians, Apollonians, and Dyrrhachians, had left his winter quarters, and was encamped near the river Genusus.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Having heard of the treaty between Persius and Gentius, and being highly provoked at the ill-treatment of the outraged ambassadors, he was resolved to make war upon him.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The praetor Anicius, who was now at Apollonia, being informed of what passed in Illyria, despatched a letter to Appius, desiring him to wait for him at the Genusus; and, in three days after, he arrived in the camp.
                    <hi rend="italics">Having added</hi>
                    to the auxiliary troops which he then had, two thousand foot and two hundred horse of the Parthinians, (the foot commanded by Epicadus, and the horse by Agalsus,) he prepared to march into Illyria, chiefly that he might relieve the Bassanians from the siege.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    But an account brought him, of the sea-coast being ravaged by a
                    <pb n="2091" xml:id="p.2091"/>
                    number of the enemy's barks, checked his efforts.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    These were eighty vessels, which, by the advice of Pantauchus, Gentius had sent to waste the lands of the Dyrrhachians and Apollonians.
                    <hi rend="italics">
                        The Roman fleet was then lying near Apollo- nia. Anicius hastily repaired thither, soon overtook the Illy- rian plunderers, brought them to an engagement, and, defeating them with very little trouble, took many of their ships, and compelled the rest to retire to Illyria. Returning thence to the camp at the Genusus, he hastened to the relief of Bassania.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Gentius did not bear up against the rumour of the praetor's coming; but, raising the siege, retired to Scodra with such precipitate haste, that he did not even take the whole of his army with him.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        There was a large body of forces, which, if their courage had been supported by the presence of their com- mander, might have given some check to the Romans;
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                        but, as he had withdrawn,
                    </hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">This passage is supplied conjecturally.</note>
                    they surrendered.
                </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The cities of that country, one after another, followed the example; their own inclinations being encouraged by the justice and clemency which the Roman praetor showed to all.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The army then advanced to Scodra, which was the chief seat of the war, not merely because Gentius had chosen it for the metropolis of his kingdom, but because it has by far the strongest fortifications of any in the territory of the Labeatians, and is of very difficult access.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Two rivers enclose it; the Clausula flowing past the eastern side of the city, and by the western, the Barbanna, which rises out of the lake Labeatus. These two rivers, uniting their streams, fall into the river Oriuns, which, running down from mount Scodrus, and being augmented by many other waters, empties itself into the Adriatic Sea.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Mount Scordus is much the highest hill in all that country; at its foot, towards the east, lies Dardania; towards the south, Macedonia; and towards the west, Illyria.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Notwithstanding that the town was so strong, from the nature of its situation, and was garrisoned by the whole force of the Illyrian nation, with the king himself at their head,
                    <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                    yet the Roman praetor, encouraged by the happy success of his first enterprises, and hoping that the fortune of the whole undertaking would correspond to its commencement, and thinking also that a sudden alarm might have a powerful effect, advanced to the walls with his troops
                    <pb n="2092" xml:id="p.2092"/>
                    in order of battle.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But, if the garrison had kept their gates shut, and manned the walls and the towers of the gates with soldiers, they might have repulsed the Romans from the walls with their efforts frustrated, instead of which they marched out
                    <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                    from the gate, and, on equal ground, commenced a battle with more courage than they supported it:
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    for, being forced to give way, and crowded together in their retreat, and above two hundred having fallen in the very entrance of the gate, the rest were so terrified, that Gentius immediately despatched Teuticus and Bellus, two of the first men of the nation, to the praetor, through whom he begged a truce, in order that he might be able to deliberate on the state of his affairs.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    He was allowed three days for the purpose, and, as the Roman camp was about five hundred paces from the city, he went on board a ship, and sailed up the river Barbanna, into the lake of Labeatus, as if in search of a retired place for consultation;
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    but, as afterwards appeared, he was led by a groundless report, that his brother Caravantius was coming, with many thousands of soldiers collected in the country, to which he had been sent.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    This rumour dying away, on the third day he sailed down the river in the same ship to Scodra; and, after sending forward messengers, to request permission to call upon the praetor, and leave being given, came into the camp. He began his discourse with reproaches against himself, for the folly of his conduct; then descended to tears and prayers, and, falling at the praetor's knees, gave himself up into his power.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    He was at first desired to keep up his spirits, and having been even invited to supper, he went back into the city to his people, and, for that day, was entertained by the praetor with every mark of respect.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    On the day following, he was delivered into custody, to Caius Cassius, a military tribune, having, though a king, received ten talents, scarcely the
                    <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/>
                    hire of a party of gladiators, and that from a king, to reduce himself to these circumstances.
                </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The first thing Anicius did, after taking possession of Scodra, was, to order the ambassadors, Petilius and Perperna, to be sought for and brought to him;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and having restored to them their former dignity, he immediately despatched Perperna to seize the king's friends and relations, who, hastening to Medeo, a city of Labeatia, conducted to the camp at Scodra, Etleva, the king's consort; his brother Caravantius; with his
                    <pb n="2093" xml:id="p.2093"/>
                    two sons, Scerdiletus and Pleuratus.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Anicius, having brought the Illyrian war to a conclusion within thirty days, sent Perperna to Rome with the news of his success; and, in a few days after, king Gentius himself, with his mother, queen, children, and brother, and other Illyrians of distinction.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This one war was announced at Rome as finished before it was known to have been begun. At the time when these things took place, Perseus laboured under dreadful apprehensions, on account of the approach, both of the new consul Aemilius, who, as he heard, was coming with formidable threats, and also of the praetor Octavius: nor did he less dread the Roman fleet, and the danger which threatened the sea-coast.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Eumenes and Athenagoras commanded at Thessalonica, with a small garrison of two thousand targeteers. Thither he sent Androcles, as governor, and ordered him to keep the troops encamped close by the naval arsenals. He ordered one thousand horse, under Antigonus, to Aenia, to guard the sea-coast; directing them, whenever they should hear of the enemy's fleet approaching the shore in any part, instantly to hasten thither, to protect the country people.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Five thousand Macedonians were sent to garrison the mountains Pythium and Petra, commanded by Histieus, Theogenes, and Medon. After making these detachments, he set about fortifying the bank of the river Enipeus, the channel being dry and fordable;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    and, in order that all the men might apply themselves to this work, the women were obliged to bring provisions from the neighbouring cities into the camp. He ordered the soldiers to
                    <hi rend="italics">fetch timber</hi>
                    from the woods which were not far distant.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Crevier supplement:
                        <quote>
                            <p>
                                Then a mound was formed and works thrown up strengthened with towers and with engines, disposed in various parts so that the enemy might not be able to force a way through without great opposition and danger.
                                <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                                Thus he trusted that he should be secure against every attack of the Romans, and that, wearied out with inac- tion and slow delay, and drained by expenses, a disgust at so difficult a war would seize on the mind of the enemy.
                                <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                                On the other side, the more diligence and caution Paullus saw the Ma- cedonians use, the more assiduously did he study to devise some means of frustrating those hopes, which the enemy had not without reason conceived.
                                <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                                But he suffered immediate distress from the scarcity of water, as the neighbouring river was al-
                                <pb n="2094" xml:id="p.2094"/>
                                most dried up, except that a little stream, and that impure, flowed in the part contiguous to the sea.
                            </p>
                            <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                            <p>
                                <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                                The consul, when those who were sent to search the neighbourhood announced that no water could be found ...
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                        <p>
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                            The whole of the foregoing passage is supplied conjecturally.
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    at last ordered the water-carriers to attend him to the shore, which was not three hundred paces distant, and there to dig holes in several places, not far from each other. The great height of the mountains gave him reason to suppose that they contained hidden springs of water, the veins of which flowing through to the sea, mingled with its waves; and the more so, as they discharged no streams above ground.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Scarcely was the surface of the sand removed, when springs began to boil up, small at first, and muddy, but in a little time they threw out clear water in great plenty, as if through the favourable interference of the gods.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This circumstance added greatly to the reputation and influence of the general in the minds of the soldiers. He then ordered them to get ready their arms; and went himself, with the tribunes and first centurions, to examine the fords, in hopes of finding a passage, where the descent would be easy for the troops, and where the ascending the other bank would be least difficult.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    After taking a sufficient view of these matters, he made it his first care to provide, that, in the movements of the army, every thing should be done regularly, and without noise, at the first order and beck of the general.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    When notice was proclaimed of what was to be done to all at the same time, every one did not distinctly hear; and as the orders received were not clear, some making additions for themselves, did more than was ordered, while others did less; while dissonant shouts were raised in every quarter, insomuch that the enemy knew sooner than the soldiers themselves what was intended.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore directed, that the military tribune should communicate, secretly, to the first centurion of the legion, then he to the next, and that so on, in order that each should tell the next to him in rank what was requisite to be done, whether the instructions were to be conveyed from front to rear, or from rear to front.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He likewise, by a new arrangement, forbade the sentinels to carry their shields when on duty; for as a sentinel did not go to fight, but to watch, he had no occasion for arms; it was his duty, when he perceived an enemy approaching, to retire, and
                    <pb n="2095" xml:id="p.2095"/>
                    to rouse the rest to arms.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    They used to stand with their hel- mets on, and their shields erected on the ground before them; when tired, they leaned on their spears; or laying their heads on the edge of their shields, stood dozing in such a manner, that from the glittering of their arms they could be seen afar off by the enemy, while themselves could see nothing. He likewise altered the practice of the advanced guards.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Formerly, the guards were kept on duty through the whole day, all under arms, the horsemen with their horses bridled; and when this happened in summer, under a continual scorching sun, both men and horses were so much exhausted by the heat and the languor contracted in so many hours, that very often, when attacked by fresh troops, a few could get the better of a greater number.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore ordered, that they should retire from the morning-watch at noon, and that others should succeed to the duty for the rest of the day; by which means the enemy could never come fresh upon them when they were wearied.
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Aemilius, after publishing, in a general assembly, his orders for these regulations, added a speech of similar purport to that which he had made in the city, that
                    <quote>
                        it was the business of the commander alone to consider what was proper to be done, sometimes singly, sometimes in conjunction with those whom he should call to council;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        and that such as were not called, ought not to pronounce their opinions either in public or in private. That it was a soldier's business to attend to these three things, —his body, that he may keep it in perfect strength and agility; his arms, in good order; and his provisions ready, in case of a sudden order; and to understand, that all other matters relating to him are under the care of the immortal gods and his captain.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        That in any army, where the soldiers formed plans, and that the chief was drawn, first one way, then another, by the rumours of the multitude, nothing was successful.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        For his part,
                    </quote>
                    he declared, that
                    <quote>
                        he would take care, as was the duty of a general, to afford them occasion of acting with success. On their part, they were to make no inquiries whatever as to what was about to take place; but, when the signal was given, to discharge the duty of a soldier.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    After these precepts, he dismissed the assembly, while the veterans themselves acknowledged, that on that day, for the first time, they had, like recruits, been taught the business of a soldier. Nor did they, by such
                    <pb n="2096" xml:id="p.2096"/>
                    expressions only, demonstrate with what perfect conviction they had listened to the consul's discourse; but the practical effect of it was immediate.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    In the whole camp, not one person was to be seen idle; some were sharpening their weapons; others scouring their helmets and cheek-pieces, their shields and breastplates; some fitted their armour to their bodies, and tested the agility of their limbs under it; some brandished their spears, others flourished their swords, and tried the points; so that it could be easily perceived that their intention was, whenever they should come to battle, to finish the war at once, either by a splendid victory or a memorable death.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    On the other side, when Perseus saw that, in consequence of the arrival of the consul, and of the opening of the spring, all was motion and bustle among the Romans, as in a new war;
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    and that the camp had been removed from Phila and pitched on the opposite bank, and that the Roman general employed himself busily, sometimes in going round and examining all his works, doubtless looking out for a place to pass the river;
                    <gap/>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Crevier supplement:
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        <quote>
                            <p>
                                and sometimes in preparing every thing requisite for attack or defence of a camp, with the closest attention, and omitted nothing which could be attempted or achieved by a great general, whether against the enemy or for increasing the effi- ciency of his own men; he (Perseus) also exerted himself no less diligently on his part to rouse the courage of his soldiers, and add more and more strength to his defences, as if he were approaching the crisis of the whole business, and never con- sidered all matters to be adequately
                                <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                                provided for, or the bank sufficiently fortified and secured. Nevertheless, amidst this most vehement ardour on both sides, their camps were for some time in a state of tranquillity. Nor was it ever recorded that such powerful armies, with their camps pitched so near to- gether, had ever lain so quiet.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                In the mean time, a report announced that king Gentius had been defeated, in Illyria, by the praetor Anicius; and that himself, his family, and his whole kingdom, were in the hands of the Romans;
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    which event greatly raised the spirits of the Romans, and struck no small degree of terror into the Macedonians and their king.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    At first, Perseus endeavoured to suppress the intelligence, and sent messengers to Pantauchus, who was on his way from that country, forbidding him to come near the camp; but some of his people had already
                    <pb n="2097" xml:id="p.2097"/>
                    seen certain boys, carried away among the Illyrian hostages; and it is certain that the more pains there are used to conceal any circumstances the more readily they are divulged, through the gossiping disposition of the attendants of kings.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    About this time, ambassadors came to the camp from Rhodes, with the same message which had excited so much resentment in the Roman senate. They were now heard by the council in the camp with much greater indignation than at Rome; some
                    <hi rend="italics">even advised</hi>
                    that they should be instantly driven out of the camp without any reply; but the consul said, that he would give them an answer in fifteen days.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Meanwhile, to show how far the influence of the Rhodians as mediators extended, he began to consult on the plan of carrying forward the war. Some, particularly the older officers, advised to force their way across the Enipeus, and through the enemy's works.
                    <quote>When they should advance in close order and make an assault, the Macedonians,</quote>
                    they said,
                    <quote>
                        would never be able to withstand them. They had been, last year, beaten out of many fortresses much higher and better fortified, which they had occupied with much stronger garrisons.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Others recommended, that Octavius, with the fleet, should sail to Thessalonica; and, by committing depredations on the seacoast, to divide the king's forces; so that when, on the appearance of another enemy behind him, he should turn about to protect the interior part of the kingdom, he would be forced to leave a passage over the Enipeus open in some place or other.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The consul himself was of opinion, that the nature of the bank, and the works erected on it, presented insuperable difficulties; and, besides its being every where furnished with engines, he had been informed, that the enemy were remarkable for using missile weapons with uncommon skill, and with a very certain aim. The consul's full conviction leaned quite another way; as soon, therefore, as the council broke up, he sent for Schœnus and Menophilus, Perrhaebian merchants, whom he knew to be men of probity and good sense, and examined them in private about the nature of the passes leading into Perrhaebia.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    They told him, that the places themselves were not difficult; but that they were occupied by parties of the king's troops; from which he conceived hopes of being able to beat off those parties, by making a sudden attack with a strong force in the night, when they were off their guard.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="2098" xml:id="p.2098"/>
                    For he considered that
                    <quote>
                        javelins, and arrows, and other missile weapons, were useless in the dark, when one cannot see at a distance what to aim at; but that, when combatants closed together in a throng, the business must depend on the sword, in which the Roman soldier was superior.
                    </quote>
                    He resolved to employ those two men as guides; and, sending for the praetor Octavius, explained to him what he intended, ordering him to sail directly with the fleet to Heracleum, and to have in readiness, there, ten days' provisions for one thousand men. He then sent Publius Scipio Nasica, and Quintus Fabius Maximus, his own son, with five thousand chosen men, to Heracleum, as if they were to embark in the fleet, to ravage the coast of the interior parts of Macedonia, as had been proposed in the council. He told them, in private, that there were provisions prepared for them on board, so that they should have no delay.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    He then ordered the guides to divide the road in such a manner that they might attack Pythium at the fourth watch on the third day. He himself, on the day following, in order to withdraw the king from the observation of other matters, attacked his advanced guards as soon as it was light in the middle of the channel of the river, where the fight was maintained by the light infantry on both sides, for the bottom was so uneven, that heavy arms could not be used.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    The slope of each bank was three hundred paces long, and the breadth of the channel, which was of various depths, somewhat more than a mile. In this middle space the fight was carried on, while the king on one side, and the consul with his legions on the other, stood spectators on the ramparts of their camps.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    At a distance, the king's troops had the advantage in fighting with missile weapons; but in close fight the Roman soldier was more steady, and was better defended, either with a target or a Ligurian buckler. About noon, the consul ordered the signal of retreat to be given, and thus the battle ended for that day, after considerable numbers had fallen on both sides.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Next morning at sun-rise, the fight was renewed with greater fury, as their passions had been irritated by the former contest; but the Romans were wounded, not only by those with whom they were immediately engaged, but much more by the multitudes that stood posted in the towers, with missiles of every sort, particularly stones; so that whenever they advanced towards the enemy's bank, the weapons thrown
                    <pb n="2099" xml:id="p.2099"/>
                    from the engines reached even the hindmost of their men. The consul, having lost far more men on that day, somewhat later called off his men.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    On the third day he declined fighting, and moved down to the lowest side of the camp, as if intending to attempt a passage through an intrenchment which stretched down to the sea. Perseus,
                    <hi rend="italics">who did not extend his cares beyond</hi>
                    the objects that lay before his eyes,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Crevier supplement:
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        <quote>
                            <p>
                                bent all his thoughts and exertions to stop the progress of the enemy in the quarter where he lay, careful of nought beside. In the mean time, Publius Nasica, with the detachment assigned to him, having departed towards the sea to Heracleum, when he arrived there, waited for nightfall, ordering his soldiers to refresh them- selves. He then explained to the principal of his officers the real directions of the consul, and when first the darkness spread itself, bending his course to the mountain, he led his troops in silence to Pythium, as he had been commanded. When they had arrived at the very summit, which rises to a height of more than ten stadia, some repose was given to the wearied soldiers. This height, as
                                <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/>
                                has been already stated, Medon, Histiaeus, and Theogenes, who were sent by Perseus, were oc- cupying with five thousand Macedonians, but so great was the negligence of the king's generals, that no one perceived that the Romans were approaching. If we are to believe Polybius, Nasica, having attacked them while asleep, easily dislodged them from the height. Nasica himself, however, narrates the affair very differently in a letter to one of the kings. He says, that the mountain was of steep ascent, but so unguarded that he could
                                <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/>
                                have taken possession of the pass with no trouble, had not a deserter from those Cretans, whom he was taking with him, fled to Perseus, and informed him what was being done. That the king himself remained in his camp, but sent two thousand Macedonians and ten thousand auxiliaries, with Medon as their leader, to take possession of the pass. That with these a most fierce engagement took place on the top of the hill, and, among other things, that he himself was thrust at with a sword by a Thracian soldier, whom he transfixed by driving his spear through his breast. That at length the
                                <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/>
                                Ma- cedonians, being conquered, gave way, and that their leader himself, throwing away his arms, sought safety in a disgrace- ful flight. The Romans pursuing the fugitives had an easy descent, without any danger, to the plain. In this state of
                                <pb n="2100" xml:id="p.2100"/>
                                things Perseus was in perplexity as to what was necessary to be done, as he feared lest, now that a way through the pass had been opened, he should
                                <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/>
                                be hemmed in by the Romans. It was absolutely necessary that he should either retire to Pydna, and await the enemy there, so as to fight with less danger under the walls of a fortified city; or that, dispersing his forces through the cities of Macedonia, conveying the corn and cattle into more
                                <milestone n="19??" unit="section"/>
                                fortified places, and devastating the fields, he should leave the bare soil to the enemy. The mind of the king fluc- tuated irresolute between these two propositions: his friends. thinking that that which was the most honourable would also be the safer, advised him to try the fortune of a battle, alleging both
                                <milestone n="20??" unit="section"/>
                                that he was superior in the number of his soldiers, and that he ought surely to trust to that valour which, while it was natural to their minds, would be inflamed by the most power- ful and sacred incitements to a valiant opposition which could act upon men; —their altars, their hearths, and their reli- gious institutions, amidst which and for which they had to fight; their parents and their
                                <milestone n="21??" unit="section"/>
                                wives, and, lastly, their king himself observing them, and exposing himself to a share of the danger. Influenced by these suggestions, the king prepared himself for a battle, and when he had retired to Pydna, at once pitched his camp, drew up his army, and assigned to each of his leaders his position and duty, as if about to fight immediately after the march. The locality was of this kind; the plain was suited for the ranging of the phalanx, which requires an open and even space, not, however, such as that it could be easily moved forward; then there were continuous hills which afforded to the light-armed troops the means of retreating at one time, and at another of wheeling round. Two
                                <milestone n="22??" unit="section"/>
                                streams, the one of which the inhabitants called Œson, the other Leucus, though they flowed with but a scanty supply of water, yet seemed likely to occasion some trouble to the Romans. Aemilius, hav- ing united his forces with Nasica, set out directly against the enemy, but at the sight of their army, which was most effective both as to the number and the strength of the soldiers, and admirably drawn
                                <milestone n="23??" unit="section"/>
                                up and ranged for battle, he stopped, struck with awe, and revolving many considerations within himself.
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">The season of the year</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The above has been introduced to supply the place of a passage which has been lost from the original text.
                    </note>
                    was a little after the summer
                    <pb n="2101" xml:id="p.2101"/>
                    solstice; the time of the day was approaching towards
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    noon; and his march had been performed amidst great quantities of dust, and the increasing heat
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    of the sun. Lassitude and thirst were already felt, and both would certainly be aggravated by mid-day coming on. He resolved, therefore, not to expose his men in that condition to an enemy, fresh and in full vigour; but so great was the ardour for battle in the minds of both parties, that the general
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    had occasion for as much art to elude the wishes of his own men, as those of the enemy. He urged the military tribunes to hasten
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    the forming of the troops, went himself round the ranks, and with exhortations inflamed their courage for the fight. At first, they called to him for the signal briskly; but afterwards, as the heat increased, their looks
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    became less lively, and their voices fainter, while many stood resting on their shields, or leaning on their javelins. He then, at length, openly ordered the foremost ranks to measure out the front of a camp, and store the baggage; on seeing which, some undisguisedly rejoiced
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    that he had not compelled them to fight when they were wearied with marching and with the scorching heat. Immediately about the general were the lieutenants-general, and the commanders of the foreign troops; among others Attalus, who, when they thought that the consul intended
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    to fight, (for even to them he did not disclose his intention of delaying,) had all approved the measure. On this sudden alteration of his plan, while the rest were silent, Nasica alone of them all ventured to advise the
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    consul, not to let slip from his hands an enemy, who, by shunning a battle, had baffled former commanders.
                    <quote>There was reason to fear,</quote>
                    he said,
                    <quote>
                        that if he should march off
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        in the night, he would have to be pursued with extreme toil and danger, into the heart of Macedonia; and the troops must be led about, as under former generals, wandering through the glens and forests of the Macedonian mountains. He therefore earnestly recommended to attack the enemy while he had
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        him in an open plain, and not to lose the opportunity of obtaining a victory, which now presented itself.
                    </quote>
                    The consul, not in the least offended at the frank advice of so illustrious a
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    youth, answered:
                    <quote>
                        Nasica, I once thought as you do now; hereafter you will come to think as I do. By the many chances of war, I have learned when it is proper to fight, when to abstain from fighting. It would
                        <pb n="2102" xml:id="p.2102"/>
                        not be right in me, at present, standing
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        at the head of the troops, to explain to you the causes that render it better to rest to-day. Ask my reasons some other time. At present you will acquiesce in the judgment of an old commander.
                    </quote>
                    The
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    youth was silent, concluding that the consul certainly saw some objections to fighting, which did not appear to him.
                </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Paullus, as soon as he saw the camp marked out, and the baggage laid up, drew off,
                    <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/>
                    first, the veterans from the rear line, then the first-rank men, while the spear-men stood in the front, lest the enemy might make any attempt; and lastly, the spear-men, beginning at the right wing, and leading them away, gradually, by single companies.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Thus were the infantry drawn off without tumult; and, in the mean time, the cavalry and light infantry faced the enemy; nor were the cavalry recalled from their station, until the rampart and trench were finished.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The king, though he was disposed to have given battle that day, was yet satisfied; since his men knew, that the delay was owing to the enemy: and he led back his troops to their station.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    When the camp had been thoroughly fortified, Caius Sulpicius Gallus, a military tribune of the second legion, who had been praetor the year before, with the consul's permission collected the soldiers in assembly, and gave them notice, lest they should any of them consider the matter as a prodigy, that,
                    <quote>on the following night, the moon would be eclipsed, from the second hour to the fourth.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    He mentioned that,
                    <quote>
                        as this happened in the course of nature, at stated times, it could be known, and foretold.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        As, therefore, they did not wonder at the regular rising and setting of the sun and moon, or at the moon's sometimes shining with a full orb, and sometimes in its wane, showing only small horns, so neither ought they to construe as a portent, its being obscured when covered with the shadow of the earth.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    When on the night preceding the day before the nones of September, at the hour mentioned, the eclipse took place, the Roman soldiers thought the wisdom of Gallus almost divine; but the Macedonians were shocked, as at a dismal prodigy, foreboding the fall of their kingdom and the ruin of their nation; nor did their soothsayers explain it otherwise.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    There was shouting and yelling in the camp of the Macedonians, until the moon emerged forth into its full light.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Both armies had been so eager for an engagement, that, next day, both the
                    <pb n="2103" xml:id="p.2103"/>
                    king and the consul were censured by many of their respective men for having separated without a battle.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    The king could readily excuse himself, not only as the enemy had led back his troops into camp, openly declining a battle; but, also, as he had posted his men on ground of such a nature, that the phalanx (which even a small inequality of surface renders useless) could not advance on it.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, besides appearing to have neglected an opportunity of fighting, and to have given the enemy room to go off in the night, if he were so inclined, was thought to waste time at the present, under pretence of offering sacrifice, though the signal had been displayed, at the first light, for going out to the field.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    At last, about the third hour, the sacrifices being duly performed, he summoned a council, and there, too, he was deemed by several to spin out, in talking and unseasonable consultation, the time that ought to be employed in action; after the conversation, however, the consul addressed to them the following speech.
                </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    "Publius Nasica, a youth of uncommon merit, was the only one of those who were for fighting yesterday, that disclosed his sentiments to me; and even he was afterwards silent, so that he seems to have come over to my opinion.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Some others have thought proper, rather to carp at their general in his absence, than to offer advice in his presence.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Now, I shall, without the least reluctance, make known to you, Publius Nasica, and to any who, with less openness, entertained the same opinion with you, my reasons for deferring an engagement.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For, so far am I from being sorry for yesterday's inaction, that I am convinced that by that course I preserved the army. And if any of you think that I hold this opinion groundlessly, let him come forward, if he pleases, and take with me a review of how many things were favourable to the enemy and adverse to us.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the first place, how far they surpass us in numbers, I am sure not one of you was at any time ignorant; and yesterday, I am convinced that you must have observed it, when you saw their line drawn out.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Of our small force, a fourth part had been left to guard the baggage; and you know that they are not the worst of the soldiers who are left in custody of the baggage.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    But suppose we were all here, can we believe it a matter of little moment, that, with the blessing of the gods, we shall this day, if judged proper, or tomorrow at farthest, march to battle out of this our own camp,
                    <pb n="2104" xml:id="p.2104"/>
                    where we have lodged last night?
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Is there no difference, whether you order a soldier to take arms in his own tent, when he has not suffered any fatigue on that day, either from a long march or laborious work; after he has enjoyed his natural rest, and is fresh; so as to lead him into the field vigorous both in body and mind; or whether, when he is wearied by such a march, or fatigued with carrying a load;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    while he is wet with sweat, and while his throat is parched with thirst, and his mouth and eyes filled with dust, you oppose him, under a scorching noon-day sun, to an enemy who has had full repose, and who brings into the battle his strength unimpaired by any previous circumstance?
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Is there, in the name of the gods, any one so dastardly, that, if matched in this manner, he would not overcome the bravest man?
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    We must consider, that the enemy had, quite at their leisure, formed their line of battle; had recruited their spirits, and were standing in regular order; whereas we must have formed our line in hurry and confusion, and have engaged before it was completed.
                </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>
                        We should then confessedly have an irregular and disorderly line, but should we have had a camp fortified, a watering-place provided, and the passage to it secured by troops, and all the country round reconnoitred; or should we have been without any one spot of our own, except the naked field on which we fought?
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Your fathers considered a fortified camp as a harbour of safety in all the emergencies of an army; out of which they were to march to battle, and in which, after being tossed in the storm of the fight, they had a safe retreat.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        For that reason, besides enclosing it with works, they strengthened it further with a numerous guard; for any general who lost his camp, though he should have been victorious in the field, yet was deemed vanquished. A camp is a residence for the victorious, a refuge for the conquered.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                        How many armies, to whom the fortune of the fight has been adverse, when driven within their ramparts, have, at their own time, and sometimes the next moment, sallied out and defeated their victors!
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        This military settlement is another native country to every soldier: the rampart is as the wall of his city, and his own tent his habitation and his home. Should we have fought while in that unsettled state, and without quarters prepared, to which, even if victorious, we might retire?
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        In
                        <pb n="2105" xml:id="p.2105"/>
                        opposition to these considerations of the difficulties and impediments to the fighting at that time, one argument is urged: What if the enemy had marched off in the course of last night? What immense fatigue, it is observed, must have been undergone in pursuing him to the remotest parts of Macedonia!
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        But, for my part, I take it as a certainty, that if he had had any intention of retreating, he would neither have waited, nor drawn out his troops to battle. For, how much more easily could he have gone off while we were at a great distance, than now, when we are close behind him! Nor could he escape observation in departing either by day or by night.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        What could be more desirable to us, who were obliged to attack their camp, defended as it was by a very high bank of a river, and enclosed likewise with a rampart and a number of towers, than that they should quit their fortifications, and, marching off with haste, give us an opportunity of attacking their rear in an open plain? These were the reasons for deferring a battle from yesterday to this day.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        For I am myself also inclined to fight; and for that reason, as the way to come at the enemy over the river Enipeus was stopped, I have opened a new way, by dislodging the enemy's guards from another pass. Nor will I rest until I shall have brought the war to a conclusion.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Silence ensued after this address; for some were convinced by his arguments, and the rest were fearful of giving offence needlessly in a matter which, from whatever cause overlooked, could not now be regained. Even on that day, neither the king nor the consul was desirous of engaging; not the king, because he was not going, as on the day before, to attack men who were fatigued after their march, were hurried in forming their line, and not completely marshalled; nor the consul, because, in his new camp, no collection was yet made of wood or forage, to bring which from the adjacent country a great number of his men had gone forth from the camp. Still fortune, whose power prevails over all human schemes, brought about a battle.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Nearer to the enemy's camp was a river, not very large, from which both parties supplied themselves with water; and that this might be done with safety, guards were stationed on each bank. On the Roman side were two cohorts, a Marrucinian and a Pelignian, with two troops of Samnite horse, commanded by a lieutenant general, Marcus Sergius Silus; and in the front of the camp
                    <pb n="2106" xml:id="p.2106"/>
                    there was posted another guard, under Caius Cluvius, lieutenant-general, composed of three cohorts, a Firmian, a Vestinian, and a Cremonian; besides two troops of horse, a Placentine and an Aesernian. While there was quiet at the river, neither party making an attack; about the ninth hour, a horse, breaking loose from those who had the care of him, ran off towards the farther bank, and three Roman soldiers followed him through the water, which was about as high as their knees. At the same time two Thracians endeavoured to bring the horse from the middle of the channel to their own bank; but one of these having been slain, and the horse having been recovered, they retired to their post. On the enemy's bank there was a body of eight hundred Thracians, of whom a few, at first enraged at their countryman being killed before their eyes, crossed the river in pursuit of his slayers; in a little time some more, and at last all of them, and engaged with the guard which defended the bank on the Roman side. Some authors say, that by the command of Paullus, the horse was driven without a bridle to the enemy's side, and men sent to bring him back, in order that the enemy might first provoke the conflict. For when favourable auspices were not obtained by the first twenty victims, at length the haruspices declared,
                    <quote>
                        that the entrails of the twenty-first portended victory to the Romans, provided they acted only upon the defensive, without striking the first blow.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    However, whether by the design of the leader or by accident, the battle was certainly brought about from this commencement, and, in a short time, was so augmented by party after party on both sides flying to carry succour to their comrades, that the commanders were compelled to come down to a general decision of the contest; for Aemilius, on hearing the tumult, came forth from his tent, and when it seemed neither easy nor safe to recall or stop the impetuosity of those who were rushing to arms, he thought it best to avail himself of the ardour of the soldiers, and to turn an accident into an opportunity.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He therefore led out his forces from the camp, and riding among their ranks exhorted them to enter upon the contest they had so greatly desired with corresponding ardour. At the same time Nasica, having been sent forward to reconnoitre what was the position of affairs amongst those who were engaged in the commencing conflict, announced that Perseus was approaching with his
                    <pb n="2107" xml:id="p.2107"/>
                    army in battle-array. First marched the Thracians, men of fierce countenance and tall of stature, and protected on their left side by bucklers which shone with remarkable brightness. A black cloak covered both shoulders, and on their right they brandished from time to time a sword of enormous weight. Next to the Thracians stood the hired auxiliaries, their armour and costume differing according to their respective nations; and among these were some Paeonians.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Next came a band of the Macedonians themselves, which they called the phalanx of the Leucaspides. A few selected for their strength and valour were more conspicuous, shining in gilded armour and scarlet cloaks: this was the middle of the army. These were succeeded by those whom they called Chalcaspides, from their brazen and glittering bucklers. This phalanx was placed next to the other on the right wing.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Besides these two phalanxes, which constituted the chief strength of the Macedonian army, the targeteers, who were also Macedonians, and carried pikes like those of the phalanx, but in other respects more lightly armed, were distributed on the wings advanced, and projecting beyond the rest of the line. The plain was illuminated with the brightness of their arms, the neighbouring hills echoed with their shouts, as they mutually cheered each other on. Such was the swiftness and boldness of all these forces as they came out to the fight, that those who were first slain fell at two hundred and fifty paces from the Roman camp.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Meanwhile Aemilius advanced, and when he saw not only the other Macedonians, but those who constituted the phalanx, some with their bucklers, and some with their targets removed from their shoulders, and with their pikes inclined in one direction receiving the attack of the Romans, admiring the firmness of the serried ranks, and the bristling rampart of outstretched pikes, he was smitten at once with astonishment and terror, as if he had never seen so fearful a spectacle, and was afterwards in the habit of frequently referring to it, and making this statement respecting himself. Carefully concealing however at the time the agitation of his troubled mind, he with serene countenance and careless aspect, and with his head and body undefended, drew up his line. The Pelignians were now fighting against the targeteers, who were ranged opposite to them, and when, after long and laborious efforts, they were unable to break through
                    <pb n="2108" xml:id="p.2108"/>
                    that compact array, Salius, who was commanding the Pelignians, seized a standard and threw it among the enemy.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    On this a prodigious conflict was excited, whilst on the one side the Pelignians strove with all their might to recover the standard, the Macedonians on the other to retain possession of it. The former strove either to cut through the long spears of the Macedonians, or to repel them with the bosses of their bucklers, or in some instances to turn them aside even with their naked hands, while the latter drove them firmly grasped with both hands with such force against the enemy, who rushed on with rash and heedless fury, that, penetrating shields and bucklers, they overthrew the men transfixed in like manner. The first ranks of the Pelignians having been thus defeated, those who stood behind them were also cut down, and the rest retreated towards the mountain which the inhabitants call Mount Olocrus, though not yet in open flight. On this the grief of Aemilius burst forth, so that he even rent his robe with mortification, for in other places as well he saw that his men were hanging back and approaching with timidity that hedge of steel, as it were, with which the Macedonian line bristled in every part.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But that skilful general observed that this conjunction of the foe was not every where close, but that here and there it opened with little interstices, either on account of the unevenness of the ground, or on account of the very length of its front, which was immensely extended, while those who attempted to occupy higher ground were necessarily, though unwillingly, separated from those who occupied lower positions, or those who were slower from those who were faster, and those who advanced from those who held back, and lastly, those who pressed upon the enemy from those who were repulsed. In order, therefore, entirely to break the ranks of the enemy, and to distribute the irresistible attack of the entire phalanx into a number of separate conflicts, he commanded his men, that wherever they should see the line of the enemy present openings, they should individually rush to those spots, and insinuating themselves like a wedge into such spaces, however narrow their extent, they should fight with impetuosity.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    This order having been issued and spread through the whole army, he led on in person one of the legions to the battle.
                </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The troops were impressed by the high dignity of his office, the personal renown of the man, and, above all, by his
                    <pb n="2109" xml:id="p.2109"/>
                    age: for, though more than sixty years old, he discharged the duties of youth, taking on himself the principal share both of the labour and danger. His legion filled up the space between the targeteers and the phalanxes, and thus disunited the enemy's line.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Behind him were the targeteers, and his front faced the shielded phalanx of Chalcaspides. Lucius Albinus, a man of consular rank, was ordered to lead on the second legion against the phalanx of the Leucaspides, which formed the centre of the enemy's line.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    On the right wing, where the fight began, at the river, he brought forward the elephants, with the cohorts of allied cavalry; and from this quarter the retreat of the Macedonians first began.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For as new contrivances generally make an important figure in the words of men, but on being put in practice ofttimes prove vain and ineffectual, so on that occasion the elephants in the line of battle were a mere name, without the least use. Their attack was followed by the Latin allies, who forced the enemy's left wing to give way.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the centre, the second legion charged and dispersed the phalanx;
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    nor was there any more evident cause of the victory, than there being many distinct fights, which first disordered that body, when it wavered, and at last quite broke it. Its force, while it is compact and bristling with extended spears, is irresistible; but if, by attacking them separately, you force them to turn about their spears, which, on account of their length and weight, are unwieldy, they are mingled in a confused mass; and, if any disorder arises on the flank or rear, they fall into irretrievable disorder.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Thus, now, they were obliged to oppose the Romans in small parties, and with their own line broken into numerous divisions; and the Romans, when any opening was made, worked themselves into their ranks.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    But had they advanced with their entire line, straight against the phalanx when in its regular order, just as happened to the Pelignians, who, in the beginning of the battle, incautiously engaged the targeteers;
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    they would have impaled themselves on the spears, and would have been unable to withstand such a firm body.
                </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    But though a massacre was made of the infantry on all sides, except those who threw away their arms and fled, the cavalry quitted the field with scarcely any loss.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    The king himself was the first in flight. With the sacred squadrons of horse he took the road to Pella, and was quickly followed by
                    <pb n="2110" xml:id="p.2110"/>
                    Cotys and the Odrysian cavalry.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The other wings of the Macedonians, likewise, went off with full ranks: because, as the line of infantry stood in the way, the slaughter of them detained the conquerors, and made them careless of pursuing the cavalry.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For a long time, the men of the phalanx were cut off, in front, on the flanks, and on the rear; at last, such as could avoid the enemy's hands, fled unarmed towards the sea; some even ran into the water, and, stretching out their hands to those on board the fleet, humbly begged their lives.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    And when they saw boats coming from all the ships, supposing that they were coming to take them in rather than to slay them, advanced farther into the water, so that some of them even swam.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But, when they were cut to pieces as enemies by the boats, such as were able regained the land by swimming back, where they met with a more dreadful death; for the elephants, which their riders had driven down to the shore, trod them under foot, and crushed them in pieces.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    It was generally acknowledged, that the Macedonians never lost so great a number of men in any battle with the Romans; for their killed amounted to twenty thousand; six thousand, who made their escape from the field to Pydna, fell alive into the hands of the Romans, and five thousand were taken straggling through the country.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Of the victorious army there fell not more than one hundred, the greater part of whom were Pelignians; but a much greater number were wounded.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    If the battle had been begun earlier, so that the conquerors might have had daylight enough for a pursuit, all their troops must have been utterly destroyed. As it happened, the approach of night both screened the fugitives, and made the Romans unwilling to follow them through an unknown country.
                </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus fled as far as the Pierian wood, with a military appearance, being attended by a numerous body of horse, together with his royal retinue;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    but when he came into the thicket, where there were numerous paths in different directions, and when darkness came on, he turned out of the main path with a very few, in whom he placed the greatest confidence.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The horsemen, abandoned by their leader, dispersed, in different directions, to their respective homes; some of whom made their way to Pella, quicker than Perseus himself, because they went by the straight and open road.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The king was hindered by his fears and the many difficulties of
                    <pb n="2111" xml:id="p.2111"/>
                    the way, till near midnight.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus was met at the palace by Euctus, governor of Pella, and the royal pages; but of all his friends who had escaped from the battle by various chances, and had reached Pella, not one would come near him, though they were repeatedly sent for. Only three persons accompanied him in his flight; Evander a Cretan, Neo a Bœotian, and Archidamus an Aetolian.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    With these he continued his retreat, at the fourth watch;
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    for he began to fear, lest those who had refused to obey his summons, might, presently, attempt something more audacious. He had an escort of about five hundred Cretans.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    He took the road to Amphipolis; leaving Pella in the night, and hastening to get over the river Axius before daylight, as he thought that it, from the difficulty of passing it, would put an end to the further pursuit of the Romans.
                </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The consul, when he returned victorious to his camp, to mar his entire joy, was much distressed by concern for his younger son.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    This was Publius Scipio, who afterwards acquired the title of Africanus by the destruction of Carthage. He was, by birth, the son of the consul Paullus, and by adoption, the grandson of the elder Africanus.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    He was then only in the seventeenth year of his age, which circumstance heightened his father's anxiety; for, pursuing the enemy with eagerness, he had been carried away by the crowd to a distant part. But when he returned late in the evening, the consul, having received his son in safety, felt unmixed joy for the very important victory.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    When the news of the battle reached Amphipolis, the matrons ran together to the temple of Diana, whom they style Tauropolos, to implore her aid. Diodorus, who was governor of the city, fearing lest the Thracians, of whom there were two thousand in garrison, might, during the confusion, plunder the city, contrived to receive in the middle of the forum a letter through a person whom he had deceitfully suborned to personate a courier.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The contents of it were, that
                    <quote>
                        the Romans had put in their fleet at Emathia, and were ravaging the territory round; and that the governors of Emathia besought him to send a reinforcement to oppose the ravagers.
                    </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    After reading this, he desired the Thracians to march to the relief of the coast of Emathia, telling them, as an encouragement, that the Romans being dispersed through the country, they might easily kill many of them, and gain a large booty.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    At the same time he threw discredit on the
                    <pb n="2112" xml:id="p.2112"/>
                    report of the defeat, alleging that, if it were true, many would have come thither direct from the retreat.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Having, on this pretence, sent the Thracians out of the town, he no sooner saw them pass the river Strymon, than he shut the gates.
                </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    On the third day after the battle, Perseus arrived at Amphipolis, and sent thence to Paullus suppliant ambassadors, with the wand of peace.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In the mean time, Hippias Medon, and Pantauchus, the principal friends of the king, went themselves to the consul, and surrendered to the Romans the city of Berœa, to which they had fled after the battle; and several other cities, struck with fear, prepared to do the same.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The consul despatched to Rome, with letters and the news of his victory, his son Quintus Fabius, Lucius Lentulus, and Quintus Metellus. He gave to his infantry the spoils of the enemy who were slain, and to his cavalry the plunder of the circumjacent country, provided, however, that they did not stay out of the camp longer than two nights. He himself then removed nearer the sea towards Pydna.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Berœa, Thessalonica, and Pella, and indeed almost every city in Macedonia, successively surrendered within two days.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    The inhabitants of Pydna, which was the nearest, had not yet sent any ambassadors;
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    the confused multitude, made up of many different nations, with the numbers who had been driven into one place in their flight from the battle, embarrassed the counsels and unanimity of the inhabitants; the gates, too, were not only shut, but closed up with walls. Milo and Pantauchus were sent to confer, under the wall, with Solon, who commanded in the place.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    By his means the crowd of military people were sent away, and the town was surrendered and given up to the soldiers to be plundered.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus, after making a single effort to procure the assistance of the Basaltians, to whom he had sent ambassadors in vain, came forth into a general assembly, bringing with him his son Philip, in order to encourage the Amphipolitans themselves, and to raise the spirits of those horse and foot soldiers who had either constantly accompanied him, or had happened to fly to the same place.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But, though he made several attempts to speak, he was always stopped by his tears;
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    so that, finding himself unable to proceed, he told Evander, the Cretan, what he wished to have laid before the people, and came down from the tribunal.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Although the multitude, on observing the aspect of the king, and his pitiable
                    <pb n="2113" xml:id="p.2113"/>
                    weeping, had themselves sighed and wept with him, yet they refused to listen to the discourse of Evander; and some, from the middle of the assembly, had the assurance to interrupt him, exclaiming,
                    <quote>
                        Depart to some other place, that the few of us who are left alive may not be destroyed on your account.
                    </quote>
                    Their daring opposition stopped Evander's mouth.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The king retired to his palace; and, causing his treasures to be put on board some barks which lay in the Strymon, went down himself to the river. The Thracians would not venture to trust themselves on board, but went off to their own homes, as did the rest of the soldiers.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    The Cretans only followed in hope of the money: but, as any distribution of it among them would probably raise more discontent than gratitude, fifty talents
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        9687
                        <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note>
                    were laid for them on the bank, to be scrambled for. After this scramble they went on board, yet in such hurry and disorder, that they sunk one of the barks, which was swamped by numbers in the mouth of the river.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    They arrived that day at Galepsus, and the next at Samothrace, to which they were bound.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Thither it is said that as many as two thousand talents
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        10
                        <hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
                    </note>
                    were conveyed.
                </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Paullus sent officers to hold the government of the several cities which had surrendered; lest, at a time when peace was but newly restored, the conquered might suffer any ill treatment. He detained with himself the ambassadors of Perseus;
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and, being uninformed of the flight of the king, detached Publius Nasica, with a small party of horse and foot, to Amphipolis, both that he might lay waste the country of Sintice, and be ready to obstruct every effort of the king. In the mean time, Melibœa was taken and sacked by Cneius Octavius.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    At Aeginium, to which Cneius Anicius, a lieutenant-general, had been despatched, two hundred men were lost by a sally made from the town; the Aeginians not being aware that the war was at an end. The consul, quitting Pydna, arrived with his whole army, on the second day, at Pella; and, pitching his camp at the distance of a mile from it, remained in that station for several days, reconnoitring on all sides the situation of the city; and he perceived that it was chosen to be the capital of the kingdom, not without good reason.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    It stands on a hill which faces the south-west, and is surrounded by morasses,
                    <pb n="2114" xml:id="p.2114"/>
                    formed by stagnant waters from the adjacent lakes, so deep as to be impassable either in winter or summer.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the part of the morass nearest to the city the citadel rises up like an island, being built on a mound of earth formed with immense labour, so as to be capable of supporting the wall, and secure against any injury from the water of the surrounding marsh.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    At a distance it seems to join the city rampart, but is divided from it by a river, and united by a bridge; so that if externally invaded it has no access from any part, and if the king chooses to confine any person within it, there is no way for an escape except by that bridge, which can be guarded with great ease.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This was the depository of the royal treasure; but, at that time, there was nothing found there but the three hundred talents which had been sent to king Gentius, and afterwards brought back. While they were stationed at Pella, audience was given to a great number of embassies, which came with congratulations, especially out of Thessaly. Then, receiving intelligence that Perseus had passed over to Samothrace, the consul departed from Pella, and after four days' march, arrived at Amphipolis.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Here the whole multitude poured out of the town to meet him; a plain demonstration that the people considered themselves not as
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Crevier supplement:
                        <quote>
                            <p>
                                bereft of a good and just king, but as delivered from a haughty tyrant. Paullus having entered the city while engaged in religious services, and performing a solemn sacrifice,
                                <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                                the altar was sud- denly kindled by lightning, while all considered the event to signify that the offerings of the consul were most acceptable to the gods, since they were consecrated by fire from heaven. The consul, after a
                                <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/>
                                short delay at Amphipolis, proceeded at once in pursuit of Perseus, and also that he might carry his victorious arms round to all the nations which had been under his sway, made for
                                <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                                the province of Odomantice, a region be- yond the river Strymon, and encamped at Sirae.
                            </p>
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
