<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 43-45 - 44</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Schlesinger" role="editor">Alfred C. Schlesinger, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 100Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books XLIII-XLV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1951: published without copyright notice</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="p.91"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="book">
                <head>Book XLIV</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> AT the beginning of the spring following the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    winter campaigns just mentioned, Quintus Marcius Philippus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XLII. xxxvii. —xlvii. and lvi. 7.</note> the consul
                    left Rome and reached Brundisium with five thousand <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This figure seems to come from Polybius. A larger
                        figure for these reinforcements is mentioned in XLIII. xii. 3. </note> men
                    whom he planned to take over with him as reinforcements for the <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> legions. The ex-consul Marcus Popilius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf. XLII. xxii. 7.</note> and some young
                    men of equally high birth accompanied the consul as tribunes of the soldiers
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Perhaps elected by the people, see
                        XLIII. xii. 7.</note> in the legions for Macedonia. About the same time
                    Gaius Marcius Figulus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A cousin of the
                        consul Philippus. Cf. Polybius XVIII. 16. 4; Livy XLIII. xi. 7. </note> the
                    praetor, who had been assigned <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> to the fleet,
                    arrived in Brundisium, and the two commanders left Italy together, reached
                    Corcyra the next day, and made port at Actium, the harbour of Acarnania, on the
                    day <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> after. Thence the consul disembarked at
                    Ambracia and marched overland to Thessaly; the praetor rounded Cape Leucas,
                    entered the Gulf of Corinth and, leaving his ships at Creusa, also took to the
                    land and made for the fleet at Chalcis through the midst of Boeotia-one day's
                    rapid journey. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At this time Aulus Hostilius had his camp in
                    Thessaly near Old Pharsalus, having on the one hand performed no military feat
                    worth mentioning, but on <pb n="p.93"/> the other hand having accustomed the
                    soldiery to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        169</note> strict military discipline in place of uncontrolled laxness and
                    having loyally furthered the interests of the allies and protected them from any
                    kind of harm. On hearing of his successor's approach, he carefully inspected his
                    men, their arms, and their horses, and with his army in parade order went to
                    meet the approaching <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> consul. Not only was the
                    first meeting of the commanders in accord with the high station both of the men
                    themselves and of the Roman name, but the utmost harmony prevailed in their
                    subsequent operations, for the proconsul remained with the <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> army. </p>
                <p> A few days later the consul addressed a meeting of his <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> soldiers. Beginning with the unnatural crimes of Perseus
                    committed against his brother and planned against his <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> father, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the
                        attacks of Perseus against his brother, cf. XL. v ff. and xx ff.; in XL.
                        lvi. 9, Philip is represented as having died in anger against Perseus, but
                        Livy gives no description of the plot here alleged. </note> he went on to
                    mention the acquisition of the throne by crime, the subsequent poisonings and
                    slaughter, the attack by scoundrelly bandits on Eumenes, the wrongs committed by
                    Perseus against the Roman people, and the plunderings of cities allied to them,
                    contrary to <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> treaty. </p>
                <p>
                    <quote>How hateful all these actions are to the gods also,</quote> said the
                    consul, <quote> Perseus will discover in the outcome of his enterprises; for the
                        gods support the cause of duty and faithfulness, the qualities by which the
                        Roman people has climbed to so great an <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        eminence. </quote> The consul then compared the strength of the Roman
                    people, who now controlled the whole earth, with that of Macedonia, and the
                    military <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> forces of the one with the other,
                    and asked how much greater were the resources of Philip and Antiochus, which had
                    been shattered by forces no greater than this Roman army? </p>
                <pb n="p.95"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the consul had aroused the ardour of
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> the
                    soldiers by a speech to this effect, he began to hold councils on strategy.
                    Gaius Marcius the praetor, after picking up the fleet at Chalcis, arrived in
                    camp. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was decided not to waste more time by
                    lingering in Thessaly, but to break camp at once and proceed thence into
                    Macedonia, while <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> the praetor was to make
                    sure that the fleet should simultaneously attack the hostile coast-line. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After the praetor's departure, the consul
                    ordered his soldiers to take with them grain for a month and broke camp nine
                    days after having assumed command; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> after a
                    day's march, he summoned the guides for various routes, bade each explain before
                    the council the route by which he would guide them, and then, after dismissing
                    the guides, laid before the council the question of which route to choose.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some preferred the road via Pythoüs;
                    others the one over the Cambunian Mountains used the preceding year by the
                    consul Hostilius; others, a route past Lake Ascuris. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For Pythoüs, cf. XLII. liii. 6 and below, xxxii. 9 and
                        xxxv. 15. Perseus entered Thessaly by the Cambunian Mountain route, cf.
                        XLII. liii. 6; Livy's account of the march of Hostilius seems to have
                        disappeared in one of the lacunae, cf. p. 14 n. 7. Volustana, mentioned
                        below, sec. 10, is at the north-east end of this route, next to Mt. Olympus.
                        Lake Ascuris is the modern Nezeros. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For a certain distance yet there was no
                    divergence in the routes; therefore the discussion as to this choice was
                    postponed until they should encamp near the point of separation of the roads.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thence the consul led his army into
                    Perrhaebia and settled down between Azorus and Doliche <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This seems to have been farther west than necessary for
                        the Ascuris route. </note> for further conference as to the road to take.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> During the same time Perseus, knowing that
                    the enemy was <pb n="p.97"/> approaching, but unaware which route he would
                    choose, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    decided to occupy all the passes with forces. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    To the summit of the Cambunian Mountains (which the Macedonians themselves call
                    Volustana) he sent ten thousand light-armed young men <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Young men</quote> seems superfluous, and editors are inclined to
                        substitute an expression suggesting whence the troops came. </note> under
                    the command of Asclepiodotus; near the fort above Lake Ascuris —Lapathus is the
                    name of the place —Hippias <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> was ordered to
                    hold the pass with a force of twelve thousand Macedonians. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Asclepiodotus is mentioned in XLII. li. 7 as a
                        commander of Gauls; Hippias appears in XLII. li. 3 and lix. 7 as a commander
                        of phalanx-men. </note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The king himself with the rest of his forces
                    remained in camp near Dium; later, so planlessly that he seemed to have lost his
                    mind, he would dash with some unencumbered cavalry along the shore, now to
                    Heracleum, now to Phila, returning without halt to Dium. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This patrolling may not have been as senseless as Livy
                        would have it; Livy seems to be convinced that the gods made Perseus mad,
                        preparatory to destroying him; but if Perseus had happened upon the Romans
                        when they actually came down from the mountains, it would have been to his
                        advantage. Cf. Diodorus XXX. 10 for the same view of Perseus' folly; <hi
                            rend="italics">ibid.</hi> 2 elaborates the incident told below, vi. 1.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the consul had settled on the plan
                    of proceeding by the pass where the king's officer was encamped near Ottolobus.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> the pass by Lake Ascuris. Cf. Herodotus VII.
                        128 on Xerxes' choice of routes in <date when="-0480">480 B.C.</date> ; he
                        went via Perrhaebia and Gonnus. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was decided, however, to send ahead four
                    thousand men to seize valuable advance positions; the commanders of this force
                    were Marcus Claudius and Quintus Marcius, the son of the consul. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Immediately the whole Roman army followed. However,
                    so steep, rough, and rugged was the road that the advance forces, travelling
                    light, barely completed a two days' march of fifteen miles <pb n="p.99"/> before
                    pitching camp. The place they occupied is <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> called Dierus. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Thence on the following day they advanced seven
                    miles, seized a hill not far from the enemy's camp, and reported by messenger to
                    the consul that they were in contact with the enemy, that they had occupied a
                    place safe and suitable for all purposes, and that he should follow them as
                    rapidly as he could march. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While the consul
                    was worrying both over the difficulty of the journey upon which he had entered
                    and over the fate of the small force which he had sent ahead into the midst of
                    hostile garrisons, he was met by the messenger near Lake Ascuris. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The consul thereupon gained confidence, and after
                    joining the advance force encamped beneath the hill which had been seized, in
                    the place best adapted through the nature of the terrain. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Not only the enemy camp, a little over a mile away, but the
                    whole region to Dium, Phila, and the seashore was before their eyes in the
                    extensive view from so lofty a ridge. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This
                    sight roused the spirits of the soldiery, after they had a birds eye view of the
                    whole campaign including all the king's forces and the land of the enemy, from
                    so near by. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Although the soldiers, made eager
                    by this sight, urged the consul to lead them at once to the enemy's camp, one
                    day's rest was given them, since they were weary from the toil of the march.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Next day, the consul, leaving part of his
                    forces to guard the camp, advanced against the enemy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hippias had recently been sent by the king to
                    guard the pass; as soon as he saw the Roman camp on its hill, he roused the
                    spirits of his men to combat; and now he marched out against the oncoming column
                    of the consul. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans had come out <pb
                        n="p.101"/> unencumbered for battle and the enemy were light troops, a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> type very
                    ready to stir up combat. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Therefore immediately
                    on meeting they discharged their weapons; many wounds were both received and
                    inflicted by either side in the hasty encounter; small numbers of both forces
                    were killed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Now that their spirits had been
                    roused for the succeeding day, a more stubborn clash of larger forces occurred;
                    and the decisive battle of the war would have been fought if there had been room
                    enough to deploy the battle line; but the ridge of the mountain running up to a
                    narrow peak barely allowed for a front of three files. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> And so while a few fought, the large remainder, especially
                    the heavy-armed, stood by as onlookers of the battle. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Light forces were also able to charge forward over the
                    rolling slopes of the ridge and engage the opposing light forces in flanking
                    attacks over terrain favourable and unfavourable. More had been wounded than
                    killed that day when the battle was broken off at nightfall. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the third day the Roman commander was at a
                    loss; for he could neither remain on the ridge without supplies nor retire
                    without disgrace and even danger, if the enemy pursued his retreat from the
                    higher ground. There remained indeed no alternative to amending a bold
                    undertaking by persistent boldness, which is occasionally wise in the long run.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In fact, the position was such that, had
                    the consul confronted an enemy like to the old-time kings of Macedonia, he <pb
                        n="p.103"/> might have suffered a great disaster. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This passage illustrates the strength of Livy's
                        dramatic sense, and his weakness as a military commentator; but he had
                        reason to point out the rashness of Marcius, who had once been badly
                        defeated by the Ligurians because he rushed into a narrow pass without
                        reconnaissance (XXXIX. xx. 5-10). </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But though <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> the king was scouring the
                    shore near Dium with cavalry, and at a distance of twelve miles could almost
                    hear the shouts and din of the fighting men, he neither added to his forces by
                    reinforcing his weary men with fresh troops, nor did he himself appear on the
                    battle-field —a matter of greatest moment —although the Roman commander, aged
                    over sixty and overburdened with flesh, performed vigorously in person all the
                    duties of a soldier. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Magnificently he pursued
                    his bold undertaking to the end; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> he left
                    Popilius to guard the ridge during his advance over pathless ground, sent ahead
                    men to clear out a road, and ordered Attalus and Misagenes, each with the
                    auxiliaries of his own nation, to act as guard for the men clearing the pass.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The consul himself sent the cavalry and
                    baggage ahead of him and brought up the rear with the legions. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The toil of the descent and the damage to
                    baggage-animals and their loads cannot be put into words. After they had
                    advanced a mere four miles, they would have given anything to return as they had
                    come, if they but could. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The confusion of an
                    attack by an enemy was caused by the elephants, which on arriving at the
                    pathless places cast off their mahouts and with horrible trumpetings caused a
                    great panic, especially among the horses, until a plan was devised for getting
                    them through. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the steep hillside the slope
                    was marked off, and at the lower end two long strong posts were set in the
                    ground, separated by a distance slightly greater than the width of one of the
                    beasts; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> on a cross-beam laid <pb n="p.105"/>
                    upon these posts, planks, each thirty feet long, were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> fastened together to form
                    a runway, and earth thrown on top of them. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> As with Hannibal's use of vinegar for breaking rock
                        (XXI. xxxvii. 2), this passage leaves several questions unanswered,
                        including the question of whether it ever happened. We can say that either
                        Livy or a copyist left out of the account of the runway a mention of the
                        stringers which would be necessary; the <quote>thirty-foot planks</quote>
                        somehow have replaced these stringers and the transverse planks which
                        presumably would provide the flooring. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next, at a slight interval below, a second
                    runway of the same sort was built, then a third, and others one after the other,
                    where the cliffs were sheer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> From firm ground
                    an elephant would advance on to the runway; before he could proceed to its end,
                    the posts were cut and the tilting of the runway forced the animal to slide
                    gently to the head of the next runway. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Some of
                    the elephants would slide standing erect, others would squat on their haunches.
                    Whenever they were met with the level expanse of another runway, they were again
                    carried down by a like collapse of the lower structure, until they arrived at
                    the more passable valley. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Romans advanced on that day hardly more
                    than seven miles. Very little of the journey did they accomplish on their feet.
                    Usually they advanced by casting themselves down, arms, baggage, and all, while
                    meeting with every kind of difficulty, so that even the leader who had chosen
                    the route could not deny that a small force could have destroyed the whole army.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> By nightfall they reached a scant level
                    area, nor did men who had unexpectedly at long last found a place which offered
                    sure footing, have the leisure to observe the unfriendly nature of the place,
                    hemmed in as it was on all sides. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For the
                    next day as well they were compelled to wait in the depths of this valley for
                    Popilius and the troops left behind <pb n="p.107"/> with him. These troops too,
                    though threatened from <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 169</note> no direction by the enemy, were harassed as by an enemy by
                    the ruggedness of the terrain. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> On the third
                    day, they proceeded with the united forces through the pass called Callipeuce
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The name (Fair Pines) suggests a
                        forested area.</note> by the natives. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On
                    the fourth day, they descended through country as pathless as before, but their
                    skill was greater through practice, and their morale was higher, since the enemy
                    had not showed himself anywhere and they were reaching the sea. On reaching the
                    plains between Heracleum and Libethrum they pitched a camp, most of which
                    occupied hills. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This was the infantry camp;
                    they embraced part of the plain too within the rampart, where the cavalry might
                    encamp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king was in his bath, they say, when the
                    presence of the enemy was announced. At this message he leapt in terror from his
                    tub and dashed out crying that he had been beaten without a battle. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> And thereafter, as his terror drove him to a
                    succession of fear-struck plans and orders, he sent out two of his friends, one
                    to Pella to cast into the sea the money stored in Phacus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The citadel of Pella, cf. below, x. 3; xlvi. 6;
                        Polybius XXIX. 3 and XXXI. 17 (25); Diodorus XXX. 11. It is not clear why
                        the treasure was thrown into the sea, and not simply dumped into the marshy
                        lake which washed the walls of Phacus, but the recovery of most of the
                        treasure by divers sounds as if it had been dumped on clean bottom. </note>
                    the other to Thessalonica to burn the dockyards. He recalled Asclepiodotus and
                    Hippias and their forces from outpost duty and opened every approach for attack.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The king ran off with all the gilded
                    statues at Dium, to prevent their falling into the hands of the enemy, and
                    compelled the inhabitants of that region to move to Pydna. Thereby <pb n="p.109"
                    /> what might have seemed the rashness of the consul <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> in advancing to a position
                    from which he could not retire without the consent of the enemy, was turned by
                    the king into well-calculated boldness. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For
                    the Romans had two passes by which they could extricate themselves: one through
                    Tempe into Thessaly, the other into Macedonia past Dium. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Both of the passes were being held by the king's forces;
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> therefore if the king, by fearlessly
                    holding his own, had resisted the first false appearance of approaching danger,
                    he would have left the Romans no retreat through Tempe to Thessaly, nor any
                    route for bringing up provisions from that direction. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy neglects the possibility of supply by sea, on
                        which the consul seems to have relied, see below, vii. 10; this is probably
                        due to the characteristic preoccupation of a Roman with the land, though one
                        must admit that the passage above cited shows that the fleet was badly
                        handled, and the coast presumably was difficult, cf. below, xlii. 5-6. </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For even without the opposition of an enemy
                    Tempe is a defile difficult of passage; for besides five miles of narrows
                    through which the road is cramped for a loaded animal, the cliffs on either side
                    are so sheer that one can hardly look down without some dizziness of eye and
                    brain. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> An additional source of fear is the
                    roar and depth of the Peneüs River flowing through the midst of the canyon. This
                    place, so unfriendly by its very nature, was blocked at four separate points by
                    the king's garrisons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> One was at the very
                    entrance near Gonnus, the second at Condylus, an impregnable fort, the third in
                    the vicinity of Lapathus, which they call the Palisade, the fourth set by the
                    road itself where the canyon, in the middle of its course, is at its narrowest.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> where it can easily be defended by no
                    more than ten soldiers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If the Romans' access
                    to <pb n="p.111"/> supplies through Tempe, as well as their line of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> retreat,
                    had been cut off, they would have had to return to the mountains through which
                    they had descended. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As they had deceived the
                    enemy in this by stealth, they could not duplicate the feat without concealment
                    and while the enemy were in possession of the higher summits; and the difficulty
                    they had undergone would have laid low all hope. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> There was no alternative left in this rash enterprise but
                    to get out into Macedonia past Dium in the teeth of the enemy, and this
                    undertaking, had not the gods deprived the king of his wits, would itself have
                    been of the utmost difficulty. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> For between
                    the foothills of Mount Olympus and the sea lies an interval of a little more
                    than a mile, half of which space is taken up with the broad estuary of the
                    Baphyrus River, while part of the plain is obstructed by either the temple of
                    Jupiter <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For this famous temple, cf.
                        Polybius IV. 62.</note> or the town. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The
                    very small remainder could have been barred off by a ditch of no extravagant
                    size and a palisade, and there was such an abundance of stone and of forest
                    timber at hand that even a wall could have been thrown up and towers erected.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Since none of these possibilities
                    revealed themselves to a mind blinded by sudden panic, the king stripped away
                    all his defences and opened every approach to assault <milestone n="17??"
                        unit="section"/> before taking refuge in Pydna. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul sighted much security as well as
                    hope in the folly and inaction of the king; he sent back a message to Spurius
                    Lucretius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> On this section, cf.
                        Polybius XXVIII. 0. 11 (9a. 12). Lucretius had been praetor in <date
                            when="-0172">172 B.C.</date> , cf. XLII. ix. 8. </note> at Larisa to
                    seize the forts abandoned by the enemy in the region of Tempe, and sending
                    Popilius to reconnoitre the crossings around Dium, arrived at that city in two
                    days' march, since he learned that everything lay open in all directions.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He ordered his camp to be <pb n="p.113"/>
                    pitched next to the temple itself, so that no sacrilege <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> against the sacred
                    precinct might be committed. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On personally
                    inspecting the city which, though not large, was adorned with public
                    installations and an abundance of statues <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Among these statues were the portraits by Lysippus of
                        the twenty-five Cavalry Companions killed at the battle of the Granicus, cf.
                        Arrian, <hi rend="italics">Anabasis</hi> I. 16. 4. </note> and was
                    magnificently fortified, the consul could hardly convince himself that no ruse
                    lurked in the unreasonable abandonment of such remarkable objects. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> After a day's delay for general reconnaissance all
                    around, he advanced, and being convinced that there would be abundant grain in
                    Pieria, he proceeded on that day to a river named Mitys. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Continuing on the following day, he accepted the surrender
                    of the city of Agassae by its inhabitants; and to win over the hearts of the
                    other Macedonians, he contented himself with hostages and promised to leave the
                    city to its people without garrison, and to accord them autonomy and freedom
                    from tribute. Advancing thence a day's journey, he encamped by the Ascordus
                    River. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Because he felt more strongly the want
                    of every sort of supplies the further he advanced from Thessaly, he retired to
                    Dium, thereby demonstrating beyond a doubt to everyone what he would have
                    suffered had he been cut off from Thessaly, since he found it unsafe to advance
                    far from there. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After Perseus had assembled all his forces and
                    officers, he blamed the commanders of his outposts, above all Asclepiodotus and
                    Hippias; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> they, he said, had surrendered the
                    keys to Macedonia to the Romans —a crime for which no one would have been more
                    justly prosecuted than himself. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After the sight of the Roman fleet at sea had
                    brought to the consul hope that the ships were bringing provisions —for
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> there was a great scarcity of grain and
                    almost a famine —he heard from the men just <pb n="p.115"/> come into port that
                    the freight ships had been left <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 169</note> in Magnesia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> As the consul was debating what should be done —so completely was his
                    struggle directed against the mere difficulty of the situation, without the
                    slightest effort on the part of the enemy to make matters worse —in <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> the nick of time a despatch arrived from Spurius
                    Lucretius that he was in possession of the forts above Tempe and around Phila,
                    and that he had found a supply of grain and other useful materials in them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Greatly pleased by this news, the consul moved
                    from Dium to Phila, both to strengthen its garrison and to distribute to the
                    soldiers the grain, transportation of which was slow. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This march started unpleasant rumours; for some put it that
                    he had retired from before the enemy out of fear, because he would have had to
                    fight a battle if he had remained in Pieria, while others said that <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> in his ignorance of the daily fluctuations in the
                    fortunes of war, and as if events were awaiting his signal, he had dropped from
                    his grasp advantages which presently could not be recovered. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> For at one move he had lost his grip on Dium and had
                    stirred up the enemy to perceiving at long last that he must recover what
                    previously he had shamefully lost. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For on
                    hearing of the departure of the consul, the king returned to Dium, rebuilt what
                    had been cast down and despoiled by the Romans, replaced the battlements knocked
                    off the walls, and strengthened the walls all around. Then he placed his camp
                    five miles from the city on the nearer bank of the Elpeüs River, intending to
                    use the river itself as a fortification since it was very hard to cross.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It flows from a ravine of Mount Olympus,
                    is scanty in summer, but again in <pb n="p.117"/> winter is swollen by rains; it
                    forms great rapids <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        169</note> above its boulders, and below, by carrying off the eroded earth
                    to the sea, produces great abysses and banks sheer on either side above a
                    deeply-hollowed channel. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thinking that the
                    enemy's advance was barred by this river, the king intended to use up the rest
                    of the summer. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the consul sent Popilius with two
                    thousand soldiers from Phila to Heracleum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    This is about five miles from Phila, on a cliff overhanging the river midway
                    between Dium and Tempe. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before Popilius brought his men against the
                    walls, he sent envoys to persuade the magistrates and chief citizens to prefer
                    making trial of the good faith and mildness of the Romans rather than of their
                    force. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This advice availed nothing, because
                    the fires of the king's camp at the Elpeüs were in sight. Then the siege began,
                    both with assaults and with field-works and engines, both from land and sea, for
                    the fleet, too, had arrived and occupied the shore side. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The younger Romans even captured the lowest
                    part of the wall by turning to military use a performance of the arena.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was the custom then, before there had
                    been introduced the present extravagance <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy notes the beginnings of lavishness in shows as
                        early as <date when="-0186">186 B.C.</date> , see XXXIX. xxii. 2, XLI.
                        xxvii. 6, and below, xviii. 8. </note> of cramming the arena with animals
                    from all over the earth, to hunt out various sorts of spectacles, for one race
                    with four-horse chariots and one with bareback riders hardly occupied the space
                    of an hour for the two events. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As one of these
                    performances, groups of about sixty <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Sixty was the usual number of soldiers in the so-called
                            <quote>century.</quote>
                    </note> youths (occasionally more at more <pb n="p.119"/> elaborate games)
                    entered under arms. Their entrance <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 169</note> was in some respects an imitation of military
                    manoeuvres, but in other respects was of a style more showy than the military
                    and more akin to the fashion of gladiatorial combats. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> After passing through various evolutions in this manoeuvre,
                    they would form in ranks, with shields close-set over their heads, the front
                    rank erect, the second somewhat stooped, the third and fourth more so, and the
                    rear rank down on their knees, so that they would form a <quote>tortoise</quote>
                    sloped like the roof of a house. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Next two
                    armed men, separated by an interval of some fifty feet, would rush out, feint at
                    each other, and mount from bottom to top of the <quote>tortoise</quote> over the
                    close-set shields. They would then act as if skirmishing at the outer edges of
                    the <quote>tortoise,</quote> now clash with each other in the centre, and leap
                    about just as if they were on solid ground. </p>
                <p> A <quote>tortoise</quote> like this was brought up to the lowest part of the
                    wall. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When soldiers on top came up to the
                    wall, they were at their highest elevation level with the defenders of the wall;
                    the defenders were routed and the soldiers of two maniples <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius (XXVIII. 11 (12)) says that a third maniple
                        formed the <quote>tortoise.</quote> Cf. Ammianus Marcellinus XXVI. 8. 9 for
                        a similar formation. </note> crossed into the city. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The only difference from the show was that the front rank
                    and those exposed on the flanks did not raise their shields over their heads,
                    but held them out in the usual position for battle in order not to expose their
                    bodies. In this way the missiles hurled from the wall did not injure the men as
                    they approached and those cast on the <quote>tortoise</quote>
                    <pb n="p.121"/> slid harmlessly like rain down to the bottom of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> slippery
                    slope. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On capturing Heracleum, the consul advanced
                    his camp there, as if he were going to advance to Dium and thence, after
                    dislodging the king, into Pieria as well. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But
                    as he was already making ready for wintering, he ordered the roads from Thessaly
                    to be repaired for the transport of provisions and suitable sites for granaries
                    to be chosen and houses built where those transporting the provisions could
                    lodge. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus at length recovered his courage from
                    the panic which had struck him down. and would have preferred that his commands
                    had not been obeyed when he ordered the treasure at Pella to be cast into the
                    sea and the dockyards at Thessalonica to be burned. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Andronicus, the envoy to Thessalonica, had killed time to
                    allow for the very thing which happened, a change of mind. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Andronicus is accused by Diodorus XXX. 11 of working in
                        this matter for a Roman victory. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nicias at Pella was less wary in casting away
                    part of <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> the money which was in Phacus, but
                    he seemed to have made his mistake in a manner not irreparable, since almost all
                    the money was brought up by divers. So great was the king's shame at this panic
                    of his that he ordered the divers secretly to be put to death, and after them
                    Andronicus and Nicias, too, so that there should be no one having knowledge of
                    so crazy an order. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, Gaius Marcius set out with the
                    fleet from Heracleum for Thessalonica, ravaged the countryside far and wide by
                    setting ashore forces at several points, and in several successful battles drove
                    back those who sallied from the city headlong within their walls. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> He was striking terror into the city itself, when <pb
                        n="p.123"/> from the engines of all types which were distributed <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> about,
                    stones shot by machine struck down not only the skirmishers about the walls who
                    rashly approached, but even the men in the ships. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Recalling the soldiers to the ships and abandoning the
                    siege of Thessalonica, they made thence for Aenea. This city is fifteen miles
                    away, set opposite Pydna in fertile land. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    After devastating its territory they followed the shore and arrived at
                    Antigonea. There they disembarked and for a time both ravaged the fields round
                    about and carried some booty off to their ships. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> Then the Macedonians, cavalry and infantry together, attacked the scattered
                    raiders and pursuing as they fled in disorder, killed about five hundred and
                    captured as many. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Nothing but utter
                    necessity, when they were kept from finding safety in their ships, aroused the
                    spirits of the Roman soldiers, both by despair of other means of safety and by
                    indignation. The fight was renewed on the shore; those aboard the ships came to
                    the rescue. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here about two hundred of the
                    Macedonians were slain and an equal number captured. From Antigonea the fleet
                    sailed to the peninsula of Pallene and landed troops to ravage it. This land
                    belonged to the territory of Cassandrea <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Established about <date when="-0300">300 B.C.</date> on
                        the site of Potidaea, which had been destroyed by Philip II in <date
                            when="-0356">356 B.C.</date>
                    </note> and was by far the most fertile of all the coast they had passed.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Here they were met by King Eumenes, who
                    had set out from Elaea <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The port of
                        Pergamum, east by south of Lesbos.</note> with twenty decked <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> According to Nissen, the use of this
                        word indicates that Livy is following Polybius here. </note> ships, as well
                    as by five decked ships sent by King Prusias. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> He was hedging on his neutrality of <date when="-0171"
                            >171 B.C.</date> , cf. XLII. xxix. 3. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> With this accession of strength, the praetor's
                    spirits rose to the point of attacking Cassandrea. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.125"/> This was founded by King Cassander precisely in the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> narrows
                    which connect the peninsula of Pallene with the rest of Macedonia and are
                    bounded on the one side by the Gulf of Macedonia, and on the other by that of
                    Torone. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For the peninsula on which this city
                    is situated rises high and projects into the sea quite as far as Mount Athos,
                    which is noted for its size; it forms, opposite to the district of Magnesia, two
                    unequal promontories, the larger named Posideum and the smaller Canastraeum.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy's description is confusing;
                        Posideum, the westward promontory, is no more than a spur on the side of the
                        main peninsula, of which Canastraeum forms the tip, extending to the
                        south-east; the slimness of this tip induced Livy or his source to call it
                        the smaller. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The siege was begun in separate divisions. The
                    Roman commander constructed works, including <hi rend="italics"
                        >chevaux-de-frise,</hi> extending from the Macedonian to the Toronaic gulf,
                    in the quarter called Clitae, in order to cut off the highway. On the other side
                    is a narrow strait <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Perhaps a moat open
                        at one end to the sea.</note> ; there Eumenes was attacking. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The Romans found that their greatest task was filling
                    the moat which Perseus had lately built as a defence. When the praetor inquired
                    why there were no mounds to be seen, where the earth dug from the moat would be,
                    he was shown certain arches. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These
                        arches were probably intended as sally-ports, cf. XXXVI. xxiii. 3; it is not
                        so clear what they had to do with the absence of soil from the moat-whether
                        the bricks had been made from the soil, or whether the latter had been taken
                        within the walls through the arches for disposal, before the brick curtains
                        were built. </note> These, he heard, were built up not to the same strength
                    as the old wall, but only to the thickness of a single brick. He therefore
                    adopted the plan of opening a path into the city by piercing the brickwork.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He further expected to effect surprise in
                    this move if he attacked the walls elsewhere with scaling ladders and, by
                    raising confusion, drew off the defenders of the city to the protection of this
                    second spot. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.127"/>
                <p> In the garrison of Cassandrea there were, besides <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> a respectable contingent
                    of young citizens, eight hundred Agrianes <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Cf. XLII. li. 5 and the note.</note> and two thousand
                    Illyrian Penestae <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These Illyrians
                        were mentioned in XLIII. xxiii. 7; Pleuratus, who sent them, is possibly the
                        exile mentioned in XLIII. xix. 13 as serving with Perseus. </note> sent from
                    their home by Pleuratus —both peoples being good fighters. They were defending
                    the walls as the Romans struggled with the utmost energy to mount them, when the
                    piercing of the brickwork of the arches in the twinkling of an eye, laid open
                    the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> If men had been there to dash in
                    armed, they would have taken the town at once. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    When the accomplishment of this breakthrough was reported to the Roman soldiers,
                    they at once eagerly raised a shout of joy, expecting to burst into the city at
                    several points. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The enemy were first struck with wonder as to
                    the meaning of this sudden uproar. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After the
                    commanders of the garrison, Pytho and Philip, had been informed that the city
                    lay open, they considered that the work had been done for the benefit of the
                    side first to press the attack, and made a sally with a strong force of Agrianes
                    and Illyrians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans, who were coming up
                    and being summoned from various points to advance into the city, were routed in
                    their scattered and unorganized state and chased to the moat, into which they
                    were driven and which they filled with the fallen. About six hundred were killed
                    there and almost to a man those caught between the wall and the moat were
                    wounded. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The praetor, being so grievously
                    dashed by his own undertaking, had become less eager to form other plans. Not
                    even Eumenes, who was attacking both by sea <pb n="p.129"/> and land, gained any
                    worth-while advantage. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Both <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> commanders
                    therefore determined to strengthen the forces on guard, so that no reinforcement
                    from Macedonia might be sent in, and since open assault was unsuccessful, to
                    attack the fortifications with siege-works. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    During the preparation of these works, ten Macedonian scout-ships, sent from
                    Thessalonica with picked Gallic auxiliaries, saw that the besieging ships were
                    anchored out to sea, and in the dead of night, in single column, hugging the
                    shore as closely as possible, entered the city. Report of this new defence force
                    compelled both the Romans and the king to abandon the siege. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They sailed around the cape and put in near Torone.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After attempting to besiege this city too,
                    and observing that it was defended by a strong force, they gave up their
                    undertaking, and made for Demetrias. On approaching it they saw the walls filled
                    with armed men, and sailed past to make a landing at Iolcus, planning to ravage
                    the fields and then attack Demetrias too. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile the consul, for his part, in order
                    not merely to remain sluggishly idle in hostile territory, sent Marcus Popilius
                    with five thousand soldiers to assail the city of Meliboea. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> This is situated in the foothills of Mount Ossa, on the
                    side sloping toward Thessaly, and conveniently threatening Demetrias. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The threat to Demetrias must have
                        consisted in cutting its line of communications, since Meliboea is
                        twenty-five miles away, air-line. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The first arrival of the enemy dismayed the
                    inhabitants of the place; then, after rallying their spirits from the unexpected
                    fright, they ran under arms to their posts at gates and wall, where the expected
                    lines of attack were, and at once dispelled the hope that the town could be
                    taken at the first rush. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Preparations for a
                    siege were therefore made and the construction of works for the assault was
                    begun. </p>
                <pb n="p.131"/>
                <p> When Perseus heard that Meliboea was being <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> attacked by the consul's
                    army at the same time that the fleet was anchored at Iolcus, in order to attack
                    Demetrias from there, he sent a certain Euphranor, one of his officers, with two
                    thousand picked soldiers to Meliboea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Euphranor's orders were that if he dislodged the Romans from Meliboea, he was to
                    enter Demetrias unobserved before the Romans brought their camp up to the city
                    from Iolcus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The besiegers of Meliboea, in
                    great panic when Euphranor suddenly made his appearance on higher ground,
                    abandoned their works and set them afire. So the siege of Meliboea was given up.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> After freeing one city from siege,
                    Euphranor at once advanced to Demetrias. He entered the walls by night and gave
                    the inhabitants such confidence that they felt sure of their ability not only to
                    defend their walls, but to protect their land from raids. Sallies were made
                    against the scattered ravagers, not without casualties to the enemy. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> However, the praetor and the king rode around the
                    walls, reconnoitring the situation of the city, in case they could attempt an
                    assault by works or by main force at any point. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> There was a rumour that Cydas the Cretan <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A substantial account of this and other intrigues is
                        given by Polybius XXIX. 6 (lc). </note> and Antimachus, the commander in
                    Demetrias, were agents in discussing terms of friendship between Eumenes and
                    Perseus. At any rate, the Romans departed from Demetrias. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Eumenes sailed to the consul, and after offering
                    congratulations on his successful entrance into Macedonia, left for Pergamum in
                    his own kingdom. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The praetor Marcius Figulus
                    sent part of his fleet into winter quarters at Sciathus, and made for Oreüs in
                        <pb n="p.133"/> Euboea with the rest of his ships, thinking that this <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> city was
                    most suitable for the forwarding of supplies to the armies in Macedonia and
                    Thessaly. </p>
                <p> The historians give highly different accounts of King Eumenes. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> If you trust Valerius Antias, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> As Livy knew, trusting Valerius Antias was a hazardous
                        proceeding. Polybius XXIX. 5 (lb) is less certain about Eumenes' attitude;
                        Valerius perhaps reported the view prevailing in Rome at the time. </note>
                    his account is that although the praetor summoned the king with frequent
                    despatches, he did not even receive naval assistance from him, nor did Eumenes
                    on his way to Asia part on good terms with the consul, being indignant because
                    he was not permitted to encamp in the Roman area; <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Eumenes, says Valerius, could not even be persuaded to
                    leave behind the Galatian cavalry he had brought with him. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> His brother Attalus, continues Valerius, not only remained
                    with the consul, but displayed genuine and unwavering good faith and notable
                    exploits in this campaign. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the war was continuing in Macedonia,
                    envoys from across the Alps from a Gallic chieftain —his name is given as
                    Balanos, but there is no record of his tribe —came to Rome promising aid for the
                    Macedonian campaign. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thanks were expressed by
                    the senate and gifts sent the envoys, a twisted necklace of two pounds of gold
                    and golden bowls of four pounds, a horse with ornamental trappings, and cavalry
                    weapons. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After the Gauls, Pamphylian <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> They had apparently been recognized as
                        free <quote>friends</quote> of Rome after a dispute as to their status under
                        the treaty with Antiochus, XXXVIII. xxxix. 17, and xv. 6. </note> envoys
                    presented in the senate-house a gold crown made of twenty thousand philips <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These coins were worth about twenty
                        silver drachmas, cf. XXXVII. lix. 4 and the note. The gift seems to have
                        been unusually large; the Rhodians gave the same when desperately trying to
                        regain Roman favour, see XLV. xxv. 7; the figure here may be wrong. The
                        philip, by weight a stater or double drachma of the Athenian standard (= 8.6
                        g.; the theoretical U.S. gold dollar of 1934 = 15r[grains troy = 0.988 g.),
                        was popularized by Philip II after the fall of Olynthus in <date
                            when="-0348">348 B.C.</date> He seems to have taken the coin from the
                        Olynthians; it paralleled an earlier issue from Philippi, which began as a
                        colony of Thasos three years before its capture by Philip, and which had an
                        Athenian adviser. Philip continued the coinage of this town. During the
                        second century, the philip was the commonest gold coin of Rome (see XXXIV.
                        lii. 7; XXXVII. lix. 4; XXXIX. v. 15 and vii. 1, and frequent allusions of
                        Plautus' <hi rend="italics">Bacchides, Poenulus,</hi> and <hi rend="italics"
                            >Trinummus</hi> ); as a result of Roman trade, philips also made their
                        appearance in central Gaul, and were locally imitated there, in the
                        Rhine-land, and even in Britain. (See Seltman, <hi rend="italics">Greek
                            Coins,</hi> pp. 200-202, and <hi rend="italics">R.E.</hi> 2196-2198.)
                    </note> and their request was <pb n="p.135"/> granted that they be permitted to
                    deposit this <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        169</note> present in the temple of Jupiter, Greatest and Best, and to offer
                    sacrifice on the Capitol; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> a gracious answer
                    was given to the envoys' request for a renewal of the state of friendship, and a
                    gift of two thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> apiece was sent them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Next, an audience was given to envoys from
                    King Prusias, and shortly thereafter to those from the Rhodians, who made a very
                    different presentation of the same request. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Both embassies treated of making terms again with King Perseus. Prusias'
                    attitude was more that of entreaty than demand, for he declared that up to this
                    time he had taken the part of the Romans, and would so continue as long as the
                    war lasted; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> however, inasmuch as envoys from
                    Perseus had come to him to discuss ending the war with the Romans, he had
                    promised to plead Perseus' cause before the senate; he requested that if they
                    could bring themselves to do so, they would put an end to their wrath, and would
                    accord him, too, their thanks for the restoration of peace. So spoke the king's
                    envoys. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Rhodians haughtily reviewed their
                    services to the Roman people, and claimed for themselves almost the greater part
                    of the victories, especially over King Antiochus; they then added that while
                    peace had existed between the Macedonians and Romans, they had entered upon
                    friendship with King Perseus; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> this they had
                    broken off against their will and on account of no fault of his toward them, but
                    because it had seemed good to the Romans to draw them into participation in the
                    war. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.137"/> For the third year, they said, they were feeling many <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    inconveniences from this war because of the interruption of commerce; their
                    island was poor, and could not be inhabited without the assistance of sea-borne
                    supplies. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Since therefore they could no
                    longer endure this privation, they had sent other envoys to Perseus in
                    Macedonia, to inform him that it was the Rhodians' wish that he should arrange a
                    peace with the Romans, and that they had sent a similar announcement to Rome.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If either party was responsible for
                    preventing the ending of the war, the Rhodians would deliberate as to what
                    action they ought to take against this party. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I feel sure that even now these statements
                    cannot be read or heard without indignation; from this one can judge what the
                    senate's state of mind was as they listened. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For the services of the Rhodians, cf. XLII. xlvi. 6.
                        According to Polybius XXVIII. 16, relations between Rome and Rhodes were
                        entirely cordial this year; in <date when="-0168">168 B.C.</date> the consul
                        Marcius suggested to an embassy of the Rhodians that they act as mediators;
                        the only result was to encourage the pro-Macedonians in Rhodes (cf. below,
                        xxxv. 4, where Livy still saddles the Rhodians with the onus in this matter;
                        also XLV. iii. 3, with which cf. Polybius XXIX. 10). Polybius suspects
                        Marcius of planning to have the Rhodians annoy the Romans and so justify
                        Rome's overriding their independence; in view of Marcius' liking for
                        intrigue (XLII. xlvii. 1-4), this is quite probable. In XLV. xxii. 2, Livy
                        suggests that Roman suspicion of Rhodes was something new in <date
                            when="-0167">167 B.C.</date> ; in XLV. xxv. 6, the
                            <quote>freeing</quote> of Lycia and Caria seems to have been ordered in
                        that year. Claudius (see below) or some other annalist seems to have misled
                        Livy by anticipating developments. Cassius Dio XX. fr. 66, 2 = Zonaras 9. 22
                        says that Perseus would have been granted peace but for the tactlessness of
                        the Rhodians. Livy certainly had no suspicion that the Romans might have
                        continued to tolerate Perseus. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Claudius has it that the senate returned no
                    answer, but only had read its decree that the Roman people gave the Carians and
                    Lycians their freedom <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Previous
                        friction between these peoples and the Rhodians was noted in XLI. vi. 8-12,
                        cf. the note, and XLII. xiv. 8. Polybius XXX. 5. 12 records a decree
                            <quote>freeing</quote> the Carians and Lycians in the year 168- <date
                            when="-0007">7 B.C.</date> , probably the time when it was actually
                        passed. </note> and that despatches should be immediately sent to both
                    peoples, on hearing which the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> chief of the
                        <pb n="p.139"/> Rhodian embassy, for whose proud language the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    senate-house had but a moment before seemed too small, now suffered deflation.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Other historians record the following
                    answer: </p>
                <p>
                    <quote> At the outset of this war the Roman people were informed by no trifling
                        sources that the Rhodians had entered upon secret plots with King Perseus
                        against the Roman state, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf.
                            XLII. xxvi. 8 for earlier Roman suspicions, which to a large extent
                            resulted from the Rhodians' non-partisanship, based on a preference for
                            a balance of power, cf. XLII. xxx. 5-6. </note> but even had this been
                        doubtful before, the words of the embassy just uttered have made the matter
                        certain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Frequently treachery unmasks
                        itself, even if it is more wary at first. And now the Rhodians pass judgment
                        throughout the world as to peace and war! <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        At the beck and call of the Rhodians will the Romans take up and lay down
                        their arms! Now we are no longer to call upon the gods to witness treaties,
                        but rather the Rhodians! <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Unless obedience
                        is rendered them, and our armies are removed from Macedonia, the Rhodians
                        will see, will they, what they must do? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        What the Rhodians will see, they themselves know. But surely the Roman
                        people, after their conquest of Perseus, which they hope will take place any
                        day, will see that they repay a suitable reward for the actions of each
                        state during the war. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Nevertheless, a present of two thousand
                    sesterces apiece was sent to the envoys, which they refused. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereafter despatches from Quintus Marcius the
                    consul were read, describing his crossing over into Macedonia, by forcing the
                    pass; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> in Macedonia he had procured supplies in
                    advance of winter from <pb n="p.141"/> various localities, and in particular had
                    received <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    twenty thousand bushels of wheat and ten thousand of barley from the Epirotes,
                    so that payment for this grain should be arranged with their envoys at Rome.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Clothes, said the consul, should be sent
                    to the army from Rome; there was need for about two hundred horses, especially
                    Numidians, and he had no supply of them where he was. A decree of the senate was
                    passed to carry out these requests of the consul. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Gaius Sulpicius the praetor <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> He was the city praetor, cf. XLIII. xv. 3. Under
                        Sulpicius' sponsorship as praetor, Ennius produced his <hi rend="italics"
                            >Thyestes</hi> (Cicero, <hi rend="italics">Brutus</hi> 78), and in his
                        consulship, Terence produced his <hi rend="italics">Andria;</hi> for
                        Sulpicius' prediction of an eclipse, see below, xxxvii. 5. </note> let a
                    contract for transporting to Macedonia six thousand togas, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> For this use of a civilian garment by soldiers, cf.
                        XXII. liv. 2 and the note. </note> thirty thousand tunics, and two hundred
                    horses, and for depositing them where the consul chose. Sulpicius also paid the
                    envoys of the Epirotes the price of the grain, and brought before the senate
                    Onesimus, son of Pytho, a Macedonian noble. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He
                    had always been a proponent of peace to the king, and had advised him to adopt
                    frequently, if not regularly, the practice which his father Philip had begun and
                    continued to the last day of his life —namely, that of reading through twice
                    daily the treaty he had made with the Romans. After Onesimus had been unable to
                    discourage the king from war, Onesimus began at first to withdraw on one excuse
                    or another, so as not to be associated with projects of which he disapproved.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Finally, when he saw that he was an object
                    of suspicion and that occasionally he was being charged by innuendo with
                    treachery, he deserted to the Romans and made himself very useful to the consul.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On being introduced to the senate, he
                    recited these facts, and the senate ordered that he be enrolled in the category
                    of allies, that a residence and entertainment <pb n="p.143"/> be provided for
                    him, that two hundred acres of the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 169</note> public land of the Roman people in the
                    district of Tarentum be given him, and that a house be bought for him at
                    Tarentum. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For similar rewards, cf.
                        II. xvi. 4-5; XXIII. xlvi. 6-7; XXVI. xxi. 9-13. </note> Gaius Decimius the
                    praetor <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">He was praetor in charge of
                        aliens, XLIII. xv. 3.</note> was entrusted with the execution of these
                    orders. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The censors conducted the census on the
                    thirteenth of December more strictly than before. Many were deprived of their
                    rank of knights, among them Publius Rutilius who as tribune of the commons had
                    violently assailed the censors; he was also removed from his tribe and
                    disenfranchised. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Severity to knights
                        was previously mentioned, XLIII. xvi. 1; either the process was interrupted
                        by the objections there described, or the censors conducted a new review at
                        this later date. Rutilius was now open to their attack, because he had left
                        the tribunate four days before on December 9. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As half the revenues of the year had by decree
                    of the senate been assigned by the quaestors to the censors for the construction
                    of public works, Titus Sempronius, out of the funds assigned to him, bought for
                    the <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> state the house of Publius Africanus
                    behind the Old Shops in the direction of the statue of Vortumnus, as well as the
                    butcher's stalls and the shops adjacent, and saw to the construction of the
                    basilica which afterward received the name of Sempronian. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Africanus was the father-in-law of the censor. The Old
                        Shops had been built in <date when="-0209">209 B.C.</date> , cf. XXVII. xi.
                        16, and were so called to distinguish them from some built in <date
                            when="-0194">194 B.C.</date> The bronze statue of the Etruscan god
                        Vortumnus stood in the <hi rend="italics">Vicus Tuscus</hi> some distance
                        south-west of the Forum, but visible from it; the statue is mentioned by
                        Cicero, <hi rend="italics">in Verrem</hi> II. I. 59, 154, and Propertius V.
                        (IV.) 2. The god, whose name seems to be good Latin, was in charge of
                        turning or exchange, and received a temple in Rome after the overthrow of
                        his home town of Volsinii in <date when="-0264">264 B.C.</date> The Basilica
                        Sempronia was later supplanted by the Basilica Julia. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The year was drawing to its close, and because
                    of concern, especially for the war with Macedonia, men were discussing what
                    consuls they should elect for this year, to bring this war at last to an end.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> A resolution of the senate was therefore
                    passed, that Gnaeus Servilius should come as promptly <pb n="p.145"/> as
                    possible to hold the elections. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The praetor
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    Sulpicius forwarded the resolution to the consul, and read to the senate a few
                    days later the return despatch from that officer. In this, he set the day for
                    the elections as . . ., and announced his return to the city previous to that
                    time. The consul made haste, and the elections were completed on the day set.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There were elected as consuls Lucius
                    Aemilius Paulus for the second time, in the fourteenth year after his first
                    term, and Gaius Licinius Crassus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On the
                    following day, there were elected to the praetorship Gnaeus Baebius Tamphilus,
                    Lucius Anicius Gallus, Gnaeus Octavius, Publius Fonteius Balbus, Marcus Aebutius
                    Helva, and Gaius Papirius Carbo. Concern for the war with Macedonia induced the
                    speeding up of the whole procedure. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Therefore
                    it was voted that these magistrates-elect should be allotted their fields of
                    operation immediately, so that when it was <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    known which consul had received Macedonia and which praetor the fleet, the
                    designated men might begin their plans and preparations of the supplies
                    necessary for war and might consult the senate if there was need for
                    consultation on any subject. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It was determined
                    to hold the Latin Festival as soon as was possible on religious grounds after
                    the entrance upon office of the magistrates, to avoid any delay to the consul
                    who was to set out for Macedonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In these
                    decrees, the fields of operation for the consuls were designated as Macedonia
                    and Italy; those for the praetors were, besides the two jurisdictions in the
                    city, the fleet, Spain, Sicily, and Sardinia. <pb n="p.147"/> Macedonia fell to
                    the lot of the consul Aemilius, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It
                        was later assumed, cf. <hi rend="italics">C.I.L.</hi> I.2 1, p. 194, <hi
                            rend="italics">elogium</hi> XV. and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics"
                            >Aemilius</hi> x that Paulus was <hi rend="italics">elected</hi> as
                        general for Macedonia; this cannot be taken literally, as it would have been
                        the senate which assigned him to a province; unless a judicious falsifying
                        of the allotment process took place, the appointment of Paulus was a bit of
                        the <hi rend="italics">felicitas</hi> of the Roman people. Crassus had a
                        respectable record as a soldier, cf. XLII. lviii. 12. </note> Italy to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note> Licinius.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Of the praetors, Gnaeus Baebius received
                    the jurisdiction over citizens, Lucius Anicius was given that over aliens and
                    was placed at the disposal of the senate, Gnaeus Octavius received the fleet,
                    Publius Fonteius Spain, Marcus Aebutius Sicily, and Gaius Papirius Sardinia. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was at once obvious to everyone that Lucius
                    Aemilius was going to prosecute this war in no sluggish fashion, not only
                    because he was a warlike man, but also because without relaxing by day or night
                    he turned over in his mind nothing but what concerned this war. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> First of all he requested the senate to send envoys to
                    Macedonia to inspect the armies and the fleet and to report their findings as to
                    what was needed by way of forces on land or sea; <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> moreover, they were to collect information as far as possible about the
                    king's forces and about the terrain under our control and under that of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They were to investigate the following:
                    whether the Romans were encamped among the mountains or whether all the narrows
                    had been passed and the plains reached; which of the allies were loyal to us,
                    which were wavering and of a loyalty dependent on fortune, and which seemed
                    definitely hostile; how large a supply of provisions had been prepared and
                    whence they could be brought, by a land route or by ships, respectively; what
                    had been achieved on land and sea during this summer. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> From good information on these points sure decisions might
                    be made for the <pb n="p.149"/> future, said Aemilius. The senate gave the
                    consul <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 169</note>
                    Gnaeus Servilius the task of choosing three men satisfactory to Lucius Aemilius
                    as envoys to Macedonia. Two days later the envoys set out —Gnaeus Domitius
                    Ahenobarbus, Aulus Licinius Nerva, and Lucius Baebius. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Report was made of two showers of stones near
                    the end of this year, one on Roman land, one on that of Veii. On both occasions
                    a nine-day rite was performed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The priests who
                    died during this year were Publius Quinctilius Varus, the <hi rend="italics"
                        >flamen</hi> of Mars, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He was
                        replaced in the following year by Lucius Postumius Albinus, XLV. xv. 10.
                    </note> and Marcus Claudius Marcellus of the Board of Ten. Gnaeus Octavius
                    replaced the latter. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Display being now on the
                    increase, it is recorded that at the games in the arena by the curule aediles
                    Publius Cornelius Scipio Nasica and Publius Lentulus, sixty-three leopards and
                    forty bears and elephants participated. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the consulship of Lucius Aemilius Paulus
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> and
                    Gaius Licinius, on the fifteenth of March, at the beginning of the new year, the
                    senators were on the <hi rend="italics">qui vive,</hi> especially as to what the
                    consul in charge of Macedonia would bring before them about his field of
                    operations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But Paulus said that he had
                    nothing to present until the envoys returned, but that the envoys were now at
                    Brundisium, after having been blown back twice to Dyrrachium on their voyage.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As soon as he acquired the information
                    which was the first necessity, he would lay matters before the senate, and this
                    would take place within a very few days. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In
                    order to avoid any delay to his <pb n="p.151"/> settingout, said Paulus, the day
                    for the Latin Festival had <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> been set at April twelfth <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The date is given below, xxii. 16, as
                        March 31; in either case, it was very early as compared with dates cited
                        elsewhere, <hi rend="italics">e.g.,</hi> XLI. xvi. 1 (May 5), XLII. xxxv. 3
                        (June 1). Actually, due to the confusion of the calendar, the festival was
                        held in late January this year, cf. below, xxxvii. 8. </note> ; after the
                    proper performance of the sacrifice, if the senate concurred, he and Gnaeus
                    Octavius would both set out. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> His colleague
                    Gaius Licinius would take care, in his absence, to get ready and send out what
                    should be made ready and sent to the war; meanwhile, said Paulus, the embassies
                    of foreign nations might be given audience. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> First the envoys from King Ptolemy and Queen
                    Cleopatra at Alexandria were announced. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Grimy,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">As part of their costume as
                        suppliants.</note> with untrimmed beard and hair, they entered the
                    senate-house bearing olive-branches, and prostrated themselves; their speech was
                    more pitiable than their array. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Antiochus, the
                    king of Syria, who had been a hostage at Rome, under the decent pretext of
                    restoring the elder Ptolemy to his throne, was waging war against the younger
                    brother, who was then in possession of Alexandria. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On Antiochus' sojourn at Rome, cf. XLI. xx; a previous
                        stage in Antiochus' encroachment on Egypt was mentioned in XLII. xxix. 5,
                        cf. Polybius XXVII. 19, also XXVIII. 18 f. (16 f.) The <quote>elder
                            Ptolemy</quote> is Ptolemy VI Philometor; the <quote>younger,</quote>
                        Euergetes II. </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Antiochus had won a naval battle at Pelusium
                    and, after leading his forces across the Nile on a hastily-constructed bridge,
                    was overawing Alexandria with his siege and seemed to be on the very point of
                    laying his hands on a very rich kingdom. Complaining of this attack, the envoys
                    begged the senate to come to the rescue of a kingdom and a royal pair who were
                    friends of Roman rule. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Such, they argued,
                    were the benefits conferred on Antiochus by the <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> Roman people, and such their influence with all kings and
                    nations that, if they sent <pb n="p.153"/> envoys to declare to Antiochus that
                    the senate did not <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> wish war to be made on kings allied to it, Antiochus would at
                    once depart from the walls of Alexandria and would lead his army back into
                    Syria. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If they hesitated to do this, shortly
                    Ptolemy and Cleopatra, robbed of their kingdom, would arrive in Rome, somewhat
                    to the shame of the Roman people, because they had offered no aid in the final
                    crisis of their fortunes. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The senators,
                    stirred by the entreaties of the Alexandrines, at once <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Polybius XXIX. 2 (1) stresses the Roman interest in
                        keeping Antiochus out of Egypt; he does not indicate that the Roman embassy
                        accompanied the Egyptians, and puts more emphasis than does Livy on Roman
                        initiative. </note> sent Gaius Popilius Laenas, Gaius Decimius, and Gaius
                    Hostilius as envoys to bring an end to the war between the kings. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> They were instructed to approach first Antiochus and
                    then Ptolemy, and to proclaim that if war was not concluded, the party
                    constituting the obstacle would not be considered either a friend or an ally to
                    the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This embassy left within three days along with
                    the envoys from Alexandria. The mission from Macedonia arrived on the last day
                    of the Quinquatrus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This festival,
                        first mentioned for the year <date when="-0207">207 B.C.</date> , occurred
                        on March 19-23, see XXVI. xxvii. 1 and the note, also Ovid, <hi
                            rend="italics">Fasti</hi> III. 810; <hi rend="italics">C.I.L.</hi> I.2
                        1, p. 312 gives a discussion of the origin of the name (probably because it
                        originally fell on the <quote>fifth</quote> day, Roman inclusive reckoning,
                        after the Ides), and points out that besides being connected with Minerva,
                        the day had associations with Mars, and seems to have been the time for
                        ceremonial readying of weapons for the campaigning season. </note> amid such
                    eagerness that, had it not been evening, the consuls would have summoned the
                    senate at once. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Next day the session was held
                    and the envoys were heard. They reported as follows: <quote> The army has been
                        led into Macedonia by trackless passes at a risk disproportionate to the
                        gain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Pieria, which the army has reached,
                        is in the hands of the king; the encampments are so nearly in contact that
                        hardly more than the Elpeüs River separates them. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The king does not offer battle, and our forces have <pb
                            n="p.155"/> not the strength to compel him to do so. Also the <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> winter
                        is an added obstacle to an active campaign. The soldiers are being supported
                        in idleness and have grain for no more than six days. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The Macedonian forces are said to number thirty
                        thousand. If Appius Claudius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy
                            has not mentioned him since XLIII. xxiii. 6; Polybius XXVIII. 13 (11)
                            tells how Appius in the meantime had tried to raise Achaean troops, but
                            had been hindered by Marcius. </note> had sufficient strength in the
                        region of Lychnidus, he could have distracted the king with a second front;
                        as it is, Appius and the force with him are in the greatest danger unless
                        either a full-fledged army is quickly sent him or his present force is
                        extricated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As to the fleet, we heard
                        after we left the camp that some of the sailors have been lost by disease,
                        and some, especially the Sicilians, have gone home, so that the ships lack
                        crews. Those who are there have not received their pay and are
                        insufficiently clothed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Eumenes and his
                        fleet have come and gone for no good reason, as if his ships were drifting
                        before the wind; and there is no good evidence that the spirit of this king
                        is unwavering. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The immediate facts reported by Livy,
                        above, x. 12-xiii. 10, and xxviii, do not bear this out; but Eumenes was not
                        above bargaining with Perseus, below, xxiv-xxv (based on Polybius), and some
                        of Livy's sources may have projected back later Roman suspicions, cf. above,
                        xiii. 9. 12-13. Livy usually falls into the attitude, natural enough for his
                        own day, that no one had any business to act contrary to Roman interests;
                        but in the second century, Rome was not the paramount power in the
                        Macedonian-Greek world, and it was not even clear that she proposed at this
                        time to take a permanent interest in the affairs of that region. </note> The
                    envoys reported that Attalus was as gallantly unswerving as Eumenes was entirely
                    undependable. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After hearing the envoys, Lucius Aemilius laid
                    before the senate the question of the conduct of the war. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The senate decreed that the consuls and the people should
                    each choose half of the tribunes for <pb n="p.157"/> eight legions; however, it
                    was voted that no one who <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> had not held office should be chosen that
                    year. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These provisions for officering
                        the legions provided for reasonably competent officers, while still avoiding
                        the suspicion of favouritism among an office-holding clique which may have
                        caused the use of popular election of tribunes the previous year XLIII. xii.
                        7. Of the eight legions, two were probably for Gaul (i.e., north Italy), and
                        two were to be Home Guard ( <hi rend="italics">urbanae</hi> ); officers less
                        competent or less congenial to the consuls could be shunted to these
                        legions. The dangers of <quote>inbreeding</quote> in office-holding at Rome
                        are especially well illustrated by the Jugurthine War; the counter-dangers
                        of politically able commoners elevated to military posts are shown by the
                        careers of Flaminius and Varro in the Second Punic War. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then from among the tribunes Lucius Aemilius
                    was to choose whomever he preferred for the two legions for Macedonia. It was
                    further voted that after the completion of the Latin Festival, the consul Lucius
                    Aemilius and Gnaeus Octavius, the praetor to whom the fleet had been allotted,
                    should depart for their field of operations. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    To them was added the praetor Lucius Anicius, whose post was the court for
                    aliens; it was voted that he should succeed Appius Claudius in the Illyrian
                    theatre near Lychnidus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Charge over the levy
                    was given to the consul Gaius Licinius. He was instructed to enroll seven
                    thousand Roman citizens and two hundred horsemen and to demand of the allies of
                    the Latin Name seven thousand infantry and four hundred cavalry, and <milestone
                        n="6??" unit="section"/> he was to send a despatch to <milestone n="7??"
                        unit="section"/> Gnaeus Servilius the commander in the province of Gaul,
                    instructing him to enroll six hundred cavalry. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    This force Licinius was ordered to send as promptly as possible to his colleague
                    in Macedonia; a limit of two legions was placed on the army on that front, and
                    each legion was to be reinforced till it contained six thousand infantry and
                    three hundred cavalry; the surplus infantry and cavalry were to be distributed
                    as garrisons. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Men unfit for military service
                    were to be discharged. An added levy was imposed on the allies of ten thousand
                    infantry and eight hundred cavalry. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This
                    force was given to Anicius besides the <pb n="p.159"/> two legions which he was
                    ordered to transport to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> Macedonia, each legion having five thousand two hundred
                    infantry and three hundred cavalry. Moreover, five thousand sailors were
                    enrolled for the fleet. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Licinius the consul
                    was ordered to hold his area with two legions, and to add to them ten thousand
                    infantry and six hundred cavalry of the allies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the senate had finished its voting, the
                    consul Lucius Aemilius went from the senate-house to a public meeting and made
                    the following speech: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> I seem to have noticed, fellow-citizens, that greater congratulations
                        were offered me when I was allotted Macedonia as my field of operations than
                        when my election as consul was announced, or on the day when I entered upon
                        office. The reason for this was none other, I believe, than that you regard
                        me as capable of bringing the long-drawn-out war in Macedonia to an end
                        worthy of the high position of the Roman people. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The gods too, I hope, approve this fall of the lot and
                        will likewise be at my side in action. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> So
                        far I can partly prophesy, and partly hope; another matter I dare to assert
                        as sure namely, that I will strive with every effort that the hope you have
                        conceived for me shall not be vain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> What
                        is required for the war has been voted by the senate, and since it is
                        determined that I shall set out at once, for which I am not reluctant, the
                        preparations will be made by that excellent man, my colleague Gaius
                        Licinius, as vigorously as if he were going to conduct the campaign.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For your part, see to it that you have
                        confidence only in the reports I make to the senate and to you, and beware
                        of nourishing by your credulity the gossip for which no sponsor will appear.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For I have noticed that, as is
                        commonly the case, so <pb n="p.161"/> now especially in this war no one is
                        so scornful of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                            168</note> rumour that his spirit cannot be weakened. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In all the clubs and even —God save us! —at
                        dinner-tables there are experts who lead armies to Macedonia, who know where
                        camp should be pitched, what places should be held with garrisons, when or
                        by what pass Macedonia should be invaded, where granaries should be set up,
                        by what routes on land or sea provisions should be supplied, when we must
                        join battle with the enemy and when it is better to remain inactive.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Not only do they decide what should be
                        done, but when anything is done contrary to their opinion, they accuse the
                        consul as if he were in the dock. Such behaviour is a great obstacle to the
                        men in the field. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> For not everyone is as
                        unwavering and as steadfast of spirit against hostile gossip as was Quintus
                        Fabius, who preferred to have his independence of command lessened by
                        popular folly rather than to neglect the best interests of the state for the
                        sake of acclaim. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I am not,
                        fellow-citizens, one who believes that no advice may be given to leaders;
                        nay rather I judge him to be not a sage, but haughty, who conducts
                        everything according to his own opinion alone. What therefore is my
                        conclusion? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Generals should receive
                        advice, in the first place from the experts who are both specially skilled
                        in military matters and have learned from experience; secondly, from those
                        who are on the scene of action, who see the terrain, the enemy, the fitness
                        of the occasion, who are sharers in the danger, as it were aboard the same
                        vessel. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Thus, if there is anyone who is
                        confident that he can advise me as to the best advantage of the state in
                        this campaign which I am about to conduct, let him not refuse his services
                        to <pb n="p.163"/> the state, but come with me into Macedonia. I will <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                        furnish him with his sea-passage, with a horse, a tent, and even
                        travel-funds. If anyone is reluctant to do this and prefers the leisure of
                        the city to the hardships of campaigning, let him not steer the ship from on
                        shore. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The city itself provides enough
                        subjects for conversation; let him confine his garrulity to these; and let
                        him be aware that I shall be satisfied with the advice originating in camp. </quote>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius XXIX. 1 (la) also mentions
                        Paulus' attack on the armchair generals, which President Roosevelt used
                        effectively <hi rend="italics">(New York Times,</hi> Mar. 18, 1942, p. 10).
                        In sec. 2, cf. the note on the text, it is possible that there was a
                        reference to Paulus' reluctance to assume the consulship in this year, a
                        reluctance to which Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> x f., refers
                        both as a fact and as an item in Paulus' speech. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> After this address and the due completion of
                    the sacrifice at the Latin Festival, <milestone n="16??" unit="section"/> which
                    was held on March 31 <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The date had
                        been set for two weeks later, according to xix. 4 above; it seems unlikely
                        that the date, once announced, could have been advanced, and there is
                        probably a confusion in the text between Ides and Kalends either here or
                        above. </note> on the Alban Mount, both the consul and the praetor Gnaeus
                    Octavius immediately set out for Macedonia. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    History records that the consul was escorted by an unusually great throng of
                    persons paying their respects to him, and that men prophesied with almost sure
                    expectation that the Macedonian war would come to an end, and that the return of
                    the consul would be prompt and in great triumph. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were occurring in Italy,
                    Perseus decided that since he had discovered that the Romans had entered the
                    pass and that the final crisis of the war impended, he must no longer postpone
                    the project which he could not bring himself to complete because expenditure of
                    money was required-namely, gaining the adherence of Gentius, king of Illyria.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Inasmuch as Perseus had agreed through his
                    envoy Hippias <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not named by Livy in
                        his description of an earlier stage of the negotiations in XLIII. xx. In the
                        present passage, Livy is following Polybius XXIX. 3-4. </note> on a payment
                    of three <pb n="p.165"/> hundred talents of silver, on condition of an exchange
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> of
                    hostages, he sent Pantauchus, one of his most trusty friends, to complete the
                    agreement. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At Meteon in the region of
                    Labeatis, Pantauchus met the Illyrian king; there he received the king's oath
                    and his hostages. Gentius too sent an envoy named Olympio to require the oath
                    and the hostages of Perseus.' <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Others were sent
                    with him to receive the money; and, at Pantauchus' suggestion, Parmenio and
                    Morcus were named as envoys to go with the Macedonians to Rhodes. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> To them instructions were given to set out for Rhodes
                    only after the oath, the hostages, and the money had been received; it was
                    thought that by the prestige of two kings at once the Rhodians could be induced
                    to war with the Romans, and that once the kings were joined by the state to
                    which <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> belonged a unique reputation for
                    sea-power, no hope on land or sea would be left the Romans. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the arrival of the Illyrians, Perseus left
                    his camp at the Elpeüs River with all his cavalry and met them at Dium.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There the terms agreed upon were executed
                    in the presence of the surrounding column of cavalry, whom the king wished to be
                    present at the ratification of the alliance with Gentius, thinking that it would
                    somewhat raise their spirits. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The hostages
                    were also given and received in the sight of all, those who were to receive the
                    money were sent to the royal treasury at Pella and those who were to accompany
                    the Illyrian envoys to Rhodes were ordered to take ship at Thessalonica.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Metrodorus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">A Rhodian, agent of the pro-Macedonian party.</note> was
                    at that port, a recent arrival from Rhodes, who stated, on the authority of
                    Dinon and Polyaratus, the <pb n="p.167"/> heads of the state, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> They were heads of the pro-Macedonian
                        party, but Livy may exaggerate their official position. </note> that the
                    Rhodians were ready for <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> war. Metrodorus was assigned as the leader of the combined
                    embassy with the Illyrians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time, identical messages,
                    suggested by the state of affairs, were sent both to Eumenes and to Antiochus,
                    as follows: by nature a free state and a king were things hostile to each other;
                    the Roman people attacked kings one by one, and —an unjust state of affairs
                    —assailed kings with the help of kings; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus' father had been overcome with the aid of Attalus; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> with Eumenes helping, and to a certain extent Perseus'
                    father Philip as well, Antiochus had been assailed <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> On Attalus, see above, XXIX. xii. 14 and XXXI. xiv; for
                        Eumenes, XXXV. xiii; XXXVI. xliv; XXXVII. xli; for Philip, XXXVII. vii.
                    </note> ; now both Eumenes and Prusias were in arms against Perseus; <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> if the kingdom of Macedonia were out of the way, next
                    would come Asia Minor, which the Romans had already made their own to some
                    extent under pretext of freeing communities, and after Asia Minor, Syria.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Already Prusias was being given a position
                    above Eumenes, already Antiochus, though victorious, was being barred from
                    Egypt, his prize of war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Perseus bade each
                    king, on considering these facts, to take such steps that either he might force
                    the Romans to make peace with Perseus, or if Rome persevered in an unjust war
                    might regard the Romans as the common enemy of all kings. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The message to Antiochus was open; to Eumenes
                    the envoy was sent under guise of ransoming prisoners, but in fact certain more
                    secret matters were under discussion, which for the time being embarrassed
                    Eumenes, who was already an object of <pb n="p.169"/> hatred and suspicion to
                    the Romans, with false and more serious charges; <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> for he was already regarded as a traitor and almost an enemy, while the two
                    kings with grasping hands vied with each other in guile and greed. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Polybius XXIX. 7-8 (Id) calls Eumenes
                            <quote>most unscrupulous</quote> and Perseus <quote>most
                            miserly,</quote> and says that Eumenes <quote>was unable by his lack of
                            scruple to get the best of Perseus' stinginess.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was a Cretan, Cydas, one of Eumenes'
                    henchmen. He had held conversations, first at Amphipolis with a certain
                    Chimarus, a fellow-countryman who was serving in Perseus' army, then later at
                    Demetrias, beneath the very walls of the city, once with a certain Menecrates
                    and again with Antimachus, both of whom were officers of the king. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For the negotiations at Demetrias, see
                        above, xiii. 9, where Antimachus only is mentioned on the Macedonian side. </note>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Herophon also, who was then sent by Perseus,
                    had similarly undertaken two previous missions to Eumenes. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> These conversations were secret, and the missions caused
                    bad rumours, but there was no knowledge of what had been discussed or upon what
                    the kings had agreed. The actual state of affairs, however, was as follows. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Eumenes did not want a victory for Perseus,
                    nor did he intend to assist him in winning one by military means, not so much
                    because of the mutual hostility of their fathers, as because of the hatred
                    engendered between himself and Perseus. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy is in this chapter expanding the account of
                        Polybius XXIX. 7-8 (Id). </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The jealousy of kings is such that Eumenes
                    would not have viewed with calmness the attainment by Perseus of such great
                    strength and prestige as awaited him if he defeated the Romans. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Eumenes also perceived that from the very outset of the war
                    Perseus had nurtured the hope of peace in every way <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy now states what his presentation of facts showed
                        before-that Perseus did not want the war, and stood on the defensive from
                        the first, see Vol. XII. 396 and 460, notes 1, Roman suspicions and
                        propaganda notwithstanding; the latter have influenced Livy extensively in
                        his commentary on events. </note> and as <pb n="p.171"/> time went on had
                    come more and more, as the threat <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> came closer, to treat and think of nothing
                    else. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Since the war was dragging on longer
                    than the Romans had hoped, they too, their commanders, and their senate would
                    not be averse, so Eumenes thought, to ending so disturbing and difficult a war.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having ascertained this willingness on
                    either side, Eumenes was eager to put on sale his good offices in an effort to
                    negotiate the peace which he thought might even come about automatically through
                    the weariness of the stronger and the fears of the weaker side. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Therefore Eumenes tried to negotiate for a reward, now for
                    not aiding the Romans' military effort on land or sea, now for securing peace
                    with the Romans; for his abstention from war, his price was a thousand talents,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Polybius says five hundred.</note>
                    for negotiating peace, fifteen hundred. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                    showed himself always ready not only to pledge his word to either course of
                    action, but even to give hostages. </p>
                <p> Perseus was very ready to undertake the attempt under pressure of fear, and as
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> to the acceptance of hostages the
                    discussion proceeded without delay, and it was agreed that, when accepted, the
                    hostages should be sent to Crete. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the
                    subject of money came up, there Perseus hesitated, and said that especially for
                    the first alternative the payment of money was dishonourable and base for kings
                    of so high a reputation, not only for the giver, but even more for the
                    recipient; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> for the hope of peace with the
                    Romans, he would not refuse an expenditure, but he would pay on the completion
                    of the enterprise, and meanwhile would deposit the funds in the temple on
                    Samothrace. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Since this island was in Perseus'
                    realm, Eumenes saw that it made no difference <pb n="p.173"/> whether the money
                    was there or at Pella; he <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> attempted to secure some sort of down payment.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And so having tried vainly to overreach
                    each other, the kings got themselves nothing but a bad reputation. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was not the only failure incurred by
                    Perseus because of miserliness, when by payment of money he could either through
                    Eumenes' efforts have secured peace. which he should have bought even at the
                    price of part of his kingdom, or had he been deceived, he could have exposed his
                    enemy with the booty on him and aroused just hostility toward him on the part of
                    the Romans. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But a previous parallel case was
                    that of the alliance with King Gentius, ready for the taking; and at this same
                    time Perseus lost through miserliness the tremendous assistance of the Gauls who
                    were scattered through the region of Illyria. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> These people may have been much the same as the
                        Bastarnae of XL. v. 10 and lvii, cf. also XLI. xix. 3-11. The name of the
                        leader, Clondicus, is the same here and in XL. lviii. 8, which makes it
                        sound like a title rather than a proper name. In Polybius XXV. 6 (XXVI. 9),
                        there is a reference to the Bastarnae joining Perseus and the Gauls (Paton's
                        interpretation),which has led some scholars to think that Polybius was
                        referring to the Bastarnae as Gauls (Galatai) here. Properly, the Bastarnae
                        were Germans rather than Gauls, as was recognized soon after Livy's time,
                        cf. Strabo VII. 306, Pliny, <hi rend="italics">N.H.</hi> IV. 81, Tacitus,
                            <hi rend="italics">Germania</hi> 46. The location of the Bastarnae was
                        to the north-east of the location here suggested for these Gauls, but cf.
                        below, xxvii. 3. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There were on their way ten thousand cavalry
                    and an equal number of infantry who matched their pace to that of the horses,
                    and in turn seized the riderless horses of fallen cavalrymen for further
                    fighting. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These men had been pledged a cash
                    payment of ten gold pieces per cavalryman, five per infantryman, and a thousand
                    for their leader. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they approached,
                    Perseus went to meet them from his camp at the Elpeüs with half of his forces
                    and began to give orders throughout the villages and cities near the road to
                    bring out provisions so that there would be plenty of grain, wine, and animals.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He <pb n="p.175"/> himself brought horses,
                    breast-ornaments, and capes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> as presents for the chief men, and a small
                    amount of gold to distribute among a few, supposing that the rank and file could
                    be led along by expectations. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He reached the
                    city of Almana and pitched camp on the banks of the Axius River. The force of
                    Gauls halted near Desudaba in Maedica, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        >Probably on the mid-Strymon.</note> waiting for their promised pay.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Thither Perseus sent Antigonus, one of the
                    wearers of the purple, to order the rank and file of the Gauls to shift camp to
                    Bylazora (this is a place in Paeonia) and the leaders to come in a body to him.
                    The Gauls were seventy-five miles from the Axius River and the king's camp.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Antigonus carried this message to them and
                    added an account of the abundance of all supplies prepared through the
                    thoughtfulness of the king, through which they would travel, and of the gifts of
                    garments, silver, and horses with which the king proposed to greet their leaders
                    on their arrival. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Gauls replied that they
                    would certainly find out about these matters from personal observation, but they
                    asked about what had been promised for immediate delivery —whether he had
                    brought with him the gold which was to be distributed among the individual
                    horsemen and footmen. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When they received no
                    reply on this point, Clondicus, their chieftain, declared: <quote> Go back then
                        and report to the king that the Gauls will not move a step farther unless
                        they receive the gold and hostages. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When this message was reported to the king,
                    he summoned his council, but when it became clear what everyone would advise,
                    the king, a trustier guardian of his cash than of his kingdom, began to
                    discourse on the treachery and savagery of the Gauls, which had been
                    demonstrated long since by disasters <pb n="p.177"/> to many people; <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> it was dangerous, he said, to receive <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> such large
                    numbers into Macedonia, for fear that they would find the Gauls more deadly as
                    allies than the Romans were as enemies; a force of five thousand cavalry was
                    sufficient, for these they could use for military <milestone n="14??"
                        unit="section"/> purposes and would not themselves be overawed by their
                    numbers. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was obvious to everyone that he was
                    troubled about the pay and nothing else; but as no one dared to give him the
                    advice he asked for, Antigonus was sent back to announce that the king could use
                    the services of five thousand cavalry only, and would not keep the rest of the
                    host. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the barbarians heard this, there
                    was an indignant outcry from the remainder that they had been to no purpose
                    lured away from their homes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Clondicus again
                    asked whether he would pay what had been agreed upon to these five thousand; and
                    when he saw that to this, too, a devious reply was being concocted, the Gauls
                    returned to the Danube, without injury to the messenger who had tricked them (a
                    fate he had hardly hoped could befall him), but plundering that part of Thrace
                    which adjoined their route. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This force of
                    Gauls, even had the king remained inactive at the Elpeüs before the Romans,
                    could if brought into Thessaly through the pass of Perrhaebia have not only
                    stripped the fields by their ravages, so that the Romans could have looked for
                    no provisions from there, but could even have stormed cities as long as Perseus
                    held the Romans <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> at the Elpeüs, in order to
                    prevent their rescuing the cities of their allies. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans would have had to consider their own plight,
                    since they could neither remain if Thessaly, the army's source of supplies, were
                    lost, nor could they advance <pb n="p.179"/> while the camp of the Macedonians
                    lay before them. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By losing this added strength, Perseus
                    weakened to no small degree the morale of the Macedonians, who had been
                    depending on this source of hope. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The same miserliness caused a rift with
                    Gentius. For when Perseus had counted out three hundred talents for the envoys
                    sent by Gentius to Pella, he permitted them to affix their seal to the money;
                    then he sent ten talents to Pantauchus and ordered this paid at once to the
                    king. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> His own people were transporting the
                    rest of the money marked with the seal of the <milestone n="10??" unit="section"
                    /> Illyrians, and he ordered them to convey it by short stages, and then when
                    the Macedonian frontier was reached, to halt there and wait for messengers from
                    him. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After Gentius had received a scant
                    portion of the money, he was continually spurred on by Pantauchus to assail the
                    Romans with an act of hostility, and so he threw into prison Marcus Perpenna and
                    Lucius Petilius, the ambassadors who happened to reach him at this time. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">See below xxxii. 2.</note>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> On hearing of this Perseus thought that
                    Gentius had committed himself to fight the Romans in any case, and sent a recall
                    to the one conveying the money, as if his only concern was to save as much booty
                    as possible for the Romans after his own defeat. </p>
                <p> Herophon also returned from the court of Eumenes, the secret negotiations being
                    still unrevealed. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Macedonians spread the
                    word that discussion about prisoners had taken place, and Eumenes, to avoid
                    suspicion, informed the consul to this same effect. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the disappointment of Herophon's return
                    from the court of Eumenes, Perseus sent Antenor and Callippus, his naval
                    commanders, with <pb n="p.181"/> forty scout-ships —there were five cutters
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Cf. XXXV. xxvi. 1, Polybius XVI.
                        2. 9 and XVIII (XVII) 1. 1, lumps these <hi rend="italics">pristes</hi> with
                        the <hi rend="italics">lembi</hi> as light fighting vessels. Livy, quoting
                        from the latter passage of Polybius, translates <hi rend="italics"
                            >pristis</hi> by <quote>beaked ship,</quote> XXXII. xxxii. 9. </note>
                    added to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                    this number —to <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Tenedos, in order to protect
                    from that base the ships scattered through the Cyclades islands on their way to
                    Macedonia with grain. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The ships were launched
                    at Cassandrea, and after crossing first to the harbours under Mount Athos and
                    thence on a calm sea to Tenedos, they sent away unharmed and even with kind
                    addresses some undecked Rhodian ships which were at the port with Eudamus their
                    commander. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then Antenor discovered that on the
                    other side of the island fifty of their freight ships were blockaded by warships
                    of Eumenes, under command of Damius, which were stationed at the mouth of the
                    harbour. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Antenor promptly sailed around and by
                    threat caused the enemy ships to retreat; the freight ships were sent to
                    Macedonia under convoy of ten scout-ships, which were instructed to return to
                    Tenedos after seeing them safe. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On the ninth
                    day thereafter they returned to the fleet, which was now anchored at Sigeum.
                    Thence they crossed to Subota, an island lying between Elaea and Chios.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On the day after the arrival of the fleet
                    at Subota, thirty-five of the ships called horse-transports, setting out from
                    Elaea with Galatian cavalry and their mounts, were making for Phanae, a cape of
                    Chios, from which they could cross to Macedonia. They were being sent to Attalus
                    by Eumenes. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When a signal reached Antenor from
                    a lookout post that these ships were at sea, he started from Subota and met them
                    between the cape of Erythrae and Chios, where <pb n="p.183"/> the strait is
                    narrowest. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Eumenes' officers least of <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> all
                    suspected that a Macedonian fleet was at large in that sea; now they thought
                    them to be Romans, now Attalus, or some men sent back by Attalus from the Roman
                    camp and on their way to Pergamum. But when the shape of the approaching
                    scout-ships was unmistakable and the rapid motion of the oars and the pointing
                    of the prows head-on revealed that enemies were approaching, then panic fell
                    upon them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Since there was no hope of
                    resistance, both because of the unwieldly type of vessel and because the
                    Galatians could hardly withstand an undisturbed voyage, <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> some of them, who were nearer to the mainland, swam ashore
                    at Erythrae and some set sail for Chios, ran their ships aground, and abandoning
                    their horses fled in rout to the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But as
                    the scoutships put troops ashore nearer the city at a more convenient
                    landing-place, the Macedonians overtook the Galatians and cut them down, partly
                    as they fled along the road and partly when they were shut out of the city
                    gates. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> For the Chians had closed their gates,
                    not knowing who were fleeing or who pursuing. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The move by Eumenes to add to Attalus' force indicates
                        that Livy's charges of treachery against Eumenes were none too well founded.
                        The exact course of the action described is not clear from the account in
                        Livy's usual impressionistic manner; but the Macedonian ships seem to have
                        let the transports pass Subota, wherever that was, and then pursued,
                        overtaking them between Phanae, the cape and harbour at the south end of
                        Chios (cf. above, XXXVI. xliii. 11 and Strabo XIV. 1. 35) and Chios city.
                        The Chians were allies of Rome. </note> About eight hundred of the Galatians
                    were killed and two hundred taken alive; some of the horses were destroyed in
                    the sea as the ships were wrecked, some were hamstrung on shore by the
                    Macedonians. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Antenor ordered twenty horses of
                    exceptional beauty, along with the prisoners, to be taken to Thessalonica by the
                    same ten scout-ships he had sent before, which he ordered to return as soon as
                    possible <pb n="p.185"/> to the fleet; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> he
                    said he would await them at Phanae. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> For about three days the fleet anchored before
                    the city. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Then they moved on to Phanae, and
                    setting sail on the unexpectedly early arrival of the ten scout-ships, crossed
                    the Aegean Sea to Delos. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these events were taking place, the
                    Roman envoys, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">To Alexandria, cf. xix.
                        13.</note> Gaius Popilius, Gaius Decimius, and Gaius Hostilius, set out from
                    Chalcis in three five-banked ships and on arriving at Delos found there forty
                    Macedonian scout-ships and five five-bankers of King Eumenes. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The holiness of the temple and the island kept them all
                    from harm. And so the Roman, the Macedonian, and Eumenes' sailors mingled in the
                    temple under the truce provided by the sacredness of the place. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Whenever signals came from the lookouts that any
                    freight-ships were passing out at sea, Antenor, Perseus' officer, would himself
                    pursue with some ships, while others of his ships were distributed among the
                    Cyclades, and either sank or plundered every ship not sailing for Macedonia.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Popilius would come to the rescue with
                    what ships he had either of his own or Eumenes'; but the Macedonians would evade
                    him by sailing at night mostly in groups of two or three ships. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At about this same time, the envoys from
                    Macedonia and Illyria <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> arrived together at
                    Rhodes, and weight was lent their words not only by the arrival of the
                    scoutships roaming all around the Cyclades and the Aegean Sea, but also by the
                    very fact of the combination between the kings Perseus and Gentius, and the
                    rumour of the arrival of the Gauls in great numbers both of infantry and
                    cavalry. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Since, then, the boldness of Dinon
                    and Polyaratus, who sided with <pb n="p.187"/> Perseus, was on the increase, not
                    only was a cordial <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> response given to the kings, but the flat statement was made that
                    the Rhodians would by their influence bring an end to the war, and that
                    therefore the kings <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> themselves should make
                    up their minds calmly to accept peace. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > Livy is following Polybius XXIX. 11 (5). Polybius says that the loss of
                        Eumenes' cavalry impressed the Rhodians, but does not mention the Gauls from
                        the North; he does not make the Rhodians sound as cock-sure as does Livy.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By now spring was beginning <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> It was late April by the then Roman
                        calendar, but actually early February, see below, xxxvii. 5-9. </note> and
                    the new commanders arrived in the field, the consul Aemilius in Macedonia,
                    Octavius with the fleet at Oreüs, and in the region of Illyria, Anicius, whose
                    task was the campaign against Gentius. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > The characterization of Gentius is based on Polybius XXIX. 13 (5). </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This king, the son of Pleuratus, king of the
                    Illyrians, and Eurydice, had two brothers, Plator, a full brother, and
                    Caravantius, born of the same mother. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    latter Gentius suspected less because of the obscurity of his father, but the
                    king killed Plator and two friends of his, Ettritus and Epicadus, energetic men,
                    for the greater security of his reign. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    rumour was that he envied his brother his betrothal to Etuta, daughter of
                    Monunius the chieftain of the Dardani, since by this marriage Plator would
                    secure the support of the Dardani; and Gentius made this really very probable by
                    marrying the girl after the murder of Plator. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Once the fear of his brother was removed, Gentius began to be oppressive to his
                    people, and the violence innate in his character was inflamed by overuse of
                    wine. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> However, when he had been stirred up to
                    fight the Romans, as has been related above, he collected all his forces at
                    Lissus. These were fifteen thousand men. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From
                    there he sent his brother with <pb n="p.189"/> a thousand infantry and fifty
                    cavalry to subdue the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> tribe of the Cavii either by force or threats, while he
                    himself advanced from Lissus five miles to the city of Bassania. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The inhabitants were allied to the Romans; and so
                    when overtures were made by messengers sent ahead of Gentius, they preferred to
                    stand siege rather than to surrender. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As
                    Caravantius arrived among the Cavii, the town of Durnium received him
                    hospitably; Caravandis, another city, shut him out; and while he was ravaging
                    their territory far and wide, a few scattered soldiers were killed by the
                    rallying farmers. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By now Appius Claudius too
                    had added auxiliaries of the Bullini and the citizens of Apollonia and
                    Dyrrachium to the army he had with him, and had set out from winter quarters to
                    a camp by the Genusus River, since he had heard of the treaty between Perseus
                    and Gentius and was incensed by the mistreatment of the molested envoys, so that
                    he was bent on campaigning against Gentius. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    About this time Anicius the praetor heard at Apollonia of affairs in the region
                    of Illyria, and sending ahead orders to Appius to wait for him at the Genusus,
                    he himself arrived in camp in three days. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He
                    added to the auxiliaries he had two thousand infantry and two hundred cavalry of
                    the young men of the Parthini —Epicadus commanded the infantry, Algalsus the
                    cavalry —and made ready to march into the region of Illyria, especially in order
                    to relieve the siege of Bassania. His urgency was restrained by a rumour of
                    scout-ships ravaging the coast. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There were
                    eighty of these ships, sent by Gentius at the suggestion of Pantauchus to
                    plunder <pb n="p.191"/> the territory of Dyrrachium and Apollonia. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> Then a <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> fleet at . . . <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Appian, <hi rend="italics">Illyrian Wars</hi> ii. 9
                        says that Anicius <quote> captured some of Gentius' scout-ships and then
                            engaged him in battle on land, defeated him, and shut him up in a
                            fortress. </quote>
                    </note> . . . they surrendered. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thereafter the cities of the region did the
                    same, the turn of their thoughts being assisted by the mildness and justice of
                    the Roman praetor. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Next he arrived at Scodra,
                    the centre of resistance not only because Gentius had appropriated it as the
                    citadel for his whole kingdom, but also because it is the best-fortified town of
                    the Labeate tribe, and is hard to approach. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Two rivers surround it, the Clausal flowing by on the side of the city which
                    faces eastward, the Barbanna on the west side, flowing from the Labeate Lake.
                    (These two streams after joining fall into the Oriundes River <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This river is elsewhere called the
                        Drilon (modern Drin); in 1858, after a period during which the Drilon
                        emptied to the south, and the Barbanna followed its own course to the sea,
                        the Drin, in flood, resumed the course reported by Livy, and was maintaining
                        it, except for some water following the southern channel, about 1940 (see
                        the <hi rend="italics">Encyclopaedia Britannica,</hi> 1944, <hi
                            rend="italics">s. v.</hi> Albania). </note> which rises on Mount
                    Scordus, is swelled by many other streams, and falls into the Adriatic Sea.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Mount Scordus, by far the highest of that
                    region, overlooks Dardania to the eastward, Macedonia to the south, and the
                    Illyrian region to the west.) <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although the
                    town was fortified by its surroundings and the whole nation of the Illyrians, as
                    well as their, king, was defending it, nevertheless the Roman praetor decided
                    that since his first moves had met with success, good fortune in the campaign as
                    a whole would follow these beginnings, and that a fast-moving threat would be
                    efficacious; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> so he advanced to the wall with
                    his army in formation. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If well-placed forces
                    had shut the gates and defended the walls and gate-towers, they <pb n="p.193"/>
                    would have routed the Romans from the wall and <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> made their attempt
                    worthless; as it was, they sallied from the gate and on level ground joined
                    battle with more spirit than they maintained. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For they were routed and huddled in flight, while over two hundred fell in the
                    very mouth of the gate, and they <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> brought in
                    with them such panic that Gentius at once sent representatives named Teuticus
                    and Bellus, leading men of the nation, to the praetor to ask for a truce so that
                    the king might deliberate over his situation. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    When he was given three days for this purpose, he boarded a ship, since the
                    Roman camp was about half a mile from the city, and sailed up the Barbanna River
                    to Lake Labeate, as if seeking a secluded spot for taking council; actually, as
                    became evident, he was stirred by an unfounded hope that his brother Caravantius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Possibly he had gone to a
                        different region from that mentioned in the preceding chapter, and was among
                        friends. </note> would arrive with many thousands of soldiers gathered in
                    the region to which he had been sent. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> After
                    the talk about this had evaporated, on the third day he brought the same ship
                    downstream to Scodra. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> First sending
                    messengers to secure an opportunity for addressing the praetor and on being
                    given the opportunity, he came into camp. At the outset of his speech he began
                    by blaming his own stupidity, and at the end gave himself up to entreaties and a
                    flood of tears, and falling at the praetor's knees, put himself into his hands.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Immediately he was bidden to take heart,
                    and after being invited to dinner, returned to his own people in the city.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> On that day he was banqueted with marks
                    of distinction by the praetor, and then put under the guard of Gaius Cassius,
                    tribune of the soldiers, after <pb n="p.195"/> having received a mere ten
                    talents, hardly the fee of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> a gladiator, though he <milestone n="15??"
                        unit="section"/> was a king dealing with a king, to induce him to sink to
                    such misfortune. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On taking over Scodra, Anicius' very first
                    order was that the ambassadors Petilius and Perpenna should be searched out and
                    brought to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When they had been restored to
                    a properly dignified state, he immediately sent Perpenna to arrest the friends
                    and relatives of the king. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Perpenna set out
                    for Meteon, the city of the Labeate tribe, and brought to camp at Scodra Etleva,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> We cannot determine whether this
                        is another queen, or whether the name Etuta in xxx. 4 refers to the same
                        woman. </note> the queen, with her two children, Scerdilaedus and Pleuratus,
                    and Caravantius the king's brother. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> After
                    completing the Illyrian campaign within thirty days, Anicius sent Perpenna to
                    Rome as messenger of this victory, and a few days later sent on King Gentius
                    himself with his mother, wife, children, and brother, as well as other leading
                    Illyrians. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> This campaign was unique in that
                    its conclusion was reported at Rome before its beginning. </p>
                <p> During the time that this was going on, Perseus also was in great fear because
                    of the arrival not only of Aemilius the new consul, who he heard had come on the
                    scene bringing dire threats, but also of Octavius the praetor. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The king was feeling equally keenly the threat from the
                    Roman fleet and the danger to the coastal area. At Thessalonica, Eumenes and
                    Athenagoras were in command with a small garrison of two thousand light
                    infantry. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Cf, XLII. li. 4 and the
                        note.</note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> To that place Perseus sent the officer
                    Androcles also, under orders to encamp right by the dockyards. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> To Aenea a thousand cavalry under Creon of Antigonea were
                    sent to <pb n="p.197"/> protect the coastal area, in order to come at once to
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> the
                    aid of the country folk at any point on the shore where they heard that enemy
                    ships had put in. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Five thousand Macedonians
                    were sent to garrison Pythoüs and Petra, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> These places guarded a pass north of Mount Olympus by
                        which the position at the Elpeüs might have been taken in the rear. </note>
                    the commanders being Histiaeus, Theogenes, and Midon. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> When these forces had left, Perseus set himself to
                    fortifying the bank of the Elpeüs, because its dry bed could be crossed. In
                    order that his entire force might be free for this operation, women gathered
                    from the near-by cities brought foodstuffs into camp; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> the soldiers, under orders, from the woods near by
                    generously . . . <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Further preparations
                        of Perseus and the arrival of Paulus at the Roman camp were described in
                        this gap. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ... to gather, and finally he ordered the
                    water-carriers to follow him to the sea, which was less than three-tenths of a
                    mile away, and to dig wells on the beach, some here, some there, at slight
                    intervals. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The immense height of the
                    mountains, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xiv. 1, says that the green woods on the
                        slopes indicated abundant ground-water. </note> especially inasmuch as they
                    produced no visible rivers, gave him the hope that underneath were hidden
                    streams, the veins of which trickled through to the sea and mingled with the
                    salt water. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hardly had the uppermost sand been
                    penetrated when jets of water spurted out, at first muddy and slight, but then
                    proceeding to pour out, as if by a miracle, with clear and copious water.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This success too gave the commander no
                    little glory and power of leadership with the soldiers. Then when the soldiers
                    were ordered to put their weapons in condition, the consul with the tribunes and
                    ranking centurions went forward to reconnoitre the crossings, in order to find
                    out where <pb n="p.199"/> the way down was easy for men under arms and where
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> on
                    the farther bank there was the least unfavourable way up. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> After gathering sufficient information on these points, he
                    introduced other changes, too; in the first place, he saw to it that everything
                    in the column should take place in good order and without confusion at the beck
                    and call of the commander; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> when orders were
                    given to the whole army at once and not all were within hearing, he said, some,
                    after receiving an unclear order, made additions of their own and did more than
                    was bidden, while others did less; hence discordant outcries arose everywhere
                    and the enemy found out what was afoot sooner than one's own men. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Therefore the consul decided that the tribune of the
                    soldiers should first give an order privately to the chief centurion of the
                    legion, and he and his subordinates in rank should then each tell to the next in
                    rank <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Centurions ranked according to
                        their place in the formation of the legion, cf. e.g. XLII. xxxiv. 5-8.
                    </note> what was to be done, whether the order was to be passed from the head of
                    the column to the rear, or from the last to the first. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The consul also made the innovation of forbidding sentries
                    to carry a shield <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xiii. 5, says a spear. </note> on post; for
                    he said that a sentry is not going into combat to use his weapons, but is to
                    keep on guard so that when he perceives the approach of the enemy, he may retire
                    and rouse the others to arms. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Men set the
                    shield before them and stand there, helmet on head; then when they are tired,
                    they lean on the spear, rest the head on the shield-rim, and stand there
                    drowsing, so that with their shining armour they can be detected by the enemy
                    from afar, while they themselves do not see ahead at all. The consul also
                    changed the practice of the outposts. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> All
                    were used to spending the entire day under arms, cavalry with their horses
                    bridled; when this took <pb n="p.201"/> place on summer days under an
                    unremitting -and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> burning sun, after so many hours of heat and weariness the tired
                    men and horses were often attacked by fresh enemy troops and superior numbers
                    thrown into confusion by even a few. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> So he
                    gave orders that men on duty in the morning should be relieved at noon by a
                    different afternoon detail; in this way a fresh enemy could never attack tired
                    men. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After he had announced to an assembly of the
                    soldiers the decision to adopt these measures, the consul added a speech in the
                    vein of his address in Rome: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> There should be a single general in an army who foresees and plans what
                        should be done, sometimes by himself, sometimes with the advisers he calls
                        into council. Those who are not called into council should not air their own
                        views publicly or privately. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> A soldier
                        should concern himself with the following: his body, to keep it as strong
                        and as nimble as possible; the good condition of his weapons; and the
                        readiness of his food-supply for unexpected orders. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> For the rest, he should realize that the immortal gods
                        and his general are taking care of him. In an army in which the soldiers
                        deliberate and the general is led about by the gossip of the rank and file,
                        conditions are utterly unsound. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> For my
                        part, I shall do the duty of a general —that is, see to it that you have an
                        opportunity for successful action. You ought not to ask what is going to
                        happen, but when the signal is given, then do your duty as soldiers.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p> After these instructions, he dismissed the assembly, while throughout the army
                    even the veterans admitted that they, like raw recruits, had for the first time
                    learned how military matters should be handled. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.203"/> Not only did they show by such remarks with how <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> much
                    approval they had heard the words of the consul, but there was also an immediate
                    response in action. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Soon you could have seen
                    no one idle in the whole camp; some were sharpening swords, others were
                    polishing helmets and cheek-pieces, still others shields and coats of mail;
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> some were fitting their armour to their
                    bodies and trying the nimbleness of their bodies under arms, others were
                    brandishing spears, others fencing with their swords and inspecting the point
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Romans relied chiefly on the
                        thrust, cf. Vegetius I. 12. </note> ; so that anyone could easily see that
                    as soon as an opportunity of joining battle with the enemy had been <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> given, they would put an end to the war either by a
                    glorious victory or by a death that would go down in history. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When Perseus, too, noticed that on the
                    arrival of the consul and the beginning of spring everything in the enemy camp
                    was full of noise and bustle as if the war were just beginning, that the camp
                    had been shifted from Phila to the bank opposite the Macedonians, and the
                    hostile commander was now going about to view Perseus' defences, no doubt
                    because he was reconnoitring a passage, now .. . <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> According to Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi>
                        xv, a period of startling inactivity on both sides ensued. The words with
                        which the text resumes may conclude an account of how the news of Gentius'
                        defeat arrived in the two camps. </note> . of the Romans was. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This affair raised the spirits of the Romans.
                    It also brought no little panic to the Macedonians and their king. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> At first he tried to hide the report of the event in
                    secret, by sending men to forbid Pantauchus, who was coming from there, to
                    approach the camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But now some boys were seen
                    by their relatives being led along with the Illyrian hostages <pb n="p.205"/>
                    and the more carefully the various details were <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> concealed, the more easily
                    they leaked out through the garrulity of the king's servants. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> About the same time envoys from Rhodes came
                    into camp with the same message about peace which had aroused great wrath in the
                    senators at Rome. They received a much less favourable audience from the council
                    in the camp. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So while some advised that the
                    envoys be thrown into chains, others that they be driven headlong out of camp
                    without an answer, the consul announced that he would make a reply a fortnight
                    later. Meanwhile, to make it clear how much influence the Rhodian peace-makers
                    had succeeded in exerting, he began to hold consultations as to the plan of
                    campaign. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some, especially the younger, wished
                    to force a way through the bank of the Elpeüs and the fortifications; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> a solid formation, they said, attacking in single
                    column would be irresistible to the Macedonians, who had the previous year been
                    driven out of so many forts, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is
                        contrary to the picture given by Livy above, chs. iv-vii, and seems to be
                        inserted to show that the speakers estimated the situation incorrectly.
                    </note> rather higher and better fortified and held with strong garrisons.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Others advised that Octavius with his
                    fleet should make for Thessalonica and by ravaging the coastal area create a
                    diversion of the king's forces, so that on the appearance of another attack in
                    his rear the king would be pulled about to guard the inner part of his kingdom
                    and be compelled to open a crossing somewhere over the Elpeüs. The consul
                    himself regarded the riverbank as impregnable by nature and by fortification
                    and, besides the fact that artillery had been placed everywhere, he had heard
                    that the enemy employed <pb n="p.207"/> missile weapons better and with more
                    deadly aim. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The whole thought of the Roman commander
                    inclined in a different direction; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and
                    dismissing his council, he summoned the Perrhaebian merchants Coenus and
                    Menophilus, men already known to him for loyalty and wisdom, and secretly
                    inquired what the passes into Perrhaebia were like. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> When they said that the terrain was not difficult, but was
                    blocked by the king's guard-forces, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xv and xvi. 1, says that the
                        passes were not guarded at this time, but that Perseus sent a force after
                        hearing that Romans, under Nasica, were on the march to Pythium. Plutarch
                        cites Polybius and Nasica himself for the story of the dislodging of the
                        Macedonians. </note> the consul conceived the hope that the guards could be
                    dislodged if he attacked suddenly by night with a strong force and surprised
                    them; for, he argued, javelins, arrows, and other missiles are useless in the
                    dark when the target cannot be sighted at a distance; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> the sword is the weapon used at close quarters in a
                    confused throng, and with that weapon the Roman soldier would win. Planning to
                    use the abovementioned merchants as guides, the consul summoned the praetor
                    Octavius, explained his plans, and ordered him to sail for Heracleum with the
                    fleet and have ten days' cooked rations for a thousand men. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> For his own part, he sent Publius Scipio Nasica and his own
                    son Quintus Fabius Maximus <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As
                        explained by Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xv, this was the
                        elder of Aemilius' sons by his first wife; the younger became Scipio
                        Africanus the Younger, cf. below, xliv. 1-2. After divorcing his wife,
                        remarrying, and having two more sons(for whom see below, XLV. xl. 7),
                        Aemilius gave the older pair in adoption. Fabius was about eighteen at this
                        time; his adoption had taken place about ten years before. </note> with five
                    thousand picked <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> men <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Plutarch, following Nasica and correcting Polybius,
                        lists three thousand Italians ( <quote>special troops</quote> — <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">e)kto\s ta/cews</foreign> = <hi rend="italics"
                            >extraordinarii</hi> ?), five thousand of the <quote>left wing</quote>
                        (= <hi rend="italics">sinistra</hi>
                        <hi rend="italics">ala, i.e.</hi> cavalry?), 120 cavalry, and 200 mixed
                        Thracians and Cretans. </note> to Heracleum, in order to feign an
                    embarkation for the purpose of the plan mentioned in the council, namely, of
                    ravaging the coastal area of inner Macedonia. Scipio and Fabius were privately
                        <pb n="p.209"/> informed that food was ready for them at the fleet, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> so that
                    they would not be <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> delayed. Next, the guides
                    were instructed to arrange the stages of the journey so that they could attack
                    Pythoüs in the fourth watch of the third day. Next day at dawn the consul
                    himself, in order to keep the king from investigating the other projects, joined
                    battle with the enemy's outposts in the middle of the <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> river-bed. The fight was conducted with light-armed troops
                    on both sides. It was impossible to fight with heavier troops in so rough a
                    stream-bed. The slope of either bank to the bottom was about three hundred
                    paces; between the banks, a space of a little over a mile lay open where the
                    torrent had hollowed it out in varying degrees from place to <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> place. There the fight took place in sight of the watchers
                    from the walls of both camps, the king on one side, the consul and his legions
                    on the <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> other. The king's light troops fought
                    better at long range with missiles; at close quarters the Romans were steadier,
                    and better protected by either the cavalry targe or the Ligurian rectangular
                        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> shield. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This is based on Polybius XXIX. 14. 4; the Ligurian
                        shield was long and light, according to Diodorus V. 39. 7. </note> About
                    noon the consul ordered the recall to be sounded for his <milestone n="20"
                        unit="section"/> men. So that day the fight was broken off with no small
                    losses to both sides. At sunrise the next day an even sharper fight took place,
                    since their spirits had been roused by the <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    combat. But the Romans received a great many wounds not only from those with
                    whom the fight had been joined, but much more from the large numbers posted on
                    the towers with all sorts of missile weapons and stones. As they came nearer to
                    the enemy's bank, the shots from the engines reached even the rear ranks. After
                    far more severe losses that day, the consul recalled his men somewhat <milestone
                        n="22" unit="section"/> later. On the <pb n="p.211"/> third day, he desisted
                    from battle and went down to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note> the lower side of the camp as if he were going
                    to attempt the crossing through the spur of the fortifications which ran down to
                    the <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> sea. What was before Perseus' eyes ...
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Judging from Plutarch, <hi
                            rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xvi, the lost four sheets told of the
                        success of Nasica in clearing the pass, Perseus' fright and retreat, and his
                        subsequent resolve to make a stand at Pydna; also of the joining of Nasica
                        with Paulus and the overtaking of the Macedonians. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The season was that immediately following the
                    turn of midsummer <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See below, xxxvii.
                        5-8 and note 1; by the then calendar, it was Sept. 3. </note> ; the time of
                    day was approaching noon; the journey had been made through much dust and an
                    ever-hotter sun. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Weariness and thirst now
                    began to make themselves felt, and since it was presently obvious that midday
                    would intensify the blazing heat, the consul decided not to expose men so
                    weakened to a fresh and unwearied enemy; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> but
                    such zeal was in their hearts for fighting at all costs that the consul needed
                    as much skill to out manoeuvre his own men as the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Since all were not yet in formation, he urged on the
                    tribunes of the soldiers to hasten the deployment; he himself went about the
                    ranks and was engaged in rousing the spirits of the men to battle by
                    exhortation. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At this they first kept eagerly
                    calling for the signal; then, in proportion as the heat increased their
                    countenances were less lively and their cries slacker, and some stood lolling on
                    their shields and leaning on their spears. Then the consul proceeded openly to
                    give the order to the ranking centurions to layout the front of the camp and
                    place the baggage. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Which was placed
                        next the wall of the camp.</note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the soldiers perceived that this was
                    being done, some rejoiced <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> openly that he had
                    not compelled men wearied by the toil of marching to fight a battle in scorching
                    heat. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Surrounding the general were his <pb
                        n="p.213"/> staff and the foreign commanders, among whom was <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> Attalus,
                    all showing approval as long as they believed the consul was going to fight (for
                    he had not revealed his doubts even to them); then at the sudden change of plan
                    they were all silent except Nasica, <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> who
                    alone dared to advise the consul not to loose his grasp on an enemy who had
                    baffled previous generals by avoiding an encounter. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Nasica feared that if the enemy departed by night, he would
                    have to be pursued with the greatest toil and risk into the interior of
                    Macedonia, and that the summer would be wasted, as under previous leaders, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As far as Livy's account goes, this
                        applies only to Marcius, above, vi-x. </note> in roaming about the bypaths
                    and passes of the Macedonian mountains; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> for
                    his own part he strongly urged attack while the consul had the enemy in open
                    country, so as not to lose the opportunity for victory which had been offered.
                    The consul, nothing offended by the outspoken warning from so famous a young
                    man, replied: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> I too have had the spirit which you now have, Nasica, and you will come
                        to have the spirit I now have. From many vicissitudes of war I have learned
                        when to fight and when to refuse battle. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        There is not time to instruct you while you are standing-to for battle as to
                        the reasons why it is better to be inactive today. You shall ask for my
                        reasoning at another time; now you will be satisfied to take the word of an
                        experienced general. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The young man held his tongue, thinking that
                    no doubt the consul saw some obstacles to battle which he himself did not
                    envisage. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After Paulus saw that the camp had been laid
                    out and the baggage placed, he quietly withdrew the <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> rear formation first from behind the <pb n="p.215"/>
                    battle-line, next the chief formation, while the forward <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> formation stood its ground
                    at the front of the battle-line, in case the enemy should make a move; last of
                    all he withdrew the forward formation, taking the soldiers of one maniple at a
                    time, starting with the right wing. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In this
                    way, while the cavalry and the light-armed troops faced the enemy from in front
                    of the battle-line, the infantry were withdrawn without confusion, and the
                    cavalry were not called away from their posts until the facade of the rampart
                    and the ditch facing the enemy had been completed. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Although the king would have been prepared to fight that
                    day without reluctance, he was satisfied to let it be seen that the delay was
                    due to the enemy, and he too withdrew his forces into camp. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the fortification of the camp was
                    complete, Gaius Sulpicius Gallus, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> He
                        is mentioned by Cicero, <hi rend="italics">De Senectute</hi> xiv. 49 as a
                        geometer and astronomer. For his praetorship, see XLIII. ii. 5. Pliny, <hi
                            rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> II. xii. 53, Frontinus I. xii. 8, and
                        Zonaras 9. 23 speak of a prediction by Sulpicius; Justinus 33. 1. 7, Cicero,
                            <hi rend="italics">De Republica</hi> I. xv. 23, Valerius Maximus 8. 11.
                        1, and Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xvii say that the
                        explanation followed the eclipse. A fragment of Polybius XXIX. 16 (6) states
                        that the eclipse was interpreted as portending the fall of a king; therefore
                        it cheered the Romans and discouraged the Macedonians, see below, sec. 9.
                        Modern reckoning sets the date of the eclipse as June 21, which would mean
                        that the calendar was at least 70 days ahead of time, cf. p. 87, Appendix.
                    </note> tribune of the soldiers with the second legion, who had been praetor the
                    year before, summoned the soldiers to an assembly, by permission of the consul,
                    and announced that no one should regard it as a bad omen when on the following
                    night an eclipse of <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> the moon would take
                    place from the second to the fourth hour of the night. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Since this occurred in the regular order of nature at
                    certain times, said Sulpicius, it could be calculated ahead of time and
                    foretold. Therefore just as they were not surprised —inasmuch as both the
                    risings and the settings of the sun and moon are well understood —when they saw
                    the moon shining now full, now during its wane with a narrow arc, no more ought
                    they to count it a prodigy that the moon is darkened <pb n="p.217"/> whenever it
                    is hidden in the shadow of the earth. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the night preceding the 4th of September,
                    when the moon was eclipsed at the predicted hour, the Roman soldiers regarded
                    the wisdom of Gallus as almost divine; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the
                    Macedonians took it as a dire portent, foretelling the downfall of the kingdom
                    and the nation, and no soothsayer shook their conviction. There was uproar and
                    wailing in the Macedonian camp until the moon emerged to shine as usual. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the following day, so great was the
                    eagerness of both armies for battle that some of their followers blamed both the
                    king and the consul for separating without a fight. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The king had a rejoinder ready at hand: not only that the
                    enemy had taken the lead in openly declining battle and leading his men back to
                    camp, but that he had posted his forces in a position to which the phalanx could
                    not be advanced, since even slightly unfavourable terrain makes a phalanx
                    useless. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> As for the consul, besides his
                    seeming loss of an opportunity for battle on the previous day and his giving the
                    enemy a chance of withdrawing by night if they wished, he seemed on this day too
                    to be wasting time on the pretext of offering sacrifice, although he should have
                    given the signal at dawn and gone out to battle. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xvii. 6,
                        says that the consul's sacrifice to Heracles obtained good omens only with
                        the twenty-first victim; also that the consul waited till the afternoon so
                        that the sun would not be in the eyes of his troops. </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At the third hour, after due completion of
                    the sacrifice, he at last called a council, and in doing so seemed to some to be
                    expending in talk and untimely advisement the time needed for carrying out
                    action. In reply to such talk the consul delivered the following speech: </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "That excellent young man, Publius <pb
                        n="p.219"/> Nasica, alone among all those who favoured fighting <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> yesterday
                    disclosed his opinion to me; he too kept silent later, so that he may have
                    seemed to have exchanged his view for mine. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Certain others thought it better to criticize their general behind his back
                    rather than to advise him openly. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both to you,
                    Publius Nasica, and to any others who less openly shared your opinion, I shall
                    not hesitate to give an accounting for having postponed the battle. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> For I am so far from regretting our inactivity
                    yesterday that I believe I saved the army by so planning. That none of you may
                    believe me to hold this opinion groundlessly, come let each, if he please,
                    review with me how many factors weighed for the enemy and against us. First of
                    all, of their great superiority in numbers I am sure that you were all
                    previously aware, and that you took notice of it on seeing the battle-line drawn
                    up yesterday. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Out of this small force of ours,
                    one-fourth of the men were left to guard the baggage; and you know that the
                    guarding of the packs is not put in the hands of the most cowardly. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> But suppose we had been united: can we possibly
                    consider it a small advantage that we shall go out, with the good help of the
                    gods, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For similar expressions of
                        precautionary piety, see VI. xxiii. 10, VII. xxxii. 17, XXI. xxi. 6. </note>
                    from this camp in which we have spent last night, to do battle either today or
                    at latest tomorrow if we so determine? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Does it
                    make no difference whether you bid a soldier take up arms and lead him into
                    battle when he is wearied neither by the toil of a <milestone n="8??"
                        unit="section"/> journey nor by construction on that day, when he is rested
                    and refreshed in his own tent, when he is full of strength and vigorous in body
                    and in spirit? Or whether he <pb n="p.221"/> is wearied by a long march and
                    tired by his load, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> dripping with sweat, his throat dry with thirst, his mouth and
                    eyes full of dust, with the midday sun beating down upon him? <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Will you pit him against an enemy fresh and rested, who
                    brings into battle a strength unsapped by previous exertion? Who, by the gods'
                    good faith, when he is thus matched, sluggish though he be and unwarlike, will
                    not overcome the bravest fighter? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> "What of the fact that the enemy had drawn up
                    their line completely at leisure, had made ready their spirits, were standing
                    each <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> at his post in the ranks, while we at
                    that time had to incur the hasty turmoil of drawing up our line and had to enter
                    battle in disorder? <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Oh yes, you say, we should have had a
                    battle-line undeployed and disorderly; but our camp was fortified, our
                    water-supply found, the way to it secured by placing guards, and reconnaissance
                    made all around. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Or did our men have nothing
                    but the bare ground on which to fight . . .? Your ancestors regarded a fortified
                    camp as a haven against all the mischances of an army, whence they might go out
                    to fight, and whither they might find shelter from the storm of battle.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Therefore when they had walled in their
                    camp with fortifications, they used also to strengthen it with a powerful
                    garrison, because one who had been stripped of his camp, even though he had won
                    the battle, would be considered the loser. Camp is the shelter of the conqueror,
                    the refuge of the conquered. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> How many armies
                    meeting with none too favourable fortune in battle, after being driven within
                    their rampart, have in their own good time, sometimes after only a moment,
                    sallied forth and routed the victorious enemy? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    This abode is a second <pb n="p.223"/> home for the soldier, its rampart takes
                    the place of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> city walls and his own tent is the soldier's dwelling and
                    hearthside. Should we have fought like nomads with no abode, so that, whether
                    conquered or conquerors, we might return —where? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "To this statement of the difficulties and
                    hindrances to battle, here is the rejoinder: what if the enemy had departed
                    during the interval of last night? How much toil would we have had to expend in
                    the renewed pursuit far into the utmost end of Macedonia? <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> For my part I am sure that he would never have remained
                    here or led his forces out into battle-line had he decided to retreat from here.
                    For how much easier it would have been to depart while we were at a distance
                    than now when we are on his neck and he cannot trick us by leaving either by
                    night or day? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> What more can we wish than to
                    attack our enemy in open country from the rear of his retreating and dispersed
                    column after he has left his fortifications, instead of attacking, as we have
                    attempted to do, his camp protected by the lofty bank of a river, and barricaded
                    as well with a rampart and plenty of towers? </p>
                <p>
                    <quote> These were my reasons for postponing battle from yesterday to today.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For I too prefer to fight; and
                        therefore since the way to the enemy was barred by the Elpeüs River, I have
                        opened a new road by expelling the enemy's guards from a different pass, and
                        I will not turn back till I have fought to a finish. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this speech silence ensued, partly
                    because men had changed over to his opinion, partly because they shrank from
                    offending him to no purpose in a matter which was in any case a lost opportunity
                    and could not be brought back. Nor <pb n="p.225"/> even on that day did either
                    the consul or the king <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 168</note> care to fight, the king because he would have had to attack
                    men no longer weary from travel as on the previous day, nor in turmoil as they
                    marshalled their line of battle and hardly in formation, the consul because
                    neither wood nor fodder had been collected in the new camp and a large number of
                    soldiers had gone out of camp to seek them from the near-by countryside. Without
                    either general wishing it, Fortune, which is stronger than human planning,
                    brought on the battle. There was a stream of no great size nearer the camp of
                    the enemy, from which both the Macedonians and the Romans were drawing water
                    after posting guards on either bank in order to accomplish this mission safely.
                    There were two cohorts on the Roman side, a Marrucinian and a Paelignian, and
                    two troops of Samnite cavalry under the command of the staff-officer Marcus
                    Sergius Silus; another fixed outpost was stationed before the camp under the
                    staff-officer Gaius Cluvius, composed of three cohorts, from Firmum, the
                    Vestini, and Cremona respectively, and two troops of cavalry from Placentia and
                    Aesernia. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Marrucini, Paeligni,
                        Samnites, and Vestini were Italian <quote>allies</quote> of the Romans;
                        Firmum, Cremona, Placentia, and Aesernia were colonies with Latin rights. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While there was quiet at the river, since
                    neither side took the offensive, about the ninth hour a baggage-animal shied
                    from the hands of his grooms and escaped toward the other bank. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Plutarch credits Aemilius with ordering
                        a horse to be let loose, in order to bring on the battle. </note> While
                    three soldiers were chasing him through the water, which was about knee-deep,
                    two Thracians dragged the animal from mid-stream to their bank; the Romans
                    pursued them, killed one, <pb n="p.227"/> recaptured the animal, and retired to
                    their post. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> There was a guard of eight hundred Thracians on the Macedonian
                    bank. At first a few of these, angry at the killing of their fellow-countryman
                    before their eyes, crossed the river in pursuit of the killers, then more went,
                    and finally the whole force, and with the guard . . <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Two leaves of the MS. are missing at this point.
                        Judging from Plutarch, these pages contained a description of the advance of
                        the armies from camp, their battle-order, skirmishing by the light-armed
                        troops in which the Macedonians had the advantage, the charge of the
                        Paelignians against some Macedonian light infantry and their collision with
                        the phalanx (cf. below, sec. 9), and perhaps the impression made on Aemilius
                        by the phalanx, an impression which he was careful not to show at the time.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ... led... the battle. The men were stirred by
                    the prestige of his office, the fame of the man, and above all by his age, for
                    though he was over sixty he kept assuming functions of men in their prime in
                    undergoing an outstanding amount of toil and danger. The legion filled the space
                    between the light infantry and the phalanxes and broke the enemy line.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the rear were the light infantry; the
                    consul faced a unit with metal shields —these were called the Bronze Shields.
                    Lucius Albinus the ex-consul was ordered to lead the second legion against the
                    White Shield phalanx <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Plutarch speaks
                        of this unit as having gilded armour.</note> ; this was the centre of the
                    hostile line. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the right wing, where the
                    battle had begun near the river, the consul brought up the elephants and the
                    squadrons of the allies; and from this point the flight of the Macedonians first
                    began. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For, as frequently men's new inventions
                    appear strong when described, but in actual trial, when there is need for action
                    rather than a description of how they will act, these inventions disappear
                    without achieving any result, so in this battle the anti-elephant corps was <pb
                        n="p.229"/> a mere name without practical effect. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Zonaras 9. 22 (p. 269) says that these were infantry
                        with sharp spikes projecting from their helmets and shields, and also
                        cavalry, both forces having been drilled to fight elephants; dummy elephants
                        were used to accustom the horses to them. The words of Livy at the beginning
                        of sec. 4 seem to be a direct quotation from Polybius XXIX. 17. 2 (12). </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The charge <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> of the elephants was
                    followed up by the allies of the Latin Name, who routed the left wing.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the centre the charge of the second
                    legion scattered the phalanx. No reason for the victory was more obvious than
                    the fact that there were many scattered engagements which first threw into
                    confusion and then disrupted the wavering phalanx. The power of this formation
                    when closed up and bristling with spears extended is irresistible; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> but if by attacks at several points you compel them
                    to swing their spears about, unwieldy because of their length and weight, they
                    become tangled in a haphazard mass; and if indeed some sort of uproar is heard
                    on a flank or from the rear, <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> they are involved
                    in utter confusion. Such was the case on this occasion, when the phalanx was
                    compelled to meet the Romans who were attacking in groups, while the Macedonian
                    line was broken at many points. The Romans for their part kept infiltrating
                    their units wherever gaps presented themselves. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> If they had attacked frontally in solid line against an orderly phalanx, as
                    happened to the Paelignians who at the beginning of the battle recklessly met
                    the light infantry, the Romans would have spitted themselves on the spears and
                    would not have withstood the solid line. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> A variant account of the battle is given by Frontinus
                        II. iii. 20, who says that Paulus arranged his line in wedges, and tried to
                        draw out the Macedonians by attacking with skirmishers ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >velites</hi> ); when this failed, Paulus retreated, to induce the
                        Macedonians to break formation; when this also failed, the Roman cavalry
                        from the left wing were ordered to charge along the front of the phalanx and
                        break off the spear-points with their shields; when this manoeuvre
                        succeeded, the Macedonians broke and fled. Livy seems to have a far
                        preferable account. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, while the infantry were being
                    slaughtered all over the field, except for those who cast away their weapons and
                    fled, the cavalry on the <pb n="p.231"/> other hand retired from the fight
                    almost unscathed. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The king himself was the leader in the flight.
                    Directly from Pydna he set out for Pella with the Sacred Squadrons of cavalry;
                    immediately Cotys and the Odrysan cavalry followed them. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The other Macedonian squadrons also continued to retreat in
                    orderly formation because the line of the infantry in between kept the victors
                    busy with slaughter and caused them to forget the pursuit of the cavalry.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For a long time the phalanx was cut to
                    pieces from the front, from the flanks, and from the rear. Finally those who
                    slipped through the hands of the Romans fled weaponless to the sea, and some
                    even entered the water and raising their hands to the men on board ship humbly
                    begged for life. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they saw small boats
                    gathering from all around the fleet, they thought that these were coming to pick
                    them up, to take them prisoner rather than to kill them, and so they advanced
                    farther into the water, some even swimming. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But when they were mercilessly cut down from the boats, those who could made for
                    shore again by swimming and ran into a more dreadful form of destruction; for
                    the elephants, guided by their mahouts to the shore, trampled and crushed the
                    men coming out of the water. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                <p> It is readily agreed that the Romans never killed so many Macedonians in any
                    other single battle. For about twenty thousand men were slain; about six
                    thousand who escaped from the battlefield to Pydna were taken alive, and five
                    thousand stragglers were captured in flight. Of the victors not more than one
                    hundred fell and by far the greater part of them were Paeligni; somewhat more
                    were wounded. If fighting had broken out earlier, so that sufficient <pb
                        n="p.233"/> daylight would have remained for the victors to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> pursue,
                    the entire Macedonian force would have been wiped out; as it was, the approach
                    of night both sheltered the fugitives and inspired in the Romans a reluctance to
                    pursue over unknown terrain. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus fled to the Pierian Forest along the
                    military road with a large column of cavalry and the royal entourage. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> As soon as they arrived in the forest, where there
                    were many divergent ways, and night was approaching, the king left the road with
                    a very few of his most trusty men. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    cavalry, left without a commander, took various routes in dispersing to their
                    own cities; a very few went on to Pella more rapidly than the king, since they
                    had gone by the direct and clear way. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king
                    was bothered till about midnight by losing his way and by various difficulties
                    of the route. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the palace Perseus was waited
                    upon by the commanders of Pella, Euctus, and Eulaeus, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Aemilius</hi> xxiii, calls
                        them <quote>the mintmasters,</quote> and says that Perseus put them to
                        death. </note> and the royal pages. On the other hand, of his friends who by
                    various haps had come safely from the battle to Pella, not one came to him,
                    though they were summoned many times. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There
                    were only three companions in flight with him, Evander the Cretan, Neon the
                    Boeotian, and Archidamus the Aetolian. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With
                    these he escaped in the fourth watch, being now afraid that those who refused to
                    come to him would presently venture on a bolder stroke. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> His escort was composed of about five hundred Cretans. He
                    was making for Amphipolis; but he had left Pella at night because of his anxiety
                    to cross the Axius River before dawn, since he thought that because of the
                    difficulty of crossing this would be the limit of the Roman pursuit. </p>
                <pb n="p.235"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consul returned victorious to <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> camp, he
                    was prevented from enjoying an unalloyed delight by the sting of worry over his
                    younger son. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This was Publius Scipio, who was
                    also called Africanus later after the destruction of Carthage, born son to the
                    consul Paulus and by adoption grandson of Africanus. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> This son was then in his seventeenth year, a fact which in
                    itself increased the anxiety for him, and had been carried away in another
                    direction by a crowd while in hot pursuit of the enemy. When he returned very
                    late, then at last on the safe recovery of his son the consul felt the joy of so
                    great a victory. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The soldiers hailed
                        him as <hi rend="italics">imperator</hi> for the third time (Mommsen, <hi
                            rend="italics">Münzwesen</hi> 633, number 486). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> At Amphipolis the news of the battle had by
                    now arrived; there was a gathering of the matrons in the temple of Diana whom
                    they call Tauropolos, to pray for help. Diodorus, who was in charge of the city,
                    feared that the Thracians, two thousand of whom were in the garrison, would
                    plunder the city during the confusion. Hence he craftily hired a man to play the
                    part of dispatch bearer, from whom he received papers in the middle of the
                    market place. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The message in these despatches
                    was that the Roman fleet had put in at Emathia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The district west of Amphipolis, toward the Chalcidic
                        peninsula. </note> and was harassing the surrounding countryside, and that
                    the officers in charge of Emathia requested him to send a force against the
                    ravagers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After reading this, he urged the
                    Thracians to start out to defend the coast of Emathia, telling them that they
                    would cause great slaughter and get great booty among the Romans scattered all
                    over the fields. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the same time he minimized
                    the report of the loss of a battle; if this were true, he said, man after man
                    would have been arriving direct from the rout. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Having got rid of <pb n="p.237"/> the Thracians on this pretext, he barred the
                    gates as <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note>
                    soon as he saw that they had crossed the Strymon. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the second day after the battle Perseus
                    arrived at Amphipolis. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> From there he sent
                    ambassadors with the staff of Mercury to Paulus. Meanwhile Hippias, Midon, and
                    Pantauchus, the chief among the king's friends, set out of their own accord from
                    Beroea, where they had taken refuge after the battle, and surrendered to the
                    Romans at the consul's camp. Others too, overcome with fear, were thereafter
                    preparing to do the same. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul sent as
                    messengers of his victory his son Quintus Fabius, Lucius Lentulus, and Quintus
                    Metellus with despatches to Rome and granted the spoils of the slain enemy to
                    the infantry, <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and to the cavalry the right to
                    plunder the surrounding territory, provided that they were not absent from camp
                    for more than two nights. He himself moved camp nearer to the sea by Pydna.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Beroea first, then Thessalonica and Pella,
                    and then almost all Macedonia was surrendered within two days. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The people of Pydna who were nearest had not yet sent
                    envoys; a heterogeneous crowd of numerous nationalities together and the mob
                    which had been amalgamated by flight from the battlefield were standing in the
                    way of planning and agreement among the citizens. The gates were not only closed
                    but built up solid. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Midon and Pantauchus were
                    sent up to the walls to confer with Solon, who was in charge of the garrison;
                    through him dismissal of the mob of soldiers was arranged. The city when
                    surrendered was given to the Roman troops to plunder. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> After Perseus had tried his only expedient, to
                    get aid from the Bisaltae, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A tribe
                        living just west of Amphipolis.</note> to whom he sent envoys <pb n="p.239"
                    /> without result, he appeared before an assembly bringing <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> his son Philip with him,
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> in order to strengthen by exhortation the
                    spirits of the people of Amphipolis themselves, and of the cavalry and infantry
                    who had either accompanied him or had in their flight reached the same goal.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He began to speak several times, but
                    tears choked him, and when he could not open his mouth he instructed Evander the
                    Cretan in the matters which he wished to discuss with the people and went down
                    from the sacred spot. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">I.e.,</hi> the speakers' stand, cf. VIII. xiv. 12,
                        describing the consecration of the Roman Rostra. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> At the sight of the king and his truly
                    pitiable weeping the crowd itself groaned and wept; but with equal readiness
                    they would have none of Evander's speech; and some dared to shout from the midst
                    of the assembly, <quote>Get away from here so that we few survivors may not
                        perish on your account.</quote> The vehemence of these interruptions choked
                    off Evander's speech. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Thereafter the king
                    went home, put his money, his gold, and his silver into the scout-ships which
                    were moored in the Strymon and himself went down to the river. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The Thracians and the rest of the mob of soldiers, not
                    daring to trust themselves to ships, slipped away to their homes; the Cretans
                    followed Perseus in hopes of cash. Because apportionment would create more hard
                    feelings than gratitude, fifty talents were set out on the river-bank for them
                    to scramble for. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When after this scramble
                    they were boarding the ships in riotous fashion, they sank one scout-ship at the
                    mouth of the river by overcrowding it. On that day the party reached Galepsus,
                    on the next Samothrace, their destination; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> it
                    is said that two thousand talents were brought there. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Paulus sent men to take charge of all the <pb
                        n="p.241"/> surrendered cities, so that no wrong should be done <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 168</note> to the
                    conquered in the first days of peace; he kept the king's ambassadors with him
                    and, since he did not know of the king's flight, sent Publius Nasica to
                    Amphipolis with a small force of infantry and cavalry, <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> both to ravage Sintica and to interfere with any moves of
                    the king. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Meanwhile Meliboea was captured and
                    plundered by Gnaeus Octavius. At Aeginium, to besiege which the staff-officer
                    Gnaeus Anicius had been sent, two hundred men were lost in a sally from the town
                    because the people of Aeginium did not know that the war was over. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consul set out from Pydna with his whole
                    army and on the second day reached Pella, pitched camp a mile from there, and
                    remained in this camp for a few days, examining the site of the city from all
                    sides and noticing that it had not been chosen to be the capital without good
                    reason. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It is situated on a hill sloping to
                    the south-west; swamps of a depth impenetrable in summer or winter surround it,
                    formed by the ponding of rivers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The citadel
                    Phacus projects like an island from the swamp itself, where it comes nearest the
                    city, and is set on an embankment, a huge construction designed to bear the
                    weight of a wall and remain undamaged by the water of the surrounding swamp.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At a distance it appears to be joined to
                    the city wall, but it is separated by a river within the walls and likewise
                    connected by a bridge, so that there is no approach for a besieger from without
                    nor is there any escape for anyone imprisoned by the king within, except over a
                    very easily guarded bridge. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The royal treasury
                    was located there; but at that time nothing was found except the three hundred
                    talents which had been sent to King Gentius and then withheld. <pb n="p.243"/>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> During the days in camp at Pella, numerous
                    embassies <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        168</note> were received which came, especially from Thessaly, to offer
                    congratulations. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Then on receiving the news
                    that Perseus had crossed to Samothrace, the consul set out from Pella and
                    arrived at Amphipolis on the fourth day's march. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The pouring out of the entire populace to meet him showed
                    to any one that Paulus had not robbed them of a just and good king. . . <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Lost at this point is the account of
                        Paulus' entry into Amphipolis and his subsequent march to the eastward, cf.
                        XLV. iv. 2. </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
