<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>History of Rome, books 21-45 - 44</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rev. Canon Roberts</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.7 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation by</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">1</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>English Translation</resp>
                                <name>Rev. Canon Roberts</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York, New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>E. P. Dutton and Co.</publisher>
                                <date>1912</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/26/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Jason Bates</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: liv.rob_eng2.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2013-09-13 11:20:31  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.1  2009-12-01 18:17:55  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.6  2009/07/17 16:01:55  rsingh04
major fixes to Livy texts. separated english from latin in loeb texts, added separate abbs for each book since texts do not have all the books.  got rid of views because they didn't work well and were a pain.  things should not link up between different texts much better

Revision 1.5  2008/11/14 22:05:52  lcerrato
fixing author names for consistent sorting

Revision 1.4  2008/11/14 20:52:40  rsingh04
updated titles

Revision 1.3  2008/11/14 18:45:59  lcerrato
fixed dup books 27, added header for book 28 and book 21 (found online)

Revision 1.2  2006/10/04 13:29:19  gcrane
small mods

Revision 1.1  2006/09/02 14:04:03  gcrane
copies of the xlation without any automagically added sections

Revision 1.1  2006/04/28 02:13:21  gcrane
added HEADs for individual books

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:55:30  packel
Added to repository. Passed SGML parse.
                </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="book">
                <head>Pydna and the Fall of Macedonia</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the beginning of the following spring,
                        the consul Q. Marcius Philippus arrived in Brundisium with the 5000 men who
                        were to reinforce his legions. M. Popilius, an ex-consul, and a number of
                        young men of equally noble birth, followed the consul as military tribunes
                        for the legions in Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> C. Marcius
                        Figulus, who was to command the fleet, reached Brundisium at the same time,
                        and he and the consul left Italy together. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        The following day they made Corcyra, the next day Actium, the seaport of
                        Acarnania. The consul landed at Ambracia and proceeded by land to Thessaly.
                        Figulus sailed past Leucatas and entered the Gulf of Corinth. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Leaving his ship at Creusa he hurried on through
                        the middle of Boeotia-a one day's march for a lightly-equipped soldier-to
                        join the fleet at Chalcis. A. Hostilius was at the time in a camp near
                        Palaepharsalus in Thessaly. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He had not
                        fought any important action but he had checked the licence and disorder of
                        his soldiers and brought them up to a state of complete military efficiency,
                        and he had been consistently honourable in his conduct towards the allies
                        and protected them from all injustice and oppression. On hearing of the
                        arrival of his successor he made a careful inspection of the arms, the men
                        and the horses, and went to meet the consul with his army in complete
                        equipment. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Their first meeting was quite
                        in accord with their rank and their character as Romans, and subsequently
                        they worked in perfect harmony as long as the proconsul stayed with the
                        army. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> A few days later the consul addressed his
                        troops. He first alluded to Perseus's contemplated assassination of his
                        father, and his actual murder of his brother, and then went on to describe
                        how, after his <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> crimes had secured him the crown, he had
                        recourse to poisoning and bloodshed; how he laid an infamous plot against
                        Eumenes, inflicted injuries against the people of Rome, and plundered the
                        cities of the allies of Rome in violation of the existing treaty. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> He would find out in the ruin of his fortunes
                        how hateful all this conduct was to the gods, for the gods bestowed their
                        favour on natural affection and honourable dealing; it was by these that the
                        Roman people gained their lofty position in the world. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He next drew a comparison between the strength of Rome,
                        embracing as she does the world, and the strength of Macedonia, army against
                        army. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> "How much greater," he exclaimed,
                        "were the forces of Philip and Antiochus, and yet they were shattered by
                        armies no stronger than ours today." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After kindling the spirits of his men by
                        speeches of this kind, he consulted his staff on the strategy of the war. C.
                        Marius, the praetor, who had taken over the command of the fleet, was also
                        present. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They decided not to waste any
                        more time in Thessaly, but to go forward at once into Macedonia, and the
                        praetor was to make <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> a naval attack on
                        the enemy's coast at the same time. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                        consul issued orders for the soldiers to take a month's supply of corn. Ten
                        days after taking over the command of the army he broke up the camp, and at
                        the end of the first <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> day's march he
                        called the guides together and told them to explain to the council what
                        route each of them would choose. After they had withdrawn he asked the
                        council to say which they thought best. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        Some preferred the route through the Pythian Pass; others were in favour of
                        the road over the Cambunian Range which the consul Hostilius had taken the
                        previous year; others again chose the road by Lake Ascuris. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> All these routes had a considerable section in common;
                        the further discussion was therefore adjourned until they reached the point
                        where they began to diverge. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> From there he
                        marched into Perrhaebia and went into camp between Azorus and Doliche, to
                        hold a second consultation as to the best route to take. During this time
                        Perseus had heard that the enemy were approaching, but did not know which
                        route they were taking. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He decided to
                        occupy all the passes, and sent 10,000 light infantry under Asclepiodotus to
                        hold a peak in the Cambunian Range-its local name is Volustana. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> At a fortified place above Lake Ascuris, called
                        Lapathus, Hippias with 12,000 Macedonians was posted to defend the pass.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Perseus himself with the rest of his
                        force formed an entrenched camp at Dium. And here it would almost seem as if
                        his reasoning faculties were benumbed and he <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> was destitute of all resource, for he used to start
                        from his camp at Dium with an escort of light cavalry, and gallop to
                        Heraclea or to Phila, returning at the same speed to Dium. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the meanwhile the consul had made up
                        his mind to march through the pass near Ottolobus, where as already stated
                        the king's forces were; 4000 men were nevertheless sent on in advance to
                        occupy suitable positions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were under
                        the command of M. Claudius and Q. Marcius, the consul's son. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> The whole of the force followed very soon
                        afterwards. The road, however, was so steep and rough and stony that the
                        light troops in advance had, with great difficulty, covered only fifteen
                        miles when they formed their camp and rested at a place called Dierum.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the following day they advanced
                        seven miles and after seizing some rising ground not far from the enemy's
                        camp, they sent word to the consul that they had reached the enemy, and had
                        established themselves in a safe and extremely advantageous position, so
                        that he might follow at such speed as he could. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The messenger found the consul at Lake Ascuris in a
                        state of anxiety about the difficulties of the route upon which he had
                        entered and also about the fate of those few troops whom he had sent in
                        advance to the positions occupied by the enemy. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He was greatly relieved at hearing the message sent
                        him, and marching on with his main body reunited the whole of his force and
                        encamped in an admirable position on the slopes of the hill already
                        occupied. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Its height was such that it
                        commanded a view not only of the enemy's camp, which was not more than a
                        mile distant, but of the whole of the country up to Dium and Phila and the
                        far-extended line of the sea coast. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        soldiers' spirits rose when they saw the whole weight of the war, the entire
                        military strength of the king and the hostile country so near them.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They pressed the consul to lead them
                        at once against the enemy, but he allowed them one day's rest after the
                        toils of the march. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The next day, leaving
                        a detachment to guard the camp, he led them out to battle. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Hippias had recently been sent by the king
                        to guard the pass, and as soon as he caught sight of the Roman camp on the
                        hill he prepared his men for battle and marched to meet the enemy's column
                        as it advanced. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans went into the
                        fight in light equipment; the enemy force, too, consisted of light infantry;
                        these troops are the readiest to commence an action. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> When the two bodies met they at once discharged their
                        missiles; many wounds were inflicted in their random charges, a few were
                        killed. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The following day they engaged in
                        a more exasperated temper and in great strength, and had there been more
                        space in which to deploy their lines a decisive action might have been
                        fought. The summit of the mountain narrows into a wedge-shaped ridge which
                        hardly allows a front to be formed of three men abreast. So while the actual
                        fighting was carried on by a few, the rest, especially the heavy infantry,
                        stood and watched it. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The light infantry
                        were able to run forward through the dips in the ridge and attack the flanks
                        of the enemy's light infantry, both where the ground was favourable and
                        where it was not. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Night put an end to the
                        battle in which more had been wounded than killed. </p>
                    <p> The next day the Roman commander was at a loss what to do. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> To stay on the bare mountain height was impossible; it
                        was equally impossible for him to retreat without loss of honour and even
                        without danger should the enemy attack him from the higher ground. There was
                        only one course left, to carry through the adventure with the same rashness
                        with which he had entered upon it; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> a
                        policy which the result sometimes proves to be a wise one. Matters had come
                        to this-if the consul had had an enemy like the old kings of Macedonia he
                        might have incurred a crushing defeat. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Whilst, however, Perseus was riding with his cavalry along the coast at Dium
                        and heard twelve miles away the noise and clamour of the fighting, he did
                        not strengthen his line by sending fresh men to replace those who had borne
                        the burden of the combat, nor, what was most important of all, did he
                        himself appear on the field. And yet the Roman commander, more than sixty
                        years old and very stout, was discharging personally all the duties of a
                        soldier with unflagging energy. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To the
                        very last he showed the same splendid audacity as he had at the beginning.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Leaving Popilius to hold the summit
                        he made preparations to cross the ridge and sent men to clear a way where
                        before there was not even a track. Attalus and Misagenes with their two
                        contingents were told off to protect the pioneers. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> The cavalry and baggage formed the front part of the
                        column, the consul with his legions followed. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It is impossible to describe the toil and
                        difficulty they experienced in descending the mountain, with the baggage and
                        animals and their packs perpetually falling. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> They had hardly gone four miles when the one thing they desired above all
                        else was to return if possible to their starting point. The elephants caused
                        almost as much confusion in the line as the enemy might have done; when they
                        came to places which could not be crossed they flung their drivers off and
                        created great alarm, especially among the horses, by their appalling roar,
                        until a plan was devised for getting them across. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The steepness of the slope was measured and two long
                        stout poles were firmly fastened in the ground at the bottom of it somewhat
                        wider apart than the breadth of the animal. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> On the top of the poles a cross-beam was fastened and with their ends
                        resting on this beam, balks 30 feet long were fastened together so as to
                        form a bridge, and then covered with earth. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> A short distance away another similar bridge was constructed, and then a
                        third, and so on wherever the descent was precipitous. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The elephant went from the solid ground on to the
                        bridge, and just before he reached the lower end of it the poles were cut
                        away and the bridge subsided down to the beginning of the next bridge below
                        it. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The elephants were thus compelled to
                        slide quietly down, some on their feet, some on their haunches. When the
                        level of the next bridge was reached. the lower end was made to fall in the
                        same way and the elephants were carried down until they reached more level
                        ground. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Romans advanced little more than seven
                        miles that day. Very little of this was done on their feet; their mode of
                        progression was for the most part to roll down with their arms and the other
                        things they had to carry in a most uncomfortable and painful manner; so much
                        so indeed that even their general himself who was responsible for the
                        expedition admitted that the entire army could have been annihilated by a
                        small body of assailants. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At nightfall
                        they came to a small plain shut in on all sides. They had at last reached a
                        place which afforded them a sure foothold, but they had not much time for
                        looking round and seeing how exposed the position was. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The next day they had to wait in this valley for
                        Popilius and the detachment left with him, and these men, though the enemy
                        nowhere threatened them, found a most troublesome enemy in the difficulties
                        of the descent. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The army, once more
                        united, marched the next day through the pass called by the natives
                        Callipeuce. From there the march was as rough and difficult as before, but
                        they had learnt by experience and were in a more hopeful mood because the
                        enemy nowhere showed himself, and they were approaching the sea. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> When they had descended into the level country
                        between Heracleum and Libethrum, they formed their camp. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The greater part of the infantry were on rising ground;
                        that part of the plain where the cavalry had their tents was enclosed with
                        the rest by the rampart. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The king was having his bath when news was
                        brought of the approach of the enemy. On hearing it he sprang in a panic
                        from his seat and rushed out, exclaiming that he was conquered without a
                        battle. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Amidst distracted plans and
                        contradictory orders he sent two of his ''friends", the one to Pella to
                        throw into the sea the treasures that were stored at Phacus, the other to
                        burn the fleet. He recalled Asclepiodotus and Hippias and their troops from
                        the places they were occupying, and left all the approaches to Macedonia
                        open to the enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> All the gilded statues
                        were carried off from Dium to prevent their falling into the hands of the
                        enemy, and the inhabitants were forced to remove to Pydna. Thus what might
                        have been thought recklessness on the part of the consul in advancing to a
                        place from which he could not retreat, had the enemy chosen to stop him, was
                        actually made to look like a carefully-planned-out act of daring. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans had two passes through which they
                        might emerge from their present position: <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        one through Tempe into Thessaly, the other past Dium and into Macedonia; and
                        both were held by the king's troops. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If,
                        therefore, there had been an intrepid general who could have held out for
                        ten days against what at first sight looked like a steadily advancing
                        danger, there would have been no retreat open to the Romans through Tempe
                        into Thessaly, nor any possibility of carrying supplies through; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> for the pass of Tempe is a difficult one to
                        traverse, even if it is not occupied by an enemy. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In addition to the narrowness of the road which for
                        five miles affords scanty footing for a loaded animal, there are on both
                        sides sheer cliffs, so precipitous that you cannot look down without feeling
                        dizzy. The noise and depth of the Peneus flowing through the middle of the
                        ravine adds to the stern and forbidding effect. This district, so strong by
                        nature, was held by detachments of the king's troops at four different
                        places. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> One was posted at the mouth of the
                        pass at Gonnus; a second in Condylus, an impregnable stronghold; <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> a third at Lapathus, which they call Charax; a
                        fourth on the road itself in the middle of the narrowest part of the valley.
                        where ten men could easily make a successful defence. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The conveyance of supplies and their own
                        return through Tempe were thus alike cut off, and they would have had to
                        make their way back to the mountains over which they had come. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> They had escaped the observation of the enemy
                        before; they could not do so now with his troops posted on the commanding
                        heights, and the difficulties they had experienced destroyed all hopes.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> There was no course left in this rash
                        adventure but to go through the midst of the enemy and enter Macedonia by
                        way <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> of Dium, and this, if the gods had
                        not deprived the king of his reason, would have been a task of enormous
                        difficulty. The spurs of Mount Olympus leave only a width of a mile between
                        the mountain and the sea. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Half this space
                        is filled by the broad marshes at the mouth of the Baphyrus, the rest of the
                        ground is taken up either by the temple of Jupiter or the town itself. The
                        little bit that is left could be blocked by a small fosse and rampart, and
                        there was such a quantity of stones and growing timber at hand that a wall
                        might have been thrown up and turrets raised. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> Blinded by the suddenness of the danger, the king took
                        none of these things into consideration; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        he withdrew his garrisons, leaving every place open and defenceless, and
                        fled to Pydna. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul saw in the foolish and cowardly
                        conduct of his enemy the strongest assurance of safety for himself and his
                        army, and the bright prospect of final victory. Orders were despatched to
                        Sp. Lucretius at Larisa to seize the strongholds round Tempe which the enemy
                        had abandoned and Popilius was sent forward to reconnoitre the passes round
                        Dium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When he found that the country was
                        clear in every direction he made an advance, and after marching for two days
                        arrived at Dium. He ordered the site for the camp to be marked out just
                        under the temple in order that the sanctity of the place might in no way be
                        violated. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On entering the place he found
                        that though it was not large, it was, nevertheless, so adorned by public
                        buildings and a whole multitude of statues, and so strongly fortified, that
                        it was difficult to believe there was not some sinister motive behind the
                        purposeless abandonment of so much wealth and splendour. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> After spending a day in thoroughly exploring the
                        neighbourhood, he resumed his advance, and in the belief that there would be
                        an abundant supply of corn in Pieria, he marched as far as the River Mitys,
                        and the next day to Agassae. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                        population surrendered this city to him, and with the view of making a
                        favourable impression on the rest of the Macedonians, he contented himself
                        with demanding hostages, and left the city without stationing a garrison and
                        promised that the citizens should be exempt from tribute and live under
                        their own laws. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another day's march
                        brought him to the River Ascordus, where he encamped. As he found that the
                        further he advanced from Thessaly the greater was the difficulty of
                        obtaining any supplies whatever, he returned to Dium, and there was no doubt
                            <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> in any one's mind as to what they
                        would have had to endure had they been cut off altogether from Thessaly,
                        seeing that it was not safe to march any distance from it. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> Perseus assembled all his troops together with their
                        generals and severely censured the commandants of the
                        garrisons-Asclepiodotus and Hippias most of all. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> He declared that they had handed over the keys of
                        Macedonia to the Romans, but no one could more justly be charged with this
                        than he himself. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When the consul descried
                        the fleet out at sea, he quite hoped that the ships were bringing supplies,
                        for provisions were extremely dear and the supply almost exhausted. But from
                        those who had already entered the harbour he learnt that the cargo ships had
                        been left behind at Magnesia. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Whilst he
                        was quite undecided what to do-for he had to contend with the difficulties
                        of the situation quite apart from anything the enemy might do to aggravate
                        them-a despatch was handed to him from Sp. Lucretius stating that he had
                        discovered that the strongholds commanding the Vale of <milestone n="12??"
                            unit="section"/> Tempe, and those in the neighbourhood of Phila, all
                        held abundance of corn and of other necessary supplies. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul was highly delighted at
                        receiving this information and marched from Dium to Phila that he might
                        strengthen the garrison there, and at the same time distribute the corn to
                        his men, as the supplies were being so slowly brought up. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> This movement provoked comments that were anything but
                        favourable. Some said he retreated through fear of the enemy, because had he
                        remained in Pieria he would have had to give battle. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Others held that unaware of the perpetual changes of
                        fortune, he had thrown away the opportunities which presented themselves,
                        and let slip through his fingers what it would very soon be impossible to
                        recover. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For the evacuation of Dium woke
                        up his enemy, who then for the first time realised the necessity of
                        recovering what had been previously lost through his own fault. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> When he heard of the consul's withdrawal he
                        returned to Dium, repaired what had been shattered and devastated by the
                        Romans, replaced the battlements which had been shaken down, strengthened
                        the walls in all directions, and finally fixed his camp on the other bank of
                        the Elpeus. This river is an extremely dangerous one to cross, and it served
                        to protect his camp. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It rises on Mount
                        Olympus; in summer it is a narrow brook, but when swollen by winter storms
                        it rushes over the boulders in enormous eddies and washing out the earth at
                        the bottom and carrying it down to the sea, it forms whirlpools of great
                        depth, and the continual hollowing out of the channel leaves the banks
                        precipitous on both sides. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As Perseus
                        believed that the advance of the enemy would be arrested by this river, it
                        was his intention to spend the rest of the summer there. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The consul meanwhile sent Popilius with 2000 men from
                        Phila to Heracleum. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This place is about
                        five miles distant from Phila, midway between Dium and Tempe, and is
                        situated on a cliff which overhangs the river. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Before Popilius commenced the assault he
                        tried to induce the magistrates and chief men to test the good faith and
                        clemency of the Romans rather than their strength. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> His appeal made no impression on them, for they saw the
                        fires in the distance of the king's camp by the Elpeus. Then the attack
                        began in earnest, by land and also by sea-for the fleet was moored off the
                        shore-by direct assault as well as by the employment of siege engines and
                        artillery. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some young Romans turned their
                        training in the Circus games to purposes of war and in this way seized the
                        lowest portion of the wall. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Before the
                        extravagant habit came in of filling the Circus with animals from all parts
                        of the world, it was the practice to devise various forms of amusement, as
                        the chariot and horse races were over within the hour. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Amongst other exhibitions, bodies of youths, numbering
                        generally about sixty, but larger in the more elaborate games, were
                        introduced fully armed. To some extent they represented the maneuvers of an
                        army, but their movements were more skilful and resembled more nearly the
                        combat of gladiators. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After going through
                        various evolutions, they formed a solid square with their shields held over
                        their heads, touching one another; those in the front rank standing erect;
                        those in the second slightly stooping; those in the third and fourth bending
                        lower and lower; whilst those in the rear rank rested on their knees. In
                        this way they formed a testudo, which sloped like the roof of a house.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> From a distance of fifty feet two
                        fully armed men ran forward and, pretending to threaten one another, went
                        from the lowest to the highest part of the testudo over the closely locked
                        shields; at one moment assuming an attitude of defiance on the very edge,
                        and then rushing at one another in the middle of it just as though they were
                        jumping about on solid ground. </p>
                    <p> A testudo formed in this way was brought up against the lowest part of the
                        wall. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the soldiers who were mounted
                        on it came close up to the wall they were at the same height as the
                        defenders, and when these were driven off, the soldiers of two companies
                        climbed over into the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The only
                        difference was that the front rank and the files did not raise their shields
                        above their heads for fear of exposing themselves; they held them in front
                        as in battle. Thus they were not hit by the missiles from the walls, and
                        those which were hurled on the testudo rolled off harmlessly to the ground
                        like a shower of rain from the roof of a house. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Now that Heracleum was taken, the consul encamped
                        there, apparently with the intention of marching to Dium and, after driving
                        the king from there, on to Pieria. But he was already making his
                        preparations for wintering, and ordered roads to be constructed for the
                        transport of supplies <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> from Thessaly,
                        suitable places for storing corn to be selected and houses to be built where
                        those who brought up the supplies could be lodged. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Perseus had recovered from his panic,
                        he began to wish that his commands had not been obeyed, when in his hurry he
                        ordered his treasure at Pella to be thrown into the sea and the naval
                        arsenal at Thessalonica to be burnt. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        Andronicus, who had been sent for that purpose to <milestone n="3??"
                            unit="section"/> Thessalonica, had delayed carrying out his orders and,
                        as it happened, left the king time for repentance. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Nicias was not so cautious and had thrown that part of
                        the money which was lying at Phacus overboard, but the mistake proved to be
                        not irremediable, for almost the whole was fished up by divers. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> The king was so ashamed of his fright that he
                        ordered the divers to be secretly put to death, and the same fate overtook
                        Andronicus and Nicias, in order that no one alive might know anything about
                        his insane orders. C. Marcius sailed with his fleet from Heracleum to
                        Thessalonica and disembarking armed forces on many points along the coast
                        devastated the country far and wide. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                        engaged successfully the troops who hurried out of the city and drove them
                        back in hasty flight to the shelter of their walls. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He was now creating alarm in the city itself, but the
                        citizens placed artillery of all kinds on the walls, and not only those who
                        ventured near the walls but even the men on board were hit by the stones
                        which hurtled from their engines. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        troops were accordingly ordered again on board and the siege of Thessalonica
                        was abandoned. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They sailed thence to
                        Aelia, about fifteen miles distant, lying opposite to Pydna, and possessing
                        a fertile soil. After devastating this district they coasted along as far as
                        Antigonea. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Here they went ashore and
                        carried off a considerable amount of plunder to the ships. While thus
                        engaged they were attacked by a composite force of Macedonian infantry and
                        cavalry, who put them to flight and pursued them down to the shore, killing
                        some 500 of them and taking quite as many prisoners. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> Finding themselves prevented from gaining the safe
                        shelter of their ships, the very necessity of their situation rekindled the
                        courage of the Romans, and under the incentives of shame and despair they
                        renewed the fight on the beach. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The men
                        in the ships helped them and about 200 Macedonians were slain and an equal
                        number were taken prisoners. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The fleet sailed on to the territory of
                        Pallene where they went ashore to plunder. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        This district, by far the most fertile of all those on the coast along which
                        they had sailed, belonged to Cassandrea. Here Eumenes, who had sailed from
                        Elaea, met them with twenty decked ships, and five had also been sent by
                        Prusias. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This accession of strength
                        emboldened the praetor to attempt the capture of Cassandrea. This city was
                        built by Cassander on the narrow isthmus which connects the district of
                        Pallene with the rest of Macedonia, and is washed on one side by the
                        Toronaic Gulf and on the other by the Gulf of Macedonia. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The tongue of land on which it stands projects into the
                        sea, forming a promontory equal in extent to the towering Mount Athos. In
                        the direction of Magnesia it has two headlands; the larger one is called the
                        Posideum, the smaller the Cape of Canastra. The attack was commenced on two
                        sides. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Roman commander, at a place
                        called Clitae, carried his lines through from the Macedonian to the Toronaic
                        Gulf and hedged them with forked poles to cut off all communication with the
                        north. On the other side there was a canal, and here Eumenes was operating.
                        The Romans had a very heavy task in filling up a fosse which Perseus had
                        recently excavated for the defence of the town. The praetor, seeing no heaps
                        lying about anywhere, enquired where the earth out of the fosse had been
                        carried. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some arches were pointed out to
                        him which had been built, not up to the thickness of the old wall, but to
                        that of a single brick. The consul formed the design of breaking through
                        these and penetrating into the city, and he thought he might do this
                        unobserved, if the scaling parties assaulted the walls elsewhere and called
                        off the defenders to these threatened points. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The garrison of Cassandrea consisted of a far from
                        contemptible force of able-bodied townsmen, and in addition 800 Agrianes and
                        2000 Illyrians sent by Pleuratus from Peneste, all keen fighters. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Whilst these were defending the walls where the
                        Romans were doing their utmost to surmount them, the brickwork of the arches
                        was broken down in a moment and the city laid open. If those who had made
                        the breaches had been armed, they would have taken the place at once.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> When the soldiers heard that this had
                        been effected, they were so delighted that they raised a sudden cheer and
                        prepared to break into the city at various points. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> For a moment the enemy wondered what this
                        sudden cheer meant. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Then, on learning that
                        the city lay open, the commandants of the garrison, Pytho and Philip,
                        thinking that this would be an advantage to whichever side was the first to
                        attack, made a sortie with a strong body of Agrianes and Illyrians and
                        charged the Romans who were coming up from all sides and were massing with
                        the intention of entering the city in regular formation. Unable to present a
                        firm front or proper line of battle, they were routed and pursued as far as
                        the fosse, into which they were driven headlong, and lay in heaps.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Nearly 600 were killed there, and
                        almost all who were caught between the wall and the fosse were wounded.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His attempt thus recoiling on himself
                        made the praetor somewhat slow in forming other plans. Eumenes, too, who was
                        making a combined attack by land and sea, was equally unsuccessful.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It was decided therefore to post
                        strong detachments on both sides of the city to prevent any succour being
                        introduced from Macedonia, and then, as direct assault had failed, to
                        commence a regular siege. Whilst they were preparing for this, ten swift
                        ships belonging to Perseus's fleet were sent up from Thessalonica with a
                        picked force of Gaulish mercenaries on board. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> When they caught sight of the Roman fleet standing out
                        to sea, they waited till the depth of night, and then sailing in single line
                        they made for the nearest point on which to disembark, and so entered the
                        city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The news of this addition to the
                        defence compelled Eumenes and the Romans to raise the siege. Sailing round
                        the promontory they brought up at Torone. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        This place, too, they prepared to attack, but on finding that there was a
                        strong body of defenders they gave up the attempt and shaped their course to
                        Demetrias. On approaching the walls they saw that they were fully manned, so
                        they sailed on to Iolcus, intending after devastating the district to attack
                        Demetrias from that side. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In order that he might not remain
                        perfectly inactive in the enemy's country, the consul sent M. Popilius with
                        5000 men to attack Meliboea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This city
                        lies on the lower spurs of Ossa, looking towards Thrace and in a position to
                        command Demetrias. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At first the appearance
                        of the enemy dismayed the inhabitants, but on recovering from their alarm,
                        they flew to arms and ran to the gates and walls, wherever they suspected
                        that an entrance might be forced, and in this way put an end to any hopes
                        that the city might be taken at the first assault. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Preparations were accordingly made for a regular siege
                        and the construction of the necessary works was commenced. Perseus heard
                        that Meliboea was being attacked by the consul's army and that the fleet was
                        lying off Iolcus, preparatory to an attack on Demetrias. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He sent one of his generals, a man called Euphranor,
                        with a picked force of 2000 men to Meliboea. This officer was ordered, in
                        case he cleared the Romans away from Meliboea, to make a secret march to
                        Demetrias and enter the city before the Romans advanced against it from
                        Iolcus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> His sudden appearance on the
                        ground above the Roman lines created great alarm amongst the besiegers of
                        Meliboea; their works were abandoned and burnt. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The siege of the one city being raised, Euphranor
                        hurried on to Demetrias. In the night . . . not only the walls . . . but
                        even their fields they felt sure could be protected from ravages. They made
                        sorties and attacked the scattered groups of plunderers, not without
                        wounding many of them. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> However, the
                        praetor and Eumenes rode round the walls, examining the situation of the
                        city, to see if they could not make an attempt somewhere, either by
                        siege-works or by storm. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was a
                        rumour that negotiations for the establishment of friendly relations between
                        Perseus and Eumenes had been carried on by Cydas of Crete and Antimachus,
                        the governor of Demetrias. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> At all events,
                        the Romans withdrew from Demetrias. Eumenes sailed away to visit the consul,
                        and after congratulating him upon his successful invasion of Macedonia, went
                        home. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The praetor sent part of his fleet
                        to Sciathus to lie up for the winter; with the rest of his ships he steered
                        for Oreum in Euboea, as he considered that city the most suitable base from
                        which supplies could be sent to the armies in Macedonia and Thessaly.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Very different accounts are given of
                        Eumenes. If you are to believe Valerius Antias, the praetor received no
                        assistance from his fleet, though he had often written for his co-operation,
                        and further, when he left for Asia, he was not on good terms with the
                        consul, nor could the consul induce him to leave behind the Gaulish cavalry
                        whom he had brought with him. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Valerius
                        goes on to say that Eumenes's brother Attalus remained with the <milestone
                            n="14??" unit="section"/> consul, was unswervingly loyal to him and
                        rendered splendid service in the war. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the Macedonian war was going on,
                        envoys from a Transalpine Gaulish chieftain Balanos-his name is given but
                        not that of his tribe-went to Rome with promises of assistance in the war.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Thanks were accorded to them by the
                        senate, and presents sent to their chief-a golden chain, two pounds in
                        weight, and four golden bowls, each weighing one pound, a horse with all its
                        trappings, and a complete set of equestrian armour. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The Gauls were followed by a deputation from Pamphylia,
                        who brought into the senate-house a golden crown made out of 20,000
                        "philippei," and begged that they might be allowed to place it as an
                        offering in the shrine of Jupiter Optimus Maximus in the Capitol. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> Permission was granted, and the senate also
                        acceded to their request for a renewal of the league of friendship with
                        Rome; they each received a present of 2000 ases. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> An audience was then granted to envoys from Prusias,
                        and shortly afterwards to those from Rhodes. Both embassies dealt with the
                        same subject, but on very different lines; they both pleaded for peace with
                        Perseus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The tone of Prusias's
                        representatives was one of entreaty rather than demand. Prusias declared
                        that he had stood by the Romans up to that time, and would continue to do so
                        as long as the war lasted, but when envoys from Perseus approached him with
                        the object of bringing the war with Rome to an end he had promised to
                        intercede for him with the senate. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He
                        begged them, if they could make up their minds to lay aside their
                        resentment, to look favourably upon him as the instrument of procuring
                        peace. Such was the appeal which the king's envoys made. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Rhodians were far less deprecatory.
                        They enumerated the services they had rendered to the people of Rome, and
                        practically claimed the greater share in the victory over Antiochus at all
                        events. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Whilst there was peace between
                        Macedonia and Rome, friendly relations were formed between them and Perseus.
                        Much against their will they had broken off that friendship, without his
                        having done anything to deserve such treatment, because the Romans had
                        thought good to draw them as allies into the war. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> For three years they had been suffering many of the
                        evils of war; the sea had been closed to them, and without supplies by sea
                        their island was in a state of destitution. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> They could not put up with this state of things any longer, and had
                        therefore sent to Macedonia to inform Perseus that the Rhodians wished him
                        to come to terms with Rome, and they had sent their envoys on a similar
                        mission to Rome. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Rhodians would
                        consider how they would have to act against those who prevented the war from
                        being brought to a close. I am quite certain that even today such language
                        cannot be read or heard without a deep feeling of indignation. <milestone
                            n="13" unit="section"/> It can then be imagined what the state of mind
                        of the senators was as they listened to it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> According to Claudius no reply was
                        vouchsafed to them, but the decree of the senate was read over, in which the
                        people of Rome made an order that Caria and Lycia should be free States, and
                        it was decided that this decree should be at once transmitted to both
                        nations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On hearing this the leader of the
                        legation, whose boastful language the House had a few moments before hardly
                        been able to endure, fell down in a state of collapse. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Other writers assert the reply they received was to the
                        following effect: At the outset of the war the Roman people had ascertained
                        on trustworthy evidence that the Rhodians had been forming secret designs in
                        conjunction with Perseus against the Republic, <milestone n="4??"
                            unit="section"/> and if there had been any doubt as to this before, the
                        language of the envoys had now reduced it to a certainty. Dishonest dealing,
                        even if at the beginning it has been somewhat cautious, generally betrays
                        itself in the long run. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The Rhodians were
                        now acting as arbitrators of peace and war over the whole world; the Romans
                        were to take up and lay down their arms at the beck and nod of Rhodes; it
                        was no longer the gods who were to be invoked as the witnesses and guardians
                        of treaties, but the Rhodians. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Was this
                        really so? Unless they obeyed the orders of Rhodes and withdrew their armies
                        from Macedonia, were the Rhodians going to consider what steps to take?
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> What steps they would take the
                        Rhodians knew best, but the people of Rome would consider, after Perseus had
                        been crushed, and they hoped that time was not far off, what recompense they
                        should make to each State according to its deserts in that war. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> However, a present of 2000 ases was sent to each
                        of the delegates, but they refused to accept it. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next thing was a despatch from the
                        consul Q. Marcius, which was read in the senate, describing his march over
                        the mountains and his invasion of Macedonia. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Supplies had been accumulated there and drawn from other places against
                        the winter, and he had received from the Epirots 20,000 modii of wheat and
                        10,000 of barley on the understanding that the money for that corn should be
                        paid to their agents in Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Clothing for
                        the soldiers would have to be sent from Rome; about 200 horses were needed,
                        mainly for the Numidians; he had no chance of getting them in the country
                        where he was. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate made an order
                        that everything should be carried out in accordance with the consults
                        requirements. The praetor C. Sulpicius contracted for the supply of 6000
                        togas, 30,000 tunics and 200 horses to be transported to Macedonia and
                        delivered to the consul, subject to his approval. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> He also paid the Epirot representatives for the corn
                        and introduced to the senate Onesimus the son of Pytho, a Macedonian of high
                        rank, who had always urged peaceful counsels on the king and advised him to
                        keep up the custom, which his father Philip had observed to the last days of
                        his life, of reading over twice daily the text of his treaty with Rome, or
                        if he could not always do so, to do it frequently. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> When he saw that he could not deter him from war, he
                        gradually withdrew himself on various pretexts from attendance on the king
                        so that he might not be involved in proceedings which he did not approve of.
                        At last, when he found that he had aroused suspicion and that now and again
                        charges of treason were brought against him, he went over to the Romans and
                        became extremely useful to the consul. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On his introduction to the senate he
                        mentioned these circumstances, and the senate made an order for him to be
                        formally enrolled amongst the allies, quarters and free hospitality to be
                        provided for him, 200 jugera of the State domain in the Tarentine district
                        to be allotted to him, and a house to be purchased for him in Tarentum. The
                        praetor C. Decimius was charged with the execution of this order. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> On December 13 the censors revised the roll of
                        burgesses more strictly than on the last occasion. Many of the equites were
                        degraded; amongst them P. Rutilius who, as tribune of the plebs, had shown
                        so much bitterness in prosecuting them. He was now expelled from his tribe
                        and registered among the aerarii. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On a
                        resolution of the senate, half the proceeds of the year's revenue was
                        assigned to them by the quaestor for the construction of public works.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Out of the sum allotted to him
                        Tiberius Sempronius purchased for the State the dwelling-house of P.
                        Africanus behind the "Old Shops" by the statue of Vertumnus, together with
                        the butchers' stalls and the booths adjoining. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> He also signed a contract for the construction of the
                        building afterwards known as the Basilica Sempronia. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now near the end of the year and as
                        men's thoughts were mainly preoccupied with the Macedonian war, there was
                        much discussion as to whom they were to choose as consuls for the year to
                        bring the war to a close. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate
                        accordingly passed a resolution that Cneius Servilius should come to hold
                        the elections as soon as possible. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        praetor Sulpicius forwarded the resolution to the consul and a despatch was
                        received from him a few days later which he read to the senate, in which he
                        said that he would come to the City on . . . The consul arrived in good time
                        and the elections were held on the day fixed. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The new consuls were L. Aemilius Paulus for the second
                        time, fourteen years after his first consulship, and C. Licinius Crassus.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The election of praetors followed.
                        Anxiety about the Macedonian war stimulated the senate to expedite all their
                        business. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They desired the consuls
                        designate to ballot for their provinces immediately, so that as soon as it
                        was known to which consul Macedonia <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> was
                        allotted, and which praetor was to command the fleet, they might at once
                        form their plans and make every preparation for the war, and in case the
                        necessity arose, refer any question to the senate. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> When they had entered upon office, the magistrates were
                        to celebrate the Latin Festival at the earliest date which the religious
                        observances connected with it allowed, in order that nothing might detain
                        the consul who was to go to Macedonia. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        Macedonia fell to Aemilius, the other consular province was Italy and that
                        fell to Licinius. The praetors' provinces were assigned as follows: Cn.
                        Baebius received the civic and L. Anicius the alien jurisdiction; the latter
                        was to be at the disposal of the senate for any special service. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> Cn. Octavius took the command of the fleet, P.
                        Fonteius went to Spain, M. Aebutius to Sicily, and C. Papirius to Sardinia.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It very soon became clear to everybody
                        that L. Aemilius was not going to show any lack of energy in the prosecution
                        of the war; amongst other proofs of this was the exclusive attention he gave
                        night and day to everything that had to do with it. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The very first thing he did was to ask the senate to
                        send a commission to Macedonia to inspect the armies and the fleet and to
                        report from their own personal knowledge what was required for the land and
                        sea forces. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They were also to find out
                        what they could about the king's troops and how much of the country was
                        under our control and how much under the king's, and whether the Romans were
                        still encamped in mountainous and difficult country, or whether they had
                        cleared all the passes and reached open country. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Then with regard to our allies they were to ascertain
                        who were still faithful, who were making their fidelity depend upon the
                        issue of the war, and what States were openly hostile. They were further to
                        find out what amount of supplies had been accumulated; from what sources
                        further supplies could be brought by land or sea; and what were the results
                        of the year's campaign by land and sea. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        When accurate information on these points had been received, it would be
                        possible to form definite plans for the future. The senate authorised the
                        consul Cn. Servilius to send as commissioners into Macedonia those whom L.
                        Aemilius approved of. Those selected were C. Domitius Ahenobarbus, A.
                        Licinius Nerva, and L. Baebius. They started in two days' time. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> As the year was closing, reports came in of two
                        showers of stones: one in the Roman district, the other on Veientine ground.
                        Intercessions and sacrifices were offered for nine days on each occasion.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Two members of the priesthood died
                        this year: P. Quinctilius Varus, a Flamen of Mars, and M. Claudius
                        Marcellus, a keeper of the Sacred Books. Cn. Octavius was appointed in his
                        place. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It has been noted as a sign of the
                        increasing scale on which the Circus games were conducted that in those of
                        the curule aediles P. Cornelius Scipio Nasica and P. Lentulus, sixty-three
                        African panthers and forty bears and elephants formed part of the show. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The new consuls, L. Aemilius Paulus and C.
                        Licinius, entered on their duties at the beginning of the year, March 15.
                        The senate were mainly anxious to know what the consul who was to command in
                        Macedonia had to report about his province. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> Paulus said that he had nothing to lay before them, as the commissioners
                        had not yet returned; after being twice driven out of their course back to
                        Dyrrhachium they were now at Brundisium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        When he had received the necessary information, which would be in a very few
                        days. he would make his report. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That
                        nothing might delay his departure, he had fixed the Latin Festival for April
                        12. When the sacrifice had been duly performed, he and Cn. Octavius would go
                        as soon as the senate authorised their departure. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> In his absence it would be his colleague's care to see
                        that whatever had to be prepared or despatched to the war would be got ready
                        and sent off. Meantime the foreign deputations could be received in
                        audience. </p>
                    <p> The first to be called in were the envoys from the two monarchs, Ptolemy and
                        Cleopatra. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were in mourning garb with
                        beard and hair untrimmed, and when they entered the House holding the olive
                        branch of supplication, they prostrated themselves to the ground. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Their language was even more piteous than their
                        dress. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Antiochus, king of Syria, who had
                        been in Rome as a hostage, was now, under the specious pretext of restoring
                        the elder Ptolemy to his throne, waging war against his younger brother and
                        was threatening Alexandria at the time. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He
                        had won a naval victory off Pelusium, and after hurriedly throwing a bridge
                        over the Nile he had led his army across, and was terrifying Alexandria with
                        the prospect of a siege, and it seemed almost certain that he would gain
                        possession of the powerful realm of Egypt. After stating these facts the
                        envoys implored the senate, to come to the assistance of the kingdom and its
                        rulers, who were friends of Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They
                        urged that the kindness which the Roman people had shown to <milestone
                            n="11??" unit="section"/> Antiochus and their authority amongst all
                        kings and nations were such that if they sent word to him and informed him
                        that the senate disapproved of war being levied against monarchs who were
                        their friends, he would at once quit the walls of Alexandria and take his
                        army back to Syria. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> If the senate
                        hesitated to do this, they would soon have Ptolemy and Cleopatra coming as
                        fugitives from their realm, and the Roman people would feel somewhat ashamed
                        at not having sent them help in their extremity. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The senators were much moved by the appeal of the
                        Alexandrians, and at once sent C. Popilius Laenas, C. Decimius and C.
                        Hostilius to put an end to the war between the monarchs. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> They were instructed to approach Antiochus first and
                        then Ptolemy, and announce to them that if they did not abstain from war
                        they should not regard the one who was responsible for its continuance as
                        either a friend or an ally. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Roman delegates accompanied by the
                        Alexandrians left in three days' time. On the last day of the Quinquatrus
                        the commissioners arrived from Macedonia. Their return had been so anxiously
                        awaited that had it not been in the evening the consuls would at once have
                        convened the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The next day the
                        senate gave them audience. They reported that the passage of the army over
                        pathless mountains had resulted in more peril than profit. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> They had advanced into Pieria, but the king was holding
                        the country, and the armies were in such close contact that only the River
                        Enipeus separated them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The king did not
                        give any opportunity of fighting, nor were our men strong enough to force a
                        battle; winter, too, had stopped active operations; our men were living in
                        idleness, and had not corn for more than six . . . The Macedonians were said
                        to number 30,000 fighting men. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If Appius
                        Claudius had had a strong enough army at Lychnidus, the king might have had
                        his attention distracted between two fronts; at the present moment, Appius
                        and such force as he had with him were in the utmost danger, unless either a
                        regular army was sent there without delay, or they were withdrawn from their
                        present position. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On leaving the camp they
                        proceeded to the fleet. Here they learnt that some of the crews had been
                        carried off by disease, some, mostly the Sicilian seamen, had gone home, and
                        the ships were undermanned; the men who were in them had not received their
                        pay and were without proper clothing. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        Eumenes and his fleet had come and gone without any apparent reason, just as
                        though they had been carried there by the wind; no dependence could be
                        placed on that king. Whilst all Eumenes's movements were doubtful, Attalus
                        was behaving with exemplary fidelity. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the commissioners had been heard, L.
                        Aemilius said that the question before the House was the conduct of the war.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate decreed that the consuls
                        and the people should each appoint an equal number of military tribunes for
                        the eight legions, but they wished that none should be appointed that year
                        who had not held high office; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> L. Aemilius
                        was to choose out of the whole number those whom he wished for the two
                        legions in Macedonia, and when the Latin Festival was over the consul and
                        Cn. Octavius, the praetor who was to command the fleet, should leave for
                        their respective commands. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In addition to
                        these, L. Anicius, who had the alien jurisdiction, was to go to Illyria and
                        succeed Appius Claudius in command at Lychnidus. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The task of raising fresh troops was imposed on the
                        consul C. Licinius. He was ordered to enrol 7000 Roman citizens and 200
                        cavalry, and from the Latin allies 7000 infantry and 400 cavalry. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> He was also to send written <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> instructions to Cn. Servilius in Gaul, requiring him to
                        enrol 600 cavalry. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was to send this new
                        army as soon as possible to his colleague in Macedonia. In that province
                        there were not more than two legions: they were each to be brought up to the
                        full strength of 6000 infantry and 300 cavalry; <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> the rest of the infantry and cavalry were to be
                        distributed amongst the various garrisons; those who were unfit for military
                        service were to be discharged. There were, in addition, the 10,000 infantry
                        and 800 cavalry furnished by the allies. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        This force was supplementary to the two legions, each consisting of 5000
                        infantry and 300 cavalry, which Anicius was ordered to transport to
                        Macedonia; 5000 seamen were also conscripted for the fleet. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> Licinius was ordered to hold his province with
                        the two legions and the 10,000 infantry and 800 cavalry from the allies.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the senate had made all these
                        arrangements, the consul L. Aemilius left the House and proceeded to the
                        Assembly, where he delivered the following speech: <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> "I think, Quirites, that my having received, through
                        the ballot, Macedonia as my province has been greeted more warmly than when
                        I was congratulated on my election as consul, or on the day when I entered
                        on office. And the sole reason for this, I believe, is that you thought I
                        could be the means of bringing this long-protracted war to such a close as
                        shall be worthy of the greatness of Rome. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                        I hope that the decision of the ballot has been regarded with favour by the
                        gods also, and that they will aid me in executing the task before me.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Some things I can prognosticate,
                        others I can feel hopeful about. This I venture to affirm with absolute
                        certainty-I will strive to the utmost of my power, that the hopes you have
                        formed of me shall not turn out to be vain. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                        /> All measures necessary for the war the senate has already taken, and as
                        they have decided that I must start immediately, and there is nothing to
                        hinder me, my distinguished colleague, C. Licinius, will carry out those
                        measures with as much energy as if he himself were going to conduct the war. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "What I write to the senate or to you, I
                        ask you to believe, and not strengthen, by giving credence to them, the idle
                        rumours of which no one will confess himself the author. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> For it is a common experience, and I have noticed it
                        especially in this war, that no one can be so indifferent to public opinion
                        as not to find his courage and energy influenced by it. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In all public places where people congregate, and
                        actually-would you believe it! in private parties, there are men who know
                        who are leading the armies into Macedonia, where their camps ought to be
                        placed, what strategical positions ought to be occupied, when and by what
                        pass Macedonia ought to be entered, where the magazines are to be formed, by
                        what mode of land and sea transport <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/>
                        supplies are to be conveyed, when actions are to be fought, and when it is
                        better to remain inactive. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And they not
                        only lay down what ought to be done, but when anything is done contrary to
                        their opinion they arraign the consul as though he were being impeached
                        before the Assembly. This greatly interferes with the successful prosecution
                        of a war, for it is not everybody who can show such firmness and resolution
                        in the teeth of hostile criticism as Fabius did; he preferred to have his
                        authority weakened by the ignorance and caprice of the people rather than
                        gain popularity by disservice to the State. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                        /> I am not one of those who think that generals are not to be advised; on
                        the contrary, the man who always acts on his own initiative shows, in my
                        judgment, more arrogance than wisdom. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> How
                        then does the case stand? Commanders ought first of all to get the advice of
                        thoughtful and far-seeing men who have special experience of military
                        affairs; then from those who are taking part in the operations, who know the
                        country and recognise a favourable opportunity when it comes, who, like
                        comrades on a voyage, share the same dangers. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> If, then, there is any man who in the interests of the
                        commonwealth feels confident that he can give me good advice in the war
                        which I am to conduct, let him not refuse to help his country, but go with
                        me to Macedonia. I will supply him with a ship, a horse, a tent, and with
                        his travelling expenses as well. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> If
                        anyone thinks this too much trouble, let him not try to act as a sea pilot
                        whilst he is on land. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The city itself
                        affords plenty of subjects for conversation, let him confine his loquacity
                        to these; he may rest assured that the discussions in our councils of war
                        will satisfy us." <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> After delivering this
                        speech and offering the customary sacrifice on the Alban Mount at the Latin
                        Festival on March 31, the consul left, in company with the praetor, for
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> It is recorded that the consul
                        was escorted by an unusually large crowd of well-wishers, and that people
                        predicted with hopeful confidence the near close of the Macedonian war and
                        the early return and brilliant triumph of the consul. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these proceedings in Italy, Perseus
                        could not make up his mind to carry out his project of gaining Gentius, king
                        of the Illyrians, as an ally, as he would have to spend money in so doing.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But when he found that the Romans had
                        cleared the passes and that the supreme crisis of the war was at hand, he
                        felt that this business ought not to be put off any longer. Through Hippias,
                        who acted for him, he agreed to pay a sum of 300 silver talents on condition
                        that hostages were exchanged on both sides. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Pantauchus, one of his closest friends, was sent to complete the
                        transaction. Pantauchus met the Illyrian king at Meteon in the district of
                        Libea, and there he received the king's sworn word and the hostages.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Gentius sent as his representative a
                        man called Olympius to claim from Perseus his sworn word and the hostages.
                        Men were sent with him to receive the money, and at the suggestion of
                        Pantauchus, Parmenio and Morcus were selected to accompany them to Rhodes.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Their instructions were not to go to
                        Rhodes till they had received the king's sworn word and the hostages, as at
                        the request of both kings the Rhodians might be induced to declare war
                        against Rome. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The adhesion of that nation,
                        whose naval reputation was then at its height, would, it was supposed, leave
                        the Romans no hope of victory either on sea or land. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Perseus went from his camp by the Elpeus with all his
                        cavalry, and met the Illyrians at Dium. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                        There, with the cavalry drawn up all round them, the contracting parties
                        ratified the covenant between them, Perseus thinking that their presence at
                        this solemn ratification would give them fresh courage. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Then the hostages were exchanged in the sight of all;
                        those who were to receive the money were then sent to the royal treasury at
                        Pella; those who were to accompany the Illyrian envoys to Rhodes received
                        instructions to embark at Thessalonica. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Metrodorus, who had recently come from Rhodes, was there, and he asserted on
                        the authority of Dinon and Polyaratus, leading men in the city, that the
                        Rhodians were prepared for war. He was appointed head of the joint
                        Macedonian and Illyrian legation. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the same time some considerations,
                        suggested by the political conditions of the time, were submitted in common
                        to Eumenes and Antiochus. Perseus reminded them that free commonwealths and
                        monarchs are in the nature of things antagonistic. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Rome was attacking them one by one, and what was still
                        worse, kings were using their power against kings. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> His own father had been crushed by the help of Attalus;
                        the attack on Antiochus had been made with the assistance of Eumenes and, to
                        some extent, of his own father Philip; now Eumenes and Prusias were in arms
                        against himself. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If royalty were abolished
                        in Macedonia, Asia would be the next. They had already become masters of
                        some parts of it under the pretext of making the cities free. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> Then Syria's turn would come. Prusias was now
                        held in higher honour than Eumenes, and Antiochus was kept out of the Egypt
                        which he had conquered-the prize of war. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        He urged them to reflect on these things, and either insist upon the Romans
                        making peace with him, or else regard those who persisted in carrying on an
                        unjust war as the common enemies of all kings. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> The communication to Antiochus was sent openly, the
                        emissary to Eumenes was sent ostensibly to arrange for the ransom of the
                        prisoners. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As a matter of fact, more
                        clandestine negotiations were going on, which for the time aroused suspicion
                        and ill-will against Eumenes amongst the Romans, and still graver, though
                        unfounded, charges were made against him, for he was regarded as a traitor
                        and a declared enemy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There was a Cretan
                        called Cydas, an intimate friend of Eumenes. This man went with a certain
                        Chimarus, a country man of his, who was serving under Perseus, to
                        Amphipolis, then afterwards to Demetrias, where he held conversations under
                        the actual walls of the city, first with Menecrates and then with
                        Antimachus, both of them generals of Perseus. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> Hierophon also, who was the emissary on this occasion,
                        had previously been on two missions to Eumenes. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> These secret missions and colloquies were notorious,
                        but what had actually taken place, or what agreement had been come to
                        between the monarchs, was not known. The facts were these. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Eumenes was not eager for Perseus to be
                        victorious, nor had he any intention of helping him in the war, not so much
                        because of the differences he had with his father as because of personal
                        aversion he and the son felt for each other. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> The jealousy of the two monarchs was such that Eumenes would not have
                        seen with complacency Perseus winning such an accession of power and glory
                        as would have awaited him had he defeated the Romans. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He knew also that from the very beginning of the war
                        Perseus had tried every means of gaining peace, and the nearer the danger
                        the more his actions and thoughts were, day and night, turned to this
                        object. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As regarded the Romans, he
                        believed that since the war had dragged on longer than they expected, both
                        their generals and the senate would not be averse from bringing to a close
                        such a tedious and difficult war. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Having
                        thus discovered what both sides wished for, he was all the more desirous of
                        winning their good graces by offering for a consideration his assistance
                        towards securing what he believed would come about of itself through the
                        weariness of the stronger and the fears of the weaker side. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> He fixed his price in the one case for not lending
                        assistance to the Romans either by land or sea, and in the other for
                        mediating peace. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For refusing assistance
                        he asked 1000 talents, for bringing about peace, 1500. Impelled by his fears
                        Perseus was very prompt in commencing negotiations and made no delay in
                        discussing the question of hostages; it was settled that those whom he
                        received should be sent to Crete. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But when
                        it came to the mention of money he drew back and said that a money payment
                        for another object would, between monarchs of so great a name, <milestone
                            n="9??" unit="section"/> be in any case sordid and unbecoming both to
                        him who made it and him who accepted it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        Still in the hope of obtaining peace with Rome he did not grudge the
                        expense, though he would only hand over the money when the transaction was
                        completed; meanwhile he would deposit it in the temple at Samothrace.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As that island belonged to Perseus,
                        Eumenes saw that it made no difference whether it were there or at Pella,
                        and he proposed to carry away a portion at once. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Thus after trying unsuccessfully to trick each other
                        they gained nothing but an evil name. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This was not the only chance which Perseus
                        threw away in his avarice. Had he paid the money, it is possible that he
                        might have had peace through Eumenes's instrumentality, and this was worth
                        purchasing even at the cost of a part of his kingdom, or if Eumenes had
                        played him false he could have <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> held him
                        up as his enemy loaded with his gold, and made the Romans regard him justly
                        as their enemy. But the alliance with Gentius which had been already mooted
                        and the invaluable support now offered of the Gauls who were pouring through
                        Illyria, were both lost to him through his avarice. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> A body of 1000 cavalry came to offer their services,
                        and with them the same number of foot soldiers. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> These latter used to run alongside the horses and when
                        the trooper fell they seized the riderless horses and rode on them into the
                        battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These men had agreed to serve for
                        ten gold pieces for each horseman and five for each footman; their leaders
                        were to receive a thousand. Perseus went with half his whole force from his
                        camp at the Elpeus and began to give notice through all the villages and
                        cities adjoining their route that they were to prepare ample supplies of
                        corn, wine and cattle. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He took with him
                        some horses with their trappings and some military cloaks as presents to
                        their officers, and a <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> small quantity of
                        gold to be distributed amongst a few of the troops, trusting that the mass
                        of the soldiery would be attracted by the hope of more. He went as far as
                        the city of Almana and fixed his camp by the River Axius. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The Gaulish army was lying in the neighbourhood of
                        Desudaba in Maedica waiting for the stipulated pay. Perseus sent Antigonus,
                        one of the nobles of his Court, to order the soldiers to shift their camp to
                        Bylazora, a place in Paeonia, and their officers to go in a body to him.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They were seventy-five miles distant
                        from the king's camp on the Axius. After Antigonus had given them these
                        orders and told them what an abundance of everything the king's care had
                        provided for them on their line of march, and what presents of clothing and
                        silver and horses the king had ready for the officers when they <milestone
                            n="10??" unit="section"/> arrived, they replied that they would find out
                        all about this on the spot. They then enquired whether they had brought the
                        gold to be distributed according to the agreement amongst the horse and
                        foot. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> To this there was no reply. Then
                        their chief Claudicus said, "Go back! Tell the king the Gauls will not move
                        a step further unless they receive the gold and the hostages." <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> On this being reported to the king he held a
                        council of war. When it became obvious what the unanimous decision would be,
                        the king began to descant on the perfidy and savagery of the Gauls, vices
                        which many had already experienced to their ruin. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> It was a dangerous thing to admit so vast a multitude
                        into Macedonia; they might find them more troublesome as allies than the
                        Romans as enemies; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> 5000 cavalry were
                        quite enough to make use of in the war, and not too many to be dangerous.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was quite clear to every one that the
                        only thing the king was afraid of was having to pay such a large host, and
                        as no one had the courage to attempt to dissuade him, Antigonus was sent
                        back to say that the king would only employ 5000 of their cavalry and would
                        not detain the rest. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When the barbarians
                        heard this, there were murmurs of indignation from the rest of the army at
                        having been called away from their homes to no purpose. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Claudicus again enquired whether he would pay the
                        stipulated sum to the 5000. He detected something evasive in the answer and
                        sent the crafty messenger back unhurt-treatment which the man himself hardly
                        ventured to hope for. The Gauls returned to the Hister, devastating those
                        parts of Thrace which lay near their line of march. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> This band might have been led against the Romans
                        through the mountain pass of Perrhaebia into Thessaly while the king
                        remained quiet at the Elpeus, and could not only have plundered and stripped
                        the fields so that the Romans could have looked for no supplies from those
                        districts, but also have utterly destroyed the cities to prevent their
                        affording any assistance to their allies, while Perseus was holding the
                        Romans <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> at the Elpeus. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> The Romans would have had to think of their own safety,
                        for they could not have stayed where they were when Thessaly which fed their
                        army was lost, nor could they have made any advance with the camp of the
                        Macedonians in front of them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> By losing
                        such an opportunity Perseus encouraged the Romans and discouraged to a great
                        extent the Macedonians who had hung their hopes on his taking advantage of
                        it. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The same niggardly conduct turned Gentius
                        against him. After he had paid 300 talents to the emissaries of Gentius at
                        Pella, he allowed them to seal the money up. Then ten talents were sent to
                        Pantauchus with instructions that they were to be given to the king at once.
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He told his people, who were carrying
                        the rest of the money sealed with the seal of the Illyrians, to make
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> short journeys, and when they had
                        reached the frontier, to wait there for his instructions. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> After Gentius had received that small portion of the
                        money, he was constantly being urged by Pantauchus to provoke the Romans by
                        some hostile act; accordingly he threw the two Roman envoys into prison, who
                        happened to be with him at the time, M. Perpenna and L. Petilius. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> On hearing this, Perseus thought that Gentius
                        was, in any case, driven by the force of circumstances into war with Rome,
                        and in this belief he sent a message to have the money brought back, as
                        though his one idea was that after his defeat as much spoil as possible
                        might be reserved for the Romans. Hierophon returned from Eumenes without
                        any one knowing what secret understanding had been arrived at between them.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They themselves gave it out in public
                        that it had to do with the exchange of prisoners, and Eumenes sent the same
                        explanation to the consul to allay his suspicions. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Seeing how his schemes had miscarried,
                        Perseus sent his two naval commanders, Antenor and Calippus, with forty
                        swift ships and five cutters to Tenedos to protect the corn ships which were
                        making their way <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> to Macedonia through
                        the scattered groups of the Cyclades. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                        ships took the water at Cassandrea, in the two harbours under Mount Athos,
                        and from there sailed to Tenedos in a calm sea. Some undecked vessels
                        belonging to Rhodes were lying in the harbour and Eudamus, their commander,
                        was allowed to take them away unharmed, as though they were friends.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On learning that fifty of his
                        transports on the other side of the island were blockaded by the war-galleys
                        of Eumenes which were stationed at the entrance to the harbour, Antenor
                        promptly sailed round and the enemy ships made off on his appearance.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Ten swift ships were told off to
                        escort the transports to Macedonia, and when they had seen them safe they
                        were to return to Tenedos. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Eight days
                        afterwards they rejoined the fleet which was now anchored off Sigeum. From
                        here they sailed to Sabota, an island situated between Elaea and Chios.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The day after they arrived,
                        thirty-five vessels called "hippagogi," carrying Gaulish horses and
                        troopers, happened to be on their way from Elaea to Phanae, a headland in
                        Chios, intending to sail from there to Macedonia. They were sent to Attalus
                        by Eumenes. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When Antenor received a signal
                        that these ships were at sea, he started for Sabota and met them in the
                        narrowest part of the channel between the headland of Erythrae and Chios.
                        The last thing that Eumenes's officers expected was the appearance of a
                        Macedonian fleet cruising in those waters. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                        They first thought that they were Romans and then that it was Attalus or
                        some that had been sent back by Attalus from the Roman camp and were on
                        their way to Pergamum. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But when the build
                        of the approaching vessels could no longer be mistaken and the prows
                        steering straight for them at increasing speed revealed the approach of an
                        enemy, there was great alarm. The clumsy nature of their ships and the
                        difficulty of keeping the Gauls quiet, destroyed all hope of resistance.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Some of those who were nearer to the
                        mainland swam to Erythrae; others crowded on all sail and ran their ships
                        aground in Chios, and, abandoning the horses, fled in wild disorder towards
                        the city. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> But the Macedonian vessels,
                        taking a shorter course, landed their marines nearer the city and some of
                        the Gauls were cut down as they fled along the road, others outside the city
                        gate. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Chians had closed their gates,
                        not knowing who were fleeing and who were pursuing. Nearly 800 Gauls were
                        killed and 200 made prisoners. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Some of
                        the horses in the wrecked ships were drowned; others were hamstrung by the
                        Macedonians on the beach. There were twenty horses of exceptional beauty,
                        and Antenor gave orders for the ten vessels which he had previously sent to
                        carry these and the prisoners to Thessalonica and return as soon as
                        possible; he should wait for them at Phanae. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> The fleet lay off Chios for three days and then sailed
                        to Phanae. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The ten ships returned sooner
                        than was expected; the whole fleet then put out to sea and sailed across the
                        Aegean to Delos. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During these operations the Roman
                        commissioners, C. Popilius, C. Decimius and C. Hostilius, left Chalcis with
                        three quinqueremes and arrived at Delos. There they found the forty vessels
                        belonging to the Macedonians and five quinqueremes belonging to Eumenes.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The sanctity of the temple and the
                        island prevented them from injuring one another. The Romans, the Macedonians
                        and the crews from Eumenes' ships went about together in the city and the
                        temple in the peaceful security of a locality sacred and inviolate.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Antenor received a signal from the
                        look-out that several transports were sailing past. He started in pursuit
                        with some of his ships and dispersed the rest among the Cyclades. He either
                        sunk or plundered them all, with the exception of those heading for
                        Macedonia. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Popilius tried to save all he
                        could, both of his own ships and those of Eumenes, but <milestone n="5??"
                            unit="section"/> the Macedonian barques sailed by night, two or three
                        together, and so escaped observation. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        About this time the Macedonian and Illyrian envoys arrived in Rhodes. Their
                        representations had all the more weight owing to the appearance of the
                        Macedonian ships cruising amongst the Cyclades and in the Aegean, the united
                        action which Perseus and Gentius were taking, and the rumour that the Gauls
                        were coming with a large force of infantry and cavalry. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Dinon and Polyaratus, the leaders of Perseus' faction,
                        felt themselves now strong enough to send a favourable reply to the two
                        monarchs, and even went so far as to proclaim publicly that they possessed
                        sufficient authority to put an end to the war, the kings themselves
                        therefore <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> must resign themselves to the
                        acceptance of peace terms. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was now the beginning of spring, and
                        the new generals had reached their provinces. The consul Aemilius was in
                        Macedonia, Octavius with the fleet at Oreum, and Anicius was in Illyria to
                        conduct the war against Gentius. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                        father of Gentius was Pleuratus, formerly king of Illyria; his mother's name
                        was Eurydice. Gentius had two brothers, one named Plator, the other, a
                        half-brother, named Caravantius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He felt
                        no uneasiness about the latter, as the father was a man of low birth, but to
                        make his throne more secure he put Plator to death, and two of his friends
                        with him, Ettritus and Epicadus, both of them able and enterprising men.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was commonly said that his jealousy
                        was aroused by Plator's betrothal to Etuta, a daughter of Monunus, the
                        prince of the Dardani, as though by this marriage he would secure the whole
                        nation to his interest, and the fact that after Plator's death his brother
                        married the girl made this conjecture highly probable. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> When all fear of his brother was removed, Gentius began
                        to harass and oppress his people, and his naturally violent temper was
                        inflamed by excessive indulgence in wine. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        However, as I have said above, he was bent upon war with Rome, and assembled
                        the whole of his forces at Lissus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They
                        numbered 15,000 men. He sent his brother Caravantius with 1000 infantry and
                        500 horse to effect the subjugation of the Cavii, either by intimidation or
                        force, whilst he himself advanced against Bassania, a city five miles
                        distant from Lissus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The population were
                        friendly to Rome, and when Caravantius sent a demand for submission they
                        chose to stand a siege rather than surrender. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> One of the towns belonging to the Cavii, Durnium,
                        opened its gates to Caravantius; another city, Caravandis, shut its gates
                        against him, and when he began an extensive devastation of their fields the
                        peasants rose and killed a considerable number of the scattered plunderers. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By this time Appius Claudius, who had
                        strengthened the army he had with him by contingents from the Ballini, the
                        Apolloniates and the Dyrrhachians, had left his winter quarters and was
                        encamped near the River Genusus. The intelligence brought to him of the
                        league between Perseus and Gentius, and the outrageous treatment of the
                        Roman envoys, decided him to commence hostilities against him. <milestone
                            n="11" unit="section"/> The praetor Anicius, who was at this time in
                        Apollonia, heard what was going on in Illyria, and sent a message to Appius
                        requesting him to wait for him by the Genusus. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> In three days he arrived at the camp and brought with
                        him in addition to his own force 2000 infantry and 200 cavalry, sent by the
                        Parthini, the infantry under the command of Epicadus, the cavalry under that
                        of Algalus. He was making preparations to march into Illyria, his principal
                        object being the raising of the siege of Bassania. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> The projected invasion was delayed by a report that
                        eighty pirate barques were ravaging the coast. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> They had been sent by Gentius on the advice of
                        Pantauchus to devastate the fields of Apollonia and Dyrrhachium. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> Then the fleet . . . they surrendered. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> One after another the cities in that part
                        of the country took the same course; their natural inclinations were
                        strengthened by the clemency and justice with which the Roman praetor
                        treated them all. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He marched on to Scodra,
                        the most important place in the war. Gentius had selected it as the
                        stronghold, so to speak, of his kingdom, and it was by far the most strongly
                        fortified and most difficult of access of any place in the country of the
                        Libeates. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It is surrounded by two rivers,
                        the Clausal on the eastern side and the Barbanna, which rises in the
                        Libeatus Lake, on the west. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> These two
                        rivers meet and flow into the Oriundis, which rises in Mount Scordus and,
                        augmented by many tributaries in its course, empties itself into the
                        Hadriatic. Mount Scordus is quite the loftiest mountain in the country, and
                        overlooks Dardania on the east, Macedonia on the south, and Illyria on the
                        west. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Although the town was protected by
                        its situation and defended by the whole strength of Illyria under the king
                        himself, the Roman praetor determined to attack it. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> His first operations had been successful, and he
                        believed that the same good fortune would carry him through, and that the
                        alarm created by his sudden appearance would have its effect. Had the gates
                        been kept shut and the defenders stationed on the walls and towers, the
                        attempt would have failed and the Romans would have been driven away from
                        the walls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As it was, however, they made a
                        sortie from the gate, and they began a <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/>
                        battle on open ground with more courage than they kept it up. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> They were driven back, and more than 200 men were
                        killed as they squeezed together in their flight through the confined space
                        of the gate. This created such a panic that Gentius at once sent two of the
                        foremost men in the country, Teuticus and Bellus, to the praetor to ask for
                        a cessation of hostilities, to allow him time to consider his position.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was allowed three days-the Roman
                        camp was only five miles away-and went on board ship and sailed up the
                        Barbanna to Lake Libeatus as though in quest of a retired spot for
                        reflection but, as it turned out, he had been misled by a false report that
                        his brother Caravantius was <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> approaching
                        with several thousand men, whom he had raised in the country to which he had
                        been sent. After the rumour proved groundless he went down in the same ship
                        to Scodra, and sent to ask for permission to interview the praetor.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> His request was granted and he went
                        to the camp. He began his speech by blaming his own folly, and then, falling
                        on his knees, amidst tears and supplications he placed himself entirely in
                        the hands of the praetor. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> He was told to
                        be of good courage, and even received an invitation to supper. He went back
                        to the city to see his friends, and was for that day treated with all honour
                        at the praetor's table. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The next thing
                        was his being handed over to the custody of C. Cassius, one of the military
                        tribunes, after having, himself a king, received from a king a paltry ten
                            <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> talents-hardly as much as a
                        gladiator earns-in order that he might sink into this condition. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After the capture of Scodra the first
                        thing Anicius did was to order the two envoys, Petilius and Perpenna, to be
                        found and brought to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> They were
                        provided with the clothing and insignia of their rank, and Perpenna was at
                        once sent to arrest the friends and kinsfolk of the king. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He went to Metione and brought back to the camp at
                        Scodra Etleva, the king's wife, and his two sons, Scerdilaedus and
                        Pleuratus, and also Caravantius his brother. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> Anicius had brought the war in Illyria to a close in less than a month,
                        and Perpenna was sent to Rome to announce his victory. A few days later he
                        sent Gentius to Rome, together with his mother, his wife, his children and
                        his brother, and also some of the principal men of Illyria. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> This is the only war the close of which was reported in
                        Rome before they had heard that it had begun. All through this time, Perseus
                        on his side was in a state of great alarm by the advance of the consul
                        Aemilius who, he understood, was on the march in <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> a most dangerous mood, and no less so by the forward
                        movement of Octavius with the Roman fleet menacing the coast. Eumenes and
                        Athenagoras were in command of Thessalonica with a small force of 2000
                        cetrati. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He sent Androcles there also with
                        orders to remain encamped close to the naval arsenal; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> 1000 cavalry under Creon of Antigonea were sent to
                        Aenea to guard the coast, so that at whatever point they heard the hostile
                        ships were threatening, they might at once go to the help of the country
                        folk; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> 5000 Macedonians were sent to
                        garrison Pytho and Petra under the command of Histieaus, Theogenes and
                        Midon. After they had left, Perseus set himself to fortify the bank of the
                        Elpeus, because, as the river-bed was now dry, it could easily be crossed.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To allow of the whole army being free
                        for this work, supplies of food were brought into the camp by women from the
                        neighbouring cities. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Out of the woods
                        near the soldiers were ordered . . . </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Lastly he ordered the water-carriers to
                        follow him to the sea, which was less than 300 paces distant, and to dig at
                        short intervals from each other on the shore. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> The towering height of the mountains led him to expect
                        that as no rivulets flowed from above the ground they contained hidden
                        streams which flowed as it were through veins into the sea and mingled with
                        its waters. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Hardly had the surface of the
                        sand been removed when springs bubbled up, muddy at first and scanty, but
                        they soon poured forth a clear and copious supply of water, as though it
                        were a gift from the gods. This incident added much to their general's
                        prestige and authority amongst the soldiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> Orders were then issued for the troops to get their arms ready, and the
                        consul with the military tribunes and the centurions of the first rank went
                        out to examine the place where they were to cross, where the men under arms
                        could find an easy descent, and where the ascent of the opposite bank
                        presented least difficulty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After
                        satisfying himself on these points, the consul's first care was that
                        everything should be done in an orderly fashion and without confusion, in
                        obedience to the word of command. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When an
                        order was promulgated to all the troops at the same time, it was not
                        distinctly heard by everybody, and in their uncertainty as to what had been
                        said, some made additions for themselves and went beyond what had been
                        ordered, while some did less than they were told to do. Then confused shouts
                        arose throughout the column and the enemy knew the general's intentions
                        before they did. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> He therefore gave
                        directions for the military tribunes to communicate the order privately to
                        the first centurion of the legion and he was to notify what was to be done
                        to each of the centurions, rank by rank, whether the order was to be
                        transmitted from front to rear of the column or from rear to front. He also
                        forbade the sentinels to follow the new fashion of wearing their shields; a
                        sentinel did not go into battle to make use of his arms; his duty was on
                        becoming aware of the enemy's approach to retire and call the rest to arms.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They used to stand, wearing their
                        helmets and holding their shields in front of them, and then, when they were
                        tired, they leaned on their spears, rested their heads on the rim of their
                        shields and went to sleep as they stood, so that the glitter of their armour
                        made them visible to the enemy while they themselves saw nothing in front of
                        them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He also altered the regulations with
                        regard to the outlying pickets. They used to stand all day under arms, the
                        cavalry with their horses bridled, and in the days of summer under a
                        cloudless and scorching sun, the men themselves and their horses were
                            <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> so languid and exhausted by the
                        heat after so many hours that often, when attacked by a small body of the
                        enemy who were fresh and unwearied, they were discomfited, though greatly
                        superior in numbers. He thereupon gave orders that those who were sent out
                        in the morning should quit their posts at noon and be relieved by others who
                        went on duty for the rest of the day. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In
                        this way it was never possible for a fresh and unwearied enemy to attack
                        them when they were suffering from fatigue. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After Aemilius had paraded his troops and
                        announced to them his intention of making these reforms, he went on to
                        address them on very much the same lines as in his speech to the Assembly.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He reminded them that it was the duty
                        of the commander alone to provide for the welfare of his army and to advise
                        as to what ought to be done, sometimes alone and sometimes in consultation
                        with those whom he has called into council. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> Those who were not called into council had no right to ventilate their
                        own opinions either publicly or privately. It was the soldier's duty to be
                        careful about these three things: To keep his body as strong and agile as
                        possible; to keep his arms in good order, and to have his food ready against
                        any sudden order of his commander. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All
                        other matters, he must understand, are under the care of the gods and of his
                        general. In an army where the soldiers take upon them to give advice and the
                        general is swayed by the opinions of the multitude, there is no safety.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He, as their commander, would do his
                        duty and be on the watch to give them an opportunity of fighting a
                        successful battle. It was not for them to ask what was going to happen, as
                        soon as the signal was given, it was their duty to do all that a soldier
                        could do. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With these instructions he dismissed the
                        troops, and even the veterans generally confessed that on that day they had
                        for the first time, as though they were raw recruits, learnt what military
                        service meant. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And it was not only by
                        remarks of this kind that they showed how greatly they appreciated the
                        consul's words-they began at once to act on them. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In a short time you would see no one in the camp idle;
                        some were sharpening their swords; others rubbing up their helmets and
                        cheek-pieces and their cuirasses; others fastening on their armour and
                        testing their agility under its weight; others poising their spears; others
                        again making their swords flash with rapid thrusts and keeping their eyes on
                        the point. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> So that anyone could easily see
                        that on the very first opportunity of coming to close quarters with the
                        enemy they would finish the war by a splendid victory or, in their own case,
                        by a glorious death. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Perseus, too, when
                        he saw that after the consul's arrival-it was the beginning of spring as
                        well-all was bustle and movement with the enemy as though for a fresh
                        campaign, and that the camp was shifted from Phila to the bank of the river,
                        and the consul was going on his rounds, at one time to inspect the works and
                        evidently looking out for a place where he could cross the river; at another
                        . . . </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This incident raised the spirits of the
                        Romans and produced considerable alarm amongst the Macedonians and their
                        king. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> At first he tried to stifle the
                        report by sending to Pantauchus, who was on his way to the camp, to forbid
                        him from entering it; but some boys, who were being taken away amongst the
                        Illyrian hostages, had been seen by their friends. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> So the greater the pains taken to conceal the details,
                        the more easily did they leak out through the love of gossip in the king's
                        Court. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Just after this the envoys from
                        Rhodes arrived at the Roman camp bringing with them the same demand for
                        peace which had so roused the ire of the Roman senate. They received a much
                        more hostile hearing from the council of war in the camp. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> Some thought they ought to be driven helter-skelter out
                        of the camp; the consul said he would give them an answer in a fortnight's
                        time. Meanwhile, to make it clear how far the influence of the Rhodians
                        extended in their efforts to bring about peace, he began to discuss the plan
                        of operations with his council. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Some,
                        mainly the younger officers, were for crossing the Elpeus and storming the
                        opposite bank and the defensive works above it. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> After their expulsion the year before from their forts,
                        which were on higher ground, better fortified and strongly held, they
                        thought the Macedonians would be unable to stand a general attack made in
                        full force. Others were of opinion that Octavius ought to take his fleet to
                        Thessalonica and devastate the coast. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By
                        thus menacing his rear they would compel the king to divide his forces and
                        march away to protect the interior of his kingdom, thus leaving the passage
                        of the river in some direction open. The consul considered the river bank
                        insurmountable, owing to its steepness and the works which defended it,
                        especially as artillery was in position everywhere, and he had heard that
                        the enemy used their missile weapons more skillfully, and with a surer aim. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The consul had quite made up his mind to
                        adopt another course, and the council broke up. There were two Perrhaebian
                        traders, Coenus and Menophilus, whose honesty and sagacity he knew he could
                        trust. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He sent for them and questioned
                        them privately about the routes leading into Perrhaebia. They told him that
                        the country was not difficult; it was held by detachments of the king's
                        troops. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Hearing this he thought that by a
                        sudden night attack delivered in force, when the enemy were not expecting
                        it, they could be dislodged and driven back. Javelins and arrows and other
                        missiles were useless in the dark, when it was impossible to see what to aim
                        at; it was in close hand-to-hand fighting with the sword, in the melee of
                        battle, that the Roman soldier was victorious. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> He decided to take these men as guides, and sent for
                        Octavius, to whom he explained his plans, and he gave him instructions to
                        sail to Heracleum and have in readiness ten days' rations for 1000 men.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> P. Scipio Nasica and Q. Fabius
                        Maximus, his own son, were sent overland to Heracleum with 5000 select
                        troops, as though they were going on board the fleet to devastate the
                        Macedonian coast-the scheme which had been advocated in the council.
                            <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> They were privately informed that, to
                        avoid any delay, there was food ready for these troops on board the fleet.
                        The two guides were then ordered so to regulate the length of each day's
                        march as to allow of an attack being made on Pythium in the fourth watch of
                        the third day. </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> To prevent the king from directing his
                        attention elsewhere, the consul, at dawn on the following day, commenced an
                        action with the enemy's outposts in the middle of the river-bed, and the
                        fighting was kept up by the light infantry on both sides; heavier troops
                        could not possibly fight on such uneven ground. <milestone n="16"
                            unit="section"/> From the top of each bank down to the river-bed was
                        about 300 paces; the actual channel of the river between the banks, which
                        varied in depth, was over a mile wide. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        There in mid-channel the fight went on, the king watching it from his
                        intrenchments on the one side and the consul from the rampart surrounded by
                        his legionaries on the other. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> As long as
                        they were not in touch and could use their missiles the king's men fought at
                        an advantage, but when it came to close fighting the Roman was more steady
                        and better protected, whether by the shield or the Ligurian buckler.
                            <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> About noon the consul ordered the
                        retreat to be sounded, so the action was broken off for that day with a not
                        inconsiderable number killed on both sides. <milestone n="20" unit="section"
                        /> The next day the conflict was renewed at sunrise with even greater
                        bitterness, as their passions had been roused by the previous contest.
                            <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> But the Romans were wounded, not only
                        by those with whom they were actually fighting, but to a much greater extent
                        by the missiles of every kind which were discharged by the multitude of
                        assailants posted on the turrets, and especially by the huge stones from the
                        ballistae. Whenever they got nearer to the bank held by the enemy the
                        discharges from the catapults reached even the hindmost. After losing far
                        more on that day, the consul recalled his men somewhat later than the day
                        before. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> On the third day he abstained
                        from fighting and went down to the lowest part of the camp, as if to attempt
                        a passage through that part of the enemy's line, which was carried down to
                        the sea. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> . . . </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was past the summer solstice and the
                        time of day was approaching noon; the march had been made amidst clouds of
                        dust and under a burning sun. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Lassitude
                        and thirst were already felt, and it was certain that both would be
                        aggravated at high noon. The consul was determined not to expose his men
                        while thus suffering to an enemy who was fresh and in full vigour.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But such was the eagerness of the men
                        for battle under any circumstances that it needed as much skill on the part
                        of the consul to beguile his own men as to deceive the enemy. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The battle line was not completely formed, and he
                        urged the military tribunes to hasten its formation; he rode round the ranks
                        and fired the spirits of the men by his words. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> On this they at first eagerly demanded the signal for
                        battle; then under the increasing heat their faces showed less animation and
                        their voices became weaker; some hung over their shields and propped
                        themselves up with their spears. Now at last he gave the order to the
                        centurions of the first rank to mark out the front line for a camp and to
                        deposit the baggage. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the soldiers
                        became aware of what was happening, some openly expressed their delight that
                        he <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> had not compelled them to fight,
                        exhausted as they were with the toilsome march and the intense heat.
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The staff officers and the commandants
                        of the foreign contingents, Attalus amongst them, were standing round the
                        commander-in-chief and unanimously approving of what they thought was his
                        decision, namely, to give battle. Not even to them had he disclosed his
                        intention of delaying action. The sudden change of plan made nearly all of
                        them silent. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nasica alone had the courage
                        to admonish the consul not to do as former commanders had done, and by
                        avoiding battle let the enemy slip through his fingers. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> If Perseus got away in the night, he was afraid that
                        infinite trouble and danger would be incurred in following him into the
                        heart of Macedonia, and they would spend the summer as previous generals had
                        done, in feeling their way through the passes and tracks of the Macedonian
                        mountains. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He strongly advised the consul
                        to attack the enemy while he had him in level and open country, and not to
                        lose the proffered chance of victory. The consul was not at all offended at
                        the frank admonition of so distinguished a youth. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> "Nasica," he replied, "I, too, once felt as you do now,
                        and one day you will feel as I do now. I have learnt, through the many
                        accidents of war, when to fight and when to abstain from fighting.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I have no time now, standing as I am
                        at the head of the line, to explain to you why it is better to rest today.
                        Ask me for my reasons some other time; for the time being you will be
                        content to submit to the authority of a veteran commander." <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> The young man was silent; he was sure that his
                        general saw some impediments in the way of a battle which were not apparent
                        to him. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Aemilius Paulus saw that the site of
                        the camp had been marked out and the baggage <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> collected, he first quietly withdrew the triarii from
                        the back of the line, then the principes, leaving the hastati standing in
                        front, in case the enemy made any movement. Finally he retired these also,
                        withdrawing those on the right first, maniple by maniple. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> In this way the infantry were withdrawn without
                        creating any confusion, leaving the cavalry and light infantry facing the
                        enemy. The cavalry were not recalled from their position until the rampart
                        and fosse in front of the camp were carried their full length. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> The king was quite ready to give battle that day,
                        but as his men were aware that the delay was due to the enemy he was quite
                        content, and he too led his men back to camp. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> When the fortification of the camp was completed, C.
                        Sulpicius Gallus, a military tribune attached to the second legion, who had
                        been a praetor the year before, obtained the consul's permission to call the
                        soldiers on parade. He then explained that on the following night the moon
                        would lose her light from the second hour to the fourth, and no one must
                        regard this as a portent, because this <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/>
                        happened in the natural order of things at stated intervals, and could be
                        known beforehand and predicted. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Just in
                        the same way, then, as they did not regard the regular rising and setting of
                        the sun and moon or the changes in the light of the moon from full circle to
                        a thin and waning crescent as a marvel, so they ought not to take its
                        obscuration when it is hidden in the shadow of the earth for a supernatural
                        portent. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the next night-September 4-the
                        eclipse took place at the stated hour, and the Roman soldiers thought that
                        Gallus possessed almost divine wisdom. It gave a shock to the Macedonians as
                        portending the fall of their kingdom and the ruin of their nation, nor could
                        their soothsayers give any other explanation. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Shouts and howls went on in the Macedonian camp until
                        the moon emerged and gave her light. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> So
                        keen had both sides been to encounter one another that on the morrow both
                        Perseus and the consul were alike blamed by some of their own men for having
                        retired without a battle The king was at no loss for his defence-the enemy
                        had openly declined battle and was the first to withdraw his troops into
                        camp; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and, besides, the position which he
                        had chosen was such that the phalanx could not be brought up to it, even a
                        slightly uneven ground would make it useless. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> As to the consul, not only did it look as if he had let
                        slip the opportunity of fighting the previous day and given the enemy a
                        chance, if he wished, of going away in the night, but even now he seemed to
                        be wasting time on the pretext of offering sacrifice, although the signal
                        for battle had been hoisted at dawn and he ought to have taken the field.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It was not till the third hour after
                        the sacrifices had been duly performed that he summoned a council of war and
                        even then he was thought by some to be wasting the time, which ought to have
                        been spent on the battlefield, in unseasonable speeches and discussions.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul addressed the council as
                        follows: "Out of all those who were in favour of my giving battle yesterday,
                        P. Nasica, a most excellent young man, was the only one who disclosed his
                        real thoughts to me, and after that he remained <milestone n="2??"
                            unit="section"/> silent, so that it would seem that he has come over to
                        my side. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There are some others who
                        preferred to find fault with their commander behind his back rather than
                        offer their advice in his presence. I have no objection to giving my reasons
                        for delaying battle to you, Nasica, and to all who entertain the same
                        sentiments as you did, though less openly, for I am so far from regretting
                        our inaction yesterday that I believe I have saved the army through it.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> If any of you think that I have no
                        grounds for this belief, I ask him to consider with me, if he will, how many
                        things there were in the enemy's favour and to our disadvantage. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> First of all, as to his superiority in numbers, I
                        am perfectly certain that none of you were unaware how great that is and
                        especially yesterday when you watched his men deploying into line.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Out of our own scanty numbers
                        one-fourth had been left to guard the baggage, and you know that it is not
                        the least efficient who are left in charge of that. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> But supposing we had been in full force, are we to take
                        no account of the fact that we have remained undisturbed in the camp last
                        night, ready with the help of the gods to take the field this very day or,
                        at the latest, tomorrow? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Is it a matter of
                        indifference whether you order the soldier to take up his arms on a day when
                        he has not been fatigued by a toilsome march and the labour of intrenching
                        the camp, when he has been resting undisturbed in his tent, and so lead him
                        into battle full of energy and vigorous in body and mind, or whether on the
                        other hand you expose him fatigued by a long march and exhausted by the work
                        of preparing <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> the camp, with the sweat
                        pouring from him and his jaws parched with thirst, his mouth and eyes full
                        of dust, under a scorching noonday sun, to an enemy who is fresh, rested and
                        bringing into battle a strength and energy which have not been used up
                        beforehand? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Who, in heaven's name, being
                        thus prepared for battle, even though he were an utter coward, would not
                        conquer the bravest of men? After the enemy had, quite at their leisure,
                        formed their line, their minds prepared <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/>
                        for battle, and all standing in their ordered ranks, do you suppose that we
                        were then to form our line in haste and confusion and meet them when we were
                        in disorder? </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Some might say: 'Even if we had not our
                        battle line in proper formation, had we no fortified camp, no provision for
                        water, no troops to guard the access to it? Had we nothing which we could
                        call our own except the bare ground on which to fight?' <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Your ancestors looked upon a camp as a safe haven for
                        the army against every mischance, from which they went out to battle, where,
                        after being tossed in the storm of battle, they could find a safe retreat.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was for that reason that after they
                        had fenced it with earthworks, they strengthened it with a powerful guard,
                        for he who lost his camp, even if victorious on the field, was held to be
                        defeated. A camp is a resting-place for the victor, a shelter for the
                        vanquished. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> How many armies to whom the
                        fortune of battle has proved unkindly have been driven inside their ramparts
                        and then at their own time, sometimes almost immediately, have made a sortie
                        and repulsed their victorious foe? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here is
                        the soldier's second fatherland, here is his abode, with the rampart for its
                        walls; here each finds in his tent, his home and his household gods. Ought
                        we to have fought as homeless wanderers with no place to receive us after
                        our victory? </p>
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> "In reply to these difficulties and
                        hindrances it is asked, 'What if the enemy had gone off last night?' How
                        much exhausting toil should we have had to endure in following him into the
                        heart of Macedonia! <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I am perfectly certain
                        that if he had decided to depart he would not have awaited us, nor drawn up
                        his troops on the field. How much easier would it have been for him to get
                        away when we were at a distance, than it is now when we are close upon him
                        and he cannot withdraw by day or night without our becoming aware of it!
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> What could we wish for better than,
                        instead of being obliged to attack their camp in its strong position on the
                        bank of a river, fenced with a rampart and numerous towers, we attack them
                        in the rear after they have left their intrenchments and are making their
                        way in a straggling column through open country? <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> These were my reasons for postponing the battle from
                        yesterday to today, for it is my intention to give battle, and as the way to
                        the enemy across the Elpeus has been blocked by him, I have opened up a
                        fresh way by dislodging his men who were holding another pass, and I shall
                        not stop till I have brought the war to a close." </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When he had finished there was silence;
                        some had been brought round to his view; others were afraid of giving
                        needless offence by criticising the neglect of an opportunity which, to
                        whatever it might be due, could not be remedied. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> Even on this day neither the consul nor the king was
                        prepared to engage. The king would not be able to attack them as they were
                        yesterday, wearied with their march, deploying hurriedly into line and not
                        in battle order; the consul held back because neither wood nor fodder had
                        been brought into the newly-formed camp, and a large proportion of his
                        troops had left the camp to collect these from the fields near. <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> Against the intention of both commanders Fortune,
                        who overrides the plans of men, brought about a conflict. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> There was a river, not a large one, near the enemy's
                        camp from which both the Romans and the Macedonians drew their water,
                        protected by detachments stationed on either bank. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> On the Roman side were two cohorts, Marrucinians and
                        Paelignians, and two squadrons of Samnite horse under the command of M.
                        Sergius Silus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Another body was stationed
                        in front of the camp under C. Cluvius; these consisted of Firman, Vestinian
                        and Cremensian troops, and two squadrons of cavalry from Placentia and
                        Aeserna. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Whilst all was quiet at the
                        river, neither side offering any provocation, a mule broke loose about three
                        o'clock in the afternoon from the men in charge and escaped to the opposite
                        bank. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Three soldiers went after it through
                        the water, which was up to their knees. Two Thracians were dragging the
                        beast out of the river back to their own bank, when they were followed by
                        some Romans, who killed one of them, recaptured the mule, and went back to
                        their posts. There were 800 Thracians guarding the enemy's bank. <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> A few of these, enraged at seeing a comrade
                        killed before their eyes, ran across the river in pursuit of those who slew
                        him; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> then more joined in and at last the
                        whole body, and with them the . . . </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> . . . led them into battle. His men were
                        deeply impressed by reverence for his authority, the reputation he had
                        acquired, and, above all, his age, for though more than sixty years old, he
                        took upon himself to a large extent the duties and dangers which are usually
                        the lot of younger men. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The interval
                        between the "caetrati" and the divisions of the phalanx was filled up by the
                        legion, and thus the enemy's line was interrupted. The "caetrati" were in
                        their rear; the legion were fronting the shieldmen of the phalanx, who were
                        known as the "chalcaspides." <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> L. Albinus,
                        an ex-consul, was ordered to lead the second legion against the phalanx of
                        "leucaspides"; these formed the centre of the enemy's line. On the Roman
                        right, where the battle had begun, close to the river, he brought up the
                        elephants and the cohorts of allied troops. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                        /> It was here that the Macedonians first gave ground. For just as most new
                        devices amongst men seem valuable as far as words go, but when they are put
                        to a practical test and have to be acted upon they fail to produce results,
                        so it was with the elephants; those of the Macedonians were of no use
                        whatever. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The contingents of the Latin
                        allies followed up the charge of the elephants and repulsed the left wing.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The second legion which had been sent
                        against the centre broke up the phalanx. The most probable explanation of
                        the victory is that several separate engagements were going on all over the
                        field, which first shook the phalanx out of its formation and then broke it
                        up. As long as it was compact, its front bristling with levelled spears, its
                        strength was irresistible. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If by attacking
                        them at various points you compel them to bring round their spears, which
                        owing to their length and weight are cumbersome and unwieldy, they become a
                        confused and involved mass, but if any sudden and tumultuous attack is made
                        on their flank or rear, they go to pieces like a falling house. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> In this way they were forced to meet the repeated
                        charges of small bodies of Roman troops with their front dislocated in many
                        places, and wherever there were gaps the Romans worked their way amongst
                        their ranks. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If the whole line had made a
                        general charge against the phalanx while still unbroken, as the Paeligni did
                        at the beginning of the action against the "caetrati," they would have
                        spitted themselves upon their spears and have been powerless against their
                        massed attack. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The infantry were being slaughtered all
                        over the field; only those who threw away their arms were able to make good
                        their escape. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The cavalry, on the other
                        hand, quitted the field with hardly any loss, the king himself being the
                        first to flee. He was already on his way to Pella with his "sacred" cavalry,
                        and Cotys and the Odrysaeans were following at his heels. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The rest of the Macedonian horse also got away with
                        their ranks unbroken, because the infantry were between them and the enemy,
                        and the latter were so fully occupied in massacring the infantry that they
                        forgot to pursue the cavalry. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For a long
                        time the slaughter of the phalanx went on in front, flank and rear. At last
                        those who had escaped out of the hands of the enemy threw away their arms
                        and fled to the shore; some even went into the water and, stretching out
                        their hands in supplication to the men in the fleet, implored them to save
                        their lives. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> When they saw boats from all
                        the ships rowing to the place where they were they thought that they were
                        coming to take them up as prisoners rather than slay them, and they waded
                        further into the water, some even swimming. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                        /> But when they found that they were being killed by the men in the boats,
                        those who could swim back to land met with a more wretched fate, for the
                        elephants, forced by their drivers to the water's edge, trampled on them and
                        crushed them to death as they came out. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It
                        is universally admitted that never had so many Macedonians been killed by
                        the Romans in a single battle. As many as 20,000 men perished; 6000 who had
                        fled to Pydna fell into the enemy's hands, and 5000 were made prisoners in
                        their flight. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Of the victors not more than
                        100 fell, and of these the majority were Paelignians; the wounded were much
                        more numerous. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> If the battle had begun
                        earlier and there had been sufficient daylight for the victors to continue
                        the pursuit, the whole force would have been wiped out. As it was, the
                        approach of night shielded the fugitives and made the Romans chary of
                        following them over unknown country. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="43" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Perseus fled to the Pierian forest,
                        accompanied by his suite and a numerous body of cavalry. <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> When he had entered the forest at a point where several
                        roads diverged, as night was approaching he struck into a side-path with a
                        very small body of those most faithful to him. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> The cavalry, left without a leader, dispersed to their
                        various cities; and a few reached Pella in advance of Perseus himself,
                        having gone by a straight road. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Up to
                        midnight the king had considerable trouble and anxiety in trying to find his
                        way. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Eulacus and Euctus and the royal
                        pages were ready to meet the king in the gloomy palace, but of all his
                        friends who had lived through the battle and regained Pella, not one came to
                        him in spite of his repeated invitations. There were only three who shared
                        his flight, Euander of Crete, Neo a Boeotian, and Archidamus the Aetolian.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Fearing that those who refused to go
                        to him might soon venture <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> upon a more
                        serious step, he fled away at the fourth watch, followed by certainly not
                        more than 500 Cretans. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He was intending to
                        go to Amphipolis, but he had left Pella in the night, anxious to cross the
                        Axius before daylight, as he thought the difficulty of crossing that river
                        might stop the Roman pursuit. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="44" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On his return to camp the consul's joy in
                        his victory was damped by his anxiety about his younger son. <milestone
                            n="2" unit="section"/> This was P. Scipio, who had been adopted as
                        grandson by Scipio Africanus, and himself received the title of Africanus,
                        from the destruction of Carthage in after years. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> He was only seventeen at the time-a further cause for
                        anxiety-and while he was in full pursuit of the enemy, he was carried away
                        by the press into another part of the field. On his return late in the day
                        to the camp, his father, finding him safe and sound, could at last feel
                        unmixed joy in his great victory. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The news
                        of the battle had already been carried to Amphipolis, and the matrons
                        flocked to the temple of Diana-the Tauropolon-to invoke her aid. Diodorus,
                        the governor of the city, was apprehensive lest the Thracian garrison, some
                        2000 strong, should in the tumult and confusion plunder the city. He
                        therefore hired a man to impersonate a letter-carrier, and received a
                        pretended despatch from him in the middle of the forum. It stated that the
                        Roman fleet had put in at Emathia, and the fields all round were being
                        ravaged. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The officers in charge of Emathia
                        implored him to send the garrison to deal with the ravagers. <milestone
                            n="6" unit="section"/> After reading the despatch he urged the Thracians
                        to go and defend the coast of Emathia; they would inflict great slaughter on
                        the Romans while scattered through the fields, and would also secure large
                        booty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the same time he made light of
                        the report of an unfavourable battle; if, he said, it were true, fugitive
                        after fugitive would have come in fresh from the fight. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> In this way he got rid of the Thracians, and as soon as
                        he saw that they had crossed the Strymon, he shut the gates. </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Three days after the battle Perseus
                        arrived at Amphipolis, and from that city he sent heralds with a caduceus to
                        Paulus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the meanwhile Hippias, Midon,
                        and Pantauchus, the principal men among the king's friends who had fled from
                        the field of battle to Beroea, went and made their surrender to the Roman
                        consul. In the case of others also, their fears prompted them, one after
                        another, to do the same. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul sent
                        his son Q. Fabius, together with L. Lentulus and Q. Metellus, with
                        despatches to Rome announcing his victory. He gave the spoils taken from the
                        enemy's army lying on the field of battle to the foot soldiers and the
                        plunder from the surrounding country to the cavalry on condition that they
                        were not <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> absent from the camp more than
                        two nights. The camp at Pydna was shifted to a site nearer the sea.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> First of all Beroea, then Thessalonica
                        and Pella, and almost the whole of Macedonia, city by city, surrendered
                        within two days. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The people of Pydna, who
                        were the nearest to the consul, had not yet sent envoys, for their citizens
                        were prevented from coming to any decision in their council by the mixed
                        population drawn from many nationalities and also by the crowd of fugitives
                        from the battle. The gates were not only closed but walled up. <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> Midon and Pantauchus were sent up to the walls to
                        hold a parley with Solon, the commandant of the garrison; by his means the
                        mob of fighting men was sent way. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                        surrendered town was given up to the soldiers to plunder. Perseus' one hope
                        was in the help of the Bisaltians, but finding this hope vain he came before
                        the assembled citizens of <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> Amphipolis,
                        with his son Philip, with the intention of kindling the courage of the
                        Amphipolitans themselves and of the men, both infantry and cavalry, who had
                        accompanied him or been carried there in their flight. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> But as often as he tried to speak he was prevented by
                        his tears, and finding that he could not utter a word, he told Euander what
                        he wanted to bring before the people and went down from the tribunal.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The sight of the king and his
                        distressful weeping moved the people themselves to groans and tears, but
                        they would not listen to Euander. Some in the middle of the Assembly had the
                        audacity to shout out, "Go away, both of you, lest we, the few survivors,
                        perish on your account." <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Their daring
                        opposition closed Euander's lips. Then the king retired to his house, and
                        after placing an amount of gold and silver on board some boats lying in the
                        Strymon, went down to the river. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                        Thracians would not venture on board and dispersed to their homes, so did
                        the rest of the soldiers; the Cretans, attracted by the money, followed him.
                        As the distribution of it amongst them would cause more jealousy than
                        gratitude, 50 talents were placed on the bank to be scrambled for. Whilst
                        they were going on board, after the scrambling, in wild confusion, they sunk
                        a boat in the mouth of the river through overcrowding. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> That day they arrived at Galepsus and the day after
                        they reached Samothrace, for which they were making. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> It is asserted that 2000 talents were conveyed there.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="46" type="chapter">
                    <p>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Paulus placed Roman officers in charge of
                        the cities which had surrendered, so that the vanquished party might not be
                        ill-treated now that peace was established. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                        /> He kept the heralds from Perseus with him, and as he was unaware of the
                        king's flight he sent P. Nasica with a small detachment of horse and foot to
                        Amphipolis for the purpose of ravaging Sintice and frustrating any attempt
                        which the king might make. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the same
                        time Meliboea was taken and sacked by Cn. Octavius. Cn. Anicius was sent to
                        Aegeum, but as the citizens did not know that the war was over they made a
                        sortie from the town and the Romans lost 200 men. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> The following day the consul left Pydna with the whole
                        of his army and formed his camp two miles distant from Pella. He remained
                        there several days, surveying the city from every side, and he observed that
                        it was not without good reason that it had been chosen as the royal
                        residence. It is situated on the south-west slope of a hill and surrounded
                        by a marsh too deep to be crossed on foot either in summer or winter.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The citadel the "Phacus," which is
                        close to the city, stands in the marsh itself, <milestone n="6??"
                            unit="section"/> projecting like an island, and is built on a huge
                        substructure which is strong enough to carry a wall and prevent any damage
                        from the infiltration from the water of the lagoon. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> At a distance it appears to be continuous with the city
                        wall, but it is really separated by a channel which flows between the two
                        walls and is connected with the city by a bridge. Thus it cuts off all means
                        of access from an external foe, and if the king shut anyone up there, there
                        could be no possibility of escape except by the bridge, which could be very
                        easily guarded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The royal treasure was
                        kept there, but nothing was found there at that time beyond the 300 talents
                        which had been sent to Gentius and then kept back. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> During the time the camp was at Pella numerous
                        embassies of congratulation were received, mostly from Thessaly. On
                        receiving intelligence that Perseus had sailed to Samothrace the consul left
                        Pella, and after a few days' march arrived at Amphipolis. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> The fact of the whole population coming out to meet him
                        was a sufficient proof that they <milestone n="11??" unit="section"/> were
                        not mourning the loss of a good and just king. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
