<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Ab Urbe Condita" type="work">Ab Urbe Condita, books 3-4 - 4</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Liv.">Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor n="Foster" role="editor">Benjamin Oliver Foster, Ph.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 300Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Livy</author>
                        <title>Books III and IV With An English Translation</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="book">
                <head>Book IV</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> MARCUS GENUClUS and Gaius Curtius succeeded
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note>
                    these men as consuls. It was a year of quarrels both at home and abroad. For at
                    its commencement Gaius Canuleius, a tribune of the plebs, proposed a bill
                    regarding the intermarriage of patricians and plebeians which the patricians
                    looked upon as involving the debasement of their blood and the subversion of the
                    principles inhering in the <hi rend="italics">gentes,</hi> or families;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and a suggestion, cautiously put forward
                    at first by the tribunes, that it should be lawful for one of the consuls to be
                    chosen from the plebs, was afterwards carried so far that nine tribunes proposed
                    a bill giving the people power to choose consuls as they might see fit, from
                    either the plebs or the patriciate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> To carry
                    out this last proposal would be, in the estimation of the patricians, not merely
                    to give a share of the supreme authority to the lowest of the citizens, but
                    actually to take it away from the nobles and bestow it on the plebs. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Fathers therefore rejoiced to hear that the
                    people of Ardea had revolted because of the unjust decision which deprived them
                    of their land; that the men of Veii had ravaged the Roman frontier; and that the
                    Volsci and Aequi were murmuring at the fortification of Verrugo; <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is Livy's first mention of
                        Verrugo, which was situated on a steep hill in the Trerus valley. </note> so
                    decidedly did they prefer even an unfortunate war to an ignominious peace.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Accordingly they made the most of these
                    threats, that the proposals of the tribunes might be silenced amidst the <pb
                        n="p.259"/> din or so many wars; and ordered levies to be held <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note> and
                    military preparations to be made with the utmost energy, and if possible, even
                    more strenuously than had been done when Titus Quinctius was consul. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Thereupon Gaius Canuleius curtly proclaimed in the
                    senate that it was in vain the consuls sought to frighten the plebs out of their
                    concern for the new laws; and, declaring that they should never hold the levy,
                    while he lived, until the plebs had voted on the measures which he and his
                    colleagues had brought forward, at once convened an assembly. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At one and the same time the consuls were
                    inciting the senate against the tribune, and the tribune was arousing the people
                    against the consuls. The consuls declared that the frenzy of the tribunes could
                    no longer be endured; the end had now been reached, and there was more war being
                    stirred up at home than abroad. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This state of
                    things was, to be sure, as much the fault of the senators as of the plebs, and
                    the consuls were as guilty as the tribunes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    That tendency which a state rewarded always attained the greatest growth; it was
                    thus that good men were produced, both in peace and in war. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In Rome the greatest reward was given to sedition, which
                    had, therefore, ever been held in honour by all and sundry. Let them recall the
                    majesty of the senate when they had taken it over from their fathers, and think
                    what it was likely to be when they passed it on to their sons, and how the plebs
                    could glory in the increase of their strength and consequence. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There was no end in sight, nor would be, so long as the
                    fomenters of insurrection were honoured in proportion to the success of their
                    projects. What tremendous schemes had Gaius Canuleius set on foot! <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> He was aiming to contaminate the <hi rend="italics"
                        >gentes</hi> and <pb n="p.261"/> throw the auspices, both public and
                    private, into <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        445</note> confusion, that nothing might be pure, nothing unpolluted; so
                    that, when all distinctions had been obliterated, no man might recognise either
                    himself or his kindred. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The right to
                        ascertain the will of the gods by auspices was claimed as an exclusively
                        patrician prerogative. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> chap. vi. § 1. </note>
                    For what else, they asked, was the object of promiscuous marriages, if not that
                    plebeians and patricians might mingle together almost like the beasts?
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The son of such a marriage would be
                    ignorant to what blood and to what worship he belonged; he would pertain half to
                    the patricians, half to the plebs, and be at strife even with himself. It was
                    not enough for the disturbers of the rabble to play havoc with all divine and
                    human institutions: they must now aim at the consulship. And whereas they had at
                    first merely suggested in conversations that one of the two consuls should be
                    chosen from the plebeians, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This is
                        inaccurate. We see from chap. i. § 2 that the suggestion was that one of the
                        consuls <hi rend="italics">might</hi> be (not <hi rend="italics">should</hi>
                        be) a plebeian. </note> they were now proposing a law that the people should
                    elect consuls at its pleasure from patriciate or plebs. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Its choice would without doubt always fall upon plebeians
                    of the most revolutionary sort, and the result would be that they would have
                    consuls of the type of Canuleius and Icilius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    They called on Jupiter Optimus Maximus to forbid that a power regal in its
                    majesty should sink so low. For their parts, they would sooner die a thousand
                    deaths than suffer so shameful a thing to be done. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> They felt certain that their forefathers too, had they
                    divined that all sorts of concessions would make the commons not more tractable
                    but more exacting, and that the granting of their first demands would lead to
                    others, ever more unjust, would rather have faced any conflict whatsoever than
                    have permitted such laws to be imposed upon them. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Because they had yielded then, in the matter of the
                    tribunes, they had <pb n="p.263"/> yielded a second time; it was impossible
                    there <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note>
                    should be any settlement of the trouble, if in one and the same state there were
                    both plebeian tribunes and patricians; one thing or the other must go, — the
                    patriciate or the tribunate. It was better late than never to oppose their
                    rashness and temerity. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Were they to be
                    suffered with impunity first to sow discord and stir up neighbouring wars, and
                    then to prevent the state from arming and defending itself against the wars they
                    had raised themselves? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> When they had all but
                    invited in the enemy, should they refuse to allow the enrolment of armies to
                    oppose that enemy; while Canuleius had the hardihood to announce in the senate
                    that unless the Fathers permitted his laws to be received, as though he were a
                    conqueror, he would forbid the levy? What else was this than a threat that he
                    would betray his native City to attack and capture? How must that speech
                    encourage, not the Roman plebs, but the Volsci, the Aequi, and the Veientes!
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Would they not hope that, led by
                    Canuleius, they would be able to scale the Capitol and the Citadel? Unless the
                    tribunes had robbed the patricians of their courage when they took away their
                    rights and their dignity, the consuls were prepared to lead them against
                    criminal citizens sooner than against armed enemies. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At the very time when these opinions were
                    finding expression in the senate, Canuleius held forth in this fashion in behalf
                    of his laws and in opposition to the consuls: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    "How greatly the patricians despised you, Quirites, how unfit they deemed you to
                    live in the City, within the same walls as themselves, I think I have often
                    observed before, but never more clearly than at this very moment, <pb n="p.265"
                    /> when they are rallying so fiercely against these <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note> proposals of ours.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Yet what else do we intend by them than to
                    remind our fellow citizens that we are of them, and that, though we possess not
                    the same wealth, still we dwell in the same City they inhabit? <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> In the one bill we seek the right of intermarriage, which
                    is customarily granted to neighbours and foreigners —indeed we have granted
                    citizenship, which is more than intermarriage, even to defeated enemies;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> —in the other we propose no innovation,
                    but reclaim and seek to exercise a popular right, to wit that the Roman People
                    shall confer office upon whom it will. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What
                    reason is there, pray, why they should confound heaven and earth; why they
                    should almost have attacked me just now in the senate; why they should declare
                    that they will place no restraint on force, and should threaten to violate our
                    sacrosanct authority? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If the Roman People is
                    granted a free vote, that so it may commit the consulship to what hands it
                    likes, if even the plebeian is not cut off from the hope of gaining the highest
                    honours —if he shall be deserving of the highest honours —will this City of ours
                    be unable to endure? Is her dominion at an end? When we raise the question of
                    making a plebeian consul, is it the same as if we were to say that a slave or a
                    freedman should attain that office? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Have you
                    any conception of the contempt in which you are held? They would take from you,
                    were it possible, a part of this daylight. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    That you breathe, that you speak, that you have the shape of men, fills them
                    with resentment. Nay, they assert, if you please, that it is sinning against
                    Heaven to elect a plebeian consul. Tell me, if we are not admitted to consult
                    the <pb n="p.267"/> Fasti <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Dies fasti</hi> were the days on which it was lawful to
                        pronounce judgment. <hi rend="italics">Fasti</hi> often means, as here, the
                        calendar kept by the pontiffs on which such days were marked. It was not
                        until <date when="-0304">304 B.C.</date> , when Cn. Flavius posted a list of
                        them in the Forum (ix. xlvi. 5), that the plebeians could know with
                        certainty when they fell. </note> or the Commentaries of the Pontiffs, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Minutes of the proceedings of the
                        pontifical college. They probably furnished guidance regarding ceremonies.
                    </note> are we <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        445</note> therefore ignorant of what all men, even foreigners, know, viz.
                    that the consuls succeeded to the place of the kings, and possess no jot nor
                    tittle of right or dignity that belonged not to the kings before? <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Come! Would you believe the story was ever heard how
                    Numa Pompilius —not only no patrician, but not even a Roman citizen —was sent
                    for from the country of the Sabines, and reigned at Rome, by command of the
                    people and with the senators' consent? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> And
                    again, how Lucius Tarquinius, who was not even of Italian stock —not to mention
                    Roman —being the son of Demaratus of Corinth, and an immigrant from Tarquinii,
                    was made king, while the sons of Ancus were still living? <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> And how after him Servius Tullius, son of a captive woman
                    from Corniculum, who had nobody for his father and a bond-woman for his mother,
                    held the royal power by his innate ability and worth? For why should I speak of
                    Titus Tatius the Sabine, with whom Romulus himself, the Father of the City,
                    shared his sovereignty? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Well then, so long as
                    men despised no family that could produce conspicuous excellence, the dominion
                    of Rome increased. And are you now to scorn a plebeian consul, when our
                    ancestors were not above accepting alien kings, and when the City was not closed
                    against the meritorious foreigner, even after the expulsion of the kings?
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The Claudian family at least we not only
                    received from the Sabine country, after the kings had been driven out, and gave
                    them citizenship, but even admitted them to the number of patricians. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> Shall the son of a stranger <pb n="p.269"/> become
                    patrician and then consul, but a Roman <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 445</note> citizen, if plebeian, be cut off from all hope
                    of the consulship? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> Do we not believe it
                    possible that a bold and strenuous man, serviceable both in peace and in war,
                    should come from the plebs, —a man like Numa, Lucius Tarquinius, or Servius
                    Tullius? <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Or shall we refuse, even if such an
                    one appear, to let him approach the helm of state? Must we rather look forward
                    to consuls like the decemvirs, the vilest of mortals, who nevertheless were all
                    of patrician birth, than to such as shall resemble the best of the kings, new
                    men though they were? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "'But,' you will say, ' from the time the
                    kings were expelled no plebeian has ever been consul.' Well, what then?. Must no
                    new institution be adopted? Ought that which has not yet been done —and in a new
                    nation many things have not yet been done —never to be put in practice, even if
                    it be expedient? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There were neither pontiffs
                    nor augurs in the reign of Romulus; Numa Pompilius created them. There was no
                    census in the state, no registration of centuries and classes; Servius Tullius
                    made one. There had never been any consuls; when the kings had been banished,
                    consuls were elected. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Neither the power nor
                    the name of dictator had ever been known; in the time of our fathers they began.
                    Plebeian tribunes, aediles, and quaestors, there were none; men decided to have
                    them. Within the past ten years we have elected decemvirs for drawing up the
                    laws, and removed them from the commonwealth. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Who can question that in a city founded for eternity and of incalculable growth,
                    new powers, priesthoods, and rights of families and individuals, must be
                    established? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Was not this very <pb n="p.271"/>
                    provision, that patricians and plebeians might not <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note> intermarry, enacted by the
                    decemvirs a few years since, with the worst effect on the community and the
                    gravest injustice to the plebs? Or can there be any greater or more signal
                    insult than to hold a portion of the state unworthy of intermarriage, as though
                    it were defiled? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> What else is this but to
                    suffer exile within the same walls and banishment? They guard against having us
                    for connections or relations, against the mingling of our blood with theirs.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Why, if this pollutes that fine nobility
                    of yours —which many of you, being of Alban or of Sabine origin, possess not by
                    virtue of race or blood, but through co-optation into the patriciate, having
                    been chosen either by the kings, or, after their expulsion, by decree of the
                    people —could you not keep it pure by your own private counsels, neither taking
                    wives from the plebs nor permitting your daughters and sisters to marry out of
                    the patriciate? No plebeian would offer violence to a patrician maiden: that is
                    a patrician vice. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> No one would have compelled
                    anybody to enter a compact of marriage against his will. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But let me tell you that in the statutory prohibition and
                    annulment of intermarriage between patricians and plebeians we have indeed at
                    last an insult to the plebs. Why, pray, do you not bring in a law that there
                    shall be no intermarrying of rich and poor? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    That which has always and everywhere been a matter of private policy, that a
                    woman might marry into whatever family it had been arranged, that a man might
                    take a wife from that house where he had engaged himself, you would subject to
                    the restraint of a most arrogant aw, that thereby you might break up our civil
                        <pb n="p.273"/> society and make two states out of one. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Why do <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 445</note> you not enact that a plebeian shall not live
                    near a patrician, nor go on the same road? That he shall not enter the same
                    festive company? That he shall not stand by his side in the same Forum? For what
                    real difference does it make if a patrician takes a plebeian wife, or a plebeian
                    a patrician? What right, pray, is invaded? <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The children of course take the father's rank. There is nothing we are seeking
                    to gain from marriage with you, except that we should be accounted men and
                    citizens. Neither have you any reason to oppose us, unless you delight in vying
                    with each other how you may outrage and humiliate us. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Finally I would ask, is it you, or the Roman People, who have supreme
                        authority? Did the banishment of the kings bring you dominion, or to all men
                        equal liberty? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ought the Roman People to
                        be permitted, if it so desire, to enact a law; or shall you, as each
                        proposal is brought up, proclaim a levy by way of penalty, and so soon as I,
                        the tribune, begin to summon the tribes to vote, shall you, the consul, at
                        once administer the oath to those of military age and march them out to
                        camp, with threats against the plebs and with threats against the tribune?
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> How would it be if you had not twice
                            <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> In the plebeian secessions of
                            494 and <date when="-0449">449 B.C.</date>
                        </note> already proved how little those threats of yours are worth against
                        the unanimous will of the plebs? ' I suppose it was consideration for our
                        good that made you refrain from fighting? Or was this rather the reason
                        there was no strife, because the stronger side was also the more moderate?
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Neither will there be any struggle
                        now, Quirites; they will always test your courage; but will never put your
                        strength to the proof. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And <pb n="p.275"/>
                        so the commons are ready, consuls, for those wars <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note> you deal in, be they
                        feigned or genuine, if you give them back their right of intermarriage, and
                        make this a single state at last; if you enable them to coalesce, to unite,
                        to merge with you in domestic alliances; if the hope of attaining honours is
                        held out to strenuous men and brave; if they are granted a share in the
                        partnership of government; if, in the enjoyment of equal liberty, they are
                        allowed to govern and obey in turn, with the annual change of magistrates.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If anyone shall prevent these reforms,
                        you may talk of wars, and multiply them in the telling; but nobody will give
                        in his name, nobody will take up arms, nobody will fight for haughty masters
                        with whom he has no association in the honours of the state nor in the
                        marriages of private life. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consuls had come forth to the people
                    and set speeches had given place to wrangling, the tribune demanded what reason
                    there was why a plebeian should not be chosen consul; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> to whom Curtius replied, with truth perhaps, yet, in the
                    circumstances, to little purpose, <quote> because no plebeian has the auspices,
                        and that is the reason the decemvirs have forbidden intermarriages, lest the
                        auspices should be confounded by the uncertain standing of those born of
                        them. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At this the plebs fairly blazed with
                    indignation, because it was declared that; they could not take auspices, as
                    though they were hated by the immortal gods; nor was the controversy ended —for
                    the plebeians had got a most energetic champion in their tribune, and rivalled
                    him themselves in determination, —until <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> at
                    last the patricians were beaten, and allowed the law <pb n="p.277"/> regarding
                    intermarriage to be passed, chiefly because they <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note> thought that so the
                    tribunes would either wholly give over their contention for plebeian consuls or
                    would postpone it until after the war, and that the plebs meantime, contented
                    with the right to intermarry, would be ready to submit to the levy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But since Canuleius was grown so great through
                    his victory over the patricians and the favour of the plebs, the other tribunes
                    were encouraged to take up the quarrel; and they fought for their measure with
                    the utmost violence, hindering the levy, though the rumours of war increased
                    from day to day. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The consuls, since they were
                    powerless to do anything through the senate when the tribunes interposed their
                    veto, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The first recorded instance of
                        the tribunician veto being exercised upon a decree of the senate. </note>
                    held councils of their leading men in private. It was clear that they must
                    submit to be conquered either by the enemy or by their fellow citizens.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Of all the consulars only Valerius and
                    Horatius <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Leaders of that element in
                        the senate which stood for a policy of conciliation, and authors of the
                        Valerio-Horatian laws (17. li.-lv.). </note> took no part in their
                    deliberations. Gaius Claudius spoke in favour of arming the consuls against the
                    tribunes; the Quinctii, both Cincinnatus and Capitolinus, were opposed to
                    bloodshed and to injuring those whom they had acknowledged by a solemn treaty
                    with the plebs to be inviolable. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The upshot of
                    these consultations was this, that they permitted military tribunes with
                    consular authority to be chosen indifferently from the patriciate and the plebs,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The office thus instituted (very
                        probably by a special law, <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> chap. xxxv. § 10) was
                        not finally given up till <date when="-0367">367 B.C.</date> During this
                        period consuls were chosen twenty-two times and tribunes fifty-one times.
                    </note> but made no change in the election of consuls. With this decision both
                    tribunes and commons were content. An election was called, for <pb n="p.279"/>
                    choosing three tribunes with consular powers. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    No <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 445</note>
                    sooner was it proclaimed than everybody who had ever spoken or acted in a
                    seditious manner, especially those who had been tribunes, fell to canvassing
                    voters and bustling about all over the Forum in the white robes of candidates;
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> so that the patricians, what with despair
                    of obtaining office now that the plebs were so wrought up, and what with scorn
                    if they must share its administration with these fellows, were deterred from
                    standing. At last, however, they were compelled by their leaders to compete,
                    lest they might seem to have surrendered the control of the commonwealth.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The outcome of this election showed how
                    different are men's minds when struggling for liberty and station from what they
                    are when they have laid aside their animosities and their judgment is unbiassed;
                    for the people chose all the tribunes from among the patricians, quite satisfied
                    that plebeians should have been allowed to stand. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Where shall you now find in one single man that moderation,
                    fairness, and loftiness of mind, which at that time characterized the entire
                    people? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the year three hundred and ten from B.C.
                    444 the founding of Rome, military tribunes for the first time took office in
                    place of consuls. Their names were Aulus Sempronius Atratinus, Lucius Atilius,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Other Atilii were plebeians (see
                            <hi rend="italics">e. g.</hi> Liv. v. xiii. 3), hence Niebuhr
                        conjectured that Livy was in error in stating that the three tribunes were
                        all patricians. </note> and Titus Cloelius. During their administration
                    domestic harmony insured peace abroad, as well. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> (Some say that on account of a war with Veii, which broke out in addition to
                    the war with the Aequi and Volsci and the revolt of the men of Ardea, two
                    consuls were unable to cope with so many wars at once, and therefore three
                    military tribunes were created. These writers say nothing of the <pb n="p.281"/>
                    promulgation of a law about the election of consuls <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 444</note> from the plebs, but record
                    that the three tribunes enjoyed the authority and insignia <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">The lictors, with their rods and axes.</note> of
                    consuls.) <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Still, the power of that magistracy
                    was not yet upon a firm footing, for three months after they had taken up their
                    office they laid it down, the augurs having decreed that there had been a flaw
                    in their election, because Gaius Curtius, who had presided over the assembly,
                    had not properly selected the ground for the tent. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">tabernaculum</hi> was a tent
                        erected on the <hi rend="italics">templum,</hi> or place marked out for the
                        augural ceremony. Through an aperture in its roof the sky was watched for
                        the flight of birds. Any flaw in the procedure would vitiate the subsequent
                        election. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Ambassadors from Ardea came to Rome,
                    complaining of the injustice done them, and with such fairness that it was
                    evident that if they <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> were granted redress,
                    through the restoration of their land, they would abide by the treaty and remain
                    friendly. The senate replied that the judgment of the people could not be
                    rescinded by them, not only because they had no precedent or authority for such
                    action, but also because they had regard to the harmony between the orders.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> If the Ardeates would bide their time and
                    leave the senate to decide upon a remedy for the injury done them, the day would
                    come when they would be glad that they had controlled their anger, and they
                    would learn that the senators had been equally concerned that no wrong should be
                    done them and that what had been done should be speedily redressed. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> So the ambassadors, having said that they would refer
                    the whole matter to their people, were courteously dismissed. </p>
                <p> The patricians, since the state was without any curule magistrate, met and chose
                    an interrex. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A dispute whether consuls or
                    military tribunes should be appointed kept the state in an interregnum for <pb
                        n="p.283"/> several days. The interrex and the senate held out <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 444</note> for the
                    election of consuls; the plebeian tribunes and the plebs were for military
                    tribunes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Victory rested with the senators,
                    not only because the plebs gave up the idle contest whether they should confer
                    this honour or that upon the patricians, but also because the leaders of the
                    plebs preferred an election in which they would not be reckoned candidates to
                    one in which they would be passed over as unworthy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes, too, of the plebs relinquished the unavailing
                    contest in favour of the leaders of the patricians. Titus Quinctius Barbatus, as
                    interrex, declared the election of Lucius Papirius Mugillanus and Lucius
                    Sempronius Atratinus. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In their consulship the
                    treaty with the Ardeates was renewed; and in this lies the proof that these men
                    were consuls that year, although their names are found neither in the ancient
                    annals <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Perhaps the <hi rend="italics"
                            >Annales Maximi.</hi>
                    </note> nor in the lists of magistrates; <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Livy perhaps has in mind <hi rend="italics">libri
                            consulares,</hi> or lists of consuls. </note> I suppose that, because
                    there were military tribunes in the beginning of the year, the consuls who were
                    elected in their place were passed over as if the tribunes had been in power
                    throughout the year. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Licinius Macer testifies
                    that the names of these consuls were given both in the treaty with Ardea and in
                    the Linen Rolls in the temple of Moneta. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The temple of Juno Moneta was erected on the Capitoline
                        Hill in <date when="-0344">344 B.C.</date> (VII. xxviii. 6). The Linen Rolls
                        which Livy tells us were preserved there contained chronological lists of
                        magistrates. </note> Things were quiet both abroad and at home, despite the
                    numerous alarms which neighbouring states had caused. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This year, whether it had tribunes only or
                    B.C. 443 tribunes succeeded by consuls, was followed by one <pb n="p.285"/>
                    which had consuls about whom there is no question. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 443</note> These were Marcus Geganius
                    Macerinus, for the second time, and Titus Quinctius Capitolinus, for the fifth
                    time. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This same year saw the adoption of the
                    censorship, an institution which originated in a small way but afterwards grew
                    to such dimensions that it was invested with the regulation of the morals and
                    discipline of the Romans. The distribution of honour and ignominy amongst the
                    senate and the centuries of the knights was controlled by this magistracy, while
                    jurisdiction over public and private sites, together with the revenues of the
                    Roman People, were entirely subject to its discretion. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> What first gave rise to the office was this: the people had
                    not been rated for many years and the census could not be postponed; yet the
                    consuls, when so many nations threatened war, had no time for this work.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The subject was brought up in the senate,
                    where it was held that the task, which was a laborious one and beneath the
                    dignity of a consul, required its own proper magistrates, who should have a
                    staff of clerks, assume the custody of the records, and regulate the form of the
                    census. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senators, though it was a small
                    matter, nevertheless gladly welcomed the suggestion, in order that there might
                    be more patrician magistracies in the administration of the state. They thought
                    even then, I imagine, as afterwards proved to be the case, that it would not be
                    long before the consequence of those who held the office would lend authority
                    and dignity to the office itself. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The tribunes
                    also, regarding it as a necessary rather than a showy service, as in those days
                    it actually was, did not hold out against the plan, lest they <pb n="p.287"/>
                    might seem to be vexatiously obstinate even in <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 443</note> trifles. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The principal men in the state scorned the office, and the
                    taking of the census was, by the votes of the people, committed to Papirius and
                    Sempronius (whose consulship is questioned), that they might round out their
                    incomplete year of office with this magistracy. They were called censors from
                    their function. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these things were going on in Rome,
                    there came envoys from Ardea begging the Romans in the name of their ancient
                    alliance, renewed by the recent treaty, to send help to their city, which was on
                    the brink of ruin. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the enjoyment of peace,
                    which they had most wisely preserved with the Roman People, had been denied
                    them, owing to civil war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This is said to have
                    had its cause and origin in the rivalry of factions, which have been and will be
                    fraught with destruction to more nations than foreign wars, or famine and
                    pestilence, or whatsoever other scourges men attribute, as the most desperate
                    national calamities, to the wrath of Heaven. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A
                    maiden of plebeian family who was famous for her beauty had two youthful
                    suitors. One was of her own class and relied on the approval of her guardians,
                    who were themselves of the same standing. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    other was a noble, captivated solely by her good looks, who was supported by the
                    favour of the optimates, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> the aristocratic party. </note> which resulted
                    in the introduction of party strife into the household of the girl herself. The
                    noble was preferred by the mother, who wished her daughter to make as grand a
                    match as possible. The guardians, mindful even in a matter like this of
                    political interests, held out for their fellow plebeian. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> When the dispute could not be settled <pb n="p.289"/>
                    privately, a suit was instituted. After listening to the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 443</note> pleas of the mother and
                    the guardians, the magistrates decreed that the mother should have power to
                    decide as she saw fit about the marriage. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But
                    violence was stronger than they; for the guardians, after openly addressing a
                    crowd of their own party in the market-place, on the injustice <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The injustice probably lay in the
                        disregard of the guardians' traditional right to dispose of the hand of
                        their ward. The mother herself would be a ward. </note> of the decision,
                    collected a party and carried the girl off from her mother's house. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> To confront them an even more warlike band of nobles
                    gathered, under the leadership of the injured and indignant youth, and a
                    desperate battle followed. The plebs were routed, but, unlike the Roman plebs,
                    having armed and withdrawn from their city and encamped upon a certain hill,
                    they sallied forth, sword and torch in hand, to sack the farms of the nobles.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They even prepared to besiege the city
                    itself, for the entire body of artizans, even those who had hitherto had no part
                    in the quarrel, had been called out by the hope of plunder; <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> nor was there wanting any form of the horrors of war, as
                    though the nation had been infected with the madness of the two young men who
                    sought a fatal marriage in the ruin of their country. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Neither side saw that there had been enough of war and arms
                    at home; the optimates called upon the Romans to relieve their beleaguered city;
                    the plebeians sent for the Volsci to help them capture Ardea. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The Volsci, with the Aequian Cluilius for their leader,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This looks as though the Volscian
                        party were free lances, since a regular army would hardly have been led by
                        an Aequian. </note> were the first to reach Ardea, and threw up
                    intrenchments against the walls of their enemies. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> When the news was brought to Rome, Marcus Geganius the
                    consul immediately set out with an army. When three miles from the enemy he
                    chose a place for his camp; and as the day was <pb n="p.291"/> now fast drawing
                    to a close, ordered his soldiers <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 443</note> to refresh themselves. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Then in the fourth watch he marched out, and commencing a
                    contravallation, made such speed that at sunrise the Volsci perceived that they
                    were more securely hemmed in by the Romans than was the city by themselves; and
                    on one side the consul had thrown out a work to join the walls of Ardea, in
                    order that his friends in the town might be enabled to come and go. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Apparently the Volsci had not succeeded
                        in drawing their lines completely round the city. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Volscian commander, who had maintained his
                    men up to that time not out of a store provided in advance, but with corn taken
                    from day to day in pillaging the country-side, was no sooner shut in by the
                    rampart than he found himself all at once destitute of everything. He therefore
                    invited the consul to a parley, and said that if the Roman general had come for
                    the purpose of raising the siege, he would lead the Volscians off. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The consul replied that it was for the conquered to
                    accept terms, not to make them; the Volsci had consulted their own pleasure in
                    coming to attack the allies of the Roman People; it would be otherwise with
                    their departure. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He ordered them to surrender
                    their general, to lay down their arms, and, confessing themselves defeated, to
                    yield to his authority; if they did not, he would be their determined enemy,
                    whether they attempted to go or to stay, and would rather bring back to Rome a
                    victory over the Volsci than a treacherous peace with them. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The Volsci, testing the small hope that arms held out to
                    them —for all other hope had been cut off —fought, not to speak of other
                    disadvantages, in a position that was unfavourable for battle and still more
                    unfavourable <pb n="p.293"/> for flight; and being cut to pieces on every side,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.443</note> left
                    off fighting and fell to entreaties; and after giving up their general and
                    handing over their weapons, were sent under the yoke, with a single garment
                    each, and so dismissed, overwhelmed with shame and disaster. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> But on their encamping not far from the city of Tusculum,
                    the Tusculans, upon an old grudge, attacked them in their defenseless state, and
                    exacted so heavy a penalty that they scarce left any to report the massacre.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Roman commander, finding Ardea
                    distracted by sedition, composed its troubles by beheading the ringleaders of
                    the revolt and confiscating their property to the public treasury of the
                    Ardeates. The townsmen thought that the great service which the Roman People had
                    thus rendered them had cancelled the injustice of the judgment, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Whereby certain land over which Ardea
                        and Aricia were in litigation was awarded by the Roman People to themselves.
                        See III. lxxi. and IV. i. 4. </note> but the Roman senate felt that
                    something still remained to do in order to wipe out that reminder of the
                    national greed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul returned to the
                    City and triumphed, making Cluilius, the leader of the Volsci, walk before his
                    chariot, and displaying the spoils which he had taken from the hostile army,
                    before sending them under the yoke. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> It is no easy thing to do, but the consul
                    Quinctius equalled in civil life the fame of his armed colleague; for so well
                    did he maintain domestic peace and concord, by tempering the law to high and
                    low, that the Fathers regarded him as a strict consul, and the plebs as mild
                    enough. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He held his own, too, with the
                    tribunes, more by his personal influence than by contending with them. Five
                    consulships administered on the self-same principles, and a life which had been
                    throughout of consular <pb n="p.295"/> dignity, made the man himself almost more
                    revered <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 433</note>
                    than his office. Hence there was no talk of military tribunes while these men
                    were consuls. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Fabius Vibulanus and Postumus <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 442</note> Aebutius
                    Cornicen were elected to the consulship. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These
                    men, perceiving that they succeeded to a period of great renown for civil and
                    military achievements, and that nothing made the year so memorable in the eyes
                    of neighbouring peoples, both allies and enemies, as the earnestness with which
                    the Romans had come to the assistance of the Ardeates in their dangerous crisis,
                    were the more concerned to erase completely from men's minds the disgrace of the
                    judgment. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They accordingly caused the senate
                    to decree that inasmuch as the citizens of Ardea had been reduced by domestic
                    troubles to a small number, colonists should be enrolled to defend that city
                    against the Volsci. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This was the form in which
                    the decree was drawn up and published, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        > As a <hi rend="italics">senatus consultum,</hi> to be submitted to the
                        people for ratification. </note> that the plebs and the tribunes might not
                    perceive that a plan was on foot for rescinding the judgment; but the senators
                    had privately agreed that they would enrol as colonists a much larger proportion
                    of Rutulians than Romans, and that no land should be parcelled out except that
                    which had been sequestered by the infamous decision, nor a single clod assigned
                    there to any Roman until all the Rutulians had been provided for. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Thus the land reverted to the Ardeates. As triumvirs
                    for establishing the colony at Ardea they appointed Agrippa Menenius, Titus
                    Cloelius Siculus, Marcus Aebutius Helva. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These
                    men not only had a far from popular service to perform, and offended the plebs
                    by assigning to the allies land which the Roman People <pb n="p.297"/> had
                    adjudged to be its own; but failed to satisfy even <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 442</note> the great patricians,
                    because they had done nothing to conciliate any man's goodwill. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> They therefore avoided vexatious attacks before the people
                    —where the tribunes had already summoned them for trial —by remaining in the
                    colony, which bore witness to their integrity and justice. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was peace at home and abroad during
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 441-440</note>
                    this and the following year, when Gaius Furius Paculus and Marcus Papirius
                    Crassus were consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The games which the
                    decemvirs had vowed in pursuance of a decree of the senate, during the secession
                    of the plebs from the patricians, were that year celebrated. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Occasion for dissension was sought in vain by Poetelius,
                    who though he had got himself elected plebeian tribune for the second time, by
                    proclaiming that he would carry through these very measures, was unsuccessful in
                    forcing the consuls to lay before the senate a proposal for assigning land to
                    the plebs; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and when, after a hard struggle, he
                    obtained a vote of the senate to determine whether consuls or tribunes should be
                    elected, the decision was for consuls. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Men
                    only laughed when the tribune threatened to hold up the levy, for the
                    neighbouring peoples were quiet, and war and warlike preparations were alike
                    uncalled for. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> To this tranquil period succeeded the
                    consulship of Proculus Geganius Macerinus and Lucius Menenius Lanatus, a year
                    conspicuous for numerous deaths and dangers, for seditions, famine, and for the
                    yoke of sovereignty, to which, won over by largesses, men almost bowed their
                    necks. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The one thing lacking was foreign war,
                    and if that had been added to their burden they could hardly have held out,
                    though all <pb n="p.299"/> the gods had aided them. The troubles began with
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 441-440</note>
                    a dreadful famine, whether because the season was unfavourable for crops, or
                    that the attraction of assemblies and city-life had left the fields
                    uncultivated; for both explanations have been given. The patricians accused the
                    plebeians of idleness, and the tribunes of the plebs accused the consuls now of
                    dishonesty, now of carelessness. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the end
                    they brought the plebs, with no opposition on the senate's part, to elect Lucius
                    Minucius prefect of the corn-supply. He was destined, while filling this
                    magistracy, to be more successful in safe-guarding liberty than in discharging
                    the duties of his office, although in the end he also earned and received both
                    gratitude and glory for relieving the scarcity. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> For although he had dispatched to neighbouring peoples many embassies by land
                    and sea without result —save that a little corn was brought in from Etruria —he
                    found that he had not materially improved the supply. He then fell back upon the
                    plan of distributing the shortage. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He forced
                    men to declare their stocks of corn and to sell the surplus above the
                    requirements of a month; he deprived the slaves of a portion of their daily
                    ration; he brought charges against the dealers and exposed them to the anger of
                    the people; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and by this bitter inquisition
                    rather revealed than alleviated the scarcity, so that many of the plebeians lost
                    hope, and sooner than suffer torment by prolonging their existence, covered up
                    their heads <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> As the ancients usually
                        did when conscious that they were about to die. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>
                        the story of Caesar's death in Suetonius ( <hi rend="italics">Iulius,</hi>
                        lxxxii). </note> and threw themselves into the Tiber. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then Spurius Maelius, of the equestrian <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 440-439</note> order,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">ordo
                            equester</hi> here means the eighteen centuries of cavalry, and must not
                        be confused with the later <hi rend="italics">ordo equester,</hi> consisting
                        of all citizens below senatorial rank, whose property was assessed at
                        400,000 sesterces. Maelius was a plebeian <hi rend="italics">eques.</hi>
                    </note> a man for those times very rich, undertook to do a useful thing in a way
                    that set a very bad example and had a motive still worse. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For having <pb n="p.301"/> bought up corn in Etruria with
                    his own money, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        440-439</note> through the agency of friends and clients there — which very
                    circumstance had hindered, I can well believe, the public efforts to bring down
                    prices —he set about distributing it gratis. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The plebeians were captivated by this munificence; wherever he went, conspicuous
                    and important beyond the measure of a private citizen, they followed in his
                    train; and the devotion and hope he inspired in them gave him no uncertain
                    assurance of the consulship. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He himself, so
                    insatiable of fortune's promises is the heart of man, began to cherish a loftier
                    and less allowable ambition; and since even the consulship would have to be
                    wrested from unwilling nobles, considered how he might be king: nothing else, he
                    felt, would adequately reward him for his elaborate schemes and the toil and
                    moil of the great struggle he must make. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    consular election was now at hand, and found him with his plans not yet fully
                    ripened. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the sixth time Titus Quinctius
                    Capitolinus was chosen consul, a most unsuitable man for the purposes of a
                    would-be revolutionary. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For colleague he was
                    given Agrippa Menenius, surnamed Lanatus; and Lucius Minucius either was
                    reappointed prefect of the corn-supply or had been named for an indefinite
                    period, so long as the situation should require; for authorities do not agree,
                    but the name of the prefect is entered in the Linen Rolls among the magistrates
                    for both years. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This Minucius was discharging
                    the same function in his public capacity which Maelius had undertaken to perform
                    as a private citizen, and the same sort of men <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> corn-dealers. </note> were coming and going in
                    both their houses. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Thus Minucius discovered
                    the affair and reported to the senate that weapons were <pb n="p.303"/> being
                    collected at the house of Maelius, that he <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 440-439</note> was haranguing people
                    there, and that they were certainly contriving a kingdom; the time for executing
                    the plot was not yet fixed; all else had been agreed upon: the tribunes had been
                    bribed to betray liberty, and the leaders of the mob had been assigned their
                    parts. He said that he had withheld his report of these things almost longer
                    than was safe, that he might not become voucher for anything of an uncertain or
                    trivial nature. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On hearing this the leaders
                    of the senate loudly blamed the consuls of the year before because they had
                    suffered these donations and plebeian gatherings to take place in a private
                    house, and the new consuls because they had waited till information of so grave
                    a crime was laid before the senate by the prefect of the corn-supply, though it
                    wanted a consul not only to report it but to punish it; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> but Quinctius said that the consuls were blamed unjustly,
                    for, constrained by the laws of appeal, which had been enacted in order to break
                    down their authority, they had by no means so much power in their office as they
                    had will to punish so heinous an offence in the way it deserved. There was need,
                    he continued, of a man, and one who was not only brave, but free and unfettered
                    by the laws. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> He would therefore name Lucius
                    Quinctius dictator; there was a spirit whose stature was equal to that great
                    power. Despite the universal approval of this step, Quinctius at first refused,
                    and asked what they meant by exposing him at the end of his life to so fierce a
                    struggle. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Then, when men called out on every
                    side that there was not only more wisdom but more courage in that old man's
                    heart than in all the rest and loaded him with not <pb n="p.305"/> unmerited
                    compliments, and when the consul would <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 440-439</note>
                    <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> not recede from his purpose, at length
                    Cincinnatus uttered a prayer to the immortal gods that they would not suffer his
                    old age to bring harm or shame to the republic in so perilous a case, and was
                    pronounced dictator by the consul. He then himself named Gaius Servilius Ahala
                    his master of the horse. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next day, after disposing guards at <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 439</note> several
                    points he went down into the Forum, where the novel and surprising sight drew
                    upon him the attention of the plebs. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The
                    followers of Maelius and their leader himself perceived that it was against them
                    that the force of that high authority was aimed; while those who knew nothing of
                    the plans for setting up a king asked what outbreak or what sudden war had
                    called for the majesty of a dictator or for Quinctius (now past his eightieth
                    year) to direct the state. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then Servilius, the
                    master of the horse, being sent by the dictator to Maelius, said: <quote>The
                        dictator summons you.</quote> When Maelius, trembling, asked what he wanted,
                    Servilius replied that he must stand his trial and clear himself of a charge
                    which Minucius had lodged against him with the senate. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Then Maelius drew back into the crowd of his retainers, and
                    at first, glancing this way and that, attempted to avoid the issue; but finally,
                    when the attendant, being so commanded by the master of the horse, would have
                    led him away, he was torn from his grasp by the bystanders and fled, calling on
                    the Roman plebs to protect him, declaring that he was overthrown by <milestone
                        n="5??" unit="section"/> a plot of the patricians because he had acted
                    kindly by the commons, and begging them to help him in his extremity and not
                    permit him to be murdered before their eyes. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    While <pb n="p.307"/> he was screaming out these appeals, Servilius Ahala <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 439</note> overtook
                    and slew him; then, bespattered with his blood and guarded by a company of young
                    nobles, he returned to the dictator and reported that Maelius, having been
                    summoned to appear before him, had repulsed the attendant and was rousing up the
                    populace when he received the punishment he had deserved. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Whereat the dictator exclaimed, <quote>Well done, Gaius
                        Servilius; you have delivered the commonwealth!</quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then, as the crowd was in a turmoil, not
                    knowing what to think of the deed, he bade convoke them to an assembly. There he
                    asserted that Maelius had been justly slain, even though he had been innocent of
                    plotting to make himself king, since he had been cited before the dictator by
                    the master of the horse and had not obeyed. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> He
                    himself, he said, had sat to hear the cause, and if the hearing had been
                    concluded Maelius would have prospered as his cause deserved; but, planning
                    violence to avoid undergoing trial, he had been repressed by violence.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Neither would it have been right to deal
                    with Maelius as with a citizen. The man had been born amongst a free people
                    enjoying rights and laws, in a City from which he knew that the kings had been
                    banished, and how in that very year the king's nephews, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> This is inexact; from I. lvi. 7 we learn that it was
                        Brutus, the father of the young men in question, who was nephew to the king,
                        on the mother's side. </note> sons of the consul who had freed his country,
                    had, on the exposure of a compact they had made to bring the princes back to
                    Rome, been beheaded by their father's orders. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    He knew that in this City the consul Tarquinius Collatinus had been commanded,
                    out of hatred for the name he bore, to lay down his office and go into exile;
                    that here, some years after, Spurius Cassius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See II. xli.</note> had been punished for aiming at <pb
                        n="p.309"/> royalty; that here, but lately, the decemvirs had <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 439</note> been
                    visited with confiscation, banishment, and death, because of kingly arrogance.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Yet in this same City a Spurius Maelius
                    had conceived the hope of reigning. And who was this fellow? To be sure, no
                    nobility, no honours, no merits, opened wide the road to tyranny for any man;
                    nevertheless the Claudii <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The reference
                        is to Appius Claudius the decemvir.</note> and Cassii had been encouraged by
                    consulships and decemvirates, by their own honours and those of their
                    forefathers, and by the splendour of their families, to aim at forbidden
                    heights; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Spurius Maelius, a rich corn-dealer,
                    a man who might have desired but ought scarcely to have hoped to become a
                    plebeian tribune, had flattered himself that for a couple of pounds of spelt he
                    had purchased the liberty of his fellow citizens; <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> he had imagined that by flinging food to them he could
                    entice into slavery a people who had conquered all their neighbours, so that a
                    state which could scarce have stomached him as a senator would endure him for
                    its king, having the insignia and authority of Romulus its founder, who was
                    descended from the gods and had returned to them. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> This ought to be regarded as a thing no less monstrous than
                    wicked; nor was his blood sufficient expiation, unless the roof and walls within
                    which such madness had been conceived should be demolished, and the goods which
                    had been tainted with the offer of them as the price to buy a tyranny be
                    confiscated; he therefore bade the quaestors sell those goods and place the
                    proceeds in the public treasury. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quinctius then commanded the man's house <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 438</note> to be
                    pulled down, that the bare site might commemorate the frustration of his wicked
                    purpose. The <pb n="p.311"/> place was named Aequimaelium. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The Aequimaelium was in the Vicus Iugarius, below the
                        Capitol. Cicero derives the name from <hi rend="italics">aequus</hi>
                        <quote>just,</quote> because Maelius was justly punished ( <hi
                            rend="italics">de Domo,</hi> 101); Varro from <hi rend="italics"
                            >aequus</hi>
                        <quote>level</quote> ( <hi rend="italics">L.L.</hi> V. 157). </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Lucius Minucius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 438</note> was presented with an ox
                    and a gilded statue outside the Porta Trigemina, without opposition even on the
                    part of the plebs, since Minucius divided the corn of Maelius among them at the
                    price of one <hi rend="italics">as</hi> the peck. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> I find it stated by some historians that this Minucius went
                    over from the patricians to the plebeians, and being co-opted an eleventh
                    tribune of the plebs, allayed the rebellious feeling which arose from the
                    killing of Maelius; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but it is hardly credible
                    that the patricians should have permitted the number of tribunes to be
                    increased, and that this precedent, of all others, should have been introduced
                    by a patrician; or that the plebs, having once obtained this concession, should
                    not have held fast to it, or at least have tried to do so. But what proves more
                    conclusively than anything the falsity of the inscription on his portrait is
                    this, that it was enacted by law a few years before that the tribunes might not
                    co-opt a colleague. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The Lex Trebonia
                        of <date when="-0448">448 B.C.</date> (III. lxv. 4) required the election
                        officials to continue the voting until ten tribunes had been chosen, but
                        said nothing about the co-optation of an eleventh. </note>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Quintus Caecilius, Quintus Junius, and Sextus
                    Titinius were the only members of the college of tribunes who had not supported
                    the law conferring honours on Minucius, and had never ceased to accuse now
                    Minucius, now Servilius, before the plebs, and to complain of the unmerited
                    death of Maelius. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So they forced through a
                    measure providing that military tribunes should be elected instead of consuls,
                    not doubting that for some of the six places —for this was now the number that
                    might be filled —plebeians would be chosen, if they would promise to avenge the
                    death of Maelius. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The plebeians, though they
                    had been aroused that year by many different commotions, elected no more than
                    three tribunes with consular powers, and among <pb n="p.313"/> these Lucius
                    Quinctius, son of Cincinnatus, from <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 438</note> whose dictatorship men were trying to derive
                    the odium for inspiring a mutiny. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Aemilius
                    Mamercus, a man of the highest standing, was ahead of Quinctius in the voting;
                    Lucius Julius was elected third. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the term of these magistrates, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 437</note> Fidenae, a
                    Roman colony, revolted to Lars Tolumnius and the Veientes. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> To their defection they added a worse crime, for when Gaius
                    Fulcinius, Cloelius Tullus, Spurius Antius, and Lucius Roscius, Roman envoys,
                    came to inquire the reason of this new policy, at the command of Tolumnius they
                    put them to death. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some persons seek to
                    palliate the king's act, saying that an ambiguous expression of his upon a lucky
                    throw of dice, which made him seem to order them to kill the envoys, was heard
                    by the Fidenates and was responsible for the men's death. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But it is quite incredible that the king on being
                    interrupted by the Fidenates, his new allies, come to consult him about a murder
                    that would violate the law of nations, should not have withdrawn his attention
                    from the game, and that the attribution of the crime to a mistake did not come
                    later. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It is easier to believe that he wished
                    the people of Fidenae to be involved by the consciousness of so heinous a deed,
                    that it might be impossible for them to hope for any reconciliation with the
                    Romans. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The envoys who had been slain at
                    Fidenae were honoured, at the public cost, with statues on the Rostra. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A slight anachronism, as the speaker's
                        platform in the Forum was not called Rostra till <date when="-0338">338
                            B.C.</date> , when Gaius Menenius decorated it with the <hi
                            rend="italics">rostra</hi> (beaks) of the ships taken at Antium (VIII.
                        xiv. 12). </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> With the Veientes and Fidenates, not only
                    because they were neighbouring peoples, but also in consequence of the nefarious
                    act with which they had begun the war, a bitter struggle now impended. </p>
                <pb n="p.315"/>
                <p> Accordingly, out of regard for the general welfare, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 437</note> the plebeians and their
                    tribunes kept quiet, and raised no opposition to the election as consuls of
                    Marcus Geganius Macerinus (for the third time) and Lucius Sergius Fidenas.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I suppose that the name was given him from
                    the war which he then waged; for he was the first who fought a successful battle
                    on this side the Anio with the king of the Veientes; but he gained no bloodless
                    victory, and so there was more grief for the citizens who were lost than
                    rejoicing over the defeat of the enemy; and the senate, as is usual in an
                    alarming situation, commanded the appointment of a dictator, Mamercus Aemilius.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He named as his master of the horse a man
                    who had been his colleague the year before, when they had both been military
                    tribunes with consular authority, namely Lucius Quinctius Cincinnatus, a young
                    man worthy of his father. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To the troops which
                    the consuls levied were added veteran centurions experienced in war, and the
                    losses of the last battle were made good. The dictator bade Titus Quinctius
                    Capitolinus and Marcus Fabius Vibulanus follow him as his lieutenants.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The high authority of the dictatorship,
                    in the hands of one who was equal to it, drove the enemy out of Roman territory
                    and across the Anio. They withdrew their camp and pitched upon the hills between
                    Fidenae and the Anio; nor did they descend into the plains until the forces of
                    the Faliscans had come to their support. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Then, and not till then, did the Etruscans encamp before the walls of Fidenae.
                    The Roman dictator likewise went into camp not far off, on the banks of both
                    rivers, at their confluence, and threw up a rampart between his army and the
                    enemy, where he <pb n="p.317"/> was able to span the interval with
                    intrenchments. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> where the distance from bank to bank was not
                        too great. </note>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 437</note> Next day
                    he formed up in line of battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The enemy were of several minds. The
                    Faliscans, chafing under service performed away from home <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Their city Falerii (now Civita Castellana) was about
                        twenty-five miles north of Rome. </note> and fairly self-confident, demanded
                    battle: the Veientes and Fidenates anticipated greater success from a
                    prolongation of the war. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Tolumnius, though the
                    views of his own followers were more agreeable to him, announced that he would
                    fight on the following day, lest the Faliscans might not tolerate a protracted
                    campaign. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The dictator and the Romans were
                    encouraged at the enemy's reluctance; and the next day, on the soldiers
                    threatening that they would at once attack the camp and the city, unless the
                    enemy came to an engagement, both armies marched out in line of battle into the
                    plain between the two camps. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Veientes,
                    having men to spare, dispatched a party round the mountains to assail the camp
                    of the Romans during the engagement. The army of the three nations was so drawn
                    up that the Veientes held the right wing, the Faliscans the left, and the
                    Fidenates formed the centre. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The dictator
                    advanced on the right, against the Faliscans, and Quinctius Capitolinus on the
                    left, to meet the Veientes; while the master of the horse, with the cavalry, led
                    the attack on the centre. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For a brief moment
                    all was hushed and still; since the Etruscans were resolved not to begin
                    fighting unless they were forced, and the dictator kept looking back to the
                    Citadel of Rome, that the augurs might thence make him a signal, as they had
                    arranged to do, the moment the omens were propitious. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As soon as he descried the signal, he first sent his
                    cavalry against the enemy, <pb n="p.319"/> cheering as they charged; and the
                    infantry followed <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        437</note> with a furious attack. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> At no
                    point could the Etruscan legions withstand the onset of the Romans; their horse
                    made the chief resistance, and of all their horse by far the bravest was the
                    king himself, who rode against the Romans, as they scattered in every direction
                    for the pursuit, and prolonged the struggle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There was at that time among the cavalrymen a
                    tribune of the soldiers named Aulus Cornelius Cossus, a man of strikingly
                    handsome person and no less distinguished for courage and strength. Proud of his
                    name, which was very famous when it came to him, he left to his descendants one
                    still greater and more glorious. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> This man,
                    seeing how Tolumnius, wherever he charged, brought confusion to the Roman
                    squadrons, and recognizing him, conspicuous in his royal dress, as he galloped
                    swiftly up and down the line, exclaimed, <quote> Is this the breaker of human
                        leagues, the violater of the law of nations? <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                        /> I will speedily offer him up as a sacrificial victim, if only it is the
                        will of Heaven that there should be aught sacred on this earth, to the manes
                        of the envoys! </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Clapping spurs to his charger and levelling
                    his spear, he made for his one enemy. Having struck and unhorsed his man, he
                    himself leaped quickly to the ground by the help of his lance, and as the king
                    struggled to his feet flung him back with the boss of his shield, and plunging
                    the spear again and again into his body, pinned him to earth. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Then stripping the spoils from the corpse and cutting off
                    the head, he bore it victoriously on the point of his spear and drove the enemy
                    before him, panic-stricken at the sight of their slain king. Thus <pb n="p.321"
                    /> even the cavalry was routed, which alone had made <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 437</note> the issue of the contest
                    doubtful. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The dictator pressed on after the
                    flying legions, and pursuing them to their camp cut them to pieces. Large
                    numbers of the Fidenates escaped, thanks to their knowledge of the ground, into
                    the mountains. Cossus crossed the Tiber with his cavalry, and from the fields of
                    the Veientes brought a vast quantity of booty back to town. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> During the battle there was also fighting at the Roman camp
                    with a part of the forces of Tolumnius which he had dispatched against it, as
                    has been said before. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Fabius Vibulanus first
                    manned the rampart with a cordon of defenders; and then, when the attention of
                    the enemy was fixed on the wall, sallied out of the Porta Principalis, on the
                    right, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A Roman camp was divided by
                        the Via Principalis, which ran from one side to the other, with a gate at
                        each end of it, called respectively <hi rend="italics">Porta Principalis
                            dextra,</hi> and <hi rend="italics">P. P. sinistra.</hi>
                    </note> with his reserves, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi
                            rend="italics">triarii</hi> were experienced troops, a body of which
                        made a part of each legion. They were usually, as here, kept in reserve
                        until a crisis called for their employment ( <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>
                        VIII. viii.). </note> and fell suddenly upon them. In consequence of the
                    panic thus occasioned, though the slaughter was less, because fewer were
                    engaged, yet the rout was quite as complete as in the battle-line. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Having been everywhere victorious, the
                    dictator, as decreed by the senate and ratified by the people, returned to the
                    City in triumphal procession. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By far the
                    greatest spectacle in the triumph was Cossus, bearing the spoils of honour of
                    the slain king, while the soldiers sang rude verses about him, comparing him to
                    Romulus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The spoils he fastened up as an
                    offering, with solemn dedication, in the temple of Jupiter Feretrius, near the
                    spoils of Romulus, which had been the first to be called <hi rend="italics"
                        >opima,</hi> and were at that time the only ones. Cossus had drawn the gaze
                    of the citizens away from the car of the dictator upon himself, and the honours
                    of that crowded festival were virtually his alone. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> The <pb n="p.323"/> dictator, at the people's behest,
                    presented to Jupiter <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 437</note> on the Capitol a golden chaplet of a pound in weight, from
                    the public treasury. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Following all previous historians, I have
                    stated that Aulus Cornelius Cossus was a military tribune when he brought the
                    second spoils of honour to the temple of Jupiter Feretrius. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> But besides that only those are properly held to be
                        <quote>spoils of honour</quote> which one commander has taken from another
                    commander, and that we know no <quote>commander</quote> but him under whose
                    auspices the war is waged, the very words inscribed upon the spoils disprove
                    their account and mine, and show that it was as consul that Cossus captured
                    them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Having heard from the lips of Augustus
                    Caesar, the founder or renewer of all the temples, that he had entered the
                    shrine of Jupiter Feretrius, which he repaired when it had crumbled with age,
                    and had himself read the inscription on the linen breast-plate, I have thought
                    it would be almost sacrilege to rob Cossus of such a witness to his spoils as
                    Caesar, the restorer of that very temple. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Nepos tells us ( <hi rend="italics">Att.</hi> xx. 3)
                        that the restoration of this temple was undertaken at the suggestion of
                        Atticus. It was therefore probably done not later than <date when="-0032">32
                            B.C.</date> , the year in which Atticus died. </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Where the error in regard to this matter lies,
                    in consequence of which such ancient annals and also the books of the
                    magistrates, written on linen and deposited in the temple of Moneta, which
                    Licinius Macer cites from time to time as his authority, only give Aulus
                    Cornelius Cossus as consul (with Titus Quinctius Poenus) seven years later, is a
                    matter on which everybody is entitled to his opinion. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> For there is this further reason why so famous a battle
                    could not be transferred to the later year, that the consulship of Cossus fell
                    within a period of about three years when there were no wars, owing to a
                    pestilence and a dearth of crops, so that <pb n="p.325"/> certain annals, as
                    though death-registers, offer <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 437</note> nothing but the names of the consuls.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The third year after Cossus's consulship
                    saw him military tribune with consular powers, and in the same year he was
                    master of the horse, in which office he fought another famous
                    cavalry-engagement. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Here is freedom for
                    conjecture, but in my opinion it is idle; for one may brush aside all theories
                    when the man who fought the battle, after placing the newly-won spoils in their
                    sacred resting-place, testified in the presence of Jupiter himself, to whom he
                    had vowed them, and of Romulus —witnesses not to be held lightly by a forger
                    —that he was Aulus Cornelius Cossus, consul. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> It is possible that this paragraph was inserted by
                        Livy, without altering the context, some time after the original publication
                        of Books I-V. This would account for the appearance in the preceding
                        paragraph of the version which Livy now rejects, and also for its
                        reappearance in chap. xxxii. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Niebuhr, <hi
                            rend="italics">Röm. Gesch.</hi> ii. 517. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When Marcus Cornelius Maluginensis and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 436-435</note> Lucius
                    Papirius Crassus were consuls, armies invaded the country of the Veientes and
                    the Faliscans and drove off booty consisting of men and flocks; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> they nowhere encountered their enemies in the fields nor
                    met with any opportunity to give them battle; still, they besieged no cities,
                    for a pestilence attacked the people. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And
                    seditions were attempted at home, but not brought about, by Spurius Maelius,
                    tribune of the plebs, who, imagining that the popularity of his name would
                    enable him to stir up trouble, had appointed a day for the prosecution of
                    Minucius, and had also proposed a law for confiscating the goods of Servilius
                    Ahala, maintaining that <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> Maelius had been
                    circumvented by Minucius with false accusations, and flinging it up to Servilius
                    that he had killed a citizen who had not been condemned. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> These charges were even less regarded by the people than
                    was their author. But the increasing virulence of the disease gave concern, and
                    so did certain alarms and prodigies; <pb n="p.327"/> in particular that it was
                    frequently announced that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 436-435</note> farm-buildings had been thrown down by
                    earthquakes. A supplication was therefore offered up by the people under the
                    direction of the duumviri. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e. duumviri sacrorum,</hi> in charge of the Sibylline
                        books, from which they derived the form of prayer used in this service.
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The pestilence was worse next year, when Gaius
                    Julius (for the second time) and Lucius Verginius were the consuls, and caused
                    such fears and ravages in the City and the country that not only did <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> no one go out beyond the Roman marches to pillage,
                    nor either patricians or plebs have any thought of waging war, but the men of
                    Fidenae, who at first had kept to their mountains or their city walls, actually
                    came down into Roman territory, bent on plunder. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Then, when they had called in an army from Veii —for the Faliscans could not
                    be driven into renewing the war either by the calamity of the Romans or the
                    entreaties of their allies, —the two peoples crossed the Anio and set up their
                    standards not far from the Colline Gate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    consternation in the City was therefore no less than in the fields; the consul
                    Julius disposed his troops on the rampart and walls, and Verginius took counsel
                    with the senate in the temple of Quirinus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> It
                    was resolved that Quintus Servilius, whose surname some give as Priscus, others
                    as Structus, should be appointed dictator. Verginius delayed till he could
                    consult his colleague; then, with his consent, he that night named the dictator,
                    who appointed as his master of the horse Postumus Aebutius Helva. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator commanded everybody to be outside
                    the Colline Gate at break of day. All those who were able to bear arms were at
                    hand. The <pb n="p.329"/> standards were taken out of the treasury and brought
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 436-435</note>
                    to the dictator. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While this was going on, the
                    enemy withdrew to a more elevated position. Thither the dictator marched under
                    arms, and not far from Nomentum joined battle with the Etruscan forces and put
                    them to rout. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> From there he drove them into
                    the city of Fidenae, which he surrounded with a rampart; but could not capture
                    it with scaling-ladders, since it was a lofty, well-fortified town, nor
                    accomplish anything by blockade, for they not only had corn enough for their
                    necessities, but in fact were lavishly supplied with it from stores which they
                    had collected in advance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> In despair therefore
                    alike of storming the place and of forcing it to surrender; the dictator,
                    operating in a region which was familiar from its nearness to Rome, began, on
                    the farthest side of the city, which was least guarded because its peculiar
                    character made it the safest of all, to drive a mine into the citadel.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He himself, advancing against the city
                    from widely separated points-with his army in four divisions, that they might
                    relieve one another in the attack —by <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> fighting
                    continuously day and night distracted the enemy's attention from the work, until
                    a tunnel had been dug through the hill and a passage-way constructed up into the
                    citadel; when the Etruscans, intent on groundless alarms and unmindful of their
                    real danger, were apprised by the shouts of the enemy above their heads that
                    their city had been taken. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> In that year Gaius Furius Paculus and Marcus
                    Geganius Macerinus the censors approved a public building erected in the Campus
                    Martius, and the census of the people was taken there for the first time. </p>
                <pb n="p.331"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> That the same consuls were re-elected <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 434</note> the
                    following year (Julius for a third and Verginius for a second term) I find
                    stated by Licinius Macer: Valerius Antias and Quintus Tubero give Marcus Manlius
                    and Quintus Sulpicius as the consuls for that year. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> For the rest, in spite of the great discrepancy in their
                    statements, both Tubero and Macer cite the authority of the Linen Rolls; neither
                    writer dissembles the fact that the elder historians had recorded that there
                    were military tribunes for that year. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Licinius
                    sees fit to follow without hesitation the Linen Rolls: Tubero is uncertain where
                    the truth lies. With all the other matters which are shrouded in antiquity this
                    question too may be left undecided. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        It is typical of Livy's indifference to documents that he should not have
                        taken the trouble to consult the Linen Rolls himself. As to the fact,
                        Diodorus Siculus, xii. 53, gives Marcus Manlius, Quintus Sulpicius, and
                        Servius Cornelius Cossus as military tribunes for the year <date
                            when="-0320">320 B.C.</date> , and the statement of Antias and Tubero
                        may have arisen from the loss of the third name, and the consequent
                        assumption that consuls were in office. </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There was great alarm in Etruria in
                    consequence of the capture of Fidenae. Not only were the people of Veii
                    terrified by the fear of a similar disaster, but the Faliscans too remembered
                    that they had commenced the war in alliance with the Fidenates, although they
                    had not supported them in their revolt. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Accordingly when the two states, sending envoys round amongst the twelve cities,
                    had obtained their consent to have a council proclaimed for all Etruria at the
                    shrine of Voltumna, the senate, feeling that they were threatened with a great
                    outbreak in that quarter, ordered that Mamercus Aemilius be again named
                    dictator. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> By him Aulus Postumius Tubertus was
                    appointed master of the horse, and preparations for war were set about as much
                    more energetically than on the last occasion, as the danger from all Etruria was
                    greater than it had been from two cities. </p>
                <pb n="p.333"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This affair ended a good deal more quietly
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 434</note> than
                    anybody had anticipated. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was reported by
                    merchants <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> This implies that the
                        meetings of the league were made occasions for fairs. Cp. the fair at the
                        shrine of Feronia, I. xxx. 5. </note> that the Veientes had been refused
                    assistance and had been told that having embarked on the war at their own
                    discretion they must prosecute it with their own forces nor seek the alliance of
                    those in their adversity with whom they had not shared the prospect of success.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Whereupon the dictator, that his
                    appointment might not have been for nothing, was desirous, being deprived of the
                    means of winning military renown, of accomplishing some peaceful achievement to
                    signalize his dictatorship. He therefore laid his plans to weaken the
                    censorship, either thinking its powers excessive, or troubled less by the
                    greatness of the office than by its long duration. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> So, calling an assembly, he said that the immortal gods had
                    undertaken to manage the foreign relations of the state and to make everything
                    safe: he himself would do what needed to be done within the City, and would
                    defend the liberty of the Roman People. Now the greatest safeguard was that
                    great powers should not be long-continued, but that a limit of time should be
                    imposed on them, since no limit of jurisdiction could be. Other magistracies
                    were tenable for one year, the censorship for five. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> It was a serious matter for the same man to have authority
                    over people for so many years, in a great part of their affairs. He announced
                    that he should propose a law that the censorship might not last longer than a
                    year and a half. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> With vast enthusiasm on the
                    part of the people the law was next day enacted, and Mamercus exclaimed, <quote>
                        That you may have positive proof, Quirites, how little I approve prolonged
                        authority, I lay down my <pb n="p.335"/> dictatorship. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thus, having resigned his own <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 434</note> magistracy
                    and assigned a limit for the other, he was escorted to his home by the people,
                    with striking manifestations of rejoicing and good-will. The censors, in their
                    indignation that Mamercus had abridged a magistracy of the Roman People, removed
                    him from his tribe, and assessing him at eight times his former tax,
                    disfranchised him. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi
                            rend="italics">aerarii</hi> were the lowest class of citizens. They
                        could neither vote nor hold office; were not eligible for service in the
                        legion; and shared in the burdens of the state only by the payment of taxes
                            <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> — <hi rend="italics">aes</hi>
                        —assessed by the censors, instead of being determined by the citizen's sworn
                        declaration, as was the case with members of the five classes. </note> This
                    they say Mamercus bore with great fortitude, having regard rather to the cause
                    of his humiliation than to the humiliation itself. The leading patricians,
                    though they had opposed the curtailment of the jurisdiction of the censorship,
                    were offended by this example of censorial ruthlessness, since each of them
                    perceived that he should be subjected to the censor for a longer period and more
                    frequently than he should hold the <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> censor's
                    office. The people at any rate are said to have been so enraged that no man's
                    influence but that of Mamercus himself could have shielded the censors from
                    their violence. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The tribunes of the plebs by persistent <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 433-432</note>
                    opposition prevented the consular elections from taking place. At last, when
                    matters had been brought almost to an interregnum, they succeeded in their
                    contention that military tribunes with consular powers should be chosen.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Though they hoped their victory would be
                    rewarded by the choice of a plebeian, they were disappointed: all those who were
                    elected were patricians, Marcus Fabius Vibulanus, Marcus Folius, Lucius Sergius
                    Fidenas. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> An epidemic that year afforded a
                    respite from other troubles. A temple was vowed to Apollo in behalf of the
                    people's health. The duumviri did many things by direction of the Books <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Viz.</hi> the Sibylline Books. </note> for the <pb
                        n="p.337"/> purpose of appeasing the angry gods and averting <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 433-432</note> the
                    plague from the people. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Nevertheless the
                    losses were severe, both in the City and the country, and men and cattle were
                    stricken without distinction. They even feared that famine would succeed the
                    epidemic, since the farmers were down with the disease. They therefore sent to
                    Etruria and the Pomptine district, and to Cumae, and finally to Sicily itself,
                    for, corn. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nothing was said about consular
                    elections; military tribunes with consular authority were chosen as follows:
                    Lucius Pinarius Mamercus, Lucius Furius Medullinus, Spurius Postumius Albus —all
                    patricians. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This year the violence of the disease was
                    mitigated, and there was no risk of a dearth of corn, since precautions had been
                    taken in advance. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Schemes for instigating war
                    were discussed in the councils of the Volsci and Aequi, and in Etruria at the
                    shrine of Voltumna. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There the enterprise was
                    put over for a year, and it was decreed that no council should convene before
                    that date, though the Veientes complained —without effect —that Veii was
                    threatened with the same destruction as had overtaken Fidenae. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Meanwhile in Rome the leaders of the plebs,
                    who had now for a long time, while there was peace with other nations, been
                    thwarted in their hopes of attaining to greater honours, began to appoint
                    meetings at the houses of the plebeian tribunes. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> There they considered their plans in secret; they
                    complained that they were held in such contempt by the plebs that although
                    military tribunes with consular powers had been elected for so many years, no
                    plebeian had ever been admitted to that office. <milestone n="11" unit="section"
                    /> Their ancestors had shown great foresight in <pb n="p.339"/> providing that
                    no patrician should be eligible for the <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 433-432</note> plebeian magistracies;
                    otherwise they would have been obliged to have patricians as tribunes of the
                    plebs, so contemptible did they appear, even to their own class, being no less
                    despised by the commons than by the nobles. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Others exonerated the plebs and threw the blame upon the patricians: it was
                    owing to their artful canvassing that the plebeians found the road to office
                    blocked; if the plebs might have a breathing-spell from the mingled prayers and
                    menaces of the nobles, they would think of their friends when they went to vote,
                    and to the protection they had already won would add authority. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Auxlium</hi> alludes to the plebeian tribunate, <hi
                            rend="italics">imperium</hi> to the military tribunate with consular
                        powers. </note>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It was resolved in order to do away with
                    canvassing, that the tribunes <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi> the plebeian tribunes. </note> should propose a
                    law forbidding anyone to whiten his toga, for the purpose of announcing himself
                    a candidate. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The office-seeker
                        pipe-clayed his toga; hence <hi rend="italics">candidatus,</hi>
                        <quote>candidate.</quote>
                    </note> This may now appear a trivial thing and one scarcely to be considered
                    seriously, but at that time it kindled a furious struggle between the patricians
                    and the plebs. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Yet the tribunes prevailed and
                    carried their law; and it was clear that the plebeians in their irritated mood
                    would support the men of their own order. That they might not be at liberty to
                    do so, the senate decreed that consuls should be elected. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The reason alleged was a sudden outbreak
                    B..431 of hostilities on the part of the Aequi and Volsci, which the Latins and
                    the Hernici had reported. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius
                    Cincinnatus, son of Lucius —the same who is given the added surname Poenus, —
                    and Gnaeus Julius Mento were made consuls. Nor was the fear of war deferred.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> After a levy, held under a <hi
                        rend="italics">lex sacrata</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Whoever offended against such a law
                        was forfeited ( <hi rend="italics">sacer</hi> ) to the gods. </note> which
                    was their most effective <pb n="p.341"/> means of collecting soldiers, strong
                    armies marched <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        431</note> out from both nations and met on Algidus, where the Aequi
                    encamped <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> in one place and the Volsci in
                    another, and their generals took more pains than ever before to intrench, and to
                    drill their men. For this reason the report occasioned the more dismay in Rome.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The senate resolved that a dictator should
                    be appointed, since, though often beaten, those nations had renewed the war with
                    greater efforts than at any previous time, and a considerable proportion of the
                    young Romans had been carried off by the plague. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Above all, men were frightened by the wrong-headedness of the consuls, their
                    want of harmony between themselves, and their opposition to each other in all
                    their plans. Some writers say that these consuls were defeated on Algidus, and
                    that this was the reason of the dictator's being named. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Thus much is clear: though they might differ in other
                    matters, they were agreed on one thing, to oppose the wishes of the Fathers for
                    the appointment of a dictator; until, as the reports grew more and more
                    alarming, and the consuls refused to be guided by the senate, Quintus Servilius
                    Priscus, a man who had filled with distinction the highest offices, cried out,
                        <quote> To you, tribunes of the plebs, since matters <milestone n="8??"
                            unit="section"/> have come to an extremity, the senate appeals, that in
                        this great national crisis you may compel the consuls, by virtue of your
                        authority, to name a dictator. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Hearing this the tribunes felt that an
                    opportunity had come for increasing their power; they conferred apart, and then
                    announced, in behalf of the college, that they were resolved that the consuls
                    should obey the senate; if they persisted further <pb n="p.343"/> to oppose the
                    unanimous opinion of that most <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 431</note> honourable order, they should command them to
                    be put in prison. The consuls preferred to be defeated by the tribunes rather
                    than by the senate. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They declared that the
                    senators had betrayed the rights of the highest office in the state and had
                    ignominiously surrendered the consulship to the tribunician power, since
                    apparently it was possible for the consuls to be subjected to the official
                    compulsion of a tribune, and even —what could a private citizen fear more than
                    that? —be carried off to gaol. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was
                    determined by lot —for the colleagues had not been able to agree even about this
                    —that Titus Quinctius should name the dictator. He appointed Aulus Postumius
                    Tubertus, his father-in-law, a man of the sternest authority; and by him Lucius
                    Julius was chosen master of the horse. At the same time a levy was proclaimed
                    and a cessation of legal business, and it was ordered that nothing else should
                    be done in all the City but prepare for war. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    The examination of those who claimed exemption from military service was put
                    over till after the war, and so even those whose cases were uncertain were
                    disposed to give in their names. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> For
                        fear that —their claims being then disallowed —they would be treated as
                        deserters. </note> Men were required also of the Hernici and the Latins, and
                    in both instances the dictator was zealously obeyed. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These measures were all carried out with great
                    dispatch. Gnaeus Julius the consul was left behind to protect the city; and
                    Lucius Julius, the master of the horse, to meet the sudden demands which arise
                    in war, that the troops might not be hampered in camp by the want of anything
                    that they might need. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The dictator, repeating
                    the words <pb n="p.345"/> after Aulus Cornelius the pontifex maximus, vowed
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 431</note> to
                    celebrate great games <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Not to be
                        confounded with the annual <hi rend="italics">Ludi Magni</hi> established by
                        A. Postumius after his victory at Lake Regillus, <date when="-0499">499
                            B.C.</date> The present reference is to votive games to be given, in the
                        event of victory, as payment in full for the assistance of the gods. </note>
                    if he succeeded in quelling the outbreak, and, dividing his army with the consul
                    Quinctius, set out from Rome and came to the enemy. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Seeing that the opposing forces occupied two camps with a
                    little space between, the Roman generals followed their example and encamped
                    about a mile from the enemy, the dictator nearer to Tusculum and the consul to
                    Lanuvium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thus the four armies in their four
                    intrenchments had in their midst a field of sufficient extent not merely for
                    small preliminary skirmishes but even for drawing up lines of battle on both
                    sides. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor from the moment the Romans had
                    pitched their camp near that of the enemy did they once cease skirmishing; and
                    the dictator was well content that his men should match their strength against
                    their adversaries, and by trying the outcome of these contests come, little by
                    little, to count upon a general victory. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    enemy in consequence abandoned all hope of success in a regular battle and
                    attacked the consul's camp at night, committing their cause to the hazard of a
                    dangerous enterprise. The shout which suddenly broke out aroused not only the
                    consul's sentries and after them his entire army, but the dictator as well.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When circumstances required instant
                    action, the consul proved to be wanting neither in resolution nor in judgment.
                    With a part of his soldiers he reinforced the guards at the gates; with a part
                    he lined the palisade. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the other camp, with
                    the dictator, there was less confusion and a correspondingly clearer perception
                    what was needful to be done. Reinforcements were immediately sent to the
                    consul's camp, under Spurius Postumius Albus <pb n="p.347"/> the lieutenant: the
                    dictator himself, taking a part of <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 431</note> his forces, marched by a slight detour to a
                    place absolutely screened from the fighting, that he might thence strike the
                    enemy unawares as he faced the other way. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    lieutenant Quintus Sulpicius he put in charge of the camp; to the lieutenant
                    Marcus Fabius he assigned the cavalry, but ordered him not to move his command
                    till daybreak, as it would be hard to control in the confusion of the night.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Everything that any wise and active
                    general could have commanded and carried out in such a situation was duly
                    commanded and carried out by him; but an unusual proof of judgment and daring
                    and one which reflects no ordinary credit upon him was this, that he actually
                    attacked the enemy's camp (from which, as he ascertained, they had marched out
                    with more than half their troops), dispatching Marcus Geganius with some chosen
                    cohorts on that service. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This officer found
                    his foes absorbed in the issue of the dangerous work undertaken by their
                    fellows, and with no thought for themselves, neglecting their sentinels and
                    outguards; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> he attacked them, captured their
                    camp almost before they fully realized that they were assailed, and sent up a
                    prearranged signal of smoke, on seeing which the dictator cried out that the
                    enemy's camp was taken and bade spread the news. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> By this time the day was breaking and
                    everything could be seen. Fabius had delivered a charge with his cavalry; the
                    consul had made a sally from the camp against the enemy, who were already
                    wavering; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> while the dictator, on the other
                    side of the field, attacking the supports and the second line, had fallen upon
                    the foe from every side, as they <pb n="p.349"/> wheeled about to meet the wild
                    shouts and sudden <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        431</note> onsets, with his victorious foot and horse. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly, being now hemmed in on every side, the enemy
                    would have suffered to a man the penalty of their rebellion, had not Vettius
                    Messius, a Volscian more distinguished by his deeds than by his birth, called
                    out in a clear voice to his men, who were already crowding together in a circle,
                        <quote> Are you going to offer yourselves up here to the weapons of the
                        enemy, defenceless and unavenged? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> To what
                        end then are you armed, or why without provocation did you make war,
                        turbulent in peace and sluggards in the field? What hope is there while you
                        stand here? Do you think that some god will protect you and deliver you from
                        this plight? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> It is your swords must make a
                        way for you! Come, where you see me go before, there you must follow, if you
                        would look on homes, parents, wives and children! It is not a wall or
                        rampart that blocks your path, but armed men like yourselves. In courage you
                        are their equals; in necessity, which is the last and chiefest weapon, you
                        are the better men. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> So he spoke, and acted on the word. Renewing
                    their shouts they followed after, and hurled themselves against the Romans where
                    the cohorts of Postumius Albus had confronted them. And they forced the victors
                    to give ground, until the dictator came up, as his men were already falling
                    back, and the fighting all centred on that spot. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> On one single warrior, Messius, hung the fortunes of the enemy. Many were the
                    wounds on either side, and great was the slaughter everywhere. Now even the
                    Roman leaders were bleeding as they fought. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Only Postumius left the battle, struck by a stone that broke his head. <pb
                        n="p.351"/> A wounded shoulder could not drive the dictator <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 431</note> from so
                    critical a fight; nor would Fabius retire for a thigh almost pinned to his
                    horse; nor the consul for an arm that was hewn away. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Messius pressed on with a band of courageous
                    youths over the slain bodies of his enemies, and reached the Volscian camp,
                    which had not yet been taken; and on that point the entire battle converged.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul, after pursuing his opponents
                    clear up to the rampart, assailed the camp itself and the palisade; and thither
                    from another part of the field the dictator brought up his troops. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The assault was no less vigorous than the battle had
                    been. They say that the consul even cast his standard into the stockade, to make
                    his men the more eager in the charge, and that in seeking to recover it they
                    made the first breach. The dictator too had breached the rampart and had already
                    carried the fighting into the camp. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then the
                    enemy began on every hand to throw down their arms and surrender. Finally the
                    camp itself was captured, and the enemy were all sold into slavery, except the
                    senators. A portion of the booty was restored to the Latins and the Hernici, on
                    their identifying it as their own; a part was sold at auction by the dictator;
                    who then left the consul in command of the camp and returning himself in triumph
                    to the City laid down his office. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The memory
                    of the noble dictatorship assumes a sombre hue in a tradition that Aulus
                    Postumius' son, who, tempted by an opportunity of fighting to advantage, had
                    left his post unbidden, was in the hour of his victory beheaded by his father's
                    orders. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> One is loath to believe this story,
                    and the diversity of opinion allows one to reject it. It is an indication <pb
                        n="p.353"/> of its falsity that we speak of Manlian, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">Alluding to the story told at VIII. vii. 1.</note> not
                    Postumian <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        431</note> discipline, whereas he who had first established so rigorous a
                    precedent would himself have received that notorious stigma of cruelty. Besides,
                    Manlius was given the surname <hi rend="italics">Imperiosus</hi> — <quote>the
                        Despotic</quote> —while Postumius received no such grim distinction. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Gnaeus Julius the consul dedicated the temple
                    of Apollo in the absence of his colleague, without drawing lots. Quinctius
                    resented this, when he had dismissed his army and returned to the City; but his
                    complaint of it in the senate was without effect. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> To the history of a year famous for its great
                    events, is appended a statement —as though the incident was then regarded as of
                    no importance to the Roman state-that the Carthaginians, destined to be such
                    mighty enemies, then for the first time sent over an army into Sicily to assist
                    one of the factions in the domestic quarrels of the Sicilians. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> A mistake. The Carthaginians had
                        obtained a foothold in Sicily long before this time, and (according to
                        Herodotus, vii. 166), were defeated in a great naval battle by the Sicilians
                        on the same day that Salamis was fought ( <date when="-0480">480 B.C.</date>
                        ). </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> An effort was made in the City by the B.C.
                    tribunes of the plebs to procure the election of military tribunes with consular
                    powers, but it was unsuccessful. Lucius Papirius Crassus <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The same who had been consul in 435? Livy usually notes
                        the second election to a consulship with the word <hi rend="italics"
                            >iterum.</hi> Diodorus, xii. 72, gives our consul's name as Gaius.
                    </note> and Lucius Julius were chosen consuls. The Aequi, through their envoys,
                    sought a treaty from the senate. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Instead of
                    granting a treaty, the senate suggested that they surrender; but they asked and
                    obtained a truce for eight years. The Volscian commonwealth, in addition to the
                    disaster it had suffered on Algidus, had become involved in quarrels and
                    seditions, in consequence of an obstinate struggle between the advocates of
                    peace and those of war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Romans everywhere
                    enjoyed peace. A law concerning the <pb n="p.355"/> valuation of fines was most
                    welcome to the people. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 430-427</note>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Having learned through the treachery of a
                    member of the college that the tribunes were drawing one up, the consuls
                    anticipated their action and themselves proposed it. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> An earlier law ( <hi rend="italics">Menenia
                            Sextia,</hi>
                        <date when="-0452">452 B.C.</date> ) had fixed the limit of fines which
                        magistrates might impose on their own responsibility at two sheep for poor
                        men and thirty oxen for rich men. The present law ( <hi rend="italics"
                            >Papiria Julia</hi> ) provided for a uniform money equivalent for these
                        fines, <hi rend="italics">viz.</hi> twenty and three thousand asses
                        respectively. </note>
                </p>
                <p> The next consuls were Lucius Sergius Fidenas (for the second time) and Hostius
                    Lucretius Tricipitinus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nothing noteworthy was
                    done this year. They were succeeded in the consulship by Aulus Cornelius Cossus
                    and Titus Quinctius Poenus, who was elected for the second time. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> The Veientes made inroads into Roman territory. It
                    was rumoured that certain young men of Fidenae had shared in the pillaging. The
                    investigation of this report was intrusted to Lucius Sergius, Quintus Servilius,
                    and Mamercus Aemilius; and certain men were banished to Ostia, because it was
                    not clear why they had been away from Fidenae during those days. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> A number of settlers were added to the colony, and
                    land was assigned them which had belonged to men who had fallen in the war.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A drought that year caused great
                    suffering. Not only did the skies provide too little rain, but the earth as well
                    was deficient in native moisture and could hardly supply the perennial streams.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> In some cases the failure of the sources
                    caused the dry springs and brooks to be lined with cattle perishing of thirst;
                    others were carried off by a mange, and their diseases were by contact
                    communicated to mankind. At first they attacked country people and slaves; then
                    the City was infected. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> And not only were
                    men's bodies smitten by the plague, but a horde of superstitions, mostly
                    foreign, took possession of their minds, as the class of men who find their
                    profit in superstition-ridden souls <pb n="p.357"/> introduced strange
                    sacrificial rites into their homes, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 430-437</note> pretending to be seers; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> until the public shame finally reached the leading
                    citizens, as they beheld in every street and chapel outlandish and unfamiliar
                    sacrifices being offered up to appease Heaven's anger. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The aediles were then commissioned to see to it that none
                    but Roman gods should be worshipped, nor in any but the ancestral way. </p>
                <p> Revenge on the men of Veii was postponed till the following year, when Gaius
                    Servilius Ahala and Lucius Papirius Mugillanus were consuls. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Even then a religious scruple prevented the immediate
                    declaration of war and dispatch of armies; they resolved that fetials must first
                    be sent to require restitution. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Not long
                    before there had been a battle with the Veientes near Nomentum and Fidenae, and
                    this had been followed not by peace but by a truce. Its time had now run out,
                    and indeed the enemy had begun to fight again before its expiration;
                    nevertheless fetials were sent; yet their words, when they sought reparation
                    after taking the customary oath, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">For
                        the procedure of the fetials see I. xxxii.</note> were not attended to.
                        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> A dispute then arose whether war should
                    be declared by command of the people, or whether a senatorial decree was enough.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> If the war was a new war it must
                        be sanctioned by vote of the people; if merely a continuation of the old war
                        this was unnecessary. </note> The tribunes prevailed, by threatening to
                    hinder the levy, and forced the consul Quinctius to refer the question of war to
                    the people. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> All the centuries voted for it.
                    In this respect also the plebs had the better, that they made good their wish
                    that consuls should not be elected for the following year. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Four military tribunes with consular powers
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 426</note> were
                    elected, Titus Quinctius Poenus, who had just been consul, Gaius Furius, Marcus
                    Postumius, and Aulus Cornelius Cossus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Of
                    these, Cossus had charge <pb n="p.359"/> of the City; the three others held a
                    levy and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 426</note>
                    marching against Veii gave a demonstration how unprofitable it was in war to
                    parcel out authority. By pursuing each his own counsels, one having this
                    opinion, another that, they gave the enemy room to take them at a disadvantage;
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> for their army was confused when some bade
                    sound the charge, while others commanded the recall; and at this favourable
                    moment the Veientes fell upon them. The camp, which was close by, received the
                    demoralized and fleeing men, and so they suffered more disgrace than actual
                    harm. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The nation was filled with grief, for it
                    was not used to being conquered; disgusted with the tribunes, people demanded a
                    dictator: therein, they said, lay the hope of the state. And when they seemed
                    likely to be thwarted in that also, by a scrupulous feeling that no one but a
                    consul could name a dictator, the augurs were consulted and removed the
                    impediment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Aulus Cornelius named as dictator
                    Mamercus Aemilius and was himself appointed by Mamercus master of the horse, so
                    true is it that when the fortune of the state required real worth, the
                    animadversion of the censor could by no means prevent men's seeking a director
                    of their affairs in a house undeservedly stigmatized. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified">See chap. xxiv.</note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Veientes, elated by their success,
                    dispatched envoys round about to the peoples of Etruria, boasting that they had
                    routed three Roman commanders in one fight. Nevertheless they obtained no
                    general support from the league, though they attracted volunteers from all
                    quarters by the prospect of booty. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Only the
                    people of Fidenae voted to renew the war; and, as though it were forbidden to
                    commence war without a crime, as before in the blood <pb n="p.361"/> of the
                    ambassadors, so now they imbued their swords <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 426</note> in that of the new
                    settlers, and joined the men of Veii. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Consultations followed between the leaders of the two nations whether they
                    should take Veii or Fidenae for the headquarters of their campaign. Fidenae
                    seemed the fitter; and accordingly the Veientes crossed the Tiber and
                    transferred the war to Fidenae. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At Rome there
                    was a wild alarm. The troops were recalled from Veii, though even their spirits
                    were much daunted in consequence of their failure, and encamped before the
                    Colline Gate. Armed men were disposed along the walls, a cessation of the courts
                    was proclaimed in the Forum, the shops were closed, and everything assumed more
                    the look of a camp than of a city. <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The dictator, sending heralds this way and
                    that through the streets, summoned the frightened citizens to an assembly, where
                    he rebuked them for possessing hearts so easily dismayed by trivial fluctuations
                    of fortune that on sustaining a slight reverse —and <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> that not due to the valour of the enemy or the cowardice of
                    the Roman army, but to a disagreement among their generals —they were seized
                    with dread of the Veientine enemy whom they had six times defeated, and of
                    Fidenae which they had captured almost more often than they had attacked it.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Both the Romans and their enemies were the
                    same as they had been for so many generations; they had the same courage, the
                    same bodily vigour, the same weapons; he was himself the same dictator Mamercus
                    Aemilius who had formerly put to flight the armies of the Veientes and the
                    Fidenates, with the Faliscans added, before Nomentum; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and, as master of the horse, Aulus <pb n="p.363"/>
                    Cornelius would be the same man in battle that <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 426</note> he had shown himself in
                    the former war, when as military tribune he had slain Lars Tolumnius, king of
                    the Veientes, in full sight of both armies, and had borne the spoils of honour
                    to the temple of Jupiter Feretrius. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Let them
                    remember then that theirs were the triumphs, theirs the spoils, theirs the
                    victory; while their enemies were stained with the crime of putting envoys to
                    death against the law of nations, with the slaughter in time of peace of
                    settlers at Fidenae, with the broken truce, with rebelling unsuccessfully for
                    the seventh time. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Let them think of these
                    things and arm. When once they should have pitched their camp near the camp of
                    the enemy, he was very confident the dastardly foe would not long rejoice over
                    the humiliation of a Roman army; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but that the
                    Roman People would perceive how much better those men had served the state who
                    had named him for the third time dictator, than had those who, because he had
                    torn from the censorship its tyrannical powers, had fixed a stigma upon his
                    second dictatorship. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Then, having offered vows
                    to the gods, he marched out and encamped a mile and a half this side of Fidenae,
                    protected on his right by mountains, on his left by the river Tiber. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> His lieutenant Titus Quinctius Poenus he commanded to
                    secure the mountains and secretly to occupy the ridge which lay to the enemy's
                    rear. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the morrow, when the Etruscans, in high
                    feather at what, on the previous day, had been more good luck than good
                    fighting, sallied forth to offer battle, the dictator delayed a little, till his
                    scouts should report that Quinctius had come out <pb n="p.365"/> on the ridge
                    near the citadel of Fidenae; and then <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 426</note> forming his infantry in line of battle led
                    them at the double against the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He
                    directed the master of the horse not to begin to fight until he got his orders:
                    when he required the help of the cavalry, he would himself give the signal; let
                    him then bear himself as one mindful of his battle with a king, of his glorious
                    offering, of Romulus and Jupiter Feretrius. The armies came together with great
                    fury. The Romans were consumed with hatred. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Traitors</quote> was the name they gave the Fidenates, and
                        <quote>brigands</quote> the men of Veii; they called them breakers of
                    truces, stained with the horrid murder of ambassadors, sprinkled with the gore
                    of their own settlers, faithless allies and cowardly enemies; and fed their rage
                    at once with deeds and with words. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They had shaken the enemy's resistance at the
                    very first onset, when suddenly the gates of Fidenae were flung open and a
                    strange kind of army, never seen before or heard of, came pouring out.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Fire was the weapon of that vast
                    multitude, and blazing torches threw a glare upon the entire throng when, as
                    though inspired with a wild insanity, they rushed headlong on their enemy.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For an instant the strangeness of this
                    kind of battle dismayed the Romans. Then the dictator, calling up the master of
                    the horse and his cavalry, sending for Quinctius to come down from the
                    mountains, and urging on the fight himself, hurried to the left wing, which, as
                    though it found itself in a conflagration rather than a line of battle, had
                    shrunk back in terror from the flames, and in a loud voice cried out: <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Will you quit your post, <pb n="p.367"/> subdued with smoke like a swarm
                        of bees, and yield <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                            >B.C. 426</note> to an unarmed foe? Will you not extinguish fire with
                        the sword? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Will you not seize these
                        self-same brands, and each for himself —if we must fight with fire, not with
                        javelins —attack them with their own weapons? Come, call to mind the Roman
                        name, your fathers' valour and your own; turn this blaze upon the enemy's
                        city and destroy Fidenae with its own flames, since your kindness was
                        powerless to gain its friendship! The blood of your envoys and your
                        colonists and your devastated borders exhort you to do as I say. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> At the dictator's command the whole array was
                    set in motion. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Here they caught up torches
                    which had been flung away; there they wrested them violently from their bearers:
                    both sides were armed with fire. The master of the horse on his part invented a
                    new kind of cavalry-fighting. Commanding his men to pull off the bridles from
                    their horses, he led the way, and setting spurs to his own, was carried by the
                    unbridled charger into the midst of the flames. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> The other horses too were urged on and bore their riders at full tilt against
                    the enemy; while the dust that rose and mingled with the smoke darkened the eyes
                    both of the men and of their mounts. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But the
                    sight which had frightened the infantry had no terror for the horses, and the
                    cavalry overthrew their enemies in heaps wherever they advanced. Then a new
                    shout was heard. Both armies in astonishment looked that way; and when the
                    dictator called out that Quinctius the lieutenant and his followers had assailed
                    the enemy in the rear, the cheering was renewed, and he pressed home his own
                    attack more sharply. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.369"/> Now that two battle-fronts and two distinct attacks <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 426</note> hemmed in
                    the Etruscans and forced them back from front and rear; and there was no way for
                    them to flee, either back into their camp or into the mountains, whence a new
                    foe had appeared to block their path; and the horses, with loose reins, had
                    borne their riders far and wide; —the Veientes for the most part ran in disorder
                    to the Tiber, while those of the Fidenates who survived turned towards the city
                    of Fidenae. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In their panic they fled into the
                    middle of the carnage. Some were cut down on the banks of the river; others,
                    forced into the water, were swept away by the current; even experienced swimmers
                    were borne down by weariness and wounds and fear; only a few out of the many
                    swam across. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The other party was carried on
                    through the camp to the city. Thither the Romans too pushed forward in the
                    impetuosity of the pursuit —especially Quinctius, and with him those who had
                    just come down from the hills and were the freshest soldiers for the work,
                    having arrived at the close of the battle. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After these troops, mingling with the enemy,
                    had entered the gate, they made their way on to the wall, where they raised a
                    signal to show their friends that the town was taken. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When the dictator saw it —for by this time he had himself
                    penetrated to the deserted camp of the enemy, —he checked his soldiers, who were
                    eager to scatter in search of booty, by encouraging the hope that they would
                    find larger spoils in the city; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and, leading
                    them to the gate, was received within the walls and marched directly to the
                    citadel, whither he saw that the throng of fugitives was rushing Nor was <pb
                        n="p.371"/> the slaughter in the city less than it had been in <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 426</note> the
                    battle, until they threw away their arms, and asking nothing but their lives,
                    surrendered to the dictator. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The city and the
                    camp were sacked. Next day the cavalrymen and centurions drew lots for a single
                    captive each, while those who had shown conspicuous bravery received two. The
                    rest were sold at auction, and the dictator marched his victorious army,
                    enriched with plunder, back to Rome, and triumphed. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> After commanding his master of the horse to lay down his
                    office, he himself abdicated, giving up in peace on the sixteenth day the
                    supreme authority he had received in time of war and danger. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Certain annalists have recorded that there was a naval
                    battle also with the Veientes, near Fidenae, a thing equally difficult and
                    incredible; for even to-day the river is not wide enough for that, and in those
                    times it was somewhat narrower, as we learn from the old writers; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> unless possibly there were a few ships assembled to
                    dispute the passage of the river and this was exaggerated, as so often happens,
                    by those who added to the inscription <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">sc.</hi> under the portrait of Aemilius. Livy is thinking
                        of the partiality characteristic of such family records. </note> the false
                    claim of a naval victory. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next year there were military <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 425-424</note>
                    tribunes with consular powers, namely Aulus Sempronius Atratinus, Lucius
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus, Lucius Furius Medullinus, Lucius Horatius Barbatus.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Veientes were granted a truce of
                    twenty years, and the Aequi one of three, though they had asked for a longer
                    one. There was a respite also from civil disturbances. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The following year was noteworthy neither for
                    foreign war nor dissension at home, but gained celebrity from the games which
                    had been vowed <pb n="p.373"/> during the war and were splendidly carried out by
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 425-424</note>
                    the military tribunes and attended by a great concourse of neighbouring peoples.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The tribunes with consular authority were
                    Appius Claudius Crassus, Spurius Nautius Rutulus, Lucius Sergius Fidenas, and
                    Sextus Julius Iulus. The spectacle was rendered the more agreeable to the
                    visitors by the courtesy which their hosts had united in a resolution to extend
                    to them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> After the games seditious speeches
                    were made by the plebeian tribunes, who berated the populace because, in their
                    besotted admiration of the men they hated, they kept themselves in perpetual
                    servitude, and not only dared not aspire to claim participation in the
                    consulship, but even in the matter of choosing military tribunes —an <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> election open alike to patricians and plebeians —took
                    no thought either for themselves or for their friends. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Let them cease therefore to wonder why no one busied
                    himself for the good of the plebs; toil was bestowed and danger risked, they
                    said, in causes which held out hopes of emolument and honour; there was nothing
                    men would not attempt if those who made great efforts were afforded the prospect
                    of great rewards; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but that some one plebeian
                    tribune should rush blindly into a struggle where the risk was enormous and the
                    reward was nothing, and in consequence of which he might be certain that the
                    patricians, against whom he would be striving, would pursue him with relentless
                    animosity, and that the plebs, for whom he would have fought, would not add the
                    least tittle to his honours, was a thing to be neither expected nor demanded.
                    Great hearts were begotten of great honours. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    No plebeian would despise himself when plebeians should cease <pb n="p.375"/> to
                    be despised. It was high time they made trial in <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 425-424</note> one or two cases, to
                    see whether there were some plebeian fit to hold high office, or whether it were
                    almost a portent and a miracle that there should exist any brave and energetic
                    man of plebeian origin. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> By exerting their
                    utmost force they had carried the point that military tribunes with consular
                    powers might be chosen even from the plebs. Men whose worth had been proven at
                    home and in the field had stood for the office; during the first years they had
                    been buffeted about, rejected, and laughed at by the patricians; finally, they
                    had ceased to expose themselves to insult. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    They could see no reason, they said, why they should not even repeal a statute
                    which authorized something that would never come; there would surely be less
                    shame in the injustice of the law than in being passed over on account of their
                    own unworthiness. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Speeches of this sort, being listened to with
                    approval, incited certain men to stand for the military tribuneship, with the
                    promise that they would propose in their term of office such and such measures
                    of advantage to the plebs. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Hopes were held out
                    of dividing up the public domain and planting colonies, and of levying a tax on
                    the occupants of the land and distributing the money as pay for the soldiers.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The first attempt to tax the
                        patricians enjoying the use of the public land for the purpose of paying the
                        soldiers, who had always been required to serve gratis. See chap. lix. § 11. </note>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The military tribunes then watched for an
                    opportunity when people were out of town, and recalling the senators by a secret
                    notification, got the senate to pass a resolution, in the absence of the
                    tribunes of the plebs, that <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> since the Volsci
                    were rumoured to have made a plundering expedition into the country of the
                    Hernici, the tribunes of the soldiers should go and investigate <pb n="p.377"/>
                    the affair, and that a consular election should be <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 425-424</note> held. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes set out, leaving Appius Claudius, the
                    decemvir's son, as prefect of the City. He was an energetic young man and imbued
                    from his very cradle with hatred of the tribunes and the plebs. The plebeian
                    tribunes had no ground of contention either with the absent officials who had
                    obtained the resolution of the senate, or with Appius, now that the thing was
                    done. <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Gaius <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 423</note> Sempronius Atratinus and
                    Quintus Fabius Vibulanus were elected consuls. </p>
                <p> A foreign episode, but worth relating, is ascribed to this year, viz. that
                    Volturnum, the Etruscan city which is now Capua, was taken by the Samnites, and
                    named Capua from their leader Capys, or, as is more probable, from its champaign
                    country. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The name is now connected
                        with Greek <foreign xml:lang="greek">kh=pos</foreign>
                        <quote>orchard</quote> or <quote>garden</quote> not (as Livy thought) with
                            <hi rend="italics">campus</hi>
                        <quote>plain.</quote>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Now they captured it after being admitted by
                    the Etruscans —who were worn out with fighting —to a share in the city and its
                    fields; then, on a holiday, when the old settlers were heavy with sleep and
                    feasting, the newcomers fell upon them in the night and slew them. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the train of these events, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">The events described in chap.
                        xxxvi.</note> the consuls whom I have named took up their duties, on the
                    13th of December. By this time not only had those who had been dispatched for
                    this purpose reported that a Volscian invasion was imminent, but <milestone
                        n="4??" unit="section"/> envoys from the Latins, and the Hernici as well,
                    announced that never before had the Volscians been more energetic, whether in
                    selecting generals or in levying an army; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that
                    everywhere men were muttering that they must either give up for ever all
                    thoughts of arms and war, and submit to the yoke, or must not lag behind those
                    with whom they were contending for <pb n="p.379"/> supremacy, either in courage
                    or in endurance or in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 423</note> military discipline. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Their tidings were true, but they caused no answerable activity among the
                    senators; and Gaius Sempronius, to whom the command had been assigned by lot,
                    trusting to fortune as though it were the most constant thing in the world,
                    because he had commanded the victorious nation against the people they had
                    defeated, conducted everything so carelessly and rashly that Roman discipline
                    was more in evidence in the Volscian army than in the Roman. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly Fortune, as on many another occasion, waited on
                    desert. In the first battle, which Sempronius entered without caution or
                    deliberation, his line was not strengthened with reserves nor was his cavalry
                    skilfully posted, when the fighting began. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    battle-cries were the first intimation how the affair was likely to go;
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> for the enemy's was louder and fuller,
                    that of the Romans dissonant and uneven and, dragging more with each repetition,
                    betrayed the faintness of their hearts. This caused the enemy to charge the more
                    boldly, thrusting with shields and making play with swords. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> On the Roman side helmets nodded, as their wearers looked
                    this way and that for help, and irresolute soldiers made falteringly for the
                    nearest group; at one moment the standards would be left behind by the retreat
                    of the front-rankers, at the next they would be falling back among their proper
                    maniples. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> It was not yet a definite flight,
                    not yet a victory; the Romans sought rather to protect themselves than to fight;
                    the Volscians advanced and bore hard against the Roman line, but saw more of
                    their enemies killed than running away. </p>
                <pb n="p.381"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But now the Romans were everywhere <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 423</note> falling
                    back, and it was in vain that Sempronius the consul upbraided or encouraged
                    them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was no virtue either in his
                    authority or in his dignity; and his men would presently have shown the enemy
                    their backs, had not a cavalry decurion <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">decurion</hi> commanded a <hi
                            rend="italics">decuria</hi> (ten men). There were three <hi
                            rend="italics">decuriae</hi> in a <hi rend="italics">turma,</hi> or
                        squadron, and ten <hi rend="italics">turmae</hi> in the three centuries of
                        horse which accompanied a legion. </note> named Sextus Tempanius, just as
                    the situation was becoming desperate, come with prompt courage to the rescue.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In a loud voice he cried out that the
                    horsemen who wished to save the state should leap down from their horses, and
                    when the troopers in every squadron had bestirred themselves as if at the
                    command of the consul, he added: <quote> Unless this bucklered <note
                            anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">parma</hi> (
                                <quote>buckler</quote> or <quote>target</quote> ) was the trooper's
                            shield, much smaller than the <hi rend="italics">scutum</hi> of the
                            foot-soldier. </note> cohort stops the enemy's rush it is all over with
                        our supremacy. Follow my spear as your guidon; <note anchored="true"
                            place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">vexillum,</hi> a small red
                            flag, was used as a cavalry ensign. </note> show Romans and Volscians
                        that when you are mounted no cavalry are your equals, nor any infantry, when
                        you fight on foot! </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When a cheer had shown their approval of this
                    exhortation, he advanced with uplifted spear. Wherever they went they forced a
                    passage; holding their targets up before them, they charged where they saw the
                    distress of their friends was greatest. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    fortune of the day was restored at every point where their onset carried them;
                    nor was there any doubt that if those few men could have been present everywhere
                    at the same time the enemy would have turned tail. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the Volscian general saw that their
                    attack could not anywhere be stopped, he ordered his troops to give ground to
                    the men with bucklers, the enemy's new cohort, until, carried forward in their
                    rush, they should be cut off from their friends. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> On this being done, the horsemen were intercepted, and were unable to break
                    through in <pb n="p.383"/> the same way as they had got over, since their
                    enemies <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 423</note>
                    were most thickly crowded together where they had made their path. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> When the consul and the Roman legions could nowhere
                    see the soldiers who a moment before had been a shield to the entire army, they
                    pressed forward to save at any cost so many heroic men from being surrounded and
                    borne down by the enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Volscians, facing
                    two ways, sustained on one side the onset of the consul and the legions, and on
                    the other front pressed home their attack upon Tempanius and his troopers;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> who, having failed, in spite of many
                    attempts, to force their way through to their friends, had seized a certain
                    mound and, forming a circle, were defending themselves, not without taking
                    vengeance on their assailants. The battle did not end till nightfall. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Neither did the consul relax his efforts anywhere,
                    but kept the enemy engaged as long as there was any light. Darkness put a stop
                    to the indecisive struggle, and the terror in each camp was such, in consequence
                    of men's ignorance of the outcome, that both armies, abandoning their wounded
                    and a good part of their baggage, retreated to the nearest hills, as though
                    defeated. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Nevertheless the mound was besieged
                    till after midnight. But when word was brought to the besiegers that their camp
                    was abandoned, they too supposed that their side had been defeated, and every
                    man fled where his panic led him in the darkness. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Tempanius feared an ambush and kept his soldiers close till
                    daylight. Then, descending with a few followers to reconnoitre, he discovered by
                    questioning some wounded enemies that the camp of the Volscians was deserted,
                    whereupon he joyfully called his men down from the hill and made his way <pb
                        n="p.385"/> into the Roman camp. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> There he
                    found everything <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        423</note> abandoned and forlorn and the same desolation he had met with on
                    the ground of the enemy; and, before the Volsci could learn of their blunder and
                    return, he carried with him such of the wounded as he was able, and not knowing
                    what way the consul had gone, took the nearest road to the City. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thither the rumour of an unsuccessful
                    engagement and the abandonment of the camp had already made its way, and more
                    than all the rest the horsemen had been mourned, with public as well as private
                    lamentations. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The consul Fabius was keeping
                    watch before the gates —for the panic had permeated even the City —when cavalry
                    were espied a long way off, and caused no little trepidation, since men knew not
                    who they could be. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But being soon after
                    recognized, they turned the people's fear to such rejoicing that the City was
                    filled with the noise of congratulations on the safe and victorious return of
                    the horse; and from the houses which a little while before had been filled with
                    sadness and had bewailed their sons as dead, the inhabitants ran out into the
                    street, and trembling mothers and wives, heedless of decorum in their happiness,
                    hurried to meet the troops, and flung themselves with utter abandonment into the
                    arms of their loved ones, being scarcely able to control themselves for joy.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The plebeian tribunes, who had set a day
                    for the trial of Marcus Postumius and Titus Quinctius, because of their
                    responsibility for the reverse at Veii, thought a favourable opportunity was
                    afforded by the odium recently incurred by the consul Sempronius for renewing
                    men's displeasure with them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> So, having called
                    a meeting, they loudly declared that the state <pb n="p.387"/> had been betrayed
                    at Veii by its generals; and that <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 423</note> then, because they had gone scot free, the
                    army fighting with the Volsci had been betrayed by the consul, their heroic
                    cavalry given over to slaughter, and the camp basely abandoned. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then Gaius Junius, one of the tribunes, commanded the
                    cavalryman Tempanius to be called, and turning to him spoke as follows: <quote>
                        Sextus Tempanius, I ask you whether you think that Gaius Sempronius the
                        consul either joined battle at a suitable moment, or strengthened his line
                        with supports, or performed any of the duties of a good consul; <milestone
                            n="7" unit="section"/> and whether you yourself, when the Roman legions
                        had been beaten, dismounted the cavalry of your own motion and restored the
                        fortunes of the battle; then, when you and your troopers had been cut off
                        from our line, if either the consul himself came to your rescue or sent
                        supports; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> furthermore, whether you had any
                        help anywhere next day, or you and your cohort forced a way to the camp by
                        your own valour; whether you found any consul in the camp and any army, or a
                        deserted camp and wounded and forsaken soldiers. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> In the name of your courage and your loyalty, which
                        alone have preserved the republic in this war, you must now answer these
                        questions; finally you must tell us where Gaius Sempronius and our legions
                        are; whether you were abandoned, or yourself abandoned the consul and the
                        army; —in one word, whether we have been defeated or victorious. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> To these questions Tempanius is said to have
                    replied in homely terms but with a soldierly dignity, in which was neither
                    self-praise nor self-complacent criticism of others. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Touching the degree of skill in military matters possessed
                    by Gaius Sempronius, it <pb n="p.389"/> was not for a soldier, he said, to
                    appraise a general: <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        423</note> that had been the Roman People's business when it elected
                    Sempronius consul at the comitia. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was not,
                    therefore, to him that they must address inquiries concerning the strategy of
                    commanders and the qualifications of consuls; even the weighing of such
                    abilities demanded great mental and intellectual powers. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But that which he had seen he was able to report; and he
                    had seen the consul, before he had himself been cut off from the main army,
                    fighting in the front line, encouraging his men, and moving about amidst the
                    standards of the Romans and the enemy's missiles. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> He had afterwards been carried out of sight of his friends;
                    but still, from the din and shouting, he had made out that the struggle had been
                    prolonged till nightfall, and he did not believe that it had been possible to
                    break through to the hillock which he himself had held, in view of the enemy's
                    numbers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Where the army was, he did not know;
                    he supposed that, just as he himself had protected himself and his men by taking
                    up a strong position, so likewise the consul, in order to save his army, had
                    occupied a place of greater security than the camp. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> And he did not believe that the Volsci were any better off
                    than the Roman People; chance and darkness had at every point confused both
                    armies. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On his going on to beg that they would
                    not detain him, exhausted by toil and wounds, it is said that he was dismissed
                    with the highest praise, no less for his moderation than for his bravery.
                    Meanwhile the consul had already reached the shrine of Quies <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i. e.</hi> Sleep or Repose. </note> on the Labican road.
                    Thither wagons and beasts of burden were dispatched from the City, and brought
                    the soldiers back, weary from fighting and the <pb n="p.391"/> nightmarch.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> A little later the consul entered the
                    City, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 423</note>
                    and showed no less concern to extol Tempanius with well-merited praise than to
                    clear himself of blame. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> While the citizens
                    were grieving over their defeat, and were filled with resentment against their
                    commanders, Marcus Postumius, who had been military tribune with consular
                    authority at Veii, was brought before them for trial and condemned to pay a fine
                    of ten thousand pounds of bronze. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">Aes grave</hi> ( <quote>heavy bronze</quote> ) is used to
                        distinguish the original <hi rend="italics">as libralis</hi> ( <hi
                            rend="italics">i. e.</hi> of a pound in weight) from the reduced <hi
                            rend="italics">as</hi> of a later time. </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Titus Quinctius his colleague, having been
                    victorious both in the Volscian country, when consul under the auspices of the
                    dictator Postumius Tubertus, and at Fidenae, as lieutenant to the other
                    dictator, Mamercus Aemilius, shifted all the blame for the present campaign upon
                    his colleague who had already been condemned, and was acquitted by all the
                    tribes. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> It is said that the memory of his
                    father Cincinnatus, whom the people venerated, was a help to him, and also the
                    fact that Quinctius Capitolinus, now well-stricken in years, supplicated and
                    implored them not to suffer him, who had but a little time to live, to be the
                    bearer of such sad news to Cincinnatus. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The plebs elected in their absence Sextus
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 422</note>
                    Tempanius, Marcus Asellius, Tiberius Antistius, and Tiberius Spurillius to be
                    plebeian tribunes. These were men whom the cavalry had also chosen, at the
                    instance of Tempanius, to act as centurions over them. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> When they had dismounted to fight as infantry; see
                        chap. xxxviii. </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The senate, feeling that the hatred of
                    Sempronius made the title of consul offensive, ordered the election of military
                    tribunes with consular powers. The successful candidates were Lucius Manlius
                    Capitolinus, Quintus Antonius Merenda, Lucius Papirius Mugillanus. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> At the very beginning of the year Lucius Hortensius,
                    tribune of the plebs, brought an <pb n="p.393"/> action against Gaius
                    Sempronius, consul of the year <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 422</note> before. The tribune's four colleagues besought
                    him in full sight of the Roman People not to persecute their general, in whom
                    nothing could be reckoned amiss save his ill-fortune; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> but this Hortensius would not brook, regarding it as a test
                    of his perseverance and persuaded that the defendant was relying not on the
                    entreaties of the tribunes, which were thrown out merely to preserve
                    appearances, but on their veto. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> And so,
                    turning now to Sempronius, he demanded to be told where the well-known patrician
                    spirit was, and where the courage that placed its confident reliance upon
                    innocence; was it in the shadow of the tribunate that a former consul had found
                    a hiding-place? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And again, addressing his
                    colleagues, he asked, <quote> But what do you mean to do, if I persist in
                        prosecuting the defendant? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Will you rob
                        the people of their rights and overthrow the authority of the tribunes?
                    </quote> When they replied that the authority of the Roman People was supreme
                    over Sempronius and all other men, and that they neither desired nor were able
                    to annul the people's judgment; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but that if
                    their entreaties in behalf of their commander, who stood in the relation of a
                    parent to them, should prove ineffectual, they would put on mourning with him,
                    then Hortensius declared, <quote> The Roman plebs shall not see its tribunes
                        clad in mourning. Gaius Sempronius may go free, for me, since his command
                        has gained him this, to be so beloved by his soldiers. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Nor was the loyalty of the four tribunes more
                    pleasing to both plebs and senators than was the disposition of Hortensius to
                    yield so readily to reasonable entreaties. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Fortune now ceased to favour the Aequi, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy perhaps begins at this point to
                        follow another annalist, who had described a successful campaign of the
                        Aequi not noticed by his authority for what has just preceded. </note> who
                    had <pb n="p.395"/> accepted the dubious victory of the Volsci as their <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 422</note> own.
                        <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The next year Numerius Fabius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 421</note> Vibulanus
                    and Titus Quinctius Capitolinus, the son of Capitolinus, were consuls. Under the
                    leadership of Fabius, to whom this command had been assigned by lot, nothing
                    worthy of relation was accomplished. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Aequi
                    had scarce made an irresolute show of battle when they were routed and driven
                    disgracefully from the field, and the consul got no credit by the affair. He was
                    accordingly denied a triumph; but because he had relieved the ignominy incurred
                    by Sempronius's defeat, he was allowed to enter the City in an ovation. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But while the war had been concluded with less
                    of a struggle than men had feared, in the City tranquillity gave place to
                    unexpected and serious quarrels, which broke out between the plebs and the
                    senators, and began over the duplication of the number of quaestors. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> This measure —that besides the two city quaestors two
                    others should be elected to assist the consuls in the administration of wars
                    —was proposed by the consuls and received the hearty approval of the senate, but
                    the tribunes of the plebs made a fight to have half of the quaestors —hitherto
                    patricians had been chosen —taken from the plebs. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Against this provision both consuls and senators at first
                    exerted themselves with all their might; afterwards they were ready to concede
                    that, just as in the case of tribunes with consular powers, so likewise with the
                    quaestors, the people should be unrestricted in their choice; but making no
                    headway with this offer, they dropped the whole question of enlarging the number
                    of quaestors. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was then taken up where they
                    had left it by the tribunes; and other <pb n="p.397"/> revolutionary schemes
                    came to the fore in quick <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 421</note> succession, among them one for enacting an
                    agrarian law. When the senate, because of these disturbances, preferred that
                    consuls be elected rather than tribunes, yet was unable to pass a resolution on
                    account of tribunician vetoes, the government passed from the consuls to an
                    interrex; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> nor was even this accomplished
                    without a violent struggle, for the tribunes tried to prevent the patricians
                    from holding a meeting. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The greater part of
                    the ensuing year dragged on with contests between the new tribunes and several
                    interreges. At one time the tribunes would keep the patricians from meeting to
                    appoint an interrex; at another time they would interpose their veto against the
                    interrex, that the senate might not pass a resolution to hold the consular
                    elections. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Finally Lucius Papirius Mugillanus
                    was named interrex, and upbraiding now the senators, now the tribunes of the
                    plebs, reminded them how the state, abandoned and forsaken by men, had been
                    protected by the providential care of Heaven, and existed by the grace of the
                    Veientine truce and the dilatory policy of the Aequi. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> If an alarm should break out in that quarter, was it their
                    pleasure that the republic should be caught without a patrician magistrate? that
                    there should be no army, no general to enrol an army? <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Or did they expect to beat off a foreign foe with a civil
                    war? But if both should come at once, the help of the gods themselves would
                    scarce suffice to stay the destruction of the Roman commonwealth. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Why would they not every man abate somewhat of his
                    full rights and compromise harmoniously on a middle course, the Fathers
                    consenting that military tribunes should be chosen instead of consuls, the <pb
                        n="p.399"/> tribunes interposing no veto to prevent four quaestors <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 421</note> being
                    taken promiscuously from plebeians and patricians by free election of the
                    people? </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The election of tribunes was held first. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 420</note> The
                    tribunes with consular powers who were chosen were all patricians, namely Lucius
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus (for the third time), Lucius Furius Medullinus (for the
                    second time), Marcus Manlius, and Aulus Sempronius Atratinus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The last-named held the election for quaestors. Among the
                    several plebeians who sought the place were the son of a plebeian tribune, named
                    Aulus Antistius, and the brother of another, Sextus Pompilius. Yet neither the
                    authority nor the support of these men could prevent the people from giving the
                    preference, because of their noble birth, to men whose fathers and grandfathers
                    they had seen consuls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This made all the
                    tribunes furious, but more than all the rest Pompilius and Antistius, who were
                    incensed at the defeat of their kinsmen. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> What
                    in the world, they asked, was the meaning of this? Had neither their own
                    services nor the wrongs which the patricians had inflicted, nor even the
                    pleasure of exercising a right —since what had before been unlawful was now
                    permitted —availed to elect a single quaestor from the plebs, let alone a
                    military tribune? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Of no avail had been a
                    father's entreaties for his son, a brother's for his brother, not though they
                    had been tribunes of the plebs, and invested with an inviolable office, created
                    for the protection of liberty. There was fraud in the matter, beyond question,
                    and Aulus Sempronius had employed more artifice than honesty in the election.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was by his wrong-doing, they
                    complained, that their relations had been defeated for office. And so, <pb
                        n="p.401"/> since they could not attack the man himself, secure <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 420</note> as he was
                    not only in his innocence but in the magistracy which he was filling, they
                    turned their anger upon Gaius Sempronius, the cousin of Atratinus; and
                    prosecuted him, with the co-operation of their colleague Marcus Canuleius, on
                    the score of the humiliation suffered in the Volscian war. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The same tribunes frequently mentioned in the senate the
                    division of the public lands, a measure which Gaius Sempronius had always
                    stoutly resisted, for they reckoned —and rightly —that either he would abandon
                    the cause and his defence would become a matter of less concern to the
                    patricians, or that persevering in his attitude he would give offence, up to the
                    moment of his trial, to the plebeians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                    chose to face the storm of unpopularity and to injure his own cause rather than
                    be found wanting in that of the nation; and he held fast to the same opinion,
                    that there should be no largess, for that would redound to the advantage of the
                    three tribunes. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was not land for the plebs
                    they were then looking for, he declared, but hatred for himself; he was as ready
                    as another to confront that tempest with a courageous heart; nor ought the
                    senate to set so high a value upon himself or any other citizen that their
                    tenderness for him should bring about a general disaster. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> His spirit was not a whit less firm when the day of trial
                    came. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He pleaded his own cause; the senators
                    exerted in vain every means of mollifying the plebs; and he was condemned to pay
                    a fine of fifteen thousand <hi rend="italics">asses.</hi>
                </p>
                <p> The same year a Vestal virgin named Postumia was put on trial for unchastity.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> She was innocent of the charge, though
                    open to suspicion because of her <pb n="p.403"/> pretty clothes and the
                    unmaidenly freedom of her <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 420</note> wit. After she had been remanded and then
                    acquitted, the pontifex maximus, in the name of the college, commanded her to
                    abstain from jests, and to dress rather with regard to sanctity than coquetry.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In this same year Cumae, a city which the
                    Greeks then held, was captured by the Campanians. </p>
                <p> The ensuing year had as military tribunes with consular powers Agrippa Menenius
                    Lanatus, Publius Lucretius Tricipitinus, and Spurius Nautius Rutulus. <milestone
                        n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was a year remarkable, thanks to the good
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 419-18</note>
                    fortune of the Roman People, for a great danger but not a disaster. The slaves
                    conspired to set fire to the City at points remote from one another, and, while
                    the people should be busy everywhere with rescuing their houses, to seize the
                    Citadel and the Capitol with an armed force. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Jupiter brought their wicked schemes to naught, and on the evidence of two of
                    their number the guilty were arrested and punished. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Each informant was rewarded from the public treasury with
                    ten thousand pounds of bronze —which passed for wealth in those days —and with
                    freedom. </p>
                <p> The Aequi then began to prepare again for war; and word was brought to Rome on
                    good authority that new enemies, the Labicani, were making common cause with the
                    old ones. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> As for the Aequi, the citizens had
                    by now grown accustomed to war with them, as to an annual occurrence; but they
                    dispatched envoys to Labici, and having got them back with an ambiguous answer,
                    from which it appeared that though war was not as yet being organized, yet peace
                    would not long continue, they commissioned the Tusculans to watch that no fresh
                    outbreak should occur at that place. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                <pb n="p.405"/>
                <p> To the military tribunes with consular authority <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 419-418</note> who held office the
                    ensuing year, Lucius Sergius Fidenas, Marcus Papirius Mugillanus, and Gaius
                    Servilius, son of the Priscus who as dictator had captured Fidenae, there came,
                        <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> just as they had entered on their
                    magistracy, ambassadors from Tusculum, who announced that the Labicani had armed
                    and, after devastating the Tusculan countryside in company with an Aequian army,
                    had encamped on Algidus. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Thereupon war was
                    declared against the Labicani, and the senate resolved that two of the tribunes
                    should proceed to the front, while one attended to matters in Rome. At this a
                    dispute immediately broke out amongst the tribunes, each of whom boasted of his
                    superiority as a general and spurned the care of the City as a thankless and
                    ignoble task. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> While the astonished senators
                    watched this unseemly rivalry amongst the colleagues, Quintus Servilius
                    exclaimed, <quote> Since you have no respect for this order nor for the
                        republic, a father's authority shall end your quarrel. My son shall preside
                        over the City, without recourse to lots. I only hope that those who are
                        eager to make the campaign may conduct it with more consideration and
                        harmony than they display in seeking it. </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> It was determined not to make a general levy
                    on the entire people, but ten tribes were chosen by lot. From these the two
                    tribunes enrolled the men of military age and led them to war. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The bickerings which had commenced between them in the City
                    grew much hotter in the camp, from the same eagerness to command; they could not
                    agree on anything; each strove for his own opinion; each desired his own plans
                    and his own orders to be the <pb n="p.407"/> only valid ones; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> each despised the other and was <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 419-418</note> in turn despised by
                    him, until at last, reproved by their lieutenants, they arranged to exercise the
                    supreme command on alternate days. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When the
                    report of this reached Rome, it is said that Quintus Servilius, taught by years
                    and experience, besought the immortal gods that the strife between the tribunes
                    might not result more disastrously to the republic than had been the case at
                    Veii, and as though certain defeat were imminent, urged his son to enlist
                    soldiers and make ready arms. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor was he a
                    false prophet. For under the leadership of Lucius Sergius, whose day it was to
                    command, the Romans found themselves in an unfavourable position close to the
                    enemy's camp, whither they had been drawn, when the Aequi feigned fear and
                    retired to their rampart, by the vain hope of capturing it; and there they were
                    suddenly attacked by the Aequi and driven pellmell down a sloping valley, where
                    many of them, as they rather tumbled down than retreated, were overtaken and put
                    to the sword. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That day they defended their
                    camp with difficulty, and on the next, when the enemy had almost surrounded it,
                    they abandoned it by a disgraceful flight through the opposite gate. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> The generals and their lieutenants and such of the
                    army's strength as kept to the standards made for Tusculum: the others,
                    scattering through the fields, this way and that, hastened to Rome by divers
                    roads and reported a much heavier defeat than had been sustained. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> There was the less dismay for the reason that the
                    event had tallied with men's apprehensions, and because reserves which they
                    could look to in the hour of danger had been made ready by the tribune <pb
                        n="p.409"/> of the soldiers. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It was by his
                    orders too that the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        419-418</note> lesser magistrates had quieted the confusion in the City,
                    when the scouts whom he had hurriedly sent out reported that the generals and
                    the army were at Tusculum, and that the enemy had not broken camp. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> And —what raised men's courage most — Quintus
                    Servilius Priscus was in consequence of a senatorial decree named dictator —a
                    man whose clear vision in public affairs the state had proved on many previous
                    occasions, but particularly in the outcome of this war, because he alone had
                    viewed the quarrel of the tribunes with anxiety, before their defeat. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Having appointed his son, by whom, when military
                    tribune, he had himself been pronounced dictator, to be master of the horse, —as
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> some authorities have recorded; for
                    others write that Servilius Ahala was master of the horse that year, —he set out
                    with a fresh army for the war, sent for the troops which were at Tusculum, and
                    fixed his camp two miles from the enemy. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In consequence of their success, the Aequi
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 417-416</note>
                    had taken over the arrogance and carelessness which the Roman generals had
                    shown, and the result was seen in the very first battle. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> When the dictator had attacked with his cavalry and had
                    thrown the enemy's front ranks into confusion, he ordered the legions to advance
                    rapidly, and when one of his standard-bearers hesitated, cut him down.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> So eager for combat were the troops, that
                    the Aequi could not stop their rush, and when, defeated in the field, they had
                    withdrawn to their camp in a disordered flight, it was stormed with less
                    expenditure of time and effort than the battle itself had cost. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Having captured and sacked the camp, the dictator <pb
                        n="p.411"/> relinquished the plunder to his soldiers; and the cavalry, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 417-416</note> which
                    had pursued the enemy as they fled from their encampment, came back with the
                    report that all <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the Labicani, after their
                    defeat, and a great part of the Aequi, had taken refuge in Labici. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Next day the army marched to Labici and, drawing a
                    cordon about the town, stormed it with ladders and plundered it. Leading his
                    victorious army back to Rome, the dictator resigned his office eight days after
                    his appointment; and the senate seized the opportunity, before the tribunes of
                    the plebs could stir up agrarian troubles by proposing a division of the Labican
                    territory, to resolve, in a largely-attended meeting, that a colony should be
                    planted in Labici. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Fifteen hundred colonists
                    were sent from the City, and each received two <hi rend="italics">iugera.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The <hi rend="italics">iugerum</hi>
                        was about five-eighths of an acre. </note>
                </p>
                <p> The year that followed the capture of Labici, having as military tribunes with
                    consular powers Agrippa Menenius Lanatus, Gaius Servilius Structus, and Publius
                    Lucretius Tricipitinus (all these for the second time), together with Spurius
                    Rutilius Crassus; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and the succeeding year,
                    with Aulus Sempronius Atratinus (for his third term) and Marcus Papirius
                    Mugillanus and Spurius Nautius Rutulus (for their second) were a period of
                    tranquillity in foreign relations but of civil discord arising out of agrarian
                    laws. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="48" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Those who stirred up the people were Spurius
                    Maecilius, tribune of the plebs for the fourth time, and Marcus Metilius, for
                    the third, both having been elected in their absence. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> On their proposing a law that the land which had been
                    captured from enemies should be divided up among the citizens, a plebiscite
                    which would mean the confiscation of the <pb n="p.413"/> fortunes of a great
                    part of the nobles —for <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> there <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 417-416</note> was
                    scarcely any land, as might be expected in the case of a city situated on alien
                    soil, which had not been gained by force of arms; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> nor was much, if any, of that which had been sold or
                    assigned by the state held by other than plebeians, —it appeared that a
                    desperate struggle was at hand between the plebs and the patricians. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> The military tribunes had hit upon no plan of action
                    either in the senate or in the private conferences which they held with the
                    leading men, when Appius Claudius, grandson of him who had been decemvir for
                    drawing up the laws, himself the youngest of the council of senators, announced
                    —so <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> the story goes —that he was bringing them
                    from his house an old family device; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> for it
                    had been his great-grandfather <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Really
                        his great-great-grandfather ( <hi rend="italics">abavus</hi> ). </note>
                    Appius Claudius who had pointed out to the senators that the only way to break
                    the power of the tribunes lay through the veto of their colleagues. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> It was not difficult for the leading men of the state
                    to induce upstart politicians <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        term <hi rend="italics">novus homo</hi> was usually applied to a man who was
                        the first of his family to hold a curule office (curule aedileship,
                        praetorship, consulship). </note> to change their minds, if they would but
                    suit their discourse meantime rather to the exigencies of the crisis than to
                    their lofty station. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The sentiments of such
                    fellows varied with their fortunes: when they saw that their colleagues, by
                    taking the lead in the management of affairs, had appropriated all the favour of
                    the populace in advance and had left no room there for themselves, they would
                    incline without reluctance to the cause of the senate, by supporting which they
                    might gain the goodwill not only of the order as a whole, but also of the
                    foremost senators. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When they had all
                    expressed their approval, and especially Quintus Servilius Priscus, who praised
                    the young man as <pb n="p.415"/> one who had not degenerated from the Claudian
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 417-416</note>
                    stock, everybody was given the task of inducing such of the tribunician college
                    as he could to interpose their vetoes. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    senate adjourned and the leading members began to canvass the tribunes.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> By arguments in which they mingled
                    warnings with the promise that their action would earn the tribunes the personal
                    gratitude of individuals, as well as that of the senate as a body, they got six
                    men to promise their opposition. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Next day
                    when the senate, in accordance with a preconcerted plan, had taken up the
                    question of the sedition which Maecilius and Metilius were beginning by
                    proposing a donation of the most objectionable type, the principal senators made
                    speeches in which each took occasion to say that he could think of nothing to
                    suggest and saw no help for the situation anywhere save in the assistance of the
                    tribunes; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> this was the power to whose
                    protection the harassed republic, like a private citizen in distress, now fled
                    for succour; it was a, glorious thing both for the men themselves and for their
                    office that the tribunate possessed no less strength for the resistance of its
                    wicked colleagues than for troubling the senate and promoting discord between
                    the orders. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Loud shouts were then heard from
                    the entire senate and appeals were addressed to the tribunes from every part of
                    the Curia. Then, after silence had been obtained, those who had been won over by
                    the favour of the chief senators declared their readiness to veto the measure
                    which their colleagues had proposed but the senate deemed subversive of the
                    republic. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The thanks of the senate were voted
                    the protesters. The authors of the bill convened an assembly, and accusing their
                        <pb n="p.417"/> colleagues of being traitors to the interests of the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 417-416</note> plebs
                    and slaves of the consulars, and in other ways bitterly denouncing them,
                    withdrew their measure. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="49" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> There would have been two wars in the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 415-411</note>
                    ensuing year, in which Publius Cornelius Cossus, Gaius Valerius Potitus, Quintus
                    Quinctius Cincinnatus, and Numerius Fabius Vibulanus were military tribunes with
                    consular powers, had not the war with Veii been delayed, thanks to the
                    superstition of the <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> Veientine leaders, whose
                    farms an overflow of the Tiber had laid waste, chiefly by ruining the
                    farmhouses. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At the same time the Aequi were
                    deterred by the defeat they had suffered three years before from marching to the
                    assistance of the Bolani, a tribe of their own race. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> These people had made incursions into the neighbouring
                    territory of Labici and attacked the new settlers. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The consequences of this outrage they had hoped to avoid by
                    means of the co-operation of all the Aequi; but, having been abandoned by their
                    friends, they lost their town and their lands, in a war which does not even
                    merit description, as the result of a siege and a single skirmish. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> An attempt on the part of Lucius Decius, a plebeian
                    tribune, to carry a law providing that colonists should be sent to Bolae too, as
                    well as to Labici, was frustrated through the intervention of his colleagues,
                    who intimated that they would permit no plebiscite to pass unless it had the
                    warrant of the senate. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Bolae was retaken the next year, and the Aequi
                    planted a colony there and strengthened the town with new defenders. Rome now
                    had the following military tribunes with consular powers, Gnaeus Cornelius
                    Cossus, Lucius Valerius Potitus, Quintus Fabius Vibulanus (for the second time),
                    and Marcus <pb n="p.419"/> Postumius Regillensis. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> To this last was intrusted <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 415-414</note> the campaign against
                    the Aequi. He was a wrongheaded man, yet he showed it more in the hour of
                    victory than during the campaign. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> For he was
                    energetic in raising an army and leading it to Bolae, where, after breaking the
                    spirit of the Aequi in some trifling engagements, he finally forced an entrance
                    into the town. He then diverted the quarrel from the enemy to his
                    fellow-citizens; and though he had proclaimed at the time of the attack that the
                    booty should belong to the soldiers, when he had taken the town he broke his
                    promise. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This, I am inclined to believe, was
                    the cause of the army's resentment, rather than the fact that in a
                    recently-plundered city inhabited by new settlers, there was less booty than the
                    tribune had predicted. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The ill-feeling was
                    increased, when, being sent for by his colleagues on account of tribunician
                    disturbances, he had returned to the City, by a stupid and almost insane remark
                    he was heard to make in an assembly, where Marcus Sextius, a plebeian tribune,
                    in introducing an agrarian measure, announced that he should propose also that
                    colonists be dispatched to Bolae —for it was proper, he said, that the city and
                    lands of the Bolani should belong to those who had captured them in war.
                        <quote>Woe to my soldiers,</quote> exclaimed Postumius, <quote>unless they
                        hold their peace!</quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> —a saying which presently, on being reported
                    to the senators, offended them no less than it had the assembly. And the tribune
                    of the plebs, a keen and not uneloquent man, having got for one of his
                    adversaries a man of haughty spirit and unbridled tongue, whom he could irritate
                    and provoke to say things that would not only make himself disliked <pb
                        n="p.421"/> but his cause and the entire senate as well, made a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 415-414</note> point
                    of involving Postumius in a dispute more <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/>
                    often than any other member of the college of military tribunes. On this
                    particular occasion, after that savage and brutal threat, he cried, <quote> Do
                        you hear him, Quirites, threatening his soldiers with punishment like
                        slaves? <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Shall this wild beast seem to
                        you, notwithstanding, more deserving of so great an office than those who
                        would present you with a city and with lands, and send you out to colonies;
                        who would provide a home for your old age; who fight for your interests
                        against these cruel and insolent adversaries? <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> And does it surprise you that so few espouse your
                        cause? What are they to expect of you? Those offices which you give by
                        preference to your opponents, rather than to the champions of the Roman
                        People? <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> You groaned just now when you
                        heard his remark. What of it? If you should be asked to vote this very
                        moment, you would elect this man who threatens you with chastisement in
                        preference to those who wish to secure you lands and houses and fortunes.
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="50" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When this saying of Postumius reached the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 414</note>
                    troops, it stirred up much greater indignation in the camp: did the man who had
                    fraudulently cut off his soldiers from their spoils also threaten them with
                    punishment? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And while they murmured openly,
                    the quaestor Publius Sestius, thinking that the mutiny could be quelled with the
                    same violence which had occasioned it, sent a lictor to arrest a certain
                    brawling soldier; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> whereupon shouts and
                    objurgations broke forth, and Sestius was hit with a stone and retreated from
                    the scuffle, while the man who had wounded him thundered after him that the
                    quaestor <pb n="p.423"/> had got what the general had threatened to give his
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 414</note> men.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Being summoned to deal with this
                    disturbance, Postumius aggravated everything by his harsh inquisitions and
                    savage punishments. Finally his anger got beyond all bounds, and when the shout
                    of those whom he had ordered to be put to death under a hurdle <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> See the account, in I. li. 9, of the
                        execution of Herdonius Here water is not mentioned, and the victim was
                        probably placed on the ground and crushed beneath the stones which were
                        heaped upon the hurdle. </note> had caused a crowd to gather, he ran down in
                    a frenzy of passion from his tribunal to those who would have interrupted the
                    execution. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> There, when the lictors and
                    centurions assailed the mob and tried to drive them back, on this side and on
                    that, resentment ran so high that a military tribune was overwhelmed with a
                    volley of stones from his own soldiers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This
                    dreadful deed having been announced in Rome, the tribunes of the soldiers wished
                    to institute a senatorial inquiry into the death of their colleague, but the
                    plebeian tribunes interposed their vetoes. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    dispute was closely connected with another struggle. The senators had become
                    apprehensive lest the plebs, what with their fear of investigations and their
                    indignation, should elect military tribunes from their own class; they therefore
                    used all their efforts to have consuls chosen. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Since the plebeian tribunes would not allow the resolution of the senate <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Providing for the investigation of the
                        murder of Postumius. </note> to go through, and also vetoed the election of
                    consuls, the state reverted to an interregnum. The victory then rested with the
                    senators. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius Vibulanus, acting as interrex,
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 413</note> held
                    an election, and Aulus Cornelius Cossus and Lucius Furius Medullinus were chosen
                    consuls. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In their consulship, early in the
                    year, a senatorial resolution was passed that the tribunes should bring the
                    investigation of Postumius's murder before the plebs at the earliest possible
                    moment, and that the <pb n="p.425"/> plebs should appoint whomsoever they wished
                    to <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 413</note> have
                    charge of the inquiry. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The plebs unanimously
                    referred the matter to the consuls. They accomplished their task with the utmost
                    moderation and leniency, punishing a few only, —and these are generally believed
                    to have committed suicide; —yet <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> they were
                    unable to prevent the transaction from being bitterly resented by the plebs, who
                    complained that the measures which had been proposed in their interests lay all
                    this while neglected, whereas the law that was passed concerning their
                    punishment and their lives was carried out at once, and most effectually. It
                    would have been a very suitable occasion, now that the mutiny had been avenged,
                    to appease their anger by offering to divide the Bolan territory. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Had the senators done this, they would have lessened
                    men's desire for the agrarian law which was meant to expel the patricians from
                    their wrongful occupation of the public domain. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> As it was, a sense of injury was aroused by the very circumstance that the
                    nobility not only persisted in retaining the public lands, which they held by
                    force, but would not even divide among the plebeians the unoccupied ground which
                    had recently been taken from the enemy and would soon, they thought, become,
                    like all the rest, the booty of a few. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The same year the Volsci laid waste the
                    borders of the Hernici, and the legions were led out to meet them by the consul
                    Furius. Not finding the enemy there, they captured Ferentinum, to which a great
                    number of Volsci had retired. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There was less
                    plunder there than they had expected, because the Volsci, having small hopes of
                    defending the town, removed their possessions by night and abandoned <pb
                        n="p.427"/> it; next day, when it was taken, it was practically <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 413</note> deserted.
                    The town itself and its territory were given to the Hernici. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="52" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After this year, which the moderation of the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 412-411</note>
                    tribunes had made a quiet one, came the plebeian tribuneship of Lucius Icilius,
                    when Quintus Fabius Ambustus and Gaius Furius Paculus were consuls. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> While Icilius, at the very outset of the year, was
                    endeavouring to stir up sedition by the promulgation of agrarian laws, as
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> if it had been the appointed task of his
                    name and family, a pestilence broke out, which, though it was more threatening
                    than fatal, diverted men's thoughts from the Forum and political conflicts to
                    their homes and the care of the sick, and is thought to have been less hurtful
                    than the sedition would have been. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The state
                    had escaped with very few deaths, considering the great number of those who had
                    fallen ill, when the year of pestilence was succeeded, in the consulship of
                    Marcus Papirius Atratinus and Gaius Nautius Rutulus, by a scarcity of corn,
                    owing to the neglect of tillage usual at such times. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Indeed the famine would have been more baneful than the
                    disease, had they not supplemented the supply of corn by dispatching emissaries
                    to all the peoples round about who dwelt on the Tuscan sea or by the Tiber, to
                    purchase it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Samnites who held Capua and
                    Cumae insolently refused to permit the envoys to trade with them, but the
                    Sicilian tyrants, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy probably has
                        Dionysius I. in mind; though in reality it was several years later when he
                        became tyrant of Syracuse. </note> on the contrary, lent them generous
                    assistance; and the largest supplies of all were brought down the Tiber, with
                    the hearty goodwill of the Etruscans. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls experienced a lack of men in the afflicted City, and, being unable to
                    find more than one senator for an embassy, were obliged to add <pb n="p.429"/>
                    two knights to each. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> With the exception of the
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 412-411</note>
                    disease and the shortage of corn, there was no internal or foreign trouble
                    during these two years. But no sooner had these anxieties departed, than there
                    came an outbreak of all the ills which were wont to harass the state, domestic
                    quarrels and war abroad. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="53" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the consulship of Marcus Aemilius and <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 410</note> Gaius
                    Valerius Potitus the Aequi prepared to go to war, and the Volsci, though they
                    did not take up arms as a nation, made the campaign as volunteers serving for
                    pay. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> When, on the rumour of their advance, —
                    for they had already crossed over into Latin and Hernican territory, —Valerius
                    the consul was raising troops, and Marcus Menenius, tribune of the plebs and
                    proposer of an agrarian law, was obstructing the levy, and everybody who did not
                        <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> wish to go was availing himself of the
                    tribune's protection and refusing the oath, on a sudden came the news that the
                    citadel of Carventum had been seized by the enemy. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This humiliation not only gave the patricians the means of
                    stirring up feeling against Menenius, but supplied the rest of the tribunes, who
                    had already been persuaded to veto the agrarian law, with a more justifiable
                    pretext for resisting their colleague. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    dispute was long drawn out. The consuls called gods and men to witness that the
                    responsibility for whatever defeat or disgrace had already been or threatened to
                    be visited on them by the enemy would rest with Menenius, because of his
                    interference with the levy; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Menenius, on the
                    other hand, protested loudly that if the occupants of the public domain would
                    surrender their illegal possession of it, he was prepared to withdraw his
                    opposition to the muster. At this juncture nine tribunes interposed a resolution
                        <pb n="p.431"/> which ended the contention. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> They proclaimed in <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 410</note> the name of the college that they would support the consul
                    Gaius Valerius if, in enforcing the levy, he resorted, despite the veto of their
                    colleague, to fines and other forms of coercion against those who refused to
                    serve. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Armed with this decree, the consul
                    caused the few who appealed to the tribune to be haled before him; the rest were
                    cowed into taking the oath. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The army marched
                    to the citadel of Carventum; and although the soldiers were hated by the consul
                    and returned his hostility, yet the moment they came to the place, they manfully
                    drove out the garrison and recovered the stronghold, which had been laid open to
                    attack by the negligence that had permitted men to slip away from the garrison
                    in quest of booty. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There was a considerable
                    accumulation of spoils from this constant raiding, because everything had been
                    heaped up there for safety. All this the consul ordered the quaestors to sell at
                    auction and place the proceeds in the public treasury, giving out word that the
                    army should share in the plunder only when the men had not refused to serve.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This increased the enmity of plebs and
                    soldiers towards the consul. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> And so when he
                    entered the City in an ovation, as the senate had decreed, the soldiers, with
                    military freedom, shouted out rude verses now abusing the consul and now
                    praising Menenius, while at every mention of the tribune's name the enthusiasm
                    of the attendant populace vied with the voices of the men in cheers and
                    applause. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This circumstance caused the
                    patricians more anxiety than the sauciness of the soldiers towards the consul,
                    which was virtually an established custom; and as though they made no question
                    that Menenius would be chosen for one of the military tribunes, if he were <pb
                        n="p.433"/> a candidate, they held a consular election and so <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 410</note> excluded
                    him. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls elected were Gnaeus Cornelius
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 409</note>
                    Cossus and (for the second time) Lucius Furius Medullinus. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Never before had the plebs felt so aggrieved that they were
                    not allowed to choose military tribunes. They showed their disappointment, and
                    likewise avenged it, at the election of quaestors, when plebeians were for the
                    first time chosen to that office; though among the four to be elected room was
                    made for one patrician, Caeso Fabius Ambustus. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Three plebeians, Quintus Silius, Publius Aelius, and Publius Pupius, were
                    preferred before young men of the most distinguished families. I find that those
                    who encouraged the people to make so free with their votes were the Icilii.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Three members of that family, a family
                    most hostile to the patricians, had been made plebeian tribunes for that year,
                    in consequence of the many great hopes they had held out to the populace, always
                    more than eager to accept such promises. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These
                    men had declared that they would make no move in their behalf, if even in the
                    election of quaestors —the only election which the senate had left open to both
                    classes —the people could not find sufficient resolution to accomplish what they
                    had so long wished to do and the laws permitted. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> And so the plebs felt that they had won a great victory, not estimating the
                    significance of that quaestorship by the limits of the office itself, but
                    feeling that the way to consulships and triumphs was thrown open to new men.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The patricians, on the other hand, were as
                    angry as though they had not merely shared their offices with the plebs but had
                    lost them. They said that if such <pb n="p.435"/> things were to be, it was
                    wrong for them to rear <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin"
                        >B.C. 409</note> children, who after being driven out from the places of
                    their forefathers would behold others in possession of their honours, and would
                    be left, without power or authority, to serve no other purpose than to offer up
                    sacrifices, as salii and flamens, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                            <hi rend="italics">salii</hi> were a very ancient college of priests
                        whose name was derived from a weapon-dance which figured in their ritual.
                        The <hi rend="italics">flamen</hi> ('kindler') was the special priest of
                        some god, thus the <hi rend="italics">Flamen Dialis</hi> was attached to the
                        cult of Jupiter, the <hi rend="italics">Flamen Martialis</hi> to that of
                        Mars, etc. </note> for the people. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    feelings of both sides were overwrought. The plebs had plucked up courage and
                    they had three very distinguished leaders for the popular cause. The patricians,
                    perceiving that every election where the plebs were free to choose either sort
                    of candidate would be like that of the quaestors, strove to bring about a
                    consular election, which was not yet open to both orders. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The Icilii, on the contrary, maintained that military
                    tribunes should be chosen; it was high time, they said, that the plebs were
                    given their share of honours. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But the consuls had no measure on foot which
                    the tribunes could oppose and so wring from them what they wanted, when, by a
                    wonderful piece of luck, the Volsci and Aequi were reported to have crossed the
                    border and raided the lands of the Latins and the Hernici. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> As the consuls, in order to meet this invasion, were
                    commencing to raise an army, in pursuance of a resolution of the senate, the
                    tribunes obstructed the levy with all their might, declaring that the incident
                    had been a fortunate one for the plebeians and themselves. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> There were three of them, and they were all very active and
                    belonged to a family which might now be called noble, considering that they were
                    plebeians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Two of them assumed the task of
                    keeping constant watch on the consuls, each taking one of them; to the third was
                    given the duty of haranguing the plebs, for the purpose, now of <pb n="p.437"/>
                    restraining, now of urging them on. The consuls could <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 409</note> neither bring about the
                    levy, nor the tribunes the election, they desired. Then, as fortune was
                    inclining to the cause of the plebs, came couriers who reported that while the
                    soldiers who were in garrison at the citadel of Carventum had dispersed to
                    plunder, the Aequi had come, and killing the few guards, had rushed the place.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Some of the soldiers had been cut down as
                    they were hurrying back to the fortress, others as they roamed the fields. This
                    national reverse added strength to the contention of the tribunes. It was in
                    vain they were importuned to cease at last their opposition to the war.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They yielded neither to the public need
                    nor to men's hatred of themselves, and carried their point —that the senate
                    should pass a decree for the election of military tribunes. It was, however,
                    expressly provided that no one should be accepted as a candidate who had that
                    year been tribune of the plebs, and that no tribune of the Plebs should be
                    re-elected. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> It is evident that the senate
                    wished to stigmatize the Icilii, whom they charged with seeking the consulship
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Livy here employs
                            <quote>consulship</quote> as a convenient, if not quite accurate,
                        substitute for <quote>consular tribuneship.</quote>
                    </note> as a reward for their seditious conduct while tribunes. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The levy was then begun and preparation made for war, with
                    the consent of all the orders. Whether both consuls marched to the citadel of
                    Carventum, or one stayed behind to hold an election, is uncertain in view of the
                    contradictory accounts of the authorities. Thus much is clear (for in this they
                    do not differ), that the Romans, after a long and futile siege, retired from the
                    citadel of Carventum and recaptured Verrugo, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> See iv. i. 4. Livy has not mentioned the previous loss
                        of Verrugo to the Volsci. </note> in the Volscian country, with the same
                    army, which spread great <pb n="p.439"/> devastation both among the Aequi and in
                    the <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 409</note>
                    territory of the Volsci, and gathered enormous spoils. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> At Rome, though the plebeians were so far
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 408</note>
                    victorious as to have the election they preferred, yet in the outcome of the
                    election the patricians won the day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> For the
                    military tribunes with consular authority were all three, contrary to the
                    universal expectation, chosen from the patricians, viz., Gaius Julius lulus,
                    Publius Cornelius Cossus, and Gaius Servilius Ahala. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The patricians are said to have employed a ruse (and the
                    Icilii taxed them with it at the time), in that they mixed a rabble of unworthy
                    competitors with the deserving, and the disgust which the notorious turpitude of
                    certain of them provoked turned the people against the plebeian candidates. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then came a rumour that the Volsci and Aequi,
                    whether encouraged by their defence of the citadel of Carventum or angered by
                    the loss of the garrison at Verrugo, had risen in prodigious strength;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that the Antiates were the head and front
                    of the war; that their envoys had gone about among the tribes of both races,
                    upbraiding their cowardice in having hidden behind their walls the year before
                    and allowed the Romans to pillage their lands and overwhelm the garrison at
                    Verrugo. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They would presently be sending out,
                    not merely armed expeditions across their borders, but colonies too; and not
                    only, they said, had the Romans divided up their possessions amongst themselves,
                    but they had even taken Ferentinum from them and bestowed it on the Hernici.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These words aroused indignation, and a
                    number of young men were enlisted wherever the envoys went. So the forces of all
                    the tribes drew together at Antium, where they encamped and waited for the
                    enemy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="p.441"/> When these things had been reported at Rome, <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 408</note> amid
                    excitement even greater than the situation warranted, the senate at once had
                    recourse to its final counsel in emergencies, and ordered the appointment of a
                    dictator. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> It is said that Julius and Cornelius
                    resented this, and that a very bitter discussion took place. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> In vain the leading senators complained that the military
                    tribunes were not amenable to senatorial control, and eventually appealed to the
                    tribunes of the plebs and reminded them that their authority had in a similar
                    case operated to restrain the consuls. But the tribunes of the plebs were
                    delighted with the want of harmony amongst the senators. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> They could give no assistance, they said, to men who did
                    not regard them as citizens, or even as human beings. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> If some day offices were thrown open to all, and they were
                    given a share in the government, they would then see to it that no proud
                    magistrate thwarted the decrees of the senate. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> Meanwhile let the patricians live with no regard for laws and magistracies,
                    and let the tribunes act as they saw fit. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This quarrel, so inopportune at a time when
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 407</note> a
                    great war was in hand, had quite taken possession of men's thoughts, and for a
                    long time Julius and Cornelius —first <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> one and
                    then the other —had argued that, since they were themselves quite capable of
                    directing that campaign, it was unfair that they should be summarily deprived of
                    the office which the people had intrusted to them; <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> when Servilius Ahala arose and said that he had been so
                    long silent not because of any doubt as to his opinion —for what good citizen
                    considered his own interests apart from those of the nation? —but because he had
                        <pb n="p.443"/> wished that his colleagues should of their own free <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 407</note> will give
                    in to the senators' authority, instead of suffering the power of the tribunes to
                    be invoked against them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Even then, if the
                    circumstances allowed of it, he would gladly, he said, have given them time to
                    retreat from their too obstinate contention; but since war's necessity did not
                    wait upon man's deliberations, he should place the public welfare above the
                    favour of his colleagues; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and if the senate
                    held to its opinion, he should name a dictator that night, contenting himself,
                    if any one vetoed the senate's resolution, with the expression of its wishes.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Having by this course gained the
                    well-merited praise and friendly support of all, he named as dictator Publius
                    Cornelius, by whom he was himself appointed master of the horse, thus showing
                    such persons as considered the case of his colleagues and himself that favour
                    and high office sometimes come more easily when men do not covet them.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The war was no way noteworthy. In a single
                    battle, and an easy one, they defeated the enemy at Antium. The victorious army
                    laid waste the Volscian country and took by storm a fortress at Lake Fucinus,
                    where three thousand men were taken prisoners, the rest being driven within
                    their city-walls, leaving their fields defenceless. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator, after so conducting the campaign that he
                    seemed barely to have taken advantage of his luck, returned to the City, with
                    more good fortune than renown, and resigned his magistracy. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The tribunes of the soldiers, without saying a word about
                    electing consuls, —I suppose because of their indignation at the appointment of
                    a dictator, —proclaimed an election of military tribunes. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At that the patricians were <pb n="p.445"/> more concerned
                    than ever, as they might well be <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"
                        type="margin">B.C. 407</note> when they saw their cause betrayed by their
                    own fellows. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Accordingly, just as in the
                    preceding year they had used the least worthy of the plebeian competitors to
                    arouse a dislike of them all, even the deserving, so at this time, by setting up
                    as candidates the senators of the greatest splendour and popularity, they
                    secured all the places, in order that no plebeian might be chosen. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Four men were elected, all of whom had held that
                    office before. They were Lucius Furius Medullinus, Gaius Valerius Potitus,
                    Numerius Fabius Vibulanus, and Gaius Servilius Ahala. This last was continued in
                    office partly for his other good qualities, partly because of the approval he
                    had just gained by his singular moderation. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In that year, since the term of the truce
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 406</note> with
                    Veii had run out, steps were taken to demand restitution, through ambassadors
                    and fetials. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Arriving at the frontier, these
                    men were met by an embassy of the Veientes, who asked them not to proceed to
                    Veii until they themselves should have gone before the Roman senate. The senate,
                    considering that the Veientes were in the throes of civil discord, agreed not to
                    demand a settlement of them; so far were they from taking advantage of another
                    people's difficulties. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> And in the Volscian
                    country the Romans suffered a disaster, in the loss of their garrison at
                    Verrugo. On that occasion the element of time was of such moment that, although
                    the troops who were being besieged there by the Volsci appealed for help and
                    might have been relieved if their friends had made haste, yet the army
                    dispatched for that purpose only arrived in season to surprise <pb n="p.447"/>
                    the enemy as they were dispersed in quest of booty, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 406</note> just after putting the
                    garrison to the sword. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The delay was due quite
                    as much to the tribunes as to the senate, for they got reports that the garrison
                    was making a strenuous resistance and failed to consider that no valour can
                    transcend the limits of human endurance. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But
                    the heroic soldiers were not unavenged, living or dead. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The following year, when Publius and Gnaeus
                    Cornelius Cossus, Numerius Fabius Ambustus, and Lucius Valerius Potitus were
                    consular tribunes, war broke out with Veii on account of the insolent reply of
                    the Veientine senate, who, when envoys demanded restitution of them, bade them
                    be <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> answered that unless they got quickly out
                    from their city and their borders, they would give them what Lars Tolumnius had
                    given the others. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italics">i.e.</hi> death (see chap. xvii). </note>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This angered the Fathers, and they decreed
                    that the military tribunes should propose to the people a declaration of war on
                    the Veientes at the earliest possible day. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As
                    soon as this was promulgated, the young men protested loudly that the Volscian
                    war was not yet brought to a conclusion; two garrisons had just been destroyed,
                    and the other outposts were being held at great risk; not a year went by without
                    a pitched battle; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> and as though they had not
                    troubles enough, a new war was being started with a neighbouring and very
                    powerful people, who were sure to raise all Etruria against them. </p>
                <p> This smouldering discontent was fanned into a blaze by the plebeian tribunes.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They persistently declared that it was
                    the plebs with whom the senators were chiefly at war; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> them they deliberately plagued with campaigning and exposed
                    to be <pb n="p.449"/> slaughtered by the enemy; them they kept at a <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 406</note> distance
                    from the City, and assigned to foreign service, lest they might have thoughts,
                    if they remained peaceably at home, of liberty and colonies, and might agitate
                    for public lands or the free use of their votes. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> And laying hold of veteran soldiers, they enumerated the
                    campaigns of each and his wounds and scars; asking where one could now find a
                    whole place on their bodies to receive fresh wounds, or what blood they had left
                    to shed for their country. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> When the tribunes
                    by repeating these arguments in their talk and in their speeches had produced in
                    the plebs a reluctance to undertake the war, the authors of the bill put off the
                    time for voting on it, since it was clear that if subjected to the storm of
                    disapproval it would fail to pass. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meantime it was determined that the military
                    tribunes should lead the army into the country of the Volsci; only Gnaeus
                    Cornelius was left in Rome. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The three
                    tribunes, on its appearing that the Volsci had no camp anywhere and did not
                    propose to risk a battle, divided their army into three and advanced in
                    different directions to lay waste the country. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Valerius marched upon Antium, Cornelius against Ecetrae, and wherever they went
                    they plundered farms and buildings far and wide, to divide the forces of the
                    Volsci; Fabius led his troops to Anxur, the principal object of their attack,
                    and laid siege to it, without doing any pillaging. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Anxur, the Tarracinae of our day, <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> Anxur was likely the Volscian name. The present form of
                        the name is Terracina. </note> was a city which sloped down towards the
                    marshes. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> On this side Fabius threatened an
                    assault, while four cohorts <pb n="p.451"/> marched round under Gaius Servilius
                    Ahala, and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C.
                        406</note> seizing the hill which overhangs the city, assailed the walls
                    from this superior position, where there was no force to oppose them, with great
                    noise and confusion. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Hearing the din, the
                    soldiers who were defending the lowest part of the town against Fabius were
                    bewildered, and permitted him to bring up scaling-ladders; and soon the whole
                    place was alive with enemies, who for a long time gave no quarter, slaughtering
                    without distinction those who fled and those who resisted, the armed and the
                    unarmed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> And so the vanquished, since they
                    could hope for no mercy if they yielded, were compelled to fight; when suddenly
                    the command was given that none should be hurt but those who carried weapons.
                    Thereupon, all the survivors voluntarily laid down their arms, and about
                    twenty-five hundred of them were taken alive. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Fabius made his soldiers leave the rest of the spoils until his colleagues could
                        <milestone n="9??" unit="section"/> come up, saying that their armies had
                    helped to capture Anxur by diverting the rest of the Volsci from the defence of
                    that place. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When they arrived, the three
                    armies sacked the town, which long years of prosperity had filled with riches.
                    It was this generous treatment on the part of their commanders which first
                    reconciled the plebs to the patricians. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In
                    addition to this the senate then granted the people the most seasonable boon
                    which has ever been bestowed on them by the chiefs of the state, when they
                    decreed, without waiting for any suggestion by the plebs or their tribunes, that
                    the soldiers should be paid from the public treasury, whereas till then every
                    man had served at his own costs. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="60" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Nothing, it is said, was ever welcomed by <pb
                        n="p.453"/> the plebs with such rejoicing. Crowds gathered at B.C. 406 the
                    Curia and men grasped the hands of the senators as they came out, saying that
                    they were rightly called Fathers, and confessing that they had brought it to
                    pass that no one, so long as he retained a particle of strength, would grudge
                    his life's blood to so generous a country. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Not
                    only were they pleased at the advantage that their property would at least not
                    diminish while their bodies were impressed for the service of the state, but the
                    voluntary character of the offer, which had never been mooted by plebeian
                    tribunes nor extorted by any words of their own, multiplied their satisfaction
                    and increased their gratitude. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The tribunes of
                    the plebs were the only persons who did not partake in the general joy and good
                    feeling of both orders. They said that the measure would neither be so agreeable
                    to the Fathers nor so favourable to the whole body of the citizens as the latter
                    believed; it was a plan which at first sight had promised to be better than
                    experience would prove it. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For where, they
                    asked, could the money be got together, save by imposing a tribute on the
                    people? The senators had therefore been generous at other men's expense; and
                    even though everyone else should submit to it, those who had already earned
                    their discharge would not endure that others should serve on better terms than
                    they had themselves enjoyed, and that the same men who had paid their own
                    expenses should also contribute to the expenses of others. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> By these arguments they influenced a part of the plebs.
                    Finally, when the assessment had already been proclaimed, the tribunes even
                    announced that they would protect anybody who should refuse to contribute to a
                    tax for paying the soldiers. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The <pb n="p.455"
                    /> Fathers had made a good beginning and persevered <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 406</note> in supporting it. They
                    were themselves the first to contribute, and since there was as yet no silver
                    coinage, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The elder Pliny ( <hi
                            rend="italics">N.H.</hi> xxxiii. 42) says that the Romans did not use
                        coined silver until the defeat of King Pyrrhus ( <date when="-0275">275
                            B.C.</date> ) </note> some of them brought uncoined bronze in waggons to
                    the treasury, and even made a display of their contributing. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> After the senators had paid most faithfully, according to
                    their rating, the chief men of the plebs, friends of the nobles, began, as had
                    been agreed, to bring in their quota. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the
                    crowd saw that these men were applauded by the patricians and were looked upon
                    as good citizens by those of military age, they quickly rejected the protection
                    of the tribunes and vied with one another who should be the first to pay.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And on the law being passed declaring war
                    on the Veientes, an army consisting in great part of volunteers marched, under
                    command of the new military tribunes, upon that city. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="61" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Now the tribunes were Titus Quinctius <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 405-404</note>
                    Capitolinus, Quintus Quinctius Cincinnatus, Gaius Julius Iulus (for the second
                    time), Aulus Manlius, Lucius Furius Medullinus (for the third time), and Manius
                    Aemilius Mamercus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> By them Veii was for the
                    first time besieged. Shortly after this siege began, the Etruscans held a
                    numerously attended council at the shrine of Voltumna, but could reach no
                    decision as to whether the entire nation should go to war in defence of the
                    Veientes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The siege languished during the year
                    that followed, for some of the tribunes and a part of the army were called away
                    to fight the Volsci. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The military tribunes with consular powers for
                    this year were Gaius Valerius Potitus (for the third time), Manius Sergius
                    Fidenas, Publius Cornelius Maluginensis, Gnaeus Cornelius Cossus, Gaius Fabius
                    Ambustus, and (for the second time) Spurius Nautius <pb n="p.457"/> Rutulus.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A pitched battle was fought with the <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified" type="margin">B.C. 405-404</note> Volsci
                    between Ferentinum and Ecetra, in which fortune favoured the Romans. The
                    tribunes then laid siege to Artena, a Volscian town. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> While attempting a sortie the enemy were driven back into
                    the city and afforded the Romans an opportunity of forcing an entrance, so that
                    the whole place, except the citadel, was captured; to this fortress, which was
                    naturally strong, a band of armed men retired; below the citadel a large number
                    were killed or taken prisoner. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The citadel was
                    then besieged, but could neither be taken by assault, having a sufficient
                    garrison in proportion to its area, nor appeared likely to surrender, for the
                    whole public store of grain had been conveyed into the fortress before the
                    capture of the town. The Romans would have withdrawn, discouraged, had not a
                    slave betrayed the place into their hands. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    This man admitted some soldiers by way of a steep approach, and they captured it
                    and slew the sentries; whereupon the rest of the garrison was seized with a
                    sudden panic and surrendered. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> After
                    demolishing the citadel and the town of Artena, the legions were withdrawn from
                    the Volsci and all the might of Rome was brought to bear upon Veii. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The traitor was given the property of two families
                    as a reward, besides his liberty, and was named Servius Romanus. <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Later it was the custom to give a slave
                        thus manumitted by the state the name of the officiating magistrate. </note>
                    There are those who think that Artena had belonged to the Veientes, not to the
                    Volsci. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Their mistake is due to the fact that
                    there was a city of the same name between Caere and Veii; but this place was
                    destroyed by the Roman kings, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Livy
                        does not mention the incident in Book I.</note> and it had been a dependency
                    of Caere, not of Veii; the other town of the same name, whose overthrow I have
                    just related, was in Volscian territory. </p>
                <pb n="p.459"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
