<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd">
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>A Dialogue on Oratory</title>

<author>Cornelius Tacitus</author>
<editor role="translator">Alfred John Church</editor>
<editor role="translator">William Jackson Brodribb</editor>
    <respStmt>
        <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
        <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
        <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>about 1,340 lines</extent>
    <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2001-03-12</date>
    </publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
    <monogr>
        <title>The Agricola and Germany of Tacitus and the Dialogue on Oratory</title>
        <author>Tacitus</author>
        <respStmt>
            <name>Sara Bryant</name>
            <resp>edited for Perseus</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <imprint>
            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
            <publisher>MacMillan and Co.</publisher>
            <date>1877</date>
        </imprint>
        <imprint>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <publisher>Modern Library</publisher>
            <date>1942 reprint</date>
        </imprint>
    </monogr>
    <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433081560181">HathiTrust</ref>
    </biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>

<head>A DIALOGUE ON ORATORY</head>
<div1 type="chapter" n="1"><p>You often ask me, Justus Fabius, how it is that while the genius and the fame of so many distinguished orators have shed a lustreon the past, our age is so forlorn and so destitute of the glory of 
eloquence that it scarce retains the very name of orator. That title indeed 
we apply only to the ancients, and the clever speakers of this day we call 
pleaders, advocates, counsellors, anything rather than orators. To answer 
this question of yours, to undertake the burden of so serious an inquiry, 
involving, as it must, a mean opinion either of our capacities, if we cannot 
reach the same standard, or of our tastes, if we have not the wish, is a 
task on which I should scarcely venture had I to give my own views instead 
of being able to reproduce a conversation among men, for our time, 
singularly eloquent, whom, when quite a youth, I heard discussing this very 
question. And so it is not ability, it is only memory and recollection which 
I require. I have to repeat now, with the same divisions and arguments, 
following closely the course of that discussion, those subtle reflections 
which I heard, powerfully expressed, from men of the highest eminence, each 
of whom assigned a different but plausible reason, thereby displaying the 
peculiarities of his individual temper and genius. Nor indeed did the 
opposite side lack an advocate, who, after much criticism and ridicule of 
old times, maintained the superiority of the eloquence of our own days to 
the great orators of the past.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="2"><p>It was 
the day after Curiatius Maternus had given a reading of his <placeName key="tgn,2226609">Cato</placeName>, by which 
it was said that he had irritated the feelings of certain great personages, 
because in the subject of his tragedy he had apparently forgotten himself 
and thought only of <placeName key="tgn,2226609">Cato</placeName>. While all <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> was 
discussing the subject, he received a visit from Marcus Aper and <placeName key="tgn,2008628">Julius</placeName>

Secundus, then the most famous men of genius at our bar. Of both I 
was a studious hearer in court, and I also would follow them to their homes 
and when they appeared in public, from a singular zeal for my profession, 
and a youthful enthusiasm which urged me to listen diligently to their 
trivial talk, their more serious debates, and their private and esoteric 
descourse. Yet many ill-naturedly thought that Secundus had no readiness of 
speech, and that Aper had won his reputation for eloquence by his cleverness 
and natural powers, more than by training and culture. As a fact, Secundus 
had a pure, terse, and a sufficiently fluent style, while Aper, who was 
imbued with learning of all kinds, pretended to despise the culture which he 
really possessed. He would have, so he must have thought, a greater 
reputation for industry and application, if it should appear that his genius 
did not depend on any supports from pursuits alien to his profession.</p></div1> 

<div1 type="chapter" n="3"><p>So we entered the study of Maternus, and found 
him seated with the very book which he had read the day before, in his 
hands. Secundus began. Has the talk of ill-natured people no effect in 
deterring you, Maternus, from clinging to your <placeName key="tgn,2226609">Cato</placeName> with its provocations? 
Or have you taken up the book to revise it more carefully, and, after 
striking out whatever has given a handle for a bad interpretation, will you 
publish, if not a better, at least a safer, <placeName key="tgn,2226609">Cato</placeName>? </p>
<p>You shall read, was 
the answer, what Maternus owed it to himself to write, and all that you 
heard you will recognise again. Anything omitted in the <placeName key="tgn,2226609">Cato</placeName> Thyestes shall 
supply in my next reading. This is a tragedy, the plan of which I have in my 
own mind arranged and formed. I am therefore bent on hurrying on the 
publication of the present book, that, as soon as my first work is off my 
hands, I may devote my whole soul to a fresh task. </p>
<p>It seems, said Aper, 
so far from these tragedies contenting you, that you have abandoned the 
study of the orator and pleader, and are giving all your time to Medea and 
now to Thyestes, although your friends, with their many causes, and your 
clients from the colonies, municipalities, and towns, are calling you to the 
courts. You could hardly answer their demands even if you had not imposed 
new work on your-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">PERSONS AND SITUATION 
INTRODUCED</note>
self, the work of adding to the dramas of <rs type="placename">Greece</rs> a Domitius and a Cato, histories and names from 
our own <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="4"><p>This severity of yours, replied Maternus, would be quite a blow to us, had 
not our controversy from its frequency and familiarity become by this time 
almost a regular practice. You, in fact, never cease from abusing and 
inveighing against poets, and I, whom you reproach with neglect of my 
professional duties, every day undertake to plead against you in defence of 
poetry. So I am all the more delighted at the presence of a judge who will 
either forbid me for the future to write verses, or who will compel me by 
his additional authority to do what I have long desired, to give up the 
petty subleties of legal causes, at which I have toiled enough, and more 
than enough, and to cultivate a more sacred and more stately 
eloquence.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="5"><p>For my part, said Secundus, 
before Aper refuses me as a judge, I will do as is usually done by upright 
and sensible judges, who excuse themselves in cases in which it is evident 
that one side has an undue influence with them. Who knows not that no one is 
nearer my heart from long friendship and uninterrupted intercourse than 
Saleius Bassus, an excellent man, as well as a most accomplished poet? 
Besides, if poetry is to be put on her defence, I know not a more 
influential defendant. </p>
<p>He may rest secure, said Aper, both Saleius 
Bassus himself, and anyone else who is devoted to the pursuit of poetry and 
the glory of song, if he has not the gift of pleading causes. But assuredly, 
as I have found an arbiter for this dispute, I will not allow Maternus to 
shelter himself behind a number of associates. I single him out for 
accusation before you on the ground that, though naturally fittest for that 
manly eloquence of the orator by which he might create and retain 
friendships, acquire connections, and attach the provinces, he is throwing 
away a pursuit than which it is impossible to imagine one in our state 
richer in advantages, more splendid in its prospects, more attractive in 
fame at home, more illustrious in celebrity throughout our whole empire and 
all the world. If, indeed, what is useful in life should be the aim of all 
our plans and actions, what can be safer than to practise an art armed with 
which a man can always bring

aid to friends, succour to 
strangers, deliverance to the imperilled, while to malignant foes he is an 
actual fear and terror, himself the while secure and intrenched, so to say, 
within a power and a position of lasting strength? When we have a flow of 
prosperity, the efficacy and use of this art are seen in the help and 
protection of others; if, however, we hear the sound of danger to ourselves, 
the breast-plate and the sword are not, I am well assured, a stronger 
defence on the battle-field than eloquence is to a man amid the perils of a 
prosecution. It is both a shield and a weapon; you can use it alike for 
defence and attack, either before a judge, before the senate, or before the 
emperor. What but his eloquence did Eprius <placeName key="tgn,2040171">Marcellus</placeName> oppose the other day to 
the senators in their fury? Armed with this, and consequently terrible, he 
baffled the sagacious but untrained wisdom of Helvidius Priscus, which knew 
nothing of such encounters. Of its usefulness I say no more. It is a point 
which I think my friend Maternus will be the last to dispute.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="6"><p>I pass now to the pleasure derived from the orator's 
eloquence. Its delights are enjoyed not for a single moment, but almost on 
every day and at every hour. To the mind of an educated gentleman, naturally 
fitted for worthy enjoyments, what can be more delightful than to see his 
house always thronged and crowded by gatherings of the most eminent men, and 
to know that the honour is paid not to his wealth, his childlessness, or his 
possession of some office, but to himself? Nay, more; the childless, the 
rich, and the powerful often go to one who is both young and poor, in order 
to intrust him with difficulties affecting themselves or their friends. Can 
there be any pleasure from boundless wealth and vast power equal to that of 
seeing men in years, and even in old age, men backed by the influence of the 
whole world, readily confessing, amid the utmost affluence of every kind, 
that they do not possess that which is the best of all? Again, look at the 
respectable citizens who escort the pleader to and from the court. Look at 
his appearance in public, and the respect shown him before the judges. What 
a delight it must be to rise and stand amid the hushed crowd, with every eye 
on him alone, the people assembling and gathering round him in a circle, and 
taking from the orator any emotion he

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">SATISFACTIONS OF ORATOR'S CAREER</note>
has himself assumed. I am 
now reckoning the notorious joys of an orator, those which are open to the 
sight even of the uneducated; the more secret, known only to the advocate 
himself, are yet greater. If he produces a careful and well-prepared speech, 
there is a solidity and stedfastness in his satisfaction, just as there is 
in his style; if, again, he offers his audience, not without some tremblings 
at heart, the result of a fresh and sudden effort, his very anxiety enhances 
the joy of success, and ministers to his pleasure. In fact, audacity at the 
moment, and rashness itself, have quite a peculiar sweetness. As with the 
earth, so with genius. Though time must be bestowed on the sowing and 
cultivation of some plants, yet those which grow spontaneously are the more 
pleasing.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="7"><p>To speak my own mind, I did 
not experience more joy on the day on which I was presented with the robe of 
a senator, or when, as a new man, born in a far from influential state, I 
was elected qu&aelig;stor, or tribune, or pr&aelig;tor, than on those on 
which it was my privilege, considering the insignificance of my ability as a 
speaker, to defend a prisoner with success, to win a verdict in a cause 
before the Court of the Hundred, or to give the support of my advocacy in 
the emperor's presence to the great freedmen themselves, or to ministers of 
the crown. On such occasions I seem to rise above tribunates, 
pr&aelig;torships, and consulships, and to possess that which, if it be not 
of natural growth, is not bestowed by mandate, nor comes through interest. 
Again, is there an accomplishment, the fame and glory of which are to be 
compared with the distinction of the orator, who is an illustrious man at 
<rs type="placename">Rome</rs>, not only with the busy class, intent on public 
affairs, but even with people of leisure, and with the young, those at least 
who have a right disposition and a worthy confidence in themselves? Whose 
name does the father din into his children's ears before that of the orator? 
Whom, as he passes by, do the ignorant mob and the men with the tunic 
oftener speak of by name and point out with the finger? Strangers too and 
foreigners, having heard of him in their towns and colonies, as soon as they 
have arrived at <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>, ask for him and are eager, as 
it were to recognise him.</p></div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="8"><p>As 
for Marcellus Eprius, whom I have just mentioned, and Crispus Vibius (it is 
pleasanter to me to cite recent and modern examples than those of a distant 
and forgotten past), I would venture to argue that they are quite as great 
men in the remotest corners of the world as at <rs type="placename">Capua</rs> 
or <rs type="placename">Vercellae</rs>, where they are said to have been born. 
Nor do they owe this to the three hundred million sesterces of the one, 
although it may seem that they must thank their eloquence for having 
attained such wealth. Eloquence itself is the cause. Its inspiration and 
superhuman power have throughout all times shown by many an example what a 
height of fortune men have reached by the might of genius. But there are, as 
I said but now, instances close at hand, and we may know them, not by 
hearsay, but may see them with our eyes. The lower and meaner their birth, 
the more notorious the poverty and the straitened means amid which their 
life began, the more famous and brilliant are they as examples to show the 
efficacy of an orator's eloquence. Without the recommendation of birth, 
without the support of riches, neither of the two distinguished for virtue, 
one even despised for the appearance of his person, they have now for many 
years been the most powerful men in the state, and, as long as it suited 
them, they were the leaders of the bar. At this moment, as leading men in 
the emperor's friendship they carry all before them, and even the leading 
man himself of the State esteems and almost reverences them. Vespasian 
indeed, venerable in his old age and most tolerant of truth, knows well that 
while his other friends are dependent on what he has given them, and on what 
it is easy for him to heap and pile on others, Marcellus and Crispus, in 
becoming his friends, brought with them something which they had not 
received and which could not be received from a prince. Amid so much that is 
great, busts, inscriptions, and statues hold but a very poor place. Yet even 
these they do not disregard, and certainly not riches and affluence, which 
it is easier to find men denouncing than despising. It is these honours and 
splendours, aye and substantial wealth, that we see filling the homes of 
those who from early youth have given themselves to practice at the bar and 
to the study of oratory.</p></div1>
 
<div1 type="chapter" n="9">
<note anchored="yes" place="marg">THE ORATOR'S 
FAME</note><p>As for song and verse to which 
Maternus wishes to devote his whole life (for this was the starting-point of 
his entire argument), they bring no dignity to the author, nor do they 
improve his circumstances. Although your ears, Maternus, may loathe what I 
am about to say, I ask what good it is if Agamemnon or Jason speaks 
eloquently in your composition. Who the more goes back to his home saved 
from danger and bound to you? Our friend Saleius is an admirable poet, or, 
if the phrase be more complimentary, a most illustrious bard; but who walks 
by his side or attends his receptions or follows in his train? Why, if his 
friend or relative or even he himself stumbles into some troublesome affair, 
he will run to Secundus here, or to you, Maternus, not because you are a 
poet or that you may make verses for him; for verses come naturally to 
Bassus in his own home, and pretty and charming they are, though the result 
of them is that when, with the labour of a whole year, through entire days 
and the best part of the nights, he has hammered out, with the midnight oil, 
a single book, he is forced actually to beg and canvass for people who will 
condescend to be his hearers, and not even this without cost to himself. He 
gets the loan of a house, fits up a room, hires benches, and scatters 
programmes. Even if his reading is followed by a complete success, all the 
glory is, so to say, cut short in the bloom and the flower, and does not 
come to any real and substantial fruit. He carries away with him not a 
single friendship, not a single client, not an obligation that will abide in 
anyone's mind, only idle applause, meaningless acclamations and a fleeting 
delight. We lately praised Vespasian's bounty, in giving Bassus four 
thousand pounds, as something marvellous and splendid. It is no doubt a fine 
thing to win an emperor's favour by talent; but how much finer, if domestic 
circumstances so require, to cultivate oneself, to make one's own genius 
propitious, to fall back on one's own bounty. Consider too that a poet, if 
he wishes to work out and accomplish a worthy result, must leave the society 
of his friends, and the attractions of the capital; he must relinquish every 
other duty, and must, as poets themselves say, retire to woods and groves, 
in fact, into solitude.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="10"><p>Nor again do 
even reputation and fame, the only ob-

ject of their devotion, 
the sole reward of their labours, by their own confession, cling to the poet 
as much as to the orator; for indifferent poets are known to none, and the 
good but to a few. When does the rumour of the very choicest readings 
penetrate every part of <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>, much less is talked of 
throughout our numerous provinces? How few, when they visit the capital from 
<rs type="placename">Spain</rs> or <rs type="placename">Asia</rs>, to say 
nothing of our Gallic neighbours, ask after Saleius Bassus! And indeed, if 
any one does ask after him, having once seen him, he passes on, and is 
satisfied, as if he had seen a picture or a statue. I do not wish my remarks 
to be taken as implying that I would deter from poetry those to whom nature 
has denied the orator's talent, if only they can amuse their leisure and 
push themselves into fame by this branch of culture. For my part I hold all 
eloquence in its every variety something sacred and venerable, and I regard 
as preferable to all studies of other arts not merely your tragedian's 
buskin or the measures of heroic verse, but even the sweetness of the lyric 
ode, the playfulness of the elegy, the satire of the iambic, the wit of the 
epigram, and indeed any other form of eloquence. But it is with you, 
Maternus, that I am dealing; for, when your genius might carry you to the 
summit of eloquence, you prefer to wander from the path, and though sure to 
win the highest prize you stop short at meaner things. Just as, if you had 
been born in <rs type="placename">Greece</rs>, where it is an honour to 
practise even the arts of the arena, and if the gods had given you the 
vigour and strength of Nicostratus, I should not suffer those giant arms 
meant by nature for combat to waste themselves on the light javelin or the 
throwing of the quoit, so now I summon you from the lecture-room and the 
theatre to the law court with its pleadings and its real battles. I do this 
the more because you cannot even fall back on the refuge which shelters 
many, the plea that the poet's pursuit is less liable to give offence than 
that of the orator. In truth, with you the ardour of a peculiarly noble 
nature bursts forth, and the offence you give is not for the sake of a 
friend, but, what is more dangerous, for the sake of <placeName key="tgn,2226609">Cato</placeName>. Nor is this 
offending excused by the obligation of duty, or by the fidelity of an 
advocate, or by the impulse of a casual and sudden speech.

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">MORE SUBSTANTIAL THAN POET'S</note>
You have, it seems, prepared 
your part in having chosen a character of note who would speak with 
authority. I foresee your possible answer. Hence, you will say, came the 
decisive approval; this is the style which the lecture-room chiefly praises, 
and which next becomes the world's talk. Away then with the excuse of quiet 
and safety, when you are deliberately choosing a more doughty adversary. For 
myself, let it be enough to take a side in the private disputes of our own 
time. In these, if at any time necessity has compelled us on behalf of an 
imperilled friend to offend the ears of the powerful, our loyalty must be 
approved, our liberty of speech condoned.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="11"><p>Aper having said this with his usual spirit and with vehemence 
of utterance, Maternus replied good-humouredly with something of a smile. I 
was preparing to attack the orators at as great length as Aper had praised 
them, for I thought that he would leave his praises of them and go on to 
demolish poets and the pursuit of poetry, but he appeased me by a sort of 
stratagem, granting permission to those who cannot plead causes, to make 
verses. For myself, though I am perhaps able to accomplish and effect 
something in pleading causes, yet it was by the public reading of tragedies 
that I first began to enter the path of fame, when in <placeName key="tgn,2538429">Nero</placeName>'s time I broke 
the wicked power of Vatinius by which even the sanctities of culture were 
profaned, and if at this moment I possess any celebrity and distinction I 
maintain that it has been acquired more by the renown of my poems than of my 
speeches. And so now I have resolved to throw off the yoke of my labours at 
the bar, and for trains of followers on my way to and from the court and for 
crowded receptions I crave no more than for the bronzes and busts which have 
invaded my house even against my will. For hitherto I have upheld my 
position and my safety better by integrity than by eloquence, and I am not 
afraid of having ever to say a word in the senate except to avert peril from 
another.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="12"><p>As to the woods and groves 
and that retirement which Aper denounced, they bring such delight to me that 
I count among the chief enjoyments of poetry the fact that it is composed 
not in the midst of bustle, or with a suitor sitting before one's door, or 
amid the wretchedness and tears of

prisoners, but that the soul 
withdraws herself to abodes of purity and innocence, and enjoys her holy 
resting-place. Here eloquence had her earliest beginnings; here is her 
inmost shrine. In such guise and beauty did she first charm mortals, and 
steal into those virgin hearts which no vice had contaminated. Oracles spoke 
under these conditions. As for the present money-getting and blood-stained 
eloquence, its use is modern, its origin in corrupt manners, and, as you 
said, Aper, it is a device to serve as a weapon. But the happy golden age, 
to speak in our own poetic fashion, knew neither orators nor accusations, 
while it abounded in poets and bards, men who could sing of good deeds, but 
not defend evil actions. None enjoyed greater glory, or honours more august, 
first with the gods, whose answers they published, and at whose feasts they 
were present, as was commonly said, and then with the offspring of the gods 
and with sacred kings, among whom, so we have understood, was not a single 
pleader of causes, but an Orpheus, a Linus, and, if you care to dive into a 
remoter age, an Apollo himself. Or, if you think all this too fabulous and 
imaginary, at least you grant me that Homer has as much honour with 
posterity as Demosthenes, and that the fame of Euripides or Sophocles is 
bounded by a limit not narrower than that of Lysias or Hyperides. You will 
find in our own day more who disparage <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>'s than <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName>'s glory. Nor is 
any production of Asinius or Messala so famous as Ovid's Medea or the 
Thyestes of Varius.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="13"><p>Look again at the 
poet's lot, with its delightful companionships. I should not be afraid of 
comparing it with the harassing and anxious life of the orator. Orators, it 
is true, have been raised to consulships by their contests and perils, but I 
prefer <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName>'s serene, calm, and peaceful retirement, in which after all he 
was not without the favour of the divine Augustus, and fame among the people 
of <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>. We have the testimony of the letters of 
Augustus, the testimony too of the people themselves, who, on hearing in the 
theatre some of <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName>'s verses, rose in a body and did homage to the poet, 
who happened to be present as a spectator, just as to Augustus himself. Even 
in our own day, Pomponius Secundus need not yield to Domitius Aper on the 
score of a

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">QUIET BEAUTY THE POET'S 
LOT</note>
dignified life or an enduring reputation. As for your Crispus and 
Marcellus, whom you hold up to me as examples, what is there in their lot to 
be coveted? Is it that they are in fear themselves, or are a fear to others? 
Is it that, while every day something is asked from them, those to whom they 
grant it feel indignant? Is it that, bound as they are by the chain of 
flattery, they are never thought servile enough by those who rule, or free 
enough by us? What is their power at its highest? Why, the freedmen usually 
have as much. For myself, as <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName> says, let "the sweet muses" lead me to 
their sacred retreats, and to their fountains far away from anxieties and 
cares, and the necessity of doing every day something repugnant to my heart. 
Let me no longer tremblingly experience the madness and perils of the forum, 
and the pallors of fame. Let me not be aroused by a tumult of morning 
visitors, or a freedman's panting haste, or, anxious about the future, have 
to make a will to secure my wealth. Let me not possess more than what I can 
leave to whom I please, whenever the day appointed by my own fates shall 
come; and let the statue over my tomb be not gloomy and scowling, but bright 
and laurel-crowned. As for my memory, let there be no resolutions in the 
senate, or petitions to the emperor.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="14"><p>Excited and, I say say, full of enthusiasm, Maternus had hardly finished 
when Vipstanus Messala entered his room, and, from the earnest expression on 
each face, he conjectured that their conversation was unusually serious. 
Have I, he asked, come among you unseasonably, while you are engaged in 
private deliberation, or the preparation of some case? </p>
<p>By no means, by 
no means, said Secundus. Indeed I could wish you had come sooner, for you 
would have been delighted with the very elaborate arguments of our friend 
Aper, in which he urged Maternus to apply all his ability and industry to 
the pleading of causes, and then too with Maternus's apology for his poems 
in a lively speech, which as suited a poet's defence, was uncommonly 
spirited, and more like poetry than oratory. </p>
<p>For my part, he replied, I 
should have been infinitely charmed by the discourse, and I am delighted to 
find that

you excellent men, the orators of our age, instead of 
exercising your talents simply on law-business and rhetorical studies, also 
engage in discussions which not only strengthen the intellect but also draw 
from learning and from letters a pleasure most exquisite both to you who 
discuss such subjects and to those too whose ears your words may reach. 
Hence the world, I see, is as much pleased with you, Secundus, for having by 
your life of Julius Asiaticus given it the promise of more such books, as it 
is with Aper for having not yet retired from the disputes of the schools, 
and for choosing to employ his leisure after the fashion of modern 
rhetoricians rather than of the old orators.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="15"><p>Upon this Aper replied, You still persist, Messala, in admiring 
only what is old and antique and in sneering at and disparaging the culture 
of our own day. I have often heard this sort of talk from you, when, 
forgetting the eloquence of yourself and your brother, you argued that 
nobody in this age is an orator. And you did this, I believe, with the more 
audacity because you were not afraid of a reputation for ill-nature, seeing 
that the glory which others concede to you, you deny to yourself. I feel no 
penitence, said Messala, for such talk, nor do I believe that Secundus or 
Maternus or you yourself, Aper, think differently, though now and then you 
argue for the opposite view. I could wish that one of you were prevailed on 
to investigate and describe to us the reasons of this vast difference. I 
often inquire into them by myself. That which consoles some minds, to me 
increases the difficulty. For I perceive that even with the Greeks it has 
happened that there is a greater distance between Aeschines and Demosthenes 
on the one hand, and your friend Nicetes or any other orator who shakes 
<placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName> or <placeName key="tgn,7002672">Mitylene</placeName> with a chorus of rhetoricians and their noisy applause, 
on the other, than that which separates Afer, Africanus, or yourselves from 
<placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> or Asinius.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="16"><p>The question you 
have raised, said Secundus, is a great one and quite worthy of discussion. 
But who has a better claim to unravel it than yourself, you who to profound 
learning and transcendent ability have added reflection and study? </p>
<p>I 
will open my mind to you, replied Messala, if first I can

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">ANCIENTS VERSUS MODERNS</note>
prevail on you to give me your 
assistance in our discussion. I can answer for two of us, said Maternus; 
Secundus and myself will take the part which we understand you have not so 
much omitted as left to us. Aper usually dissents, as you have just said, 
and he has clearly for some time been girding himself for the attack, and 
cannot bear with patience our union on behalf of the merits of the ancients. 
</p>
<p>Assuredly, said Aper, I will not allow our age to be condemned, unheard 
and undefended, by this conspiracy of yours. First, however, I will ask you 
whom you call ancients, or what period of orators you limit by your 
definition? When I hear of ancients, I understand men of the past, born ages 
ago; I have in my eye Ulysses and Nestor, whose time is about thirteen 
hundred years before our day. But you bring forward Demosthenes and 
Hyperides who flourished, as we know, in the period of Philip and Alexander, 
a period, however, which they both outlived. Hence we see that not much more 
than four hundred years has intervened between our own era and that of 
Demosthenes. If you measure this space of time by the frailty of human life, 
it perhaps seems long; if by the course of ages and by the thought of this 
boundless universe, it is extremely short and is very near us. For indeed, 
if, as Cicero says in his Hortensius, the great and the true year is that in 
which the position of the heavens and of the stars at any particular moment 
recurs, and if that year embraces twelve thousand nine hundred and ninety 
four of what we call years, then your Demosthenes, whom you represent as so 
old and ancient, began his existence not only in the same year, but almost 
in the same month as ourselves.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="17"><p>But I 
pass to the Latin orators. Among them, it is not, I imagine, Menenius 
Agrippa, who may seem ancient, whom you usually prefer to the speakers of 
our day, but Cicero, Caelius, Calvus, <placeName key="tgn,2037959">Brutus</placeName>, Asinius, Messala. Why you 
assign them to antiquity rather than to our own times, I do not see. With 
respect to <placeName key="tgn,2031372">Cicero</placeName> himself, it was in the consulship of Hirtius and Pansa, as 
his freedman <placeName key="tgn,2082201">Tiro</placeName> has stated, on the 5th of December, that he was slain. In 
that same year the Divine Augustus elected himself and Quintus Pedius 
consuls in the room of Pansa and Hirtius. Fix at fifty-six years the

subsequent rule of the Divine Augustus over the state; add <placeName key="tgn,2720789">Tiberius</placeName>'s 
three-and-twenty years, the four years or less of Caius, the twenty-eight 
years of Claudius and <placeName key="tgn,2538429">Nero</placeName>, the one memorable long year of Galba, <placeName key="tgn,2561792">Otho</placeName>, and 
Vitellius, and the now six years of the present happy reign, during which 
Vespasian has been fostering the public weal, and the result is that from 
<placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>'s death to our day is a hundred and twenty years, one man's 
life-time. For I saw myself an old man in <rs type="placename">Britain</rs> 
who declared that he was present at the battle in which they strove to drive 
and beat back from their shores the arms of C&aelig;sar when he attacked 
their island. So, had this man who encountered C&aelig;sar in the field, 
been brought to <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> either as a prisoner, or by his 
own choice or by some destiny, he might have heard C&aelig;sar himself and 
<placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, and also have been present at our own speeches. At the last largess 
of the Emperor you saw yourselves several old men who told you that they had 
actually shared once and again in the gifts of the divine Augustus. Hence we 
infer that they might have heard both Corvinus and Asinius. Corvinus indeed 
lived on to the middle of the reign of Augustus, Asinius almost to its 
close. You must not then divide the age, and habitually describe as old and 
ancient orators those with whom the ears of the self-same men might have 
made acquaintance, and whom they might, so to say, have linked and coupled 
together.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="18"><p>I have made these 
preliminary remarks to show that any credit reflected on the age by the fame 
and renown of these orators is common property, and is in fact more closely 
connected with us than with Servius Galba or Caius Carbo, and others whom we 
may rightly call "ancients." These indeed are rough, unpolished, awkward, 
and ungainly, and I wish that your favourite Calvus or Caelius or even 
<placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> had in no respect imitated them. I really mean now to deal with the 
subject more boldly and confidently, but I must first observe that the types 
and varieties of eloquence change with the age. Thus Caius Gracchus compared 
with the elder <placeName key="tgn,2068381">Cato</placeName> is full and copious; Crassus compared with Gracchus is 
polished and ornate; <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> compared with either is lucid, graceful, and 
lofty; Corvinus again is softer and sweeter and more finished in his phrases 
than <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>. I do not ask

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">DISTINCTION OF EPOCHS 
ARBITRARY</note>
who is the best speaker. Meantime I am content to have 
proved that eloquence has more than one face, and even in those whom you 
call ancients several varieties are to be discovered. Nor does it at once 
follow that difference implies inferiority. It is the fault of envious human 
nature that the old is always the object of praise, the present of contempt. 
Can we doubt that there were found critics who admired Appius Caecus more 
than <placeName key="tgn,2068381">Cato</placeName>? We know that even <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> was not without his disparagers, who 
thought him inflated, turgid, not concise enough, but unduly diffuse and 
luxuriant, in short anything but Attic. You have read of course the letters 
of Calvus and <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, and from these it is easy to perceive that 
in <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>'s opinion Calvus was bloodless and attenuated, <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName> slovenly and 
lax. <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> again was slightingly spoken of by Calvus as loose and 
nerveless, and by <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName>, to use his own words, as "languid and effeminate." 
If you ask me, I think they all said what was true. But I shall come to them 
separately after a while; now I have to deal with them collectively.</p></div1> 

<div1 type="chapter" n="19"><p>While indeed the admirers of the ancients 
fix as the boundary, so to say, of antiquity, the period up to Cassius 
Severus who was the first, they assert, to deviate from the old and plain 
path of the speaker, I maintain that it was not from poverty of genius or 
ignorance of letters that he adopted his well known style, but from 
preference and intellectual conviction. He saw, in fact, that, as I was just 
now saying, the character and type of oratory must change with the 
circumstances of the age and an altered taste in the popular ear. The people 
of the past, ignorant and uncultured as they were, patiently endured the 
length of a very confused speech, and it was actually to the speaker's 
credit, if he took up one of their days by his speech-making. Then too they 
highly esteemed long preparatory introductions, narratives told from a 
remote beginning, a multitude of divisions ostentatiously paraded, proofs in 
a thousand links, and all the other directions prescribed in those driest of 
treatises by Hermagoras and Apollodorus. Any one who was supposed to have 
caught a scent of philosophy, and who introduced some philosophical 
commonplace into his speech, was praised up to the skies. And no wonder; for 
this was new

and unfamiliar, and even of the orators but very few 
had studied the rules of rhetoricians or the dogmas of philosophers. But now 
that all these are common property and that there is scarce a bystander in 
the throng who, if not fully instructed, has not at least been initiated 
into the rudiments of culture, eloquence must resort to new and skilfully 
chosen paths, in order that the orator may avoid offence to the fastidious 
ear, at any rate before judges who decide by power and authority, not by law 
and precedent, who fix the speaker's time, instead of leaving it to himself, 
and, so far from thinking that they ought to wait till he chooses to speak 
on the matter in question, continually remind him of it and recall him to it 
when he wanders, protesting that they are in a hurry.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="20"><p>Who will now tolerate an advocate who begins by 
speaking of the feebleness of his constitution, as is usual in the openings 
of Corvinus? Who will sit out the five books against Verres? Who will endure 
those huge volumes, on a legal plea or form, which we have read in the 
speeches for Marcus Tullius and Aulus Caecina? In our day the judge 
anticipates the speaker, and unless he is charmed and imposed on by the 
train of arguments, or the brilliancy of the thoughts, or the grace and 
elegance of the descriptive sketches, he is deaf to his eloquence. Even the 
mob of bystanders, and the chance listeners who flock in, now usually 
require brightness and beauty in a speech, and they no more endure in the 
law-court the harshness and roughness of antiquity, than they would an actor 
on the stage who chose to reproduce the gestures of Roscius or Ambivius. So 
again the young, those whose studies are on the anvil, who go after the 
orators with a view to their own progress, are anxious not merely to hear 
but also to carry back home some brilliant passage worthy of remembrance. 
They tell it one to another, and often mention it in letters to their 
colonies and provinces, whether it is a reflection lighted up by a neat and 
pithy phrase, or a passage bright with choice and poetic ornament. For we 
now expect from a speaker even poetic beauty, not indeed soiled with the old 
rust of Accius or Pacuvius, but such as is produced from the sacred 
treasures of <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,1015191">Virgil</placeName>, and Lucan. Thus the age of our orators,

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">ANCIENTS INSUFFERABLY DULL</note>
in conforming 
itself to the ear and the taste of such a class, has advanced in beauty and 
ornateness. Nor does it follow that our speeches are less successful because 
they bring pleasure to the ears of those who have to decide. What if you 
were to assume that the temples of the present day are weaker, because, 
instead of being built of rough blocks and ill-shaped tiles, they shine with 
marble and glitter with gold?</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="21"><p>I will 
frankly admit to you that I can hardly keep from laughing at some of the 
ancients, and from falling asleep at others. I do not single out any of the 
common herd, as Canutius, or Arrius, and others in the same sick-room, so to 
say, who are content with mere skin and bones. Even Calvus, although he has 
left, I think, one-and-twenty volumes, scarcely satisfies me in one or two 
short speeches. The rest of the world, I see, does not differ from my 
opinion about him; for how few read his speeches against Asitius or Drusus! 
Certainly his impeachment of Vatinius, as it is entitled, is in the hands of 
students, especially the second of the orations. This, indeed, has a finish 
about the phrases and the periods, and suits the ear of the critic, whence 
you may infer that even Calvus understood what a better style is, but that 
he lacked genius and power rather than the will to speak with more dignity 
and grace. What again from the speeches of Caelius do we admire? Why, we 
like of these the whole, or at least parts, in which we recognise the polish 
and elevation of our own day; but, as for those mean expressions, those gaps 
in the structure of the sentences, and uncouth sentiments, they savour of 
antiquity. No one, I suppose, is so thoroughly antique as to praise Caelius 
simply on the side of his antiqueness. We may, indeed, make allowance for 
Caius Julius C&aelig;sar, on account of his vast schemes and many 
occupations, for having achieved less in eloquence than his divine genius 
demanded from him, and leave him indeed, just as we leave <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName> to his 
philosophy. Undoubtedly in his speeches he fell short of his reputation, 
even by the admission of his admirers. I hardly suppose that any one reads 
C&aelig;sar's speech for Decius the Samnite, or that of <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName> for King 
Deiotarus, or other works equally dull and cold, unless it is some one who 
also admires their poems. For they did write poems, and sent them to 
libraries, with

no better success than <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName>, but with better 
luck, because fewer people know that they wrote them. </p>
<p>Asinius too, 
though born in a time nearer our own, seems to have studied with the Menenii 
and Appii. At any rate he imitated Pacuvius and Accius, not only in his 
tragedies but also in his speeches; he is so harsh and dry. Style, like the 
human body, is then specially beautiful when, so to say, the veins are not 
prominent, and the bones cannot be counted, but when a healthy and sound 
blood fills the limbs, and shows itself in the muscles, and the very sinews 
become beautiful under a ruddy glow and graceful outline. I will not attack 
Corvinus, for it was not indeed his own fault that he did not exhibit the 
luxuriance and brightness of our own day. Rather let us note how far the 
vigour of his intellect or of his imagination satisfied his critical 
faculty.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="22"><p>I come now to <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName>. He had 
the same battle with his contemporaries which I have with you. They admired 
the ancients; he preferred the eloquence of his own time. It was in taste 
more than anything else that he was superior to the orators of that age. In 
fact, he was the first who gave a finish to oratory, the first who applied a 
principle of selection to words, and art to composition. He tried his skill 
at beautiful passages, and invented certain arrangements of the sentence, at 
least in those speeches which he composed when old and near the close of 
life, that is when he had made more progress, and had learnt by practice and 
by many a trial, what was the best style of speaking. As for his early 
speeches, they are not free from the faults of antiquity. He is tedious in 
his introductions, lengthy in his narrations, careless about digressions; he 
is slow to rouse himself, and seldom warms to his subject, and only an idea 
here and there is brought to a fitting and a brilliant close. There is 
nothing which you can pick out or quote, and the style is like a rough 
building, the wall of which indeed is strong and lasting, but not 
particularly polished and bright. Now I would have an orator, like a rich 
and grand householder, not merely be sheltered by a roof sufficient to keep 
off rain and wind, but by one to delight the sight and the eye; not merely 
be provided with such furniture as is enough for necessary purposes, but 
also possess among his treasures gold and jewels, so that he may

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">CICERO HIMSELF FAULTY</note>
find a frequent pleasure 
in handling them and gazing on them. On the other hand, some things should 
be kept at a distance as being now obsolete and ill-savoured. There should 
be no phrase stained, so to speak, with rust; no ideas should be expressed 
in halting and languid periods after the fashion of chronicles. The orator 
must shun an offensive and tasteless scurrility; he must vary the structure 
of his sentences and not end all his clauses in one and the same way.</p></div1> 

<div1 type="chapter" n="23"><p>Phrases like "Fortune's wheel" and "Verrine 
soup," I do not care to ridicule, or that stock ending of every third clause 
in all <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName>'s speeches, "it would seem to be," brought in as the close of 
a period. I have mentioned them with reluctance, omitting several, although 
they are the sole peculiarities admired and imitated by those who call 
themselves orators of the old school. I will not name any one, as I think it 
enough to have pointed at a class. Still, you have before your eyes men who 
read Lucilius rather than <placeName key="tgn,2399200">Horace</placeName>, and Lucretius rather than Virgil, who have 
a mean opinion of the eloquence of Aufidius Bassus, and Servilius Nonianus 
compared with that of Sisenna or Varro, and who despise and loathe the 
treatises of our modern rhetoricians, while those of Calvus are their 
admiration. When these men prose in the old style before the judges, they 
have neither select listeners nor a popular audience; in short the client 
himself hardly endures them. They are dismal and uncouth, and the very 
soundness of which they boast, is the result not so much of real vigour as 
of fasting. Even as to health of body, physicians are not satisfied with 
that which is attained at the cost of mental worry. It is a small matter not 
to be ill; I like a man to be robust and hearty and full of life. If 
soundness is all that you can praise him for, he is not very far from being 
an invalid. Be it yours, my eloquent friends, to grace our age to the best 
of your ability, as in fact you are doing, with the noblest style of 
oratory. You, Messala, imitate, I observe, the choicest beauties of the 
ancients. And you, Maternus and Secundus, combine charm and finish of 
expression with weight of thought. There is discrimination in the phrases 
you invent, order in the treatment of your subject, fullness, when the case 
demands it, conciseness, when it is possible, elegance in your style, and 
perspicuity in every

sentence. You can express passion, and yet 
control an orator's licence. And so, although ill-nature and envy may have 
stood in the way of our good opinions, posterity will speak the truth 
concerning you.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="24"><p>Aper having finished 
speaking, Maternus said, You recognise, do you not, our friend Aper's force 
and passion? With what a torrent, what a rush of eloquence has he been 
defending our age? How full and varied was his tirade against the ancients! 
What ability and spirit, what learning and skill too did he show in 
borrowing from the very men themselves the weapons with which he forthwith 
proceeded to attack them! Still, as to your promise, Messala, there must for 
all this be no change. We neither want a defence of the ancients, nor do we 
compare any of ourselves, though we have just heard our own praises, with 
those whom Aper has denounced. Aper himself thinks otherwise; he merely 
followed an old practice much in vogue with your philosophical school of 
assuming the part of an opponent. Give us then not a panegyric on the 
ancients (their own fame is a sufficient panegyric) but tell us plainly the 
reasons why with us there has been such a falling off from their eloquence, 
the more marked as dates have proved that from the death of <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName> to this 
present day is but a hundred and twenty years.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="25"><p>Messala replied, I will take the line you have prescribed for 
me. Certainly I need not argue long against Aper, who began by raising what 
I think a controversy about a name, implying that it is not correct to call 
ancients those whom we all know to have lived a hundred years ago. I am not 
fighting about a word. Let him call them ancients or elders or any other 
name he prefers, provided only we have the admission that the eloquence of 
that age exceeded ours. If again he freely admits that even in the same, 
much more in different periods, there were many varieties of oratory, 
against this part too of his argument I say nothing. I maintain, however, 
that just as among Attic orators we give the first place to Demosthenes and 
assign the next to Aeschines, Hyperides, Lysias and Lycurgus, while all 
agree in regarding this as pre-eminently the age of speakers, so among 
ourselves <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName> indeed was superior to all the elo-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">CAUSES OF DECLINE</note>
quent men of his day, though Calvus, 
Asinius, C&aelig;sar, Caelius, and <placeName key="tgn,2037959">Brutus</placeName> may claim the right of being 
preferred to those who preceded and who followed them. It matters nothing 
that they differ in special points, seeing that they are generically alike. 
Calvus is the more terse, Asinius has the finer rhythm, C&aelig;sar greater 
brilliancy, Caelius is the more caustic, <placeName key="tgn,2037959">Brutus</placeName> the more earnest, <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> the 
more impassioned, the richer and more forcible. Still about them all there 
is the same healthy tone of eloquence. Take into your hand the works of all 
alike and you see that amid wide differences of genius, there is a 
resemblance and affinity of intellect and moral purpose. Grant that they 
disparaged each other (and certainly there are some passages in their 
letters which show mutual ill-will), still this is the failing, not of the 
orator, but of the man. Calvus, Asinius, <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> himself, I presume, were apt 
to be envious and ill-natured, and to have the other faults of human 
infirmity. <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName> alone of the number in my opinion laid open the 
convictions of his heart frankly and ingenuously, without ill-will or envy. 
Is it possible that he envied <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, when he seems not to have envied even 
C&aelig;sar? As to Servius Galba, and Caius Laelius, and others of the 
ancients whom Aper has persistently assailed, he must not expect me to 
defend them, for I admit that their eloquence, being yet in its infancy and 
imperfectly developed, had certain defects.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="26"><p>After all, if I must put on one side the highest and most 
perfect type of eloquence and select a style, I should certainly prefer the 
vehemence of Caius Gracchus or the sobriety of Lucius Crassus to the curls 
of Maecenas or the jingles of Gallio: so much better is it for an orator to 
wear a rough dress than to glitter in many-coloured and meretricious attire. 
Indeed, neither for an orator or even a man is that style becoming which is 
adopted by many of the speakers of our age, and which, with its idle 
redundancy of words, its meaningless periods and licence of expression, 
imitates the art of the actor. Shocking as it ought to be to our ears it is 
a fact that fame, glory, and genius are sacrificed by many to the boast that 
their compositions are given with the tones of the singer, the gestures of 
the dancer. Hence the exclamation, which, though often heard, is a shame 
and

an absurdity, that our orators speak prettily and our actors 
dance eloquently. For myself I would not deny that Cassius Severus, the only 
speaker whom Aper ventured to name, may, if compared with his successors, be 
called an orator, although in many of his works he shows more violence than 
vigour. The first to despise arrangement, to cast off propriety and delicacy 
of expression, confused by the very weapons he employs, and often stumbling 
in his eagerness to strike, he wrangles rather than fights. Still, as I have 
said, compared with his successors, he is far superior to all in the variety 
of his learning, the charm of his wit, and the solidity of his very 
strength. Not one of them has Aper had the courage to mention, and, so to 
say, to bring into the field. When he had censured Asinius, Caelius, and 
Calvus, I expected that he would show us a host of others, and name more, or 
at least as many who might be pitted man by man against <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, C&aelig;sar, 
and the rest. As it is, he has contented himself with singling out for 
disparagement some ancient orators, and has not dared to praise any of their 
successors, except generally and in terms common to all, fearing, I suppose, 
that he would offend many, if he selected a few. For there is scarce one of 
our rhetoricians who does not rejoice in his conviction that he is to be 
ranked before <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, but unquestionably second to Gabinianus.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="27"><p>For my own part I shall not scruple to mention men 
by name, that, with examples before us, we may the more easily perceive the 
successive steps of the ruin and decay of eloquence. </p>
<p>Maternus here 
interrupted him. Rather prepare yourself to fulfil your promise. We do not 
want proof of the superior eloquence of the ancients; as far as I am 
concerned, it is admitted. We are inquiring into the causes, and these you 
told us but now you had been in the habit of discussing, when you were less 
excited and were not raving against the eloquence of our age, just before 
Aper offended you by attacking your ancestors. </p>
<p>I was not offended, 
replied Messala, by our friend Aper's argument, nor again will you have a 
right to be offended, if any remark of mine happens to grate on your ears, 
for you

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">EDUCATION AT FAULT</note>
know that it is 
a rule in these discussions that we may speak out our convictions without 
impairing mutual good-will. </p>
<p>Proceed, said Maternus. As you are speaking 
of the ancients, avail yourself of ancient freedom, from which we have 
fallen away even yet more than from eloquence.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="28"><p>Messala continued. Far from obscure are the causes which you 
seek. Neither to yourself or to our friends, Secundus and Aper, are they 
unknown, though you assign me the part of speaking out before you what we 
all think. Who does not know that eloquence and all other arts have declined 
from their ancient glory, not from dearth of men, but from the indolence of 
the young, the carelessness of parents, the ignorance of teachers, and 
neglect of the old discipline? The evils which first began in <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> soon spread through <rs type="placename">Italy</rs>, 
and are now diffusing themselves into the provinces. But your provincial 
affairs are best known to yourselves. I shall speak of <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>, and of those native and home-bred vices which take 
hold of us as soon as we are born, and multiply with every stage of life, 
when I have first said a few words on the strict discipline of our ancestors 
in the education and training of children. Every citizen's son, the child of 
a chaste mother, was from the beginning reared, not in the chamber of a 
purchased nurse, but in that mother's bosom and embrace, and it was her 
special glory to study her home and devote herself to her children. It was 
usual to select an elderly kinswoman of approved and esteemed character to 
have the entire charge of all the children of the household. In her presence 
it was the last offence to utter an unseemly word or to do a disgraceful 
act. With scrupulous piety and modesty she regulated not only the boy's 
studies and occupations, but even his recreations and games. Thus it was, as 
tradition says, that the mothers of the Gracchi, of C&aelig;sar, of 
Augustus, <placeName key="tgn,2381157">Cornelia</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,2034307">Aurelia</placeName>, Atia, directed their children's education and 
reared the greatest of sons. The strictness of the discipline tended to form 
in each case a pure and virtuous nature which no vices could warp, and which 
would at once with the whole heart seize on every noble lesson. Whatever its 
bias, whether to the soldier's or the lawyer's art, or to the study of 
eloquence, it would make that its sole aim, and imbibe it in its 
fullness.</p></div1>

<div1 type="chapter" n="29"><p>But in our day we 
entrust the infant to a little Greek servant-girl who is attended by one or 
two, commonly the worst of all the slaves, creatures utterly unfit for any 
important work. Their stories and their prejudices from the very first fill 
the child's tender and uninstructed mind. No one in the whole house cares 
what he says or does before his infant master. Even parents themselves 
familiarise their little ones, not with virtue and modesty, but with jesting 
and glib talk, which lead on by degrees to shamelessness and to contempt for 
themselves as well as for others. Really I think that the characteristic and 
peculiar vices of this city, a liking for actors and a passion for 
gladiators and horses, are all but conceived in the mother's womb. When 
these occupy and possess the mind, how little room has it left for worthy 
attainments! Few indeed are to be found who talk of any other subjects in 
their homes, and whenever we enter a classroom, what else is the 
conversation of the youths. Even with the teachers, these are the more 
frequent topics of talk with their scholars. In fact, they draw pupils, not 
by strictness of discipline or by giving proof of ability, but by assiduous 
court and cunning tricks of flattery.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="30"><p>I say nothing about the learners' first rudiments. Even with these little 
pains are taken, and on the reading of authors, on the study of antiquity 
and a knowledge of facts, of men and of periods, by no means enough labour 
is bestowed. It is rhetoricians, as they are called, who are in request. 
When this profession was first introduced into our city, and how little 
esteem it had among our ancestors, I am now about to explain; but I will 
first recall your attention to the training which we have been told was 
practised by those orators whose infinite industry, daily study and 
incessant application to every branch of learning are seen in the contents 
of their own books. You are doubtless familiar with <placeName key="tgn,2239741">Cicero</placeName>'s book, called 
<placeName key="tgn,2051402">Brutus</placeName>. In the latter part of it (the first gives an account of the ancient 
orators) he relates his own beginnings, his progress, and the growth, so to 
say, of his eloquence. He tells us that he learnt the civil law under 
Quintus Mucius, and that he thoroughly imbibed every branch of philosophy 
under <placeName key="tgn,2029654">Philo</placeName> of the Academy and under Diodotus the Stoic; that not content 
with the teachers under

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">ANCIENT EDUCATION 
HUMANISTIC</note>
whom he had had the opportunity of studying at <rs type="placename">Rome</rs>, he travelled through <rs type="placename">Achaia</rs> and <rs type="placename">Asia Minor</rs> so as to 
embrace every variety of every learned pursuit. Hence we really find in 
<placeName key="tgn,2027172">Cicero</placeName>'s works that he was not deficient in the knowledge of geometry, 
music, grammar, or, in short, any liberal accomplishment. The subtleties of 
logic, the useful lessons of ethical science, the movements and causes of 
the universe, were alike known to him. The truth indeed is this, my 
excellent friends, that <placeName key="tgn,2027172">Cicero</placeName>'s wonderful eloquence wells up and overflows 
out of a store of erudition, a multitude of accomplishments, and a knowledge 
that was universal. The strength and power of oratory, unlike all other 
arts, is not confined within narrow and straitened limits, but the orator is 
he who can speak on every question with grace, elegance, and persuasiveness, 
suitably to the dignity of his subject, the requirements of the occasion, 
and the taste of his audience.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="31"><p>Such 
was the conviction of the ancients, and to produce this result they were 
aware that it was necessary not only to declaim in the schools of 
rhetoricians, or to exercise the tongue and the voice in fictitious 
controversies quite remote from reality, but also to imbue the mind with 
those studies which treat of good and evil, of honour and dishonour, of 
right and wrong. All this, indeed, is the subject-matter of the orator's 
speeches. Equity in the law-court, honour in the council-chamber, are our 
usual topics of discussion. Still, these often pass into each other, and no 
one can speak on them with fulness, variety, and elegance but he who has 
studied human nature, the power of virtue, the depravity of vice, and the 
conception of those things which can be classed neither among virtues nor 
vices. These are the sources whence flows the greater ease with which he who 
knows what anger is, rouses or soothes the anger of a judge, the readier 
power with which he moves to pity who knows what pity is, and what emotions 
of the soul excite it. An orator practised in such arts and exercises, 
whether he has to address the angry, the biassed, the envious, the 
sorrowful, or the trembling, will understand different mental conditions, 
apply his skill, adapt his style, and have every instrument of his craft in 
readiness, or in reserve for every occasion. Some there are whose assent is 
more secured by

an incisive and terse style, in which each 
inference is rapidly drawn. With such, it will be an advantage to have 
studied logic. Others are more attracted by a diffuse and smoothly flowing 
speech, appealing to the common sentiments of humanity. To impress such we 
must borrow from the Peripatetics commonplaces suited and ready prepared for 
every discussion. The Academy will give us combativeness, Plato, sublimity, 
Xenophon, sweetness. Nor will it be unseemly in an orator to adopt even 
certain exclamations of honest emotion, from Epicurus and Metrodorus, and to 
use them as occasion requires. It is not a philosopher after the Stoic 
school whom we are forming, but one who ought to imbibe thoroughly some 
studies, and to have a taste of all. Accordingly, knowledge of the civil law 
was included in the training of the ancient orators, and they also imbued 
their minds with grammar, music, and geometry. In truth, in very many, I may 
say in all cases, acquaintance with law is desirable, and in several this 
last-mentioned knowledge is a necessity.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="32"><p>Let no one reply that it is enough for us to learn, as occasion 
requires, some single and detached subject. In the first place we use our 
own property in one way, a loan in another, and there is evidently a wide 
difference between possessing what one exhibits and borrowing it. Next, the 
very knowledge of many subjects sits gracefully on us, even when we are 
otherwise engaged, and makes itself visible and conspicuous where you would 
least expect it. Even the average citizen, and not only the learned and 
critical hearer, perceives it, and forthwith showers his praises in the 
acknowledgment that the man has been a genuine student, has gone through 
every branch of eloquence, and is, in short, an orator. And I maintain that 
the only orator is, and ever has been, one who, like a soldier equipped at 
all points going to the battle-field, enters the forum armed with every 
learned accomplishment. </p>
<p>All this is so neglected by the speakers of our 
time that we detect in their pleadings the style of every-day conversation, 
and unseemly and shameful deficiencies. They are ignorant of the laws, they 
do not understand the senate's decrees, they actually scoff at the civil 
law, while they quite

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">MODERN EDUCATION 
PROFESSIONAL</note>
dread the study of philosophy, and the opinions of the 
learned; and eloquence, banished, so to say, from her proper realm, is 
dragged down by them into utter poverty of thought and constrained periods. 
Thus she who, once mistress of all the arts, held sway with a glorious 
retinue over our souls, now clipped and shorn, without state, without 
honour, I had almost said without her freedom, is studied as one of the 
meanest handicrafts. This then I believe to be the first and chief cause of 
so marked a falling off among us from the eloquence of the old orators. If 
witnesses are wanted, whom shall I name in preference to Demosthenes among 
the Greeks, who is said by tradition to have been a most attentive hearer of 
Plato? <placeName key="tgn,2027172">Cicero</placeName> too tells us, I think, in these very words, that whatever he 
had achieved in eloquence he had gained, not from rhetoricians, but in the 
walks of the Academy. There are other causes, some of them great and 
important, which it is for you in fairness to explain, as I have now done my 
part, and, after my usual way, have offended pretty many persons who, if 
they happen to hear all this, will, I am sure, say that, in praising an 
acquaintance with law and philosophy as a necessity for an orator, I have 
been applauding my own follies.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="33"><p>For 
myself, replied Maternus, I do not think that you have completed the task 
which you undertook. Far from it. You have, I think, only made a beginning, 
and indicated, so to say, its traces and outlines. You have indeed described 
to us the usual equipment of the ancient orators, and pointed out the 
contrast presented by our idleness and ignorance to their very diligent and 
fruitful studies. I want to hear the rest. Having learnt from you what they 
knew, with which we are unacquainted, I wish also to be told the process of 
training by which, when mere lads, and when about to enter the forum, they 
used to strengthen and nourish their intellects. For you will not, I 
imagine, deny that eloquence depends much less on art and theory than on 
capacity and practice, and our friends here seem by their looks to think the 
same. </p>
<p>Aper and Secundus having assented, Messala, so to say, began 
afresh. As I have, it seems, explained to your satis-

faction the 
first elements and the germs of ancient eloquence in showing you the studies 
in which the orator of antiquity was formed and educated, I will now discuss 
the process of his training. However, even the studies themselves involve a 
training, and no one can acquire such profound and varied knowledge without 
adding practice to theory, fluency to practice, and eloquence itself to 
fluency. Hence we infer that the method of acquiring what you mean to 
produce publicly, and of so producing what you have acquired, is one and the 
same. Still, if any one thinks this somewhat obscure, and distinguishes 
broadly between theory and practice, he will at least allow that a mind 
thoroughly furnished and imbued with such studies will enter with a far 
better preparation on the kinds of practice which seem specially appropriate 
to the orator.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="34"><p>It was accordingly 
usual with our ancestors, when a lad was being prepared for public speaking, 
as soon as he was fully trained by home discipline, and his mind was stored 
with culture, to have him taken by his father, or his relatives to the 
orator who held the highest rank in the state. The boy used to accompany and 
attend him, and be present at all his speeches, alike in the law-court and 
the assembly, and thus he picked up the art of repartee, and became 
habituated to the strife of words, and indeed, I may almost say, learnt how 
to fight in battle. Thereby young men acquired from the first great 
experience and confidence, and a very large stock of discrimination, for 
they were studying in broad daylight, in the very thick of the conflict, 
where no one can say anything foolish or self-contradictory without its 
being refuted by the judge, or ridiculed by the opponent, or, last of all, 
repudiated by the very counsel with him. Thus from the beginning they were 
imbued with true and genuine eloquence, and, although they attached 
themselves to one pleader, still they became acquainted with all advocates 
of their own standing in a multitude of cases before the courts. They had 
too abundant experience of the popular ear in all its greatest varieties, 
and with this they could easily ascertain what was liked or disapproved in 
each speaker. Thus they were not in want of a teacher of the very best and 
choicest kind,

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">PRACTITIONER VERSUS 
PROFESSOR</note>
who could show them eloquence in her true features, not in 
a mere resemblance; nor did they lack opponents and rivals, who fought with 
actual steel, not with a wooden sword, and the audience too was always 
crowded, always changing, made up of unfriendly as well as of admiring 
critics, so that neither success nor failure could be disguised. You know, 
of course, that eloquence wins its great and enduring fame quite as much 
from the benches of our opponents as from those of our friends; nay, more, 
its rise from that quarter is steadier, and its growth surer. Undoubtedly it 
was under such teachers that the youth of whom I am speaking, the disciple 
of orators, the listener in the forum, the student in the law-courts, was 
trained and practised by the experiences of others. The laws he learnt by 
daily hearing; the faces of the judges were familiar to him; the ways of 
popular assemblies were continually before his eyes; he had frequent 
experience of the ear of the people, and whether he undertook a prosecution 
or a defence, he was at once singly and alone equal to any case. We still 
read with admiration the speeches in which Lucius Crassus in his nineteenth, 
C&aelig;sar and Asinius Pollio in their twenty-first year, Calvus, when very 
little older, denounced, respectively, <placeName key="tgn,1017122">Carbo</placeName>, Dolabella, <placeName key="tgn,2226590">Cato</placeName>, and 
Vatinius.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="35"><p>But in these days we have 
our youths taken to the professors' theatre, the rhetoricians, as we call 
them. The class made its appearance a little before <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>'s time, and was 
not liked by our ancestors, as is evident from the fact that, when Crassus 
and Domitius were censors, they were ordered, as <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> says, to close "the 
school of impudence." However, as I was just saying, the boys are taken to 
schools in which it is hard to tell whether the place itself, or their 
fellow-scholars, or the character of their studies, do their minds most 
harm. As for the place, there is no such thing as reverence, for no one 
enters it who is not as ignorant as the rest. As for the scholars, there can 
be no improvement, when boys and striplings with equal assurance address, 
and are addressed by, other boys and striplings. As for the mental exercises 
themselves, they are the reverse of beneficial. Two kinds of subject-matter 
are dealt with before

the rhetoricians, the persuasive and the 
controversial. The persuasive, as being comparatively easy and requiring 
less skill, is given to boys. The controversial is assigned to riper 
scholars, and, good heavens! what strange and astonishing productions are 
the result! It comes to pass that subjects remote from all reality are 
actually used for declamation. Thus the reward of a tyrannicide, or the 
choice of an outraged maiden, or a remedy for a pestilence, or a mother's 
incest, anything, in short, daily discussed in our schools, never, or but 
very rarely in the courts, is dwelt on in grand language. </p>
<p><note anchored="yes" type="ed">[The rest of Messala's speech is lost. Maternus is now again the 
speaker.]</note></p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="36"><p>Great eloquence, like 
fire, grows with its material; it becomes fiercer with movement, and 
brighter as it burns. On this same principle was developed in our state too 
the eloquence of antiquity. Although even the modern orator has attained all 
that the circumstances of a settled, quiet, and prosperous community allow, 
still in the disorder and licence of the past more seemed to be within the 
reach of the speaker, when, amid a universal confusion that needed one 
guiding hand, he exactly adapted his wisdom to the bewildered people's 
capacity of conviction. Hence, laws without end and consequent popularity; 
hence, speeches of magistrates who, I may say, passed nights on the Rostra; 
hence, prosecutions of influential citizens brought to trial, and feuds 
transmitted to whole families; hence, factions among the nobles, and 
incessant strife between the senate and the people. In each case the state 
was torn asunder, but the eloquence of the age was exercised, and, as it 
seemed, was loaded with great rewards. For the more powerful a man was as a 
speaker, the more easily did he obtain office, the more decisively superior 
was he to his colleagues in office, the more influence did he acquire with 
the leaders of the state, the more weight in the senate, the more notoriety 
and fame with the people. Such men had a host of clients, even among foreign 
nations; the magistrates, when leaving <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> for the 
provinces, showed them respect, and courted their favour as soon as they 
returned. The pr&aelig;torship and the consulship seemed to offer themselves 
to them,

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">ORATORY VITAL IN REPUBLIC</note>
and 
even when they were out of office, they were not out of power, for they 
swayed both people and senate with their counsels and influence. Indeed, 
they had quite convinced themselves that without eloquence no one could win 
or retain a distinguished and eminent position in the state. And no wonder. 
Even against their own wish they had to show themselves before the people. 
It was little good for them to give a brief vote in the senate without 
supporting their opinion with ability and eloquence. If brought into popular 
odium, or under some charge, they had to reply in their own words. Again, 
they were under the necessity of giving evidence in the public courts, not 
in their absence by affidavit, but of being present and of speaking it 
openly. There was thus a strong stimulus to win the great prizes of 
eloquence, and as the reputation of a good speaker was considered an honour 
and a glory, so it was thought a disgrace to seem mute and speechless. Shame 
therefore quite as much as hope of reward prompted men not to take the place 
of a pitiful client rather than that of a patron, or to see hereditary 
connections transferred to others, or to seem spiritless and incapable of 
office from either failing to obtain it or from holding it weakly when 
obtained.</p></div1>
<div1 type="chapter" n="37"><p>Perhaps you have had in your 
hands the old records, still to be found in the libraries of antiquaries, 
which Mucianus is just now collecting, and which have already been brought 
together and published in, I think, eleven books of Transactions, and three 
of Letters. From these we may gather that Cneius Pompeius and Marcus Crassus 
rose to power as much by force of intellect and by speaking as by their 
might in arms; that the Lentuli, Metelli, Luculli, and Curios, and the rest 
of our nobles, bestowed great labour and pains on these studies, and that, 
in fact, no one in those days acquired much influence without some 
eloquence. We must consider too the eminence of the men accused, and the 
vast issues involved. These of themselves do very much for eloquence. There 
is, indeed, a wide difference between having to speak on a theft, a 
technical point, a judicial decision, and on bribery at elections, the 
plundering of the allies, and the massacre of citizens. Though it is better 
that these evils should not befall us, and the best condition of 

the state is that in which we are spared such sufferings, still, when 
they did occur, they supplied a grand material for the orator. His mental 
powers rise with the dignity of his subject, and no one can produce a noble 
and brilliant speech unless he has got an adequate case. Demosthenes, I take 
it, does not owe his fame to his speeches against his guardians, and it is 
not his defence of Publius Quintius, or of Licinius Archias, which make 
<placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName> a great orator; it is his Catiline, his <placeName key="tgn,7010922">Milo</placeName>, his Verres, and 
Antonius, which have shed over him this lustre. Not indeed that it was worth 
the state's while to endure bad citizens that orators might have plenty of 
matter for their speeches, but, as I now and then remind you, we must 
remember the point, and understand that we are speaking of an art which 
arose more easily in stormy and unquiet times. Who knows not that it is 
better and more profitable to enjoy peace than to be harassed by war? Yet 
war produces more good soldiers than peace. Eloquence is on the same 
footing. The oftener she has stood, so to say, in the battle-field, the more 
wounds she has inflicted and received, the mightier her antagonist, the 
sharper the conflicts she has freely chosen, the higher and more splendid 
has been her rise, and ennobled by these contests she lives in the praises 
of mankind.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="38"><p>I pass now to the forms 
and character of procedure in the old courts. As they exist now, they are 
indeed more favourable to truth, but the forum in those days was a better 
training for eloquence. There no speaker was under the necessity of 
concluding within a very few hours; there was freedom of adjournment, and 
every one fixed for himself the limits of his speech, and there was no 
prescribed number of days or of counsel. It was Cneius Pompeius who, in his 
third consulship, first restricted all this, and put a bridle, so to say, on 
eloquence, intending, however, that all business should be transacted in the 
forum according to law, and before the pr&aelig;tors. Here is a stronger 
proof of the greater importance of the cases tried before these judges than 
in the fact that causes in the Court of the Hundred, causes which now hold 
the first place, were then so eclipsed by the fame of other trials that not 
a speech of <placeName key="tgn,2068515">Cicero</placeName>, or C&aelig;sar, or <placeName key="tgn,2200724">Brutus</placeName>, or Caelius, or Calvus, or, in 
short, any

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">REPUBLICAN ORATORY 
SPACIOUS</note>
great orator is now read, that was delivered in that Court, 
except only the orations of Asinius Pollio for the heirs of Urbinia, as they 
are entitled, and even Pollio delivered these in the middle of the reign of 
Augustus, a period of long rest, of unbroken repose for the people and 
tranquillity for the senate, when the emperor's perfect discipline had put 
its restraints on eloquence as well as on all else.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="39"><p>Perhaps what I am going to say will be thought 
trifling and ridiculous; but I will say it even to be laughed at. What 
contempt (so I think at least) has been brought on eloquence by those little 
overcoats into which we squeeze, and, so to say, box ourselves up, when we 
chat with the judges! How much force may we suppose has been taken from our 
speeches by the little rooms and offices in which nearly all cases have to 
be set forth. Just as a spacious course tests a fine horse, so the orator 
has his field, and unless he can move in it freely and at ease, his 
eloquence grows feeble and breaks down. Nay more; we find the pains and 
labour of careful composition out of place, for the judge keeps asking when 
you are going to open the case, and you must begin from his question. 
Frequently he imposes silence on the advocate to hear proofs and witnesses. 
Meanwhile only one or two persons stand by you as you are speaking and the 
whole business is transacted almost in solitude. But the orator wants shouts 
and applause, and something like a theatre, all which and the like were the 
every day lot of the orators of antiquity, when both numbers and nobility 
pressed into the forum, when gatherings of clients and the people in their 
tribes and deputations from the towns and indeed a great part of <rs type="placename">Italy</rs> stood by the accused in his peril, and <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>'s 
citizens felt in a multitude of trials that they themselves had an interest 
in the decision. We know that there was a universal rush of the people to 
hear the accusation and the defence of <placeName key="tgn,2074227">Cornelius</placeName>, Scaurus, <placeName key="tgn,1013243">Milo</placeName>, Bestia, and 
Vatinius, so that even the coldest speaker might have been stirred and 
kindled by the mere enthusiasm of the citizens in their strife. And 
therefore indeed such pleadings are still extant, and thus the men too who 
pleaded, owe their fame to no other speeches more than these.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="40"><p>Again, what stimulus to genius and what fire to 
the

orator was furnished by incessant popular assemblies, by the 
privilege of attacking the most influential men, and by the very glory of 
such feuds when most of the good speakers did not spare even a Publius 
Scipio, or a Sulla, or a Cneius Pompeius, and following the common impulse 
of envy availed themselves of the popular ear for invective against eminent 
citizens. I am not speaking of a quiet and peaceful accomplishment, which 
delights in what is virtuous and well regulated. No; the great and famous 
eloquence of old is the nursling of the licence which fools called freedom; 
it is the companion of sedition, the stimulant of an unruly people, a 
stranger to obedience and subjection, a defiant, reckless, presumptuous 
thing which does not show itself in a well-governed state. What orator have 
we ever heard of at <rs type="placename">Sparta</rs> or at <rs type="placename">Crete</rs>? A very strict discipline and very strict laws 
prevailed, tradition says, in both those states. Nor do we know of the 
existence of eloquence among the Macedonians or Persians, or in any people 
content with a settled government. There were some orators at <rs type="placename">Rhodes</rs> and a host of them at <rs type="placename">Athens</rs>, but there the people, there any ignorant fellow, 
anybody, in short, could do anything. So too our own state, while it went 
astray and wore out its strength in factious strife and discord, with 
neither peace in the forum, unity in the senate, order in the courts, 
respect for merit, or seemly behaviour in the magistrates, produced beyond 
all question a more vigorous eloquence, just as an untilled field yields 
certain herbage in special plenty. Still the eloquence of the Gracchi was 
not an equivalent to <rs type="placename">Rome</rs> for having to endure their 
legislation, and Cicero's fame as an orator was a poor compensation for the 
death he died.</p></div1> 
<div1 type="chapter" n="41"><p>And so now the forum, 
which is all that our speakers have left them of antiquity, is an evidence 
of a state not thoroughly reformed or as orderly as we could wish. Who but 
the guilty or unfortunate apply to us? What town puts itself under our 
protection but one harassed by its neighbours or by strife at home? When we 
plead for a province is it not one that has been plundered and ill-treated? 
Surely it would be better not to complain than to have to seek redress. 
Could a community be found in which no one did wrong, an orator would be as 
superfluous among its inno-

<note anchored="yes" place="marg">SUPERFLUOUS UNDER 
IMPERIAL RULE</note>
cent people as a physician among the healthy. As the 
healing art is of very little use and makes very little progress in nations 
which enjoy particularly robust constitutions and vigorous frames, so the 
orator gets an inferior and less splendid renown where a sound morality and 
willing obedience to authority prevail. What need there of long speeches in 
the senate, when the best men are soon of one mind, or of endless harangues 
to the people, when political questions are decided not by an ignorant 
multitude, but by one man of pre-eminent wisdom? What need of voluntary 
prosecutions, when crimes are so rare and slight, or of defences full of 
spiteful insinuation and exceeding proper bounds, when the clemency of the 
judge offers itself to the accused in his peril?</p>
<p>Be assured, my most 
excellent, and, as far as the age requires, most eloquent friends, that had 
you been born in the past, and the men we admire in our own day, had some 
god in fact suddenly changed your lives and your age, the highest fame and 
glory of eloquence would have been yours, and they too would not have lacked 
moderation and self-control. As it is, seeing that no one can at the same 
time enjoy great renown and great tranquillity, let everybody make the best 
of the blessings of his own age without disparaging other periods. 
</p>
<p>Maternus had now finished. There were, replied Messala, some points I 
should controvert, some on which I should like to hear more, if the day were 
not almost spent. It shall be, said Maternus, as you wish, on a future 
occasion, and anything you have thought obscure in my argument, we will 
again discuss. Then he rose and embraced Aper. I mean, he said, to accuse 
you before the poets, and so will Messala before the antiquarians. And I, 
rejoined Aper, will accuse you before the rhetoricians and professors. 
</p>
<p>They laughed good-humouredly, and we parted.</p>
</div1>
</body></text></TEI.2>
