<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Amours</title>
				<author>P. Ovidius Naso</author>
				<editor role="editor">various</editor>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:FIPSE">The Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education
					(FIPSE)</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>

			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>P. Ovidius Naso</author>
						<title>Ovid's Art of Love (in three Books), the Remedy of Love, the Art of
							Beauty, the Court of Love, the History of Love, and Amours</title>
						<respStmt>
							<name>Anne Mahoney</name>
							<resp>edited for Perseus</resp>
						</respStmt>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Calvin Blanchard</publisher>
							<date>1855</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl n="CTS">
				<cRefPattern n="line"
					matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+).(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2']//tei:l[@n='$3'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts book and poem and line</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				<cRefPattern n="poem"
					matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts book and poem</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				<cRefPattern n="book"
					matchPattern="(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts book</p>
				</cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Am.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState n="chunk" unit="poem"/>
				<refState unit="line"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English </language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin </language>
				<language ident="fre">French </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0959.phi001.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
			<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="ep">
					<p>The epigram is not here translated. </p>
				</div>

				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1">
					<head>Elegy I: By Dryden</head>
					<l n="1">For mighty wars I thought to tune my lute,</l>
					<l n="2">And make my measures to my subject suit.</l>
					<l n="3">Six feet for ev'ry verse the muse design'd,</l>
					<l n="4">But Cupid laughing, when he saw my mind,</l>
					<l n="5">From ev'ry second verse a foot purloin'd.</l>
					<l n="6">"Who gave thee, boy, this arbitrary sway,</l>
					<l n="7">On subjects, not thy own, commands to lay,</l>
					<l n="8">Who Phoebus only, and his laws obey ?</l>
					<l n="9">'Tis more absurd, than if the queen of love</l>
					<l n="10">Should in Minerva's arms to battle move;</l>
					<l n="11">Or manly Pallas from that queen should take</l>
					<l n="12">Her torch, and o'er the dying lover shake.</l>
					<l n="13">In fields as well may Cynthia sow the corn,</l>
					<l n="14">Or <placeName key="tgn,1092955">Ceres</placeName> wind in woods the
						bugle-horn;</l>
					<l n="15">As well may Phoebus quit the trembling string,</l>
					<l n="16">For sword and shield; and Mars may learn to sing.</l>
					<l n="17">Already thy dominions are too large;</l>
					<l n="18">Be not ambitious of a foreign charge.</l>
					<l n="19">If thou wilt reign o'er all, and ev'ry where,</l>
					<l n="20">The god of music for his harp may fear.</l>
					<l n="21">Thus when with soaring wings I seek renown,</l>
					<l n="22">Thou pluck'st my pinions, and I flutter down.</l>
					<l n="23">Could I on such mean thoughts my muse employ,</l>
					<l n="24">I want a mistress, or a blooming boy."</l>
					<l n="25">Thus I complain'd; his bow the stripling bent,</l>
					<l n="26">And chose an arrow fit for his intent.</l>
					<l n="27">The shaft his purpose fatally pursues;</l>
					<l n="28">" Now, poet, there's a subject for thy muse,"</l>
					<l n="29">He said: (too well, alas, he knows his trade,)</l>
					<l n="30">For in my breast a mortal wound he made.</l>
					<l n="31">Far hence ye proud Hexameters remove,</l>
					<l n="32">My verse is pac'd, and tramell'd into love.</l>
					<l n="33">With myrtle wreaths my thoughtful brows enclose,</l>
					<l n="34">While in unequal verse I sing my woes. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="2">
					<head>Elegy II: By Creech</head>
					<l n="1">Ah me! why am I so uneasy grown?</l>
					<l n="2">Ah! why so restless on my bed of down?</l>
					<l n="3">Why do I wish to sleep, but wish in vain?</l>
					<l n="4">Why am I all the tedious night in pain?</l>
					<l n="5">What cause is this, that ease, that rest denies?</l>
					<l n="6">And why my words break forth in gentle sighs?</l>
					<l n="7">Sure I should know if love had fix'd his dart;</l>
					<l n="8">Or creeps he softly in with treacherous art,</l>
					<l n="9">And then grows tyrant, there and wounds the heart?</l>
					<l n="10">'Tis so, the shaft sticks deep, and galls my breast;</l>
					<l n="11">'Tis tyrant love, that robs my thoughts of rest!</l>
					<l n="12">Well, shall I tamely yield, or must I fight?</l>
					<l n="13">I'll yield; 'tis patience makes a burden light:</l>
					<l n="14">A shaken torch grows fierce, and sparks arise;</l>
					<l n="15">But, if unmov'd, the fire looks pale and dies.</l>
					<l n="16">The hard-mouth'd horse smarts for his fierce disdain</l>
					<l n="17">The gentle's ridden with a looser rein.</l>
					<l n="18">Love smooths the gentle, but the fierce reclaims;</l>
					<l n="19">He fires their breasts, and fills their souls with flames.</l>
					<l n="20">I yield; great Love, my former crimes forgive,</l>
					<l n="21">Forget my rebel thoughts, and let me live;</l>
					<l n="22">No need of force: I willingly obey,</l>
					<l n="23">And now unarm'd, shall prove no glorious prey.</l>
					<l n="24">Go take thy mother's doves, thy myrtle crown,</l>
					<l n="25">And for thy chariot, Mars shall lend his own;</l>
					<l n="26">There thou shalt sit in thy triumphant pride,</l>
					<l n="27">And, whilst glad shouts resound on ev'ry side,</l>
					<l n="28">Thy gentle hands thy mother's doves shall guide.</l>
					<l n="29">And there to make thy glorious pomp and state,</l>
					<l n="30">A train of sighing youths, and maids shall wait,</l>
					<l n="31">Yet none complain of an unhappy fate.</l>
					<l n="32">There newly conquer'd I, still fresh my wound,</l>
					<l n="33">Will march along, my hands with myrtle bound;</l>
					<l n="34">There modesty, with veils thrown o'er her face,</l>
					<l n="35">Now doubly blushing at her own disgrace;</l>
					<l n="36">There sober thoughts, and whatso'er disdains</l>
					<l n="37">Love's rules, shall feel his power, and bear his chains:</l>
					<l n="38">Then all shall fear, all bow, yet all rejoice;</l>
					<l n="39">"Io triumphe" be the public voice.</l>
					<l n="40">Thy constant guards, soft fancy, hope and fear,</l>
					<l n="41">Anger, and soft caresses shall be there:</l>
					<l n="42">By these strong guards are men and gods o'erthrown;</l>
					<l n="43">These conquer for thee, Love, and these alone,</l>
					<l n="44">Thy mother, from the sky thy pomp shall grace,</l>
					<l n="45">And scatter sweetest roses in thy face:</l>
					<l n="46">There glorious Love shall ride, profusely dress'd</l>
					<l n="47">With all the richest jewels of the east:</l>
					<l n="48">Rich gems thy quiver, and thy wheels infold,</l>
					<l n="49">And hide the poorness of the baser gold.</l>
					<l n="50">Then thou shalt conquer many, then.thy darts</l>
					<l n="51">Shall scatter thousand wounds on tender hearts:</l>
					<l n="52">Thy shafts themselves will fly, thy neighb'ring fire</l>
					<l n="53">Will catch mens' breasts, and kindle warm desire.</l>
					<l n="54">Thus conqu'ring <placeName key="tgn,2097807">Bacchus</placeName> looks in
						Indian groves,</l>
					<l n="55">He drawn by tigers, thou by murm'ring doves.</l>
					<l n="56">Well then, since I too can increase thy train,</l>
					<l n="57">Spend not thy force on me, and rage in vain;</l>
					<l n="58">Look on thy kinsman Caesar's happy slaves,</l>
					<l n="59">The same victorious arm that conquers, saves. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="3">
					<head>Elegy III: To His Mistress. By Charles Hopkins.</head>
					<l n="1">Be just, dear maid, an equal passion prove,</l>
					<l n="2">Or show me cause why I should ever love.</l>
					<l n="3">I do not at your cold disdain repine,</l>
					<l n="4">Nor ask your love, do you but suffer mine.</l>
					<l n="5">I dare not aim at more exalted bliss,</l>
					<l n="6">And Venus will bestow her vot'ry this.</l>
					<l n="7">Take hin, who will for endless ages serve:</l>
					<l n="8">Take him whose faithful flame will never swerve</l>
					<l n="9">Though no illustrious names my race adorn;</l>
					<l n="10">Who am but of equestrian order born;</l>
					<l n="11">Though a few ploughs serve my paternal fields,</l>
					<l n="12">Nor my small table many dishes yields;</l>
					<l n="13">Yet Bacchus, Phoebus, and the tuneful nine,</l>
					<l n="14">Are all my friends, and to my side incline,</l>
					<l n="15">And love's great god, at last, will make me thine.</l>
					<l n="16">Heav'n knows, dear maid, I love no other fair;</l>
					<l n="17">In thee lives all my love, my heav'n lies there.</l>
					<l n="18">Oh! may I by indulgent Fate's decree,</l>
					<l n="19">With thee lead all my life, and die with thee.</l>
					<l n="20">Thy beauties yield me my transporting theme;</l>
					<l n="21">And while I celebrate thy charming name,</l>
					<l n="22">My verse shall be as sacred as my flame.</l>
					<l n="23">Jove's sev'ral rapes, his injur'd Io's wrongs,</l>
					<l n="24">Are made immortal in his poet's songs.</l>
					<l n="25">Verse still reveals where Leda's flames began,</l>
					<l n="26">Rais'd by the secret godhead in the swan,</l>
					<l n="27">The story of the rape Europa bore,</l>
					<l n="28">Shall last while winds shall rage, or waters roar.</l>
					<l n="29">Your name shall live like theirs, while verse endures,</l>
					<l n="30">And mine be ever writ, and read with yours. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="4">
					<head>Elegy IV: To His Mistress, whose husband is invited to a feast with him.
						The poet instructed her how to behave herself in his company. By <placeName key="tgn,1014723">Dryden</placeName>.</head>
					<l n="1">Your husband will be with us at the treat,</l>
					<l n="2">May that be the last supper he shall eat.</l>
					<l n="3">And am poor I, a guest invited there,</l>
					<l n="4">Only to see, while he may touch the fair?</l>
					<l n="5">To see you kiss, and hug your nauseous lord,</l>
					<l n="6">While his lewd hand descends below the board?</l>
					<l n="7">No wonder that Hippodamia's charms,</l>
					<l n="8">At such a sight, the Centaurs urg'd to arms:</l>
					<l n="9">That in a rage, they threw their cups aside,</l>
					<l n="10">Assail'd the bridegroom, and would force the bride.</l>
					<l n="11">I am not half a horse, (I would I were :)</l>
					<l n="12">Yet hardly can from you my hands forbear.</l>
					<l n="13">Take, then, my counsel; which observ'd, may be,</l>
					<l n="14">Of some importance both to you and me.</l>
					<l n="15">Be sure to come before your man be there,</l>
					<l n="16">There's nothing can be done, but come howe'er.</l>
					<l n="17">Sit next him, (that belongs to decency;)</l>
					<l n="18">But tread upon my foot in passing by.</l>
					<l n="19">Read in my looks what silently they speak,</l>
					<l n="20">And slily, with your eyes, your answer make.</l>
					<l n="21">My lifted eye-brow shall declare my pain,</l>
					<l n="22">My right hand to his fellow shall complain;</l>
					<l n="23">And on the back a letter shall design,</l>
					<l n="24">Beside a note that shall be writ in wine.</l>
					<l n="25">Whene'er you think upon our last embrace,</l>
					<l n="26">With your fore-finger gently touch your face.</l>
					<l n="27">If any word of mine offend my dear,</l>
					<l n="28">Pull with your hand the velvet of your ear;</l>
					<l n="29">If you are pleas'd with what I do or say,</l>
					<l n="30">Handle your rings, or vith your fingers play.</l>
					<l n="31">As suppliants use at altars, hold the board,</l>
					<l n="32">Whene'er you wish the devil may take your lord.</l>
					<l n="33">When he fills for you, never touch the cup,</l>
					<l n="34">But bid th' officious cuckold drink it up:</l>
					<l n="35">The waiter on those services employ;</l>
					<l n="36">Drink you, and I will snatch it from the boy,</l>
					<l n="37">Watching the part where your sweet mouth hath been,</l>
					<l n="38">And thence, with eager lips, will suck it in.</l>
					<l n="39">If he, with clownish manners, thinks it fit</l>
					<l n="40">To taste, and offer you the nasty bit,</l>
					<l n="41">Reject his greasy kindness, and restore</l>
					<l n="42">Th' unsav'ry morsel he had chew'd before.</l>
					<l n="43">Nor let his arms embrace your neck, nor rest</l>
					<l n="44">Your tender cheek upon his hairy breast;</l>
					<l n="45">Let not his hand within your bosom stray,</l>
					<l n="46">And rudely with your pretty bubbies play.</l>
					<l n="47">But, above all, let him no kiss receive,</l>
					<l n="48">That's an offence I never can forgive;</l>
					<l n="49">Do not, oh! do not that sweet mouth resign,</l>
					<l n="50">Lest I rise up in arms, and cry 'tis mine.</l>
					<l n="51">I shall thrust in betwixt, and void of fear</l>
					<l n="52">The manifest adult'rer will appear.</l>
					<l n="53">These things are plain to sight, but more I doubt</l>
					<l n="54">What you conceal beneath your petticoat;</l>
					<l n="55">Take not his leg between your tender thighs,</l>
					<l n="56">Nor with your hand provoke my foe to rise.</l>
					<l n="57">How many love inventions I deplore,</l>
					<l n="58">Which I myself have practis'd all before !</l>
					<l n="59">How oft have I been forc'd the robe to lift</l>
					<l n="60">In company; to make a homely shift</l>
					<l n="61">For a bare bout, ill huddled o'er in haste,</l>
					<l n="62">While o'er my side the fair her mantle cast!</l>
					<l n="63">You to your husband shall not be so kind,</l>
					<l n="64">But lest you should, your mantle leave behind.</l>
					<l n="65">Encourage him to tope, but kiss him not,</l>
					<l n="66">Nor mix one drop of water in his pot.</l>
					<l n="67">If he be fuddled well, and snores apace,</l>
					<l n="68">Then we may take advice from time and place.</l>
					<l n="69">When all depart, while compliments are loud,</l>
					<l n="70">Be sure to mix among the thickest crowd;</l>
					<l n="71">There I will be, and there we cannot miss,</l>
					<l n="72">Perhaps to grubble, or at least to kiss.</l>
					<l n="73">Alas, what length of labor I employ,</l>
					<l n="74">Just to secure a short and transient joy!</l>
					<l n="75">For night must part us, and when night is come</l>
					<l n="76">Tuck'd underneath his arm, he leads you home.</l>
					<l n="77">He locks you in, I follow to the door,</l>
					<l n="78">His fortune envy, and my own deplore;</l>
					<l n="79">He kisses you, he more than kisses too,</l>
					<l n="80">Th' outrageous cuckold thinks it all his due.</l>
					<l n="81">But add not to his joy by your consent,</l>
					<l n="82">And let it not be given, but only lent;</l>
					<l n="83">Return no kiss, nor move in any sort,</l>
					<l n="84">Make it a dull and a malignant sport.</l>
					<l n="85">Had I my wish he should no pleasure take,</l>
					<l n="86">But slubber o'er your bus'ness for my sake;</l>
					<l n="87">And whate'er fortune shall this night befall,</l>
					<l n="88">Coax me to morrow by forswearing all. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="5">
					<head>Elegy V: By Duke</head>
					<l n="1">'Twas noon when I, scorch'd with the double fire</l>
					<l n="2">Of the hot sun and my more hot desire,</l>
					<l n="3">Stretch'd on my downy couch at ease was laid,</l>
					<l n="4">Big with expectance of the lovely maid.</l>
					<l n="5">The curtains but half drawn, a light let in</l>
					<l n="6">Such as in shades of thickest groves is seen,</l>
					<l n="7">Such as remains when the sun flies away,</l>
					<l n="8">Or when night's gone, and yet it is not day.</l>
					<l n="9">This light to modest maids must be allow'd,</l>
					<l n="10">Where shame may hope its guilty head to shroud.</l>
					<l n="11">And now my love <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> did
						appear,</l>
					<l n="12">Loose on her neck fell her divided hair;</l>
					<l n="13">Loose as her flowing gown, that wanton'd in the air.</l>
					<l n="14">In such a garb, with such a grace and mien,</l>
					<l n="15">To her rich bed came the Assyrian queen;</l>
					<l n="16">So Lais looked when all the youth of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName></l>
					<l n="17">With adoration did her charms confess.</l>
					<l n="18">Her envious gown to pull away I tried,</l>
					<l n="19">But she resisted still, and still denied;</l>
					<l n="20">But so resisted that she seem'd to be</l>
					<l n="21">Unwilling to obtain the victory;</l>
					<l n="22">So I at last an easy conquest had,</l>
					<l n="23">Whilst my fair combatant herself betray'd.</l>
					<l n="24">But when she naked stood before my eyes,</l>
					<l n="25">Gods, with what charms did she my soul surprise!</l>
					<l n="26">What snowy arms did I both see and feel!</l>
					<l n="27">With what rich globes did her soft bosom swell!</l>
					<l n="28">Plump as ripe clusters rose each glowing breast,</l>
					<l n="29">Courting the hand, and suing to be press'd!</l>
					<l n="30">What a smooth plain was on her belly spread,</l>
					<l n="31">Where thousand little loves and graces play'd!</l>
					<l n="32">What thighs! what legs ! but why strive I in vain,</l>
					<l n="33">Each limb, each grace, each feature to explain</l>
					<l n="34">One beauty did through her whole body shine;</l>
					<l n="35">I saw, admir'd, and press'd it close to mine</l>
					<l n="36">The rest who knows not? Thus entranc'd we lay,</l>
					<l n="37">Till in each other's arms we died away;</l>
					<l n="38">0 give me such a noon, ye gods, to ev'ry day! </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="6">
					<head>Elegy VI: To His Mistress's Porter, to open the gate to him. By an unknown
						hand.</head>
					<l n="1">Slave, if thou worthy of thy chains wouldst be,</l>
					<l n="2">A grateful office do to love and me.</l>
					<l n="3">Unbar the wicket, and a friend admit;</l>
					<l n="4">The trouble is not much, nor favour great.</l>
					<l n="5">I ask thee not to spread the foldings wide;</l>
					<l n="6">Keep it at jar,-I'll softly by thee slide.</l>
					<l n="7">I to love's labours have so long been us'd,</l>
					<l n="8">My shapes are to a lath's lank size reduc'd.</l>
					<l n="9">The smallest crevice will my bus'ness do,</l>
					<l n="10">It cannot be so straight but I'll slip through.</l>
					<l n="11">Love guides me when by night I walk the street,</l>
					<l n="12">And when I grope my way directs my feet.</l>
					<l n="13">By night I was a youth afraid to walk,</l>
					<l n="14">Frighted by children and old nurses' talk;</l>
					<l n="15">I wonder'd men could wander in the gloom,</l>
					<l n="16">And kept, for fear of spirits, close at home.</l>
					<l n="17">Love and his mother, when they knew my care,</l>
					<l n="18">Cried, "Fool, thou shalt not long these phantoms fear."</l>
					<l n="19">Nor fear'd I long, for love my heart possess'd;</l>
					<l n="20">Those visions vanish'd, and my terrors ceas'd:</l>
					<l n="21">Nor ghosts nor scourers did I dread, but stroll'd</l>
					<l n="22">The streets a-nights, and grew in peril bold.</l>
					<l n="23">Thee only do I fear, and trembling stand</l>
					<l n="24">To wait the motions of thy tardy hand:</l>
					<l n="25">With soft request thy succour I implore,</l>
					<l n="26">Nor sue to Jove nor dread the Thund'rer more.</l>
					<l n="27">See how the gate is moistened with my tears!</l>
					<l n="28">What marks of my impatient love it bears!</l>
					<l n="29">Remember, when thou for the lash wert stripp'd</l>
					<l n="30">Who sav'd thee, at whose suit thou wert not whipp'd.</l>
					<l n="31">Did not I sooth thy angry lady's mind,</l>
					<l n="32">And make thy peace? Be thou to me as kind.</l>
					<l n="33">Think what soft things to move her soul I said,</l>
					<l n="34">And let them in a lover's favour plead.</l>
					<l n="35">But ah! the tender things that made her kind,</l>
					<l n="36">Work no such wonders on thy cruel mind.</l>
					<l n="37">Wouldst thou my friendly offices repay,</l>
					<l n="38">Fate throws a fair occasion in thy way;</l>
					<l n="39">Unlock the gate, the morning will not stay.</l>
					<l n="40">Unlock the gate; and as thou'rt kind to me,</l>
					<l n="41">So may thy gentle lady prove to thee;</l>
					<l n="42">May she to loose thy hateful chains incline,</l>
					<l n="43">And stead of water, be thy portion wine.</l>
					<l n="44">But what avail my soothing words? Thy ear</l>
					<l n="45">Is deaf, inhuman! to my moving pray'r.</l>
					<l n="46">Your gates with posts of pond'rous oak are barr'd,</l>
					<l n="47">As if your house was for a siege prepar'd;</l>
					<l n="48">Why all this fence? what foe have you to fear?</l>
					<l n="49">And why in peace do you provide for war?</l>
					<l n="50">Thus rudely if your lady's friends you treat,</l>
					<l n="51">What usage must her foes expect to meet?</l>
					<l n="52">Unlock the gate,-the morning will not stay;</l>
					<l n="53">Unlock the gate, and give my love its way.</l>
					<l n="54">Or is it sloth or is it sleep that brings,</l>
					<l n="55">This let to love, and pinions down his wings!</l>
					<l n="56">Why else do I in vain repeat my prayer,</l>
					<l n="57">Is it, thou dost not, or thou wilt not hear?</l>
					<l n="58">When first I waited at thy gate, and thought</l>
					<l n="59">To 'scape thy care, I was at midnight caught.</l>
					<l n="60">With over-dilligence thou then look'st out,</l>
					<l n="61">To spy what lover was upon the scout.</l>
					<l n="62">These are wild guesses, thou'rt perhaps employ'd</l>
					<l n="63">More sweetly, and enjoy'st what I enjoy'd.</l>
					<l n="64">And while I'm waiting with impatience here,</l>
					<l n="65">Thy envied fortune's with the faithless fair.</l>
					<l n="66">Oh, for thy pleasure, give me all thy pains,</l>
					<l n="67">Let us change chances, and be mine thy chains.</l>
					<l n="68">Unlock the gate, the morning will not stay,</l>
					<l n="69">Unlock the gate, and kindness past repay.</l>
					<l n="70">Hark: or I dream, or on the hinge I hear</l>
					<l n="71">The wicket turn, or bolts unloosen'd jar.</l>
					<l n="72">I dream, indeed, the bolts as they were laid,</l>
					<l n="73">Stand fix'd: the noise was by my fancy made.</l>
					<l n="74">But all, alas! is hush'd, I hear no sound,</l>
					<l n="75">All in the silence of the night is drown'd.</l>
					<l n="76">Here, hopeless of admittance, I attend,</l>
					<l n="77">While on my head the pearly dews descend.</l>
					<l n="78">Unlock the gate, the morning will not stay,</l>
					<l n="79">Unlock the gate, I will no longer pray,</l>
					<l n="80">But force by sword and fire my readier way.</l>
					<l n="81">What need of fire or sword? myself alone,</l>
					<l n="82">More pow'rful, than or sword or fire am grown.</l>
					<l n="83">Around your heads shall flaming torches fly,</l>
					<l n="84">And Jove the house shall burn, as well as I.</l>
					<l n="85">Night, love, and wine encourage and inflame:</l>
					<l n="86">These triumph over fear, and that o'er shame.</l>
					<l n="87">All ways I've tried, but all successless prove,</l>
					<l n="88">Nor threats can fright thee, nor entreaties move;</l>
					<l n="89">Deaf to my pray'rs as to my tears thou'rt blind,</l>
					<l n="90">Thy gate is less obdurate than thy mind.</l>
					<l n="91">But see, the ruddy morn begins to rise,</l>
					<l n="92">And paints with rosy streaks the eastern skies,</l>
					<l n="93">While crowing cocks the lab'rer's sloth revile,</l>
					<l n="94">And summon wretches to their daily toil.</l>
					<l n="95">Throw then, fond man, thy fragrant chaplet by,</l>
					<l n="96">And let it at thy lady's threshold lie.</l>
					<l n="97">When in the morn thy faded flow'rs she spies,</l>
					<l n="98">Kind thoughts of me may in her bosom rise,</l>
					<l n="99">Perhaps she may resent her porter's crime,</l>
					<l n="100">And grieve that here so ill I spent my time.</l>
					<l n="101">Against me though thou shut'st thy lady's gate,</l>
					<l n="102">I cannot one, that serves my mistress, hate.</l>
					<l n="103">You both who did against my hopes rebel,</l>
					<l n="104">Ah, porter; and ah, cruel gate, farewell. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="7">
					<head>Elegy VII: To His Mistress, whom he had beaten. By Henry Cromwell.</head>
					<l n="1">Come, if ye're friends, and let these hands be bound,</l>
					<l n="2">Which could with impious rage a mistress wound:</l>
					<l n="3">What more did Ajax in his fury do,</l>
					<l n="4">When all the sacred grazing herd he slew?</l>
					<l n="5">Or he<note anchored="true" place="foot" resp="ed">Orestes</note> who spared
						not her who gave him breath?</l>
					<l n="6">So ill the son reveng'd his father's death!</l>
					<l n="7">Then I had broke the most religious ties,</l>
					<l n="8">Both to my parents and the deities:</l>
					<l n="9">I tore (0 heav'ns!) her finely braided hair,</l>
					<l n="10">How charming then look'd the disorder'd fair.</l>
					<l n="11">So Atalanta in her chaise is drawn,</l>
					<l n="12">Where the <placeName key="tgn,2136419">Arcadian</placeName> beasts her empire
						own:</l>
					<l n="13">So Ariadne, left upon the shore,</l>
					<l n="14">Does all alone her lost estate deplore.</l>
					<l n="15">Who would not then have rail'd and talk'd aloud</l>
					<l n="16">(Which to the helpless sex might be allowed.)</l>
					<l n="17">She only did upbraid me with her eye,</l>
					<l n="18">Whose speaking tears did want of words supply.</l>
					<l n="19">0, that some merciful superior pow'r</l>
					<l n="20">Had struck me lame before that fatal hour,</l>
					<l n="21">And not have suffer'd me to pierce my heart</l>
					<l n="22">So deeply, in the best and tend'rest part;</l>
					<l n="23">To make a lady that subjection own,</l>
					<l n="24">Which is not to the meanest Roman known.</l>
					<l n="25">'Twas Diomede, who first a goddess struck,</l>
					<l n="26">I from his hand that curs'd example took;</l>
					<l n="27">But he was far less criminal than I,</l>
					<l n="28">I was a lover, he an enemy.</l>
					<l n="29">March like a conqueror in triumph now,</l>
					<l n="30">With laurel wreaths encompassing your brow,</l>
					<l n="31">And render to the mighty gods your vow:</l>
					<l n="32">So, as you pass, th' attending gazing crowd,</l>
					<l n="33">By their applause shall speak your courage loud:</l>
					<l n="34">Let your sad captive in the front appear,</l>
					<l n="35">With streaming cheeks, and with dishevell'd hair.</l>
					<l n="36">Such lips were form'd for kinder words than these,</l>
					<l n="37">Wounds made by lovers' furious ecstasies.</l>
					<l n="38">Though like a torrent I was hurried on,</l>
					<l n="39">A slave to passion which I could not shun,</l>
					<l n="40">I might have only pierc'd her tender ear</l>
					<l n="41">With threatening language, such as virgins fear.</l>
					<l n="42">Fear having chill'd the current of her blood,</l>
					<l n="43">She pale as Parian marble statue stood;</l>
					<l n="44">Tears, which suspense did for a while restrain,</l>
					<l n="45">Gush'd forth, and down her cheeks the deluge ran.</l>
					<l n="46">As when the sun does by a powerful beam</l>
					<l n="47">Dissolve the frost, it runs into a stream.</l>
					<l n="48">The lamentable objects struck me dead,</l>
					<l n="49">And tears of blood to quench those tears I shed;</l>
					<l n="50">Thrice at her feet the prostrate suppliant fell,</l>
					<l n="51">And thrice did she repulse the criminal.</l>
					<l n="52">What would I not your anger to abate,</l>
					<l n="53">Redeem your favour, or remove your hate?</l>
					<l n="54">To your revenge no means or method spare;</l>
					<l n="55">Revenge, alas! is easy to the fair. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="8">
					<head>Elegy VIII: He Curses a Bawd, for going about to debauch his mistress. By
						Sir Charles Sedley.</head>
					<l n="1">There is a bawd renown'd in <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName>'
						wars,</l>
					<l n="2">Aud dreadful still with honorable scars;</l>
					<l n="3">Her youth and beauty, craft and guile supply,</l>
					<l n="4">Sworn foe to all degrees of chastity.</l>
					<l n="5">Dypsas, who first taught love-sick maids the way</l>
					<l n="6">To cheat the bridegroom on the wedding-day,</l>
					<l n="7">And then a hundred subtle tricks devis'd,</l>
					<l n="8">Wherewith the am'rous theft might be disguis'd;</l>
					<l n="9">Of herbs and spells she tries the guilty force,</l>
					<l n="10">The poison of a mare that goes to horse.</l>
					<l n="11">Cleaving the midnight air upon a switch,</l>
					<l n="12">Some for a bawd, most take her for a witch.</l>
					<l n="13">Each morning sees her reeling to her bed,</l>
					<l n="14">Her native blue o'ercome with drunken red:</l>
					<l n="15">Her ready tongue ne'er wants a useful lie,</l>
					<l n="16">Soft moving words, nor charming flattery.</l>
					<l n="17">Thus I o'erheard her to my <placeName key="tgn,2075531">Lucia</placeName>
						speak:</l>
					<l n="18">"Young <placeName key="tgn,2274809">Damon</placeName>'s heart wilt thou for
						ever break</l>
					<l n="19">He long has lov'd thee, and by me he sends</l>
					<l n="20">To learn thy motions, which he still attends;</l>
					<l n="21">If to the park thou go'st, the plays are ill;</l>
					<l n="22">If to the plays, he thinks the air would kill.</l>
					<l n="23">The other day he gaz'd upon thy face,</l>
					<l n="24">As he would grow a statue in the place;</l>
					<l n="25">And who indeed does not? like a new star,</l>
					<l n="26">Beauty like thine strikes wonder from afar.</l>
					<l n="27">Alas! methinks thou art ill-dress'd to-night;</l>
					<l n="28">This point's too poor; thy necklace is not right;</l>
					<l n="29">This gown was by some botching tailor made,</l>
					<l n="30">It spoils thy shape; this fucus is ill laid.</l>
					<l n="31">Hear me, and be as happy as thou'rt fair:</l>
					<l n="32">Damon is rich, and what thou wanst, can spare.</l>
					<l n="33">Like thine his face, like thine his eyes are thought.</l>
					<l n="34">Would he not buy, he might himself be bought."</l>
					<l n="35">Fair <placeName key="tgn,2075531">Lucia</placeName> blush'd. "It is a sign of
						grace,</l>
					<l n="36">(Dypsas replied,) that red becomes thy face.</l>
					<l n="37">All lovers now by what they give are weighed,</l>
					<l n="38">And she is best belov'd that best is paid;</l>
					<l n="39">The sun-burnt Latins, in old Tatius' reign,</l>
					<l n="40">Did to one man perhaps their love restrain:</l>
					<l n="41"><placeName key="tgn,2096104">Venus</placeName> in her Aeneas' city rules,</l>
					<l n="42">And all adore her deity but fools.</l>
					<l n="43">Go on, ye fair, chaste only let such live</l>
					<l n="44">As none will ask, and know not how to give.</l>
					<l n="45">Life steals away, and our best hours are gone</l>
					<l n="46">Ere the true use or worth of them be known.</l>
					<l n="47">Things long neglected, of themselves decay;</l>
					<l n="48">What we forbear, time rudely makes his prey.</l>
					<l n="49">Beauty is best preserv'd by exercise,</l>
					<l n="50">Nor for that task can one or few suffice.</l>
					<l n="51">Wouldst thou grow rich, thou must from many take:</l>
					<l n="52">From one 'twere hard continually to rake.</l>
					<l n="53">Without new gowns and coaches, who can live ?</l>
					<l n="54">What does thy poet but new verses give?</l>
					<l n="55">A poet, the last thing that earth does breed,</l>
					<l n="56">Whose wit, for sixpence, any one may read.</l>
					<l n="57">Hang the poor lover, and his pedigree;</l>
					<l n="58">The thriving merchant, or fat judge, give me.</l>
					<l n="59">Love truly none, but seem in love with all,</l>
					<l n="60">And at old friends to thy new lovers rail.</l>
					<l n="61">Sometimes deny, 'twill appetite procure;</l>
					<l n="62">The sharp-set hawks will stoop to any lure.</l>
					<l n="63">Then grant again, lest he a habit get</l>
					<l n="64">Of living from thee; but be sure thou let</l>
					<l n="65">No empty lover in; murmur sometimes,</l>
					<l n="66">And at first hurt, reproach him with thy crimes.</l>
					<l n="67">Seem jealous, when thou'st been thyself to blame;</l>
					<l n="68">'Twill stop his mouth, if thou the first complain.</l>
					<l n="69">All thou hast done be ready to forswear:</l>
					<l n="70">For lovers' oaths fair <placeName key="tgn,2096104">Venus</placeName> has no
						ear.</l>
					<l n="71">Whilst lie is with thee, let some woman bring</l>
					<l n="72">Some Indian stuff or foreign precious thing;</l>
					<l n="73">Which thou must say thou want'st, and he must buy,</l>
					<l n="74">Though for it six months hence in gaol he lie.</l>
					<l n="75">Thy mother, sister, brother, and thy nurse,</l>
					<l n="76">Must have a pull each at thy lover's purse.</l>
					<l n="77">Let him from rivals never be secure,</l>
					<l n="78">That hope once gone, love will not long endure;</l>
					<l n="79">Show him the presents by those rivals sent,</l>
					<l n="80">So shall his bounty thy request prevent.</l>
					<l n="81">When he will give no more, ask him to lend:</l>
					<l n="82">If he wants money, find a trusting friend.</l>
					<l n="83">Get hangings, cabinets, and looking-glass,</l>
					<l n="84">Or any thing for which his word will pass.</l>
					<l n="85">Practise these rules, thou'lt find the benefit!</l>
					<l n="86">I lost my beauty ere I got this wit."</l>
					<l n="87">I at that word step'd from behind the door,</l>
					<l n="88">And scarce my nails from her thin cheeks forbore.</l>
					<l n="89">Her few gray hairs in rage I vow'd to pull,</l>
					<l n="90">And thrust her drunken eyes into her skull.</l>
					<l n="91">"Poor in a dungeon's bottom may'st thou rot,</l>
					<l n="92">Die with a blow with thy beloved pot;</l>
					<l n="93">No brandy, and eternal thirst, thy lot." </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="9">
					<head>Elegy IX: Of Love and War. By Henry Cromwell.</head>
					<l n="1">Trust me, my Atticus, in love are wars;</l>
					<l n="2">And Cupid has his camp, as well as <placeName key="tgn,2090583">Mars</placeName>:</l>
					<l n="3">The age that's fit for war best suits with love,</l>
					<l n="4">The old in both unserviceable prove,</l>
					<l n="5">Infirm in war, and impotent in love.</l>
					<l n="6">The soldiers which a general does require,</l>
					<l n="7">Are such as ladies would in bed desire:</l>
					<l n="8">Who but a soldier, and a lover, can</l>
					<l n="9">Bear the night's cold, in show'rs of hail and rain?</l>
					<l n="10">One in continual watch his station keeps,</l>
					<l n="11">Or on the earth in broken slumbers sleeps;</l>
					<l n="12">The other takes his still repeated round</l>
					<l n="13">By mistress' house — then lodges on the ground.</l>
					<l n="14">Soldiers, and lovers, with a careful eye,</l>
					<l n="15">Observe the motions of the enemy:</l>
					<l n="16">One to the walls makes his approach in form,</l>
					<l n="17">Pushes the siege, and takes the town by storm:</l>
					<l n="18">The other lays his close to Celia's fort,</l>
					<l n="19">Presses his point, and gains the wish'd-for port.</l>
					<l n="20">As soldiers, when the foe securely lies</l>
					<l n="21">In sleep, and wine dissolv'd, the camp surprise;</l>
					<l n="22">So when the jealous to their rest remove,</l>
					<l n="23">And all is hush'd, — the other steals to love.</l>
					<l n="24">You then, who think that love's an idle fit,</l>
					<l n="25">Know, that it is the exercise of wit.</l>
					<l n="26">In flames of love the fierce Achilles burns,</l>
					<l n="27">And, quitting arms, absent Briseis mourns:</l>
					<l n="28">From the embraces of Andromache</l>
					<l n="29">Went Hector arm'd for war, and victory.</l>
					<l n="30">As Agamemnon saw Cassandra pass</l>
					<l n="31">With hair dishevell'd, and disorder'd dress,</l>
					<l n="32">H' admir'd the beauties of the prophetess:</l>
					<l n="33">The god of war was caught in th' act of love;</l>
					<l n="34">A story know to all the court above.</l>
					<l n="35">Once did I pass my hours in sloth and ease,</l>
					<l n="36">Cool shades and beds of down could only please;</l>
					<l n="37">When a commanding beauty rais'd my mind,</l>
					<l n="38">I left all little trifling thoughts behind,</l>
					<l n="39">And to her service all my heart resign'd:</l>
					<l n="40">Since, like an active soldier, have I spent</l>
					<l n="41">My time in toils of war, in beauty's tent:</l>
					<l n="42">And for so sweet a pay all dangers underwent.</l>
					<l n="43">You see, my Atticus, by what I prove,</l>
					<l n="44">Who would not live in idleness-must love. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="10">
					<p>Poem 10, in which the poet complains that his mistress has asked him for
						money, is not here translated. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="11">
					<head>Elegy XI: To Nape, praying her to deliver his letter to her mistress. By
						Henry Cromwell.</head>
					<l n="1">Nape, who know'st so well to set the hair,</l>
					<l n="2">And all the fashions of the modish fair,</l>
					<l n="3">Like thee no lady's woman in the town</l>
					<l n="4">Can forward an intrigue, or pin a gown;</l>
					<l n="5">No maid than thee can boast a quicker eye,</l>
					<l n="6">Nor sooner the sour husband's coming spy.</l>
					<l n="7">Here, Nape, take this billet-doux, and bear</l>
					<l n="8">My soul's soft wishes to the absent fair.</l>
					<l n="9">If I can guess, thy heart is not of flint,</l>
					<l n="10">Nor is there the least vein of iron in't;</l>
					<l n="11">I something in thy looks and manners see</l>
					<l n="12">Above the rudeness of thy low degree;</l>
					<l n="13">A softer turn, to pity more inclined,</l>
					<l n="14">Than vulgar souls, a more complacent mind;</l>
					<l n="15">Thou feel'st, if I can guess, an equal flame,</l>
					<l n="16">And thine and my distemper is the same.</l>
					<l n="17">If how I do, she asks, do thou reply,</l>
					<l n="18">For the dear night, and night's dear joys, I die.</l>
					<l n="19">Tell her the letter will the rest explain,</l>
					<l n="20">And does my soul, and all its hopes contain.</l>
					<l n="21">But time, while I am speaking, flies: be sure</l>
					<l n="22">To give the billet in a leisure hour:</l>
					<l n="23">Don't be content with her imperfect view,</l>
					<l n="24">But make her, when she has it, read it through.</l>
					<l n="25">I charge thee, as she reads, observe her eyes,</l>
					<l n="26">Catch, if thou canst, her gentle looks and sighs;</l>
					<l n="27">As these are sure presages of my joy,</l>
					<l n="28">So frowns and low'rs my flattering hopes destroy.</l>
					<l n="29">Pray her, when she has read it, to indite</l>
					<l n="30">An answer, and a long epistle write.</l>
					<l n="31">I hate a billet, where at once I view</l>
					<l n="32">A page all empty, but a line or two.</l>
					<l n="33">Let her without a margin fill it up,</l>
					<l n="34">And crowd it from the bottom to the top.</l>
					<l n="35">But why should I her pretty fingers tire?</l>
					<l n="36">A word's enough, and all that I desire.</l>
					<l n="37">Ah, Nape, let her only bid me come;</l>
					<l n="38">The page is large, which for that word has room.</l>
					<l n="39">Her letter, like a conqu'ror's, shall be bound</l>
					<l n="40">With bays, for it with conquests shall be crown'd. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="12">
					<head>Elegy XII: He curses his letter because it was not answered.</head>
					<l n="1">Ah, pity me, my friends! the cruel fair</l>
					<l n="2">Will neither read my just complaint, nor hear.</l>
					<l n="3">The billet-doux I sent her she return'd,</l>
					<l n="4">And e'en to ope the tender letter scorn'd</l>
					<l n="5">Ill was the omen, for the slave I sent</l>
					<l n="6">Trip'd at the sill as out of doors he went.</l>
					<l n="7">If e'er you on an errand go for me,</l>
					<l n="8">More careful, sirrah! how you stumble, be;</l>
					<l n="9">Step soberly, and warily along;</l>
					<l n="10">The end's ne'er right if the beginning's wrong.</l>
					<l n="11">Sinee thus in vain her pity I implore,</l>
					<l n="12">I'll ne'er to tablets trust my passion more;</l>
					<l n="13">Nor with my wax for death my warrant seal;</l>
					<l n="14">Worse than her scorn, what torture can I feel?</l>
					<l n="15">From combs of Cosica the wax was ta'en,</l>
					<l n="16">The latent poison was the lover's bane.</l>
					<l n="17">Bees there from venom'd flow'rs their honey suck,</l>
					<l n="18">And surely to my wax that venom stuck.</l>
					<l n="19">Chance on the seal did my misfortune paint,</l>
					<l n="20">And show'd my doom by the vermilion teint.</l>
					<l n="21">Curse on the instruments of my disgrace !</l>
					<l n="22">May you lie rotting in some filthy place;</l>
					<l n="23">By carts run o'er may you to bits be torn,</l>
					<l n="24">And your mishap revenge <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>'s
						scorn !</l>
					<l n="25">The man that first to smooth your surface toil'd,</l>
					<l n="26">The wooden work with hands impure defil'd;</l>
					<l n="27">Gibbets and racks should of the wood be made,</l>
					<l n="28">And the rough tools of all the murd'ring trade.</l>
					<l n="29">Bats roosted in its branches as it grew,</l>
					<l n="30">And birds of prey for shelter thither flew:</l>
					<l n="31">The vulture, and all kind of rav'nous fowl,</l>
					<l n="32">There hatch their young, and there the om'nous owl.</l>
					<l n="33">How mad to use such tablets must I be?</l>
					<l n="34">Curst and ill fated, as their parent tree!</l>
					<l n="35">Were these fit things soft sentiments to bear,</l>
					<l n="36">And to a lady tell a lover's care?</l>
					<l n="37">Lawyers, on you, might horrid jargon write,</l>
					<l n="38">With sound the ear, with sense the soul to flight.</l>
					<l n="39">Well might your plain the wicked writings bear</l>
					<l n="40">Where the rich miser robs the ruin'd heir.</l>
					<l n="41">When I first purchas'd you, I feared no less,</l>
					<l n="42">Your numbers even made me doubt success:</l>
					<l n="43">May you by worms be in old age devour'd,</l>
					<l n="44">And by all mortals as by me abhor'd. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="13">
					<head>Elegy XIII: To the Morning, not to make haste. By an unknown hand.</head>
					<l n="1">Aurora, rising from old Tithon's bed,</l>
					<l n="2">Does o'er the eastern skies her roses spread:</l>
					<l n="3">Stay, beauteous morn, awhile thy chariot stay,</l>
					<l n="4">Awhile with lagging wheels retard the day.</l>
					<l n="5">So may young birds, as often as the spring</l>
					<l n="6">Renews the year, o'er Memnon's ashes sing.</l>
					<l n="7">Now I lie folded in <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>'s
						arms,</l>
					<l n="8">And all her soul is mine, and all her charms;</l>
					<l n="9">I now am to her panting bosom press'd,</l>
					<l n="10">And now, if ever lover was, am bless'd.</l>
					<l n="11">As yet sweet sleep sits heavy on our eyes,</l>
					<l n="12">And warbling birds forbid, as yet to rise.</l>
					<l n="13">Stay, beauteous morning, for to love-sick maids</l>
					<l n="14">And youths, how grateful are these dusky shades!</l>
					<l n="15">All stay, and do not, from the blushing east,</l>
					<l n="16">With dawning glories break our balmy rest.</l>
					<l n="17">When night's black mantle does those glories hide,</l>
					<l n="18">The pilot by the stars his ship can guide,</l>
					<l n="19">And in mid-sea a certain course pursue,</l>
					<l n="20">As safe as when he has the sun in view.</l>
					<l n="21">What pleasure in thy light should mortals take?</l>
					<l n="22">Thou dost the weary traveller awake;</l>
					<l n="23">Though to the down his heavy head reclines,</l>
					<l n="24">Up he must lift it for the morning shines.</l>
					<l n="25">The soldier braces on his brazen shield,</l>
					<l n="26">Quits his warm tent, and fits him for the field:</l>
					<l n="27">The lab'ring hind his harrow takes, and now</l>
					<l n="28">The peasant yokes his oxen to the plough:</l>
					<l n="29">The boy half wak'd, and rubbing still his eyes,</l>
					<l n="30">Is loth alike to go to school, or rise;</l>
					<l n="31">While o'er his task he does imperfect nod,</l>
					<l n="32">He fears the ferula, he dreads the rod.</l>
					<l n="33">The bridegroom, starting from his bride's embrace,</l>
					<l n="34">Runs to his lawyer to consult his case;</l>
					<l n="35">A word is wanting in the dower deed,</l>
					<l n="36">And what to save the portion must he plead?</l>
					<l n="37">Now hungry serjeants quit their tempting ease,</l>
					<l n="38">To haunt the crowded courts and pick up fees.</l>
					<l n="39">Thy rise brings labour to the female band,</l>
					<l n="40">And puts the spindle in the spinster's hand:</l>
					<l n="41">Light are these toils, and little is the pain</l>
					<l n="42">To rise to work, and rest at night again;</l>
					<l n="43">But who that e'er knew love's transporting joys,</l>
					<l n="44">Could from the arms of youth and beauty rise?</l>
					<l n="45">Oft have I wish'd that night would keep her ground,</l>
					<l n="46">And all her stars be at thy rising found;</l>
					<l n="47">Oft have I wish'd the winds would stop thy way,</l>
					<l n="48">Repel thy car, or clouds involve the day.</l>
					<l n="49">Dost thou in envy lash each lazy steed,</l>
					<l n="50">And whirl thy chariot with unwonted speed?</l>
					<l n="51">Black was thy son, and in his hue's express'd</l>
					<l n="52">The gloomy passions of his parent's breats;</l>
					<l n="53">He, born of Cephalus, his ravish'd sire,</l>
					<l n="54">Is a known proof of thy adult'rous fire.</l>
					<l n="55">Thou, by his colour, wouldst thy crime conceal;</l>
					<l n="56">Ah, that to Tithon I the tale could tell!</l>
					<l n="57">Search all the records of Heaven's lechers round,</l>
					<l n="58">A fouler story cannot there be found.</l>
					<l n="59">In Cephalus' embraces when you lay,</l>
					<l n="60">And oft by theft renew'd your wanton play;</l>
					<l n="61">When Tithon's impotence you made your sport,</l>
					<l n="62">Did you not think the joyous moments short?</l>
					<l n="63">Lock'd in his arms did you in transports lie,</l>
					<l n="64">Ah! would you not, like me, to Phoebus cry,</l>
					<l n="65">"Stop, stop thy rapid course? Am I to blame</l>
					<l n="66">That Tithon's old, and cannot feel thy flame?</l>
					<l n="67">See how the moon does her Endymion keep</l>
					<l n="68">In night conceal'd, and drown'd in dewy sleep.</l>
					<l n="69">As lovely is the moon, as fair as thou,</l>
					<l n="70">Who freely, where she loves, her favours does bestow.</l>
					<l n="71">Jove, when he rob'd Amphitryon of his joy,</l>
					<l n="72">Did two whole nights in am'rous thefts employ;</l>
					<l n="73">Unknown when in Alcmena's arms he lay,</l>
					<l n="74">The night he doubles and suspends the day."</l>
					<l n="75">The morning heard my railing, and for shame</l>
					<l n="76">Blush'd that by force she must disturb my flame;</l>
					<l n="77">Bright Phoebus rushing forth, the glorious day</l>
					<l n="78">Drove the dear shades, that hid our joys, away. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="14">
					<head>Elegy XIV: He comforts his mistress for the loss of her hair by the means
						she took to beautify it. By an unknown hand.</head>
					<l n="1">I us'd to warn you, not with so much care,</l>
					<l n="2">And waste of ointment, to adorn your hair:</l>
					<l n="3">That warning now is useless, you have none,</l>
					<l n="4">And with your hair that trouble too is gone.</l>
					<l n="5">Where are the silken tresses, which adown</l>
					<l n="6">Your shoulders hung? A web was never spun</l>
					<l n="7">So fine, but, ah! those flowing curls are gone.</l>
					<l n="8">Ah fatal art! ah fatal care, and pains!</l>
					<l n="9">That robb'd me of the dearest of my chains.</l>
					<l n="10">Nor of a black, nor of a golden hue</l>
					<l n="11">They were, but of a dye between the two.</l>
					<l n="12">How could you hurt, or poison with perfume,</l>
					<l n="13">Those curls that were so easy to the comb?</l>
					<l n="14">That to no pains expos'd you, when you set</l>
					<l n="15">Their shining tresses for young hearts a net?</l>
					<l n="16">That ne'er provok'd you with your maids to war,</l>
					<l n="17">For hurting you with your entangled hair?</l>
					<l n="18">You ne'er were urg'd to some indecent fray,</l>
					<l n="19">Nor in a fury snatch'd the comb away.</l>
					<l n="20">The teeth ne'er touch'd you, and her constant care,</l>
					<l n="21">Without ill arts, would have preserv'd your hair.</l>
					<l n="22">Behind your chair I oft have seen her stand,</l>
					<l n="23">And comb and curl it with a gentle hand:</l>
					<l n="24">Oft have I seen it on your shoulders play</l>
					<l n="25">Uncomb'd, as on your purple bed you lay.</l>
					<l n="26">Your artless tresses with more charms appear,</l>
					<l n="27">Than when adorn'd with all your cost and care.</l>
					<l n="28">When on the grass the Thracian nymphs recline,</l>
					<l n="29">Of <placeName key="tgn,2097807">Bacchus</placeName> full, and weary of their
						wine,</l>
					<l n="30">Less lovely are their locks, than yours, less fair</l>
					<l n="31">The ringlets of their soft dishevell'd hair:</l>
					<l n="32">Softer was thine, like fleecy down it felt,</l>
					<l n="33">And to the finger did as freely yield,</l>
					<l n="34">How didst thou torture it, the curls to turn,</l>
					<l n="35">Now with hot irons at thy toilet burn?</l>
					<l n="36">This rack, with what obedience did it bear?</l>
					<l n="37">"Ah spare," I cried, "thy patient tresses spare!</l>
					<l n="38">To hurt them is a sin: this needless toil</l>
					<l n="39">Forbear, and do not, what adorns thee, spoil.</l>
					<l n="40">'Tis now too late to give your labour o'er,</l>
					<l n="41">Those tortur'd ringlets are, alas ! no more.</l>
					<l n="42">Ah, cease the cruel thought, and cease to pass</l>
					<l n="43">Such irksome minutes at your faithful glass !</l>
					<l n="44">In vain thou seek'st thy silken locks to find;</l>
					<l n="45">Banish the dear remembrance from thy mind.</l>
					<l n="46">No weeds destroy'd them with their pois'nous juice,</l>
					<l n="47">Nor canst thou witches' magic charms accuse,</l>
					<l n="48">Nor rival's rage, nor dire enchantment blame,</l>
					<l n="49">Nor envy's blasting tongue, nor fever's flame.</l>
					<l n="50">The mischief by thy own fair hands was wrought;</l>
					<l n="51">Nor dost thou suffer for another's fault.</l>
					<l n="52">How oft I bade thee, but in vain, beware</l>
					<l n="53">The venom'd essence, that destroy'd thy hair?</l>
					<l n="54">Now with new arts thou shalt thy pride amuse,</l>
					<l n="55">And curls, of German captives borrow'd, use.</l>
					<l n="56">Drusus to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> their vanquish'd
						nation sends</l>
					<l n="57">And the fair slave to thee her tresses lends.</l>
					<l n="58">With alien locks thou wilt thy head adorn,</l>
					<l n="59">And conquests gain'd by foreign beauties scorn.</l>
					<l n="60">How wilt thou blush, with other charms to please,</l>
					<l n="61">And cry, "How fairer were my locks than these !"</l>
					<l n="62">By heav'ns, to heart she takes her head's disgrace,</l>
					<l n="63">She weeps, and covers with her hands her face.</l>
					<l n="64">She weeps, as in her lap her locks she views;</l>
					<l n="65">What woman would not weep, such locks to lose!</l>
					<l n="66">Ah, that they still did on her shoulders flow,</l>
					<l n="67">Ah, that they now, where once they grew, did grow!</l>
					<l n="68">Take courage, fair <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>, never
						fear,</l>
					<l n="69">Thou shalt not long these borrow'd tresses wear:</l>
					<l n="70">Time for your beauty shall this loss repair</l>
					<l n="71">And you again shall charm with native hair. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="15">
					<p>Poem 15, in which the poet boasts his work will outlive him, is not here
						translated. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1">
					<p>Poem 1, in which the poet introduces his second book, is not here translated.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="2">
					<p>Poem 2, addressed to <placeName key="tgn,1121604">Bagoe</placeName>, is not
						here translated. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="3">
					<head>Elegy III: To a Eunuch, who had the keeping of his mistress</head>
					<l n="1">How hard's my hap, to have my fair consign'd</l>
					<l n="2">To one, who is imperfect in his kind;</l>
					<l n="3">To one, who ne'er can have the pow'r to prove</l>
					<l n="4">As woman, or as man, the mutual joys of love!</l>
					<l n="5">Who practis'd first on boys the cutting steel,</l>
					<l n="6">Deserv'd himself the fatal wound to feel.</l>
					<l n="7">Couldst thou be capable of Cupid's fires,</l>
					<l n="8">Or the least sensible of love's desires,</l>
					<l n="9">Some pity thou wouldst have on me, and grant</l>
					<l n="10">Thy aid, for what thou canst not know I want.</l>
					<l n="11">Ill suits thee now, the warrior's lance to wield,</l>
					<l n="12">To mount the manag'd horse, or lift the brazen shield:</l>
					<l n="13">Arms are for men, and not for such as thee,</l>
					<l n="14">Who shouldst from ev'ry manly thought be free.</l>
					<l n="15">No banner shouldst thou, but thy lady's bear,</l>
					<l n="16">And have no other leader but the fair.</l>
					<l n="17">Much it behoves thee then to strive to gain</l>
					<l n="18">Her favour, and thou need'st not strive in vain.</l>
					<l n="19">Consult her pleasure, and her will obey,</l>
					<l n="20">To favour that's the sure, the ready way:</l>
					<l n="21">Without it, how unhappy wilt thou be!</l>
					<l n="22">Life is without it of no use to thee.</l>
					<l n="23">Thou'rt beautiful, and mayst thy prime enjoy,</l>
					<l n="24">And well thy beauty and thy youth employ.</l>
					<l n="25">Study to serve thy gentle mistress well,</l>
					<l n="26">And merit her good graces by thy zeal;</l>
					<l n="27">Watch as thou wilt, the trouble thou mayst spare,</l>
					<l n="28">She'll easily deceive thy utmost care.</l>
					<l n="29">When two fond lovers are agreed to meet,</l>
					<l n="30">Canst thou their well-concerted plot defeat?</l>
					<l n="31">The ways of kindness thou shouldst rather use;</l>
					<l n="32">By being civil thou wilt nothing lose;</l>
					<l n="33">And when an opportunity is fail,</l>
					<l n="34">For thy own sake be friendly to our pray'r.</l>
					<l n="35">A friend be to thy lady, not a guard,</l>
					<l n="36">And we, with bounteous hand, thy friendship will reward. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="4">
					<head>Elegy IV: That he loves all sorts of women.</head>
					<l n="1">Vice by my verse I never will defend,</l>
					<l n="2">Nor by false arms to fence my own pretend.</l>
					<l n="3">Frankly my failings I with shame confess;</l>
					<l n="4">To hide my errors would not make them less.</l>
					<l n="5">My faults, whate'er I suffer by't, I own,</l>
					<l n="6">That others, if they please, those faults may shun</l>
					<l n="7">I hate myself, my follies, and would fain</l>
					<l n="8">Be, were it in my pow'r, another man.</l>
					<l n="9">How difficult it is, ye righteous Gods,</l>
					<l n="10">Against our wills to bear such heavy loads.</l>
					<l n="11">I have not strength to guard myself from ill,</l>
					<l n="12">And, as I wish, to rule my wicked will.</l>
					<l n="13">I'm hurry'd on, as by the boistrous sea</l>
					<l n="14">The driving bark is swiftly borne away.</l>
					<l n="15">No certain form inflames my am'rous breast,</l>
					<l n="16">All beauty is alike to me the best;</l>
					<l n="17">A hundred causes kindle my desires,</l>
					<l n="18">And love ne'er wants a torch to light my fires.</l>
					<l n="19">When on the earth the modest virgin looks,</l>
					<l n="20">That very modesty of hers provokes;</l>
					<l n="21">And if I chance to meet a forward fair,</l>
					<l n="22">I'm taken with her frank and easy air:</l>
					<l n="23">I figure to myself a thousand charms,</l>
					<l n="24">A thousand raptures in her wanton arms.</l>
					<l n="25">If, like the damsels of the <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName>
						race,</l>
					<l n="26">She's rude, I look upon it as grimace;</l>
					<l n="27">That sullen as she seems at first, 'tis art,</l>
					<l n="28">That I the more may prize the conquest or her heart.</l>
					<l n="29">New joys, if she's a wit, I hope to find;</l>
					<l n="30">And with her body, to possess her mind:</l>
					<l n="31">If foolish, I in that can see no harm,</l>
					<l n="32">And in her very folly find a charm.</l>
					<l n="33">I know a maid so very fond, and dull,</l>
					<l n="34">To me she thinks Callimachus a fool.</l>
					<l n="35">I soon am pleas'd with one that's pleas'd with me,</l>
					<l n="36">Alike we in our taste and wish agree:</l>
					<l n="37">But if the fair my verses don't approve,</l>
					<l n="38">I bragging tell her, she will like my love;</l>
					<l n="39">If with her tongue, or with her heel she's brisk,</l>
					<l n="40">Her prattle pleases, and her gamesome frisk;</l>
					<l n="41">But if she's heavy, I suppose at night</l>
					<l n="42">She'll change, and prove, as I would have her, light,</l>
					<l n="43">The fair that sings, enchants me with her voice;</l>
					<l n="44">Oh, what a gust it gives a lover's joys!</l>
					<l n="45">When her shrill shakes afresh his bosom wound,</l>
					<l n="46">And from her lips he kisses off the sound;</l>
					<l n="47">When her soft fingers touch the silver strings,</l>
					<l n="48">And sweetly to the sounding lute she sings;</l>
					<l n="49">Who can resist such strong redoubled charms?</l>
					<l n="50">Her music melts me, as her beauty warms</l>
					<l n="51">If in the dance the nimble nymph I find,</l>
					<l n="52">And view how she her pliant limbs does wind,</l>
					<l n="53">How artfully she to the music moves,</l>
					<l n="54">I cry, "How happy is the man she loves!"</l>
					<l n="55">My humour, in a word, is plainly this,</l>
					<l n="56">All objects please, and nothing comes amiss.</l>
					<l n="57">To love, and be belov'd my sole employ:</l>
					<l n="58">Dispos'd to be enjoy'd, and to enjoy.</l>
					<l n="59">This lady for her length I like, her spread</l>
					<l n="60">Will swell my arms, and fill the joyous bed;</l>
					<l n="61">She's like the lusty heroines of old,</l>
					<l n="62">And with a strong embrace her lover will enfold.</l>
					<l n="63">This lass, because she's little, I approve;</l>
					<l n="64">The least are lightest in the sports of love.</l>
					<l n="65">With every size my passion does agree,</l>
					<l n="66">And tall and short are both alike to me.</l>
					<l n="67">I fancy, when undress'd I find the fair,</l>
					<l n="68">'Tis less her want of charms, than want of care.</l>
					<l n="69">If with her dishabille, I cry, " I'm pleas'd,"</l>
					<l n="70">How beauteous would she be if she were dress'd</l>
					<l n="71">And when she does her best apparel wear,</l>
					<l n="72">I think her riches in her pride appear.</l>
					<l n="73">The fair, the olive, are to me the same,</l>
					<l n="74">Alike the swarthy, and the sandy dame.</l>
					<l n="75">When her black curls adown her shoulders flow,</l>
					<l n="76">Such Leda's were, her skin as white as snow;</l>
					<l n="77">And when her golden locks her head adorn,</l>
					<l n="78">I straight compare her to the saffron morn.</l>
					<l n="79">My love with no complexion disagrees,</l>
					<l n="80">But all alike my ready passion please.</l>
					<l n="81">The younger by their bloom my heart secure,</l>
					<l n="82">The elder win it as they're more mature;</l>
					<l n="83">And though the younger may excel in charms,</l>
					<l n="84">The elder clasp you with experienc'd arms</l>
					<l n="85">What all the city like, is liked by me,</l>
					<l n="86">And I with them and all my loves agree.</l>
					<l n="87">I'm proud to be the rival of the town,</l>
					<l n="88">And to their taste will still conform my own. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="5">
					<head>Elegy V: To His False Mistress. By Eusden.</head>
					<l n="1">Cupid, be gone! I can for beauty sigh,</l>
					<l n="2">But not be forc'd to wish each hour to die;</l>
					<l n="3">For so I wish whene'er my restless thoughts</l>
					<l n="4">Dwell on her falsehoods and repeated faults.</l>
					<l n="5">All other plagues know sometimes to be civil,</l>
					<l n="6">But woman is a sure, perpetual evil.</l>
					<l n="7">No pimp I bribe to prove thy perjur'd vows,</l>
					<l n="8">Nor intercepted once thy billet-doux.</l>
					<l n="9">0, cou dst thou but my arguments disprove!</l>
					<l n="10">A cause so good is here unwish'd in love.</l>
					<l n="11">Happy, who dares t' avow his censur'd flame,</l>
					<l n="12">And vindicate the secret tripping dame.</l>
					<l n="13">Blushless, tho' guilty, with uplifted eyes,</l>
					<l n="14">"'Tis false, my life, by yon bright Heaven," she cries.</l>
					<l n="15">Himself he fools, and madly feeds his grief,</l>
					<l n="16">Who from conviction seeks the sad relief.</l>
					<l n="17">Wretched I saw thy wantonness unsought,</l>
					<l n="18">By thee in sleep secure and eyeless thought;</l>
					<l n="19">With glances on each other how you hung!</l>
					<l n="20">How ev'ry nod had more than half a tongue!</l>
					<l n="21">How roll'd thy glowing eyes! how lewd they spoke!</l>
					<l n="22">E'en from thy artful fingers language broke;</l>
					<l n="23">While writing on the board with pens they vied,</l>
					<l n="24">And the spilt wine the want of ink supplied.</l>
					<l n="25">The silent speech too well I understood,</l>
					<l n="26">For to deceive a lover yet who could?</l>
					<l n="27">Tho' thou didst write in a laconic hand,</l>
					<l n="28">And words for sentences were taught to stand.</l>
					<l n="29">Now ended was the treat, and ev'ry guest</l>
					<l n="30">Indulg'd his ease, and lay compos'd to rest:</l>
					<l n="31">Your close, lascivious kisses then I spied,</l>
					<l n="32">And something more than lips to lips applied;</l>
					<l n="33">Such from a sister brothers ne'er receive,</l>
					<l n="34">But yielding fair ones to warm lovers give.</l>
					<l n="35">Not so <placeName key="tgn,2118015">Diana</placeName> would to Phoebus
						press,</l>
					<l n="36">But Cytherea so her <placeName key="tgn,2090583">Mars</placeName> would
						bless.</l>
					<l n="37">Too far provok'd, at last I cried aloud,</l>
					<l n="38">"On whom are pleasures, due to me, bestow'd?</l>
					<l n="39">I must not, will not, cannot bear this sight;</l>
					<l n="40">'Tis lawful, sure, to seize upon my right.</l>
					<l n="41">These raptures to us both in common are,</l>
					<l n="42">But whence, ye furies, claims a third his share?"</l>
					<l n="43">Enrag'd I spoke, and o'er her cheeks were spread</l>
					<l n="44">Swift newborn glories in a sudden red;</l>
					<l n="45">Such blushes on the bridal night adorn</l>
					<l n="46">The trembling virgin; such the rising morn.</l>
					<l n="47">So sweet a hue the lab'ring <placeName key="tgn,2056258">Cynthia</placeName>
						shows,</l>
					<l n="48">Or the fair lily damask'd by the rose;</l>
					<l n="49">Or iv'ry, which time's yellow taint defies,</l>
					<l n="50">When twice enrich'd with proud Assyrian dies:</l>
					<l n="51">Such were her looks, and a diviner grace</l>
					<l n="52">Had never brighten'd that enchanting face.</l>
					<l n="53">She cast her eyes down on the humble ground;</l>
					<l n="54">Her eyes, so cast, an unknown sweetness found.</l>
					<l n="55">Mournful her looks; her mournful looks became</l>
					<l n="56">Shining thro' grief, and beautiful in shame.</l>
					<l n="57">I rush'd, resolv'd her golden locks to tear,</l>
					<l n="58">And with mad violence disrobe the fair;</l>
					<l n="59">But as I viewed her face, th' extended hand</l>
					<l n="60">Shrunk back, nor hearken'd to the harsh command.</l>
					<l n="61">Others protection seek by dint of arms,</l>
					<l n="62">Her only safeguard was -- her wondrous charms.</l>
					<l n="63">I, who but late look'd insolently brave,</l>
					<l n="64">Fell from my height, and couch'd a suppliant slave:</l>
					<l n="65">I rav'd no longer at another's bliss,</l>
					<l n="66">But begg'd the transport of as sweet a kiss.</l>
					<l n="67">Smiling she said, " How grateful thy request!</l>
					<l n="68">If e'er my kisses please thee, take the best."</l>
					<l n="69">Oh, with what gust as from her soul they came!</l>
					<l n="70">Such might melt Jove, and stop the vengeful flame;</l>
					<l n="71">I fear'd my rival too enjoy'd the same.</l>
					<l n="72">These, better than from me she learn'd I thought,</l>
					<l n="73">Something taught new, alas! I wish'd untaught;</l>
					<l n="74">What most gave pleasure, that now stings the most;</l>
					<l n="75">Why were our darting tongues entirely lost?</l>
					<l n="76">Nor fret I thou in kissing shouldst excel,</l>
					<l n="77">And yet 'tis strange to know to kiss so well;</l>
					<l n="78">But ah! such lectures only could be read</l>
					<l n="79">By youthful tutors, and imbib'd abed.</l>
					<l n="80">That sage who'er these large improvements made,</l>
					<l n="81">Was by his pupil preciously repay'd. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="6">
					<head>Elegy VI: On the Death of His Mistress's Parrot. By <placeName key="tgn,2266465">Creech</placeName>.</head>
					<l n="1">Alas! poor Poll, my Indian talker, dies!</l>
					<l n="2">Go, birds, and celebrate his obsequies;</l>
					<l n="3">Go, birds, and beat your breasts, your faces tear,</l>
					<l n="4">And pluck your gaudy plumes instead of hair;</l>
					<l n="5">Let doleful tunes the frighted forest wound,</l>
					<l n="6">And your sad notes supply the trumpet's sound.</l>
					<l n="7">Why, Philomel, dost mourn the Thracian rage?</l>
					<l n="8">It is enough, thy grief at last assuage;</l>
					<l n="9">His crimson faults are now grown white with age.</l>
					<l n="10">Now mourn this bird; the cause of all thy woe</l>
					<l n="11">Was great, 'tis true, but it was long ago.</l>
					<l n="12">Mourn, all ye wing'd inhabitants of air,</l>
					<l n="13">But you, my turtle, take the greatest share;</l>
					<l n="14">You too liv'd constant friends and free from strife</l>
					<l n="15">Your kindness was entire, and long as life:</l>
					<l n="16">What Pylades to his Orestes vow'd.</l>
					<l n="17">To thee, poor Poll, thy friendly turtle show'd,</l>
					<l n="18">And kept his love as long as fate allow'd.</l>
					<l n="19">But, ah! what did thy faith, thy plumes, and tail,</l>
					<l n="20">And what thy pretty speaking art, avail?</l>
					<l n="21">And what that thou wert giv'n, and pleas'd my miss,</l>
					<l n="22">Since now the bird's unhappy glory dies ?</l>
					<l n="23">A lovely verdant green grac'd ev'ry quill,</l>
					<l n="24">The deepest vivid red did paint thy bill;</l>
					<l n="25">In speaking thou didst ev'ry bird excel,</l>
					<l n="26">None prattled, and none lisp'd the words so well.</l>
					<l n="27">'Twas envy only sent this fierce disease;</l>
					<l n="28">Thou wert averse to war, and liv'dst in peace,</l>
					<l n="29">A talking harmless thing, and lov'dst thine ease.</l>
					<l n="30">The fighting quails still live 'midst all their strife,</l>
					<l n="31">And even that, perhaps, prolongs their life.</l>
					<l n="32">Thy meat was little, and thy prattling tongue</l>
					<l n="33">Would ne'er permit to make thy dinner long:</l>
					<l n="34">Plain fountain water all thy drink allow'd,</l>
					<l n="35">And nut and poppy-seed were all thy food.</l>
					<l n="36">The preying vultures and the kites remain,</l>
					<l n="37">And the unlucky crow still caws for rain;</l>
					<l n="38">The chough still lives 'midst fierce <placeName key="tgn,2070580">Minerva</placeName>'s hate,</l>
					<l n="39">And scarce nine hundred years conclude her fate;</l>
					<l n="40">But my poor Poll now hangs his sickly head,</l>
					<l n="41">My Poll, my present from the east, is dead.</l>
					<l n="42">Best things are sooner snatch'd by cov'tous fate,</l>
					<l n="43">To worse she freely gives a longer date;</l>
					<l n="44">Thersites brave Achilles' fate surviv'd,</l>
					<l n="45">And <placeName key="tgn,2069653">Hector</placeName> fell, whilst all his
						brothers liv'd.</l>
					<l n="46">Why should I tell what vows <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>
						made?</l>
					<l n="47">How oft she begg'd thy life, how oft she pray'd ?</l>
					<l n="48">The seventh day came, and now the Fates begin</l>
					<l n="49">To end the thread, they had no more to spin;</l>
					<l n="50">Yet still he talk'd, and when death nearer drew,</l>
					<l n="51">His last breath said, "<placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>, now
						adieu!"</l>
					<l n="52">There is a shady cypress grove below,</l>
					<l n="53">And thither (if such doubtful things we know)</l>
					<l n="54">The ghosts of pious birds departed go;</l>
					<l n="55">'Tis water'd well, and verdant all the year,</l>
					<l n="56">And birds obscene do never enter there;</l>
					<l n="57">There harmless swans securely take their rest,</l>
					<l n="58">And there the single Phoenix builds her nest;</l>
					<l n="59">Proud peacocks there display their gaudy train,</l>
					<l n="60">And billing turtles coo o'er all the plain:</l>
					<l n="61">To these dark shades my parrot's soul shall go,</l>
					<l n="62">And with his talk divert the birds below;</l>
					<l n="63">Whilst here his bones enjoy a noble grave,</l>
					<l n="64">A little marble, and an epitaph:-</l>
					<l n="65">"In talking I did ev'ry bird excel,</l>
					<l n="66">And my tomb proves my mistress lov'd me well." </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="7">
					<head>Elegy VII: He protests that he never had anything to do with the
						chambermaid. By the same hand.</head>
					<l n="1">And must I still be guilty, still untrue,</l>
					<l n="2">And when old crimes are purg'd, still charg'd with new?</l>
					<l n="3">What tho' at last my cause I clearly gain?</l>
					<l n="4">Yet I'm asham'd so oft to strive in vain,</l>
					<l n="5">And when the prize will scarce reward the pain.</l>
					<l n="6">If at the play I in fop-corner sit,</l>
					<l n="7">And with a squinting eye gloat o'er the pit,</l>
					<l n="8">Or view the boxes, you begin to fear,</l>
					<l n="9">And fancy straight some rival beauty there.</l>
					<l n="10">If any looks on me, you think you spy</l>
					<l n="11">A private assignation in her eye;</l>
					<l n="12">A silent soft discourse in ev'ry grace,</l>
					<l n="13">And tongues in all the features of her face.</l>
					<l n="14">If I praise any one, you tear your hair,</l>
					<l n="15">Show frantic tricks, and rage with wild despair;</l>
					<l n="16">If discommend, 0 then 'tis all deceit,</l>
					<l n="17">I strive to cloak my passion by the cheat.</l>
					<l n="18">If I look well, I then neglect your charms,</l>
					<l n="19">Lie dull and lazy in your active arms;</l>
					<l n="20">If weak my voice, if pale my looks appear,</l>
					<l n="21">0 then I languish for another fair.</l>
					<l n="22">Would I did sin, and you with cause complain,</l>
					<l n="23">For when we strive to shun, yet strive in vain,</l>
					<l n="24">'Tis comfort sure to have deserv'd the pain.</l>
					<l n="25">But sure fond fancies now such heats engage,</l>
					<l n="26">Your cred'lous peevish humour spoils your rage.</l>
					<l n="27">In frequent chidings I no force can see,</l>
					<l n="28">You frown too often to prevail with me;</l>
					<l n="29">The ass grows dull by stripes; the constant blow</l>
					<l n="30">Beats off his briskness, and he moves but slow.</l>
					<l n="31">But now I'm lavish of my kind embrace,</l>
					<l n="32">And Moll, forsooth, supplies her lady's place!</l>
					<l n="33">Kind love, forbid that I should stoop so low;</l>
					<l n="34">What! unto mean, ignoble beauties bow ?</l>
					<l n="35">A chambermaid ! no faith, my love flies high;</l>
					<l n="36">My quarry is a miss of quality.</l>
					<l n="37">Fye, who would clasp a slave ? who joy to feel</l>
					<l n="38">Her hands of iron and her sides of steel ?</l>
					<l n="39">'Twill damp an eager thought, 'twill check my mind,</l>
					<l n="40">To feel those knobs the lash hath left behind.</l>
					<l n="41">Besides, she dresses well, with lovely grace</l>
					<l n="42">She sets thy tow'r, and does adorn thy face;</l>
					<l n="43">Thy nat'ral beauty all her hearts improve,</l>
					<l n="44">And make me more enamour'd of my love.</l>
					<l n="45">Then why should I tempt her, and why betray</l>
					<l n="46">Thy useful slave, and have her turn'd away?</l>
					<l n="47">I swear by <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName>, by love's darts
						and bow,</l>
					<l n="48">(A desp'rate oath, you must believe me now,)</l>
					<l n="49">I am not guilty, I've not broke my vow! </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="8">
					<head>Elegy VIII: To Corinna's Chambermaid. By the same hand.</head>
					<l n="1">Dear, skilful <placeName key="tgn,2165330">Betty</placeName>, who dost far
						excel</l>
					<l n="2">My lady's other maids in dressing well;</l>
					<l n="3">Dear Betty, fit to be preferred above</l>
					<l n="4">To <placeName key="tgn,2075297">Juno</placeName>'s chamber, or the queen of
						love;</l>
					<l n="5">Genteel, well-bred, not rustically coy,</l>
					<l n="6">Not easy to deny desired joy;</l>
					<l n="7">Thro' whose soft eyes still secret wishes shine,</l>
					<l n="8">Fit for thy mistress' use, but more for mine;</l>
					<l n="9">Who, <placeName key="tgn,2165330">Betty</placeName>, did the fatal secret
						see?</l>
					<l n="10">Who told <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> you were kind to
						me!</l>
					<l n="11">Yet when she chid me for my kind embrace,</l>
					<l n="12">Did any guilty blush spread o'er my face!</l>
					<l n="13">Did I betray thee, maid, or could she spy</l>
					<l n="14">The least confession in my conscious eye !</l>
					<l n="15">Not that I think it a disgrace to prove</l>
					<l n="16">Stol'n sweets, or make a chambermaid my love;</l>
					<l n="17">Achilles wanton'd in Briseis' arms,</l>
					<l n="18">Atrides bow'd to fair <placeName key="tgn,2087009">Cassandra</placeName>'s
						charms:</l>
					<l n="19">Sure I am less than these,-then what can bring</l>
					<l n="20">Disgrace to me, that so became a king !</l>
					<l n="21">But when she look'd on you, poor harmless maid,</l>
					<l n="22">You blush'd, and all the kind intrigue betray'd;</l>
					<l n="23">Yet still I vow'd, I made a stout defence,</l>
					<l n="24">I swore, and look'd as bold as innocence;</l>
					<l n="25">"Damme, -- egad!" all that, and -- "let me die!"'</l>
					<l n="26">Kind <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName>, do not hear my
						perjury;</l>
					<l n="27">Kind <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName>, stop thy ears when
						lovers lie.</l>
					<l n="28">Now, <placeName key="tgn,2165330">Betty</placeName>, how will you my oaths
						requite?</l>
					<l n="29">Come, pr'ythee let's compound for more delight;</l>
					<l n="30">Faith, I am easy, and but ask a night.</l>
					<l n="31">What! start at the proposal? how! deny</l>
					<l n="32">Pretend fond fears of a discovery ?</l>
					<l n="33">Refuse, lest some sad chance the thing betray ?</l>
					<l n="34">Is this your kind, your damn'd obliging way ?</l>
					<l n="35">Well, deny on; I'll lie, I'll swear no more;</l>
					<l n="36"><placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> now shall know thou art a
						whore.</l>
					<l n="37">I'll tell, since you my fair address forbid,</l>
					<l n="38">How often, when, and where, and what we did! </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="9">
					<head>Elegy IX: To Love. By the Earl of <placeName key="tgn,7014348">Rochester</placeName>.</head>
					<l n="1">O Love! how cold and slow to take my part,</l>
					<l n="2">Thou idle wanderer about my heart!</l>
					<l n="3">Why thy old faithful soldier wilt thou see</l>
					<l n="4">Oppress'd in thy own tents? they murder me;</l>
					<l n="5">Thy flames consume, thy arrows pierce thy friends;</l>
					<l n="6">Rather on foes pursue more noble ends.</l>
					<l n="7">Achilles' sword would certainly bestow</l>
					<l n="8">A cure as certain as it gave the blow.</l>
					<l n="9">Hunters, who follow flying game, give o'er</l>
					<l n="10">When the prey's caught, hope still leads on before;</l>
					<l n="11">We, thine own slaves, feel thy tyrannic blows.</l>
					<l n="12">While thy tame hand's unmov'd against thy foes.</l>
					<l n="13">On men disarm'd, how can you gallant prove ?</l>
					<l n="14">And I was long ago disarm'd by love.</l>
					<l n="15">Millions of dull men live, and scornful maids;</l>
					<l n="16">We'll own love valiant when he these invades.</l>
					<l n="17"><placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> from each corner of the wide
						world snatch'd</l>
					<l n="18">A laurel, or't had been to this day thatch'd;</l>
					<l n="19">But the old soldier has his resting-place,</l>
					<l n="20">And the good batter'd horse is turn'd to grass:</l>
					<l n="21">The harass'd whore, who liv'd a wretch to please,</l>
					<l n="22">Has leave to be a bawd, and take her ease.</l>
					<l n="23">For me then, who have truly spent my blood,</l>
					<l n="24">Love, in thy service, and so boldly stood</l>
					<l n="25">In <placeName key="tgn,2087042">Celia</placeName>'s trenches, were't not
						wisely done,</l>
					<l n="26">E'en to retire, and live at peace at home ?</l>
					<l n="27">No-might I gain a godhead to disclaim</l>
					<l n="28">My glorious title to my endless flame,</l>
					<l n="29">Divinity with scorn I would forswear,</l>
					<l n="30">Such sweet, dear, tempting devils women are.</l>
					<l n="31">Whene'er those flames grow faint, I quickly find</l>
					<l n="32">A fierce black storm pour down upon my mind;</l>
					<l n="33">Headlong I'm hurl'd like horsemen who in vain</l>
					<l n="34">Their fury-flaming coursers would restrain.</l>
					<l n="35">As ships, just when the harbour they attain,</l>
					<l n="36">Are snatch'd by sudden blasts to sea again,</l>
					<l n="37">So Love's fantastic storms reduce my heart,</l>
					<l n="38">Half rescu'd, and the god resumes his dart.</l>
					<l n="39">Strike here, this undefended bosom wound,</l>
					<l n="40">And for so brave a conquest be renown'd.</l>
					<l n="41">Shafts fly so fast to me from ev'ry part,</l>
					<l n="42">You'll scarce discern the quiver from my heart.</l>
					<l n="43">What wretch can bear a livelong night's dull rest,</l>
					<l n="44">Or think himself in lazy slumbers blest?</l>
					<l n="45">Fool-is not sleep the image of pale death?</l>
					<l n="46">There's time for rest when fate has stopp'd your breath.</l>
					<l n="47">Me may my soft deluding dear deceive,</l>
					<l n="48">I'm happy in my hopes, while I believe:</l>
					<l n="49">Now let her flatter, then as fondly chide,</l>
					<l n="50">Often may I enjoy, oft be denied.</l>
					<l n="51">With doubtful steps the god of war does move,</l>
					<l n="52">By thy example, in ambiguous love.</l>
					<l n="53">Blown to and fro, like down from thy own wing,</l>
					<l n="54">Who knows when joy or anguish thou wilt bring?</l>
					<l n="55">Yet at thy mother's and thy slave's request,</l>
					<l n="56">Fix an eternal empire in my breast;</l>
					<l n="57">And let th' inconstant charming sex,</l>
					<l n="58">Whose wilful scorn does lovers vex,</l>
					<l n="59">Submit their hearts before thy throne;</l>
					<l n="60">The vassal world is then thy own. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="10">
					<head>Elegy X: <placeName key="tgn,2071526">Ovid</placeName> tells Graecinus,
						that he is fallen in love with a couple of ladies. By an unknown
						hand.</head>
					<l n="1">What you affirm'd, my friend, is prov'd untrue,</l>
					<l n="2">That none at once could madly dote on two.</l>
					<l n="3">Deceiv'd, unarm'd, we Cupid soon o'ercame,</l>
					<l n="4">And I glow shameless with a double flame.</l>
					<l n="5">They both are fair, both dress'd so nicely well,</l>
					<l n="6">That the pre-eminence is hard to tell.</l>
					<l n="7">Sometimes for this, sometimes for that I burn,</l>
					<l n="8">And each more beauteous sparkles in her turn.</l>
					<l n="9">Each claims my passion, and my heart divides</l>
					<l n="10">As to and fro the doubtful galliot rides.</l>
					<l n="11">Here driven by winds, and there redriven by tides.</l>
					<l n="12">Why doubly chain'd ? was not a single fair</l>
					<l n="13">Enough to load me with perpetual care?</l>
					<l n="14">Why are more leaves brought to the shady wood,</l>
					<l n="15">Stars to the sky, or waters to the flood ?</l>
					<l n="16">Yet better so than not to love at all;</l>
					<l n="17">Still on my foes may such dull blessings fall.</l>
					<l n="18">May they, insipidly supine, be spread</l>
					<l n="19">Along the middle of a widowed bed;</l>
					<l n="20">While I with sprightliness love's vigil's keep,</l>
					<l n="21">Stretch'd out for something far more sweet than sleep.</l>
					<l n="22">Others from ruin fly, to mine I run,</l>
					<l n="23">To be by women pleasingly undone,</l>
					<l n="24">Longing for two, since undestroy'd by one.</l>
					<l n="25">Still let my slender limbs for love suffice;</l>
					<l n="26">I want no nerves, but want the bulky size.</l>
					<l n="27">My limbs, tho' lean are not in vain display'd;</l>
					<l n="28">From me no female ever rose a maid.</l>
					<l n="29">Oft have I, when a luscious night was spent,</l>
					<l n="30">Saluted morn, nor cloy'd nor impotent.</l>
					<l n="31">Happy, who gasps in love his latest breath;</l>
					<l n="32">Give me, ye gods, so softly sweet a death !</l>
					<l n="33">Let the rough warriors grapple on the plain,</l>
					<l n="34">And with their blood immortal honour gain;</l>
					<l n="35">Let the vile miser plough for wealth the deep,</l>
					<l n="36">And, shipwrek'd in the unfatbom'd waters, sleep</l>
					<l n="37">May <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName> grant me but my last
						desire,</l>
					<l n="38">In the full height of rapture to expire.</l>
					<l n="39">Perhaps some friend, with kindly dew supplied,</l>
					<l n="40">Weeping will say, "As Ovid liv'd, he died." </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="11">
					<p>Poem 11, in which the poet prays that his Mistress will be safe as she
						travels by sea, is not here translated. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="12">
					<head>Elegy XII: The Poet rejoices for the favours he has received of his
						mistress.</head>
					<l n="1">Io Triumphe! I have won the prize,</l>
					<l n="2">For in my arms the fair <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>
						lies.</l>
					<l n="3">Nor jealous husband, nor a guardian's care,</l>
					<l n="4">Nor door defended with a double bar,</l>
					<l n="5">Could fence against a lover's artifice,</l>
					<l n="6">For in my arms the fair <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>
						lies.</l>
					<l n="7">With reason of my victory I boast,</l>
					<l n="8">The conquest gain'd, and yet no blood is lost;</l>
					<l n="9">I scal'd no walls, I pass'd no ditch profound,</l>
					<l n="10">Safe were my wars, and all without a wound.</l>
					<l n="11">My only work a charming girl to gain;</l>
					<l n="12">The pleasure well rewards the little pain.</l>
					<l n="13">Ten years the Greeks did in one siege employ,</l>
					<l n="14">But levell'd were, at length, the walls of <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>;</l>
					<l n="15">What glory was there by th' Atrides won,</l>
					<l n="16">So many chiefs before a single town!</l>
					<l n="17">Not thus did I my pleasant toils pursue,</l>
					<l n="18">And the whole glory to myself is due;</l>
					<l n="19">Myself was horse and foot, myself alone</l>
					<l n="20">The captain and the soldier was in one,</l>
					<l n="21">And fought beneath no banner but my own.</l>
					<l n="22">Whether by strength I combated, or wile,</l>
					<l n="23">Fortune did ever on my actions smile;</l>
					<l n="24">I only owe my triumph to my care,</l>
					<l n="25">And by my patience only won the fair.</l>
					<l n="26">Nor was my cause of quarrel new; the same</l>
					<l n="27">Set <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and proud <placeName key="tgn,2097781">Asia</placeName> in a flame.</l>
					<l n="28">For Helen, ravish'd by the Dardan boy,</l>
					<l n="29">Was the war wag'd that sunk the pride of <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>;</l>
					<l n="30">The Centaurs double form'd, half man, half beast,</l>
					<l n="31">Defil'd with horrid war the nuptial feast;</l>
					<l n="32">Inflam'd by wine and woman's magic charms,</l>
					<l n="33">They turn'd the jolly face of joy to arms.</l>
					<l n="34">'Twas woman urg'd the strife; a second fair</l>
					<l n="35">Involv'd the Trojans in a second war.</l>
					<l n="36">What wreck, what ruin, did a Woman bring</l>
					<l n="37">On peaceful <placeName key="tgn,7003080">Latium</placeName>, and its pious
						king!</l>
					<l n="38">When <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> was young and in her
						infant state</l>
					<l n="39">What woes did woman to our sires create!</l>
					<l n="40">Into what peril was that city brought,</l>
					<l n="41">When <placeName key="tgn,7021127">Sabine</placeName> fathers for their
						daughters fought !</l>
					<l n="42">Two lusty bulls I in the meads have view'd</l>
					<l n="43">In combat join'd, and by their side there stood</l>
					<l n="44">A milk-white heifer, who provok'd the fight,</l>
					<l n="45">By each contended, but the conqueror's right;</l>
					<l n="46">She gives them courage, her they both regard,</l>
					<l n="47">As one that caus'd the war, and must reward.</l>
					<l n="48">Compell'd by Cupid in his host to list</l>
					<l n="49">(And who that has a heart can love resist ?)</l>
					<l n="50">His soldier I have been, without the guilt</l>
					<l n="51">Of blood, in any of our battles spilt;</l>
					<l n="52">For him I've fought, as many more have done,</l>
					<l n="53">And many rivals met, but murder'd none. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="13">
					<head>Elegy XIII: To Isis. A prayer that the goddess would assist <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>, and prevent her
						miscarrying.</head>
					<l n="1">With cruel art <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> would
						destroy</l>
					<l n="2">The ripening fruit of our repeated joy.</l>
					<l n="3">While on herself she practises her skill,</l>
					<l n="4">She's like the mother, not the child, to kill.</l>
					<l n="5">Me she would not acquaint with what she did,</l>
					<l n="6">From me a thing, which I abhorr'd, she hid;</l>
					<l n="7">Well might I now be angry, but I fear,</l>
					<l n="8">Ill as she is, I might endanger her.</l>
					<l n="9">By me, I must confess, she did conceive,</l>
					<l n="10">The fact is so, or else I so believe;</l>
					<l n="11">We've cause to think, what may so likely be,</l>
					<l n="12">So is, and then the babe belongs to me</l>
					<l n="13">Oh Isis, who delight'st to haunt the fields,</l>
					<l n="14">Where fruitful <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> his golden
						harvest yields,</l>
					<l n="15">Where with seven mouths into the sea it falls,</l>
					<l n="16">And hast thy walks around Canope's walls,</l>
					<l n="17">Who <placeName key="tgn,7017750">Memphis</placeName> visit'st, and the
						Pharian tower,</l>
					<l n="18">Assist <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> with thy friendly
						powers.</l>
					<l n="19">Thee by thy silver Sistra I conjure,</l>
					<l n="20">A life so precious by thy aid secure;</l>
					<l n="21">So mayst thou with <placeName key="tgn,2060004">Osiris</placeName> still find
						grace:</l>
					<l n="22">By Anubis's venerable face,</l>
					<l n="23">I pray thee, so may still thy rights divine</l>
					<l n="24">Flourish, and serpents round thy offerings twine</l>
					<l n="25">May Apis with his horns the pomp attend,</l>
					<l n="26">And be to thee, as thou'rt to her, a friend.</l>
					<l n="27">Look down, oh Isis! on the teeming fair,</l>
					<l n="28">And make at once her life and mine thy care:</l>
					<l n="29">Have pity on her pains; the help you give</l>
					<l n="30">To her, her lover saves, in her I live.</l>
					<l n="31">From thee this favour she deserves; she pays</l>
					<l n="32">Her vows to thee on all thy solemn days;</l>
					<l n="33">And when the Galli at thy altars wait,</l>
					<l n="34">She's present at the feast they celebrate.</l>
					<l n="35">And thou, Lucina, who the labouring womb</l>
					<l n="36">Dost with compassion view, to her assistance come:</l>
					<l n="37">Nor dost thou, when to thee thy votaries pray</l>
					<l n="38">For speedy help, thy wanted help delay.</l>
					<l n="39">Lucina, listen to <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>'s
						pray'r;</l>
					<l n="40">Thy votary she, and worthy of thy care.</l>
					<l n="41">I'll with my off'rings to thy altar come,</l>
					<l n="42">With votive myrrh thy sacred fane perfume;</l>
					<l n="43">The vows I make that thou my fair mayst bless,</l>
					<l n="44">In words inscrib'd, I'll on thy shrine express:-</l>
					<l n="45">"<placeName key="tgn,2071526">Ovid</placeName>, the servant of <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>, pray'd</l>
					<l n="46">The goddess here, the teeming dame to aid."</l>
					<l n="47">Ah, goddess! of my humble suit allow;</l>
					<l n="48">Give place to my inscription and my vow.</l>
					<l n="49">If frighted as I am, I may presume</l>
					<l n="50">Your conduct to direct in time to come,</l>
					<l n="51"><placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>, since you've suffer'd thus
						before,</l>
					<l n="52">Ah, try the bold experiment no more! </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="14">
					<head>Elegy XIV: To his Mistress, who endeavoured to make herself
						miscarry.</head>
					<l n="1">What boots it that the fair are free from war,</l>
					<l n="2">And what that they're forbid the shield to bear,</l>
					<l n="3">Against themselves if they knew arms employ</l>
					<l n="4">And madly with new wounds their lives destroy?</l>
					<l n="5">The cruel mother who did first contrive</l>
					<l n="6">Her babe to butcher ere 'twas scarce alive,</l>
					<l n="7">Who thus from nature's tender dictates swerv'd,</l>
					<l n="8">To perish by her proper hands deserv'd.</l>
					<l n="9">Why do the sex forget their softness? why</l>
					<l n="10">Such projects for a foolish fancy try?</l>
					<l n="11">The belly must be smooth, no wrinkle there</l>
					<l n="12">To shock the lover's wanton glance appear;</l>
					<l n="13">His touch as well as sight they fain would please,</l>
					<l n="14">And the womb early of its burden ease.</l>
					<l n="15">Had woman sooner known this wicked trade,</l>
					<l n="16">Among the race of men what havock had they made.</l>
					<l n="17">Mankind had been extinct, and lost the seed,</l>
					<l n="18">Without a wonder to restore the breed,</l>
					<l n="19">As when Deucalion and his Purrha hurl'd</l>
					<l n="20">The stones that sow'd with men the delug'd world,</l>
					<l n="21">Had Thetis, goddess of the sea, refus'd</l>
					<l n="22">To bear the burden, and her fruit abus'd,</l>
					<l n="23">Who would have Priam's royal seat destroy'd?</l>
					<l n="24">Or had the vestal whom fierce <placeName key="tgn,2090583">Mars</placeName>
						enjoy'd,</l>
					<l n="25">Stifled the twins within her pergnant womb,</l>
					<l n="26">What founder would have then been born to <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>?</l>
					<l n="27">Had <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName>, when she with Aeneas
						teem'd,</l>
					<l n="28">To death, ere born, Anchises' son condemn'd,</l>
					<l n="29">The world had of the Caesars been depriv'd;</l>
					<l n="30">Augustus ne'er had reign'd, nor <placeName key="tgn,2008628">Julius</placeName> liv'd.</l>
					<l n="31">And thou, whose beauty is the boast of fame,</l>
					<l n="32">Hadst perish'd, had thy mother done the same;</l>
					<l n="33">Nor had I liv'd love's faithful slave to be,</l>
					<l n="34">Had my own mother dealt as ill by me.</l>
					<l n="35">Ah, vile invention, ah, accurs'd design,</l>
					<l n="36">To rob of rip'ning fruit the loaded vine</l>
					<l n="37">Ah, let it grow for nature's use mature,</l>
					<l n="38">Ah, let it its full length of time endure;</l>
					<l n="39">'Twill of itself, alas! too soon decay,</l>
					<l n="40">And quickly fall, like autumn leaves, away</l>
					<l n="41">Why barb'rously dost thou thy bowels tear</l>
					<l n="42">To kill the human load that quickens there?</l>
					<l n="43">On venom'd drugs why venture, to destroy</l>
					<l n="44">The pledge of pleasure past, the promis'd boy?</l>
					<l n="45">Medea, guilty of her childrens' blood,</l>
					<l n="46">The mark of ev'ry age's curse has stood;</l>
					<l n="47">And Atys, murder'd by his mothers rage,</l>
					<l n="48">Been pitied since by each succeeding age;</l>
					<l n="49">Thy cruel parents by false lords abus'd,</l>
					<l n="50">Had yet some plea, tho' none their crime excus'd.</l>
					<l n="51">What, Jason, did your dire revenge provoke?</l>
					<l n="52">What, Tereus, urge you to the fatal stroke?</l>
					<l n="53">What rage your reason led so far away,</l>
					<l n="54">As furious hands upon yourself to lay?</l>
					<l n="55">The tigresses that haunt th' Armenian wood,</l>
					<l n="56">Will spare their proper young, though pinch'd for food;</l>
					<l n="57">Nor will the Libyan lionesses slay</l>
					<l n="58">Their whelps, -- but woman are more fierce than they;</l>
					<l n="59">More barb'rous to the tender fruit they bear,</l>
					<l n="60">Nor nature's call, tho' loud she cries, will hear.</l>
					<l n="61">But righteous vengeance oft their crimes pursues,</l>
					<l n="62">And they are lost themselves, who would their</l>
					<l n="63">children lose;</l>
					<l n="64">The pois'nous drugs with mortal juices fill</l>
					<l n="65">Their veins, and, undesign'd, themselves they kill</l>
					<l n="66">Themselves upon the bier are breathless borne,</l>
					<l n="67">With hair tied up that was in ringlets worn,</l>
					<l n="68">Thro' weeping crowds that on their course attend;</l>
					<l n="69">Well may they weep for their unhappy end.</l>
					<l n="70">Forbid it, heaven, that what I say may prove</l>
					<l n="71">Presaging to the fair I blame and love;</l>
					<l n="72">Thus let me ne'er, ye pow'rs, her death deplore,</l>
					<l n="73">'Twas her first fault, and she'll offend no more;</l>
					<l n="74">No pardon she'll deserve a second time,</l>
					<l n="75">But, without mercy, punish then her crime. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="15">
					<head>Elegy XV: The Poet addresses the ring which he has sent a present to his
						mistress. By an unknown hand.</head>
					<l n="1">Go, happy ring, who art about to bind</l>
					<l n="2">The fair one's finger; may the fair be kind.</l>
					<l n="3">Small is the present, tho' the love be great;</l>
					<l n="4">May she swift slip thee on thy taper seat.</l>
					<l n="5">As she and I, may thou with her agree,</l>
					<l n="6">And not too large, nor yet too little be.</l>
					<l n="7">To touch her hand thou wilt the pleasure have;</l>
					<l n="8">I now must envy what myself I gave.</l>
					<l n="9">O! would a Proteus or a Circe change</l>
					<l n="10">Me to thy form, that I like thee might range !</l>
					<l n="11">Then would I wish thee with her breasts to play,</l>
					<l n="12">And her left hand beneath her robes to stray.</l>
					<l n="13">Tho' straight she thought me, I will then appear</l>
					<l n="14">Loose and unfix'd, and slip I know not where.</l>
					<l n="15">Whene'er she writes some secret lines of love,</l>
					<l n="16">Lest the dry gum and wax should sticking prove,</l>
					<l n="17">He first she moistens : then sly care I take,</l>
					<l n="18">And but, when lines I like, impression make.</l>
					<l n="19">Of in her pocket fain she would me hide,</l>
					<l n="20">Close will I press her finger, and not slide;</l>
					<l n="21">Then cry, "My life, I ne'er shall thee disgrace,</l>
					<l n="22">And I am light; give me my proper place.</l>
					<l n="23">Still let me stick when in the bath you are;</l>
					<l n="24">If I catch damage,'tis not worth your care.</l>
					<l n="25">Yea, when the ring thy naked body spies,</l>
					<l n="26">It will transform, and I a man arise."</l>
					<l n="27">Why do I rave? thou little trifle, go,</l>
					<l n="28">And that I die for her let the dear creature know. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="16">
					<head>Elegy XVI: He invites his mistress into the country.</head>
					<l n="1">I'm now at -- where my eyes can view,</l>
					<l n="2">Their old delights, but what I want in you:</l>
					<l n="3">Here purling streams cut thro' my pleasing bowr's,</l>
					<l n="4">Adorn my banks, and raise my drooping flow'rs;</l>
					<l n="5">Here trees with bending fruit in order stand,</l>
					<l n="6">Invite my eye, and tempt my greedy hand;</l>
					<l n="7">But half the pleasure of enjoyment's gone;</l>
					<l n="8">Since I must pluck them single and alone;</l>
					<l n="9">Why could not nature's kindness first contrive,</l>
					<l n="10">That faithful lovers should like spirits live,</l>
					<l n="11">Mix'd in one point and yet divided lie,</l>
					<l n="12">Enjoying an united liberty?</l>
					<l n="13">But since we must thro' distant regions go,</l>
					<l n="14">Why was not the same way design'd for two?</l>
					<l n="15">One single care determined still for both,</l>
					<l n="16">And the kind virgin join'd the loving youth?</l>
					<l n="17">Then should I think it pleasant way to go</l>
					<l n="18">Oe'r Alpine frost, and trace the hills of snow;</l>
					<l n="19">Then should I dare to view the horrid moors,</l>
					<l n="20">And walk the deserts of the Libyan shores;</l>
					<l n="21">Hear Scylla bark, and see <placeName key="tgn,2233588">Charybdis</placeName>
						rave,</l>
					<l n="22">Suck in and vomit out the threat'ning wave;</l>
					<l n="23">Fearless through all I'd steer my feeble barge,</l>
					<l n="24">Secure, and safe with the celestial charge,</l>
					<l n="25">But now, though here my grateful fields afford</l>
					<l n="26">Choice fruits to cheer their malancholy lord;</l>
					<l n="27">Though here obedient streams the gard'ner leads,</l>
					<l n="28">In narrow channels through my flow'ry beds;</l>
					<l n="29">The poplars rise, and spread a shady grove,</l>
					<l n="30">Where I might lie, my little life improve,</l>
					<l n="31">And spend my minutes 'twixt a muse and love:</l>
					<l n="32">Yet these contributes little to my ease,</l>
					<l n="33">For without you they lose the power to please;</l>
					<l n="34">I seem to walk oe'r the fields of naked sand,</l>
					<l n="35">Or tread an antic maze in fairy land,</l>
					<l n="36">Where frightful specires, and pale shades appear,</l>
					<l n="37">And hollow groans invade my troubled ear;</l>
					<l n="38">Where ev'ry breeze that through my arbour flies,</l>
					<l n="39">First sadly murmurs, and then turns to sighs.</l>
					<l n="40">The vines love elms; what elms from vines remove?</l>
					<l n="41">Then why should I be parted from my love?</l>
					<l n="42">And yet by me you once devoutly swore,</l>
					<l n="43">By your own eyes, those stars that I adore,</l>
					<l n="44">That all my bus'ness you would make your own,</l>
					<l n="45">And never suffer me to be alone:</l>
					<l n="46">But faithless woman nat'rally deceives,</l>
					<l n="47">Their frequent oaths are like the falling leaves,</l>
					<l n="48">Which when a storm has from the branches tore</l>
					<l n="49">Are lost by ev'ry blast, and seen no more:</l>
					<l n="50">Yet if you will be true, your vows retrieve,</l>
					<l n="51">Be kind, and I can easily forgive ;</l>
					<l n="52">Prepare your coach, to me direct your course,</l>
					<l n="53">Drive fiercely on, and lash the lazy horse;</l>
					<l n="54">And while you ride I will prolong the day,</l>
					<l n="55">And try the power of verse to smooth your way.</l>
					<l n="56">Sink down ye mountains, sink ye lofty hills,</l>
					<l n="57">Ye vallies be obedient to her wheels,</l>
					<l n="58">Ye streams be dry, ye hindr'ing woods remove,</l>
					<l n="59">'Tis love that drives, and all must yield to love ! </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="17">
					<head>Elegy XVII: He tells <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> he
						will always be her slave</head>
					<l n="1">If there's a wretch, who thinks it is a shame,</l>
					<l n="2">To serve a lovely and a loving dame:</l>
					<l n="3">If such a slave he loads with infamy,</l>
					<l n="4">I'm willing he should judge as hard of me;</l>
					<l n="5">I'm willing all the world should know my shame</l>
					<l n="6">If <placeName key="tgn,2081683">Venus</placeName> will abate my raging
						flame.</l>
					<l n="7">Let me a fair and gentle mistress have,</l>
					<l n="8">And then proclaim aloud that I'm her slave.</l>
					<l n="9">Beauty is apt to swell a maiden's mind,</l>
					<l n="10">And thus <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> is to pride
						inclin'd:</l>
					<l n="11">But as she is above all maiden's fair,</l>
					<l n="12">What's pride in them is insolence in her;</l>
					<l n="13">Less fair I wish she was, or knew it less;</l>
					<l n="14">How learnt she, she is lovely by her face!</l>
					<l n="15">Her mirror tells her so, she often tries</l>
					<l n="16">Her mirror, and believes her charming eyes.</l>
					<l n="17">The looks she then puts on, are still her best,</l>
					<l n="18">And she ne'er uses it but when she's dress'd.</l>
					<l n="19">Though wide the empire of your beauties spread,</l>
					<l n="20">Beauty to draw my am'rous glances made:</l>
					<l n="21">Compare your servant's merit with your eyes,</l>
					<l n="22">You'll find no cause his service to dispise.</l>
					<l n="23">Don't think I press upon your pride too hard.</l>
					<l n="24">For little things may be with great compar'd:</l>
					<l n="25">We're told Calypso, an immortal pow'r,</l>
					<l n="26">Detain'd a mortal in th' Ogygian pow'r,</l>
					<l n="27">And when her pray'r to stay he would not grant,</l>
					<l n="28">So strong her love, she kept him by constraint.</l>
					<l n="29">A Nereid took the Pythian to her arms.</l>
					<l n="30">And <placeName key="tgn,2033144">Numa</placeName> knew divine <placeName key="tgn,2118102">Egeria</placeName>'s charms.</l>
					<l n="31"><placeName key="tgn,2094117">Vulcan</placeName> though lame, and of a form
						obscene,</l>
					<l n="32">Was oft made happy by the Paphian queen;</l>
					<l n="33">She matter'd not his limping, but approv'd</l>
					<l n="34">His flame, and saw no faults in him she lov'd</l>
					<l n="35">My verses are unequal like his feet,</l>
					<l n="36">Yet the long kindly with the shorter meet.</l>
					<l n="37">As they with them, why shouldst thou not with me</l>
					<l n="38">Comply, my life and my divinity !</l>
					<l n="39">Myself, when I am in thy arms, I'll own</l>
					<l n="40">Thy subject, and the bed shall be thy throne;</l>
					<l n="41">Thou there, my lovely queen, shall give me laws,</l>
					<l n="42">Nor in my absence, to rejoice have cause,</l>
					<l n="43">Nor ever shall my services be blam'd</l>
					<l n="44">Nor shalt thou of thy servant be asham'd.</l>
					<l n="45">My poetry's my purse, my fortun's there,</l>
					<l n="46">I have no other way to win the fair;</l>
					<l n="47">Nor is that way the worst; the brightest dames</l>
					<l n="48">Would in my verse immortalize their names.</l>
					<l n="49">My muse the place of an estate supplies,</l>
					<l n="50">And none that know her worth, her wealth despise.</l>
					<l n="51">Some tempted by <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>'s spreading
						fame,</l>
					<l n="52">In envy rob her, and usurp her name;</l>
					<l n="53">What would they give, d'ye think, to be the same ?</l>
					<l n="54">But neither could Eurotas, nor the Po,</l>
					<l n="55">With poplar shaded, in one channel flew;</l>
					<l n="56">By diff'rent, and by distant banks they glide,</l>
					<l n="57">Are rivers both, but various in their tide.</l>
					<l n="58">There are more beauties, but there's none like thine,</l>
					<l n="59">There are more versed, but thou hast only mine;</l>
					<l n="60">No other charms can e'er inspire my muse,</l>
					<l n="61">And other themes I with disdain refuse. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="18">
					<head>Elegy XVIII: To Macer, blaming him for not writing of love as he
						did.</head>
					<l n="1">While, Macer, you Achilles' choler sing,</l>
					<l n="2">And <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> before the walls of
							<placeName key="tgn,7002329">Ilium</placeName> bring;</l>
					<l n="3">While feats of arms in Phrygian fields you tell,</l>
					<l n="4">And how old Tory by Grecion vengeance fell;</l>
					<l n="5">I my soft hours in softer songs employ,</l>
					<l n="6">And all my leisure give to love and joy.</l>
					<l n="7">When to high acts, my voice I strive to raise,</l>
					<l n="8">Love laughs at my attempt, and mocks my lays;</l>
					<l n="9">"Begone!" I often to my mistress cry,</l>
					<l n="10">But have not courage, yet, myself to fly.</l>
					<l n="11">Whene'er she sees me in this sullen fit,</l>
					<l n="12">She fondles me, and, on my knee will sit:</l>
					<l n="13">"Enough of this (say I), for shame give o'er,</l>
					<l n="14">Enough of love, we'll play the fool no more."</l>
					<l n="15">" Ah, is it then a shame to love?" she cries,</l>
					<l n="16">And chides, and melts me with her weeping eyes.</l>
					<l n="17">Around my neck her snowy arms she throws,</l>
					<l n="18">And to my lips with stifling kisses grows.</l>
					<l n="19">How can I all this tenderness refuse ?</l>
					<l n="20">At once my wisdom, and my will I lose;</l>
					<l n="21">I'm conquer'd, and renounce the glorious train</l>
					<l n="22">Of arms, and war, to sing of love again:</l>
					<l n="23">My themes are acts, which I myself have done,</l>
					<l n="24">And my muse sings no battles but my own.</l>
					<l n="25">Once I confess I did the drama try,</l>
					<l n="26">And ventur'd with success on tragedy;</l>
					<l n="27">My genius with a moving scene agrees,</l>
					<l n="28">And if I ventured further I might please:</l>
					<l n="29">But love my heroics makes a jest,</l>
					<l n="30">And laughs to see me in my buskins drest.</l>
					<l n="31">Asham'd, and weary of this tragic whim,</l>
					<l n="32">For tender thoughts I quitted the sublime.</l>
					<l n="33">My mind my mistress bends another way,</l>
					<l n="34">Her must my muse in all her songs obey;</l>
					<l n="35">Though oft I do not what I write approve,</l>
					<l n="36">Like, or not like it, I must sing of love.</l>
					<l n="37">Whether for <placeName key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>'s illustrious
						dame,</l>
					<l n="38">To great Ulysses I a letter frame,</l>
					<l n="39">Or for Oenone tender things indite,</l>
					<l n="40">Or soft complaints for injur'd Phillis write;</l>
					<l n="41">Whether fair Canace's incestuous care</l>
					<l n="42">I sooth, or flatter Dido's fierce despair;</l>
					<l n="43">Whether I fan Medea's raging fire,</l>
					<l n="44">Or for sweet Sappho touch the Lesbian lyre;</l>
					<l n="45">Whether I Phaedra's lawless love relate,</l>
					<l n="46">Or Theseus' flight and Ariadne's fate:</l>
					<l n="47">Oh, that Sabinus, my departed friend,</l>
					<l n="48">Could from all quarters now his answers send!</l>
					<l n="49">Ulysses' hand should to his queen be known,</l>
					<l n="50">And wretched Phaedra hear from Theseus' son;</l>
					<l n="51">Dido Aeneas' answer should receive,</l>
					<l n="52">And Phillis Demophoon's, if alive;</l>
					<l n="53">Jason should to Hypsipyle return</l>
					<l n="54">A sad reply, and Sappho cease to mourn:</l>
					<l n="55">Nor him whom she can ne'er possess, desire,</l>
					<l n="56">But give to Phoebus fane her votive lyre.</l>
					<l n="57">As much as you in lofty epics deal,</l>
					<l n="58">You, Macer, show that you love's passion feel,</l>
					<l n="59">And sensible of beauty's powerful charm,</l>
					<l n="60">You hear their call amid the noise of arms.</l>
					<l n="61">A place for <placeName key="tgn,7008038">Paris</placeName> in your verse we
						find,</l>
					<l n="62">And Helen's to the young adult'rer kind;</l>
					<l n="63">There lovely Laodamia mourns her lord,</l>
					<l n="64">The first that fell by <placeName key="tgn,2069653">Hector</placeName>'s
						fatal sword.</l>
					<l n="65">If well I know you, and your mind can tell,</l>
					<l n="66">The theme's as grateful, and you like as well</l>
					<l n="67">To tune your lyre for Cupid as for <placeName key="tgn,2090583">Mars</placeName>,</l>
					<l n="68">And Thracian combats change for Paphian wars;</l>
					<l n="69">If well I know you, and your works design</l>
					<l n="70">Your will, you often quit your camp for mine. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="19">
					<head>Elegy XIX: By Dryden.</head>
					<l n="1">If for thyself thou wilt not watch thy whore,</l>
					<l n="2">Watch her for me that I may love her more.</l>
					<l n="3">What comes with ease we nauseously receive,</l>
					<l n="4">Who but a sot would scorn to love with leave?</l>
					<l n="5">With hopes and fears my flames are blown up higher;</l>
					<l n="6">Make me despair, and then I can desire.</l>
					<l n="7">Give me a jilt to tease my jealous mind;</l>
					<l n="8">Deceits are virtues in the female kind.</l>
					<l n="9"><placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> my fantastic humour
						knew,</l>
					<l n="10">Play'd trick for trick, and kept herself still new;</l>
					<l n="11">She, that next night I might the sharper come,</l>
					<l n="12">Fell out with me, and sent me fasting home.</l>
					<l n="13">Or some pretence to lie alone would take ;</l>
					<l n="14">Whene'er she pleas'd her head and teeth would ache:</l>
					<l n="15">Till having won me to the highest strain,</l>
					<l n="16">She took occasion to be sweet again.</l>
					<l n="17">With what a gust, ye gods, we then embrac'd!</l>
					<l n="18">How ev'ry kiss was dearer than the last!</l>
					<l n="19">Thou whom I now adore, be edified,</l>
					<l n="20">Take care that I may often be denied;</l>
					<l n="21">Forget the promis'd hour, or feign some fright,</l>
					<l n="22">Make me lie rough on bulks each other night.</l>
					<l n="23">These are the arts that best secure thy reign,</l>
					<l n="24">And this the food that must my fires maintain.</l>
					<l n="25">Gross easy love does, like gross diet, pall;</l>
					<l n="26">In squeasy stomachs honey turns to gall.</l>
					<l n="27">Had Danae not been kept in brazen tow'rs,</l>
					<l n="28">Jove had not thought her worth his golden show'rs:</l>
					<l n="29">When <placeName key="tgn,2075297">Juno</placeName> to a cow turn'd Io's
						shape,</l>
					<l n="30">The watchman help'd her to a second leap.</l>
					<l n="31">Let him who loves an easy whetstone whore,</l>
					<l n="32">Pluck leaves from trees, and drink the common shore.</l>
					<l n="33">The jilting harlot strikes the surest blow,</l>
					<l n="34">A truth which I by sad experience know;</l>
					<l n="35">The kind, poor, constant creature we despise,</l>
					<l n="36">Man but pursues the quarry while it flies.</l>
					<l n="37">But thou dull husband of a wife too fair,</l>
					<l n="38">Stand on thy guard, and watch the precious ware;</l>
					<l n="39">If creaking doors, or barking dogs, thou hear,</l>
					<l n="40">Or windows scratch'd, suspect a rival there.</l>
					<l n="41">An orange wench would tempt thy wife abroad;</l>
					<l n="42">Kick her, for she's a letter-bearing bawd.</l>
					<l n="43">In short, be jealous as the devil in hell,</l>
					<l n="44">And set my wit on work to cheat thee well.</l>
					<l n="45">The sneaking city-cuckold is my foe;</l>
					<l n="46">I scorn to strike but when he wards the blow.</l>
					<l n="47">Look to thy hits and leave off thy conniving,</l>
					<l n="48">I'll be no drudge to any wittol living;</l>
					<l n="49">I have been patient, and forborne thee long,</l>
					<l n="50">In hope thou wouldst not pocket up thy wrong:</l>
					<l n="51">If no affront can rouse thee, understand</l>
					<l n="52">I'll take no more indulgence at thy hand.</l>
					<l n="53">What, ne'er to be forbid thy house and wife</l>
					<l n="54">Damn him who loves to lead so ill a life.</l>
					<l n="55">Now I can neither sigh, nor whine, nor pray;</l>
					<l n="56">All those occasions thou hast ta'en away.</l>
					<l n="57">Why art thou so incorrigibly civil ?</l>
					<l n="58">Do somewhat I may wish thee at the devil</l>
					<l n="59">For shame, be no accomplice in my treason;</l>
					<l n="60">A pimping husband is too much in reason.</l>
					<l n="61">Once more wear horns, before I quite forsake her</l>
					<l n="62">In hopes whereof, I rest thy cuckold-maker. </l>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="1">
					<head>Elegy I: The Poet deliberates with himself whether he should continue
						writing elegies, or attempt tragedy.</head>
					<l n="1">Unhurt by steel, arose an ancient wood,</l>
					<l n="2">A mansion fit for some retiring god;</l>
					<l n="3">With craggy stones a secret grot was hung,</l>
					<l n="4">And in the midst a sacred fountain sprung;</l>
					<l n="5">The courting birds repeating songs of love,</l>
					<l n="6">With soft complainings sweetly fill'd the grove:</l>
					<l n="7">Here wand'ring thoughtful, and intent to choose</l>
					<l n="8">Some theme unsung, to please the busy muse;</l>
					<l n="9">Fair elegy came on with gentle pace,</l>
					<l n="10">Unforc'd her air and easy was her grace.</l>
					<l n="11">Her flaxen hair, in curious tresses wreath'd,</l>
					<l n="12">Ambrosial sweets and heav'nly odours breath'd;</l>
					<l n="13">A simple dress the careless charmer bore,</l>
					<l n="14">And loving looks, and smiles unartful wore.</l>
					<l n="15">Next came the goddess of the tragic scene,</l>
					<l n="16">With stately tread, and proud majestic mien</l>
					<l n="17">Her front severe, with hanging curls was drown'd,</l>
					<l n="18">Her length of robe was full, and swept the ground:</l>
					<l n="19">Her hand held out, a regal sceptre grac'd,</l>
					<l n="20">And Lydian buskins half her legs embrac'd.</l>
					<l n="21">She first; "Must love for ever tune thy voice,</l>
					<l n="22">Fond idle bard, and trifling in thy choice</l>
					<l n="23">Thy wanton songs employ the drunkard's tongue,</l>
					<l n="24">In ev'ry street thy ribald lays are sung;</l>
					<l n="25">The finger marks thee in thy passing by,</l>
					<l n="26">'Behold, where goes the slave of love,' they cry.</l>
					<l n="27">Thy lewd exploits, thou profligate, are grown</l>
					<l n="28">The public theme, and talk of all the town;</l>
					<l n="29">Whilst unconcern'd, and lost to sense of shame,</l>
					<l n="30">Thou still runn'st on nor mind'st thy ruin'd fame.</l>
					<l n="31">Enough thou'st told the plaints of fond desire,</l>
					<l n="32">Now let a nobler inspiration fire;</l>
					<l n="33">Thy matter cramps thy genius, learn to find</l>
					<l n="34">A manly subject, and exert thy mind.</l>
					<l n="35">In songs for girls, fond toys, and idle play,</l>
					<l n="36">Thy muse has wanton'd all her hours away.</l>
					<l n="37">But youth at length has fill'd its measure up;</l>
					<l n="38">My friend, 'tis time to taste of t'other cup.</l>
					<l n="39">Now in my service let thy force be shown,</l>
					<l n="40">Assert my honour, and retrieve thy own;</l>
					<l n="41">Thy sprightly fancy, and inventive wit,</l>
					<l n="42">The lofty style of tragic scenes will fit."</l>
					<l n="43">She said; and proudly rising in her gait,</l>
					<l n="44">Thrice shook her tresses, and display'd her state.</l>
					<l n="45">With open look (nor was my sight beguil'd)</l>
					<l n="46">And joyous eyes her rival sweetly smil'd;</l>
					<l n="47">Sustain'd her hand a myrtle branch upright?</l>
					<l n="48">Or did my fancy form the charming sight?</l>
					<l n="49">"Still so severe, 0, tragedy ! (she cried);</l>
					<l n="50">And canst thou ne'er forego thy sullen pride?</l>
					<l n="51">I not compare my lowly lays to thine;</l>
					<l n="52">Too weak materials for the vast design.</l>
					<l n="53">The style unlabour'd, negligent the dress,</l>
					<l n="54">My verse is humbler, and my matter less.</l>
					<l n="55">Gay, wanton, soft, my business is to move,</l>
					<l n="56">With melting strains, the playful god of love.</l>
					<l n="57">Bereft of me, fair <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName> wants her
						charms,</l>
					<l n="58">I help the goddess, and prepare her arms.</l>
					<l n="59">My luring art, and soothing lays prevail,</l>
					<l n="60">Where lofty port, and tragic buskins fail.</l>
					<l n="61">I more deserve, by making that my care,</l>
					<l n="62">Thy rigid pride allows not thee to bear:</l>
					<l n="63">By me, <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> first was taught to
						try</l>
					<l n="64">Tobreak from prison, and deceive the spy;</l>
					<l n="65">I first induc'd the fearful fair to slide</l>
					<l n="66">With tremb'ling caution from her husband's side;</l>
					<l n="67">When to thy arms, all loose, and disarray'd,</l>
					<l n="68">Prepar'd for pleasure, flew the melting maid.</l>
					<l n="69">Fix'd on her door, how oft I've hung on high,</l>
					<l n="70">Expos'd, and patient of each gazing eye !</l>
					<l n="71">How oft, in secret, while the keeper stay'd,</l>
					<l n="72">Within her woman's panting bosom laid !</l>
					<l n="73">Once sent a birthday gift, the cruel dame</l>
					<l n="74">In pieces tore, and gave me to the flame.</l>
					<l n="75">I taught thee first to cultivate thy mind;</l>
					<l n="76">Thy fancy brightened, and thy wit refin'd;</l>
					<l n="77">Thou to my care those merits must allow,</l>
					<l n="78">For which my rival would seduce thee now;"</l>
					<l n="79">They spoke. I answer'd, "Let me both conjure</l>
					<l n="80">To spare a mind with terrors unsecure;</l>
					<l n="81">Nor to my charge, when once pronounc'd, be laid</l>
					<l n="82">As crimes, the words my trembling tongue has said.</l>
					<l n="83">To gain me glory, thy decrees ordain</l>
					<l n="84">The regal sceptre and the tragic strain;</l>
					<l n="85">With painful labour need I toil for fame,</l>
					<l n="86">When easier tasks already raise my name?</l>
					<l n="87">Thou mak'st my love immortal; thee I choose:</l>
					<l n="88">Be thou my queen, and still command my muse.</l>
					<l n="89">Majestic pow'r, forgive my simple choice,</l>
					<l n="90">Thy gentle rival has obtain'd my voice.</l>
					<l n="91">Short is the time in which her palm is won;</l>
					<l n="92">Ere thine is gain'd, the poet's life is done."</l>
					<l n="93">I lowly said: she gracious gave assent,</l>
					<l n="94">And diff'rent ways the parting rivals went.</l>
					<l n="95">Ye gentle loves, complete the work assign'd,</l>
					<l n="96">A greater labour seems to press behind. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="2">
					<head>Elegy II: To his Mistress at the horse-race. By Henry Cromwell.</head>
					<l n="1">Not in the Circus do I sit to view</l>
					<l n="2">The running horses, but to gaze on you;</l>
					<l n="3">Near you I choose an advantageous place,</l>
					<l n="4">And whilst your eyes are fix'd upon the race,</l>
					<l n="5">Mine are on you -- Thus do we feast our sight,</l>
					<l n="6">Each alike pleas'd with objects of delight;</l>
					<l n="7">In softer whispers I my passion move,</l>
					<l n="8">You of the rider talk, but I of love.</l>
					<l n="9">When, to please you, I straight my subject quit</l>
					<l n="10">And change my wishes to your favourite;</l>
					<l n="11">Oh. might I ride, and be so much your care,</l>
					<l n="12">I'd start with courage from the barrier,</l>
					<l n="13">And with a swift short compass brush the goal --</l>
					<l n="14">Unless the sight of you my course restrains,</l>
					<l n="15">And makes my hands forego the loosen'd reins;</l>
					<l n="16">As Pelops gaz'd on Hippodamia's face,</l>
					<l n="17">Till he had almost lost th' important race;</l>
					<l n="18">Yet he his mistress by her favour won;</l>
					<l n="19">So may our prize assist us when we run.</l>
					<l n="20">"What mean these starts? you must not, can't remove:</l>
					<l n="21">This kind auspicious place was fram d for love.</l>
					<l n="22">I fear you're crowded,- Gentlemen, forbear,</l>
					<l n="23">Pray let your arms and knees the lady spare;</l>
					<l n="24">Madam, your gown hangs down-nay, pray let me --</l>
					<l n="25">Oh heav'ns ! what fine, what curious legs I see!</l>
					<l n="26">Sure, who <placeName key="tgn,2118015">Diana</placeName> in a forest
						drew,</l>
					<l n="27">Copied in this the graceful'st parts from you;</l>
					<l n="28">Such Atalant discovering as she ran,</l>
					<l n="29">What rapt'rous wishes seiz'd Menalion</l>
					<l n="30">I burn'd and rag'd before -- what then are these,</l>
					<l n="31">But flames on flames, and waters to the seas?</l>
					<l n="32">By these a thousand other charms are guess'd,</l>
					<l n="33">Which are so advantageously suppress'd.</l>
					<l n="34">Oh for some air! this scorching heat remove,</l>
					<l n="35">Your fan would do't, but 'tis the heat of love."</l>
					<l n="36">But now the pomp appears, the sacred throng</l>
					<l n="37">Command applauses from the heart and tongue;</l>
					<l n="38">First victory with expanded wings does move,</l>
					<l n="39">Be near, O Goddess ! to assist my love;</l>
					<l n="40">To <placeName key="tgn,2090583">Mars</placeName> let warriors acclamations
						raise,</l>
					<l n="41">The merchants' tongues resound with <placeName key="tgn,2065549">Neptune</placeName>'s praise;</l>
					<l n="42">Whilst I, whom neither seas nor arms invite,</l>
					<l n="43">In love alone, the fruit of peace, delight;</l>
					<l n="44">To their Apollo let the prophets pray,</l>
					<l n="45">And hunters to <placeName key="tgn,2118015">Diana</placeName> homage pay.</l>
					<l n="46">Let the mechanics to <placeName key="tgn,2080793">Minerva</placeName>
						vow,</l>
					<l n="47">Rustics to <placeName key="tgn,2068435">Ceres</placeName>, and to <placeName key="tgn,2097807">Bacchus</placeName> bow;</l>
					<l n="48">Whilst I devote myself to thee alone,</l>
					<l n="49">Kind <placeName key="tgn,2094077">Venus</placeName>, and the pow'rful god thy
						son;</l>
					<l n="50">0 be propitious to my enterprize,</l>
					<l n="51">Inform with all thy softness these fair eyes,</l>
					<l n="52">And to love's cause her gentle breast incline;</l>
					<l n="53">She grants, and has contriv'd it with a sign;</l>
					<l n="54">Do you assure it too, you who're to me</l>
					<l n="55">(With Venus' leave) the mightier deity,</l>
					<l n="56">By all these heavenly witnesses' to you</l>
					<l n="57">Will I be ever faithful, ever true.</l>
					<l n="58">Now ib the open cirque the game's begun,</l>
					<l n="59">The praetor gives the signal, now they run;</l>
					<l n="60">I see which way your wishes are inclin'd,</l>
					<l n="61">To him a certain conquest is design'd;</l>
					<l n="62">For e'en the horses seem to know your mind.</l>
					<l n="63">He takes too large a compass to come in,</l>
					<l n="64">And lets his adversary get between;</l>
					<l n="65">Recall him, Romans, for a second heat,</l>
					<l n="66">And clear the course --</l>
					<l n="67">Now see your ground you better do maintain,</l>
					<l n="68">This lady's favour, and your fame regain;</l>
					<l n="69">The prize is his.-As yours successful prove,</l>
					<l n="70">So let my wishes, which are all for love;</l>
					<l n="71">I'm yet to conquer, and your heart's the prize;</l>
					<l n="72">Something she promis'd with her sparkling eyes,</l>
					<l n="73">And smil'd ;-" Enough," did I transported cry,</l>
					<l n="74">"The rest I leave to opportunity." </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="3">
					<head>Elegy III: Of His Perjured Mistress. By Henry Cromwell.</head>
					<l n="1">Can there be gods ?-has she not falsely swore?</l>
					<l n="2">Yet is the beauty that she was before!</l>
					<l n="3">The curious tresses of her dangling hair,</l>
					<l n="4">As long, and graceful still as e'er they were;</l>
					<l n="5">That same inimitable white and red,</l>
					<l n="6">Which o'er her face was so distinctly spread,</l>
					<l n="7">The roses, and the lilies keep their place,</l>
					<l n="8">And ev'ry feature still as justly grace;</l>
					<l n="9">Her sparkling eyes their lustre still retain,</l>
					<l n="10">That form, that perfect shape does still remain,</l>
					<l n="11">As if she ne'er had sinn'd ; and heav'n, ('tis plain)</l>
					<l n="12">Suff'ring the fairer sex to break their vows,</l>
					<l n="13">To the superior pow'r of beauty bows.</l>
					<l n="14">T' inforce my credit to her perjuries,</l>
					<l n="15">Oft would she swear by those persuasive eyes;</l>
					<l n="16">As if that charm had been too weak to move,</l>
					<l n="17">Sh'as added mine;-tell me, ye pow'rs above,</l>
					<l n="18">Why all this pain ? why are these guiltless eyes</l>
					<l n="19">For her offence th' atoning sacrifice ?</l>
					<l n="20">Was't not enough Andromeda has died,</l>
					<l n="21">An expiation for her mother's pride ?</l>
					<l n="22">Is't not enough, that unconcern'd you see</l>
					<l n="23">(Vain witnesses for truth, for faith, for me,)</l>
					<l n="24">Such an affront put on divinity,</l>
					<l n="25">Yet no revenge the daring crime pursue,</l>
					<l n="26">But the deceiv'd must be her victim too?</l>
					<l n="27">Either the gods are empty notions, crept</l>
					<l n="28">Into the minds of sleepers as they slept,</l>
					<l n="29">In vain are fear'd, are but the tricks of law,</l>
					<l n="30">To keep the foolish cred'lous world in awe;</l>
					<l n="31">Or, if there be a god, he loves the fair,</l>
					<l n="32">And all things at their sole disposal are.</l>
					<l n="33">For us are all the instruments of war</l>
					<l n="34">Design'd, the sword of <placeName key="tgn,2090583">Mars</placeName>, and
							<placeName key="tgn,2565867">Pallas</placeName>' spear;</l>
					<l n="35">'Gainst us alone Apollo's bows are bent,</l>
					<l n="36">And at our hands Jove's brandish'd thunder sent.</l>
					<l n="37">Yet of the ladies, oh ! how fond are they !</l>
					<l n="38">Dare not the inj'ries they receive, repay,</l>
					<l n="39">But those who ought to fear them they obey.</l>
					<l n="40">Jove to his votaries is most severe;</l>
					<l n="41">Temples nor altars does his lightning spare.</l>
					<l n="42">Obliging Semele in flames expires,</l>
					<l n="43">But those who merit, can escape the fires.</l>
					<l n="44">Is this the justice of your pow'rs divine?</l>
					<l n="45">Who then will offer incense at a shrine ?</l>
					<l n="46">Why do we thus reproach the deities ?</l>
					<l n="47">Have they not hearts ?-and surely they have eyes,</l>
					<l n="48">Nay, had I been a god, I had believ'd</l>
					<l n="49">The lovely criminals, and been deceiv'd;</l>
					<l n="50">Had wav'd the judgments to their perj'ries due,</l>
					<l n="51">And sworn myself that all they spoke was true.</l>
					<l n="52">Since then the gods such ample gifts bestow,</l>
					<l n="53">As make you absolute o'er men below;</l>
					<l n="54">Pray let me find some mercy in your reign,</l>
					<l n="55">Or spare at least your lover's eyes from pain. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="4">
					<head>Elegy IV: To a man that locked up his wife. By Sir Charles Sedley</head>
					<l n="1">Vex not thyself and her, vain man, since all</l>
					<l n="2">By their own vice or virtue stand or fall.</l>
					<l n="3">She's truly chaste, and worthy of that name,</l>
					<l n="4">Who hates the ill, as well as fears the shame;</l>
					<l n="5">And that vile woman whom restraint keeps in,</l>
					<l n="6">Tho' she forbear the act, has done the sin.</l>
					<l n="7">Spies, locks, and bolts may keep her brutal part,</l>
					<l n="8">But thou'rt an odious cuckold in her heart.</l>
					<l n="9">They that have freedom use it least, and so</l>
					<l n="10">The power of ill does the design overthrow.</l>
					<l n="11">Provoke not vice by a too harsh restraint;</l>
					<l n="12">Sick men long most to drink, who know they mayn't.</l>
					<l n="13">The fiery courser, whom no art can stay,</l>
					<l n="14">Or rugged force, does oft fair means obey;</l>
					<l n="15">And he that did the rudest arm disdain,</l>
					<l n="16">Submits with quiet to the looser rein.</l>
					<l n="17">A hundred eyes had <placeName key="tgn,2086061">Argus</placeName>, yet the
						while</l>
					<l n="18">One silly maid did all those eyes beguile;</l>
					<l n="19">Danae, tho' shut within a brazen tow'r,</l>
					<l n="20">Felt the male virtue of the golden show'r;</l>
					<l n="21">But chaste Penelope, left to her own will</l>
					<l n="22">And free disposal, never thought of ill;</l>
					<l n="23">She to her absent lord preserv'd her truth,</l>
					<l n="24">For all th' addresses of the smoother youth,</l>
					<l n="25">What's rarely seen, our fancy magnifies;</l>
					<l n="26">Permitted pleasure who does not despise ?</l>
					<l n="27">Thy care provokes beyond her face, and more</l>
					<l n="28">Men strive to make tho cuckold than the whore.</l>
					<l n="29">They're wondrous charms we think, and long to know</l>
					<l n="30">That in a wife enchants a husband so:</l>
					<l n="31">Rage, swear, and curse, no matter, she alone</l>
					<l n="32">Pleases, who sighs, and cries, " I am undone."</l>
					<l n="33">But could thy spies say, " We have kept her chaste,"</l>
					<l n="34">Good servants then, but an ill wife thou hast;</l>
					<l n="35">Who fears to be a cuckold is a clown,</l>
					<l n="36">Not worthy to partake of this lewd town,</l>
					<l n="37">Where it is monstrous to be fair and chaste,</l>
					<l n="38">And not one inch of either sex lies waste.</l>
					<l n="39">Wouldst thou be happy ? with her ways comply,</l>
					<l n="40">And in her case lay points of honour by:</l>
					<l n="41">The friendship she begins, wisely improve,</l>
					<l n="42">And a fair wife gets one a world of love:</l>
					<l n="43">So shalt thou welcome be to ev'ry treat,</l>
					<l n="44">Live high, not pay, and never run in debt. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="5">
					<head>Elegy V: The Dream. By Henry Cromwell.</head>
					<l n="1">'Twas in the midst and silent dead of night,</l>
					<l n="2">When heavy sleep oppos'd my weary sight,</l>
					<l n="3">This vision did my troubled mind affright:-</l>
					<l n="4">To Sol expos'd there stood a rising ground,</l>
					<l n="5">Which cast beneath a spacious shade around;</l>
					<l n="6">A gloomy grove of spreading oaks below,</l>
					<l n="7">And various birds were perch'd on ev'ry bough;</l>
					<l n="8">Just on the margin of a verdant mead,</l>
					<l n="9">Where murm'ring brooks refreshing waters spread</l>
					<l n="10">To shun the heat I sought this cool recess,</l>
					<l n="11">But in this shade I felt my heat no less;</l>
					<l n="12">When browzing o'er the flow'ry grass appear'd</l>
					<l n="13">A lovely cow, the fairest of the herd.</l>
					<l n="14">By spotless white distinguished from the rest,</l>
					<l n="15">Whiter than milk from her own udder press'd;</l>
					<l n="16">Whiter than falling, or the driven snow,</l>
					<l n="17">Before descending mists can make it flow.</l>
					<l n="18">She, with a lusty bull, her happy mate,</l>
					<l n="19">Delighted, on the tender herbage sat;</l>
					<l n="20">There, as he crops the flow'rs, and chews the cud,</l>
					<l n="21">Feasting a second time upon his food,</l>
					<l n="22">His limbs with sudden heaviness oppress'd,</l>
					<l n="23">He bends his head, and sinks to pleasing rest.</l>
					<l n="24">A noisy crow, cleaving the liquid air,</l>
					<l n="25">Thrice with lewd bill pick'd off the heifer's hair;</l>
					<l n="26">The glossy white imbib'd a spreading blot,</l>
					<l n="27">But on her breast appear'd a livid spot.</l>
					<l n="28">The cow rose slowly from her consort's side,</l>
					<l n="29">But when afar the grazing bull she spied,</l>
					<l n="30">Frisk'd to the herd, with an impetuous haste,</l>
					<l n="31">And pleas'd, in new luxuriant soil, her taste.</l>
					<l n="32">Oh, learn'd diviner!</l>
					<l n="33">What may this visionary dream portend,</l>
					<l n="34">If dreams in any future truth can end ?</l>
					<l n="35">The prophet nicely weighs what I relate,</l>
					<l n="36">And thus denounces in the voice of fate:-</l>
					<l n="37">"That heat you tried to shun i' th' shady grove,</l>
					<l n="38">But shunn'd in vain, was the fierce heat of love.</l>
					<l n="39">The cow denotes the nymph, your only care,</l>
					<l n="40">(For white's th' expressive image of the fair,)</l>
					<l n="41">And you the bull, abandon'd to despair.</l>
					<l n="42">The picking crow some busy bawd implies,</l>
					<l n="43">Who with base arts will soon seduce your prim.</l>
					<l n="44">You saw the cow to fresher pasture range,</l>
					<l n="45">So will your nymph for richer lovers change;</l>
					<l n="46">As mixing with the herd you saw her rove,</l>
					<l n="47">So will the fair pursue promiscuous love;</l>
					<l n="48">Soon will you find a foul incestuous blot,</l>
					<l n="49">As on the cow you view'd the livid spot."</l>
					<l n="50">At this my blood retired, with dismal fright,</l>
					<l n="51">And left me pale as death ; my fainting sight</l>
					<l n="52">Was quite o'ercast in dusky shades of night. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="6">
					<head>Elegy VI: To a River, as he was going to his mistress. By Rhymer.</head>
					<l n="1">Thy course, thy noble course a while forbear,</l>
					<l n="2">I am in haste now going to my dear!</l>
					<l n="3">Thy banks how rich, thy stream how worthy praise</l>
					<l n="4">Alas, my haste ! sweet river, let me pass.</l>
					<l n="5">No bridges here, no ferry, not an oar,</l>
					<l n="6">Or rope to haul me to the farther shore !</l>
					<l n="7">I have remember'd thee a little one,</l>
					<l n="8">Who now with all this flood com'st blund'ring down.</l>
					<l n="9">Did I refuse my sleep, my wine, my friend,</l>
					<l n="10">To spur along, and must I here attend ?</l>
					<l n="11">No art to help me to my journey's end!</l>
					<l n="12">Ye Lapland powers, make me so far a witch,</l>
					<l n="13">I may astride get over on a switch.</l>
					<l n="14">Or, for some griffin, or that flying horse,</l>
					<l n="15">Or any monster to assist my course;</l>
					<l n="16">I wish his art that mounted to the moon,</l>
					<l n="17">In shorter journey would my job be done.</l>
					<l n="18">Why rave I for what crack-brain'd bards devise,</l>
					<l n="19">Or name their lewd unconscionable lies ?</l>
					<l n="20">Good river, let me find thy courtesy,</l>
					<l n="21">Keep within bounds, and mayst thou ne'er be dry.</l>
					<l n="22">Thou canst not think it such a mighty boast,</l>
					<l n="23">A torrent has a gentle lover cross'd.</l>
					<l n="24">Rivers should rather take the lover's side,</l>
					<l n="25">Rivers themselves love's wondrous power have tried.</l>
					<l n="26">'Twas on this score Inachus, pale and wan,</l>
					<l n="27">Sickly and green, into the ocean ran ;</l>
					<l n="28">Long before <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName> the ten-years siege
						did fear,</l>
					<l n="29">Thou, <placeName key="tgn,7002633">Xanthus</placeName>, thou Neaera's chains
						didst wear;</l>
					<l n="30">Ask Achelous who his horns did drub,</l>
					<l n="31">Straight he complains of <placeName key="tgn,2086286">Hercules</placeName>'s
						club.</l>
					<l n="32">For Calydon, for all <placeName key="tgn,7002678">Aetolia</placeName></l>
					<l n="33">Was then contested such outrageous fray!</l>
					<l n="34">It neither was for gold, nor yet for fee;</l>
					<l n="35">Dejanira, it was all for thee.</l>
					<l n="36">E'en Nile so rich, that rolls thro' sev'n wide doors,</l>
					<l n="37">And uppish over all his country scours,</l>
					<l n="38">For Asop's daughter did such flame contract,</l>
					<l n="39">As not by all that stock of water slack'd.</l>
					<l n="40">I might a hundred goodly rivers name,</l>
					<l n="41">But must not pass by thee, immortal <placeName key="tgn,7011951">Thame</placeName>;</l>
					<l n="42">Ere thou couldst Isis to thy bosom take.</l>
					<l n="43">How didst thou wind and wander for her sake!</l>
					<l n="44">The lusty ---- with broad <placeName key="tgn,1124748">Humber</placeName>
						strove;</l>
					<l n="45">Was it for fame ? I say it was for love.</l>
					<l n="46">What makes the noble <placeName key="tgn,1128249">Ouse</placeName> up from
						the main</l>
					<l n="47">With hideous roar come bristling back again ?</l>
					<l n="48">He thinks his dearest Dervent left behind,</l>
					<l n="49">Or fears her false, in new embraces joined.</l>
					<l n="50">Thee also some small girl has warm'd, we guess,</l>
					<l n="51">Tho' woods and forests now hide thy soft place.</l>
					<l n="52">Whilst this I speak, it swells and broader grows,</l>
					<l n="53">And o'er the highest banks impetuous flows.</l>
					<l n="54">Dog-flood, what art to me ? or why dost check</l>
					<l n="55">Our mutual joys ? and, churl, my journey break ?</l>
					<l n="56">What wouldst, if thee indeed some noble race,</l>
					<l n="57">Or high descent, and glorious name did grace ?</l>
					<l n="58">When of no ancient house or certain seat,</l>
					<l n="59">(Nor, known before this time, untimely, great)</l>
					<l n="60">Rais'd by some sudden thaw thus high and proud,</l>
					<l n="61">No holding thee, ill-manner'd upstart flood ;</l>
					<l n="62">Not my love-tales can make thee stay thy course,</l>
					<l n="63">Thou--zounds, thou art a -- river for a horse.</l>
					<l n="64">Thou hadst no fountain, but from bears wert pist,</l>
					<l n="65">From snows, and thaws, or Scotch unsav'ry mist.</l>
					<l n="66">Thou crawl'st along, in winter foul and poor,</l>
					<l n="67">In summer puddled like a common-shore.</l>
					<l n="68">In all thy days when didst a courtesy ?</l>
					<l n="69">Dry traveller ne'er laid a lip to thee.</l>
					<l n="70">The bane to cattle, to the meadows worse,</l>
					<l n="71">For something all, I for my sufferings curse.</l>
					<l n="72">To such unworthy wretch, how am I sham'd,</l>
					<l n="73">That I the gen'rous am'rous river nam'd!</l>
					<l n="74">When <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> and Achelous I
						display'd,</l>
					<l n="75">And <placeName key="tgn,7011951">Thame</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1128249">Ouse</placeName>, what worm was in my head</l>
					<l n="76">For thy reward, discourteous river, I</l>
					<l n="77">Wish, be the summers hot, the winters dry. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="7">
					<head>Elegy VII: Ovid laments his imperfect enjoyments. By an unknown
						hand.</head>
					<l n="1">Was she not heavenly fair, and rich attir'd ?</l>
					<l n="2">Was she not that which all my soul desir'd ?</l>
					<l n="3">Yet were these arms around her idly spread,</l>
					<l n="4">And with an useless load I press'd the bed.</l>
					<l n="5">E'en to my wishes was the power denied,</l>
					<l n="6">When with my wishes the kind nymph complied</l>
					<l n="7">I lay without life's animated spring,</l>
					<l n="8">A dull, enervate, worthless, lumpish thing.</l>
					<l n="9">My neck she folded with a soft embrace,</l>
					<l n="10">Now kissed my eyes, now wanton'd o'er my face,</l>
					<l n="11">Now lov'd to dart her humid tongue to mine,</l>
					<l n="12">Now would her pliant limbs around me twine,</l>
					<l n="13">And sooth, by thousand ways, the sweet design.</l>
					<l n="14">The moving blandishments of sound she tried,</l>
					<l n="15">And, " My dear life, my soul, my all," she cried.</l>
					<l n="16">In vain, alas ! the nerves are slacken'd still,</l>
					<l n="17">And I prov'd only potent in my will;</l>
					<l n="18">A poor inactive sign of man I made,</l>
					<l n="19">And might as well for use have been a shade.</l>
					<l n="20">If old I live, how shall I old prevail,</l>
					<l n="21">When in my youth I thus inglorious fail?</l>
					<l n="22">The bloom of years becomes my shameful moan,</l>
					<l n="23">Now in full growth the ripen'd man is shown,</l>
					<l n="24">But not the strength of man to her was known.</l>
					<l n="25">Untouched by brothers, sisters thus retire,</l>
					<l n="26">Or vestals rise to watch th' eternal fire;</l>
					<l n="27">Yet many a nymph whom I forbear to name,</l>
					<l n="28">Rave kindly yielded, and indulg'd my flame</l>
					<l n="29">Nor could the vigour of their 0vid blame.</l>
					<l n="30">Corinna knows when numb'ring the delight,</l>
					<l n="31">Not less than nine full transports crown'd the night.</l>
					<l n="32">Is verse or herbs the source of present harms ?</l>
					<l n="33">Am I a captive to Thessalian charms ?</l>
					<l n="34">Has some enchantress this confusion brought,</l>
					<l n="35">And in soft wax my tortur'd image wrought</l>
					<l n="36">Deep in the liver is the needle fix'd ?</l>
					<l n="37">Plagues she by numbers, or by juices mix'd?</l>
					<l n="38">By numbers sudden the ripe harvest die,</l>
					<l n="39">And fruitful urns no more their streams supply;</l>
					<l n="40">Oaks shed, unshook, their acorns at the call,</l>
					<l n="41">And the vine wonders why her clusters fall.</l>
					<l n="42">Why may not magic act on me the same,</l>
					<l n="43">Unstring the nerves, and quite untune the frame!</l>
					<l n="44">Gall'd at the heart, and longing to perform,</l>
					<l n="45">I rais'd indeed, but rais'd an empty storm;</l>
					<l n="46">Most disappointed when the most propense,</l>
					<l n="47">And shame was second cause of impotence.</l>
					<l n="48">What limbs I touch'd ! and only touch'd ! oh, fie!</l>
					<l n="49">Where was the blissful touch ? her shift can vie</l>
					<l n="50">In feasts like these, and touch as well as I.</l>
					<l n="51">Yet to touch her e'en Nestor might grow young,</l>
					<l n="52">And centuries, like twenty-one, be strung.</l>
					<l n="53">Such was the maid; the parallel had ran</l>
					<l n="54">Graceful, if I could add, such was the man.</l>
					<l n="55">Some envious deity with vengeance glow'd,</l>
					<l n="56">So sweet a gift had been so ill bestow'd.</l>
					<l n="57">I burn to clasp her naked in my arms,</l>
					<l n="58">Did she not freely open all her charms ?</l>
					<l n="59">What boots good fortune, if we want the pow'r</l>
					<l n="60">To snatch the pleasures of the favour'd hour?</l>
					<l n="61">I, like a miser, only could behold,</l>
					<l n="62">And brooded o'er an useless mine of gold;</l>
					<l n="63">So Tantalus with fruit untouch'd is curst,</l>
					<l n="64">And dies amid the gliding stream of thirst;</l>
					<l n="65">So rises early from th' untasted fair,</l>
					<l n="66">The grave old prelate, and kneels down to pray'r,</l>
					<l n="67">Were yet her melting kisses misenploy'd?</l>
					<l n="68">Did she strive vainly to be well enjoy'd ?</l>
					<l n="69">Sure she has beauties might deaf rocks enchant,</l>
					<l n="70">Bend the proud oak, and soften adamant;</l>
					<l n="71">She would have mov'd a man tho' almost dead,</l>
					<l n="72">But with my manhood the whole life was fled.</l>
					<l n="73">If none should lend an ear, why is the song,</l>
					<l n="74">Or painted nymphs shown to a blinded throng !</l>
					<l n="75">Ye gods ! what joys did not my fancy raise !</l>
					<l n="76">I curl'd in folds of love a thousand ways.</l>
					<l n="77">Strong were my thoughts, but ah ! my body lay</l>
					<l n="78">Languid as roses pluck'd off yesterday.</l>
					<l n="79">Now all the blood the circling spirits fire,</l>
					<l n="80">And the lost field impertinent require;</l>
					<l n="81">Begone untimely nerves! I trust no more,</l>
					<l n="82">Such was the promise of your strength before.</l>
					<l n="83">Could you the fair one balk of her delight,</l>
					<l n="84">Disgrace your master by so base a fright,</l>
					<l n="85">And want the courage for so sweet a fight?</l>
					<l n="86">Did she not kindly too your stay demand,</l>
					<l n="87">And tempt it softly with a soothing hand ?</l>
					<l n="88">But when solicitings no life could gain,</l>
					<l n="89">And inspirations, tho' from her, were vain;</l>
					<l n="90">"Who bade thee thus thyself to me to bring !</l>
					<l n="91">Go for a silly unperforming thing:</l>
					<l n="92">Art thou a wretch by some curs'd spell destroy'd,</l>
					<l n="93">Or here com'st fribbling with past pleasure cloy'd?"</l>
					<l n="94">She spoke, and springing from the bed she flew,</l>
					<l n="95">And secret beauties so disclos'd to view;</l>
					<l n="96">Yet to conceal the joyless night's digrace,</l>
					<l n="97">She called for water with a smiling face,</l>
					<l n="98">And wash'd a nameless unpolluted place. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="8">
					<head>Elegy VIII: He complains that his mistress did not give him a favourable
						reception.</head>
					<l n="1">What coxcomb will in future times think fit</l>
					<l n="2">To build in love his fortune on his wit ?</l>
					<l n="3">Wealth now is worth, whatever 'twas of old,</l>
					<l n="4">And merit valu'd by its weight in gold.</l>
					<l n="5">With male and female, this is now the rule,</l>
					<l n="6">And he that's poor, of course must be a fool.</l>
					<l n="7">The dame to read my am'rous verse delights,</l>
					<l n="8">My writings likes, but scorns the man that writes;</l>
					<l n="9">They freely on her privacy presume,</l>
					<l n="10">And find admittance where I must not come;</l>
					<l n="11">Me when she does her haunted house exclude,</l>
					<l n="12">To them she's civil, as to me she's rude.</l>
					<l n="13">Me she exposes to a thousand harms,</l>
					<l n="14">To walk the streets, while they are in her arms.</l>
					<l n="15">For whom does she my passion disregard ?</l>
					<l n="16">And who has intercepted my reward ?</l>
					<l n="17">Why is the beau with so much joy embrac'd ?</l>
					<l n="18">His pockets full, it seems, his coat is lac'd:</l>
					<l n="19">He won her with his military air</l>
					<l n="20">Which cheats as often as it charms the fair.</l>
					<l n="21">Could she her longing eyes forbear to fix</l>
					<l n="22">On his fine feather, and his coach and six!</l>
					<l n="23">Enrich'd by plunder, he could never miss</l>
					<l n="24">The favour, who would buy the venal bliss.</l>
					<l n="25">No matter how he got his wealth, by war,</l>
					<l n="26">And blood: she cares not, if she has her share.</l>
					<l n="27">The upstart forward was, 'tis said, in fight,</l>
					<l n="28">And in the field of battle made a knight:</l>
					<l n="29">But had his honour come without his gold,</l>
					<l n="30">His, sure, had been like my reception, cold.</l>
					<l n="31">To men of merit how could she be coy,</l>
					<l n="32">Yet to a murd'rer prostitute the joy?</l>
					<l n="33">That head which lolls upon your panting breast,</l>
					<l n="34">Was lately cover'd with a plumy crest.</l>
					<l n="35">Can you the bully to your bed admit ?</l>
					<l n="36">Are his hard limbs for ladies' dalliance fit ?</l>
					<l n="37">His hands in your embrace you'll find embru'd</l>
					<l n="38">With clotted, and perhaps with guiltless blood;</l>
					<l n="39">How awkward must it be for you to feel,</l>
					<l n="40">Near yours, his thigh that late was cas'd with steel</l>
					<l n="41">That ring, the token of his pride and state,</l>
					<l n="42">Was with a heavy gauntlet hid of late:</l>
					<l n="43">Canst thou have commerce with a thing so foul!</l>
					<l n="44">Where's now the boasted niceness of thy soul?</l>
					<l n="45">What pleasure canst thou in his roughness find?</l>
					<l n="46">Thou that wert once the softest of thy kind!</l>
					<l n="47">Behold what marks of brutal rage he bears,</l>
					<l n="48">And how he's mangled with dishonest scars.</l>
					<l n="49">Yet to these scars, dishonest as they are,</l>
					<l n="50">His wealth he owes, his fortunes with the fair.</l>
					<l n="51">No doubt, he makes a merit of his guilt,</l>
					<l n="52">And brags what blood he has in battle spilt.</l>
					<l n="53">Fine courtship this, to win a gentle dame;</l>
					<l n="54">Thou shar'st his money, and must share his shame.</l>
					<l n="55">Me, not the meanest of Apollo's train,</l>
					<l n="56">She hates, and I repeat my verse in vain;</l>
					<l n="57">I sing before her gate; her gate I find</l>
					<l n="58">Is less obdurate than her harden'd mind.</l>
					<l n="59">Forbear your songs, Apollo's sons, forbear,</l>
					<l n="60">And bend your future thoughts to arms and war.</l>
					<l n="61">Instead of inspirations, get commands;</l>
					<l n="62">To murder, and to rapine use your hands,</l>
					<l n="63">And you with ease reduce the female bands.</l>
					<l n="64">Had Homer in the Grecian army serv'd,</l>
					<l n="65">We ne'er had heard that he had begg'd, or starv'd.</l>
					<l n="66">Of gold the thund'rer show'd the mighty pow'r,</l>
					<l n="67">Descending softly thro' the brazen tow'r,</l>
					<l n="68">And clasping Danae in a golden show'r.</l>
					<l n="69">A thousand bars the virgin fair did hold,</l>
					<l n="70">But what are iron bars to bribes of gold?</l>
					<l n="71">Against this foe her father could not guard;</l>
					<l n="72">Watchmen, and women kept a fruitless ward.</l>
					<l n="73">The damsel, who herself before was coy,</l>
					<l n="74">Melts at the sight, and meets the dazzling joy.</l>
					<l n="75">When peaceful Saturn did heav'n's sceptre sway,</l>
					<l n="76">Deep in earth's womb the fatal metal lay;</l>
					<l n="77">None then their teeming mother's bowels tore,</l>
					<l n="78">In quest of hidden wealth, in various ore;</l>
					<l n="79">Fed with the fruits which bounteous nature yields,</l>
					<l n="80">In painted gardens, and in golden fields,</l>
					<l n="81">From her rich soil are reap'd spontaneous crops,</l>
					<l n="82">And from the forest oak sweet honey drops.</l>
					<l n="83">No hinds as yet did toil their time away,</l>
					<l n="84">Nor with keen clusters wound the parent clay:</l>
					<l n="85">As yet no landmark was by lab'rers set,</l>
					<l n="86">And none had learned to plough the sea as yet</l>
					<l n="87">None as yet knew the use of sails and oars,</l>
					<l n="88">Nor ventur'd voyages beyond their shores.</l>
					<l n="89">The wit of men the race of men destroys,</l>
					<l n="90">And all its pow'rs against itself employs.</l>
					<l n="91">How subtle's human nature to contrive</l>
					<l n="92">Its proper ruin, and itself deceive!</l>
					<l n="93">Why didst thou cities with high walls surround,</l>
					<l n="94">Why arms invent thy jarring sons to wound ?</l>
					<l n="95">What quarrel hast thou with the sea, and why</l>
					<l n="96">Didst thou at first the pathless ocean try ?</l>
					<l n="97">Cannot the land content thy restless pride ?</l>
					<l n="98">Didst thou with Saturn's sons the whole divide,</l>
					<l n="99">Thou wouldst not with three worlds be satisfied.</l>
					<l n="100">'Tis strange thy vast ambition did not fly</l>
					<l n="101">O'er earth, and sea, and air, and scale the sky;</l>
					<l n="102">That man did not aspire to be a god,</l>
					<l n="103">And tread the paths by Indian Bacchus trod,</l>
					<l n="104">To give his name to some distinguish'd star,</l>
					<l n="105">And be what Hercules and Caesar are.</l>
					<l n="106">Instead of yellow harvests, now we seek</l>
					<l n="107">For solid gold, and thro' earth's entrails break;</l>
					<l n="108">The wealth we thus acquire's the soldier's prey,</l>
					<l n="109">And dearly for the blood he spills we pay.</l>
					<l n="110">The courts deny admittance to the poor,</l>
					<l n="111">In vain the needy clients crowd the door;</l>
					<l n="112">The judges to the rich decree the cause,</l>
					<l n="113">And money only gives their force to laws.</l>
					<l n="114">'Tis money makes the judge with looks severe</l>
					<l n="115">Insult the poor, and give the rich his ear;</l>
					<l n="116">'Tis money buys the title, makes the knight,</l>
					<l n="117">And dignifies with quality the cit:</l>
					<l n="118">Let money do all this, and more; the bar</l>
					<l n="119">Let money govern, and direct the war.</l>
					<l n="120">Let peace, as money sets the terms, be made,</l>
					<l n="121">But let it not the rights of love invade.</l>
					<l n="122">Let us enjoy this privilege at least,</l>
					<l n="123">That if we must be poor, we may with love be bless'd:</l>
					<l n="124">For now-a-days there's not a dame in town</l>
					<l n="125">So coy, but if you've money she's your own.</l>
					<l n="126">What tho' her keeper may an <placeName key="tgn,2086061">Argus</placeName> be
						?</l>
					<l n="127">Blind him with money, and he'll nothing see.</l>
					<l n="128">What though her husband should by chance be by?</l>
					<l n="129">He'll leave the house, let you your money fly.</l>
					<l n="130">If there's a god above, to whom belongs</l>
					<l n="131">The cause of love, and slighted lovers wrongs,</l>
					<l n="132">Revenge the false one's mercenary scorn,</l>
					<l n="133">And let ill-gotten pelf to dirt return. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="9">
					<head>Elegy IX: Upon the Death of Tibullus. By <placeName key="tgn,2693739">Stepney</placeName>.</head>
					<l n="1">If Memnon's fate bewail'd with constant dew,</l>
					<l n="2">Does, with the day, his mother's grief renew,</l>
					<l n="3">If her son's death mov'd tender Thetis' mind</l>
					<l n="4">To swell with tears the waves, with sighs the wind;</l>
					<l n="5">Sad Cupid now despairs of conqu'ring hearts,</l>
					<l n="6">Throws by his empty quiver, breaks his darts:</l>
					<l n="7">Eases his useless bows from idle strings;</l>
					<l n="8">Nor flies, but humbly creeps with flagging wings.</l>
					<l n="9">He wants, of which he robb'd fond lovers, rest;</l>
					<l n="10">And wounds with furious hands his pensive breast.</l>
					<l n="11">Those graceful curls which wantonly did flow,</l>
					<l n="12">The whiter rivals of the falling snow,</l>
					<l n="13">Forget their beauty, and in discord lie,</l>
					<l n="14">Drunk with the fountain from his melting eye.</l>
					<l n="15">Nor Phoebus, nor the muses' queen, could give</l>
					<l n="16">Their son, their own prerogative, to live.</l>
					<l n="17">Orpheus, the heir of both his parents' skill,</l>
					<l n="18">Tam'd wond'ring beasts, not death's more cruel will.</l>
					<l n="19">Linus' sad strings on the dumb lute do lie. </l>
					<l n="20">In silence forc'd to let their master die.</l>
					<l n="21">His mother weeping does his eyelids close,</l>
					<l n="22">And on his urn, tears, her last gift, bestows.</l>
					<l n="23">His sister too, with hair dishevell'd, bears</l>
					<l n="24">Part of her mother's nature, and her tears.</l>
					<l n="25">With those, two fair, two mournful rivals come,</l>
					<l n="26">And add a greater triumph to his tomb:</l>
					<l n="27">Both hug his urn, both his lov'd ashes kiss,</l>
					<l n="28">And both contend which reap'd the greater bliss.</l>
					<l n="29">Thus <placeName key="tgn,1013136">Delia</placeName> spoke (when sighs no more
						could last)</l>
					<l n="30">Renewing by remembrance pleasures past;</l>
					<l n="31">"When youth with vigour did for joy combine,</l>
					<l n="32">I was Tibullus' life, Tibullus mine;</l>
					<l n="33">1 entertained his hot, his first desire,</l>
					<l n="34">And kept alive, till age, his active fire."</l>
					<l n="35">To her then Nemesis (when groans gave leave)</l>
					<l n="36">"As I alone was lov'd, alone I'll grieve;</l>
					<l n="37">Spare your vain tears, Tibullus' heart was mine,</l>
					<l n="38">About my neck his dying arms did twine:</l>
					<l n="39">I snatch'd his soul, which true to me did prove;</l>
					<l n="40">Age ended yours, death only stopp'd my love."</l>
					<l n="41">If any poor remains survive the flames,</l>
					<l n="42">Except thin shadows, and more empty names;</l>
					<l n="43">Free in Elysium shall Tibullus rove,</l>
					<l n="44">Nor fear a second death should cross his love.</l>
					<l n="45">There shall Catullus, crown'd with bays, impart</l>
					<l n="46">To his far dearer friend his open heart.</l>
					<l n="47">There Gallus (if fame's hundred tongues all lie)</l>
					<l n="48">Shall, free from censure, no more rashly die.</l>
					<l n="49">Such shall our poet's bless'd companions be,</l>
					<l n="50">And in their deaths, as in their lives, agree.</l>
					<l n="51">But thou, rich urn, obey my strict commands,</l>
					<l n="52">Guard thy great charge from sacrilegious hands.</l>
					<l n="53">Thou, earth, Tibullus' ashes gently use,</l>
					<l n="54">And be as soft and easy as his muse. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="10">
					<head>Elegy X.</head>
					<l n="1">Now <placeName key="tgn,2068435">Ceres</placeName>' feast is come, the trees
						are blown,</l>
					<l n="2">And my <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> now must lie
						alone.</l>
					<l n="3">And why, good <placeName key="tgn,2068435">Ceres</placeName>, must thy feast
						destroy</l>
					<l n="4">Man's chief delight, and why disturb his joy ?</l>
					<l n="5">The world esteems you bountiful and good,</l>
					<l n="6">You led us from the field and from the wood,</l>
					<l n="7">And gave us fruitful corn, and wholesome food.</l>
					<l n="8">Till then poor wretched man on acorns fed;</l>
					<l n="9">Oaks gave him meat, and flow'ry fields a bed.</l>
					<l n="10">First <placeName key="tgn,2068435">Ceres</placeName> made our wheat and
						barley grow,</l>
					<l n="11">And taught us how to plough, and how to mow;</l>
					<l n="12">Who then can think that she designs to prove</l>
					<l n="13">Our piety, by coldness in our love ?</l>
					<l n="14">Or make poor lovers sigh, lament, and groan,</l>
					<l n="15">Or charge her votaries to lie alone ?</l>
					<l n="16">For <placeName key="tgn,2068435">Ceres</placeName>, though she loves the
						fruitful fields,</l>
					<l n="17">Yet sometimes feels the force of love, and yields:</l>
					<l n="18">This <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> can witness, (<placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> not always lies)</l>
					<l n="19"><placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> that nurs'd Jove, and heard
						his infant cries,</l>
					<l n="20">There he was suckled who now rules the skies.</l>
					<l n="21">That Jove his education there receiv'd,</l>
					<l n="22">Will raise her fame, and make her be believ'd;</l>
					<l n="23">Nay she herself will never strive to hide</l>
					<l n="24">Her love, 'tis too well known to be denied:</l>
					<l n="25">She saw young Jasius in the Cretan grove</l>
					<l n="26">Pursue the deer, she saw, and fell in love.</l>
					<l n="27">She then perceived when first she felt the fire,</l>
					<l n="28">On this side modesty, on that desire;</l>
					<l n="29">Desire prevail'd, and then the field grew dry,</l>
					<l n="30">The farmer lost his crop and knew not why;</l>
					<l n="31">When he had toil'd, manur'd his grounds, and plough' d,</l>
					<l n="32">Harrow'd his fields, and broke his clods, and sow'd,</l>
					<l n="33">No corn appear'd, none to reward his pain,</l>
					<l n="34">His labour and his wishes were in vain.</l>
					<l n="35">For <placeName key="tgn,7010621">Ceres</placeName> wand'red in the woods and
						groves,</l>
					<l n="36">And often heard, and often told her loves:</l>
					<l n="37">Then <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> alone a fruitful summer
						knew,</l>
					<l n="38">Where'er the goddess came a harvest grew.</l>
					<l n="39">Ida was grey with corn, the furious boar</l>
					<l n="40">Grew fat with wheat, and wonder'd at the store:</l>
					<l n="41">The Cretans wish'd that such all years would prove,</l>
					<l n="42">They wish'd that <placeName key="tgn,7010621">Ceres</placeName> would be long
						in love.</l>
					<l n="43">Well then, since then 'twas hard for you to lie</l>
					<l n="44">All night alone, why at your feast must I ?</l>
					<l n="45">Why must I mourn, when you rejoice to know</l>
					<l n="46">Your daughter safe, and queen of all below?</l>
					<l n="47">'Tis holy-day, and calls for wine and love;</l>
					<l n="48">Come, let's the height of mirth and humor prove,</l>
					<l n="49">These gifts will please our master pow'rs above. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="11">
					<head>Elegy XI: To his Mistress, that he cannot help loving her.</head>
					<l n="1">So much I've suffer'd, and so long, no more</l>
					<l n="2">I'll bear the wrongs which I have borne before.</l>
					<l n="3">Begone, vile Cupid, I'll no more endure</l>
					<l n="4">Thy slavish labors, and fatigues impure;</l>
					<l n="5">From hence, I'll put an end to all the pains</l>
					<l n="6">Thou'st cost me, and from hence shake off thy chains.</l>
					<l n="7">I hate the liv'ry I with pleasure wore,</l>
					<l n="8">And blush at bonds, which once with pride I bore:</l>
					<l n="9">But this, methinks, should have been done before.</l>
					<l n="10">To leave my wicked courses I begin,</l>
					<l n="11">As years deprive me of the gust of sin.</l>
					<l n="12">On Cupid's neck I should have trod when young,</l>
					<l n="13">And vanquish'd him when my desires were strong.</l>
					<l n="14">In that there had been virtue; now there's none,</l>
					<l n="15">The world will say so; let the world say on.</l>
					<l n="16">Much opposition I shall meet; perhaps,</l>
					<l n="17">The lewd will laugh, and threaten a relapse.</l>
					<l n="18">To bear reproaches I must be prepar'd,</l>
					<l n="19">Easy's the end, when the beginning's hard;</l>
					<l n="20">Content let me the present pain endure,</l>
					<l n="21">For the sharp medicine is the patient's cure.</l>
					<l n="22">How oft you have expos'd me to the cold,</l>
					<l n="23">While in your arms you did my rival hold!</l>
					<l n="24">How like a slave have I been forc'd to wait</l>
					<l n="25">All weathers, and how oft have watched the gate!</l>
					<l n="26">As if your house was trusted to my care</l>
					<l n="27">And I, your sentinel, did duty there.</l>
					<l n="28">Oft have I seen your sated lover come</l>
					<l n="29">With looks, as if he long'd to be at home.</l>
					<l n="30">But what most grated on my jealous mind,</l>
					<l n="31">Was that he there the waiting fool should find.</l>
					<l n="32">That aggravated most the cruel curse;</l>
					<l n="33">I would not wish my greatest foe a worse.</l>
					<l n="34">How oft have I attended you abroad,</l>
					<l n="35">Or in the city, cirque, or on the road ?</l>
					<l n="36">They took me for your husband by my care,</l>
					<l n="37">Or that your guardian or your slave I were.</l>
					<l n="38">I by the people's glances, and your own,</l>
					<l n="39">Observ'd you were acquainted with the town;</l>
					<l n="40">That of your love if I possess'd a part,</l>
					<l n="41">'Twas plain I shared with many more your heart.</l>
					<l n="42">What need I of your perjuries bring proof,</l>
					<l n="43">Suppose the common talk was not enough!</l>
					<l n="44">What do your ogles and your gestures mean,</l>
					<l n="45">Your carriage at th' assembly and the scene ?</l>
					<l n="46">There's scarce a fop you meet with in your way,</l>
					<l n="47">To whom you have not something soft to say;</l>
					<l n="48">Some token which you either understand</l>
					<l n="49">By mystic words or motion of the hand.</l>
					<l n="50">They tell me you are sick; I run to see,</l>
					<l n="51">And find, as ill as you pretend to be,</l>
					<l n="52">It is not for my rival, but for me.</l>
					<l n="53">I seldom told you of your faults, but strove</l>
					<l n="54">To cover all your failings with my love;</l>
					<l n="55">Of this I might remind you, and much more,</l>
					<l n="56">But what avails it now; th' affair is o'er:</l>
					<l n="57">A fond you found me, and a patient man,</l>
					<l n="58">And get you such another if you can.</l>
					<l n="59">I fear not now your frowns; my bark defies</l>
					<l n="60">The storm of words, and tempest of your eyes;</l>
					<l n="61">No coaxing now, your hardest phrases use,</l>
					<l n="62">Your looks, your language, all their terrors lose;</l>
					<l n="63">I am not such a fool as I have been,</l>
					<l n="64">To dread your spirit, and to sooth your spleen.</l>
					<l n="65">But, ah! by diff'rent passions I'm oppress'd,</l>
					<l n="66">Fierce love and hate contend within my breast;</l>
					<l n="67">My soul they thus divide, but love, I fear,</l>
					<l n="68">Will prove too strong, and get the mast'ry there;</l>
					<l n="69">I'll strive to hate her, but if that should prove</l>
					<l n="70">A fruitless strife, in spite of me I'll love.</l>
					<l n="71">The bull does not affect the yoke, but still</l>
					<l n="72">He bears the thing he hates against his will</l>
					<l n="73">I hate, I fly the faithless fair in vain,</l>
					<l n="74">Her beauty ever brings me back again;</l>
					<l n="75">She always in my heart will have a place,</l>
					<l n="76">I hate her humour, but I love her face;</l>
					<l n="77">No rest I to my tortur'd soul can give,</l>
					<l n="78">Nor with her nor without her can I live.</l>
					<l n="79">Oh ! that thy mind we in thy face did view,</l>
					<l n="80">Less lovely that thou wert, or else more true.</l>
					<l n="81">How diffrent are thy manners and thy sight!</l>
					<l n="82">Thy deeds forbid us and thy eyes invite.</l>
					<l n="83">Thy actions shock us, and thy beauty moves,</l>
					<l n="84">And he who hates thy faults, thy person loves.</l>
					<l n="85">Happy, ah ! ever happy should I be,</l>
					<l n="86">If I no charms or no defects could see.</l>
					<l n="87">Thee I conjure by all our past delights,</l>
					<l n="88">Our cheerful days and our transporting nights,</l>
					<l n="89">By all the imprecated gods above,</l>
					<l n="90">To whom thou art forsworn, but most by Love,</l>
					<l n="91">By thy fair face, which I as much adore</l>
					<l n="92">As all those gods, and own as much its pow'r,</l>
					<l n="93">Forgive me this offence, and I'll offend no more.</l>
					<l n="94">Be what thou wilt, thy humour good or ill,</l>
					<l n="95">I'll love thee, thou shalt be my mistress still</l>
					<l n="96">Ah, let my passion ever favour find,</l>
					<l n="97">Or be it with, or be't against my mind,</l>
					<l n="98">But rather let me sail before the wind.</l>
					<l n="99">Ah, let thy wishes with my will agree,</l>
					<l n="100">Since surely I thy slave must ever be;</l>
					<l n="101">In thee since I have centred all my joys,</l>
					<l n="102">Oh Venus ! let my love be still my choice. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="12">
					<head>Elegy XII: He complains that the praises he has bestowed on his mistress
						in his verses, have occasioned him many rivals.</head>
					<l n="1">Ill-omen'd birds, how luckless was the day,</l>
					<l n="2">When o'er my love you did your wings display!</l>
					<l n="3">What wayward orb, what inauspicious star</l>
					<l n="4">Did then rule heav'n ? what gods against me war?</l>
					<l n="5">She who so much my fatal passion wrongs,</l>
					<l n="6">Was known and first made famous by my songs.</l>
					<l n="7">I lov'd her first, and lov'd her then alone,</l>
					<l n="8">But now, I fear, I share her with the town.</l>
					<l n="9">Am I deceiv'd or can she be the same,</l>
					<l n="10">Who only to my verses owes her fame</l>
					<l n="11">My verse a price upon her beauty laid,</l>
					<l n="12">And by my praises she her market made;</l>
					<l n="13">Whom but myself can I with reason blame?</l>
					<l n="14">Without me she had never had a name.</l>
					<l n="15">Did I do this, who knew her soul so well?</l>
					<l n="16">Dearly to me she did her favours sell;</l>
					<l n="17">And when the wares were to the public known,</l>
					<l n="18">Why should I think she'd sell to me alone ?</l>
					<l n="19">'Twas I proclaim'd to all the town her charms,</l>
					<l n="20">And tempted cullies to her venal arms;</l>
					<l n="21">I made their way, I show'd them where to come,</l>
					<l n="22">And there is hardly now a rake in <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName></l>
					<l n="23">But knows her rates, and thanks my babbling muse:</l>
					<l n="24">Her house is now as common as the stews;</l>
					<l n="25">For this I'm to the muse oblig'd, and more</l>
					<l n="26">For all the mischiefs envy has in store.</l>
					<l n="27">This comes of gallantry, while some employ</l>
					<l n="28">Their talents on the fate of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>,</l>
					<l n="29">While others Caesar's godlike acts rehearse,</l>
					<l n="30"><placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> is the subject of my
						verse.</l>
					<l n="31">Oh, that I ne'er had known the art to please,</l>
					<l n="32">But written without genius and success.</l>
					<l n="33">Why did the town so readily believe</l>
					<l n="34">My verse, and why to songs such credit give ?</l>
					<l n="35">Sure poetry s the same it ever was,</l>
					<l n="36">And poets ne'er for oracles did pass.</l>
					<l n="37">Why is such stress upon my writings laid?</l>
					<l n="38">Why such regard to what by me is said ?</l>
					<l n="39">I wish the tales I've of <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName>
						told,</l>
					<l n="40">Had been receiv'd as fables were of old;</l>
					<l n="41">Of furious Scylla's horrid shape we read,</l>
					<l n="42">And how she scalp'd her hoary father's lead:</l>
					<l n="43">Of her fair face, and downward how she takes</l>
					<l n="44">The wolf's fierce form, the dog's, or curling snake's;</l>
					<l n="45">Serpents for hair, in ancient song we meet,</l>
					<l n="46">And man and horse with wings instead of feet.</l>
					<l n="47">Huge Tityon from the skies the poets flung,</l>
					<l n="48">Encelladus's wars with Jove they sung;</l>
					<l n="49">How by her spells, and by her voice, to beasts,</l>
					<l n="50">The doubtful virgin chang'd her wretched guests;</l>
					<l n="51">How Eolus did for <placeName key="tgn,2093866">Ulysses</placeName> keep</l>
					<l n="52">The winds in bottles while he plough'd the deep:</l>
					<l n="53">How Cerberus, three headed, guarded hell;</l>
					<l n="54">And from his car the son of Phoebus fell:</l>
					<l n="55">How thirsty Tantalus attempts to sip</l>
					<l n="56">The stream in vain, that flies his greedy lip:</l>
					<l n="57">How Niobe in marble drops a tear,</l>
					<l n="58">And a bright nymph was turn'd into a bear:</l>
					<l n="59">How Progne, now a swallow, does bemoan</l>
					<l n="60">Her sister nightingale, and pheasant son.</l>
					<l n="61">In Leda, Danae, and Europa's rapes,</l>
					<l n="62">They sing the king of gods in various shapes;</l>
					<l n="63">A swan he lies on ravish'd Leda's breast,</l>
					<l n="64">And Danae by a golden show'r compress'd;</l>
					<l n="65">A bull does o'er the waves Europa bear,</l>
					<l n="66">And Proteus any form he pleases wear.</l>
					<l n="67">How oft do we the Theban wonders read,</l>
					<l n="68">Of serpent's teeth transform'd to human seed!</l>
					<l n="69">Of dancing woods, and moving rocks, that throng</l>
					<l n="70">To hear sweet Orpheus, and <placeName key="tgn,2132474">Amphion</placeName>'s
						song ?</l>
					<l n="71">How oft do the Heliades bemoan,</l>
					<l n="72">In tears of gum, the fall of Phaeton!</l>
					<l n="73">The sun from Atreus' table frightened flies,</l>
					<l n="74">And backward drives his chariot in the skies.</l>
					<l n="75">Those now are nymphs that lately were a fleet;</l>
					<l n="76">Poetic license ever was so great.</l>
					<l n="77">But none did credit to these fictions give,</l>
					<l n="78">Or for true history such tales receive,</l>
					<l n="79">And though <placeName key="tgn,2044648">Corinna</placeName> in my songs is
						fair,</l>
					<l n="80">Let none conclude she's like her picture there.</l>
					<l n="81">The fable she with hasty faith receiv'd,</l>
					<l n="82">And what, so very well she lik'd, believ'd.</l>
					<l n="83">But since so ill she does the poet use,</l>
					<l n="84">'Tis time her vanity to disabuse. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="13">
					<head>Elegy XIII: Of Juno's Feast.</head>
					<l n="1">My wife, a native of Phaliscan plains,</l>
					<l n="2">Where the rich soils enrich the lab'ring swains,</l>
					<l n="3">Where purple grapes and golden apples grow,</l>
					<l n="4">A conquest we to great <placeName key="tgn,2068320">Camillus</placeName>
						owe.</l>
					<l n="5">When once to <placeName key="tgn,2075297">Juno</placeName>'s feast she
						thither went,</l>
					<l n="6">My mind to know the secret rites was bent:</l>
					<l n="7">The pious priests the solemn sports prepare,</l>
					<l n="8">And purify the fane with holy care.</l>
					<l n="9">A heifer of the place they sacrifice,</l>
					<l n="10">But ne'er to men expose their mysteries,</l>
					<l n="11">I mark'd the hidden way my consort went,</l>
					<l n="12">And follow'd down the deep and dark descent.</l>
					<l n="13">To an old wood at last I came, whose shade</l>
					<l n="14">Impress'd a horror on the gloom it made,</l>
					<l n="15">And ev'ry step with trembling feet I trod,</l>
					<l n="16">Profan'd, I thought, the dwelling of a god.</l>
					<l n="17">An altar there was rais'd by hands divine,</l>
					<l n="18">And fragrant incense flam'd around the shrine.</l>
					<l n="19">Chaste matrons there their vow'd oblations pay,</l>
					<l n="20">And celebrate with joyful hymns the day.</l>
					<l n="21">Soon as the fife the signal gives, they move</l>
					<l n="22">In long procession through the sacred grove</l>
					<l n="23">Branches and flow'rs are with devotion spread</l>
					<l n="24">O'er all the way, and priestly vestments laid.</l>
					<l n="25">Next after these, through loud acclaims, they lead</l>
					<l n="26">A cow milk white, and of Phaliscan breed;</l>
					<l n="27">Then a young steer, whose forehead ne'er had borne</l>
					<l n="28">The crooked honours of the butting horn.</l>
					<l n="29">The least of all the victims was a swine,</l>
					<l n="30">And then a ram whose horns around his temples twine.</l>
					<l n="31">A goat, whom most the goddess hates, comes last;</l>
					<l n="32">The present feels her vengeance for the past.</l>
					<l n="33">When in a wood to hide herself she tried,</l>
					<l n="34">She by the bleating of a goat was spied;</l>
					<l n="35">For this the beast is by the boys pursu'd;</l>
					<l n="36">For this she's ever greedy of its blood,</l>
					<l n="37">And he, who first the letcher wounds in play,</l>
					<l n="38">Claims by her law, and hears the prize away.</l>
					<l n="39">The tender youth, and tim'rous virgin strow</l>
					<l n="40">With robes the ground the goddess is to go.</l>
					<l n="41">The virgins' locks with golden fillets bound,</l>
					<l n="42">And sparkling diamonds glitt'ring all around;</l>
					<l n="43">Buskins embroider'd on their feet they wear,</l>
					<l n="44">And spreading trains with pride uneasy bear.</l>
					<l n="45">Here, as in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> the custom was of
						old,</l>
					<l n="46">The image of the goddess we behold</l>
					<l n="47">Borne on the heads of maidens, and behind</l>
					<l n="48">The priestesses in beauteous rank you find.</l>
					<l n="49">An awful silence reigns : the goddess last</l>
					<l n="50">Approaches, and with her the pomp is past.</l>
					<l n="51">The dress was Greek, and such Halesus wore,</l>
					<l n="52">When in a fright he fled the Grecian shore;</l>
					<l n="53">His father kill'd, an <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> ship he
						fraught,</l>
					<l n="54">And to this coast the royal treasure brought.</l>
					<l n="55">Much peril had he past, much labour known,</l>
					<l n="56">O'er lands and seas, before he reach'd our own,</l>
					<l n="57">And landing built, with happy hand, the town,</l>
					<l n="58">Where first he did this festival revive,</l>
					<l n="59">And its Greek rules to the Phaliscans give;</l>
					<l n="60">The rites and sacrifices first he show'd,</l>
					<l n="61">As practis'd now within this ancient wood.</l>
					<l n="62">Ah, may these rites to all propitious be,</l>
					<l n="63">No more to those that serv'd them than to me. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="14">
					<head>Elegy XIV: He desires his mistress, if she does cuckold him, not to let
						him know it.</head>
					<l n="1">I do not ask you would to me prove true,</l>
					<l n="2">Since you're a woman, and a fair one too.</l>
					<l n="3">Act what you please, yet study to disguise</l>
					<l n="4">The wanton scenes from my deluded eyes.</l>
					<l n="5">A stiff denial would attenuate</l>
					<l n="6">That crime which your confession would make great.</l>
					<l n="7">And 'twere unwise to trust the tell-tale light,</l>
					<l n="8">With the dark secrets of the silent night.</l>
					<l n="9">Tho' bought to be enjoy'd, a common whore</l>
					<l n="10">Ere she begins will shut the chamber door:</l>
					<l n="11">And will you turn debauch'd, then vainly own</l>
					<l n="12">How lewd you are, to this malicious town?</l>
					<l n="13">At least seem virtuous, and tho' false you be,</l>
					<l n="14">Say you are honest, and I'll credit thee.</l>
					<l n="15">Conceal your actions, and while I am by,</l>
					<l n="16">Let modest words your looser thoughts belie;</l>
					<l n="17">When to your private chamber you retire,</l>
					<l n="18">Unmask your lust, and vent each warm desire;</l>
					<l n="19">Throw off affected coyness, and remove</l>
					<l n="20">The bold intruder between thee and love:</l>
					<l n="21">Talk not of honour, lay that toy aside,</l>
					<l n="22">In men 'tis folly, and in women pride;</l>
					<l n="23">There without blushes you may naked lie,</l>
					<l n="24">Clasping his body with your tender thigh;</l>
					<l n="25">Shoot your moist dart into his mouth, to show</l>
					<l n="26">The sense you have of what he acts below;</l>
					<l n="27">Try all the ways, your pliant bodies twine,</l>
					<l n="28">In folds more strange than those of Aretine:</l>
					<l n="29">With melting looks fierce joys you may excite,</l>
					<l n="30">And with thick dying accents urge delight.</l>
					<l n="31">But when you're dress'd, then look as innocent</l>
					<l n="32">As if you knew not what such matters meant;</l>
					<l n="33">Cozen the prying town, and put a cheat</l>
					<l n="34">On it and me, I'll favour the deceit.</l>
					<l n="35">False as thou art, why must I daily see</l>
					<l n="36">Th' intriguing billet-doux he sends to thee ?</l>
					<l n="37">The wanton sonnet, or soft elegy ?</l>
					<l n="38">Why does your bed all tumbled seem to say,</l>
					<l n="39">See what they've done, see where the lovers lay!</l>
					<l n="40">Why do your locks and rumpled head-clothes show</l>
					<l n="41">'Tis more than usual sleep that made 'em so?</l>
					<l n="42">Why are the kisses which he gave, betray'd</l>
					<l n="43">By the impression which his teeth had made ?</l>
					<l n="44">Yet say you're chaste, and I'll be still deceived;</l>
					<l n="45">What much is wish'd for, is with ease believ'd.</l>
					<l n="46">But when you own what a lewd wretch thou art,</l>
					<l n="47">My blood grows cold and freezes at my heart,</l>
					<l n="48">Then do I curse thee, and thy crimes reprove,</l>
					<l n="49">But curse in vain, for still I find I love;</l>
					<l n="50">"Since she is false," oft to myself I cry,</l>
					<l n="51">"Would I were dead,"-yet 'tis with thee I'd die</l>
					<l n="52">I will not see your maid, to let me know</l>
					<l n="53">Who visits you, where, and with whom you go;</l>
					<l n="54">Nor by your lodging send my boy to scout,</l>
					<l n="55">And bring me word who passes in and out.</l>
					<l n="56">Enjoy the pleasure of the present times,</l>
					<l n="57">But let not me be knowing of your crimes.</l>
					<l n="58">Do you forswear't, tho' in the act you're caught,</l>
					<l n="59">I'll trust the oath, and think my eyes in fault. </l>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="poem" n="15">
					<head>Elegy XV: To Venus, that he may have done writing elegies.</head>
					<l n="1">To Virgil Mantua owes immortal fame,</l>
					<l n="2">Catullus to <placeName key="perseus,Verona">Verona</placeName> gives a
						name;</l>
					<l n="3">Why mayn't, if I attempt some great design,</l>
					<l n="4">Peligne be as much oblig'd to mine ?</l>
					<l n="5">Why mayn't my muse a glorious toil pursue,</l>
					<l n="6">And as much honour to my country do ?</l>
					<l n="7">A people, who, when <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> has been
						alarm'd</l>
					<l n="8">By foreign foes, in her defence have arm'd;</l>
					<l n="9">Beneath your golden banners I have fought</l>
					<l n="10">So long, your discipline so much have taught,</l>
					<l n="11">'Tis time to give me a discharge, to prove</l>
					<l n="12">Some other, some more glorious theme than love</l>
					<l n="13">See Bacchus beckons me my voice to raise,</l>
					<l n="14">Of lofty deeds to sings, in lofty lays;</l>
					<l n="15">To mount my muse on some more generous horse,</l>
					<l n="16">And try her courage in some daring course.</l>
					<l n="17">Adieu, my sighing elegies, adieu!</l>
					<l n="18">I'll be no more concern'd with love or you;</l>
					<l n="19">But what I write my being shall survive,</l>
					<l n="20">And in his verse the poet ever live.</l>
				</div>
			</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>