<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="Inst." type="work">Institutio Oratoria, books 10-12 - 10</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
                <editor n="Butler" role="edrend=itor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Quintilian</author>
                        <title>With An English Translation</title>
                        <editor n="Butler" role="editor">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1922</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="Section"
                    matchPattern="(\\w+).(\\w+).(\\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\']/tei:div[@n=\'$2\']/tei:div[@n=\'$3\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter and Section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\\w+).(\\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\']/tei:div[@n=\'$2\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book and Chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="Book"
                    matchPattern="(\\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts Book</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="page"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><change who="GRC" when="2006">tagging</change><!--
            <change>
                <date>2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>GRC</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item/>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
           <change who="Zach Himes" when="2015-11-16">Edited header, Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng" >
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" subtype="book" type="translation">
                <head>Book X</head>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    But these rules of style, while part of the
student's theoretical knowledge, are not in themselves sufficient to give him oratorical power. In
addition he will require that assured facility which
the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">e(/cis</foreign>
                    I know that many have raised
the question as to whether this is best acquired by
writing, reading or speaking, and it would indeed
be a question calling for serious consideration, if we
could rest content with any one of the three.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    But
they are so intimately and inseparably connected,
that if one of them be neglected, we shall but waste
the labour which we have devoted to the others.
For eloquence will never attain to its full development or robust health, unless it acquires strength
by frequent practice in writing, while such practice
without the models supplied by reading will be like
a ship drifting aimlessly without a steersman.
Again, he who knows what he ought to say and
how he should say it, will be like a miser brooding
over his hoarded treasure, unless he has the weapons
of his eloquence ready for battle and prepared to
deal with every emergency.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But the degree in
                    <pb xml:id="p.5"/>
                    which a thing is essential does not necessarily make
it of immediate and supreme importance for the
formation of the ideal orator. For obviously the
power of speech is the first essential, since therein
lies the primary task of the orator, and it is obvious
that it was with this that the art of oratory began,
and that the power of imitation comes next, and
third and last diligent practice in writing.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But as
perfection cannot be attained without starting at
the very beginning, the points which come first in
time will, as our training proceeds, become of quite
trivial importance. Now we have reached a stage in
our enquiry where we are no longer considering the
preliminary training of our orator; for I think the
instructions already given should suffice for that;
they are in any case as good as I could make them.
Our present task is to consider how our athlete who
has learnt all the technique of his art from his
trainer, is to be prepared by actual practice for the
contests in which he will have to engage. Consequently, we must assume that our student has
learned how to conceive and dispose his subject
matter and understands how to choose and arrange
his words, and must proceed to instruct him how to
make the best and readiest use of the knowledge
which he has acquired.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    There can then be no doubt that he must accumulate a certain store of resources, to be employed
whenever they may be required. The resources of
which I speak consist in a copious supply of words
and matter.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    But while the matter is necessarily
either peculiar to the individual case, or at best
common to only a few, words must be acquired to
suit all and every case. Now, if there were special
                    <pb xml:id="p.7"/>
                    words adapted to each individual thing, they would
require less care, since they would automatically be
suggested by the matter in hand. But since some
words are more literal, more ornate, more significant
or euphonious than others, our orator must not
merely be acquainted with all of them, but must
have them at his fingers' ends and before his very
eyes, so that when they present themselves for his
critical selection, he will find it easy to make the
appropriate choice.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    I know that some speakers
make a practice of learning lists of synonyms by
heart, in order that one word out of the several
available may at once present itself to them, and
that if, after using one word, they find that it is
wanted again after a brief interval, they may be
able to select another word with the same meaning
and so avoid the necessity of repetition. But this
practice is childish and involves thankless labour,
while it is really of very little use, as it merely
results in the assembly of a disorderly crowd of
words, for the speaker to snatch the first that comes
to hand.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    On the contrary, discrimination is necessary in
the acquisition of our stock of words; for we are
aiming at true oratory, not at the fluency of a
cheapjack. And we shall attain our aim by reading
and listening to the best writers and orators, since
we shall thus learn not merely the words by which
things are to be called, but when each particular
word is most appropriate.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    For there is a place in
oratory for almost every word, with the exception
only of a very few, which are not sufficiently seemly.
Such words are indeed often praised when they
occur in writers of iambics
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See §§ 59 and 96.</note>
                    or of the old comedy,
                    <pb xml:id="p.9"/>
                    but we need do no more than consider our own
special task. All words, with these exceptions,
may be admirably employed in some place or
other. For sometimes we shall even require low
and common words, while those which would
seem coarse if introduced in the more elegant
portions of our speech may, under certain circumstances, be appropriate enough.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Now to acquire a
knowledge of these words and to be acquainted not
merely with their meaning, but with their forms and
rhythmical values, so that they may seem appropriate
wherever employed, we shall need to read and listen
diligently, since all language is received first through
the ear. It was owing to this fact that the children
who, by order of a king, were brought up by a dumb
nurse in a desert place, although they are said to
have uttered certain words, lacked the power of
speech.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See Herodot. ii. 2. The children were alleged to have
cried
                        <quote>bekos,</quote>
                        Phrygian for bread.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There are, however, some words of such
a nature that they express the same sense by
different sounds, so that it makes no difference to
the meaning which we use, as, for instance,
                    <hi rend="italic">gladius</hi>
                    and
                    <hi rend="italic">ensis,</hi>
                    which may be used indifferently when we
have to speak of a sword. Others, again, although
properly applied to specific objects, are used by
means of a
                    <hi rend="italic">trope</hi>
                    to express the same sense, as, for
example,
                    <hi rend="italic">ferrum</hi>
                    (steel) and muro (point), which are
both used in the sense of sword.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Thus, by the
                    <hi rend="italic">figure</hi>
                    known as
                    <hi rend="italic">abuse,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        or
                        <hi rend="italic">catachresis.</hi>
                        See viii. ii. 5 and vi. 34.
                    </note>
                    we call all those who commit
a murder with any weapon whatsoever
                    <hi rend="italic">sicarii</hi>
                    (poniarders). In other cases we express our meaning
periphrastically, as, for instance, when Virgil
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecl. i.</hi>
                        81.
                    </note>
                    describes cheese as
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>Abundance of pressed milk.</quote>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    <pb xml:id="p.11"/>
                    On the other hand, in a number of instances we
employ
                    <hi rend="italic">figures</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See i. viii. 16; ix. i. 11.</note>
                    and substitute one expression for
another. Instead of
                    <quote>I know,</quote>
                    we say
                    <quote>I am not ignorant,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>the fact does not escape me,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>I have not forgotten,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>who does not know?</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>it can be doubted by none.</quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    But we may also
borrow from a word of cognate meaning. For
                    <quote>I understand,</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>I feel</quote>
                    or
                    <quote>I see</quote>
                    are often
equivalent to
                    <quote>I know.</quote>
                    Reading will provide us
with a rich store of expressions such as these,
and will enable us not merely to use them when
they occur to us, but also in the appropriate manner.
For they are not always interchangeable:
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    for
example, though I may be perfectly correct in
saying,
                    <quote>I see</quote>
                    for
                    <quote>I understand,</quote>
                    it does not
follow that I can say
                    <quote>I understand</quote>
                    for
                    <quote>my eyes have seen,</quote>
                    and though
                    <hi rend="italic">mucro</hi>
                    may be employed to
describe a sword, a sword does not necessarily mean
the same as
                    <hi rend="italic">mucro</hi>
                    (point).
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    But, although a store
of words may be acquired by these means, we must
not read or listen to orators merely for the sake of
acquiring words. For in everything which we teach
examples are more effective even than the rules
which are taught in the schools, so long as the
student has reached a stage when he can appreciate
such examples without the assistance of a teacher,
and can rely on his own powers to imitate them.
And the reason is this, that the professor of rhetoric
lays down rules, while the orator gives a practical
demonstration.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But the advantages conferred by reading and
listening are not identical. The speaker stimulates
us by the animation of his delivery, and kindles the
imagination, not by presenting us with an elaborate
                    <pb xml:id="p.13"/>
                    picture, but by bringing us into actual touch with
the things themselves. Then all is life and movement, and we receive the new-born offspring of his
imagination with enthusiastic approval. We are
moved not merely by the actual issue of the trial,
but by all that the orator himself has at stake.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover his voice, the grace of his gestures, the adaptation of his delivery (which is of supreme importance
in oratory), and, in a word, all his excellences in
combination, have their educative effect. In reading,
on the other hand, the critical faculty is a surer
guide, inasmuch as the listener's judgment is often
swept away by his preference for a particular speaker,
or by the applause of an enthusiastic audience.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    For
we are ashamed to disagree with them, and an unconscious modesty prevents us from ranking our own
opinion above theirs, though all the time the taste
of the majority is vicious, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">claque</hi>
                    may
praise even what does not really deserve approval.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, it will sometimes also happen
that an audience whose taste is bad will fail to award
the praise which is due to the most admirable utterances. Reading, however, is free, and does not hurry
past us with the speed of oral delivery; we can reread a passage again and again if we are in doubt
about it or wish to fix it in the memory. We must
return to what we have read and reconsider it with
care, while, just as we do not swallow our food till
we have chewed it and reduced it almost to a state
of liquefaction to assist the process of digestion, so
what we read must not be committed to the memory
for subsequent imitation while it is still in a crude
state, but must be softened and, if I may use the
phrase, reduced to a pulp by frequent re-perusal.
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.15"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    For a long time also we should read none save the
best authors and such as are least likely to betray our
trust in then, while our reading must be almost as
thorough as if we were actually transcribing what we
read. Nor must we study it merely in parts, but
must read through the whole work from cover to
cover and then read it afresh, a precept which applies
more especially to speeches, whose merits are often
deliberately disguised.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    For the orator frequently
prepares his audience for what is to come, dissembles
and sets a trap for them and makes remarks at the
opening of his speech which will not have their full
force till the conclusion. Consequently what he
says will often seem comparatively ineffective where
it actually occurs, since we do not realise his motive
and it will be necessary to re-read the speech after
we have acquainted ourselves with all that it contains.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Above all, it is most desirable that we should
familiarise ourselves with the facts of the case with
which the speech deals, and it will be well also,
wherever possible, to read the speeches delivered on
both sides, such as those of Aeschines and Demosthenes in the case of Ctesiphon, of Servius Sulpicius
and Messala for and against Aufidia,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See iv. ii. 106 and VI i. 20.</note>
                    of Pollio
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 113.</note>
                    and
Cassius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 116.</note>
                    in the case of Asprenas,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        C. Nonius Asprenas, a friend of Augustus, accused by
Cassius and defended by Pollio on a charge of poisoning.
                    </note>
                    and many others.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    And even if such speeches seem unequal in point of
merit, we shall still do well to study them carefully
with a view to understanding the problems raised by
the cases with which they deal: for example, we
should compare the speeches delivered by Tubero
against Ligarius and by Hortensius in defence of
Verres with those of Cicero for the opposite side,
while it will also be useful to know how different
orators pleaded the same case. For example,
                    <pb xml:id="p.17"/>
                    Calidius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably before some other tribunal. Cicero's
                        <hi rend="italic">de Domo Sua</hi>
                        was delivered before the
                        <hi rend="italic">pontifices.</hi>
                    </note>
                    spoke on the subject of Cicero's house,
Brutus wrote a declamation in defence of Milo, which
Cornelius Celsus wrongly believes to have been
actually delivered in court,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        III. vi. 93. Cornelius Celsus was an encyclopedic
writer of the early empire, whose treatise on medicine has
survived.
                    </note>
                    and Pollio and Messalla
defended the same clients,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Liburnia. See IX. ii. 34.</note>
                    while in my boyhood
remarkable speeches delivered by Domitius Afer,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See § 118.</note>
                    Crispus Passienus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Stepfather of Nero. See VI. i. 50.</note>
                    and Decimis Laelius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably the Laelius Balbus of Tac.
                        <hi rend="italic">Ann,.</hi>
                        VI. 47, 48.
                    </note>
                    in defence of Volusenus were in circulation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    The reader must not, however, jump to the conclusion that all that was uttered by the best authors is
necessarily perfect. At times they lapse and stagger
beneath the weight of their task, indulge their bent
or relax their efforts. Sometimes, again, they give
the impression of weariness: for example, Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        In a lost letter:
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        Plut.
                        <hi rend="italic">Cic.</hi>
                        24.
                    </note>
                    thinks that Demosthenes sometimes nods, and Horace
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">A. P.</hi>
                        359.
                    </note>
                    says the same of Homer himself.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    For despite their
greatness they are still but mortal men, and it will
sometimes happen that their reader assumes that
anything which he finds in them may be taken as a
canon of style, with the result that he imitates their
defects (and it is always easier to do this than to
imitate their excellences) and thinks himself a
perfect replica if he succeeds in copying the
blemishes of great men.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    But modesty and circumspection are required in pronouncing judgment on
such great men, since there is always the risk of
falling into the common fault of condemning what
one does not understand. And, if it is necessary to
err on one side or the other, I should prefer that
the reader should approve of everything than that
he should disapprove of much.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    Theophrastus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">In one of his lost rhetorical treatises.</note>
                    says that the reading of poets is
of great service to the orator, and has rightly been
followed in this view by many. For the poets will
                    <pb xml:id="p.19"/>
                    give us inspiration as regards the matter, sublimity
of language, the power to excite every kind of
emotion, and the appropriate treatment of character,
while minds that have become jaded owing to the
daily wear and tear of the courts will find refreshment in such agreeable study. Consequently Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Arch.</hi>
                        12.
                    </note>
                    recommends the relaxation provided by the reading
of poetry.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    We should, however, remember that the
orator must not follow the poets in everything, more
especially in their freedom of language and their
license in the use of figures. Poetry has been compared to the oratory of display, and further aims
solely at giving pleasure, which it seeks to secure by
inventing what is not merely untrue, but sometimes
even incredible.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    Further, we must bear in mind
that it can be defended on the ground that it is tied
by certain metrical necessities and consequently cannot always use straightforward and literal language,
but is driven from the direct road to take refuge in
certain by-ways of expression; and compelled not
merely to change certain words, but to lengthen,
contract, transpose or divide them, whereas the
orator stands armed in the forefront of the battle,
fights for a high stake and devotes all his effort to
winning the victory.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    And yet I would not have his
weapons defaced by mould and rust, but would have
them shine with a splendour that shall strike terror
to the heart of the foe, like the flashing steel that
dazzles heart and eye at once, not like the gleam of
gold or silver, which has no warlike efficacy and is
even a positive peril to its wearer.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    History, also, may provide the orator with a nutriment which we may compare to some rich and
pleasant juice. But when we read it, we must
                    <pb xml:id="p.21"/>
                    remember that many of the excellences of the historian
require to be shunned by the orator. For history
has a certain affinity to poetry and may be regarded
as a kind of prose poem, while it is written for the
purpose of narrative, not of proof, and designed from
beginning to end not for immediate effect or the
instant necessities of forensic strife, but to record
events for the benefit of posterity and to win glory
for its author. Consequently, to avoid monotony of
narrative, it employs unusual words and indulges in
a freer use of figures.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, as I have already
said,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">IV. ii. 45.</note>
                    the famous brevity of Sallust, than which
nothing can be more pleasing to the leisured ear of
the scholar, is a style to be avoided by the orator in
view of the fact that his words are addressed to a
judge who has his mind occupied by a number of
thoughts and is also frequently uneducated, while,
on the other hand, the milky fullness of Livy is
hardly of a kind to instruct a listener who looks not
for beauty of exposition, but for truth and credibility.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    We must also remember that Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        30
                        <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    thinks that not
even 'Thucydidcs or Xenophon will be of much service to an orator, although he regards the style of
the former as a veritable call to arms and considers
that the latter was the mouthpiece of the Muses.
It is, however, occasionally permissible to borrow the
graces of history to embellish our digressions, provided always that we remember that in those portions
of our speech which deal with the actual question
at issue we require not the swelling thews of the
athlete, but the wiry sinews of the soldier, and that
the cloak of many colours which Demetrius of
Phalerum
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        § 80.
                    </note>
                    was said to wear is but little suited to
the dust and heat of the forum.
                    <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>
                    There is, it is true,
                    <pb xml:id="p.23"/>
                    another advantage which we may derive from the
historians, which, however, despite its great importance, has no bearing on our present topic; I refer to
the advantage derived from the knowledge of historical facts and precedents, with which it is most desirable that our orator should be acquainted; for such
knowledge will save him from having to acquire all
his evidence from his client and will enable him to
draw much that is germane to his case from the
careful study of antiquity. And such arguments will
be all the more effective, since they alone will be
above suspicion of prejudice or partiality.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/>
                    The fact that there is so much for which we must
have recourse to the study of the philosophers is
the fault of orators who have abandoned
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        I
                        <hi rend="italic">Pref.</hi>
                        11.
                    </note>
                    to them
the fullest portion of their own task. The Stoics
more especially discourse and argue with great
keenness on what is just, honourable, expedient
and the reverse, as well as on the problems of
theology, while the Socratics give the future orator
a first-rate preparation for forensic debates and
the examination of witnesses.
                    <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>
                    But we must use the
same critical caution in studying the philosophers
that we require in reading history or poetry; that
is to say, we must bear in mind that, even when we
are dealing with the same subjects, there is a wide
difference between forensic disputes and philosophical
discussions, between the law-courts and the lecture-room, between the precepts of theory and the perils
of the bar.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="37" unit="section"/>
                    Most of my readers will, I think, demand that,
since I attach so much importance to reading, I
should include in this work some instructions as to
what authors should be read and what their special
                    <pb xml:id="p.25"/>
                    excellences may be. To do this in detail would be
an endless task.
                    <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>
                    Remember that Cicero in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Brutus,</hi>
                    after writing pages and pages on the subject
of Roman orators alone, says nothing of his own contemporaries with the exception of Caesar and Marcellus. What limit, then, would there be to my
labours if I were to attempt to deal with them and
with their successors and all the orators of Greece as
well?
                    <milestone n="39" unit="section"/>
                    No, it was a safer course that Livy adopted
in his letter to his son, where he writes that he should
read Cicero and Demosthenes and then such orators
as most resembled them. Still,
                    <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>
                    I must not conceal
my own personal convictions on this subject. I believe
that there are few, indeed scarcely a single one of
those authors who have stood the test of time who will
not be of some use or other to judicious students, since
even Cicero himself admits that he owes a great debt
even to the earliest writers, who for all their talent
were totally devoid of art.
                    <milestone n="41" unit="section"/>
                    And my opinion about
the moderns is much the same. For how few of them
are so utterly crazy as not to have the least shadow
of hope that some portion or other of their work may
have claims upon the memory of posterity? If there
is such an one, he will be detected before we have
perused many lines of his writings, and we shall
escape from him before the experiment of reading
him has cost us any serious loss of time.
                    <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>
                    On the
other hand, not everything that has some bearing on
some department of knowledge will necessarily be of
service for the formation of style, with which we are
for the moment concerned.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Before, however, I begin to speak of individual
authors, I must make a few general remarks about
the variety of judgments which have been passed
                    <pb xml:id="p.27"/>
                    upon them.
                    <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
                    For there are some who think that only
the ancients should be read and hold that they are
the sole possessors of natural eloquence and manly
vigour; while others revel in the voluptuous and
affected style of to-day, in which everything is designed to charm the ears of the uneducated majority.
                    <milestone n="44" unit="section"/>
                    And even if we turn to those who desire to follow
the correct methods of style, we shall find that some
think that the only healthy and genuinely Attic style
is to be found in language which is restrained and
simple and as little removed as possible from the
speech of every day, while others are attracted by a
style which is more elevated and full of energy and
animation. There are, too, not a few who are devoted to a gentle, elegant and harmonious style. Of
these different ideals I shall speak in greater detail,
when I come to discuss the question of the particular
styles best suited to oratory.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        XI. x. 63
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    For the moment I
shall restrict myself to touching briefly on what the
student who desires to consolidate his powers of
speaking should seek in his reading and to what kind
of reading he should devote his attention. My design is merely to select a few of the most eminent
authors for consideration.
                    <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>
                    It will be easy for the
student to decide for himself what authors most
nearly resemble these: consequently, no one will
have any right to complain if I pass over some of his
favourites. For I will readily admit that there are
more authors worth reading than those whom I propose to mention. But I will now proceed to deal
with the various classes of reading which I consider
most suitable for those who are ambitious of becoming
orators.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="46" unit="section"/>
                    I shall, I think, be right in following the principle
                    <pb xml:id="p.29"/>
                    laid down by Aratus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Arat.
                        <hi rend="italic">Phaen. 1.</hi>
                    </note>
                    in the line,
                    <quote>With Jove let us begin,</quote>
                    and in beginning with Homer. He is like
his own conception of Ocean,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        xxi. 196.
                    </note>
                    which he describes as
the source of every stream and river; for he has
given us a model and an inspiration for every
department of eloquence. It will be generally admitted that no one has ever surpassed him in the
sublimity with which he invests great themes or the
propriety with which he handles small. He is at
once luxuriant and concise, sprightly and serious,
remarkable at once for his fullness and his brevity,
and supreme not merely for poetic, but for oratorical
power as well.
                    <milestone n="47" unit="section"/>
                    For, to say nothing of his eloquence,
which he shows in praise, exhortation and consolation, do not the ninth book containing the embassy
to Achilles, the first describing the quarrel between
the chiefs, or the speeches delivered by the counsellors in the second, display all the rules of art
to be followed in forensic or deliberative oratory?
                    <milestone n="48" unit="section"/>
                    As regards the emotions, there can be no one so illeducated as to deny that the poet was the master of all,
tender and vehement alike. Again, in the few lines
with which he introduces both of his epics, has he
not, I will not say observed, but actually established
the law which should govern the composition of the
exordium? For, by his invocation of the goddesses
believed to preside over poetry he wins the goodwill
of his audience, by his statement of the greatness
of his themes he excites their attention and renders
them receptive by the briefness of his summary.
                    <milestone n="49" unit="section"/>
                    Who can narrate more briefly than the hero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Antilochus,
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        xviii. 18.
                    </note>
                    who
brings the news of Patroclus' death, or more vividly
than he
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Phoenix,
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        ix. 529.
                    </note>
                    who describes the battle between the
Curetes and the Aetolians? Then consider his
                    <pb xml:id="p.31"/>
                    similes, his amplifications, his illustrations, digressions, indications of fact, inferences, and all the
other methods of proof and refutation which he
employs. They are so numerous that the majority
of writers on the principles of rhetoric have gone to
his works for examples of all these things.
                    <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
                    And as
for perorations, what can ever be equal to the prayers
which Priam addresses to Achilles
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Il.</hi>
                        xxiv. 486
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    when he comes
to beg for the body of his son? Again, does he not
transcend the limits of human genius in his choice
of words, his reflexions, figures, and the arrangement
of his whole work, with the result that it requires a
powerful mind, I will not say to imitate, for that is
impossible, but even to appreciate his excellences?
                    <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                    But he has in truth outdistanced all that have come
after him in every department of eloquence, above
all, he has outstripped all other writers of epic, the
contrast in their case being especially striking owing
to the similarity of the material with which they
deal.
                    <milestone n="52" unit="section"/>
                    Hesiod rarely rises to any height, while a
great part of his works is filled almost entirely with
names
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Especially the
                        <hi rend="italic">Theogony.</hi>
                    </note>
                    : none the less, his maxims of moral wisdom
provide a useful model, the smooth flow of his
words and structure merit our approval, and he
is assigned the first place among writers of the
intermediate style.
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, Antimachus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Antimachus of Colophon (
                        <hi rend="italic">flor. circ.</hi>
                        405 B.C.), author of
a Thebaid.
                    </note>
                    deserves praise for the vigour, dignity and elevation of his language. But although practically all
teachers of literature rank him second among epic
poets, he is deficient in emotional power, charm, and
arrangement of matter, and totally devoid of real
art. No better example can be found to show what
a vast difference there is to being near another
writer and being second to him.
                    <milestone n="54" unit="section"/>
                    Panyasis
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Uncle of Herodotus, author of a Heracleia.</note>
                    is
                    <pb xml:id="p.33"/>
                    regarded as combining the qualities of the last two
poets, being their inferior in point of style, but
surpassing Hesiod in the choice of his subject and
Antimachus in its arrangement. Apollonius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Apollonius of Rhodes, author of the Argonautica. The
list to which reference is made consisted of the four poets
just mentioned, with the addition of Pisandros, for whom
see § 56.
                    </note>
                    is not
admitted to the lists drawn up by the professors
of literature, because the critics, Aristarchus and
Aristophanes,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Aristophanes of Byzantium.</note>
                    included no contemporary poets.
None the less, his work is by no means to be
despised, being distinguished by the consistency
with which he maintains his level as a representative of the intermediate type.
                    <milestone n="55" unit="section"/>
                    The subject
chosen by Aratus is lifeless and monotonous, affording no scope for pathos, description of character,
or eloquent speeches. However, he is adequate for
the task to which he felt himself equal. Theocritus
is admirable in his own way, but the rustic and
pastoral muse shrinks not merely from the forum,
but from town-life of every kind.
                    <milestone n="56" unit="section"/>
                    I think I hear
my readers on all sides suggesting the names of
hosts of other poets. What? Did not Pisandros
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">A Rhodian poet of the seventh century B.C.</note>
                    tell the story of Hercules in admirable style?
Were there not good reasons for Virgil and Macer
taking Nicander
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Nicander of Colophon (second century B.C.), author of
didactic poems, Theriaca and Alexipharmaca and Metamorphoses (
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">e(teroiou/mena</foreign>
                        ). Virgil imitated him in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Georgics,</hi>
                        Aenilius Macer, the friend of Ovid, in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Theriaca.</hi>
                    </note>
                    as a model? Are we to ignore
Euphorion?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Euphorion of Chalcis (220 B.C. ) wrote elaborate short
epics. See
                        <hi rend="italic">Ecl.</hi>
                        x. 50. The words are, however, put into
the mouth of Gallus with reference to his own imitations of
Euphorion.
                    </note>
                    Unless Virgil had admired him, he
would never have mentioned
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>verses written in Chalcidic strain</quote>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Eclogues.</hi>
                    Again, had Horace no justification
for coupling the name of Tyrtacus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See Hor.
                        <hi rend="italic">A. P.</hi>
                        401. Tyrtaeus, writer of war songs
(seventh century B.C.).
                    </note>
                    with that of
Homer?
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/>
                    To which I reply, that there is no one so
ignorant of poetic literature that he could not, if he
chose, copy a catalogue of such poets from some
                    <pb xml:id="p.35"/>
                    library for insertion in his own treatises. I can
therefore assure my readers that I am well aware
of the existence of the poets whom I pass over in
silence, and am far from condemning them, since I
have already said that some profit may be derived
from every author.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§ 45.</note>
                    <milestone n="58" unit="section"/>
                    But we must wait till our
powers have been developed and established to the
full before we turn to these poets, just as at banquets
we take our fill of the best fare and then turn
to other food which, in spite of its comparative
inferiority, is still attractive owing to its variety.
Not until our taste is formed shall we have leisure
to study the elegiac poets as well. Of these, Callimachus is regarded as the best, the second place
being, according to the verdict of most critics,
occupied by Philetas.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Philetas of Cos (290 B.C.).</note>
                    <milestone n="59" unit="section"/>
                    But until we have acquired
that assured facility of which I spoke,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">x. i. 1.</note>
                    we must
familiarise ourselves with the best writers only and
must form our minds and develop an appropriate tone
by reading that is deep rather than wide. Consequently, of the three writers of iambics
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>
                        invective. The other two writers are Simonides of
Amorgos and Hipponax of Ephesus. Archilochus (
                        <hi rend="italic">fl.</hi>
                        686 B.C.).
                    </note>
                    approved by
the judgment of Aristarchus, Archilochus will be far
the most useful for the formation of the facility in
question.
                    <milestone n="60" unit="section"/>
                    For he has a most forcible style, is full of
vigorous, terse and pungent reflexions, and overflowing with life and energy: indeed, some critics
think that it is due solely to the nature of his
subjects, and not to his genius, that any poets are to
be ranked above him.
                    <milestone n="61" unit="section"/>
                    Of the nine lyric poets
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The five not mentioned here are Aleman, Sappho, Ibycus,
Anacreon and Bacchylides.
                    </note>
                    Pindar is by far the greatest, in virtue of his inspired
magnificence, the beauty of his thoughts and figures,
the rich exuberance of his language and matter,
and his rolling flood of eloquence, characteristics
which, as Horace
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Od.</hi>
                        IV. ii. 1.
                    </note>
                    rightly held, make him
                    <pb xml:id="p.37"/>
                    inimitable.
                    <milestone n="62" unit="section"/>
                    The greatness of the genius of Stesichorus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Stesichorus of Himera in Sicily (
                        <hi rend="italic">flor. circ.</hi>
                        600 B.C.),
wrote in lyric verse on many legends, more especially on
themes connected with the Trojan war.
                    </note>
                    is shown by his choice of subject: for he sings of the
greatest wars and the most glorious of chieftains,
and the music of his lyre is equal to the weighty
themes of epic poetry. For both in speech and
action he invests his characters with the dignity
which is their due, and if he had only been capable
of exercising a little more restraint, he might,
perhaps, have proved a serious rival to Homer.
But he is redundant and diffuse, a fault which,
while deserving of censure, is nevertheless a defect
springing from the very fullness of his genius.
                    <milestone n="63" unit="section"/>
                    Alcaeus has deserved the compliment of being said
to make music with
                    <hi rend="italic">quill of gold</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Hor
                        <hi rend="italic">Od.</hi>
                        <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                        xiii. 26. Alcaeus of Mitylene (
                        <hi rend="italic">circa</hi>
                        600
B.C.).
                    </note>
                    in that portion
of his works in which he attacks the tyrants of his
day and shows himself a real moral force. He is,
moreover, terse and magnificent in style, while the
vigour of his diction resembles that of oratory. But
he also wrote poetry of a more sportive nature and
stooped to erotic poetry, despite his aptitude for
loftier themes.
                    <milestone n="64" unit="section"/>
                    Simonides
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Simondes of Ceos. 556–468 B.C., famous for all forms of
lyric poetry, especially funeral odes.
                    </note>
                    wrote in a simple style,
but may be recommended for the propriety and
charm of his language. His chief merit, however,
lies in his power to excite pity, so much so, in fact,
that some rank him in this respect above all writers
of this class of poetry.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="65" unit="section"/>
                    The old comedy is almost the only form of poetry
which preserves intact the true grace of Attic
diction, while it is characterized by the most eloquent freedom of speech, and shows especial power
in the denunciation of vice; but it reveals great
force in other departments as well. For its style
is at once lofty, elegant and graceful, and if we
except Homer, who, like Achilles among warriors,
                    <pb xml:id="p.39"/>
                    is beyond all comparison, I am not sure that there
is any style which bears a closer resemblance to
oratory or is better adapted for forming the orator.
                    <milestone n="66" unit="section"/>
                    There are a number of writers of the old comedy,
but the best are Aristophanes, Eupolis and Cratinus.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Contemporaries: Cratinus (519–422), Aristophanes (448–
380), Eupolis (446–410).
                    </note>
                    Aeschylus was the first to bring tragedy into
prominence: he is lofty, dignified, grandiloquent
often to a fault, but frequently uncouth and inharmonious. Consequently, the Athenians allowed
later poets to revise his tragedies and to produce
them in the dramatic contests, and many succeeded
in winning the prize by such means.
                    <milestone n="67" unit="section"/>
                    Sophocles
and Euripides, however, brought tragedy to far
greater perfection: they differ in style, but it is
much disputed as to which should be awarded the
supremacy, a question which, as it has no bearing
on my present theme, I shall make no attempt to
decide. But this much is certain and incontrovertible, that Euripides will be found of far greater service
to those who are training themselves for pleading in
court.
                    <milestone n="68" unit="section"/>
                    For his language, although actually censured
by those who regard the dignity, the stately
stride and sonorous utterance of Sophocles as being
more sublime, has a closer affinity to that of oratory,
while he is full of striking reflexions, in which,
indeed, in their special sphere, he rivals the
philosophers themselves, and for defence and attack may be compared with any orator that has
won renown in the courts. Finally, although admirable in every kind of emotional appeal, he is
easily supreme in the power to excite pity.
                    <milestone n="69" unit="section"/>
                    Menander, as he often testifies in his works, had
a profound admiration for Euripides, and imitated
him, although in a different type of work. Now,
                    <pb xml:id="p.41"/>
                    the careful study of Menander alone would, in my
opinion, be sufficient to develop all those qualities
with the production of which my present work
is concerned; so perfect is his representation of
actual life, so rich is his power of invention and
his gift of style, so perfectly does he adapt himself
to every kind of circumstance, character and emotion.
                    <milestone n="70" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed, those critics are no fools who think
the speeches attributed to Charisius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A contemporary of Demosthenos; his speeches have not
survived, but were considered to resemble those of Lysias.
                    </note>
                    were in reality
written by Menander. But I consider that he shows
his power as an orator far more clearly in his
comedies; since assuredly we can find no more
perfect models of every oratorical quality than the
judicial pleadings of his Epitrepontes,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The greater portion of the Epitrepontes has been recovered from a papyrus. The other plays are lost. The
names may be translated:
                        <quote>The Arbitrators,</quote>
                        <quote>The Heiress,</quote>
                        <quote>The Locri,</quote>
                        <quote>The Timid Man,</quote>
                        <quote>The Lawgiver,</quote>
                        <quote>The Changeling.</quote>
                    </note>
                    Epicleros
and Locri, or the declamatory speeches in the Psophodes, Nomothetes. and Hypobolimaeus.
                    <milestone n="71" unit="section"/>
                    Still, for
my own part, I think that he will be found even more
useful by declaimers, in view of the fact that they
have, according to the nature of the various controversial themes, to undertake a number of different
roles and to impersonate fathers, sons, soldiers,
peasants, rich men and poor, the angry man and
the suppliant, the gentle and the harsh. And all
these characters are treated by this poet with
consummate appropriateness.
                    <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed, such is his
supremacy that he has scarce left a name to other
writers of the new comedy, and has cast them into
darkness by the splendour of his own renown.
Still, you will find something of value in the other
comic poets as well, if you read them in not too
critical a spirit; above all, profit may be derived
from the study of Philemon,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Philemon of Soli (360–262); Menader of Athens (342–
290).
                    </note>
                    who, although it was
                    <pb xml:id="p.43"/>
                    a depraved taste which caused his contemporaries
often to prefer him to Menander, has none the
less deserved the second place which posterity has
been unanimous in awarding him.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="73" unit="section"/>
                    If we turn to history, we shall find a number of
distinguished writers; but there are two who must
undoubtedly be set far above all their rivals: their
excellences are different in kind, but have won
almost equal praise. Thucydides is compact in
texture, terse and ever eager to press forward: Herodotus is pleasant, lucid and diffuse: the former
excels in vigour, speeches and the expression of the
stronger passions; the latter in charm, conversations
and the delineation of the gentler emotions.
                    <milestone n="74" unit="section"/>
                    Theopompus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Theopompus of Chios, born about 378 B.C., wrote a
history of Greece (
                        <hi rend="italic">Hellenica</hi>
                        ) from close of Peloponnesian war
to 394 B.C., and a history of Greece in relation to Philip of
Macedon (
                        <hi rend="italic">Philippica</hi>
                        ). His master, Isocrates, urged him to
write history.
                    </note>
                    comes next, and though as a historian he
is inferior to the authors just mentioned, his style
has a greater resemblance to oratory, which is not
surprising, as he was an orator before he was urged
to turn to history. Philistus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Philistus of Syracuse, born about 430 B.C., wrote a
history of Sicily.
                    </note>
                    also deserves special
distinction among the crowd of later historians, good
though they may have been: he was an imitator of
Thucydides, and though far his inferior, was somewhat more lucid. Ephorus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Ephorus of Cumae,
                        <hi rend="italic">flor. circ.</hi>
                        340 B.C., wrote a universal
history. He was a pupil of Isocrates.
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        II. viii. 11.
                    </note>
                    according to Isocrates,
needed the spur.
                    <milestone n="75" unit="section"/>
                    Clitarchus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Clitarchus of Megara wrote a history of Persia and of
Alexander, whose contemporary he was.
                    </note>
                    has won approval by
his talent, but his accuracy has been impugned.
Timagenes
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Timagenes, a Syrian of the Augustan age, wrote a
history of Alexander and his successors.
                    </note>
                    was born long after these authors, but
deserves our praise for the very fact that he revived
the credit of history, the writing of which had fallen
into neglect. I have not forgotten Xenophon, but
he will find his place among the philosophers.
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.45"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="76" unit="section"/>
                    There follows a vast army of orators, Athens alone
having produced ten remarkable orators
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Antiphon, Andocides, Lysias (flor. 403–380), Isocrates
(435–338), Isacus, Demosthenes, Aeschines, Lycargus,
Hyperides and Dinarchus.
                    </note>
                    in the
same generation. Of these Dermosthenes is far the
greatest: indeed he came to be regarded almost as
the sole pattern of oratory. Such is the force and
compactness of his language, so muscular his style,
so free from tameness and so self-controlled, that
you will find nothing in him that is either too much
or too little.
                    <milestone n="77" unit="section"/>
                    The style of Aesehines is fuller and
more diffuse, while his lack of restraint gives an
appearance of grandeur. But he has more flesh and
less muscle. Hyperides has extraordinary charm and
point, but is better qualified, not to say more useful,
for cases of minor importance.
                    <milestone n="78" unit="section"/>
                    Lysias belongs to an
earlier generation than those whom I have just
mentioned. He has subtlety and elegance and, if
the orator's sole duty were merely to instruct, it
would be impossible to conceive greater perfection.
For there is nothing irrelevant or far-fetched in his
speeches. None the less I would compare him to a
clear spring rather than to a mighty river.
                    <milestone n="79" unit="section"/>
                    Isocrates
was an exponent of a different style of oratory: he is
neat and polished and better suited to the fencingschool than to the battlefield. He elaborated all the
graces of style, nor was he without justification. For
lie had trained himself for the lecture-room and not
the law-courts. He is ready in invention, his moral
ideals are high and the care which he bestows upon
his rhythm is such as to be a positive fault.
                    <milestone n="80" unit="section"/>
                    I do
not regard these as the sole merits of the orators of
whom I have spoken, but have selected what seemed
to me their chief excellences, while those whom I
have passed over in silence were far from being
indifferent. In fact, I will readily admit that the
                    <pb xml:id="p.47"/>
                    famous Demetrius of Phalerum,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Governed Athens as Cassander's vicegerent 317–307:
then tied to Egypt, where he died in 283.
                    </note>
                    who is said to
have been the first to set oratory on the downward path, was a man of great talent and eloquence
and deserves to be remembered, if only for the
fact that he is almost the last of the Attic
school who can be called an orator: indeed Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        ii. 95.
                        <hi rend="italic">Orat. 92.</hi>
                        The
                        <quote>intermediate</quote>
                        style is
that which lies between the
                        <quote>grand</quote>
                        and the
                        <quote>plain</quote>
                        styles.
                    </note>
                    prefers him to all other orators of the intermediate
school.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="81" unit="section"/>
                    Proceeding to the philosophers, from whom Cicero
acknowledges that he derived such a large portion
of his eloquence, we shall all admit that Plato is
supreme whether in acuteness or perception or in
virtue of his divine gift of style, which is worthy of
Homer. For he soars high above the levels of
ordinary prose or, as the Greeks call it, pedestrian
language, and seems to me to be inspired not by
mere human genius, but, as it were, by the oracles
of the god of Delphi.
                    <milestone n="82" unit="section"/>
                    Why should I speak of the
unaffected charm of Xenophon, so far beyond the
power of affectation to attain? The Graces themselves seem to have moulded his style, and we may
with the utmost justice say of him, what the writer
of the old comedy
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Eupolis,
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">peiqw/ tis e)peka/qizen e)pi\ toi=s xei/lesin.</foreign>
                    </note>
                    said of Pericles, that the goddess
of persuasion sat enthroned upon his lips.
                    <milestone n="83" unit="section"/>
                    Why
should I dwell on the elegance of the rest of the
Socratics? or on Aristotle,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <quote>Sweet</quote>
                        is the last epithet to be applied to the
surviving works of Aristotle. But Dionysius of Halicarnassus
and Cicero praise him no less warmly, referring, no doubt,
to works that are lost.
                    </note>
                    with regard to whom I
hesitate whether to praise him more for his knowledge, for the multitude of his writings, the sweetness of his style, the penetration revealed by his
discoveries or the variety of the tasks which he
                    <pb xml:id="p.49"/>
                    essayed? In Theophrastus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Theophrastus, Aristotle's successor as head of his school
(322–287). Diogenes Laertius (v. 38) says that his real name
was Tyrtamus, but that Aristotle called him Theophrastus
because of the
                        <quote>divine qualities of his style</quote>
                        (
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">fra/sis</foreign>
                        ).
                    </note>
                    we find such a superhuman brilliance of style that his name is said to be
derived therefrom.
                    <milestone n="84" unit="section"/>
                    The ancient Stoics indulged
their eloquence comparatively little. Still, they
pleaded the cause of virtue, and the rules which
they laid down for argument and proof have been of
the utmost value. But they showed themselves
shrewd thinkers rather than striking orators, which
indeed they never aimed at being.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="85" unit="section"/>
                    I now come to Roman authors, and shall follow
the same order in dealing with them. As among
Greek authors Homer provided us with the most
auspicious opening, so will Virgil among our own.
For of all epic poets, Greek or Roman, he, without
doubt, most nearly approaches to Homer.
                    <milestone n="86" unit="section"/>
                    I will
repeat the words which I heard Domitius Afer use
in my young days. I asked what poet in his opinion
came nearest to Homer, and he replied,
                    <quote>Virgil comes second, but is nearer first than third.</quote>
                    And
in truth, although we must needs bow before the
immortal and superhuman genius of Homer, there
is greater diligence and exactness in the work
of Virgil just because his task was harder. And
perhaps the superior uniformity of the Roman's excellence balances Homer's pre-eminence in his outstanding passages.
                    <milestone n="87" unit="section"/>
                    All our other poets follow a long
way in the rear. Macer and Lucretius are, it is true,
worth reading, but not for the purpose of forming
style, that is to say, the body of eloquence: both
deal elegantly with their themes, but the former is
tame and the latter difficult. The poems by which
Varro of Atax
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Varro of Atax in Gaul (82–37 B.C. ) was specially famous
for his translation of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Argontautica</hi>
                        of Apollonius Rhodius.
he also wrote didactic poetry and historical epic.
                    </note>
                    gained his reputation were translations, but he is by no means to be despised, although
his diction is not sufficiently rich to be of much
                    <pb xml:id="p.51"/>
                    service in developing the resources of eloquence.
                    <milestone n="88" unit="section"/>
                    Ennius deserves our reverence, but only as those
groves whose age has made them sacred, but whose
huge and ancient trunks inspire us with religious
awe rather than with admiration for their beauty.
There are other poets who are nearer in point of
time and more useful for our present purpose. Ovid
has a lack of seriousness even when he writes epic
and is unduly enamoured of his own gifts, but
portions of his work merit our praise.
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/>
                    On the other
hand, although Cornelius Severus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Friend and contemporary of Ovid. A considerable fragment is preserved by Sen.
                        <hi rend="italic">Suas.</hi>
                        vi. 26. The Sicilian War
was the war with Sextus Pompeius (38–36) and perhaps
formed a portion of a larger work on the Civil War. The
surviving fragment deals with the death of Cicero. The
                        <hi rend="italic">priunus liber</hi>
                        may therefore perhaps be the first book of this
larger work.
                    </note>
                    is a better versifier
than poet, yet if, as has been said, he had written his
poem on the Sicilian war in the same style throughout
as his first book, he would have had a just claim to the
second place. A premature death prevented the
powers of Serranus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Nothing is known of this poet except the name.</note>
                    from ripening to perfection, but
his youthful works reveal the highest talent and a
devotion to the true ideal of poetry, which is remarkable in one so young.
                    <milestone n="90" unit="section"/>
                    We have suffered serious loss
in the recent death of Valerius Flaccus. Saleius
Bassus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Nothing is known of this poet save that he is highly
praised by Tacitus in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Diblogues,</hi>
                        and was patronized by
Vespasian. The unfinished Argonautica of Valerius Flaccus
survives.
                    </note>
                    showed an ardent and genuinely poetic
genius, but, like that of Serranus, it was not
mellowed by years. Rabirius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A contemporary of Ovid, believed to be the author of a
fragment on the battle of Actium, found at Hereulaneum.
                    </note>
                    and Pedo
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        C. Albinovanns Pedo wrote a poem on the voyage of
Germanicus to the north of Germany. A fragment is preserved by Sen.
                        <hi rend="italic">Suas.</hi>
                        i. 14.
                    </note>
                    deserve
to be studied by those who have the time. Lucan
is fiery and passionate and remarkable for the
grandeur of his general reflexions, but, to be frank,
I consider that he is more suitable for imitation by
the orator than by the poet.
                    <milestone n="91" unit="section"/>
                    I have restricted my
list of poets to these names, because Germanicus
                    <pb xml:id="p.53"/>
                    Augustus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Domitian.</note>
                    has been distracted from the study of
poetry on which he had embarked by his care for
the governance of the world, and the gods have
thought it scarce worthy of his powers that he
should be the greatest of poets. But what can be
more sublime, more learned, more perfect in every
detail than those works to which he devoted himself
in the seclusion to which he retired after conferring
the supreme power upon his father and his brother?
Who could sing of war better than he who wages it
with such skill? To whom would the goddesses
that preside over literature sooner lend an ear? To
whom would Minerva, his familiar deity,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        He claimed to be the son of Minerva. It is doubtful if
he ever wrote any poetry. Cp. Tac
                        <hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi>
                        iv. 86, Suet.
                        <hi rend="italic">Dom.</hi>
                        2 and 20.
                    </note>
                    more
readily reveal her secrets?
                    <milestone n="92" unit="section"/>
                    Future ages shall tell of
these things more fully; to-day his glory as a poet
is dimmed by the splendour of his other virtues.
But you will forgive us, Caesar, who worship at the
shrine of literature, if we refuse to pass by your
achievements in silence and insist on testifying at
least that, as Virgil sings,
                </p>
                <quote rend="blockquote">
                    <cit>
                        <quote>
                            <l part="N">The ivy creeps amid your victor bays</l>
                        </quote>
                        <bibl default="false">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ecl.</hi>
                            viii. 13.
                        </bibl>
                    </cit>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="93" unit="section"/>
                    We also challenge the supremacy of the Greeks in
elegy. Of our elegiac poets Tibullus seems to me
to be the most terse and elegant. There are, however, some who prefer Propertius. Ovid is more
sportive than either, while Gallus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Cornelius (Gallus, the friend of Virgil, and the first distinguished writer of elegy at Rome.
                    </note>
                    is more severe.
Satire, on the other hand, is all our own. The first
of our poets to win renown in this connexion was
Lucilius, some of whose devotees are so enthusiastic
that they do not hesitate to prefer him not merely
to all other satirists, but even to all other poets.
I disagree with them as much as I do with Horace,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Sat.</hi>
                        I. iv. 11.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="94" unit="section"/>
                    who holds that Lucilius' verse has a
                    <quote>
                        muddy flow,
                        <pb xml:id="p.55"/>
                        and that there is always something in him that
might well be dispensed with.
                    </quote>
                    For his learning is
as remarkable as his freedom of speech, and it is
this latter quality that gives so sharp an edge and
such abundance of wit to his satire. Horace is far
terser and purer in style, and must be awarded the
first place, unless my judgment is led astray by my
affection for his work. Persius also, although he
wrote but one book, has acquired a high and
well-deserved reputation, while there are other
distinguished satirists still living whose praises will
be sung by posterity.
                    <milestone n="95" unit="section"/>
                    There is, however, another
and even older type of satire which derives its
variety not merely from verse, but from an admixture of prose as well. Such were the satires
composed by Terentius Varro,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        His Menippean Satires, of which only fragments survive.
Although ostensibly an imitation of the work of the Greek
Menippus of Gadara, they can still be said to belong to the
older type of satire, the
                        <quote>medley</quote>
                        or
                        <quote>hotch-potch.</quote>
                    </note>
                    the most learned
of all Romans. He composed a vast number of
erudite works, and possessed an extraordinary knowledge of the Latin language, of all antiquity and
of the history of Greece and Rome. But he is
an author likely to contribute more to the knowledge of the student than to his eloquence.
                    <milestone n="96" unit="section"/>
                    The
iambic has not been popular with Roman poets as a
separate form of composition, but is found mixed up
with other forms of verse.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The meaning is not clear. The words may mean (i that
these writers did not confine themselves to the
                        <hi rend="italic">iambus,</hi>
                        or
(iii that the
                        <hi rend="italic">iambus</hi>
                        alternates with other metres, cp.
                        <hi rend="italic">epodos</hi>
                        below.
                    </note>
                    It may be found in all
its bitterness in Catullus, Bibaculus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        M. Furius Bibaculus, contemporary of Catullus, and
writer of similar invective against the Caesareans.
                    </note>
                    and Horace,
although in the last-named the iambic is interrupted
by the epode.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">i.</hi>
                        e. the short iambic line interposed between the trimeters.
                    </note>
                    Of our lyric writers Horace is almost
the sole poet worth reading: for he rises at times to
a lofty grandeur and is full of sprightliness and
charm, while there is great variety in his figures, and
his boldness in the choice of words is only equalled
by his felicity. If any other lyric poet is to be
mentioned, it will be Caesius Bassus, who has but
                    <pb xml:id="p.57"/>
                    lately passed from us. But he is far surpassed in
talent by poets still living.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="97" unit="section"/>
                    Among writers of tragedy Accius and Pacuvius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Accius (170 90), Pacuvius (220–132).</note>
                    are most remarkable for the force of their general
reflexions, the weight of their words and the dignity
of their characters. But they lack polish, and filed
to put the finishing touches on their works, although
the fault was perhaps rather that of the times in
which they lived than of themselves. Accius is
generally regarded as the most vigorous, while those
who lay claim to learning regard Pacuvius as the
more learned of the two.
                    <milestone n="98" unit="section"/>
                    The Thyestes of Varius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        L. Varius Rufus, friend of Virgil and Horace, editor of
the
                        <hi rend="italic">Aeneid;</hi>
                        wrote epic and a single tragedy.
                    </note>
                    is a match for any Greek tragedy, and the Medea
of Ovid shows, in my opinion, to what heights that
poet might have risen if he had been ready to curb
his talents instead of indulging them. Of the
tragic writers whom I myself have seen, Pomponius
Secundus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Pomponius Secundus, died 60 A.D.; wrote a tragedy
entitled
                        <hi rend="italic">Aeneas.</hi>
                    </note>
                    is by far the best: his older critics thought
him insufficiently tragic, but admitted his eminence as
far as learning and polish were concerned.
                    <milestone n="99" unit="section"/>
                    Comedy
is our weakest point. Although Varro quotes Aelius
Stilo
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The first Roman philologist (141–70 B.C.).</note>
                    as saying that if the Muses wished to speak
Latin, they would use the language of Plautus,
although the ancients extol Caecilius,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Caecilils (219–166), Terence (194159), Afranius (flor.
circ. 150). Only fragments of Caecilius and Afranius remain.
                    </note>
                    and although
Scipio Africanus is credited with the works of
Terence (which are the most elegant of their kind,
and would be still more graceful if the poet had
confined himself to the iambic trimeter),
                    <milestone n="100" unit="section"/>
                    we still
scarcely succeed in reproducing even a faint shadow
of the charm of Greek comedy. Indeed, it seems
to me as though the language of Rome were incapable of reproducing that graceful wit which was
                    <pb xml:id="p.59"/>
                    granted to Athens alone, and was beyond the reach
of other Greek dialects to achieve. Afranius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Caecilils (219–166), Terence (194–159), Afranius (flor.
cire. 150) Only fragments of Caecilius and Afanius survive.
                    </note>
                    excels
in the purely Roman comedy, but it is to be regretted
that he revealed his own character by defiling his
plots with the introduction of indecent paederastic
intrigues.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="101" unit="section"/>
                    In history, however, we hold our own with the
Greeks. I should not hesitate to match Saillst
against Thucydides, nor would Herodotus resent
Titus Livius being placed on the same level as himself. For the latter has a wonderful charm and
transparency in narrative, while his speeches are
eloquent beyond description; so admirably adapted
is all that is said both to the circumstances and the
speaker; and as regards the emotions, especially
the more pleasing of them, I may sum him up by
saying that no historian has ever depicted them to
greater perfection.
                    <milestone n="102" unit="section"/>
                    Thus it is that, although by
different means, he has acquired no less fame than
has been awarded to the immortal rapidity of Sallust.
For I strongly approve of the saying of Servilius
Nonianus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Friend of Persius, and famous as orator, reciter and
historian; died 60 A.D.
                    </note>
                    that these historians were equal rather
than alike. Servilius, whom I myself have heard,
is himself remarkable for the force of his intellect,
and is full of general reflexions, but he is less restrained than the dignity of history demands.
                    <milestone n="103" unit="section"/>
                    But
that dignity is admirably maintained, thanks to his
style, by Aufidius Bassus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        He wrote a history of the empire down to the death of
Claudius. The work on the German war was probably a
separate work.
                    </note>
                    a slightly earlier writer,
especially in his work on the German war: he is
always praiseworthy, though at times he fails to do
his powers full justice.
                    <milestone n="104" unit="section"/>
                    But there still survives to
add lustre to this glorious age a man
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Probably Fabius Rusticus. Tacitus would have been too
young at this time to be mentioned in such terms.
                    </note>
                    worthy to be
remembered through all time: he is appreciated today, but after generations shall declare his name
                    <pb xml:id="p.61"/>
                    aloud. The bold utterances of Crenutius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Crenutius Cordus wrote a history of the Civil wars
and reign of Augustus. He was accused for his praise of
Brutus and Cassius, and committed suicide in A.D. 25. It
was he who called Cassius
                        <quote>the last of all the Romans.</quote>
                    </note>
                    also have
their admirers, and deserve their fame, though the
passages which brought him to his ruin have been
expurgated; still that which is left reveals a rich
store of lofty animation and fearless reflexions upon
life. There are other good writers as well, but I am
merely selecting from the different departments of
literature, not reviewing complete libraries.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="105" unit="section"/>
                    But it is our orators, above all, who enable us to
match our Roman eloquence against that of Greece.
For I would set Cicero against any one of their
orators without fear of refutation. I know well
enough what a storm I shall raise by this assertion,
more especially since I do not propose for the
moment
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See XII. i. 14
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                        , also XII x. 12
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    to compare him with Demosthenes; for
there would be no point in such a comparison, as I
consider that Demosthenes should be the object of
special study, and not merely studied, but even committed to memory.
                    <milestone n="106" unit="section"/>
                    I regard the excellences of these
two orators as being for the most part similar, that
is to say, their judgment, their gift of arrangement,
their methods of division, preparation and proof, as
well as everything concerned with invention. In
their actual style there is some difference. Demosthenes is more concentrated, Cicero more diffuse;
Demosthenes makes his periods shorter than Cicero,
and his weapon is the rapier, whereas Cicero's periods
are longer, and at times he employs the bludgeon as
well: nothing can be taken from the former, nor
added to the latter; the Greek reveals a more
studied, the Roman a more natural art.
                    <milestone n="107" unit="section"/>
                    As regards
wit and the power of exciting pity, the two most
powerful instruments where the feelings are concerned, we have the advantage. Again, it is possible
                    <pb xml:id="p.63"/>
                    that Demosthenes was deprived by national custom
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        xvi. 4; vi i 7 Quintilian refers to an alleged
law at Athens forbidding appeals to the emotion.
                    </note>
                    of the opportunity of producing powerful perorations, but against this may be set the fact that the
different character of the Latin language debars us
from the attainment of those qualities which are
so much admired by the adherents of the Attic
school. As regards their letters, which have in
both cases survived, and dialogues, which Demosthenes never attempted, there can be no comparison
between the two.
                    <milestone n="108" unit="section"/>
                    But, on the other hand, there is
one point in which the Greek has the undoubted
superiority: he comes first in point of time, and it
was largely due to him that Cicero was able to attain
greatness. For it seems to me that Cicero, who
devoted himself heart and soul to the imitation of
the Greeks, succeeded in reproducing the force of
Demosthenes, the copious flow of Plato, and the
charm of Isocrates.
                    <milestone n="109" unit="section"/>
                    But he did something more
than reproduce the best elements in each of these
authors by dint of careful study; it was to himself
that he owed most of, or rather all his excellences,
which spring from the extraordinary fertility of his
immortal genius. For he does not, as Pindar
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">The quotation is not found in Pindar's extant works.</note>
                    says,
                    <quote>collect the rain from heaven, but wells forth with living water,</quote>
                    since Providence at his birth conferred
this special privilege upon him, that eloquence should
make trial of all her powers in him.
                    <milestone n="110" unit="section"/>
                    For who can
instruct with greater thoroughness, or more deeply
stir the emotions? Who has ever possessed such a
gift of charm? He seems to obtain as a boon what
in reality he extorts by force, and when he wrests
the judge from the path of his own judgment, the
latter seems not to be swept away, but merely to
follow.
                    <milestone n="111" unit="section"/>
                    Further, there is such weight in all that he
                    <pb xml:id="p.65"/>
                    says that his audience feel ashamed to disagree with
him, and the zeal of the advocate is so transfigured
that it has the effect of the sworn evidence of a
witness, or the verdict of a judge. And at the same
time all these excellences, of which scarce one could
be attained by the ordinary man even by the most
concentrated effort, flow from him with every appearance of spontaneity, and his style, although no fairer
has ever fallen on the ears of men, none the less
displays the utmost felicity and ease.
                    <milestone n="112" unit="section"/>
                    It was not,
therefore, without good reason that his own contemporaries spoke of his
                    <quote>sovereignty</quote>
                    at the bar, and
that for posterity the name of Cicero has come to be
regarded not as the name of a man, but as the name
of eloquence itself. Let us, therefore, fix our eyes on
him, take him as our pattern, and let the student realise
that he has made real progress if he is a passionate
admirer of Cicero.
                    <milestone n="113" unit="section"/>
                    Asinius Pollio
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Asinius Pollio (75 B.C.—A.D. 4), the friend of Virgil,
distinguished as poet, historian and orator.
                    </note>
                    had great gifts of
invention and great precision of language (indeed,
some think him too precise), while his judgment
and spirit were fully adequate. But he is so far from
equalling the polish and charm of Cicero that he
might have been born a generation before him.
Messala,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        M. Valerius Corvinus (64 B.C.—A.D. 8), the friend of
Tibullus and distinguished as an orator.
                    </note>
                    on the other hand, is polished and transparent and displays his nobility in his utterance,
but he fails to do his powers full justice.
                    <milestone n="114" unit="section"/>
                    As
for Gaius Caesar, if he had had leisure to devote
himself to the courts, he would have been the one
orator who could have been considered a serious rival
to Cicero. Such are his force, his penetration and
his energy that we realise that he was as vigorous in
speech as in his conduct of war. And yet all these
qualities are enhanced by a marvellous elegance of
language, of which he was an exceptionally zealous
                    <pb xml:id="p.67"/>
                    student.
                    <milestone n="115" unit="section"/>
                    Caelius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        M. Rufus Caelius, defended by Cicero in the
                        <hi rend="italic">pro Catlio.</hi>
                        Killed in 48 B.C.
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp.</hi>
                        IV. ii. 123.: VII. i. 53.
                    </note>
                    has much natural talent and much
wit, more especially when speaking for the prosecution, and deserved a wiser mind and a longer life.
I have come across some critics who preferred
Calvus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Calvus ((Gaius Licinius), a distinguish poet and. with
Brutus, the leading orator of the Attic School. He died
at the age of 34 in 48 B.C.
                    </note>
                    to all other orators, and others again who
agreed with Cicero that too severe self-criticism had
robbed him of his natural vigour. But he was the
possessor of a solemn, weighty and chastened style,
which was also capable at times of genuine vehemence. He was an adherent of the Attic school and
an untimely death deprived him of his full meed of
honour, at least if we regard him as likely to have
acquired fresh qualities.
                    <milestone n="116" unit="section"/>
                    Servius Sulpicius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Servius Sulpicius Rufus, the greatest jurist of the
Ciecronian age.
                    </note>
                    acquired
a great and well-deserved reputation by his three
speeches. Cassius Severus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        assius Severus (
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
                        A.D. 34) banished by Augustus on
account of his scurrilous lampoons.
                    </note>
                    if read with discrimination, will provide much that is worthy of imitation:
if to his other merits he had added appropriateness
of tone and dignity of style,
                    <milestone n="117" unit="section"/>
                    he would deserve a
place among the greatest. For his natural talents
are great, his gift of bitterness, wit and passion
remarkable, but he allowed the sharpness of his
temper to prevail over his judgment. Moreover,
though his jests are pungent enough, this very
pungency often turned the laugh against himself.
                    <milestone n="118" unit="section"/>
                    There are many other clever speakers, but it
would be a long task to deal with them all. Domitius
Afer
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Domitius Afer (
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi>
                        59 A.D.), the leading orator of the
reigns of Tiberius and his successors.
                    </note>
                    and Julius Africanus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Iulius Africanus, a Gaul, who flourished in the reign of
Nero.
                    </note>
                    are by far the most distinguished. The former is superior in art and in
every department of oratory, indeed he may he
ranked with the old orators without fear of
                    <pb xml:id="p.69"/>
                    contradiction. The latter shows greater energy, but is too
great a precisian in the choice of words, prone to
tediously long periods and somewhat extravagant in
his metaphors. There have been distinguished
talents even of more recent date.
                    <milestone n="119" unit="section"/>
                    For example,
Trachalus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        M. Galerius Trachalus (cos. (18 A.D.)
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp</hi>
                        XII v. 5
                    </note>
                    was, as a rule, elevated and sufficiently
clear in his language: one realised that his aims
were high, but he was better to listen to than to
read. For his voice was, in my experience, unique
in its beauty of tone, while his delivery would have
done credit to an actor, his action was full of grace
and he possessed every external advantage in profusion. Vibius Crispus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Vibius Crispus, a
                        <hi rend="italic">delator</hi>
                        under Nero, died about A.D.
90, after acquiring great wealth.
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp. Juv.</hi>
                        iv. 81–93.
                    </note>
                    again, was well-balanced,
agreeable and born to charm, though he was better
in private than in public cases.
                    <milestone n="120" unit="section"/>
                    Julius Secundus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Julius Secundus, a distinguished orator of the reign of
Vespasian. One of the characters in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Dialogus</hi>
                        of Tacitus.
                    </note>
                    had he lived longer, would undoubtedly have attained
a great and enduring reputation. For he would have
acquired, as he was actually acquiring, all that was
lacking to his qualities, namely, a far greater
pugnacity and a closer attention to substance as well
as form.
                    <milestone n="121" unit="section"/>
                    But, in spite of the untimeliness of his end,
he occupies a high place, thanks to his fluency, the
grace with which he set forth whatever he desired,
the lucidity, smoothness and beauty of his speech,
the propriety revealed in the use of words, even
when employed figuratively, and the point which
characterises even his most hazardous expressions.
                    <milestone n="122" unit="section"/>
                    Subsequent writers on the history of oratory will
find abundant material for praise among the orators
who flourish to-day: for the law courts can boast
a glorious wealth of talent. Indeed, the consummate advocates of the present day are serious
rivals of the ancients, while enthusiastic effort
and lofty ideals lead many a young student
                    <pb xml:id="p.71"/>
                    to tread in their footsteps and imitate their
excellence.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="123" unit="section"/>
                    I have still to deal with writers on philosophy,
of whom Rome has so far produced but few who are
distinguished for their style. But Cicero, who is
great in every department of literature, stands out
as the rival of Plato in this department as well.
Brutus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Brutus, omitted from Qauintilian's list of orators, was a
follower of the Stoic and Academic schools. He is known
to have written treatises on Virtue, Duty and Patience.
                    </note>
                    was an admirable writer on such themes, in
which he distinguished himself far more than in his
speeches: he is equal to the serious nature of his
subject, and the reader realises that he feels what
he says.
                    <milestone n="124" unit="section"/>
                    Cornelius Celsus,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        An encyclopedic writer under Augustus and Tiberius.
His medical treatises have survived. He wrote on oratory
also, and is not infrequently quoted by Quintilian.
                    </note>
                    a follower of the Sextii,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The Sextii, father and son, were Pythagorean philosophers of the Augustan age, with something of a Stoic
tendency as well.
                    </note>
                    wrote a number of philosophical works, which have
considerable grace and polish. Among the Stoics
Plautus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">123</note>
                    is useful as giving a knowledge of the
subject.
                    <milestone n="125" unit="section"/>
                    Among the Epicureans Catius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A contemporary of Cicero, who speaks of him somewhat
contemptuously. He wrote four books
                        <hi rend="italic">de rerum matura et de summo bono.</hi>
                    </note>
                    is agreeable to read, though lacking in weight. I have
deliberately postponed the discussion of Seneca in
connexion with the various departments of literature
owing to the fact that there is a general, though
false, impression that I condemn and even detest
him. It is true that I had occasion to pass censure upon him when I was endeavouring to recall
students from a depraved style, weakened by every
kind of error, to a severer standard of taste.
                    <milestone n="126" unit="section"/>
                    But
at that time Seneca's works were in the hands
of every young man, and my aim was not to ban his
reading altogether, but to prevent his being preferred to authors superior to himself, but whom he
was never tired of disparaging; for, being conscious
of the fact that his own style was very different
                    <pb xml:id="p.73"/>
                    from theirs, he was afraid that he would fail to
please those who admired them. But the young
men loved him rather than imitated him, and fell
as far below him as he fell below the ancients.
                    <milestone n="127" unit="section"/>
                    For
I only wish they had equalled or at least approached
his level. But he pleased them for his faults alone,
and each individual sought to imitate such of those
faults as lay within his capacity to reproduce: and
then brought reproach on his master by boasting
that he spoke in the genuine Senecan manner.
                    <milestone n="128" unit="section"/>
                    Seneca had many excellent qualities, a quick and
fertile intelligence with great industry and wide
knowledge, though as regards the last quality he
was often led into error by those whom he had
entrusted with the task of investigating certain
subjects on his behalf.
                    <milestone n="129" unit="section"/>
                    He dealt with almost every
department of knowledge; for speeches, poems,
letters and dialogues all circulate under his name.
In philosophy he showed a lack of critical power,
but was none the less quite admirable in his
denunciations of vice. His works contain a number
of striking general reflexions and much that is
worth reading for edification; but his style is for
the most part corrupt and exceedingly dangerous,
for the very reason that its vices are so many and
attractive.
                    <milestone n="130" unit="section"/>
                    One could wish that, while he relied on
his own intelligence, he had allowed himself to be
guided by the taste of others. For if he had only
despised all unnatural expressions and had not been
so passionately fond of all that was incorrect, if he
had not felt such affection for all that was his own,
and had not impaired the solidity of his matter by
striving after epigrammatic brevity, he would have
won the approval of the learned instead of the
                    <pb xml:id="p.75"/>
                    enthusiasm of boys.
                    <milestone n="131" unit="section"/>
                    But even as it is, he deserves
to be read by those whose powers have been formed
and firmly moulded on the standards of a severer
taste, if only because he will exercise their critical
faculties in distinguishing between his merits and
his defects. For, as I have said, there is much in
him which we may approve, much even that we may
admire. Only we must be careful in our selection:
would he had been as careful himself. For his
genius deserved to be devoted to better aims, since
what it does actually aim at, it succeeds in achieving.
                </p>
                <p>
                    II. It is from these and other authors worthy of
our study that we must draw our stock of words, the
variety of our figures and our methods of composition,
while we must form our minds on the model of every
excellence. For there can be no doubt that in art
no small portion of our task lies in imitation, since,
although invention came first and is all-important, it
is expedient to imitate whatever has been invented
with success.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    And it is a universal rule of life that
we should wish to copy what we approve in others.
It is for this reason that boys copy the shapes of
letters that they may learn to write, and that
musicians take the voices of their teachers, painters
the works of their predecessors, and peasants the
principles of agriculture which have been proved in
practice, as models for their imitation. In fact, we
may note that the elementary study of every branch
of learning is directed by reference to some definite
standard that is placed before the learner.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    We
must, in fact, either be like or unlike those who
have proved their excellence. It is rare for nature
to produce such resemblance, which is more often
the result of imitation. But the very fact that in
                    <pb xml:id="p.77"/>
                    every subject the procedure to be followed is so
much more easy for us than it was for those who
had no model to guide them, is a positive drawback,
unless we use this dubious advantage with caution
and judgment.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The first point, then, that we must realise is that
imitation alone is not sufficient, if only for the reason
that a sluggish nature is only too ready to rest
content with the inventions of others. For what
would have happened in the days when models were
not, if men had decided to do and think of nothing
that they did not know already? The answer is
obvious: nothing would ever have been discovered.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Why, then, is it a crime for us to discover something
new? Were primitive men led to make so many
discoveries simply by the natural force of their
imagination, and shall we not then be spurred on to
search for novelty by the very knowledge that those
who sought of old were rewarded by success?
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    And
seeing that they, who had none to teach them anything, have handed down such store of knowledge
to posterity, shall we refuse to employ the experience
which we possess of some things, to discover yet
other things, and possess nought that is not owed to
the beneficent activity of others? Shall we follow
the example of those painters whose sole aim is to
be able to copy pictures by using the ruler and the
measuring rod?
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The reference is to copying by dividing the surface of
the picture to be copied, and of the material on which the
copy is to be made, into a number of equal squares.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    It is a positive disgrace to be
content to owe all our achievement to imitation.
For what, I ask again, would have been the result
if no one had done more than his predecessors?
Livius Andronicus
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Livius Andronicus, a slave from Tareotum, was the
founder of Latin poetry. He translated the
                        <hi rend="italic">Odyssey,</hi>
                        and
produced the first Latin comedy and tragedy composed in
Greek metres (240 B.C.)
                    </note>
                    would mark our supreme
achievement in poetry and the annals of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Pontifices</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The Annales Maximi kept by the Pontifex Maximus,
containing the list of the consul and giving a curt summary
of the events of each consulate.
                    </note>
                    would be our
                    <hi rend="italic">ne plus ultra</hi>
                    in history. We
                    <pb xml:id="p.79"/>
                    should still be sailing on rafts, and the art of painting
would be restricted to tracing a line round a shadow
thrown in the sunlight.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Cast your eyes over the
whole of history; you will find that no art has
remained just as it was when it was discovered, nor
come to a standstill at its very birth, unless indeed
we are ready to pass special condensation on our
own generation on the ground that it is so barren of
invention that no further development is possible;
and it is undoubtedly true that no development is
possible for those who restrict themselves to imitation.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    But if we are forbidden to add anything to
the existing stock of knowledge, how can we ever
hope for the birth of our ideal orator? For of all
the greatest orators with whom we are as yet acquainted, there is not one who has not some
deficiency or blemish. And even those who do
not aim at supreme excellence, ought to press
toward the mark rather than be content to follow
in the tracks of others.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For the man whose aim
is to prove himself better than another, even if he
does not surpass him, may hope to equal him. But
he can never hope to equal him, if he thinks it his
duty merely to tread in his footsteps: for the mere
follower must always lag behind. Further, it is
generally easier to make some advance than to
repeat what has been done by others, since there
is nothing harder than to produce an exact likeness,
and nature herself has so far failed in this endeavour
that there is always some difference which enables
us to distinguish even the things which seem most
like and most equal to one another.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Again, whatever is like another object, must necessarily be
inferior to the object of its imitation, just as the
                    <pb xml:id="p.81"/>
                    shadow is inferior to the substance, the portrait to
the features which it portrays, and the acting of the
player to the feelings which he endeavours to reproduce. The same is true of oratory. For the models
which we select for imitation have a genuine and
natural force, whereas all imitation is artificial and
moulded to a purpose which was not that of the
original orator.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    This is the reason why declamations
have less life and vigour than actual speeches, since
the subject is fictitious in the one and real in the
other. Again, the greatest qualities of the orator
are beyond all imitation, by which I mean, talent,
invention, force, facility and all the qualities which
are independent of art.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, there are
many who, after excerpting certain words from
published speeches or borrowing certain particular
rhythms, think that they have produced a perfect
copy of the works which they have read, despite
the fact that words become obsolete or current
with the lapse of years, the one sure standard being
contemporary usage; and they are not good or
bad in virtue of their inherent nature (for in themselves they are no more than mere sounds), but
solely in virtue of the aptitude and propriety (or
the reverse) with which they are arranged, while
rhythmical composition must be adapted to the
theme in hand and will derive its main charm from
its variety.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently the nicest judgment is required in
the examination of everything connected with this
department of study. First we must consider whom
to imitate. For there are many who have shown a
passionate desire to imitate the worst and most
decadent authors. Secondly, we must consider what
                    <pb xml:id="p.83"/>
                    it is that we should set ourselves to imitate in the
authors thus chosen.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For even great authors have
their blemishes, for which they have been censured
by competent critics and have even reproached each
other. I only wish that imitators were more likely
to improve on the good things than to exaggerate
the blemishes of the authors whom they seek to
copy. And even those who have sufficient critical
acumen to avoid the faults of their models will not
find it sufficient to produce a copy of their merits,
amounting to no more than a superficial resemblance,
or rather recalling those sloughs which, according to
Epicurus, are continually given off by material things.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Epicurus held that all sense-perception was caused by
the impact of such atomic sloughs:
                        <hi rend="italic">cp. Lucret.</hi>
                        iv. 42 sqq.
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    But this is just what happens to those who mould
themselves on the first impressions derived from the
style of their model, without devoting themselves to
a thorough investigation of its good qualities, and,
despite the brilliance of their imitation and the close
resemblance of their language and rhythm, not only
fail absolutely to attain the force of style and invention
possessed by the original, but as a rule degenerate
into something worse, and achieve merely those faults
which are hardest to distinguish from virtues: they
are turgid instead of grand, bald instead of concise,
and rash instead of courageous, while extravagance
takes the place of wealth, over-emphasis the place of
harmony and negligence of simplicity.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    As a result,
those who flaunt tasteless and insipid thoughts,
couched in an uncouth and inharmonious form, think
that they are the equals of the ancients; those who
lack ornament and epigram, pose as Attic; those
who darken their meaning by the abruptness with
which they close their periods, count themselves the
superiors of Sallust and Thucydides; those who are
                    <pb xml:id="p.85"/>
                    dreary and jejune, think that they are serious rivals
to Pollio, while those who are tame and listless, if
only they can produce long enough periods, swear
that this is just the manner in which Cicero would
have spoken.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    I have known some who thought that
they had produced a brilliant imitation of the style
of that divine orator, by ending their periods with
the phrase
                    <hi rend="italic">esse videatur.</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">cp.</hi>
                        ix. iv. 73.
                        <hi rend="italic">Tac.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Dial.</hi>
                        23.
                    </note>
                    Consequently it is of the
first importance that every student should realise
what it is that he is to imitate, and should know
why it is good.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The next step is for each student to consult his
own powers when he shoulders his burden. For
there are some things which, though capable of
imitation, may be beyond the capacity of any given
individual, either because his natural gifts are insufficient or of a different character. The man whose
talent is for the plain style should not seek only
what is bold and rugged, nor yet should he who has
vigour without control suffer himself through love of
subtlety at once to waste his natural energy and
fail to attain the elegance at which he aims: for
there is nothing so unbecoming as delicacy wedded
to ruggedness.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    True, I did express the opinion
that the instructor whose portrait I painted in my
second book,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Ch. 8.</note>
                    should not confine himself to teaching
those things for which he perceived his individual
pupils to have most aptitude. For it is his further
duty to foster whatever good qualities he may perceive in his pupils, to make good their deficiencies
as far as may be, to correct their faults and turn
them to better things. For he is the guide and
director of the minds of others. It is a harder task
to mould one's own nature.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    But not even our
                    <pb xml:id="p.87"/>
                    ideal teacher, however much he may desire that
everything that is correct should prevail in his
school to the fullest extent, will waste his labour in
attempting to develop qualities to the attainment of
which he perceives nature's gifts to be opposed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    It is also necessary to avoid the fault to which the
majority of students are so prone, namely, the idea
that in composing speeches we should imitate the
poets and historians, and in writing history or poetry
should copy orators and declaimers.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    Each branch
of literature has its own laws and its own appropriate
character. Comedy does not seek to increase its
height by the buskin and tragedy does not wear
the slipper of comedy. But all forms of eloquence
have something in common, and it is to the imitation
of this common element that our efforts should be
confined.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    There is a further fault to which those persons
are liable who devote themselves entirely to the
imitation of one particular style: if the rude vigour
of some particular author takes their fancy, they
cling to it even when the case on which they are
engaged calls for an easy and flowing style; if, on
the other hand, it is a simple or agreeable style that
claims their devotion, they fail to meet the heavy
demands of severe and weighty cases. For not only
do cases differ in their general aspect, but one part
of a case may differ from another, and some things
require a gentle and others a violent style, some
require an impetuous and others a calm diction, while
in some cases it is necessary to instruct and in others
to move the audience, in all these instances dissimilar and different methods being necessary.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently I should be reluctant even to advise a
                    <pb xml:id="p.89"/>
                    student to select one particular author to follow
through thick and thin. Demosthenes is by far the
most perfect of Greek orators, yet there are some
things which others have said better in some contexts
as against the many things which he has said better
than others. But it does not follow that because we
should select one author for special imitation, he
should be our only model. What then?
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Is it not
sufficient to model our every utterance on Cicero?
For my own part, I should consider it sufficient, if
I could always imitate him successfully. But what
harm is there in occasionally borrowing the vigour of
Caesar, the vehemence of Caelius, the precision of
Pollio or the sound judgment of Calvus?
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    For quite
apart from the fact that a wise man should always,
if possible, make whatever is best in each individual
author his own, we shall find that, in view of the
extreme difficulty of our subject, those who fix their
eyes on one model only will always find some one
quality which it is almost impossible to acquire therefrom. Consequently, since it is practically impossible
for mortal powers to produce a perfect and complete
copy of any one chosen author, we shall do well to
keep a number of different excellences before our
eyes, so that different qualities from different authors
may impress themselves on our minds, to be adopted
for use in the place that becomes them best.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    But imitation (for I must repeat this point again
and again) should not be confined merely to words.
We must consider the appropriateness with which
those orators handle the circumstances and persons
involved in the various cases in which they were
engaged, and observe the judgment and powers of
arrangement which they reveal, and the manner
                    <pb xml:id="p.91"/>
                    in which everything they say, not excepting those
portions of their speeches which seem designed
merely to delight their audience, is concentrated on
securing the victory over their opponents. We must
note their procedure in the exordium, the method
and variety of their statement of facts, the power
displayed in proof and refutation, the skill revealed
in their appeal to every kind of emotion, and the
manner in which they make use of popular applause
to serve their case, applause which is most honourable when it is spontaneous and not deliberately
courted. If we have thoroughly appreciated all these
points, we shall be able to imitate our models with
accuracy.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    But the man who to these good qualities
adds his own, that is to say, who makes good deficiencies and cuts down whatever is redundant, will
be the perfect orator of our search; and it is now
above all times that such perfection should be
attained when there are before us so many more
models of oratorical excellence than were available
for those who have thus far achieved the highest
success. For this glory also shall be theirs, that
men shall say of them that while they surpassed
their predecessors, they also taught those who came
after.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Such are the aids which we may derive from
external sources; as regards those which we must
supply for ourselves, it is the pen which brings at
once the most labour and the most profit. Cicero is
fully justified in describing it as the best producer
and teacher of eloquence, and it may be noted
that in the
                    <hi rend="italic">de Oratore</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        i. 150.
                    </note>
                    he supports his own
judgment by the authority of Lucius Crassus, in
whose mouth he places this remark.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    We must
                    <pb xml:id="p.93"/>
                    therefore write as much as possible and with the
utmost care. For as deep ploughing makes the soil
more fertile for the production and support of crops,
so, if we improve our minds by something more than
mere superficial study, we shall produce a richer
growth of knowledge and shall retain it with greater
accuracy. For without the consciousness of such
preliminary study our powers of speaking extempore
will give us nothing but an empty flow of words,
springing from the lips and not from the brain.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    It
is in writing that eloquence has its roots and foundations, it is writing that provides that holy of holies
where the wealth of oratory is stored, and whence it
is produced to meet the demands of sudden emergencies. It is of the first importance that we should
develop such strength as will not faint under the
toil of forensic strife nor be exhausted by continual
use.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For it is an ordinance of nature that nothing
great can be achieved in a moment, and that all the
fairest tasks are attended with difficulty, while on
births as well she has imposed this law, that the
larger the animal, the longer should be the period of
gestation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    There are, however, two questions which present
themselves in this connexion, namely, what should
be our method and what the subjects on which
we write, and I propose to treat them in this
order.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    At first, our pen must be slow yet sure: we
must search for what is best and refuse to give a
joyful welcome to every thought the moment that
it presents itself; we must first criticise the fruits of
our imagination, and then, once approved, arrange
them with care. For we must select both thoughts
and words and weigh them one by one. This done,
                    <pb xml:id="p.95"/>
                    we must consider the order in which they should be
placed, and must examine all the possible varieties
of rhythm, refusing necessarily to place each word in
the order in which it occurs to us.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    In order to do
this with the utmost care, we must frequently revise
what we have just written. For beside the fact that
thus we secure a better connexion between what
follows and what precedes, the warmth of thought
which has cooled down while we were writing is
revived anew, and gathers fresh impetus from going
over the ground again. We may compare this protess with what occurs in jumping matches. The
competitors take a longer run and go at full speed
to clear the distance which they aim at covering;
similarly, in throwing the javelin, we draw back our
arms, and in archery pull back the bow-string to
propel the shaft.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    At times, however, we may
spread our sails before the favouring breeze, but we
must beware that this indulgence does not lead us
into error. For we love all the offspring of our
thought at the moment of their birth; were that
not so, we should never commit them to writing.
But we must give them a critical revision, and go
carefully over any passage where we have reason to
regard our fluency with suspicion.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    It is thus, we
are told, that Sallust wrote, and certainly his works
give clear evidence of the labour which he expended
on them. Again, we learn from Varius that Virgil
composed but a very small number of verses every
day.
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    It is true that with orators the case is somewhat different, and it is for this reason that I
enjoin such slowness of speed and such anxious care
at the outset. For the first aim which we must fix
in our minds and insist on carrying into execution
                    <pb xml:id="p.97"/>
                    is to write as well as possible; speed will come with
practice. Gradually thoughts will suggest themselves with increasing readiness, the words will
answer to our call and rhythmical arrangement will
follow, till everything will be found fulfilling its
proper function as in a well-ordered household.
The sum of the whole matter is this:
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    write quickly
and you will never write well, write well and you
will soon write quickly. But it is just when we
have acquired this facility that we must pause awhile
to look ahead and, if I may use the metaphor, curb
the horses that would run away with us. This will
not delay our progress so much as lend us fresh
vigour. For I do not think that those who have
acquired a certain power in writing should be condemned to the barren pains of false self-criticism.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    How can anyone fulfil his duties as an advocate if he
wastes his time in putting unnecessary finish on each
portion of his pleadings? There are some who are
never satisfied. They wish to change everything
they have written and to put it in other words.
They are a diffident folk, and deserve but ill of their
own talents, who think it a mark of precision to cast
obstacles in the way of their own writing.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is it
easy to say which are the most serious offenders, those
who are satisfied with everything or those who are
satisfied with nothing that they write. For it is
of common occurrence with young men, however
talented they may be, to waste their gifts by superfluous elaboration, and to sink into silence through
an excessive desire to speak well. I remember in
this connexion a story that Julius Secundus, my contemporary, and, as is well known, my very dear friend,
a man with remarkable powers of eloquence, but
                    <pb xml:id="p.99"/>
                    with an infinite passion for precision, told me of the
words once used to him by his uncle,
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Julius Florus,
the leading orator of Gaul, for it was there that he
practised, a man eloquent as but few have ever
been, and worthy of his nephew. He once noticed
that Secundus, who was still a student, was looking
depressed, and asked him the meaning of his frowns.
The youth made no concealment of the reason:
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    he
had been working for three days, and had been unable, in spite of all his efforts, to devise an exordium
for the theme which he had been given to write,
with the result that he was not only vexed over
his immediate difficulty, but had lost all hope of
future success. Florus smiled and said,
                    <quote>Do you really want to speak better than you can?</quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    There
lies the truth of the whole matter. We must aim
at speaking as well as we can, but must not try to
speak better than our nature will permit. For to
make any real advance we need study, not selfaccusation. And it is not merely practice that will
enable us to write at greater length and with
increased fluency, although doubtless practice is
most important. We need judgement as well. So
long as we do not he back with eyes turned up to the
ceiling, trying to fire our imagination by muttering
to ourselves, in the hope that something will present
itself, but turn our thoughts to consider what the
circumstances of the case demand, what suits the
characters involved, what is the nature of the occasion and the temper of the judge, we shall acquire
the power of writing by rational means. It is thus
that nature herself bids us begin and pursue our
studies once well begun.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    For most points are of a
definite character and, if we keep our eyes open,
                    <pb xml:id="p.101"/>
                    will spontaneously present themselves. That is the
reason why peasants and uneducated persons do not
beat about the bush to discover with what they
should begin, and our hesitation is all the more
shameful if it is simply the result of education.
We must not, therefore, persist in thinking that
what is hard to find is necessarily best; for, if it
seems to us that there is nothing to be said except
that which we are unable to find, we must say
nothing at all.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    On the other hand, there is a fault
which is precisely the opposite of this, into which
those fall who insist on first making a rapid draft
of their subject with the utmost speed of which
their pen is capable, and write in the heat and
impulse of the moment. They call this their rough
copy. They then revise what they have written,
and arrange their hasty outpourings. But while
the words and the rhythm may be corrected, the
matter is still marked by the superficiality resulting
from the speed with which it was thrown together.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    The more correct method is, therefore, to exercise
care from the very beginning, and to form the
work from the outset in such a manner that it
merely requires to be chiselled into shape, not
fashioned anew. Sometimes, however, we must
follow the stream of our emotions, since their
warmth will give us more than any diligence can
secure.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    The condemnation which I have passed on such
carelessness in writing will make it pretty clear what
my views are on the luxury of dictation which
is now so fashionable. For, when we write, however
great our speed, the fact that the hand cannot follow
the rapidity of our thoughts gives us time to think,
                    <pb xml:id="p.103"/>
                    whereas the presence of our amanuensis hurries us
on, and at times we feel ashamed to hesitate or
pause, or make some alteration, as though we were
afraid to display such weakness before a witness.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    As a result our language tends not merely to be
haphazard and formless, but in our desire to produce
a continuous flow we let slip positive improprieties
of diction, which show neither the precision of the
writer nor the impetuosity of the speaker. Again, if
the amanuensis is a slow writer, or lacking in intelligence, he becomes a stumbling-block, our speed is
checked, and the thread of our ideas is interrupted
by the delay or even perhaps by the loss of
temper to which it gives rise.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover, the
gestures which accompany strong feeling, and sometimes even serve to stimulate the mind, the waving
of the hand, the contraction of the brow, the
occasional striking of forehead or side, and those
which Persius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">i. 106.</note>
                    notes when he describes a trivial
style as one that
                    <quote rend="blockquote">
                        <l part="N">
                            <quote>Thumps not the desk nor smacks of bitten nails,</quote>
                        </l>
                    </quote>
                    all these become ridiculous, unless we are alone,
Finally,
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    we come to the most important consideration of all, that the advantages of privacy are lost
when we dictate. Everyone, however, will agree
that the absence of company and deep silence are
most conducive to writing, though I would not go
so far as to concur in the opinion of those who think
woods and groves the most suitable localities for
the purpose, on the ground that the freedom of
the sky and the charm of the surroundings produce
sublimity of thought and wealth of inspiration.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    Personally I regard such an environment as a
                    <pb xml:id="p.105"/>
                    pleasant luxury rather than a stimulus to study.
For whatever causes us delight, must necessarily
distract us from the concentration due to our work.
The mind cannot devote its undivided and sincere
attention to a number of things at the same time,
and wherever it turns its gaze it must cease to
contemplate its appointed task.
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, the
charm of the woods, the gliding of the stream, the
breeze that murmurs in the branches, the song of
birds, and the very freedom with which our eyes
may range, are mere distractions, and in my opinion
the pleasure which they excite is more likely to
relax than to concentrate our attention.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    Demosthenes took a wiser view; for he would retire to
a place
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        An underground room. See Plut.
                        <hi rend="italic">Dem.</hi>
                        vii.
                    </note>
                    where no voice was to be heard, and no
prospect greeted the sight, for fear that his eyes
might force his mind to neglect its duty. Therefore, let the burner of the midnight oil seclude
himself in the silence of night, within closed doors,
with but a solitary lamp to light his labours.
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    But
for every kind of study, and more especially for
night work, good health and its chief source, simple
living, are essential; for we have fallen into the
habit of devoting to relentless labour the hour which
nature has appointed for rest and relaxation. From
those hours we must take only such time as is superfluous for sleep, and will not be missed.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    For fatigue
will make us careless in writing, and the hours of
daylight are amply sufficient for one who has no
other distractions. It is only the busy man who
is driven to encroach on the hours of darkness.
Nevertheless, night work, so long as we come to it
fiesh and untired, provides by far the best form of
privacy.
                </p>
                <pb xml:id="p.107"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    But although silence and seclusion and absolute
freedom of mind are devoutly to be desired, they
are not always within our power to attain. Consequently we must not fling aside our book at once,
if disturbed by some noise, and lament that we
have lost a day: on the contrary, we must make
a firm stand against such inconveniences, and train
ourselves so to concentrate our thoughts as to rise
superior to all impediments to study. If only you
direct all your attention to the work which you
have in hand, no sight or sound will ever penetrate
to your mind.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    If even casual thoughts often occupy
us to such an extent that we do not see passers-by,
or even stray from our path, surely we can obtain
the same result by the exercise of our will. We
must not give way to pretexts for sloth. For unless
we make up our mind that we must be fresh, cheerful and free from all other care when we approach our
studies, we shall always find some excuse for idleness.
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    Therefore, whether we be in a crowd, on a journey,
or even at some festive gathering, our thoughts should
always have some inner sanctuary of their own to
which they may retire. Otherwise what shall we
do when we are suddenly called upon to deliver
a set speech in the midst of the forum, with lawsuits in progress on every side, and with the sound
of quarrels and even casual outcries in our ears, if
we need absolute privacy to discover the thoughts
which we jot down upon our tablets? It was for
this reason that Demosthenes, the passionate lover
of seclusion, used to study on the seashore amid the
roar of the breakers that they might teach him not
to be unnerved by the uproar of the public assembly.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    There are also certain minor details which deserve
                    <pb xml:id="p.109"/>
                    our attention, for there is nothing too minute for the
student. It is best to write on wax owing to the
facility which it offers for erasure, though weak
sight may make it desirable to employ parchment
by preference. The latter, however, although of
assistance to the eye, delays the hand and interrupts
the stream of thought owing to the frequency with
which the pen has to be supplied with ink.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    But
whichever we employ, we must leave blank pages
that we may be free to make additions when we
will. For lack of space at times gives rise to a
reluctance to make corrections, or, at any rate, is
liable to cause confusion when new matter is
inserted. The wax tablets should not be unduly
wide; for I have known a young and over-zealous
student write his compositions at undue length,
because he measured them by the number of lines,
a fault which persisted, in spite of frequent admonition, until his tablets were changed, when it
disappeared.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Space must also be left for jotting
down the thoughts which occur to the writer out
of due order, that is to say, which refer to subjects
other than those in hand. For sometimes the most
admirable thoughts break in upon us which cannot
be inserted in what we are writing, but which, on
the other hand, it is unsafe to put by, since they are
at times forgotten, and at times cling to the memory
so persistently as to divert us from some other line
of thought. They are, therefore, best kept in
store.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    The next point which we have to consider is
the correction of our work, which is by far the most
useful portion of our study: for there is good reason
for the view that erasure is quite as important a
                    <pb xml:id="p.111"/>
                    function of the pen as actual writing. Correction
takes the form of addition, excision and alteration.
But it is a comparatively simple and easy task to
decide what is to be added or excised. On the
other hand, to prune what is turgid, to elevate
what is mean, to repress exuberance, arrange what
is disorderly, introduce rhythm where it is lacking,
and modify it where it is too emphatic, involves a
twofold labour. For we have to condemn what had
previously satisfied us and discover what had escaped
our notice.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    There can be no doubt that the best
method of correction is to put aside what we have
written for a certain time, so that when we return
to it after an interval it will have the air of novelty
and of being another's handiwork; for thus we may
prevent ourselves from regarding our writings with
all the affection that we lavish on a newborn child.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    But this is not always possible, especially in the case
of an orator who most frequently has to write for
immediate use, while some limit, after all, must be
set to correction. For there are some who return
to everything they write with the presumption that
it is full of faults and, assuming that a first draft
must necessarily be incorrect, think every change
an improvement and make some alteration as often
as they have the manuscript in their hands: they
are, in fact, like doctors who use the knife even
where the flesh is perfectly healthy. The result of
their critical activities is that the finished work is
full of scars, bloodless, and all the worse for their
anxious care.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    No! let there be something in all our writing which, if it does not actually please us,
at least passes muster, so that the file may only
polish our work, not wear it away. There must
                    <pb xml:id="p.113"/>
                    also be a limit to the time which we spend on its
revision. For the fact that Cinna
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        C. Helvius Cinna, the friend of Catullus. The Smyrna
was a short but exceptionally obscure and learned epic.
                    </note>
                    took nine years
to write his Smyrna, and that Isocrates required
ten years, at the lowest estimate, to complete his
Panegyric does not concern the orator, whose
assistance will be of no use, if it is so long
delayed.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    My next task is to indicate what those should
write whose aim is to acquire facility.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See x. i. 1. Ch. ix.</note>
                    At this part
of my work there is no necessity for me to set forth
the subjects which should be selected for writing,
or the order in which they should be approached,
since I have already done this in the first book,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Ch. iv.</note>
                    where I prescribed the sequence of studies for boys,
and in the second book, where I did the same for
young men. The point which concerns me now is
to show from what sources copiousness and facility
may most easily be derived.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Our earlier orators thought highly of translation
from Greek into Latin.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    In the
                    <hi rend="italic">de Oratore</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">i. 155.</note>
                    of
Cicero, Lucius Crassus says that he practised this
continually, while Cicero himself advocates it again
and again, nay, he actually published translations
of Xenophon and Plato,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        The (
                        <hi rend="italic">Economicus of</hi>
                        Xenophon, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Proutayorus</hi>
                        and
                        <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi>
                        of Plato.
                    </note>
                    which were the result of
this form of exercise. Messala likewise gave it his
approval, and we have a number of translations of
speeches from his hand; he even succeeded in
coping with the delicacy of Hyperides' speech in
defence of Phryne, a task of exceeding difficulty for
a Roman.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    The purpose of this form of exercise is
obvious. For Greek authors are conspicuous for the
variety of their matter, and there is much art in
all their eloquence, while, when we translate them,
we are at liberty to use the best words available,
                    <pb xml:id="p.115"/>
                    since all that we use are our very own.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>
                        we shall not borrow from our models, as we do in
paraphrasing Latin.
                    </note>
                    As regards
figures, too, which are the chief ornament of oratory,
it is necessary to think out a great number and variety
for ourselves, since in this respect the Roman idiom
differs largely from the Greek.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    But paraphrase from the Latin will also be of
much assistance, while I think we shall all agree that
this is specially valuable with regard to poetry;
indeed, it is said that the paraphrase of poetry was
the sole form of exercise employed by Sulpicius.
For the lofty inspiration of verse serves to elevate
the orator's style and the bold license of poetic
language does not preclude
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Lit.</hi>
                        <quote>forestall the power of using the language of ordinary prose.</quote>
                    </note>
                    our attempting to
render the same words in the language natural to
prose. Nay, we may add the vigour of oratory
to the thoughts expressed by the poet, make good
his omissions, and prune his diffuseness.
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    But I
would not have paraphrase restrict itself to the
bare interpretation of the original: its duty is
rather to rival and vie with the original in the
expression of the same thoughts. Consequently,
I disagree with those who forbid the student to
parahrase speeches of our own orators, on the
ground that, since all the best expressions have
already been appropriated, whatever we express
differently must necessarily be a change for the
worse. For it is always possible that we may discover expressions which are an improvement on
those which have already been used, and nature
did not make eloquence such a poor and starveling
thing, that there should be only one adequate
expression for any one theme.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    It can hardly be
argued that, while the gestures of the actor are
capable of imparting a wealth of varied meaning
                    <pb xml:id="p.117"/>
                    to the same words, the power of oratory is restricted
to a narrower scope, so that when a thing has once
been said, it is impossible to say anything else on
the same theme. Why, even if it be granted that
no new expression we discover can be better than
or even equal to the old, it may, at any rate, be
a good second.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Do we not often speak twice, or
even more frequently, on the same subject, sometimes even to the extent of a number of sentences
in succession? It will scarce be asserted that we
must not match ourselves against others when
we are permitted to match ourselves against ourselves. For if there were only one way in which
anything could be satisfactorily expressed, we
should be justified in thinking that the path to
success had been sealed to us by our predecessors.
But, as a matter of fact, the methods of expression
still left us are innumerable, and many roads lead
us to the same goal.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    Brevity and copiousness each
have their own peculiar grace, the merits of metaphor are one thing and of literalness another, and,
while direct expression is most effective in one case,
in another the best result is gained by a use of
figures. Further, the exercise is valuable in virtue
of its difficulty; and again, there is no better way of
acquiring a thorough understanding of the greatest
authors. For, instead of hurriedly running a careless
eye over their writings, we handle each separate
phrase and are forced to give it close examination,
and we come to realise the greatness of their excellence from the very fact that we cannot imitate
them.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Nor is it only the paraphrase of the works of
others that we shall find of advantage: much may
                    <pb xml:id="p.119"/>
                    be gained from paraphrasing our own words in a
number of different ways: for instance, we may
specially select certain thoughts and recast them
in the greatest variety of forms, just as a sculptor
will fashion a number of different images from the
same piece of wax.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    But it is the simplest subjects
which, in my opinion, will serve us best in our
attempt to acquire facility. For our lack of talent
may easily shelter itself behind the complicated
mass of detail presented by persons, cases, circumstances of time and place, words and deeds, since
the subjects which present themselves on all sides
are so many that it will always be possible to lay
hold of some one or other.
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    True merit is revealed
by the power to expand what is naturally compressed, to amplify what is small, to lend variety
to sameness, charm to the commonplace, and to
say a quantity of good things about a very limited
number of subjects.
                </p>
                <p>
                    For this purpose indefinite questions,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        See III. v. 5
                        <hi rend="italic">.sq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    of the kind
we call
                    <hi rend="italic">theses,</hi>
                    will be found of the utmost service:
in fact, Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ad Att.</hi>
                        IX. iv. 1.
                    </note>
                    still exercised himself upon such
themes after he had become the leading man in
the state.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Akin to these are the proof or refutation of general statements. For such statements
are a kind of decree or rule, and whatever problem
may arise from the thing, may equally arise from the
decision passed upon the thing. Then there are
commonplaces,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See II. i 9–11 and iv. 22.</note>
                    which, as we know, have often been
written by orators as a form of exercise. The man
who has practised himself in giving full treatment
to such simple and uncomplicated themes, will
assuredly find his fluency increased in those subjects
which admit of varied digression, and will be
                    <pb xml:id="p.121"/>
                    prepared to deal with any case that may confront him,
since all cases ultimately turn upon general questions.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    For what difference is there between the
special case where Cornelius,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See IV. iv. 8; v. xiii. 26; VI. v. 10; II. iii. 3, 35.</note>
                    the tribune of the
people, is charged with reading the text of a proposed law, and the general question whether it is
                    <hi rend="italic">lése-majestè</hi>
                    for a magistrate himself to read the
law which he proposes to the people; what does it
matter whether we have to decide whether Milo was
justified in killing Clodius, or whether it is justifiable to kill a man who has set an ambush for his
slayer, or a citizen whose existence is a danger to
the state, even though he has set no such ambush?
What difference is there between the question
whether it was an honourable act on the part of
Cato to make over Marcia to Hortensius, or whether
such an action is becoming to a virtuous man? It is
on the guilt or innocence of specific persons that
judgement is given, but it is on general principles
that the case ultimately rests.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    As for declamations
of the kind delivered in the schools of the rhetoricians, so long as they are in keeping with actual
life and resemble speeches, they are most profitable
to the student, not merely while he
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        profectus,
                        <hi rend="italic">lit.</hi>
                        <quote>progress,</quote>
                        abstract for concrete.
                    </note>
                    is still immature,
for the reason that they simultaneously exercise the
powers both of invention and arrangement, but even
when he has finished his education and acquired a
reputation in the courts. For they provide a richer
diet from which eloquence derives nourishment and
brilliance of complexion, and at the same time afford
a refreshing variety after the continuous fatigues
of forensic disputes.
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    For the same reason, the wealth
of language that marks the historian should be from
time to time imported into portions of our written
                    <pb xml:id="p.123"/>
                    exercises, and we should indulge in the easy freedom of dialogue. Nay, it may even be advantageous
to amuse ourselves with the writing of verse, just as
athletes occasionally drop the severe regime of diet
and exercise to which they are subjected and refresh
themselves by taking a rest and indulging in more
dainty and agreeable viands.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed, in my opinion,
one of the reasons why Cicero was enabled to shed
such glory upon the art of speaking is to be found
in his excursions to such bypaths of study. For if
all our material was drawn solely from actions at
law, our eloquence must needs lose its gloss, our
limbs grow stiff, and the keen edge of the intellect
be blunted by its daily combats.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    But although those who find their practice in the
contests of forensic warfare derive fresh strength
and repair their forces by means of this rich fare of
eloquence, the young should not be kept too long at
these false semblances of reality, nor should they be
allowed to become so familiar with these empty
shadows that it is difficult for them to leave them:
otherwise there is always the danger that, owing to
the seclusion in which they have almost grown
old, they will shrink in terror from the real perils
of public life, like men dazzled by the unfamiliar
sunlight.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed it is recorded that this fate
actually befell Marcus Porcius Latro, the first professor of rhetoric to make a name for himself; for
when, at the height of his fame in the schools, he was
called upon to plead a case in the forum, he put
forward the most earnest request that the court
should be transferred to some public hall. He was
so unaccustomed to speak in the open air that all his
eloquence seemed to reside within the compass of a
                    <pb xml:id="p.125"/>
                    roof and four walls.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    For this reason a young man
who has acquired a thorough knowledge from his
instructors of the methods of invention and style
(which is not by any means an endless task, if those
instructors have the knowledge and the will to
teach), and who has also managed to obtain a
reasonable amount of practice in the art, should
follow the custom in vogue with our ancestors, and
select some one orator to follow and imitate. He
should attend as many trials as possible and be a
frequent spectator of the conflicts in which he is
destined to take part.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Next he should write out
speeches of his own dealing either with the cases
which he has actually heard pleaded or with others,
provided always they be actual cases, and should
argue them from both sides, training himself with
the real weapons of his warfare, just as gladiators do
or as Brutus did in that speech in defence of Milo
which I have already mentioned.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. vi. 93; x. i. 23.</note>
                    This is better
than writing replies to old speeches, as Cestius did
to Cicero's defence of Milo in spite of the fact that,
his knowledge being confined to what was said for
the defence, he could not have possessed sufficient
acquaintance with the other side of the case.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    The young man, however, whom his instructor has
compelled to be as realistic as possible in declamation,
and to deal with every class of subject, instead of
merely selecting the easiest and most attractive cases,
as is done at present, will thus qualify himself much
more rapidly for actual forensic practice. Under existing circumstances the practice of the principle
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">I.e.</hi>
                        <quote>per totas ire materias.</quote>
                    </note>
                    which
I mentioned second is, as a rule, hampered by the
large size of the classes and the practice of allotting
certain days for recitation, to which must be added
                    <pb xml:id="p.127"/>
                    the contributory circumstance that the boys' parents
are more interested in the number of their sons'
recitations than their quality.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    But, as I think I said
in the first book,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">I. ii. 15.</note>
                    the really good teacher will not
burden himself with a larger number of pupils than
he can manage, and will prune any tendency to
excessive loquacity, limiting their remarks to the
actual points involved by the subject of the declamation and forbidding them to range, as some would
have them do, over every subject in heaven and
earth: further, he will either extend the period
within which he insists on their speaking, or will
permit them to divide their themes into several
portions.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    The thorough treatment of one theme
will be more profitable than the sketchy and superficial treatment of a number of subjects. For the
latter practice has the result that nothing is put in
its proper place and that the opening of the declamation exceeds all reasonable bounds, since the
young orator crams all the flowers of eloquence
which belong to all the different portions of the
theme into that portion which he has to deliver,
and fearing to lose what should naturally come later,
introduces wild confusion into the earlier portions
of his speech.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    Having dealt with writing, the next point
which claims our attention is premeditation, which
itself derives force from the practice of writing and
forms an intermediate stage between the labours of
the pen and the more precarious fortunes of improvisation; indeed I am not sure that it is not more
frequently of use than either. For there are places
and occasions where writing is impossible, while both
are available in abundance for premeditation. For
                    <pb xml:id="p.129"/>
                    but a few hours' thought will suffice to cover all the
points even of cases of importance; if we wake at
night, the very darkness will assist us, while even in
the midst of legal proceedings our mind will find
some vacant space for meditation, and will refuse to
remain inactive.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Again, this practice will not merely
secure the proper arrangement of our matter without
any recourse to writing, which in itself is no small
achievement, but will also set the words which we
are going to use in their proper order, and bring the
general texture of our speech to such a stage of
completion that nothing further is required beyond
the finishing touches. And as a rule the memory is
more retentive of thoughts when the attention has
not been relaxed by the fancied security which
results from committing them to writing.
                </p>
                <p>
                    But the concentration which this requires cannot
be attained in a moment or even quickly.
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    For, in
the first place, we must write much before we can
form that ideal of style which must always be
present to our minds even when engaged in premeditation. Secondly, we must gradually acquire
the habit of thought: to begin with, we shall content ourselves with covering but a few details, which
our minds are capable of reproducing with accuracy;
then by advances so gradual that our labour is not
sensibly increased we must develop our powers and
confirm them by frequent practice, a task in which
the most important part is played by the memory.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    For this reason I must postpone some of my remarks
to the portion of this work reserved for the treatment of that topic.
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        XI. ii. 1
                        <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi>
                    </note>
                    At length, however, our powers
will have developed so far that the man who is not
hampered by lack of natural ability will by dint of
                    <pb xml:id="p.131"/>
                    persistent study be enabled, when it comes to speaking, to rely no less on what he has thought out than
what he has written out and learnt by heart. At
any rate, Cicero records that Metrodorus of Scepsis,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A philosopher of the Academic school, contemporary
with Cicero,
                        <hi rend="italic">cp. de Or.</hi>
                        ii. 360.
                    </note>
                    Empylus of Rhodes,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Empylus is not mentioned elsewhere.</note>
                    and our own Hortensius
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Cp. Brut.</hi>
                        301.
                    </note>
                    were
able to reproduce what they had thought out word
for word when it came to actual pleading.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    If, however, some brilliant improvisation should
occur to us while speaking, we must not cling superstitiously to our premeditated scheme. For premeditation is not so accurate as to leave no room
for happy inspiration: even when writing we often
insert thoughts which occur to us on the spur of the
moment. Consequently this form of preparation
must be conceived on such lines that we shall find
no difficulty either in departing from it or returning
to it at will.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    For, although it is essential to bring
with us into court a supply of eloquence which has
been prepared in advance in the study and on which
we can confidently rely, there is no greater folly
than the rejection of the gifts of the moment.
Therefore our premeditation should be such that
fortune may never be able to fool us, but may, on
the contrary, be able to assist us. This end will be
obtained by developing the power of memory so
that our conceptions may flow from us without fear
of disaster, and that we may be enabled to look
ahead without anxious backward glances or the
feeling that we are absolutely dependent on what
we can call to mind. Otherwise I prefer the rashness of improvisation to the coherence given by
premeditation.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    For such backward glances place us
at a disadvantage, because our search for our premeditated ideas makes us miss others, and we draw
                    <pb xml:id="p.133"/>
                    our matter from our memory rather than from the
subject on which we are speaking. And even if we
are to rely on our memory and our subject alike,
there are more things that may be discovered than
ever yet have been.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    But the crown of all our study and the
highest reward of our long labours is the power of
improvisation. The man who fails to acquire this
had better, in my opinion, abandon the task of
advocacy and devote his powers of writing to other
branches of literature. For it is scarcely decent for
an honourable man to promise assistance to the
public at large which he may be unable to provide in
the most serious emergencies, or to attempt to enter
a harbour which his ship cannot hope to make save
when sailing before a gentle breeze.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For there are
countless occasions when the sudden necessity may be
imposed upon him of speaking without preparation
before the magistrates or in a trial which comes on
unexpectedly. And if any such sudden emergency
befalls, I will not say any innocent citizen, but some
one of the orator's friends or connexions, is he to
stand tongue-tied and, in answer to those who seek
salvation in his eloquence and are doomed, unless
they secure assistance, to ask for delay of proceedings and time for silent and secluded study, till such
moment as he can piece together the words that fail
him, commit them to memory and prepare his voice
and lungs for the effort?
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    What theory of the duties
of an orator is there which permits him to ignore
such sudden issues? What will happen when he
has to reply to his opponent? For often the expected arguments to which we have written a reply
fail us and the whole aspect of the case undergoes
                    <pb xml:id="p.135"/>
                    a sudden change; consequently the variation to
which cases are liable makes it as necessary for us
to change our methods as it is for a pilot to change
his course before the oncoming storm.
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    Again, what
use is much writing, assiduous reading and long
years of study, if the difficulty is to remain as great
as it was in the beginning? The man who is always
faced with the same labour can only confess that his
past labour has been spent in vain. I do not ask
him to prefer to speak extempore, but merely that
lie should be able to do so. And this capacity is
best acquired by the following method.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    In the first place, we must note the direction which
the argument is likely to take, since we cannot run
our race unless we know the goal and the course.
It is not enough to know what are the parts
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">See III. ix. 1.</note>
                    into
which forensic pleadings are divided or the principles determining the order of the various questions,
important though these points are. We must realise
what should come first, second, and so on, in the
several parts; for these points are so closely linked
together by the very nature of things that they
cannot be separated, nor their order changed, without giving rise to confusion.
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The orator, who speaks
methodically, will above all take the actual sequence
of the various points as his guide, and it is for this
reason that even but moderately trained speakers
find it easiest to keep the natural order in the
                    <hi rend="italic">statement of facts.</hi>
                    Secondly, the orator must know
what to look for in each portion of his case: he
must not beat about the bush or allow himself to be
thrown off the track by thoughts which suggest
themselves from irrelevant quarters, or produce a
speech which is a confused mass of incongruities,
                    <pb xml:id="p.137"/>
                    owing to his habit of leaping this way and that, and
never sticking to any one point.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Finally, he must
confine himself to certain definite bounds, and for
this
                    <hi rend="italic">division</hi>
                    is absolutely necessary. When to the
best of his ability he has dealt fully with all the
points which he has advanced, he will know that he
has reached his goal.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The precepts just given are dependent on theory.
Those to which I now come depend on individual
study. We must acquire a store of the best words
and phrases on lines that I have already laid down,
while our style must be formed by continuous and
conscientious practice in writing, so that even our
improvisations may reproduce the tone of our writing,
and after writing much, we must give ourselves
frequent practice in speaking.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    For facility is mainly
the result of habit and exercise and, if it be
lost only for a brief time, the result will be
not merely that we fall short of the requisite
rapidity, but that our lips will become clogged
and slow to open. For although we need to
possess a certain natural nimbleness of mind to
enable us, while we are saying what the instant
demands, to build up what is to follow and to
secure that there will always be some thought formed
and conceived in advance ready to serve our voice,
none the less,
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    it is scarcely possible either for natural
gifts or for methodic art to enable the mind to
grapple simultaneously with such manifold duties,
and to be equal at one and the same time to the
tasks of invention, arrangement, and style, together
with what we are uttering at the moment, what we
have got to say next and what we have to look to
still further on, not to mention the fact that it
                    <pb xml:id="p.139"/>
                    is necessary all the time to give close attention to
voice, delivery and gesture.
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    For our mental activities
must range far ahead and pursue the ideas which
are still in front, and in proportion as the speaker
pays out what he has in hand, he must make advances
to himself from his reserve funds, in order that, until
we reach our conclusion, our mind's eye may urge
its gaze forward, keeping time with our advance:
otherwise we shall halt and stumble, and pour forth
short and broken phrases, like persons who can only
gasp out what they have to say.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    There is, therefore, a certain mechanical knack,
which the Greeks call
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)/logos tribh/,</foreign>
                    which enables
the hand to go on scribbling, while the eye takes
in whole lines at once as it reads, observes the intonations and the stops, and sees what is coming
before the reader has articulated to himself what
precedes. It is a similar knack which makes possible
those miraculous tricks which we see jugglers and
masters of sleight of hand perform upon the stage,
in such a manner that the spectator can scarcely
help believing that the objects which they throw
into the air come to hand of their own accord, and
run where they are bidden.
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    But this knack will
only be of real service if it be preceded by the art
of which we have spoken,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">§§ 5–7.</note>
                    so that what is irrational
in itself will nevertheless be founded on reason. For
unless a man speaks in an orderly, ornate and fluent
manner, I refuse to dignify his utterance with the
name of speech, but consider it the merest rant.
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Nor again shall I ever be induced to admire a continuous flow of random talk, such as I note streams in
torrents even from the lips of women when they
quarrel, although, if a speaker is swept away by
                    <pb xml:id="p.141"/>
                    warmth of feeling and genuine inspiration, it frequently happens that he attains a success from improvisation which would have been beyond the reach of
the most careful preparation.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    When this occurred, the
old orators, such as Cicero,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">No such saying is found in Cicero's extant works.</note>
                    used to say that some god
had inspired the speaker. But the reason is obvious.
For profound emotion and vivid imagination sweep
on with unbroken force, whereas, if retarded by the
slowness of the pen, they are liable to grow cold and,
it put off for the moment, may never return. Above
all, if we add to these obstacles an unhealthy tendency
to quibble over the choice of words, and check our
advance at each step, the vehemence of our onset
loses its impetus; while even though our choice of
individual words may be of the happiest, the style
will be a mere patchwork with no regular pattern.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently those vivid conceptions of which I
spoke
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">VI. ii. 29.</note>
                    and which, as I remarked, are called
                    <foreign xml:lang="grc">fantasi/ai,</foreign>
                    together with everything that we intend to say,
the persons and questions involved, and the hopes
and fears to which they give rise, must be kept
clearly before our eyes and admitted to our hearts:
for it is feeling and force of imagination that make
us eloquent. It is for this reason that even the uneducated have no difficulty in finding words to express
their meaning, if only they are stirred by some strong
emotion.
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    Further the attention of the mind must be
directed not to some one thing, but simultaneously to
a number of things in continuous sequence. The
result will be the same as when we cast our eyes
along some straight road and see at once all that is on
and near it, obtaining a view not merely of its end,
but of the whole way there. Dread of the shame
of failure is also a powerful stimulant to oratory,
                    <pb xml:id="p.143"/>
                    and it may be regarded as a matter for wonder that,
whereas when writing we delight in privacy and
shrink from the presence of witnesses, in extempore
pleading a large audience has an encouraging effect,
like that which the sight of the massed standards
has on the soldier.
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                    For the sheer necessity of speaking thrusts forward and forces out our labouring
thought, and the desire to win approbation kindles
and fosters our efforts. So true is it that there is
nothing which does not look for some reward, that
eloquence, despite the fact that its activity is in itself
productive of a strong feeling of pleasure, is influenced
by nothing so much as the immediate acquisition of
praise and renown.
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>
                    Nor should any man put such
trust in his native ability as to hope that this power
will present itself to him at the outset of his career
as an orator; for the precepts which I laid down for
premeditation
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Ch. vi. 3.</note>
                    apply to improvisation also; we
must develop it by gradual stages from small beginnings, until we have reached that perfection which
can only be produced and maintained by practice.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Moreover, the orator should reach such a pitch of
excellence that, while premeditation may still be the
safer method, it will not necessarily be the better,
since many have acquired the gift of improvisation not
merely in prose, but in verse as well, as, for example,
Antipater of Sidon and Licinius Archias (for whose
powers we have the unquestionable authority of
Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">De Or.</hi>
                        iii. 194;
                        <hi rend="italic">Pro Arch.</hi>
                        viii. 18.
                    </note>
                    ), not to mention the fact that there are
many, even in our own day, who have done this and
are still doing it. I do not, however, regard this
accomplishment as being particularly valuable in
itself, for it is both unpractical and unnecessary, but
mention it as a useful example to encourage students
                    <pb xml:id="p.145"/>
                    training for the bar, in the hope that they may be
able to acquire this accomplishment.
                    <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Still our confidence in our power of speaking extempore should
never be so great that we should neglect to devote
a few minutes to the consideration of what we are
going to say. There will but rarely be occasions
when this is impossible, while in the lawsuits of
the courts there is always some time allowed for the
purpose. For no one can plead a cause with the
facts of which be is unacquainted.
                    <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>
                    Some declaimers,
it is true, are led by a perverse ambition to attempt
to speak the moment their theme has been given
them, and even ask for a word with which to start,
an affectation which is in the worst and most
theatrical taste. But eloquence has, in her turn,
nothing but derision for those that insult her thus,
and speakers who wish to seem learned to fools are
merely regarded as fools by the learned.
                    <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>
                    If, however, chance should impose the necessity upon us of
pleading a case at such short notice, we shall require
to develop special mental agility, to give all our
attention to the subject, and to make a temporary
sacrifice of our care for the niceties of language, if
we find it impossible to secure both. On such
occasions a slower delivery and a style of speaking suggestive of a certain indecision and doubt will
secure us time to think, but we must be careful to
do this in such a way as to give the impression of
thought, not of hesitation.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>
                    This precaution may be
employed while we are clearing harbour, if the wind
drive us forward before all our tackle is ready.
Afterwards, as we proceed upon our course, we shall
trim our sails, arrange our ropes, and pray that
the breeze may fill our sails. Such a procedure is
                    <pb xml:id="p.147"/>
                    preferable to yielding ourselves to an empty torrent
of words, that the storm may sweep us where it will.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>
                    But it requires no less careful study to maintain
than to acquire this facility. Theory once mastered
is not forgotten, and the pen loses but little of its
speed by disuse: but this promptitude and readiness
for action can be maintained by practice only. The
best form of exercise is to speak daily before an
audience of several persons, who should, as far as
possible, be selected from those whose judgement
and good opinion we value, since it is rare for anyone to be sufficiently critical of himself. It is even
better to speak alone than not at all.
                    <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
                    There is yet
another method of exercising this faculty: it consists
in going over our subjects in their entirety in silent
thought, although we must all the time formulate
the words to ourselves: such practice is possible at
any moment or place that finds us unoccupied, and
is, in some respects, more useful than that which I
have just mentioned;
                    <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>
                    for we are more careful about
our composition than when we are actually speaking
and in momentary fear of interrupting the continuous
flow of our language. On the other hand, the first
method is more valuable for certain purposes, as it
gives strength to our voice, fluency to our tongue
and vigour to our gesture; and the latter, as I have
already remarked,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">Ch. iii. 21.</note>
                    in itself excites the orator and
spurs him on, as he waves his hand or stamps his
foot: he is, in fact, like the lion, that is said to lash
himself to fury with his tail. But we must study
always and everywhere.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>
                    For there is scarce a single
day in our lives that is so full of occupations that we
may not, at some moment or other, snatch a few
precious minutes, as Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        <hi rend="italic">Or.</hi>
                        34.
                    </note>
                    records that Brutus was
                    <pb xml:id="p.149"/>
                    wont to do, either for writing or reading or speaking;
Gaius Carbo,
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        A supporter of Tib. Graccllus, who went over to the
senatorial party and was consul 120 B.C. Committed suicide
in the following year. Cicero praises his eloquence and
industry; p.
                        <hi rend="italic">Brut.</hi>
                        103–5,
                        <hi rend="italic">de Or.</hi>
                        I. § 154.
                    </note>
                    for example, was in the habit of indulging in such exercises even in his tent.
                    <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>
                    I must also
mention the precept (which again has the approval
of Cicero
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">There is no trace of this.</note>
                    ) that we should never be careless about
our language. Whatever we say, under whatever
circumstances, should be perfect in its way. As regards writing, this is certainly never more necessary
than when we have frequently to speak extempore.
For it maintains the solidity of our speech and gives
depth to superficial facility. We may compare the
practice of husbandmen who cut away the uppermost
roots of their vines, which run close to the surface of
the soil, that the taproots may strike deeper and gain
in strength.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>
                    Indeed I am not sure that, if we practise both with care and assiduity, mutual profit will
not result, and writing will give us greater precision
of speech, while speaking will make us write with
greater facility. We must write, therefore, whenever possible; if we cannot write, we must meditate:
if both are out of the question, we must still speak in
such a manner that we shall not seem to be taken
unawares nor our client to be left in the lurch.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>
                    It is, however, a common practice with those who
have many cases to plead to write out the most
necessary portions, more especially the beginnings of
their speeches, to cover the remainder of that which
they are able to prepare by careful premeditation
and to trust to improvisation in emergency, a practice regularly adopted by Cicero, as is clear from his
note-books. But the notes of other orators are also
in circulation; some have been discovered by
chance, just as they were jotted down previous to a
speech, while others have been edited in book form,
                    <pb xml:id="p.151"/>
                    as in the case of the speeches delivered in the courts
by Servius Sulpicius, of whose works only three
speeches survive. These memoranda, however, of
which I am speaking are so carefully drawn up that
they seem to me to have been composed by himself
for the benefit of posterity.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>
                    But Cicero's notes were
originally intended merely to meet the requirements
of the moment, and were afterwards collected
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">
                        Or perhaps
                        <quote>abbreviated.</quote>
                        Tiro was Cicero's friend,
freedman and secretary.
                    </note>
                    by
Tiro. In making this apology I do not mean to
imply that I disapprove of them, but merely wish
to make them more worthy of admiration. And in
this connexion I must state that I admit the use of
brief memoranda and note-books, which may even be
held in the hand and referred to from time to time.
                    <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>
                    But I disapprove of the advice given by Laenas, that
we should set down in our note-books, duly tabulated under the appropriate headings, summaries of
what we propose to say, even in cases where we
have already written it out in full. For reliance on
such notes as these makes us careless in learning
what we have written and mutilates and deforms our
style. For my own part I think that we should
never write out anything which we do not intend to
commit to memory. For if we do, our thoughts will
run back to what we have elaborated in writing and
will not permit us to try the fortune of the moment.
                    <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>
                    Consequently, the mind will waver in doubt between
the two alternatives, having forgotten what was
committed to writing and being unable to think of
anything fresh to say. However, as the topic of
memory will be discussed in the next book, I will
not introduce it here, as there are other points
which require to be dealt with first.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>