<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six - 10</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">D. Spillan, A.M., M.D.</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Cyrus Evans</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title>History of Rome by Titus Livius, books nine to twenty-six</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp> literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by </resp>
                                <name>D. Spillan</name>

                                <name>Cyrus Edmonds</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers</publisher>
                                <date>1849</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">2</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="628" xml:id="p.628"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="book">
                <head>BOOK X.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Submission of the Marcians accepted. The college of Augurs augmented from
                        four to nine. The law of appeal to the people carried by Valerius the
                        consul. Two more tribes added. War declared against the Sam- nites. Several
                        successful actions. In an engagement against the com- bined forces of the
                        Etruscans, Umbrians, Samnites, and Gauls, Publius Decius, after the example
                        of his father, devotes himself for the army. Dies, and, by his death,
                        procures the victory to the Romans. Defeat of the Samnites by Papirius
                        Cursor. The census held. The lustrum closed. The number of the citizens two
                        hundred and sixty-two thousand three hundred and twenty-two. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> DURING the consulate of Lucius Genucius and
                    Servius Cornelius, the state enjoyed almost uninterrupted rest from foreign
                    wars. Colonies were led out to Sora and Alba. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    For the latter, situated in the country of the Aequans, six thousand colonists
                    were enrolled. Sora had formerly belonged to the Volscian territory, but had
                    fallen into the possession of the Samnites: thither were sent four thousand
                    settlers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This year the freedom of the state
                    was granted to the Arpinians and Trebulans. The Frusinonians were fined a third
                    part of their lands, because it was discovered that the Hernicians had been
                    tampered with by them; and the heads of that conspiracy, after a trial before
                    the consuls, held in pursuance of a decree of the senate, were beaten with rods
                    and beheaded. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> However, that the Romans might
                    not pass the year entirely exempt from war, a little expedition was made into
                    Umbria; intelligence being received from thence, that excursions of men, in
                    arms, had been made, from a certain cave, into the adjacent country. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> Into this cave the troops penetrated with their
                    standards, and, the place being dark, they received many wounds, chiefly from
                    stones thrown. At length the other mouth of the cave being found, for it was
                    pervious, both the openings were filled up with wood, which being set on fire,
                    there perished by means <pb n="629" xml:id="p.629"/> of the smoke and heat, no
                    less than two thousand men; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> many of whom, at
                    the last, in attempting to make their way out, rushed into the very flames.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The two Marci, Livius Denter and Aemilius,
                    succeeding to the consulship, war was renewed with the Aequans; who, being
                    highly displeased at the colony established within their territory, as if it
                    were a fortress, having made an attempt, with their whole force, to seize it,
                    were repulsed by the colonists themselves. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    They caused, however, such an alarm at Rome, that, to quell this insurrection,
                    Caius Junius Bubulcus was nominated dictator: for it was scarcely credible that
                    the Aequans, after being reduced to such a degree of weakness, should by
                    themselves alone have ventured to engage in a war. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> The dictator, taking the field, with Marcus Titinius,
                    master of the horse, in the first engagement reduced the Aequans to submission;
                    and returning into the city in triumph, on the eighth day, dedicated, in the
                    character of dictator, the temple of Health, which he had vowed when consul, and
                    contracted for when censor. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this year a fleet of Grecians, under
                    the command of Cleonymus, a Lacedaemonian, arrived on the coast of Italy, and
                    took Thuriae, a city in the territory of the Sallentines. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Against this enemy the consul Aemilius was sent, who, in
                    one battle, completely defeated them, and drove them on board their ships.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Thuriae was then restored to its old
                    inhabitants, and peace re-established in the country of the Sallentines. In some
                    annals, I find that Junius Bubulcus was sent dictator into that country, and
                    that Cleonymus, without hazarding an engagement with the Romans, retired out of
                    Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He then sailed round the promontory of
                    Brundusium, and, steering down the middle of the Adriatic gulf, because he
                    dreaded, on the left hand, the coasts of Italy destitute of harbours, and, on
                    the right, the Illyrians, Liburnians, and Istrians, nations of savages, and
                    noted in general for piracy, he passed on to the coasts of the Venetians.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Here, having landed a small party to
                    explore the country, and being informed that a narrow beach stretched along the
                    shore, beyond which were marshes, overflowed by the tides; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> that dry land was seen at no great distance, level in the
                    nearest part, and rising behind into hills, beyond which was the mouth of a very
                    deep river, into which they had seen ships brought round and moored in safety,
                    (this was the river Meduacus,) he ordered his fleet to sail into it and <pb
                        n="630" xml:id="p.630"/> go up against the stream. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> As the channel would not admit the heavy ships, the troops,
                    removing into the lighter vessels, arrived at a part of the country occupied by
                    three maritime cantons of the Patavians, settled on that coast. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Here they made a descent, leaving a small guard with the
                    ships, made themselves masters of these cantons, set fire to the houses, drove
                    off a considerable booty of men and cattle, and, allured by the sweets of
                    plunder, proceeded still further from the shore. <milestone n="9" unit="section"
                    /> When news of this was brought to Patavium, where the contiguity of the Gauls
                    kept the inhabitants constantly in arms, they divided their young men into two
                    bands, one of which was led towards the quarter where the marauders were said to
                    be busy; the other by a different route, to avoid meeting any of the pirates,
                    towards the station of the ships, fifteen miles distant from the town.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> An attack was made on the small craft,
                    and the guards being killed, the affrighted mariners were obliged to remove
                    their ships to the other bank of the river. By land, also, the attack on the
                    dispersed plunderers was equally successful; and the Grecians, flying back
                    towards their ships, were opposed in their way by the Venetians. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Thus they were enclosed on both sides, and cut to
                    pieces; and some, who were made prisoners, gave information that the fleet, with
                    their king, Cleonymus, was but three miles distant. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Sending the captives into the nearest canton, to be kept
                    under a guard, some soldiers got on board the flat-bottomed vessels, so
                    constructed for the purpose of passing the shoals with ease; others embarked in
                    those which had been lately taken from the enemy, and proceeding down the river,
                    surrounded their unwieldy ships, which dreaded the unknown sands and flats more
                    than they did the Romans, and which showed a greater eagerness to escape into
                    the deep than to make resistance. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The
                    soldiers pursued them as far as the mouth of the river; and having taken and
                    burned a part of the fleet, which in the hurry and confusion had been stranded,
                    returned victorious. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Cleonymus, having met
                    success in no part of the Adriatic sea, departed with scarce a fifth part of his
                    navy remaining. Many, now alive, have seen the beaks of his ships, and the
                    spoils of the Lacedaemonians, hanging in the old temple of Juno. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> In commemoration of this event, there is exhibited
                    at Patavium, every year, on its anniversary day, a naval combat on the river in
                    the middle of the town. <pb n="631" xml:id="p.631"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A treaty was this year concluded at Rome with
                    the Vestinians, who solicited friendship. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Various causes of apprehension afterwards sprung up. News arrived, that Etruria
                    was in rebellion; the insurrection having arisen from the dissensions of the
                    Arretians; for the Cilnian family having grown exorbitantly powerful, a party,
                    out of envy of their wealth, had attempted to expel them by force of arms.
                    [Accounts were also received] that the Marsians held forcible possession of the
                    lands to which the colony of Carseoli, consisting of four thousand men, had been
                    sent. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> By reason, therefore, of these
                    commotions, Marcus Valerius Maximus was nominated dictator, and chose for his
                    master of the horse Marcus Aemilius Paullus. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This I am inclined to believe, rather than that Quintus Fabius, at such an age
                    as he then was, and after enjoying many honours, was placed in a station
                    subordinate to Valerius: but I think it not unlikely that the mistake arose from
                    the surname Maximus. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The dictator, having set
                    out at the head of an army, in one battle utterly defeated the Marsians, drove
                    them into their fortified towns, and afterwards, in the course of a few days,
                    took Milionia, Plestina, and Fresilia; and then finding Marsians in a part of
                    their lands, granted them a renewal of the treaty. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The war was then directed against the Etrurians; <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> and when the dictator had gone to Rome, for the
                    purpose of renewing the auspices, the master of the horse, going out to forage,
                    was surrounded by an ambuscade, and obliged to fly shamefully into his camp,
                    after losing several standards and many of his men. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The occurrence of which discomfiture to Fabius is
                    exceedingly improbable; not only because, if in any particular, certainly, above
                    all, in the qualifications of a commander, he fully merited his surname; but
                    besides, mindful of Papirius's severity, he never could have been tempted to
                    fight, without the dictator's orders. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The news of this disaster excited at Rome an
                    alarm greater than suited the importance of the affair; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> for, as if the army had been destroyed, a justitium was
                    proclaimed, guards mounted at the gates, and watches set in every street: and
                    armour and weapons were heaped on the walls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    All the younger citizens being compelled to enlist, the dictator was ordered to
                    join the army. There he found every thing in a more tranquil state than he
                    expected, and regularity established, <pb n="632" xml:id="p.632"/> through the
                    care of the master of the horse; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> the camp
                    removed to a place of greater safety; the cohorts, which had lost their
                    standards, left without tents on the outside of the ramparts; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and the troops ardently impatient for battle, that their
                    disgrace might be the sooner obliterated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He
                    therefore immediately advanced his camp into the territory of Rusella. Thither
                    the enemy also followed; and although, since their late success, they
                    entertained the most sanguine hopes from an open trial of strength, yet they
                    endeavoured to circumvent the enemy by a stratagem which they had before
                    practised with success. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> There were, at a small
                    distance from the Roman camp, the half-ruined houses of a town which had been
                    burnt in the devastation of the country. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A
                    body of troops being concealed there, some cattle was driven on, within view of
                    a Roman post, commanded by a lieutenant-general, Cneius Fulvius. When no one was
                    induced by this temptation to stir from his post, one of the herdsmen, advancing
                    close to the works, called out, that others were driving out those cattle at
                    their leisure from the ruins of the town, why did they remain idle, when they
                    might safely drive them through the middle of the Roman camp? <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> When this was interpreted to the lieutenant-general, by
                    some natives of Caere, and great impatience prevailed through every company of
                    the soldiers, who, nevertheless, dared not to move without orders, he commanded
                    some who were skilled in the language to observe attentively, whether the
                    dialect of the herdsmen resembled that of rustics or of citizens. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> When these reported, that their accent in speaking,
                    their manner and appearance, were all of a more polished cast than suited
                    shepherds; <quote>Go then,</quote> said he, <quote> tell them that they may
                        uncover the ambush which they vainly conceal; that the Romans understand all
                        their devices, and can now be no more taken by stratagem than they can be
                        conquered by arms. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When these words were heard, and carried to
                    those who lay in ambush, they immediately arose from their lurking place, and
                    marched out in order into the plain which was open to view on every side.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The lieutenant-general thought their
                    force too powerful for his small band to cope with. He therefore sent in haste
                    to Valerius for support, and in the mean time, by himself, sustained the enemy's
                    onset. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On receiving his message, the dictator ordered
                    the standards to move, and the troops to follow in arms. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> But <pb n="633" xml:id="p.633"/> every thing was executed
                    more quickly, almost, than ordered. The standards and arms were instantly
                    snatched up, and they were with difficulty restrained from running impetuously
                    on; both indignation at their late defeat stimulated them, as well as the shouts
                    striking their ears with increasing vehemence, as the contest grew hotter.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They therefore urged each other, and
                    pressed the standard-bearers to quicken their pace. The dictator, the more
                    eagerly he saw them push forward, took the more pains to repress their haste,
                    and ordered them to march at a slower rate. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On
                    the other side, the Etrurians, putting themselves in motion, on the first
                    beginning of the fray had come up with their whole force; and several expresses
                    came to the dictator, one after another, that all the legions of the Etrurians
                    had joined in the fight, and that his men could not any longer withstand them:
                    at the same time, he himself saw, from the higher ground, in how perilous a
                    situation the party was. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Confident, however,
                    that the lieutenant-general was able, even yet, to support the contest, and
                    considering that he himself was at hand to rescue him from defeat, he wished to
                    let the enemy be fatigued, as much as might be, in order that, when in that
                    state, he might fall on them with his fresh troops. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Slowly as these marched, the distance was now just
                    sufficient for the cavalry to begin their career for a charge. The battalions of
                    the legions marched in front, lest the enemy might suspect any secret or sudden
                    movement, but intervals had been left in the ranks of the infantry, affording
                    room for the horses to gallop through. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> At the
                    same instant the line raised the shout, and the cavalry, charging at full speed,
                    poured on the enemy, and spread at once a general panic. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> After this, as succour had arrived, almost too late, to the
                    party surrounded, so now they were allowed entire rest, the fresh troops taking
                    on themselves the whole business of the fight. Nor was that either long or
                    dubious. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The enemy, now routed, fled to their
                    camp, and the Romans advancing to attack it, they give way, and are crowded all
                    together in the remotest part of it. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> In their
                    flight they are obstructed by the narrowness of the gates, the greater number
                    climbed up on the mounds and ramparts, to try if they could either defend
                    themselves with the aid of the advantageous ground, or get over, by any means,
                    and escape. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> One part of the rampart,
                    happening to be badly compacted, <pb n="634" xml:id="p.634"/> sunk under the
                    weight of the multitude who stood on it, and fell into the trench. On which,
                    crying out that the gods had opened that pass to give them safety, they made
                    their way out, most of them leaving their arms behind. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> By this battle the power of the Etrurians was, a second
                    time, effectually crushed, so that, engaging to furnish a year's pay, and corn
                    for two months, with the dictator's permission, they sent ambassadors to Rome to
                    treat of peace. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This was refused, but a truce
                    for two years was granted to them. The dictator returned into the city in
                    triumph. I have seen it asserted, that tranquillity was restored in Etruria by
                    the dictator, without any memorable battle, only by composing the dissensions of
                    the Arretians, and effecting a reconciliation between the Cilnian family and the
                    commons. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Marcus Valerius was elected consul,
                    before the expiration of his dictatorship, many have believed, without his
                    soliciting the office, and even while he was absent; and that the election was
                    held by an interrex. In one point all agree, that he held the consulship with
                    Quintus Appuleius Pansa. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During this consulate of Marcus Valerius and
                    Quintus Appuleius, affairs abroad wore a very peaceable aspect. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Their losses sustained in war, together with the truce,
                    kept the Etrurians quiet. The Samnites, depressed by the misfortunes of many
                    years, had not yet become dissatisfied with their new alliance. At Rome, also,
                    the carrying away of such multitudes to colonies, rendered the commons tranquil,
                    and lightened their burthens. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But, that things
                    might not be tranquil on all sides, a contention was excited between the
                    principal persons in the commonwealth, patricians on one hand, and plebeians on
                    the other, by the two Ogulnii, Quintus and Cneius, <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> plebeian tribunes, who, seeking every where occasions of
                    criminating the patricians in the hearing of the people, and having found other
                    attempts fruitless, set on foot a proceeding by which they might inflame, not
                    the lowest class of the commons, but their chief men, the plebeians of consular
                    and triumphal rank, to <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> the completion of
                    whose honours nothing was now wanting but the offices of the priesthood, which
                    were not yet laid open to them. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They therefore
                    published a proposal for a law, that, whereas there were then four augurs and
                    four pontiffs, and it had been determined that the number of priests should be
                    augmented, the four additional pontiffs and <pb n="635" xml:id="p.635"/> five
                    augurs should all be chosen out of the commons. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> How the college of augurs could be reduced to the number of four, except by
                    the death of two, I do not understand: for it is a rule among the augurs, that
                    their number should be composed of threes, so that the three ancient tribes, the
                    Ramnes, Titienses, and Luceres, should have each its own augur; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> or, in case there should be occasion for more, that each
                    should increase its number of augurs, in equal proportion with the rest, in like
                    manner as when, by the addition of five to four, they made up the number nine,
                    so that there were three to each tribe. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    However, as it was proposed that they should be chosen out of the commons, the
                    patricians were as highly offended at the proceeding, as when they saw the
                    consulship made common; <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> yet they pretended
                    that the business concerned not them so much as it did the gods, who would
                        <quote> take care that their own worship should not be contaminated; that,
                        for their parts, they only wished that no misfortune might ensue to the
                        commonwealth. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> But they made a less vigorous opposition, as
                    being now accustomed to suffer defeat in such kind of disputes; and they saw
                    their adversaries, not, as formerly, grasping at that which they could scarcely
                    hope to reach, the higher honours; but already in possession of all those
                    advantages, on the uncertain prospect of which they had maintained the contest,
                    manifold consulships, censorships, and triumphs. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The principal struggle, however, in supporting
                    and opposing the bill, they say, was between Appius Claudius and Publius Decius
                    Mus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> After these had urged nearly the same
                    topics, respecting the privileges of patricians and plebeians, which had been
                    formerly employed for and against the Licinian law, when the proposition was
                    brought forward of opening the consulship to plebeians, Decius is said to have
                    drawn a lively description <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> of his own
                    father, such as many then present in the assembly had seen him, girt in the
                    Gabine dress, standing on a spear, in the attitude in which he had devoted
                    himself for the people and the legions, and to have added, that <quote> the
                        consul Publius Decius was <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> then deemed by
                        the immortal gods an offering equally pure and pious, as if his colleague,
                        Titus Manlius, had been devoted. And might not the same Publius Decius have
                        been, with propriety, chosen to perform the public worship of the Roman
                        people? <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Was there any danger that the gods
                        would give less attention to his prayers <pb n="636" xml:id="p.636"/> than
                        to those of Appius Claudius? Did the latter perform his private acts of
                        adoration with a purer mind, or worship the gods more religiously than he?
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Who had any reason to complain of the
                        vows offered in behalf of the commonwealth, by so many plebeian consuls and
                        dictators, either when setting out to their armies, or in the heat of
                        battle? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Were the numbers of commanders
                        reckoned, during those years since business began to be transacted under the
                        conduct and auspices of plebeians, the same number of triumphs might be
                        found. The commons had now no reason to be dissatisfied with their own
                        nobility. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the contrary, they were fully
                        convinced, that in case of a sudden war breaking out, the senate and people
                        of Rome would not repose greater confidence in patrician than in plebeian
                        commanders. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Which being the case, </quote>
                    said he, "what god or man can deem it an impropriety, if those whom ye have
                    honoured with curule chairs, with the purple bordered gown, with the palm-vest
                    and embroidered robe, with the triumphal crown and laurel, whose houses ye have
                    rendered conspicuous above others, by affixing to them the spoils of conquered
                    enemies, should add to these the badges of augurs or pontiffs? <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> If a person, who has rode through the city in a gilt
                    chariot; and, decorated with the ensigns of Jupiter, supremely good and great,
                    has mounted the Capitol, should be seen with a chalice and wand; what
                    impropriety, I say, that he should, with his head veiled, slay a victim, or take
                    an augury in the citadel? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> When, in the
                    inscription on a person's statue, the consulship, censorship, and triumph shall
                    be read with patience, will the eyes of readers be unable to endure the addition
                    of the office of augur or pontiff? In truth (with deference to the gods I say
                    it) I trust that we are, through the kindness of the Roman people, qualified in
                    such a manner that we should, by the dignity of our characters, reflect back, on
                    the priesthood, not less lustre than we should receive; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and may demand, rather on behalf of the gods, than for our
                    own sakes, that those whom we worship in our private we may also worship in a
                    public capacity. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> But why do I argue thus, as if the cause of the patricians, respecting
                        the priesthood, were untouched? and as if we were not already in possession
                        of one sacerdotal office, of the highest class? <milestone n="2"
                            unit="section"/> We see plebeian decemvirs, for performing sacrifices,
                        interpreters of the Sibylline prophecies, and of the fates <pb n="637"
                            xml:id="p.637"/> of the nation; we also see them presidents of Apollo's
                        festival, and of other religious performances. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> Neither was any injustice done to the patricians, when,
                        to the two commissioners for performing sacrifices, an additional number was
                        joined, in favour of the plebeians; nor is there now, when a tribune, a man
                        of courage and activity, wishes to add five places of augurs, and four of
                        pontiffs, to which plebeians may be nominated; <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> not, Appius, with intent to expel you from your places;
                        but, that men of plebeian rank may assist you, in the management of divine
                        affairs, with the same zeal with which they assist you in matters of human
                        concernment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Blush not, Appius, at having
                        a man your colleague in the priesthood, whom you might have a colleague in
                        the censorship or consulship, whose master of the horse you yourself may be,
                        when he is dictator, as well as dictator when he is master of the horse.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> A Sabine adventurer, the first origin
                        of your nobility, either Attus Clausus, or Appius Claudius, which you will,
                        the ancient patricians of those days admitted into their number: do not
                        then, on your part, disdain to admit us into the number of priests.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> We bring with us numerous honours; all
                        those honours, indeed, which have rendered your party so proud. <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> Lucius Sextius was the first consul chosen out of
                        the plebeians; Caius Licinius Stolo, the first master of the horse; Caius
                        Marcius Rutilus, the first dictator, and likewise censor; Quintus Publilius
                        Philo, the first praetor. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On all occasions
                        was heard a repetition of the same arguments; that the right of auspices was
                        vested in you; that ye alone had the rights of ancestry; that ye alone were
                        legally entitled to the supreme command, and the auspices both in peace and
                        war. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The supreme command has hitherto
                        been, and will continue to be, equally prosperous in plebeian hands as in
                        patrician. Have ye never heard it said, that the first created patricians
                        were not men sent down from heaven, but such as could cite their fathers,
                        that is, nothing more than free born. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> I
                        can now cite my fa- ther, a consul; and my son will be able to cite a
                        grandfather. Citizens, there is nothing else in it, than that we should
                        never obtain any thing without a refusal. The patricians wish only for a
                        dispute; nor do they care what issue their disputes may have. <milestone
                            n="12" unit="section"/> For my part, be it advantageous, happy, and
                        prosperous to you and to the commonwealth, I am of opinion that this law
                        should receive your sanction. </quote>
                    <pb n="638" xml:id="p.638"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The people ordered that the tribes should be
                    instantly called; and there was every appearance that the law would be accepted.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It was deferred, however, for that day, by
                    a protest, from which on the day following the tribunes were deterred; and it
                    passed with the approbation of a vast majority. The pontiffs created were,
                    Publius Decius Mus, the advocate for the law; Publius Sempronius Sophus, Caius
                    Marcius Rutilus, and Marcus Livius Denter. The five augurs, who were also
                    plebeians, were, Caius Genucius, Publius Aelius Paetus, Marcus Minucius Fessus,
                    Caius Marcius, and Titus Publilius. Thus the number of the pontiffs was made
                    eight; that of the augurs nine. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the same
                    year Marcus Valerius, consul, procured a law to be passed concerning appeals;
                    more carefully enforced by additional sanctions. This was the third time, since
                    the expulsion of the kings, of this law being introduced, and always by the same
                    family. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The reason for renewing it so often
                    was, I believe, no other, than that the influence of a few was apt to prove too
                    powerful for the liberty of the commons. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    However, the Porcian law seems intended, solely, for the security of the persons
                    of the citizens; as it visited with a severe penalty any one for beating with
                    stripes or putting to death a Roman citizen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    The Valerian law, after forbidding a person, who had appealed, to be beaten with
                    rods and beheaded, added, in case of any one acting contrary thereto, that it
                    shall yet be only deemed a wicked act. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> This, I
                    suppose, was judged of sufficient strength to enforce obedience to the law in
                    those days; so powerful was then men's sense of shame; at present one would
                    scarcely make use of such a threat seriously. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    The Aequans rebelling, the same consul conducted the war against them; in which
                    no memorable event occurred; for, except ferocity, they retained nothing of
                    their ancient condition. The other consul, Appuleius, invested the town of
                    Nequinum in Umbria. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The ground, the same
                    whereon Narnia now stands, was steep (on one side even perpendicular); this
                    rendered the town impregnable either by assault or works. That business,
                    therefore, came unfinished into the hands of the succeeding consuls, Marcus
                    Fulvius Paetinus and Titus Manlius Torquatus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    When all the centuries named Quintus Fabius consul for that year though not a
                    candidate, Macer Licinius and Tubero state that he himself recommended them to
                    postpone the conferring the consulship on him until a <pb n="639" xml:id="p.639"
                    /> year wherein there might be more employment for their arms; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> adding, that, during the present year, he might be more
                    useful to the state in the management of a city magistracy; and thus, neither
                    dissembling what he preferred, nor yet making direct application for it, he was
                    appointed curule aedile with Lucius Papirius Cursor. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Piso, a more ancient writer of annals, prevents me from
                    averring this as certain; he asserts that the curule aediles of that year were
                    Caius Domitius Calvinus, son of Cneius, and Spurius Carvilius Maximus, son of
                    Caius. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I am of opinion, that this latter
                    surname caused a mistake concerning the aediles; and that thence followed a
                    story conformable to this mistake, patched up out of the two elections, of the
                    aediles, and of the consuls. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The general
                    survey was performed, this year, by Publius Sempronius Sophus and Publius
                    Sulpicius Saverrio, censors; and two tribes were added, the Aniensian and
                    Terentine. Such were the occurrences at Rome. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Meanwhile, after much time had been lost in
                    the tedious siege of Nequinum, two of the townsmen, whose houses were contiguous
                    to the wall, having formed a subterraneous passage, came by that private way to
                    the Roman advanced guards; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and being conducted
                    thence to the consul, offered to give admittance to a body of armed men within
                    the works and walls. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The proposal was thought
                    to be such as ought neither to be rejected, nor yet assented to without caution.
                    With one of these men, the other being detained as an hostage, two spies were
                    sent through the mine, and certain information being <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> received from them, three hundred men in arms, guided by
                    the deserter, entered the city, and seized by night the nearest gate, which
                    being broken open, the Roman consul and his army took possession of the city
                    without any opposition. In this manner came Nequinum under the dominion of the
                    Roman people. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> A colony was sent thither as a
                    barrier against the Umbrians, and called Narnia, from the river Nar. The troops
                    returned to Rome with abundance of spoil. This year the Etrurians made
                    preparations for war in violation of the truce. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> But a vast army of the Gauls, making an irruption into their territories,
                    while their attention was directed to another quarter, suspended for a time the
                    execution of their design. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They then, relying
                    on the abundance of money which they possessed, endeavour to make allies of the
                    Gauls, instead of enemies; in <pb n="640" xml:id="p.640"/> order that, with
                    their armies combined, they might attack the Romans. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> The barbarians made no objection to the alliance, and a
                    negotiation was opened for settling the price; which being adjusted and paid,
                    and every thing else being in readiness for commencing their operations, the
                    Etrurians desired them to accompany them in their march. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> This they refused, alleging that <quote> they had
                        stipulated a price for making war against the Romans: that the payment
                        already made, they had received in consideration of their not wasting the
                        Etrurian territory, or using their arms against the inhabitants. <milestone
                            n="10" unit="section"/> That notwithstanding, if it was the wish of the
                        Etrurians, they were still willing to engage in the war, but on no other
                        condition than that of being allowed a share of their lands, and obtaining
                        at length some permanent settlement. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Many assemblies of the states of Etruria were
                    held on this subject, and nothing could be settled; not so much by reason of
                    their aversion from the dismemberment of their territory, as because every one
                    felt a dread of fixing in so close vicinity to themselves people of such a
                    savage race. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The Gauls were therefore
                    dismissed, and carried home an immense sum of money, acquired without toil or
                    danger. The report of a Gallic tumult, in addition to an Etrurian war, had
                    caused serious apprehensions at Rome; and, with the less hesitation on that
                    account, an alliance was concluded with the state of the Picentians. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The province of Etruria fell by lot to the
                    consul Titus Manlius; who, when he had but just entered the enemy's country, as
                    he was exercising the cavalry, in wheeling about at full speed, was thrown from
                    his horse, and almost killed on the spot; three days after the fall, he died.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The Etrurians, embracing this omen, as it
                    were, of the future progress of the war, and observing that the gods had
                    commenced hostilities on their behalf, assumed new courage. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> At Rome the news caused great affliction, on account both
                    of the loss of such a man and of the unseasonableness of the juncture;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> insomuch that an assembly, held for the
                    purpose of substituting a new consul, having been conducted agreeably to the
                    wishes of people of the first consequence, prevented the senate from ordering a
                    dictator to be created. All the votes and centuries concurred unanimously in
                    appointing Marcus Valerius consul, the same whom the senate would have ordered
                    to be made dictator. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They then commanded him
                    to proceed immediately into Etru- <pb n="641" xml:id="p.641"/> ria, to the
                    legions. His coming gave such a check to the Etrurians, that not one of them
                    dared thenceforward to appear on the outside of their trenches; their own fears
                    operating as a blockade. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Nor could the new
                    consul, by wasting their lands and burning their houses, draw them out to an
                    engagement; for not only country-houses, but numbers of their towns, were seen
                    smoking and in ashes, on every side. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> While
                    this war proceeded more slowly than had been expected, an account was received
                    of the breaking out of another; which was, not without reason, regarded as
                    terrible, in consequence of the heavy losses formerly sustained by both parties,
                    from information given by their new allies, the Picentians, that the Samnites
                        <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> were looking to arms and a renewal of
                    hostilities, and that they themselves had been solicited to join therein.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The Picentians received the thanks of the
                    state; and a large share of the attention of the senate was turned from Etruria
                    towards Samnium. The dearness of provisions also distressed the state very much,
                    and they would have felt the extremity of want, according to the relation of
                    those who make Fabius Maximus curule aedile that year, had not the vigilant
                    activity of that man, such as he had on many occasions displayed in the field,
                    been exerted then with equal zeal at home, in the management of the market, and
                    in procuring and forming magazines of corn. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    An interregnum took place this year, the reason of which is not mentioned.
                    Appius Claudius, and. after him, Publius Sulpicius, were interreges. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The latter held an election of consuls, and chose
                    Lucius Cornelius Scipio and Cneius Fulvius. In the beginning of this year,
                    ambassadors came from the Lucanians to the new consuls to complain, that "the
                    Samnites, finding that they could not, by any offers, tempt them to take part in
                    the war, had marched an army in a hostile manner into their country, and were
                    now laying it waste, and forcing them into a war; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> that the Lucanian people had on former occasions erred
                    enough and more than enough; that their minds were so firmly fixed that they
                    thought it more endurable to bear and suffer every hardship, rather than ever
                    again to outrage the Roman name: <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> they
                    besought the senate to take the people of Lucania into their protection, and
                    defend them from the injustice and outrage of the Samnites; that although
                    fidelity on their part to the Romans would now become necessary, a war being un-
                        <pb n="642" xml:id="p.642"/> dertaken against the Samnites, still they were
                    ready to give hostages. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The deliberation of the senate was short. They
                    all, to a man, concurred in opinion, that a compact should be entered into with
                    the Lucanians, and satisfaction demanded from the Samnites: accordingly, a
                    favourable answer was returned to the Lucanians, and the alliance concluded.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Heralds were then sent, to require of the
                    Samnites, that they should depart from the country of the allies, and withdraw
                    their troops from the Lucanian territory. These were met by persons despatched
                    for the purpose by the Samnites, who gave them warning, that <quote>if they
                        appeared at any assembly in Samnium, they must not expect to depart in
                        safety.</quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> As soon as this was heard at Rome, the senate
                    voted, and the people ordered, that war should be declared against the Samnites.
                    The consuls, then, dividing the provinces between them, Etruria fell to Scipio,
                    the Samnites to Fulvius; and they set out by different routes, each against the
                    enemy allotted to him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Scipio, while he
                    expected a tedious campaign, like that of the preceding year, was met near
                    Volaterra by the Etrurians, in order of battle. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The fight lasted through the greater part of the day, while very many fell on
                    both sides, and night came on while it was uncertain to which side victory
                    inclined. But the following dawn showed the conqueror and the vanquished; for
                    the Etrurians had decamped in the dead of the night. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> The Romans, marching out with intent to renew the
                    engagement, and seeing their superiority acknowledged by the departure of the
                    enemy, advanced to their camp; and, finding even this fortified post deserted,
                    took possession of it, evacuated as it was, together with a vast quantity of
                    spoil. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consul then, leading back his
                    forces into the Faliscian territory, and leaving his baggage with a small guard
                    at Falerii, set out with his troops, lightly accoutred, to ravage the enemy's
                    country. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All places are destroyed with fire
                    and sword; plunder driven from every side; and not only was the ground left a
                    mere waste to the enemy, but their forts and small towns were set on fire; he
                    refrained from attacking the cities into which fear had driven the Etrurians.
                    The consul Cneius Fulvius fought a glorious battle in Samnium, near Bovianum,
                    attended with success by no means equivocal. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Then, having attacked Bovianum, and not long after Aufidena, he took them by
                    storm. <pb n="643" xml:id="p.643"/> This year a colony was carried out to
                    Carseoli, into the territory of the $Aequicolae. The consul Fulvius triumphed on
                    his defeat of the Samnites. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consular elections were now at hand,
                    a report prevailed, that the Etrurians and Samnites were raising vast armies;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> that the leaders of the Etrurians were, in
                    all their assemblies, openly censured for not having procured the aid of the
                    Gauls on any terms; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and the magistrates of the
                    Samnites arraigned, for having opposed to the Romans an army destined to act
                    against the Lucanians. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That, in consequence,
                    the people were rising up in arms, with all their own strength and that of their
                    allies combined; and that this affair seemed not likely to be terminated without
                    a contest of much greater difficulty than the former. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Although the candidates for the consulship were men of
                    illustrious characters, yet this alarming intelligence turned the thoughts of
                    all on Quintus Fabius Maximus, who sought not the employment at first, and
                    afterwards, when he discovered their wishes, even declined it. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/>
                    <quote>Why,</quote> said he, <quote> should they impose such a difficult task on
                        him, who was now in the decline of life, and had passed through a full
                        course of labours, and of the rewards of labour? Neither the vigour of his
                        body, nor of his mind, remained the same; and he dreaded fortune herself,
                        lest to some god she should seem too bountiful to him, and more constant
                        than the course of human affairs allowed. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        He had himself succeeded, in gradual succession, to the dignities of his
                        seniors; and he beheld, with great satisfaction, others rising up to succeed
                        to his glory. There was no scarcity at Rome, either of honours suited to men
                        of the highest merit, or of men of eminent merit suited to the highest
                        honours. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This disinterested conduct, instead of
                    repressing, increased, while in fact it justified their zeal. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> But thinking that this ought to be checked by respect for
                    the laws, he ordered that clause to be read aloud by which it was not lawful
                    that the same person shall be re-elected consul within ten years. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The law was scarcely heard in consequence of the
                    clamour; and the tribunes of the commons declared, that this <quote> decree
                        should be no impediment; for they would propose an order to the people, that
                        he should be exempted from the obligation of the laws. </quote> Still he
                    persisted in his opposition, asking, <quote> To what purpose were laws enacted,
                        if they were eluded by the very persons who procured them? <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> The <pb n="644" xml:id="p.644"/> laws now, </quote> he
                    said, <quote>instead of being rulers, were overruled.</quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The people, nevertheless, proceeded to vote;
                    and, according as each century was called in, it immediately named Fabius
                    consul. Then at length, overcome by the universal wish of the state, he said,
                        <quote> Romans, may the gods approve your present, and all your future
                        proceedings. But since, with respect to me, ye intend to act according to
                        your own wills, let my interest find room with you, with respect to my
                        colleague. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> I earnestly request, that ye
                        will place in the consulship with me Publius Decius; a man with whom I have
                        already experienced the utmost harmony in our joint administration of that
                        office; a man worthy of you, worthy of his father. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The recommendation was deemed well founded,
                    and all the remaining centuries voted Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius consuls.
                    This year, great numbers were prosecuted by the aediles, for having in
                    possession larger quantities of land than the state allowed; and hardly any were
                    acquitted: by which means, a very great restraint was laid on exorbitant
                    covetousness. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst the new consuls, Quintus Fabius Maximus
                    a fourth, and Publius Decius Mus a third time, were settling between themselves
                    that one should command against the Samnites, and the other against the
                    Etrurians; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and what number of forces would be
                    sufficient for this and for that province; and which would be the fitter
                    commander in each war; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> ambassadors from
                    Sutrium, Nepete, and Falerii, stating that the states of Etruria were holding
                    assemblies on the subject of suing for peace, they directed the whole force of
                    their arms against Samnium. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The consuls, in
                    order that the supply of provisions might be the more ready, and to leave the
                    enemy in the greater uncertainty on what quarter the war would fall, Fabius led
                    his legions towards Samnium through the territory of Sora, and Decius his
                    through that of Sidicinum. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> As soon as they
                    arrived at the frontiers of the enemy, both advanced briskly, spreading
                    devastation wherever they came; but still they explore the country, to a
                    distance beyond where the troops were employed in plundering. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Accordingly the fact did not escape the notice of the
                    Romans, that the enemy were drawn up in a retired valley, near Tifernum, which,
                    when the Romans entered, they were preparing to attack them from the higher
                    ground. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Fabius, sending away his baggage to a
                    place of safety, and setting a small guard over it, and having given <pb n="645"
                        xml:id="p.645"/> notice to his soldiers that a battle was at hand, advanced
                    in a square body to the hiding-place of the enemy already mentioned. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> The Samnites, disappointed in making an unexpected
                    attack, determined on a regular engagement, as the matter was now likely to come
                    to an open contest. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They therefore marched out
                    into the plain; and, with a greater share of spirit than of hopes, committed
                    themselves to the disposal of fortune. However, whether in consequence of their
                    having drawn together, from every state, the whole of the force which it
                    possessed, or that the consideration of their all being at stake, heightened
                    their courage, they occasioned, even in open fight, a considerable alarm.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Fabius, when he saw that the enemy in no
                    place gave way, ordered Marcus Fulvius and Marcus Valerius, military tribunes,
                    with whom he hastened to the front, to go to the cavalry, <milestone n="11??"
                        unit="section"/> and to exhort them, that, <quote> if they remembered any
                        instance wherein the public had received advantage from the service of the
                        horsemen, they would, on that day, exert themselves to insure the invincible
                        renown of that body; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> telling them that
                        the enemy stood immovable against the efforts of the infantry, and the only
                        hope remaining was in the charge of horse. </quote> He addressed
                    particularly both these youths, and with the same cordiality, loading them with
                    praises and promises. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> But considering that,
                    in case that effort should also fail, it would be necessary to accomplish by
                    stratagem what his strength could not effect; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    he ordered Scipio, one of his lieutenants-general, to draw off the spearmen of
                    the first legion out of the line; to lead them round as secretly as possible to
                    the nearest mountains; and, by an ascent concealed from view, to gain the
                    heights, and show himself suddenly on the rear of the enemy. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> The cavalry, led on by the tribunes, rushing forward
                    unexpectedly before the van, caused scarcely more confusion among the enemy than
                    among their friends. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The line of the Samnites
                    stood firm against the furious onset of the squadrons; it neither could be
                    driven from its ground, nor broken in any part. The cavalry, finding their
                    attempts fruitless, withdrew from the fight, and retired behind the line of
                    infantry. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> On this the enemies' courage
                    increased, so that the Roman troops in the van would not have been able to
                    support the contest, nor the force thus increasing by confidence in itself, had
                    not the second line, by the consul's order, come up into the place of the first.
                        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> These fresh troops <pb n="646"
                        xml:id="p.646"/> checked the progress of the Samnites, who had now began to
                    gain ground; and, at this seasonable juncture, their comrades appearing suddenly
                    on the mountains, and raising a shout, occasioned in the Samnites a fear of
                    greater danger than really threatened them; <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    Fabius called out aloud that his colleague Decius was approaching; on which all
                    the soldiers, elated with joy, repeated eagerly, that the other consul was come,
                    the legions were arrived! <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> This artifice,
                    useful to the Romans, filled the Samnites with dismay and terror; terrified
                    chiefly lest, fatigued as they were, they should be overpowered by another army
                    fresh and unhurt. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/> As they dispersed
                    themselves in their flight on every side, there was less effusion of blood than
                    might have been expected, considering the completeness of the victory. There
                    were three thousand four hundred slain, about eight hundred and thirty made
                    prisoners, and twenty-three military standards taken. </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Apulians would have joined their forces to
                    the Samnites before this battle, had not the consul, Publius Decius, encamped in
                    their neighbourhood at Maleventum; and, finding means to bring them to an
                    engagement, put them to the rout. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Here,
                    likewise, there was more of flight than of bloodshed. Two thousand of the
                    Apulians were slain; but Decius, despising such an enemy, led his legions into
                    Samnium. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There the two consular armies,
                    overrunning every part of the country during the space of five months, laid it
                    entirely waste. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There were in Samnium
                    forty-five places where Decius, and eighty-six where the other consul, encamped.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Nor did they leave traces only of having
                    been there, as ramparts and trenches, but other dreadful mementos of it general
                    desolation and regions depopulated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Fabius
                    also took the city of Cimetra, where he made prisoners two thousand four hundred
                    soldiers; and there were slain in the assault about four hundred and thirty.
                    Going thence to Rome to preside at the elections, he used all expedition in
                    despatching that business. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> All the
                    first-called centuries voted Quintus Fabius consul. Appius Claudius was a
                    candidate, a man of consular rank, daring and ambitious; <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> and as he wished not more ardently for the attainment of
                    that honour for himself, than he did that the patricians might recover the
                    possession of both places in the consulship, he laboured, with all his own
                    power, supported by that of the whole body of the nobility, to prevail on them
                        <pb n="647" xml:id="p.647"/> to appoint him consul along with Quintus
                    Fabius. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> To this Fabius objected, giving, at
                    first, the same reasons which he had advanced the year before. The nobles then
                    all gathered round his seat, and besought him to raise up the consulship out of
                    the plebeian mire, and to restore both to the office itself, and to the
                    patrician rank, their original dignity. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Fabius then, procuring silence, allayed their warmth by a qualifying speech,
                    declaring, that <quote> he would have so managed, as to have received the names
                        of two patricians, if he had seen an intention of appointing any other than
                        himself to the consulship. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As things now
                        stood, he would not set so bad a precedent as to admit his own name among
                        the candidates; such a proceeding being contrary to the laws. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Whereupon Appius Claudius, and Lucius
                    Volumnius, a plebeian, who had likewise been colleagues in that office before,
                    were elected consuls. The nobility reproached Fabius for declining to act in
                    conjunction with Appius Claudius, because he evidently excelled him in eloquence
                    and political abilities. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the election was finished, the former
                    consuls, their command being continued for six months, were ordered to prosecute
                    the war in Samnium. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Accordingly, during this
                    next year also, in the consulate of Lucius Volumnius and Appius Claudius,
                    Publius Decius, who had been left consul in Samnium by his colleague, in the
                    character of proconsul, ceased not to spread devastation through all parts of
                    that country; until, at last, he drove the army of the Samnites, which never
                    dared to face him in the field, entirely out of the country. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Thus expelled from home, they bent their route to Etruria;
                    and, supposing that the business, which they had often in vain endeavoured to
                    accomplish by embassies, might now be negotiated with more effect, when they
                    were backed by such a powerful armed force, and could intermix terror with their
                    entreaties, they demanded a meeting of the chiefs of Etruria: <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> which being assembled, they set forth the great number of
                    years during which they had waged war with the Romans, in the cause of liberty;
                        <quote>they had,</quote> they said, <quote> tried to sustain, with their own
                        strength, the weight of so great a war: they had also made trial of the
                        support of the adjoining nations, which proved of little avail. <milestone
                            n="5" unit="section"/> When they were unable longer to maintain the
                        conflict, they had sued the Roman people for peace; and had again taken up
                        arms, because <pb n="648" xml:id="p.648"/> they felt peace was more grievous
                        to those with servitude, than war to free men. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That their one only hope remaining rested in the
                        Etrurians. They knew that nation to be the most powerful in Italy, in
                        respect of arms, men, and money; to have the Gauls their closest neighbours,
                        born in the midst of war and arms, of furious courage, both from their
                        natural temper, and particularly against the people of Rome, whom they
                        boasted, without infringing the truth, of having made their prisoners, and
                        of having ransomed for gold. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> If the
                        Etrurians possessed the same spirit which formerly Porsena and their
                        ancestors once had, there was nothing to prevent their obliging the Romans,
                        driven from all the lands on this side of the Tiber, to fight for their own
                        existence, and not for the intolerable dominion which they assumed over
                        Italy. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The Samnite army had come to them,
                        in readiness for action, furnished with arms and pay, and were willing to
                        follow that instant, even should they lead to the attack of the city of Rome
                        itself. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While they were engaged in these
                    representations, and intriguing at Etruria, the operations of the Romans in
                    their own territories distressed them severely. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> For Publius Decius, when he ascertained through his scouts the departure of
                    the Samnite army, called a council, and there said, <quote> Why do we ramble
                        through the country, carrying the war from village to village? Why not
                        attack the cities and fortified places? No army now guards Samnium. They
                        have fled their country; they are gone into voluntary exile. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The proposal being universally approved, he
                    marched to attack Murgantia, a city of considerable strength; and so great was
                    the ardour of the soldiers, resulting from their affection to their commander,
                    and from their hopes of richer treasure than could be found in pillaging the
                    country places, that in one day they took it by assault. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Here, two thousand one hundred of the Samnites, making
                    resistance, were surrounded and taken prisoners; and abundance of other spoil
                    was captured. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Decius, not choosing that the
                    troops should be encumbered in their march with heavy baggage, ordered them to
                    be called together, and said to them, <quote> Do ye intend to rest satisfied
                        with this single victory, and this booty? or do ye choose to cherish hopes
                        proportioned to your bravery? <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All the
                        cities of the Samnites, and the property left in them, are your own; since,
                        after so <pb n="649" xml:id="p.649"/> often defeating their legions, ye have
                        finally driven them out of the country. Sell those effects in your hands;
                        and allure traders, by a prospect of profit, to follow you on your march. I
                        will, from time to time, supply you with goods for sale. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> Let us go hence to the city of Romulea, where no
                        greater labour, but greater gain awaits you. </quote> Having sold off the
                    spoil, and warmly adopting the general's plan, they proceeded to Romulea.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> There, also, without works or engines, as
                    soon as the battalions approached, the soldiers, deterred from the walls by no
                    resistance, hastily applying ladders wherever was most convenient to each, they
                    mounted the fortifications. The town was taken and plundered. Two thousand three
                    hundred men were slain, six thousand taken prisoners, and the soldiers obtained
                    abundance of spoil. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> This they were obliged to
                    sell in like manner as the former; and, though no rest was allowed them, they
                    proceeded, nevertheless, with the utmost alacrity to Ferentinum. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> But here they met a greater share both of difficulty
                    and danger: the fortifications were defended with the utmost vigour, and the
                    place was strongly fortified both by nature and art. However, the soldiers, now
                    inured to plunder, overcame every obstacle. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    Three thousand of the enemy were killed round the walls, and the spoil was given
                    to the troops. In some annals, the principal share of the honour of taking these
                    cities is attributed to Maximus. They say that Murgantia was taken by Decius;
                    Romulea and Ferentinum by Fabius. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some
                    ascribe this honour to the new consuls: others not to both, but to one of these,
                    Lucius Volumnius; that to him the province of Samnium had fallen. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While things went on thus in Samnium, whoever
                    it was that had the command and auspices, powerful combination, composed of many
                    states, was formed in Etruria against the Romans, the chief promoter of which
                    was Gellius Egnatius, a Samnite. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Almost all
                    the Etrurians had united in this war. The neighbouring states of Umbria were
                    drawn in, as it were, by the contagion; and auxiliaries were procured from the
                    Gauls for hire: all their several numbers assembled at the camp of the Samnites.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When intelligence of this sudden commotion
                    was received at Rome, after the consul, Lucius Volumnius, had already set out
                    for Samnium, with the second and third legions, and fifteen thousand of the
                    allies; it was, therefore, resolved, that Appius Claudius should, at the very
                    earliest <pb n="650" xml:id="p.650"/> opportunity, go into Etruria. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> Two Roman legions followed him, the first and fourth,
                    and twelve thousand allies; their camp was pitched at a small distance from the
                    enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> However, advantage was gained by his
                    early arrival in this particular, that the awe of the Roman name kept in check
                    some states of Etruria which were disposed to war, rather than from any
                    judicious or successful enterprise achieved under the guidance of the consul.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Several battles were fought, at times and
                    places unfavourable, and increasing confidence rendered the enemy daily more
                    formidable; so that matters came nearly to such a state, as that neither could
                    the soldiers rely much on their leader, nor the leader on his soldiers. It
                    appears in three several histories, that a letter was sent by the consul to call
                    his colleague from Samnium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> But I will not
                    affirm what requires stronger proof, as that point was a matter of dispute
                    between these two consuls of the Roman people, a second time associated in the
                    same office; Appius denying that the letter was sent, and Volumnius affirming
                    that he was called thither by a letter from Appius. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Volumnius had, by this time, taken three forts in Samnium,
                    in which three thousand of the enemy had been slain, and about half that number
                    made prisoners; and, a sedition having been raised among the Lucanians by the
                    plebeians and the more indigent of the people, he had, to the great satisfaction
                    of the nobles, quelled it by sending thither Quintus Fabius, proconsul, with his
                    own veteran army. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He left to Decius the
                    ravaging of the enemy's country; and proceeded with his troops into Etruria to
                    his colleague; where, on his arrival, the whole army received him with joy.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Appius, if he did not write the letter,
                    being conscious of this, had, in my opinion, just ground of displeasure; but if
                    he had actually stood in need of assistance, his disowning it, as he did, arose
                    from an illiberal and ungrateful mind. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> For,
                    on going out to receive him, when they had scarcely exchanged salutations, he
                    said, <quote> Is all well, Lucius Volumnius? How stand affairs in Samnium? What
                        motive induced you to remove out of your province? </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Volumnius answered, that <quote> affairs in
                        Samnium were in a prosperous state; and that he had come thither in
                        compliance with the request in his letter. But, if that were a forged
                        letter, and that there was no occasion for him in Etruria, he would
                        instantly face about, and depart. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>You may depart,</quote> replied the other; <quote> no one detains you:
                        for it <pb n="651" xml:id="p.651"/> is a perfect inconsistency, that when,
                        perhaps, you are scarcely equal to the management of your own war, you
                        should vaunt of coming hither to succour others. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> To this Volumnius rejoined, <quote> May
                        Hercules direct all for the best; for his part, he was better pleased that
                        he had taken useless trouble, than that any conjuncture should have arisen
                        which had made one consular army insufficient for Etruria. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> As the consuls were parting, the
                    lieutenants-general and tribunes of Appius's army gathered round them. Some
                    entreated their own general that he would not reject the voluntary offer of his
                    colleague's assistance, which ought to have been solicited in the first
                    instance: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the greater number used their
                    endeavours to stop Volumnius, beseeching him <quote> not, through a peevish
                        dispute with his colleague, to abandon the interest of the commonwealth;
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> and represented to him, that in case
                        any misfortune should happen, the blame would fall on the person who forsook
                        the other, not on the one forsaken; that the state of affairs was such, that
                        the credit and discredit of every success and failure in Etruria would be
                        attributed to Lucius Volumnius: for no one would inquire, what were the
                        words of Appius, but what the situation of the army. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> Appius indeed had dismissed him, but the commonwealth,
                        and the army, required his stay. Let him only make trial of the inclinations
                        of the soldiers. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> By such admonitions and entreaties they, in a
                    manner, dragged the consuls, who almost resisted, to an assembly. There, longer
                    discourses were made to the same purport, as had passed before in the presence
                    of a few. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> And when Volumnius, who had the
                    advantage of the argument, showed himself not' deficient in oratory, in despite
                    of the extraordinary eloquence of his colleague; <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Appius observed with a sneer, that <quote> they ought to acknowledge
                        themselves indebted to him, in having a consul who possessed eloquence also,
                        instead of being dumb and speechless, when in their former consulate,
                        particularly during the first months, he was not able so much as to open his
                        lips; but now, in his harangues, even aspired after popularity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Volumnius replied, <quote> How much more
                        earnestly do I wish, that you had learned from me to act with spirit, than I
                        from you to speak with elegance: that now he made a final proposal, which
                        would determine, not which is the better orator, for that is not what the
                        public wants, but which is the better commander. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> The <pb n="652" xml:id="p.652"/> provinces are Etruria
                        and Samnium: that he might select which he preferred; that he, with his own
                        army, will undertake to manage the business either in Etruria or in Samnium. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The soldiers then, with loud clamours,
                    requested that they would, in conjunction, carry on the war in Etruria;
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> when Volumnius perceiving that it was the
                    general wish, said, <quote> Since I have been mistaken in apprehending my
                        colleague's meaning, I will take care that there shall be no room for
                        mistake with respect to the purport of your wishes. <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Signify by a shout whether you choose that I should
                        stay or depart. </quote> On this, a shout was raised, so loud, that it
                    brought the enemy out of their camp: they snatched up their arms, and marched
                    down in order of battle. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Volumnius likewise
                    ordered the signal to be sounded, and the standard to be advanced from the camp.
                    It is said that Appius hesitated, perceiving that, whether he fought or remained
                    inactive, his colleague would have the victory; and that, afterwards, dreading
                    lest his own legions also should follow Volumnius, he also gave the signal, at
                    the earnest desire of his men. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> On neither
                    side were the forces drawn up to advantage: for, on the one, Gellius Egnatius,
                    the Samnite general, had gone out to forage with a few cohorts, and his men
                    entered <milestone n="15??" unit="section"/> on the fight as the violence of
                    their passions prompted, rather than under any directions or orders. <milestone
                        n="16" unit="section"/> On the other, the Roman armies neither marched out
                    together, nor had time sufficient to form: Volumnius began to engage before
                    Appius came up to the enemy, consequently the engagement commenced, their front
                    in the battle being uneven; and by some accidental interchange of their usual
                    opponents, the Etrurians fought against Volumnius; and the Samnites, after
                    delaying some time on account of the absence of their general, against Appius.
                        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> We are told that Appius, during the heat
                    of the fight, raising his hands toward heaven, so as to be seen in the foremost
                    ranks, prayed thus, <quote>Bellona, if thou grantest us the victory this day, I
                        vow to thee a temple.</quote> And that after this vow, as if inspirited by
                    the goddess, he displayed a degree of courage equal to that of his colleague and
                    of the troops. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> The generals performed every
                    duty, and each of their armies exerted, with emulation, its utmost vigour, lest
                    victory should commence on the other side. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>
                    They therefore routed and put to flight the enemy, who were ill able to
                    withstand a force so much superior to any with which they had been accustomed
                        <pb n="653" xml:id="p.653"/> to contend: <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    then pressing them as they gave ground, and pursuing them closely as they fled,
                    they drove them into their camp. There, by the interposition of Gellius and his
                    Samnite cohorts, the fight was renewed for a little time. <milestone n="21"
                        unit="section"/> But these being likewise soon dispersed, the camp was now
                    stormed by the conquerors; and whilst Volumnius, in person, led his troops
                    against one of the gates, Appius, frequently invoking Bellona the victorious,
                    inflamed the courage of his men, they broke in through the rampart and trenches.
                        <milestone n="22" unit="section"/> The camp was taken and plundered, and an
                    abundance of spoil was found, and given up to the soldiers. Of the enemy seven
                    thousand three hundred were slain; and two thousand one hundred and twenty
                    taken. </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While both the consuls, with the whole force
                    of the Romans, pointed their exertions principally against the war in Etruria, a
                    new army which arose in Samnium, with design to ravage the frontiers of the
                    Roman empire, passed over through the country of the Vescians, into the
                    Campanian and Falernian territories, and committed great depredations.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Volumnius, as he was hastening back to
                    Samnium, by forced marches, because the term for which Fabius and Decius had
                    been continued in command was nearly expired, heard of this army of Samnites,
                    and of the mischief which they had done in Campania; determining, therefore, to
                    afford protection to the allies, he altered his route towards that quarter.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When he arrived in the district of Cales,
                    he found marks of their recent ravages; and the people of Cales informed him
                    that the enemy carried with them such a quantity of spoil, that they could
                    scarcely observe any order in their march: <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and
                    that the commanders then directed publicly that the troops should go immediately
                    to Samnium, and having deposited the booty there, that they should return to the
                    business of the expedition, as they must not commit to the hazard of an
                    engagement an army so heavily laden. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Notwithstanding that this account carried every appearance of truth, he yet
                    thought it necessary to obtain more certain information; <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> accordingly he despatched some horsemen, to seize on some
                    of the straggling marauders; from these he learned, on inquiry, that the enemy
                    lay at the river Vulturnus; that they intended to remove thence at the third
                    watch; and that their route was towards Samnium. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> On receiving this intelligence, which could be de- <pb n="654" xml:id="p.654"
                    /> pended upon, he set out, and sat down at such a distance from the enemy, that
                    his approach could not be discovered by his being too near them, and, at the
                    same time, that he might surprise them, as they should be coming out of their
                    camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> A long time before day, he drew nigh to
                    their post, and sent persons, who understood the Oscan language, to discover how
                    they were employed: these, mixing with the enemy, which they could easily do
                    during the confusion in the night, found that the standards had gone out thinly
                    attended; that the booty, and those appointed to guard it, were then setting
                    out, a contemptible train; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> each busied about
                    his own affairs, without any concert with the rest, or much regard to orders.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This was judged the fittest time for the
                    attack, and day-light was now approaching; he gave orders to sound the charge,
                    and fell on the enemy as they were marching out. The Samnites being embarrassed
                    with the spoil, and very few armed, some quickened their pace, and drove the
                    prey before them; others halted, deliberating whether it would be safer to
                    advance, or to return again to the camp; and while they hesitated, they were
                    overtaken and cut off. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The Romans had by this
                    time passed over the rampart, and filled the camp with slaughter and confusion:
                    the Samnite army, in addition to the disorder caused by the enemy, had their
                    disorder increased by a sudden insurrection of their prisoners; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> some of whom, getting loose, set the rest at
                    liberty, while others snatched the arms which were tied up among the baggage,
                    and being intermixed with the troops, raised a tumult more terrible than the
                    battle itself. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They then performed a
                    memorable exploit: for making an attack on Statius Minacius, the general, as he
                    was passing between the ranks and encouraging his men; then, dispersing the
                    horsemen who attended him, they gathered round himself; and dragged him, sitting
                    on his horse, a prisoner to the Roman consul. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    By this movement the foremost battalions of the Samnites were brought back, and
                    the battle, which seemed to have been already decided, was renewed: but they
                    could not support it long. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Six thousand of
                    them were slain, and two thousand five hundred taken, among whom were four
                    military tribunes, together with thirty standards, and, what gave the conquerors
                    greater joy than all, seven thousand four hundred prisoners were recovered. The
                    spoil which had been taken from the allies was immense, and the owners were
                    summoned <pb n="655" xml:id="p.655"/> by a proclamation, to claim and receive
                    their property. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> On the day appointed, all the
                    effects, the owners of which did not appear, were given to the soldiers, who
                    were obliged to sell them, in order that they might have nothing to think of but
                    their duty. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The depredations, committed on the lands of
                    Campania, had occasioned a violent alarm at Rome; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and it happened, that about the same time intelligence was
                    brought from Etruria, that, after the departure of Volumnius's army, all that
                    country had risen up in arms; and that Gellius Egnatius, the leader of the
                    Samnites, was causing the Umbrians to join in the insurrection, and tempting the
                    Gauls with high offers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Terrified at this
                    news, the senate ordered the courts of justice to be shut, and a levy to be made
                    of men of every description. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly not
                    only free-born men and the younger sort were obliged to enlist, but cohorts were
                    formed of the elder citizens, and the sons of freed-men were incorporated in the
                    centuries. Plans were formed for the defence of the city, and the praetor,
                    Publius Sempronius, was invested with the chief command. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> However, the senate was exonerated of one half of their
                    anxiety, by a letter from the consul, Lucius Volumnius, informing them that the
                    army, which had ravaged Campania, had been defeated and dispersed: whereupon,
                    they decreed a public thanksgiving for this success, in the name of the consul.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The courts were opened, after having been
                    shut eighteen days, and the thanksgiving was performed with much joy. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> They then turned their thoughts to devising measures
                    for the future security of the country depopulated by the Samnites; and, with
                    this view, it was resolved, that two colonies should be settled on the frontiers
                    of the Vescian and Falernian territories; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> one
                    at the mouth of the river Liris, which has received the name of Minturnae; the
                    other in the Vescian forest, which borders on the Falernian territory; where, it
                    is said, stood Sinope, a city of Grecians, called thenceforth by the Roman
                    colonists Sinuessa. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The plebeian tribunes were
                    charged to procure an order of the commons, commanding Publius Sempronius, the
                    praetor, to create triumvirs for conducting the colonies to those places.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But persons were not readily found to
                    give in their names; because they considered that they were being sent into what
                    was almost a perpetual advanced guard in a hostile country, not as a provision
                        <pb n="656" xml:id="p.656"/> of land. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    From these employments, the attention of the senate was drawn away by the
                    Etrurian war, growing now more formidable; and by frequent letters from Appius,
                    warning them not to neglect the disturbances in that quarter. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> That four nations were uniting their arms, the Etrurians,
                    the Samnites, the Umbrians, and the Gauls; and they had already formed two
                    separate camps, because one spot was insufficient to contain so great a
                    multitude. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> In consequence, the time of the
                    elections drawing nigh, the consul, Lucius Volumnius, was recalled to Rome, to
                    hold them. Having summoned an assembly of the people before he should call the
                    centuries to give their votes, he spoke at length on the great importance of the
                    Etrurian war, and said, that <quote> even at the time when he himself acted
                        there, in conjunction with his colleague, the war was too weighty to be
                        managed by one general or one army; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> and
                        that it was now reported, that the Umbrians had since that time joined them,
                        and a numerous body of Gauls. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He desired them to <quote> bear in mind, that
                        consuls were on that day to be chosen, who were to command in a war against
                        four nations. For his own part, were he not confident that the Roman people
                        would concur in appointing to the consulship the man who was allowed, beyond
                        dispute, to be the first commander at present in the world, he would have
                        immediately nominated a dictator. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> No one doubted but that Quintus Fabius would
                    be chosen by universal consent; and accordingly, the prerogative, and all the
                    first-called centuries, were for naming him consul with Lucius Volumnius.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The speech of Fabius was to the same
                    purpose as it had been two years before; but afterwards, when he yielded to the
                    general wish, he applied himself to procure Decius to be appointed his
                    confederate: <quote>that,</quote> he said, <quote> would be a prop to his
                        advanced age. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In the censorship, and two
                        consulships, in which they had been associated, he had experienced that
                        there could be no firmer support, in promoting the interest of the
                        commonwealth, than harmony with a colleague. At his advanced stage of life,
                        his mind could hardly conform itself to a new associate in command; and he
                        could more easily act in concert with a temper to which he had been
                        familiarized. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Volumnius subscribed to these sentiments, both
                    by bestowing due praises on Publius Decius, and enumerating <quote> the
                        advantages resulting <pb n="657" xml:id="p.657"/> from concord between
                        consuls, and the evils arising from their disagreement in the conduct of
                        military affairs; </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> at the same time remarking, <quote> how near
                        the extremity of danger matters had been brought, by the late dispute
                        between his colleague and himself. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He warmly recommended to Decius and Fabius to
                        <quote>live together with one mind and one spirit.</quote> Observed that
                        <quote> they were men qualified by nature for military command: great in
                        action, but unpractised in the strife of words and eloquence; their talents
                        were such as eminently became consuls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As
                        to the artful and the ingenious lawyers and orators, such as Appius
                        Claudius, they ought to be kept at home to preside in the city and the
                        forum; and to be appointed praetors for the administration of justice. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In these proceedings that day was spent, and,
                    on the following, the elections both of consuls and praetor were held, and were
                    guided by the recommendations suggested by the consul. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius were chosen consuls;
                    Appius Claudius, praetor; all of them absent; and, by a decree of the senate,
                    followed by an order of the commons, Lucius Volumnius was continued in the
                    command for another year. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During that year many prodigies happened. For
                    the purpose of averting which, the senate decreed a supplication for two days:
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> the wine and frankincense for the
                    sacrifices were furnished at the expense of the public; and numerous crowds of
                    men and women attended the performance. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This
                    supplication was rendered remarkable by a quarrel, which broke out among the
                    matrons in the chapel of patrician chastity, which stands in the cattle market,
                    near the round temple of Hercules. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Virginia,
                    daughter of Aulus, a patrician, but married to Volumnius the consul, a plebeian,
                    was, because she had married out of the patricians, excluded by the matrons from
                    sharing in the sacred rites: a short altercation ensued, which was afterwards,
                    through the intemperance of passion incident to the sex, kindled into a flame of
                    contention. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Virginia boasted with truth that
                    she had a right to enter the temple of patrician chastity, as being of patrician
                    birth, and chaste in her character, and, besides, the wife of one husband, to
                    whom she was betrothed a virgin, and had no reason to be dissatisfied either
                    with her husband, or his exploits or honours: to her high-spirited words, she
                    added importance by an <pb n="658" xml:id="p.658"/> extraordinary act.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> In the long street where she resided, she
                    enclosed with a partition a part of the house, of a size sufficient for a small
                    chapel, and there erected an altar. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then,
                    calling together the plebeian matrons, and complaining of the injurious
                    behaviour of the patrician ladies, she said, <quote> This altar I dedicate to
                        plebeian chastity, and exhort you, that the same degree of emulation which
                        prevails among the men of this state, on the point of valour, may be
                        maintained by the women on the point of chastity; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> and that you contribute your best care, that this altar
                        may have the credit of being attended with a greater degree of sanctity, and
                        by chaster women, than the other, if possible. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Solemn rites were performed at this altar
                    under the same regulations, nearly, with those at the more ancient one; no
                    person being allowed the privilege of taking part in the sacrifices, except a
                    woman of approved chastity, and who was the wife of one husband. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> This institution, being afterwards debased by [the
                    admission of] vicious characters, and not only by matrons, but women of every
                    description, sunk at last into oblivion. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    During this year the Ogulnii, Cneius and Quintus, being curule aediles, carried
                    on prosecutions against several usurers; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    whose property being fined, out of the produce, which was deposited in the
                    treasury, they ordered brazen thresholds for the Capitol, utensils of plate for
                    three tables in the chapel of Jupiter, a statue of Jupiter in a chariot drawn by
                    four horses placed on the roof, and images of the founders of the city in their
                    infant state under the teats of the wolf, at the Ruminal fig-tree. They also
                    paved with square stones the roads from the Capuan gate to the temple of Mars.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> By the plebeian aediles likewise, Lucius
                    Aelius Paetus and Caius Fulvius Corvus, out of money levied as fines on farmers
                    of the public pastures, whom they had convicted of malpractices, games were
                    exhibited, and golden bowls were placed in the temple of Ceres. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Then came into the consulship Quintus Fabius a
                    fifth time, and Publius Decius a fourth. They had been colleagues in the
                    censorship, and twice in the consulship, and were celebrated <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> not more for their glorious achievements, splendid as these
                    were, than for the unanimity which had ever subsisted between them. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> The continuance of this feeling I am inclined to
                    think was interrupted by a jarring between the [opposite] orders rather than
                    between themselves; the patricians endeavouring <pb n="659" xml:id="p.659"/>
                    that Fabius should have Etruria for his province, without casting lots, and the
                    plebeians insisting that Decius should bring the matter to the decision of lots.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> There was certainly a contention in the
                    senate, and the interest of Fabius being superior there, the business was
                    brought before the people. Here, between military men who laid greater stress on
                    deeds than on words, the debate was short. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Fabius said, <quote> that it was unreasonable, after he had planted a tree,
                        another should gather the fruit of it. He had opened the Ciminian forest,
                        and made a way for the Roman arms, through passes until then impracticable.
                        Why had they disturbed him, at that time of his life, if they intended to
                        give the management of the war to another? </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then, in the way of a gentle reproof, he
                    observed, that <quote> instead of an associate in command, he had chosen an
                        adversary; and that Decius thought it too much that their unanimity should
                        last through three consulates. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Declaring, in fine, that <quote> he desired
                        nothing further, than that, if they thought him qualified for the command in
                        the province, they should send him thither. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                        /> He had submitted to the judgment of the senate, and would now be governed
                        by the authority of the people. </quote> Publius Decius complained of
                    injustice in the senate; and asserted, that <quote> the patricians had laboured,
                        as long as possible, to exclude the plebeians from all access to the higher
                        honours; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and since merit, by its own
                        intrinsic power, had prevailed so far, as that it should not, in any rank of
                        men, be precluded from the attainment of honours, expedients were sought how
                        not only <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> the suffrages of the people,
                        but even the decisions of fortune may be rendered ineffectual, and be
                        converted to the aggrandizement of a few. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                        All the consuls before him had disposed of the provinces by lots; now, the
                        senate bestowed a province on Fabius without lots. If this was meant as a
                        mark of honour, the merits of Fabius were so great towards the commonwealth,
                        and towards <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> himself in particular, that
                        he would gladly second the advancement of his reputation, provided only its
                        splendour could be increased without reflecting dishonour on himself. But
                        who did not see, that, when a war of difficulty and danger, and out of the
                        ordinary course, was committed to only that one consul, the other would be
                        considered as useless and insignificant. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                        Fabius gloried in his exploits performed in Etruria: Publius Decius wished
                        for a like subject of glory, and perhaps <pb n="660" xml:id="p.660"/> would
                        utterly extinguish that fire, which the other left smother- ed, in such a
                        manner that it often broke out anew, in sudden conflagrations. <milestone
                            n="14" unit="section"/> In fine, honours and rewards he would concede to
                        his colleague, out of respect to his age and dignified character: but when
                        danger, when a vigorous struggle with an enemy was before them, he never
                        did, nor ever would, willingly, give place. <milestone n="15" unit="section"
                        /> With respect to the present dispute, this much he would gain at all
                        events, that a business, appertaining to the jurisdiction of the people,
                        should be determined by an order of that people, and not complimented away
                        by the senate. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> He prayed Jupiter,
                        supremely good and great, and all the immortal gods, not to grant him an
                        equal chance with his colleague, unless they intended to grant him equal
                        ability and success, in the management of the war. <milestone n="17"
                            unit="section"/> It was certainly in its nature reasonable, in the
                        example salutary, and concerned the reputation of the Roman people, that the
                        consuls should be men of such abilities, that under either of them a war
                        with Etruria could be well managed. </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> Fabius, after requesting of the people
                    nothing else than that, before the tribes were called in to give their votes,
                    they would hear the letters of the praetor Appius Claudius, written from
                    Etruria, withdrew from the Comitium, and with no less unanimity of the people
                    than of the senate, the province of Etruria was decreed to him without having
                    recourse to lots. </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Immediately almost all the younger citizens
                    flocked together to the consul, and readily gave in their names; so strong was
                    their desire of serving under such a commander. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Seeing so great a multitude collected round him, he said, <quote> My
                        intention is to enlist only four thousand foot and six hundred horse: such
                        of you as give in your names to-day and tomor- row, I will carry with me.
                            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I am more solicitous to bring home all
                        my soldiers rich, than to employ a great multitude. </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Accordingly, with a competent number of men,
                    who possessed greater hopes and confidence because a numerous army had not been
                    required, he marched to the town of Aharna, from which the enemy were not far
                    distant, and proceeded to the camp of the praetor Appius. When within a few
                    miles of it, he was met by some soldiers, sent to cut wood, attended by a guard.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Observing the lictors preceding him, and
                    learning that he was Fabius the consul, they were filled with joy and alacrity;
                    they expressed their thanks to the gods, and to <pb n="661" xml:id="p.661"/> the
                    Roman people, for having sent them such a commander. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Then, as they gathered round to pay their respects, Fabius
                    inquired whither they were going; and on their answering they were going to
                    provide wood, <quote>What do you tell me,</quote> said he; <quote>have you not a
                        rampart, raised about your camp?</quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When to this they replied, <quote> they had a
                        double rampart, and a trench; and, notwithstanding, were in great
                        apprehension. </quote>
                    <quote>Well then,</quote> said he, <quote>you have abundance of wood, go back
                        and level the rampart.</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They accordingly returned to the camp, and
                    there levelling the rampart, threw the soldiers who had remained in it, and
                    Appius himself, into the greatest fright, until with eager joy each called out
                    to the rest, that, <quote>they acted by order of the consul, Quintus
                        Fabius.</quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Next day the camp was moved from thence, and
                    the praetor, Appius, was dismissed to Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    From that time the Romans had no fixed post; the consul affirming, that it was
                    prejudicial to an army to lie in one spot; and that by frequent marches, and
                    changing places, it was rendered more healthy, and more capable of brisk
                    exertions: and marches were made as long as the winter, which was not yet ended,
                    permitted. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Then, in the beginning of spring,
                    leaving the second legion near Clusium, which they formerly called the
                    Camertian, and giving the command of the camp to Lucius Scipio, as proprietor,
                    he returned to Rome, in order to adjust measures for carrying on the war;
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> either led thereto by his own judgment,
                    because the war seemed to him more serious than he had believed, from report;
                    or, being summoned by a decree of the senate; for writers give both accounts.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Some choose to have it believed, that he
                    was forced back by the praetor, Appius Claudius; who, both in the senate, and
                    before the people, exaggerated, as he was wont in all his letters, the danger of
                    the Etrurian war, contending, that <quote> one general, or one army, would not
                        be sufficient to oppose four nations. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                        That whether these directed the whole of their combined force against him
                        alone, or acted separately in different parts, there was reason to fear,
                        that he would be unable to provide against every emergency. <milestone
                            n="15" unit="section"/> That he had left there but two Roman legions;
                        and that the foot and horse, who came with Fabius, did not amount to five
                        thousand. It was, therefore, his opinion, that the consul Publius Decius
                        should, without delay, set out to his colleague in Etruria; and that the
                        province of Samnium should be given to Lucius Vo- <pb n="662" xml:id="p.662"
                        /> lumnius. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> But if the consul preferred
                        going to his own province, that then Volumnius should march a full consular
                        army into Etruria, to join the other consul. </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> When the advice of the prae- tor influenced a
                    great part of the members, they say that Publius Decius recommended that
                    everything should be kept undetermined, and open for Quintus Fabius; until he
                    should either come to Rome, if he could do so without prejudice to the public,
                    or send some of his lieutenants, from whom the senate might learn the real state
                    of the war in Etruria; <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> and with what number
                    of troops, and by how many generals, it should be carried on. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Fabius, as soon as he returned to Rome,
                    qualified his discourses, both in the senate and when brought before the people,
                    in such a manner as to appear neither to exaggerate, or lessen, any particular
                    relating to the war; and to show, that, in agreeing to another general being
                    joined with him, he rather indulged the apprehensions of others, than guarded
                    against any danger to himself, or the public. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>But if they chose,</quote> he said, <quote> to give him an assistant in
                        the war, and associate in command, how could he overlook Publius Decius the
                        consul, whom he had tried during so many associations in office? <milestone
                            n="3" unit="section"/> There was no man living whom he would rather wish
                        to be joined in commission with him: with Publius Decius he should have
                        forces sufficient, and never too many enemies. <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> If, however, his colleague preferred any other
                        employment, let them then give him Lucius Volumnius as an assistant.
                    </quote> The disposal of every particular was left entirely to Fabius by the
                    people and the senate, and even by his colleague. And when Decius declared that
                    he was ready to go either to Etruria or Samnium, such general congratulation and
                    satisfaction took place, that victory was anticipated, and it seemed as if a
                    triumph, not a war, had been decreed to the consuls. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> I find in some writers, that Fabius and Decius, immediately
                    on their entering into office, set out together for Etruria, without any mention
                    of the casting of lots for the provinces, or of the disputes which I have
                    related. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Others, not satisfied with relating
                    those disputes, have added charges of misconduct, laid by Appius before the
                    people against Fabius, when absent; and a stubborn opposition, maintained by the
                    praetor against the consul, when present; and also another contention between
                    the colleagues, Decius insisting that each consul should attend to the care of
                    his own separate province. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Certainty, <pb
                        n="663" xml:id="p.663"/> however, begins to appear from the time when both
                    consuls set out for the campaign. Now, before the consuls arrived in Etruria,
                    the Senonian Gauls came in a vast body to Clusium, to attack the Roman legion
                    and the camp. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Scipio, who commanded the camp,
                    wishing to remedy the deficiency of his numbers by an advantage in the ground,
                    led his men up a hill, which stood between the camp and the city: <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> but having, in his haste, neglected to examine the
                    place, he reached near the summit, which he found already possessed by the
                    enemy, who had ascended on the other side. The legion was consequently attacked
                    on the rear, and surrounded in the middle, when the enemy pressed it on all
                    sides. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Some writers say, that the whole were
                    cut off, so that not one survived to give an account of it; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> and that no information of the misfortune reached the
                    consuls, who were, at the time, not far from Clusium, until the Gallic horsemen
                    came within sight, carrying the heads of the slain, some hanging before their
                    horses' breasts, others on the points of their spears, and expressing their
                    triumph in songs according to their custom. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    Others affirm, that the defeat was by Umbrians, not Gauls, and that the loss
                    sustained was not so great. That a party of foragers, under Lucius Manlius
                    Torquatus, lieutenant-general, being surrounded, Scipio, the proprietor, brought
                    up relief from the camp, and the battle being renewed, that the Umbrians, lately
                    victorious, were defeated, and the prisoners and spoil retaken. <milestone
                        n="13" unit="section"/> But it is more probable that this blow was suffered
                    from a Gallic than an Umbrian enemy; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> because
                    during that year, as was often the case at other times, the danger principally
                    apprehended by the public, was that of a Gallic tumult; for which reason,
                    notwithstanding that both the consuls had marched against the enemy, with four
                    legions, and a large body of Roman cavalry, joined by a thousand chosen horsemen
                    of Campania, supplied on the occasion, and a body of the allies and Latin
                    confederates, superior in number to the Romans, two other armies were posted
                    near the city, on the side facing Etruria; one in the Faliscian, the other in
                    the Vatican territory. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Cneius Fulvius and
                    Lucius Postumius Megellus, both propraetors, were ordered to keep the troops
                    stationed in those places. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, having crossed the Apennines,
                    came up with the enemy in the territory of Sentinum; their camp was pitched
                    there at the distance of about four miles. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Several <pb n="664" xml:id="p.664"/> councils were then held by the enemy, and
                    their plan of oper- ations was thus settled: that they should not encamp
                    together, nor go out together to battle; the Gauls were united to the Samnites,
                    the Umbrians to the Etrurians. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The day of
                    battle was fixed. The part of maintaining the fight was committed to the
                    Samnites and Gauls; and the Etrurians and Umbrians were ordered to attack the
                    Roman camp during the heat of the engagement. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    This plan was frustrated by three Clusian deserters, who came over by night to
                    Fabius, and after disclosing the above designs, were sent back with presents, in
                    order that they might discover, and bring intelligence of, any new scheme which
                    should be determined on. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consuls then
                    wrote to Flavius and Postumius to move their armies, the one from the Faliscian,
                    the other from the Vatican country, towards Clusium; and to ruin the enemy's
                    territory by every means in their power. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The
                    news of these depredations drew the Etrurians from Sentinum to protect their own
                    region. The consuls, in their absence, practised every means to bring on an
                    engagement. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For two days they endeavoured, by
                    several attacks, to provoke the enemy to fight; in which time, however, nothing
                    worth mention was performed. A few fell on each side, but still the minds [of
                    the Romans] were irritated to wish for a general engagement; yet nothing
                    decisive was hazarded. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> On the third day, both
                    parties marched out their whole force to the field: here, while the armies stood
                    in order of battle, a hind, chased by a wolf from the mountains, ran through the
                    plain between the two lines: there the animals taking different directions, the
                    hind bent its course towards the Gauls, the wolf towards the Romans: way was
                    made between the ranks for the wolf, the Gauls slew the hind with their
                    javelins; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> on which one of the Roman soldiers
                    in the van said, <quote> To that side, where you see an animal, sacred to Diana,
                        lying prostrate, flight and slaughter are directed; on this side the
                        victorious wolf of Mars, safe and untouched, reminds us of our founder, and
                        of our descent from that deity. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The Gauls were posted on the right wing, the
                    Samnites on the left: against the latter, Fabius drew up, as his right wing, the
                    first and third legions: against the Gauls, Decius formed the left wing of the
                    fifth and sixth. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The second and fourth were
                    employed in the war in Samnium, under the proconsul, Lucius Volumnius. In the
                    first encounter the action was <pb n="665" xml:id="p.665"/> supported with
                    strength so equal on both sides, that had the Etrurians and Umbrians been
                    present, either in the field or at the camp, in whichever place they might have
                    employed their force, the Romans must have been defeated. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> However, although the victory was still
                    undecided, fortune not having declared in favour of either party, yet the course
                    of the fight was by no means similar on both right and left wings. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The Romans, under Fabius, rather repelled than
                    offered assault; and the contest was protracted until very late in the day: for
                    their general knew very well, that both Samnites and Gauls were furious in the
                    first onset; so that, to withstand them would be sufficient. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> It was known, too, that in a protracted contest the spirits
                    of the Samnites gradually flagged, and even the bodies of the Gauls, remarkably
                    ill able to bear labour and heat, became quite relaxed; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and although, in their first efforts, they were more than
                    men, yet in their last they were less than women. He, therefore, reserved the
                    strength of his men as unimpaired as possible, until the time when the enemy
                    were the more likely to be worsted. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Decius,
                    more impetuous, as being in the prime of life and full flow of spirits, exerted
                    whatever force he had to the utmost in the first encounter; and thinking the
                    infantry not sufficiently energetic, brought up the cavalry to the fight.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Putting himself at the head of a troop of
                    young horsemen of distinguished bravery, he besought those youths, the flower of
                    the army, to charge the enemy with him; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    [telling them] <quote> they would reap a double share of glory, if the victory
                        should commence on the left wing, and through their means. </quote> Twice
                    they compelled the Gallic cavalry to give way. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    At the second charge, when they advanced farther and were briskly engaged in the
                    midst of the enemy's squadrons, by a method of fighting new to them, they were
                    thrown into dismay. A number of the enemy, mounted on chariots and cars, made
                    towards them with such a prodigious clatter from <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> the trampling of the cattle and rolling of wheels, as
                    affrighted the horses of the Romans, unaccustomed to such tumultuous operations.
                    By this means the victorious cavalry were dispersed, through a panic, and men
                    and horses, in their headlong flight, were tumbled promiscuously on the ground.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hence also the battalions of the legions
                    were thrown into disorder: <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> through the
                    impetuosity of the horses, and of the carriages which they dragged through <pb
                        n="666" xml:id="p.666"/> the ranks, many of 'the soldiers in the van were
                    trodden or bruised to death; while the Gallic line, as soon as they saw their
                    enemy in confusion, pursued the advantage, nor allowed them time to take breath
                    or recover themselves. Decius, calling aloud, <quote>Whither were they flying,
                        or what hope could they have in running away?</quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> strove to stop them as they turned their
                    backs; but finding that he could not, by any efforts, prevail on them to keep
                    their posts, so thoroughly were they dismayed, he called on his father, Publius
                    Decius, by name. He said, <quote> Why do I any longer defer the fate entailed on
                        my family? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> It is destined to our race,
                        that we should serve as expiatory victims to avert the public danger. I will
                        now offer the legions of the enemy, together with myself, to be immolated to
                        Earth, and the infernal gods. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Having thus said, he commanded Marcus Livius,
                    a pontiff, whom, at his coming out to the field, he had charged not to stir from
                    him, to dictate the form of words in which he was to devote himself, and the
                    legions of the enemy, for the army of the Roman people, the Quirites. <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> He was accordingly devoted with the same
                    imprecations, and in the same habit, in which his fa- ther, Publius Decius, had
                    ordered himself to be devoted at the Veseris in the Latin war. <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> When, immediately after the solemn imprecation, he added,
                    that <quote> he drove before him dismay and flight, slaughter and blood, and the
                        wrath of the gods celestial and infernal; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>
                        that, with the contagious influence of the furies, the ministers of death,
                        he would infect the standards, the weapons, and the armour of the enemy; and
                        that the same spot should be that of his perdition, and that of the Gauls
                        and Samnites. </quote>
                    <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> After uttering these execrations on himself
                    and the foe, he spurred forward his horse, where he saw the line of the Gauls
                    thickest, and, rushing upon the enemy's weapons, met his death. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Thenceforward the battle seemed to be fought
                    with a degree of force scarcely human. The Romans, on the loss of their general,
                    a circumstance which, on other occasions, is wont to inspire terror, stopped
                    their flight, and were anxious to begin the combat afresh. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> The Gauls, and especially the multitude which encircled the
                    consul's body, as if deprived of reason, cast their javelins at random without
                    execution; some became so stupid as not to think of either fighting or flying:
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> while on the other side, Livius, the
                    pontiff, to whom Decius <pb n="667" xml:id="p.667"/> had transferred his
                    lictors, with orders to act as propraetor, cried out aloud, that <quote> the
                        Romans were victorious, being saved by the death of their consul. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> That the Gauls and Samnites were now the victims
                        of mother Earth and the infernal gods. That Decius was summoning and
                        dragging to himself the army devoted along with him: and that, among the
                        enemy, all was full of dismay, and the vengeance of all the furies. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> While the soldiers were busy in restoring the
                    fight, Lucius Cornelius Scipio and Caius Marcius, with some reserved troops from
                    the rear, who had been sent by Quintus Fabius, the consul, to the support of his
                    colleague, came up. There the fate of Decius is ascertained, a powerful stimulus
                    to brave every danger in the cause of the public. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Wherefore, when the Gauls stood in close order, with their
                    shields formed into a fence before them, and but little prospect of success
                    appeared from a close fight, the javelins, which lay scattered between the two
                    lines, were, therefore, by order of the lieutenants-general, gathered up from
                    the ground, and thrown against the enemy's shields, and as most of them pierced
                    the fence, the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> long-pointed ones even into
                    their bodies, their compact band was overthrown in such a manner, that a great
                    many, who were unhurt, yet fell as if thunderstruck. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Such were the changes of fortune on the left wing of the
                    Romans: on the right, Fabius had at first protracted the time, as we mentioned
                    above, in slow operations; then, as soon as he perceived that neither the shout,
                    nor the efforts of the enemy, nor the weapons which they threw, retained their
                    former force, having ordered the commanders of the cavalry <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> to lead round their squadrons to the flank of the Samnites,
                    so that, on receiving the signal, they should charge them in flank, with all
                    possible violence, he commanded, at the same time, his infantry to advance
                    leisurely, and drive the enemy from their ground. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> When he saw that they were unable to make resistance, and
                    that their exhaustion was certain, drawing together all his reserves, whom he
                    had kept fresh for that occasion, he made a brisk push with the legions, and
                    gave the cavalry the signal to charge. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    Samnites could not support the shock, but fled precipitately to their camp,
                    passing by the line of the Gauls, and leaving their allies to fight by
                    themselves. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> These stood in close order under
                    cover of their shields: Fabius, therefore, having heard of the death of his
                    colleague, ordered <pb n="668" xml:id="p.668"/> the squadron of' Campanian
                    cavalry, in number about five hundred, to fall back from the ranks, and riding
                    round, to attack the rear of the Gallic line, then the chief strength of the
                    third legion to follow, with directions that wherever <milestone n="13??"
                        unit="section"/> they should see the enemy's troops disordered by the
                    charge, to follow the blow, and cut them to pieces, when in a state of
                    consternation. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> After vowing a temple and the
                    spoils of the enemy to Jupiter the Victorious, he proceeded to the camp of the
                    Samnites, whither all their forces were hurrying in confusion. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> The gates not affording entrance to such very great
                    numbers, those who were necessarily excluded, attempted resistance just at the
                    foot of the rampart, and here fell Gellius Egnatius, the Samnite general.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> These, however, were soon driven within
                    the rampart; the camp was taken after a slight resistance; and at the same time
                    the Gauls were attacked on the rear, and overpowered. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> There were slain of the enemy on that day twenty-five
                    thousand: eight thousand were taken prisoners. Nor was the victory an unbloody
                    one; for, of the army of Publius Decius, the killed amounted to seven thousand;
                    of the army of Fabius, to one thousand two hundred. <milestone n="18"
                        unit="section"/> Fabius, after sending persons to search for the body of his
                    colleague, had the spoils of the enemy collected into a heap, and burned them as
                    an offering to Jupiter the Victorious. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> The
                    consul's body could not be found that day, being hid under a heap of slaughtered
                    Gauls: on the following, it was discovered and brought to the camp, amidst
                    abundance of tears shed by the soldiers. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>
                    Fabius, discarding all concern about any other business, solemnized the
                    obsequies of his colleague in the most honourable manner, passing on him the
                    high encomiums which he had justly merited. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> During the same period, matters were managed
                    successfully by Cneius Fulvius, proprietor, he having, besides the immense
                    losses occasioned to the enemy by the devastation of their lands, fought a
                    battle with extraordinary success, in which there were above three thousand
                        <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> of the Perusians and Clusians slain, and
                    twenty military standards taken. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Samnites,
                    in their flight, passing through the Pelignian territory, were attacked on all
                    sides by the Pelignians; and, out of five thousand, one thousand were killed.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The glory of the day on which they fought
                    at Sentinum was great, even when truly estimated; but some have gone beyond
                    credibility by <pb n="669" xml:id="p.669"/> their exaggerations, who assert in
                    their writings, that there <milestone n="5??" unit="section"/> were in the army
                    of the enemy forty thousand three hundred and thirty foot, six thousand horse,
                    and one thousand chariots, that is, including the Etrurians and Umbrians, who
                    [they affirm] were present in the engagement: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    and, to magnify likewise the number of Roman forces, they add to the consuls
                    another general, Lucius Volumnius, proconsul, and his army to the legions of the
                    consul. In the greater number of annals, that victory is ascribed entirely to
                    the two consuls. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Volumnius was employed in the
                    mean time in Samnium; he drove the army of the Samnites to Mount Tifernus, and,
                    not deterred by the difficulty of the ground, routed and dispersed them.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius, leaving Decius's army in
                    Etruria, and leading off his own legions to the city, triumphed over the Gauls,
                    Etrurians, and Samnites: the soldiers attended him in his triumph. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> The victory of Quintus Fabius was not more highly
                    celebrated, in their coarse military verses, than the illustrious death of
                    Publius Decius; and the memory of the father was recalled, whose fame had been
                    equalled by the praiseworthy conduct of the son, in respect of the issue which
                    resulted both to himself and to the public. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Out of the spoil, donations were made to the soldiers of eighty-two <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 5 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3 1/4
                            <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to each, with cloaks and vests; rewards for service, in that age, by no
                    means contemptible. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Notwithstanding these successes, peace was not
                    yet established, either among the Samnites or Etrurians: for the latter, at the
                    instigation of the Perusians, resumed their arms, after his army had been
                    withdrawn by the consul; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and the Samnites made
                    predatory incursions on the territories of Vescia and Formiae; and also on the
                    other side, on those of Aesernia, and the parts adjacent to the river Vulturnus.
                    Against these was sent the praetor Appius Claudius, with the army formerly
                    commanded by Decius. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In Etruria, Fabius, on
                    the revival of hostilities, slew four thousand five hundred of the Perusians,
                    and took prisoners one thousand seven hundred and forty, who were ransomed at
                    the rate of three hundred and ten <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified">1.</note> each. All the rest of the
                    spoil was bestowed on the soldiers. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The
                    legions of the Samnites, though pursued, some by the praetor Appius Claudius,
                    the others by Lucius Volumnius, proconsul, formed a junction in the coun- <pb
                        n="670" xml:id="p.670"/> try of the Stellatians. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Here sat down the whole body of the Samnites; and Appius
                    and Volumnius, with their forces united in one camp. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> A battle was fought with the most rancorous animosity, one
                    party being spurred on by rage against men who had so often renewed their
                    attacks on them, and the other now fighting in support of their last remaining
                    hope. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Accordingly, there were slain, of the
                    Samnites, sixteen thousand three hundred, and two thousand and seven hundred
                    made prisoners: of the Roman army fell two thousand and seven hundred.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This year, so successful in the operations
                    of war, was filled with distress at home, arising from a pestilence, and with
                    anxiety, occasioned by prodigies: for accounts were received that, in many
                    places, showers of earth had fallen; and that very many persons, in the army of
                    Appius Claudius, had been struck by lightning; in consequence of which, the
                    books were consulted. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> At this time, Quintus
                    Fabius Gurges, the consul's son, having prosecuted some matrons before the
                    people on a charge of adultery, built, with the money accruing from the fines
                    which they were condemned to pay, the temple of Venus, which stands near the
                    circus. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Still we have the wars of the
                    Samnites on our hands, notwithstanding that the relation of them has already
                    extended, in one continued course, through four volumes of our history, and
                    through a period of forty-six years, from the consulate of Marcus Valerius and
                    Aulus Cornelius, who first carried the Roman arms into Samnium. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> And, not to recite the long train of disasters
                    sustained by both nations, and the toils which they underwent, by which,
                    however, their stubborn breasts could not be subdued; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> even in the course of the last year, the Samnites, with
                    their own forces separately, and also in conjunction with those of other
                    nations, had been defeated by four several armies, and four generals of the
                    Romans, in the territory of Sentinum, in that of the Pelignians, at Tifernum,
                    and in the plains of the Stellatians; had lost the general of the highest
                    character in their nation; <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> and, now, saw
                    their allies in the war, the Etrurians, the Umbrians, and the Gauls, in the same
                    situation with themselves; but, although they could now no longer stand, either
                    by their own or by foreign resources, yet did they not desist from the
                    prosecution of hostilities. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> So far were they
                    from being weary of defending liberty, even though unsuccessfully: and they
                    preferred <pb n="671" xml:id="p.671"/> being defeated to not aspiring after
                    victory. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Who does not find his patience
                    tired, either in writing, or reading, of wars of such continuance; and which yet
                    exhausted not the resolution of the parties concerned? </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius were
                    succeeded in the consulship by Lucius Postumius Megellus and Marcus Atilius
                    Regulus. The province of Samnium was decreed to both in conjunction; because
                    intelligence had been received that the enemy had embodied three armies;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> with one that Etruria was to be recovered;
                    with another the ravages in Campania were to be repeated; and the third was
                    intended for the defence of their frontiers. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Sickness detained Postumius at Rome, but Atilius set out immediately, with
                    design to surprise the enemy in Samnium, before they should have advanced beyond
                    their own borders; for such had been the directions of the senate. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans met the enemy, as if by mutual
                    appointment, at a spot where, while they could be hindered, not only from
                    ravaging, but even from entering the Samnite territory, they could likewise
                    hinder the Samnites from continuing their progress into the countries which were
                    quiet, and the lands of the allies of the Roman people. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> While their camps lay opposite to each other, the Samnites
                    attempted an enterprise, which the Romans, so often their conquerors, would
                    scarcely have ventured to undertake; such is the rashness inspired by extreme
                    despair: this was to make an assault on the Roman camp. And although this
                    attempt, so daring, succeeded not in its full extent, yet it was not without
                    effect. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> There was a fog, which continued
                    through a great part of the day, so thick as to exclude the light of the sun,
                    and to prevent not only the view of any thing beyond the rampart, but scarcely
                    the sight of each other, when they should meet. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Depending on this, as a covering to the design, when the sun was scarcely yet
                    risen, and the light which he did afford was obscured by the fog, the Samnites
                    came up to an advanced guard of the Romans at one of the gates, who were
                    standing carelessly on their post. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> In the
                    sudden surprise, these had neither courage nor strength to make resistance: an
                    assault was then made, through the Decuman gate, in the rear of the camp:
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> the quaestor's quarters in consequence
                    were taken, and the quaestor, Lucius Opimius Pansa, was there slain; on this a
                    general alarm was given to take up arms. <pb n="672" xml:id="p.672"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consul, being roused by the tumult,
                    ordered two cohorts of the allies, a Lucanian and Suessanian, which happened to
                    be nearest, to defend the head-quarters, and led the companies of the legions
                    down the principal street. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These ran into the
                    ranks, scarcely taking time to furnish themselves with arms; and, as they
                    distinguished the enemy by their shout rather than by sight, could form no
                    judgment how great their number might be: thus, ignorant of the circumstances of
                    their situation, they at first drew back, and admitted the enemy into the heart
                    of the camp. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then when the consul cried out,
                    asking them, whether they intended to let themselves be beaten out beyond the
                    rampart, and then to return again to storm their own camp, they raised the
                    shout, and uniting their efforts, stood their ground; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> then made advances, pushed closely on the enemy, and having
                    forced them to give way, drove them back, without suffering their first terror
                    to abate. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They soon beat them out beyond the
                    gate and the rampart, but not daring to pursue them, because the darkness of the
                    weather made them apprehend an ambush, and content with having cleared the camp,
                    they retired within the rampart, having killed about three hundred of the enemy.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Of the Romans, including the first
                    advanced guard and the watchmen, and those who were surprised at the quaestor's
                    quarters, two hundred and thirty perished. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This not unsuccessful piece of boldness raised the spirits of the Samnites so
                    high, that they not only did not suffer the Romans to march forward into their
                    country, but even to procure forage from their lands; and the foragers were
                    obliged to go back into the quiet country of Sora. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> News of these events being conveyed to Rome, with
                    circumstances of alarm magnified beyond the truth, obliged Lucius Postumius, the
                    consul, though scarcely recovered from his illness, to set out for the army.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> However, before his departure, having
                    issued a proclamation that his troops should assemble at Sora, he dedicated the
                    temple of Victory, for the building of which he had provided, when curule
                    aedile, out of the money arising from fines; and, joining the army, he advanced
                    from Sora towards Samnium, to the camp of his colleague. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The Samnites, despairing of being able to make head against
                    the two armies, retreated from thence, on which the consuls, separating,
                    proceeded by different routes to lay waste the enemy's lands and besiege their
                    towns. <pb n="673" xml:id="p.673"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Postumius attempted to make himself master of
                    Mili- onia, at first by storm and an assault; but these not succeeding, he
                    carried his approaches to the walls, and thus gained an entrance into the place.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The fight was continued in all parts of
                    the city from the fourth hour until near the eighth, the result being a long
                    time uncertain: the Romans at last gained possession of the town. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Three thousand two hundred of the Samnites were
                    killed, four thousand seven hundred taken, besides the other booty. From thence
                    the legions were conducted to Ferentinum, out of which <milestone n="4??"
                        unit="section"/> the inhabitants had, during the night, retired in silence
                    through the opposite gate, with all their effects which could be either carried
                    or driven. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, on his arrival,
                    approached the walls with the same order and circumspection, as if he were to
                    meet an opposition here equal to what he had experienced at Milionia. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Then, perceiving a dead silence in the city, and
                    neither arms nor men on the towers and ramparts, he restrains the soldiers, who
                    were eager to mount the deserted fortifications, lest they might fall into a
                    snare. He ordered two divisions of the confederate Latin horse to ride round the
                    walls, and explore every particular. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> These
                    horsemen observed one gate, and, at a little distance, another on the same side,
                    standing wide open, and on the roads leading from these every mark of the enemy
                    having fled by night. They then rode up leisurely to the gates, from whence,
                    with perfect safety, they took a clear view through straight streets quite
                    across the city. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> They report to the consul,
                    that the city was abandoned by the enemy, as was plain from the solitude, the
                    recent tracks on their retreat, and the things which, in the confusion of the
                    night, they had left scattered up and down. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On
                    hearing this, the consul led round the army to that side of the city which had
                    been examined, and making the troops halt at a little distance from the gate,
                    gave orders that five horsemen should ride into the city; and when they should
                    have advanced a good way into it, then, if they saw all things safe, three
                    should remain there, and the other two return to him with intelligence.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These returned and said, that they had
                    proceeded to a part of the town from which they had a view on every side, and
                    that nothing but silence and solitude reigned through the whole extent of it.
                    The consul immediately led some light-armed cohorts into the city; ordering the
                    rest to fortify a camp in the mean <pb n="674" xml:id="p.674"/> time. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> The soldiers who entered the town, breaking open the
                    doors, found only a few persons, disabled by age or sickness; <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> and such effects left behind as could not, without
                    difficulty, be removed. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> These were seized as
                    plunder: and it was discovered from the prisoners, that several cities in that
                    quarter had, in pursuance of a concerted plan, resolved on flight; that their
                    towns-people had gone off at the first watch, and they believed that the same
                    solitude they should find in the other places. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> The accounts of the prisoners proved well-founded, and the consul took
                    possession of the forsaken towns. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The war was by no means so easy with the other
                    consul, Marcus Atilius. As he was marching his legions towards Luceria, to which
                    he was informed that the Samnites had laid siege, the enemy met him on the
                    border of the Lucerian territory. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Rage
                    supplied them, on this occasion, with strength to equal his: the battle was
                    stubbornly contested, and the victory doubtful; in the issue, however, more
                    calamitous on the side of the Romans, both because they were unaccustomed to
                    defeat, and that, on leaving the field, they felt more sensibly, than during the
                    heat of the action, how much more wounds and bloodshed had been on their side.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In consequence of this, such dismay spread
                    through the camp, as, had it seized them during the engagement, a signal defeat
                    would have been the result. Even as the matter stood, they spent the night in
                    great anxiety; expecting, every instant, that the Samnites would assault the
                    camp; or that, at the first light, they should be obliged to stand a battle with
                    a victorious enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On the side of the enemy,
                    however, although there was less loss, yet there was not greater courage. As
                    soon as day appeared, they wished to retire without any more fighting; but there
                    was only one road, and that leading close by the post of their enemy; on their
                    taking which, they seemed as if advancing directly to attack the camp.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul, therefore, ordered his men to
                    take arms, and to follow him outside the rampart, giving directions to the
                    lieutenants-general, tribunes, and the prefects of the allies, in what manner he
                    would have each of them act. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They all assured
                    him that "they would do every thing in their power, but that the soldiers were
                    quite dejected; that, from their own wounds, and the groans of the dying, they
                    had passed the whole night without sleep; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> that
                    if the enemy had approached the camp before day, <pb n="675" xml:id="p.675"/> so
                    great were the fears of the troops, that they would certainly have deserted
                    their standards. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Even at present they were restrained from flight merely by shame; and,
                        in other respects, were little better than vanquished men. </quote> This
                    account made the consul judge it necessary to go himself among the soldiers, and
                    speak to them; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> and, as he came up to each, he
                    rebuked them for their backwardness in taking arms, asking, <quote> Why they
                        loitered, and declined the fight? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> If they
                        did not choose to go out of the camp, the enemy would come into it; and they
                        must fight in defence of their tents, if they would not in defence of the
                        rampart. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Men who have arms in their
                        hands, and contend with their foe, have always a chance for victory; but the
                        man who waits naked and unarmed for his enemy, must suffer either death or
                        slavery. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To these reprimands and rebukes they
                    answered, that <quote> they were exhausted by the fatigue of the battle of
                        yesterday; and had no strength, nor even blood remaining; and besides, the
                        enemy appeared more numerous than they were the day before. </quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The hostile army, in the mean time, drew
                    near; so that, seeing every thing more distinctly as the distance grew less,
                    they asserted that the Samnites carried with them pallisades for a rampart, and
                    evidently intended to draw lines of circumvallation round the camp. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/> On this the consul exclaimed, with great
                    earnestness, against submitting to such an ignominious insult, and from so
                    dastardly a foe. <quote>Shall we even be blockaded,</quote> said he, <quote> in
                        our camp, and die, with ignominy, by famine, rather than bravely by the
                        sword, if it must be so? May the gods be propitious! <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> and let every one act in the manner which he thinks
                        becomes him. The consul Marcus Atilius, should no other accompany him, will
                        go out, even alone, to face the enemy; and will fall in the middle of the
                        Samnite battalions, rather than see the Roman camp enclosed by their
                        trenches. </quote>
                    <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> The lieutenants-general, tribunes, every
                    troop of the cavalry, and the principal centurions, expressed their approbation
                    of what the consul said; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> and the soldiers at
                    length, overcome by shame, took up their arms, but in a spiritless manner; and
                    in the same spiritless manner, marched out of the camp. In a long train, and
                    that not every where connected, melancholy, and seemingly subdued, they
                    proceeded towards the enemy, whose hopes and courage were not more steady than
                    theirs. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> As soon therefore as the Roman
                    standards were be- <pb n="676" xml:id="p.676"/> held, a murmur spread from front
                    to rear of the Samnites, that, as they had feared, <quote> the Romans were
                        coming out to oppose their march; <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> that
                        there was no road open, through which they could even fly thence; in that
                        spot they must fall, or else cut down the enemy's ranks, and make their way
                        over their bodies. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then threw the baggage in a heap in the
                    centre, and, with their arms prepared for battle, formed their line, each
                    falling into his post. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> There was now but a
                    small interval between the two armies, and both stood, waiting until the shout
                    and onset should be begun by their adversary. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>
                    Neither party had any inclination to fight, and they would have separated, and
                    taken different roads, unhurt and untouched, but that each had a dread of being
                    harassed, in retreat, by the other. Notwithstanding this shyness and reluctance,
                    an engagement unavoidably began, but spiritless, and with a shout which
                    discovered neither resolution nor steadiness; nor did any move a foot from his
                    post. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Roman consul, then, in order to
                    infuse life into the action, ordered a few troops of cavalry to advance out of
                    the line and charge: most of whom being thrown from their horses and the rest
                    put in disorder, several parties ran forward, both from the Samnite line, to cut
                    off those who had fallen, and from the Roman, to protect their friends.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> In consequence the battle became a little
                    more brisk, but the Samnites had come forward with more briskness, and also in
                    greater numbers, and the disordered cavalry, with their affrighted horses, trod
                    down their own party who came to their relief. Flight commencing in this
                    quarter, caused the whole Roman line to turn their backs. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> And now the Samnites had no employment for their arms but
                    against the rear of a flying enemy, when the <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/>
                    consul, galloping on before his men to the gate of the camp, posted there a body
                    of cavalry, with orders to treat as an enemy any person who should make towards
                    the rampart, whether Roman or Samnite; and, placing himself in the way of his
                    men, as they pressed in disorder towards the camp, denounced threats to the same
                    purport: <quote>Whither are you going, soldiers?</quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> said he; <quote> here also you will find both
                        men and arms; nor, while your consul lives, shall you pass the rampart,
                        unless victorious. Choose therefore which you will prefer, fighting against
                        your own countrymen, or the enemy. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> While the consul was thus <pb n="677"
                        xml:id="p.677"/> speaking the cavalry gathered round, with the points of
                    their spears presented, and ordered the infantry to return to the fight. Not
                    only his own brave spirit, but fortune likewise aided the consul, for the
                    Samnites did not push their advantage; so that he had time to wheel round his
                    battalions, and to change his front from the camp towards the enemy. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> The men then began to encourage each other to return
                    to the battle, while the centurions snatched the ensigns from the
                    standard-bearers and bore them forward, pointing out to the soldiers the enemy,
                    coming on in a hurry, few in number, and with their ranks disordered. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> At the same time the consul, with his hands lifted
                    up towards heaven, and raising his voice so as to be heard at a distance, vowed
                    a temple to Jupiter Stator, if the Roman army should rally from flight, and,
                    renewing the battle, cut down and defeat the Samnites. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> All divisions of the army, now, united their efforts to
                    restore the fight; officers, soldiers, the whole force, both of cavalry and
                    infantry; even the powers of heaven seemed to have looked, with favour, on the
                    Roman cause; so speedily was a thorough change effected in the fortune of the
                    day, the enemy being repulsed from the camp, and, in a short time, driven back
                    to the spot where the battle had commenced. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>
                    Here they stopped, being obstructed by the heap of baggage, lying in their way,
                    where they had thrown it together; and then, to prevent the plundering of their
                    effects, formed round them a circle of troops. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
                    /> On this, the infantry assailed them vigorously in front, while the cavalry,
                    wheeling, fell on their rear: and, being thus enclosed between the two, they
                    were all either slain, or taken prisoners. The number of the prisoners was seven
                    thousand two hundred, who were all sent under the yoke; the killed amounted to
                    four thousand eight hundred. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> The victory did
                    not prove a joyous one, even on the side of the Romans: when the consul took an
                    account of the loss sustained in the two days, the number returned, of soldiers
                    lost, was seven thousand three hundred. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                    During these transactions in Apulia, the Samnites with the other army having
                    attempted to seize on Iteramna, a Roman colony situated on the Latin road, did
                    not however obtain the town; <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> whence, after
                    ravaging the country, as they were driving off spoil, consisting of men and
                    cattle, together with the colonists whom they had taken, they met the consul
                    returning victorious from Luceria, and not only lost their <pb n="678"
                        xml:id="p.678"/> booty, but marching in disorder, in a long train, and hea-
                    vily encumbered, were themselves cut to pieces. <milestone n="18" unit="section"
                    /> The consul, by proclamation, summoned the owners to Interamna, to claim and
                    receive again their property, and leaving his army there, went to Rome to hold
                    the elections. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> On his applying for a triumph,
                    that honour was refused him, because he had lost so many thousands of his
                    soldiers; and also, because he had sent the prisoners under the yoke without
                    imposing any conditions. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The other consul, Postumius, because there was
                    no employment for his arms in Samnium, having led over his forces into Etruria,
                    first laid waste the lands of the Volsinians; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    and afterwards, on their marching out to protect their country, gained a
                    decisive victory over them, at a small distance from their own walls. Two
                    thousand two hundred of the Etrurians were slain; the proximity of their city
                    protected the rest. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The army was then led into
                    the territory of Rusella, and there, not only were the lands wasted, but the
                    town itself taken. More than two thousand men were made prisoners, and somewhat
                    less than that number killed on the walls. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But
                    a peace, effected that year in Etruria, was still more important and honourable
                    than the war had been. Three very powerful cities, the chief ones of Etruria,
                    (Volsinii, Perusia, and Arretium,) sued for peace; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> and having stipulated with the consul to furnish clothing
                    and corn for his army, on condition of being permitted to send deputies to Rome,
                    they obtained a truce for forty years, and a fine was imposed on each state of
                    five hundred thousand <hi rend="italics">asses,</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1614. 11 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi>
                        8 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to be immediately paid. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the
                    consul demanded a triumph from the senate, in consideration of these services,
                    rather to comply with the general practice, than in hope of succeeding;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and when he saw that one party, his own
                    personal enemies, another party, the friends of his colleague, refused him the
                    triumph, the latter to console a similar refusal, some on the plea that he had
                    been rather tardy in taking his departure from the city; others, that he had
                    passed from Samnium into Etruria without orders from the senate; he said,
                    "Conscript fathers, I shall not be so far mindful of your dignity, as to forget
                    that I am consul. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> By the same right of office
                    by which I conducted the war, I shall now have a triumph, when <pb n="679"
                        xml:id="p.679"/> this war has been brought to a happy conclusion, Samnium
                    and Etruria being subdued, and victory and peace procured. With these words he
                    left the senate. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On this arose a contention
                    between the plebeian tribunes; some of them declaring that they would protest
                    against his triumphing in a manner unprecedented; others, that they would
                    support his pretensions, in opposition to their colleagues. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> The affair came at length to be discussed before the
                    people, and the consul being summoned to attend, when he represented, that
                    Marcus Horatius and Lucius Valerius, when consuls, and lately Caius Marcus
                    Rutilus, father of the present censor, had triumphed, not by direction of the
                    senate, but by that of the people; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> he then
                    added that <quote> he would in like manner have laid his request before the
                        public, had he not known that some plebeian tribunes, the abject slaves of
                        the nobles, would have obstructed the law. That the universal approbation
                        and will of the people were and should be with him equivalent to any order
                        whatsoever. </quote>
                    <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Accordingly, on the day following, by the
                    support of three plebeian tribunes, in opposition to the protest of the other
                    seven, and the declared judgment of the senate, he triumphed; and the people
                    paid every honour to the day. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The historical
                    accounts regarding this year are by no means consistent; Claudius asserts, that
                    Postumius, after having taken several cities in Samnium, was defeated and put to
                    flight in Apulia; and that, being wounded himself, he was driven, with a few
                    attendants, into Luceria. That the war in Etruria was conducted by Atilius, and
                    that it was he who triumphed. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Fabius writes,
                    that the two consuls acted in conjunction, both in Samnium and at Luceria; that
                    an army was led over into Etruria, but by which of the consuls he has not
                    mentioned; <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> that at Luceria, great numbers
                    were slain on both sides; and that in that battle, the temple of Jupiter Stator
                    was vowed, the same vow having been formerly made by Romulus, but the fane only,
                    that is, the area appropriated for the temple, had been yet consecrated.
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> However, in this year, the state having
                    been twice bound by the same vow, it became a matter of religious obligation
                    that the senate should order the temple to be erected. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> In the next year, we find a consul,
                    distinguished by the united splendour of his own and his father's glory, Lucius
                    Papirius Cursor, as also a war of vast importance, and a vic- <pb n="680"
                        xml:id="p.680"/> tory of such consequence, as no man, excepting Lucius
                    Papirius, the consul's father, had ever before obtained over the Samnites.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> It happened too that these had, with the
                    same care and pains as on the former occasion, decorated their soldiers with the
                    richest suits of splendid armour; and they had, likewise, called in to their aid
                    the power of the gods, having, as it were, initiated the soldiers, by
                    administering the military oath, with the <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/>
                    solemn ceremonies practised in ancient times, and levied troops in every part of
                    Samnium, under an ordinance entirely new, that <quote> if any of the younger
                        inhabitants should not attend the meeting, according to the general's
                            <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> proclamation, or shall depart
                        without permission, his head should be devoted to Jupiter. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Orders being then issued, for all to assemble
                    at Aquilonia, the whole strength of Samnium came together, amounting to forty
                    thousand men. There a piece of ground, in the middle of the camp, was enclosed
                    with hurdles and boards, and covered over-head with linen cloth, the sides being
                    all of an equal length, about two hundred feet. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> In this place sacrifices were performed, according to directions read out of
                    an old linen book, the priest being a very old man, called Ovius Paccius, who
                    affirmed, that he took these ceremonials from the ancient ritual of the
                    Samnites, being the same which their ancestors used, when they <milestone
                        n="7??" unit="section"/> had formed the secret design of wresting Capua from
                    the Etrurians. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When the sacrifices were
                    finished, the general ordered a beadle to summon every one of those who were
                    most highly distinguished by their birth or conduct: these were introduced
                    singly. Besides the other exhibitions of the solemnity, calculated to impress
                    the mind with religious awe, there were, in the middle of the covered enclosure,
                    altars erected, about which lay the victims slain, and the centurions stood
                    around with their swords drawn. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The soldier
                    was led up to the altars, rather like a victim, than a performer in the
                    ceremony, and was bound by an oath not to divulge what he should see and hear in
                    that place. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He was then compelled to swear,
                    in a dreadful kind of form, containing execrations on his own person, on his
                    family and race, if he did riot go to battle, whithersoever the commanders
                    should lead; and, if either he himself fled from the field, or, in case he
                    should see any other flying, did not immediately kill him. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> At first some, refusing to take the oath, were put to death
                    round the altars, and ly- <pb n="681" xml:id="p.681"/> ing among the carcasses
                    of the victims, served afterwards as a warning to others not to refuse it.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> When those of the first rank in the
                    Samnite nation had been bound under these solemnities, the general nominated
                    ten, whom he desired to choose each a man, and so to proceed until they should
                    have filled up the number of sixteen thousand. This body, from the covering of
                    the enclosure wherein the nobility had been thus devoted, was called the linen
                    legion. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> They were furnished with splendid
                    armour and plumed helmets, to distinguish them above the rest. They had another
                    body of forces, amounting to somewhat more than twenty thousand, not inferior to
                    the linen legion, either in personal appearance, or renown in war, or their
                    equipment. This number, composing the main strength of the nation, sat down at
                    Aquilonia. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the other side, the consuls set out from
                    the city. First, Spurius Carvilius, to whom had been decreed the veteran
                    legions, which Marcus Atilius, the consul of the preceding year, had left in the
                    territory of Interamna, marched at their head into Samnium; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and, while the enemy were busied in their superstitious
                    rites, and holding their secret meeting, he took by storm the town of Amiternum.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Here were slain about two thousand eight
                    hundred men; and four thousand two hundred and seventy were made prisoners.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Papirius, with a new army, which he raised
                    in pursuance of a decree of the senate, made himself master of the city of
                    Duronia. He took fewer prisoners than his colleague; but slew much greater
                    numbers. Rich booty was acquired in both places. <milestone n="5" unit="section"
                    /> The consuls then, overrunning Samnium, and wasting the province of Atinum
                    with particular severity, arrived, Carvilius at Cominium, and Papirius at
                    Aquilonia, where the main force of the Samnites were posted. Here, for some
                    time, there was neither a cessation of action, nor any vigorous effort.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The day was generally spent in provoking
                    the enemy when quiet, and retiring when they offered resistance; in menacing,
                    rather than making an attack. By which practice of beginning, and then
                    desisting, even those trifling skirmishes were continually left without a
                    decision. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The other Roman camp was twenty
                    miles distant, and the advice of his absent colleague was appealed to on every
                    thing which he undertook, while Carvilius, on his part, directed a greater share
                    of his attention to Aquilonia, where the state of affairs was more <pb n="682"
                        xml:id="p.682"/> critical and important, than to Cominium, which he himself
                    was besieging. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When Papirius had fully
                    adjusted every measure, preparatory to an engagement, he despatched a message to
                    his colleague, that <quote> he intended, if the auspices permitted, to fight the
                        enemy on the day following; and that it would be necessary that he
                        (Carvilius) should at the same time make an assault on Cominium, with his
                        utmost force, that the Samnites there might have no leisure to send any
                        succour to Aquilonia. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The messenger had the day for the performance
                    of his journey, and he returned in the night, with an answer to the consul, that
                    his colleague approved of the plan. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Papirius,
                    on sending off the messenger, had instantly called an assembly, where he
                    descanted, at large, on the nature of the war in general, and <milestone
                        n="11??" unit="section"/> on the present mode of equipment adopted by the
                    enemy, which served for empty parade, rather than for any thing effectual
                    towards insuring success; for <quote>plumes,</quote> he said, <quote> made no
                        wounds; that a Roman javelin would make its way through shields, however
                        painted and gilt; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> and that the army,
                        refulgent from the whiteness of their tunics, would soon be besmeared with
                        blood, when matters came to be managed with the sword. <milestone n="13"
                            unit="section"/> His father had formerly cut off, to a man, a gold and
                        silver army of the Samnites; and such accoutrements had made a more
                        respectable figure, as spoils, in the hands of the conquering foe, than as
                        arms in those of the wearers. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Perhaps it
                        was allotted, by destiny, to his name and family, that they should be
                        opposed in command against the most powerful efforts of the Samnites; and
                        should bring home spoils, of such beauty, as to serve for ornaments to the
                        public places. The immortal gods were certainly on his side, on account of
                        the leagues so often solicited and so often broken. <milestone n="15"
                            unit="section"/> Besides, if a judgment <milestone n="16??"
                            unit="section"/> might be formed of the sentiments of the deities, they
                        never were more hostile to any army, than to that which, smeared with the
                        blood of human beings mixed with that of cattle in their abominable
                        sacrifice, doomed to the twofold resentment of the gods, dreading on the one
                        hand the divinities, witnesses of the treaties concluded with the Romans, on
                            <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> the other hand the imprecations
                        expressed in the oath sworn in contradiction to those treaties, swore with
                        reluctance, abhorred the oath, and feared at once the gods, their
                        countrymen, and their enemies. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the consul had recounted these
                    particulars, as- <pb n="683" xml:id="p.683"/> certained from the information of
                    the deserters, to the soldiers already enraged of themselves, they then, filled
                    with confidence in both divine and human aid, with one universal shout, demanded
                    the battle; were dissatisfied at the action being deferred to the following day;
                    they are impatient under the intended delay of a day and a night. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Papirius, at the third watch, having received his
                    colleague's letter, arose in silence, and sent the keeper of the chickens to
                    take the auspices. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was no one
                    description of men in the camp who felt not earnest wishes for the fight: the
                    highest and the lowest were equally eager; the general watching the ardour of
                    the soldiers, and the soldiers that of the general. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> This universal zeal spread even to those employed in taking
                    the auspices; for the chickens having refused to feed, the auspex ventured to
                    misrepresent the omen, and reported to the consul that they had fed voraciously.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> When the auspices were to be
                        taken from the chickens, the keeper threw some of their food upon the
                        ground, in their sight, and opened the door of their coop. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> If they did not come out; if they came out slowly; if
                        they refused to feed, or ate in a careless manner, the omen was considered
                        as bad. On the contrary, if <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> they rushed
                        out hastily and ate greedily, so that some of the food fell from their
                        mouths on the ground, this was considered as an omen of the best import; it
                        was called <hi rend="italics">tripudium solisti- mum,</hi> originally, <hi
                            rend="italics">terripavium,</hi> from <hi rend="italics">terra,</hi> and
                            <hi rend="italics">pavire,</hi> to <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        strike. </note> The consul, highly pleased, and giving notice that the
                    auspices were excellent, and that they were to act under the direction of the
                    gods, displayed the signal for battle. Just as he was going out to the field, he
                    happened to receive intelligence from a deserter, that twenty cohorts of
                    Samnites, consisting of about four hundred each, had marched towards Cominium.
                    Lest his colleague should be ignorant of this, he instantly despatched a
                    messenger to him, and then <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> ordered the troops
                    to advance with speed, having already assigned to each division of the army its
                    proper post, and appointed general officers to command them. The command of the
                    right wing he gave to Lucius Volumnius, that of the left to Lucius Scipio, that
                    of the cavalry to the other lieutenants-general, Caius Caedicius <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> and Caius Trebonius. He ordered Spurius Nautius to
                    take off the panniers from the mules, and to lead them round quickly, together
                    with his auxiliary cohorts, to a rising ground in view; and there to show
                    himself during the heat of the engagement, and to raise as much dust as
                    possible. While <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> the <pb n="684"
                        xml:id="p.684"/> general was employed in making these dispositions, a
                    dispute arose among the keepers of the chickens, about the auspices of the day,
                    which was overheard by some Roman horsemen, who, deeming it a matter not to be
                    slighted, informed Spurius <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Papirius, the
                    consul's nephew, that there was a doubt about the auspices. The youth, born in
                    an age when that sort of learning which inculcates contempt of the gods was yet
                    unknown, examined into the affair, that he might not carry an uncertain
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> report to the consul; and then acquainted
                    him with it. His answer was, <quote> I very much applaud your conduct and zeal.
                        However, the person who officiates in taking the auspices, if he makes a
                        false report, draws on his own head the evil portended; but to the Roman
                        people and their army, the favourable omen reported to me is an excellent
                        auspice. </quote> He then commanded the centurions to place the keepers of
                    the chickens in the front of the line. The Samnites likewise brought forward
                    their standards; their main body followed, armed and decorated in such
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> a manner, that the enemy afforded a
                    magnificent show. Before the shout was raised, or the battle begun, the auspex,
                    wounded by a random cast of a javelin, fell before the standards; which
                        <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> being told to the consul, he said,
                        <quote>The gods are present in the battle; the guilty has met his
                        punishment.</quote> While the consul uttered these words, a crow, in front
                    of him, cawed with a clear voice; at which augury, the consul being rejoiced,
                    and affirming, that never had the gods interposed in a more striking manner in
                    human affairs, ordered the charge to be sounded and the shout to be raised. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> A furious conflict now ensued, but with very
                    unequal spirit [in the combatants]. Anger, hope, and ardour for conquest,
                    hurried on the Romans to battle, thirsting for their enemy's blood; while the
                    Samnites, for the most part reluctantly, as if compelled by necessity and
                    religious dread, rather stood on their defence, than made an attack. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Nor would they, familiarized as they were to defeats,
                    through a course of so many years, have withstood the first shout and shock of
                    the Romans, had not another fear, operating still more powerfully in their
                    breasts, restrained them from flying. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For they
                    had before their eyes the whole scene exhibited at the secret sacrifice, the
                    armed priests, the promiscuous carnage of men and cattle, the altars besmeared
                    with the blood of victims and of their murdered countrymen, the dreadful curses,
                    and the dire- <pb n="685" xml:id="p.685"/> ful form of imprecation, drawn up for
                    calling down perdition on their family and race. Prevented by these shackles
                    from running away, they stood, more afraid of their countrymen than of the
                    enemy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Romans pushed on both the wings,
                    and in the centre, and made great havoc among them, stupified as they were,
                    through their fears of the gods and of men. A faint resistance is now made, as
                    by men whom fear alone prevented from running away. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The slaughter had now almost reached to their standards,
                    when, on one side, appeared a cloud of dust, as if raised by the marching of a
                    numerous army: it was Spurius Nautius, (some say Octavius Metius,) commander of
                    the auxiliary cohorts: for these raised a greater quantity of dust than was
                    proportioned to the number of men, the servants of the camp, mounted on the
                    mules, trailing boughs of trees, full of leaves, along the ground. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Through the light thus obscured, arms and standards
                    were seen in front; behind, a higher and denser cloud of dust presented the
                    appearance of horsemen bringing up the rear. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    This effectually deceived, not only the Samnites, but the Romans themselves: and
                    the consul confirmed the mistake, by calling out among the foremost battalions,
                    so that his voice reached also the enemy, that <quote>Cominium was taken; and
                        that his victorious colleague was approaching;</quote> bidding his men
                        <quote> now make haste to complete the defeat of the enemy, before the glory
                        should fall to the share of the other army. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This he said as he sat on horseback, and then
                    ordered the tribunes and centurions to open passages for the horse. He had given
                    previous directions to Trebonius and Caedicius, that, when they should see him
                    waving the point of his spear aloft, they should incite the cavalry to charge
                    the enemy with all possible violence. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Every
                    particular, as previously concerted, was executed with the utmost exactness. The
                    passages were opened between the ranks, the cavalry darted through, and, with
                    the points of their spears presented, rushed into the midst of the enemy's
                    battalions, breaking down the ranks wherever they charged. Volumnius and Scipio
                    seconded the blow, and taking advantage of the enemy's disorder, made a terrible
                    slaughter. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Thus attacked, the cohorts, called
                        <hi rend="italics">linteat,</hi> regardless of all restraints from either
                    gods or men, quitted their posts in confusion; the sworn and the unsworn all
                    fled alike, no longer dreading aught but the enemies. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> The body of their infantry which <pb n="686" xml:id="p.686"
                    /> survived the battle, were driven into the camp at Aquilonia. The nobility and
                    cavalry directed their flight to Bovianum. The horse were pursued by the Roman
                    horse, the infantry by their infantry, while the wings proceeded by different
                    roads; the right, to the camp of the Samnites; the left, to the city. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> Volumnius succeeded first in gaining possession of
                    the camp. At the city, Scipio met a stouter resistance; not because the
                    conquered troops there had gained courage, but because walls were a better
                    defence against armed men than a rampart. From these they repelled the enemy
                    with stones. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> Scipio, considering that unless
                    the business were effected during their first panic, and before they could
                    recover their spirits, the attack of so strong a town would be very tedious,
                    asked his soldiers <quote> if they could endure, without shame, that the other
                        wing should already have taken the camp, and that they, after all their
                        success, should be repulsed from the gates of the city? </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Then, all of them loudly declaring their
                    determination to the contrary, he himself advanced, the foremost, to the gate,
                    with his shield raised over his head: the rest, following under the like cover
                    of their shields conjoined, burst into the city, and dispersing the Samnites who
                    were near the gate, took possession of the walls, but they ventured not to push
                    forward into the interior of the city in consequence of the smallness of their
                    number. </p>
                <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Of these transactions the consul was for some
                    time ignorant; and was busily employed in calling home his troops, for the sun
                    was now hastening to set, and the approach of night rendered every place
                    suspicious and dangerous, even to victorious troops. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Having rode forward a considerable way, he saw on the right
                    the camp taken, and heard on the left a shouting in the city, with a confused
                    noise of fighting, and cries of terror. This happened while the fight was going
                    on at the gate. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When, on riding up nearer, he
                    saw his own men on the walls, and so much progress already made in the business,
                    pleased at having gained, through the precipitate conduct of a few, an
                    opportunity of striking an important blow, he ordered the troops, whom he had
                    sent back to the camp, to be called out, and to march to the attack of the city:
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> these, having made good their entrance on
                    the nearest side, proceeded no farther, because night approached. Before
                    morning, however, the town was abandoned by the enemy. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> There <pb n="687" xml:id="p.687"/> were slain of the
                    Samnites on that day, at Aquilonia, thirty thousand three hundred and forty;
                    taken, three thousand eight hundred and seventy, with ninety-seven military
                    standards. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> One circumstance, respecting
                    Papirius, is particularly mentioned by historians: that, hardly ever was any
                    general seen in the field with a more cheerful countenance; whether this was
                    owing to his natural temper or to his confidence of success. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> From the same firmness of mind it proceeded, that he did
                    not suffer himself to be diverted from the war by the dispute about the
                    auspices; and that, in the heat of the battle, when it was customary to vow
                    temples to the immortal gods, he vowed to Jupiter the victorious, that if he
                    should defeat the legions of the enemy, he would, before he tasted of any
                    generous liquor, make a libation to him of a cup of wine and honey. This kind of
                    vow proved acceptable to the gods, and they conducted the auspices to a
                    fortunate issue. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Matters were conducted with the same success
                    by the other consul at Cominium: leading up his forces to the walls, at the
                    first dawn, he invested the city on every side, and posted strong guards
                    opposite to the gates to prevent any sally being made. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> Just as he was giving the signal, the alarming message from
                    his colleague, touching the march of the twenty Samnite cohorts, not only caused
                    him to delay the assault, but obliged him to call off a part of his troops, when
                    they were formed and ready to begin the attack. <milestone n="3" unit="section"
                    /> He ordered Decius Brutus Scaeva, a lieutenant-general, with the first legion,
                    ten auxiliary cohorts, and the cavalry, to go and oppose the said detachment;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and in whatever place he should meet the
                    foe, there to stop and detain them, and even to engage in battle, should
                    opportunity offer for it; at all events not to suffer those troops to approach
                    Cominium. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> He then commanded the scaling
                    ladders to be brought up to the walls, on every side of the city; and, under a
                    fence of closed shields, advanced to the gates. Thus, at the same moment, the
                    gates were broken open, and the assault made on every part of the walls.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Though the Samnites, before they saw the
                    assailants on the works, had possessed courage enough to oppose their approaches
                    to the city, yet now, when the action was no longer carried on at a distance,
                    nor with missile weapons, but in close fight; and when those, who had with
                    difficulty gained the walls, having overcome the disadvantage of ground, which
                        <pb n="688" xml:id="p.688"/> they principally dreaded, fought with ease on
                    equal ground, against an enemy inferior in strength, they all forsook the towers
                    and <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> walls, and being driven to the forum,
                    they tried there for a short time, as a last effort, to retrieve the fortune of
                    the fight; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> but soon throwing down their arms,
                    surrendered to the consul, to the number of eleven thousand four hundred; four
                    thousand three hundred and eighty were slain. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>
                    Such was the course of events at Cominium, such at Aquilonia. In the middle
                    space between the two cities, where a third battle had been expected, the enemy
                    were not found; for, when they were within seven miles of Cominium, they were
                    recalled by their countrymen, and had no part in either battle. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> At night-fall, when they were now within sight of
                    their camp, and also of Aquilonia, shouts from both places reaching them with
                    equal force induced them to halt; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> then, on
                    the side of the camp, which had been set on fire by the Romans, the
                    wide-spreading flames indicating with more certainty the disaster [which had
                    happened], prevented their proceeding any farther. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> In that same spot, stretched on the ground at random under
                    their arms, they passed the whole night in great inquietude, at one time wishing
                    for, at another dreading the light. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> At the
                    first dawn, while they were still undetermined to what quarter they should
                    direct their march, they were obliged to betake themselves hastily to flight,
                    being descried by the cavalry; who having gone in pursuit of the Samnites, that
                    left the town in the night, saw the multitude unprotected either by a rampart or
                    advanced guard. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> This party had likewise been
                    perceived from the walls of Aquilonia, and the legionary cohorts now joined in
                    the pursuit. The foot were unable to overtake them, but about two hundred and
                    eighty of their rear guard were cut off by the cavalry. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> In their consternation they left behind them a great
                    quantity of arms and eighteen military standards: they reached Bovianum with the
                    rest of their party in safety, as far as could be expected after so disorderly a
                    rout. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The joy of both Roman armies was enhanced by
                    the success achieved on the other side. Each consul, with the approbation of his
                    colleague, gave to his soldiers the plunder of the town which he had taken; and,
                    when the houses were cleared, set them on fire. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
                    /> Thus, on the same day, Aquilonia and Cominium were both reduced to ashes. The
                    consuls then <pb n="689" xml:id="p.689"/> united their camps, where mutual
                    congratulations took place between them and between their soldiers. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> Here, in the view of the two armies, Carvilius
                    bestowed on his men commendations and presents according to the desert of each;
                    and Papirius likewise, whose troops had been engaged in a variety of actions, in
                    the field, in the assault of the camp, and in that of the city, presented
                    Spurius Nautius, Spurius Papirius, his nephew, four centurions, and a company of
                    the spearmen, with bracelets and crowns of gold: to <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Nautius, on account of his behaviour at the head of his
                    detachment, when he had terrified the enemy with the appearance as of a numerous
                    army; to young Papirius, on account of his zealous exertions with the cavalry,
                    both in the battle and in harassing the Samnites in their flight by night, when
                    they withdrew privately from Aquilonia; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and to
                    the centurions and company of soldiers, because they were the first who gained
                    possession of the gate and wall of that town. All the horsemen he presented with
                    gorgets and bracelets of silver, on account of their distinguished conduct on
                    many occasions. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> As the time was now come for
                    withdrawing the army out of Samnium, the expediency was considered, as to
                    whether they should withdraw both, or at least one. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> It was concluded, that the lower the strength of the
                    Samnites was reduced, the greater perseverance and vigour ought to be used in
                    prosecuting the war, so that Samnium might be given up to the succeeding consuls
                    perfectly subjected. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> As there was now no army
                    of the enemy which could be supposed capable of disputing the field, there
                    remained one mode of operations, the besieging of the cities; by the destruction
                    of which, they might be enabled to enrich their soldiers with the spoil; and, at
                    the same time, utterly to destroy the enemy, reduced to the necessity of
                    fighting, their all being at stake. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The
                    consuls, therefore, after despatching letters to the senate and people of Rome,
                    containing accounts of the services which they had performed, led away their
                    legions to different quarters; Papirius going to attack Saepinum, Carvilius to
                    Volana. </p>
                <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The letters of the consuls were heard with
                    extraordinary exultation, both in the senate-house and in the assembly of the
                    people; and, in a thanksgiving of four days' continuance, the public rejoicings
                    were celebrated with zeal by individuals. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    These successes were not only important in <pb n="690" xml:id="p.690"/>
                    themselves to the Roman people, but peculiarly seasonable; for it happened, that
                    at the same time intelligence was brought that the Etrurians were again in arms.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The reflection naturally occurred to
                    people's minds, how it would have been possible, in case any misfortune had
                    happened in Samnium, to have withstood the power of Etruria; which, being
                    encouraged by the conspiracy of the Samnites, and seeing both the consuls, and
                    the whole force of the Romans, employed against them, had made use of that
                    juncture, in which the Romans had so much business on their hands, for reviving
                    hostilities. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Ambassadors from the allies,
                    being introduced to the senate by the praetor Marcus Atilius, complained that
                    their countries were wasted with fire and sword by the neighbouring Etrurians,
                    because they had refused to revolt from the Romans; and they besought the
                    conscript fathers to protect them from the violence and injustice of their
                    common enemy. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The ambassadors were answered,
                    that <quote>the senate would take care that the allies should not repent their
                        fidelity.</quote> That the <quote>Etrurians should shortly be in the same
                        situation with the Samnites.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Notwithstanding which, the business respecting
                    Etruria would have been prosecuted with less vigour, had not information been
                    received, that the Faliscians likewise, who had for many years lived in
                    friendship with Rome, had united their arms with those of the Etrurians.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The consideration of the near vicinity of
                    that nation quickened the attention of the senate; insomuch that they passed a
                    decree that heralds should be sent to demand satisfaction: which being refused,
                    war was declared against the Faliscians by direction of the senate, and order of
                    the people; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and the consuls were desired to
                    determine, by lots, which of them should lead an army from Samnium into Etruria.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Carvilius had, in the mean time, taken
                    from the Samnites Volana, Palumbinum, and Herculaneum; Volana after a siege of a
                    few days, Palumbinum the same day on which he approached the walls. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> At Herculaneum, it is true, the consul had two
                    regular engagements without any decisive advantage on either side, and with
                    greater loss on his side than on that of the enemy; but afterwards, encamping on
                    the spot, he shut them up within their works. The town was besieged and taken.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> In these three towns were taken or slain
                    ten thousand men, of whom the prisoners composed somewhat the <pb n="691"
                        xml:id="p.691"/> greater part. On the consuls casting lots for the
                    provinces, Etruria fell to Carvilius, to the great satisfaction of the soldiers,
                    who could no longer bear the intensity of the cold in Samnium. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Papirius was opposed at Saepinum with a more powerful
                    force: he had to fight often in pitched battles, often on a march, and often
                    under the walls of the city, against the eruptions of the enemy; and could
                    neither besiege, nor engage them on equal terms; for the Samnites not only
                    protected themselves by walls, but likewise protected their walls with numbers
                    of men and arms. At length, after a great deal of fighting, he forced them to
                    submit to a regular siege. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> This he carried on
                    with vigour, and made himself master of the city by means of his works, and by
                    storm. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> The rage of the soldiers on this
                    occasion caused the greatest slaughter in the taking of the town; seven thousand
                    four hundred fell by the sword; the number of the prisoners did not amount to
                    three thousand. The spoil, of which the quantity was very great, the whole
                    substance of the Samnites being collected in a few cities, was given up to the
                    soldiers. </p>
                <milestone n="46" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The snow had now entirely covered the face of
                    the country, and they could no longer dispense with the shelter of houses: the
                    consul therefore led home his troops from Samnium. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> While he was on his way to Rome, a triumph was decreed him
                    with universal consent; and accordingly he triumphed while in office, and with
                    extraordinary splendour, considering the circumstances of those times.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The cavalry and infantry marched in the
                    procession, adorned with presents. Great numbers of civic, vallar, and mural
                    crowns were seen. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> These <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> marks of honour were bestowed for having saved
                        the lives of citizens, or for having been the first to mount walls or
                        ramparts. </note> The spoils of the Samnites were inspected with much
                    curiosity, and compared, in respect of <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    magnificence and beauty, with those taken by his father, which were well known,
                    from being frequently exhibited as ornaments of the public places. Several
                    prisoners of distinction, renowned for their own exploits and those of their
                    ancestors, were led in the cavalcade. There were carried in the train two
                    millions and thirty-three thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi> in weight.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 4940 13 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> This money was said to be produced by the sale of the prisoners. Of
                    silver, taken in the cities, one thousand three hundred and thirty <pb n="692"
                        xml:id="p.692"/> pounds. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All the silver
                    and brass were lodged in the treasury, no share of this part of the spoil being
                    given to the soldiers. The ill humour in the commons was further exasperated,
                    because the tax for the payment of the army was collected by contribution;
                    whereas, said they, if the vain parade of conveying the produce of the spoil to
                    the treasury had been disregarded, donations <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    might have been made to the soldiers out of the spoil, and the pay of the army
                    also supplied out of that fund. The temple of Quirinus, vowed by his father when
                    dictator, (for that he himself had vowed it in the heat of battle, I do not find
                    in any ancient writer, nor indeed could he in <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    so short a time have finished the building of it,) the son, in the office of
                    consul, dedicated and adorned with military spoils. And of <milestone n="9??"
                        unit="section"/> these, so great was the abundance, that not only that
                    temple and the forum were decorated with them, <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> but some were also distributed among the allies and colonies in the
                    neighbourhood, to serve as ornaments to their temples and public places.
                    Immediately after his triumph, he led his army into winter quarters in the
                    territory of Vescia; because that country was harassed by the Samnites.
                    Meanwhile, <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> in Etruria, the consul Carvilius
                    having set about laying siege to Troilium, suffered four hundred and seventy of
                    the richest inhabitants to depart; they <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> had
                    paid a large sum of money for permission to leave the place: the town, with the
                    remaining multitude, he took by storm. He afterwards reduced, by force, five
                    forts strongly situated, wherein were slain two thousand four hundred of the
                    enemy, and not quite two thousand made prisoners. To the Faliscians, who sued
                    for peace, he granted <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> a truce for a year, on
                    condition of their furnishing a hundred thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    in weight, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 322 18 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and that year's <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> pay for his army.
                    This business completed, he returned home to a triumph, which, though it was
                    less illustrious than that of his colleague, in respect of his share in the
                    defeat of the Samnites, was yet raised to an equality with it, by <milestone
                        n="15" unit="section"/> his having put a termination to the war in Etruria.
                    He carried into the treasury three hundred and ninety thousand <hi
                        rend="italics">asses</hi> in weight. <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 1259 7 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italics"
                            >d.</hi>
                    </note> Out of the remainder of the money accruing to the public from the
                    spoils, <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> he contracted for the building of a
                    temple to Fors Fortuna, near to that dedicated to the same goddess by king
                    Servius Tullius; and gave to the soldiers, out of the spoil, one hun- <pb
                        n="693" xml:id="p.693"/> dred and two <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 6 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 7 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> each, and double that sum to the centu- rions and horsemen, who received
                    this donative the more gratefully, on account of the parsimony of his colleague. </p>
                <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The favour of the consul saved from a trial,
                    before the people, Postumius; who, on a prosecution being commenced against him
                    by Marcus Scantius, plebeian tribune, evaded, as was said, the jurisdiction of
                    the people, by procuring the commission of lieutenant-general, so the indictment
                    against him could only be held out as a threat, and not put in force. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> The year having now elapsed, new plebeian tribunes
                    had come into office; and for these, in consequence of some irregularity in
                    their appointments, others had been, within five days after, substituted in
                    their room. The lustrum was closed this year by the censors Publius Cornelius
                    Arvina and Caius Marcius Rutilus. The number of citizens rated was two hundred
                    and sixty-two thousand three hundred and twenty-two. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> These were the twenty-sixth pair of censors since the first
                    institution of that office; and this the nineteenth lustrum. In this year,
                    persons who had been presented with crowns, in consideration of meritorious
                    behaviour in war, first began to wear them at the exhibition of the Roman games.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Then, for the first time, palms were
                    conferred on the victors according to a custom introduced from Greece. In the
                    same year the paving of the road from the temple of Mars to Bovillae was
                    completed by the curule aediles, who exhibited those games out of fines levied
                    on the farmers of the pastures. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Lucius
                    Papirius presided at the consular election, and returned consuls Quintus Fabius
                    Gurges, son of Maximus, and Decius Junius Brutus Scaeva. Papirius himself was
                    made praetor. This year, prosperous in many particulars, was scarcely sufficient
                    to afford consolation for one calamity, a pestilence, which afflicted both the
                    city and country: the mortality was prodigious. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> To discover what end, or what remedy, was appointed by the gods for that
                    calamity, the books were consulted: in the books it was found that Aesculapius
                    must be brought to Rome from Epidaurus. Nor were any steps taken that year in
                    that matter, because the consuls were fully occupied in the war, except that a
                    supplication was performed to Aesculapius for one day. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
