<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng" type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Address to the Priests </title>
                <title>for his house, Plancius, Sextius, Coelius, Milo, Ligarius, etc.</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
                        <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D.
                            Yonge, B. A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>George Bell &amp; Sons, York Street, Covent
                                Garden</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
                <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="la">Latin</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
			<change>
				<date>7/14/97</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>DAS</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item> 
$Log: cic.yonge3_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.7  2013-09-13 11:20:04  balmas01
reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version

Revision 1.5  2011-03-17 16:00:49  lcerrato
fixing gap tags against source

Revision 1.4  2010/08/31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword

Revision 1.3  2010/08/31 18:30:20  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/10/09 19:49:14 rsingh04 
more reorganizing of texts module by collection 

Revision 1.6 2009/06/25 15:53:30 student 
fixed bibl error - zr 

Revision 1.5 2008/12/11 19:08:11 lcerrato 
fixed typo ought not to he to ought not to be 

Revision 1.4 2006/05/05 17:38:08 packel
                    fixed date tags 

Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 20:50:19 packel 
places/dates now actually tagged 

Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 15:59:25 packel 
removed stray item tags
                    
Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:31:48 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.11 2005/03/08 17:57:33 lcerrato 
changed Marcus Carius in Pro Plancio 60 to Manius Curius based on Latin, report and other sources 

Revision 1.10 2005/03/08 17:51:43 lcerrato 
Changed Sulla in Resp. Answers of Soothsayers 59 to Scylla
                    based on Latin and user report 

Revision 1.9 2003/10/10 20:51:02 lcerrato 
added semicolon in run on sentence 

Revision 1.8 2003/07/01 22:15:02 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.7 2000/10/17 18:37:22 lcerrato 
changed typo in the bearing of the senate to in the hearing of the senate at Pro Caelio 60
                    
Revision 1.6 2000/09/05 18:16:21 lcerrato 
made many Revisions to tags, spacing, general proofreading, spellchecking 

Revision 1.5 2000/03/04 20:34:17 dasmith
                    Added separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.4 1999/10/14 21:36:04 dasmith 
Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt 

Revision 1.3 1999/08/12 17:17:40 dasmith 
Fixed refsDecl 

Revision 1.2 1999/08/04 18:12:22 textgod 
Random changes over a period of months. 

Revision 1.1 1997/08/18 14:51:50 textgod 
Added to repository. 
                </item>
			</change>
		<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO FOR HIS HOUSE. ADDRESSED TO THE PRIESTS</head>
            <argument>
                <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
                <p>Cicero soon after his consulship, had purchased the house of Marcus Crassus on
                    the <placeName key="tgn,2565724">Palatine Hill</placeName>, which adjoined that
                    in which he had always lived with his father; it was one of the finest houses in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, and cost him nearly thirty
                    thousand pounds, and was joined to the colonnade or portico called by the name
                    of Catulus, who had built it out of the Cimbric spoils on that area where
                    Flaccus formerly lived, whose house had been demolished by public authority for
                    his seditious union with Caius Gracchus. </p>
                <p>As soon as Clodius had carried his decree against Cicero after his flight, he
                    immediately began plundering and destroying all his houses; the consuls,
                            <persName><surname>Piso</surname></persName> and Gabinius, divided the
                    greater part of his furniture and of the ornaments of his house and villa
                    between them; and, in the hope of making the loss of his house at <placeName
                        key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName> irretrievable, Clodius consecrated the
                    area on which it stood to the service of religion, building on it a temple to
                    Liberty, and he pulled down the adjoining portico of Catulus in order to rebuild
                    it of the same order as the temple. The law being that a consecration, legally
                    performed, made the thing consecrated inapplicable ever after to any private
                    use. </p>
                <p>The affair was to be determined by the college of priests, who were the judges in
                    all cases relating to religion; since the senate could only make a provisional
                    decree, that, if the priests discharged the ground from the service of religion,
                    then in that case the consuls should rebuild the house at the public charge. The
                    cause now came before the priests on the last day of September. Cicero
                    endeavoured, in the first place, to disabuse their minds of any enmity to him
                    which might have been instilled into their minds by Clodius on account of his
                    late conduct with respect to Pompey. (For there had been a great scarcity at
                        <placeName key="tgn,7013962">Rome</placeName>, partly occasioned by the
                    great multitudes that had come from all parts of <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                        >Italy</placeName> on Cicero's account; and Cicero had supported a
                    resolution of the senate by which Pompey was entreated to undertake the province
                    of restoring plenty to the city, and to this end the consuls had been ordered to
                    draw up a law by which the whole administration of the corn and provisions of
                    the republic was granted to Pompey for five years. And in consequence of
                    Cicero's advocacy of the measure Clodius endeavoured to excite odium against
                    him, as having deserted the cause of the senate to pay court to Pompey; though
                    the measure had been very successful, as the credit of Pompey's name immediately
                    reduced the price of provisions in the markets.) </p>
                <p>As, however, the main question turned upon the legality of the consecration,
                    Cicero applies to establish the fact of its illegality by proving that Clodius
                    could not legally consecrate anything, as his election to the tribunate was
                    illegal; since his adoption into a plebeian family, or at least into that
                    particular family into which he had been adopted, was in violation and defiance
                    of all the laws made for such cases; if his adoption was illegal, clearly he
                    could not have legally been elected tribune, nor have legally done any action as
                    tribune. </p>
                <p>The priests decided that if he who performed the office of consecration had not
                    been legally authorized to do so, then the area in question might without any
                    scruple of religion be restored to Cicero. The point of law they left to the
                    senate, who, after many interruptions from Clodius and Serranus, passed a decree
                    that Cicero's damage should be made good to him, and his houses rebuilt at the
                    public charge. </p>
                <p>Cicero himself thought very highly of this speech, and published it immediately;
                    and says, in one of his <bibl n="Cic. Att. 4.2">letters to Atticus, (iv.
                        2)</bibl> that “if ever he was great in speaking, he was so especially now,
                    as his indignation and the greatness of the injury done to him gave him especial
                    energy and force of oratory.” Some critics, but apparently without any good
                    reason, have doubted the genuineness of this oration.</p>
            </argument>
        </front>
        <body>
            <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
            <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
            <p>Many things, O priests, have been devised and established with divine wisdom by our
                ancestors; but no action of theirs was ever more wise than their determination that
                the same men should superintend both what relates to the religious worship due to
                the immortal gods, and also what concerns the highest interests of the state, so
                that they might preserve the republic as the most honourable and eminent of the
                citizens, by governing it well, and as priests by wisely interpreting the
                requirements of religion. But if there has ever been a time when an important cause
                has depended on the decision and power of the priests of the Roman people, this
                indeed is that cause; being such that the dignity of the whole republic, the safety
                of all the citizens, their lives, their liberties, their altars, their hearths,
                their household gods, their properties and condition as citizens, and their homes,
                all appear to be committed and entrusted to your wisdom integrity, and power.
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> You have got to decide this day whether you
                prefer for the future to deprive frantic and profligate magistrates of the
                protection of wicked and unprincipled citizens, or even to arm them with the cloak
                of religion and of the respect due to the immortal gods. For if that pest and
                conflagration of the republic succeeds in defending his own mischievous and fatal
                tribunate by appeals to divine religion, when he cannot maintain it by any
                considerations of human equity, then we must seek for other ceremonies, for other
                ministers of the immortal gods, for other interpreters of the requirements of
                religion. But if those things which were done by the madness of wicked men in the
                republic at a time when it was oppressed by one party, deserted by another, and
                betrayed by a third, are annulled by your authority and your wisdom, O priests, then
                we shall have cause rightly and deservedly to praise the wisdom of our ancestors in
                selecting the most honourable men of the state for the priesthood. </p>
            <p><milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But since that madman has thought that he should
                find a ready road to your attention by blaming the sentiments that I in the last few
                days have expressed in the senate concerning the republic, I will deviate from the
                natural arrangement of my speech, and I will make a reply to what I will not call
                the speech of that furious fellow, (for that is more than he is capable of,) but to
                his abuse, that being an employment which he has fortified himself in the practice
                of by his own intolerable bad temper, and by the length of time that he has been
                allowed to indulge it with impunity. <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And in the first place, I ask you this, O you insane and frantic man, what excessive
                punishment for your wickednesses and crimes is it that distracts you so as to make
                you think that these men—men of their high character, who support the dignity of the
                republic, not only by their wisdom, but also by their dignified appearance—are angry
                with me, because in delivering my opinion I connected the safety of the citizens
                with the honour of Cnaeus Pompeius, and that they are likely at this present time to
                have different feelings with respect to the general interests of religion from those
                which they entertained when I was absent? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>“Oh,”
                says he, “you had the advantage before the priests, but now you must inevitably get
                worst off since you have had recourse to the people.” Is it so? Will you transfer
                that which is the greatest defect in the ignorant multitude,—namely, its fickleness
                and inconstancy, and change of opinion, as frequent as the changes of the weather,
                to these men, whose gravity protects them from inconsistency, while their fixed and
                definite principles of religion and the antiquity of precedents, and the authority
                of written records and monuments, effectually deters them from all capricious change
                of sentiment? “Are you,” says he, “the man whom the senate was unable to do without?
                whom the good lamented? whom the republic regretted? by whose restoration we
                expected that the authority of the senate was restored? and who destroyed that
                authority the very first thing you did?” I am not at present speaking of my own
                matters; I will first of all reply to your impudence. <milestone n="3"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="5" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Did you then, O you deadly pest of the republic, by means of the sword and arms, by
                the terror of an armed force, by the wickedness of the consuls, and the threats of
                most audacious men,—by enlisting slaves, by besieging the temples, by occupying the
                forum, by oppressing the senate, contrive to compel the departure of that citizen
                from his home and from his country, in order to prevent actual battles between the
                virtuous and wicked citizens,—though you now confess that he was regretted and sent
                for back and recalled by the senate, by all good men, and by the whole of <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, as the only means of preserving the
                republic? “But on that day of disturbance you ought not,” says he, “to have come
                into the senate, you ought not to have entered the Capitol.” <milestone n="6"
                    unit="section"/>But I did not come, and I kept in my own house as long as that
                disturbance lasted; while it was notorious that your slaves had come with you armed
                into the Capitol, ready for plunder and for the massacre of all good men, with all
                that band of wicked and profligate partisans of yours. And when this was reported to
                me, I know that I remained at home, and would not give you and your gladiators power
                of renewing the massacre. After news was brought to me that the Roman people had
                assembled at the Capitol, because of their fear for, and difficulty of procuring
                corn, and that the ministers of your crimes had been frightened and had fled, some
                having dropped their swords, and some having had them taken from them, I came
                forward not only without any armed band, but with only a very few friends.
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Should I, when Publius Lentulus the consul,
                who had conferred the greatest benefits on me and on the republic,—when Quintus
                Metellus, your brother, O Metellus, who, though he had been my enemy, had still
                preferred my safety and dignity to any desire to keep alive our quarrel, and to your
                entreaties that he would do so, sent for me to the senate,—when that great multitude
                of citizens, who had lately shown such zeal in my behalf, entreated me by name to
                show my gratitude to them,—should I, I say, have declined to come forward,
                especially when it was notorious that you with your band of runaway slaves had
                already left the place? Have you dared to call me—me, the guardian and defender of
                the Capitol and of every temple—the enemy of the Capitol, because, when the two
                consuls were holding the senate in the Capitol, I came thither? Is there any time at
                which it can be discreditable to have attended the senate? or was that business
                which was then being transacted of such a nature that I was bound to repudiate the
                affair itself, and to condemn those who were promoting it? <milestone n="4"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="8" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>First, I say that it is the duty of a virtuous senator at all times to attend the
                senate; and I do not agree with those who determine that they themselves will not
                come to the senate at unfavourable seasons, and who do not understand that this
                excessive obstinacy of theirs is exceedingly pleasant and acceptable to those men
                whose wishes they intend to counteract. “But some departed out of fear, because they
                thought that they could not remain with safety in the senate.” I do not name them,
                nor do I ask whether they had any real reason for fearing anything. I imagine that
                every one had a right to form his own opinion as to what grounds he had for fear. Do
                you ask why I was not afraid? Why, because it was known that you had gone away. Do
                you ask why, when some good men thought that they could not remain with safety in
                the senate, I did not think so too? or why, when I thought that it was impossible
                for me to remain in the city at all with safety, they did not think so too? Are then
                others to be allowed, and rightly enough, to have no fear for themselves at a time
                when I am in danger; and yet am I bound to be afraid not only when I am myself in
                peril, but when others are also? </p>
            <p><milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Or am I to be blamed because I did not express an
                opinion condemnatory of both the consuls? Ought I then to condemn those men, of all
                men in the world, by whose law it was brought about that I, who had never been
                condemned and who had deserved well of the republic, should be saved from enduring
                the punishment of condemned criminals? Was I, of all men in the world, I who had
                been restored to my former dignity by their means, to denounce by my expressed
                opinion the admirable sentiments of those men, who, even if they had been in error,
                ought to have been borne with by me and by all good men, on account of their
                exceeding good-will displayed in ensuring my preservation? And what were the
                opinions which I delivered? In the first place, that one which the common
                conversation of the people had already previously fixed in our minds; in the second
                place, that one which had been discussed in the senate on the preceding days; and
                thirdly, that which the senate in a very full house adopted, expressing its
                agreement with me; so that so sudden or novel proposition was brought forward by me,
                and moreover, if there be any fault in the opinion, it is sot more the fault of the
                individual who advanced it than of all those men who approved of it. <milestone
                    n="10" unit="section"/>“But the decision of the senate was not free, because of
                the fear in which they were.” If you make out that they who left it were in fear, at
                least grant that they who remained were not alarmed. But if no free decision could
                be come to without the presence of those men who were absent at that time, I say
                that the motion about framing a resolution of the senate began to be made when every
                one was present; it was carried by acclamation by the entire senate. <milestone
                    n="5" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But I ask, since I am the prime mover in and the chief cause of this vote, what fault
                is found with the vote itself? Was there not good reason for adopting an
                unprecedented plan? Was not I as much concerned as any one in that matter? or, had
                we any other resource? What circumstances, what reasons could there be of greater
                consequence than famine? than sedition? than the designs of you and your partisans?
                who thought that, if an opportunity was given them of inflaming the minds of the
                ignorant, you, under the pretence afforded by the scarcity of provisions, would be
                able to renew your wicked and fatal practices. </p>
            <p><milestone n="11" unit="section"/> As for corn, some of the countries which usually
                supply it had not got it; some had sent it into other countries, I imagine because
                of the great variety of sellers; and some were keeping it back, shut up in their
                stores, in order suddenly to send it, so that the supply might be more acceptable if
                they seemed to come to our aid when we were in a state of actual famine. The matter
                was not one of uncertain opinions, it was a case of actually existing danger,
                present to our eyes; it was not one which we were looking forward to in conjecture,
                but one which we were actually beholding by present experience. For when the
                scarcity was getting more severe, so that it was actually want and famine that was
                dreaded, and not mere dearness of price, there was a rush towards the Temple of
                Concord, when the consul Metellus summoned the senate to meet in that place. And if
                that was the genuine effect of the grief of men suffering under famine, certainly
                the consuls had good reason to undertake the affair, certainly the senate had good
                reason to adopt some determination or other. </p>
            <p>But if the scarcity was the pretext, and if you in reality were the exciter and
                kindler of sedition, ought we not all to have striven to take away all shadow of
                pretext for your madness?<milestone n="12" unit="section"/> What, if both these
                causes existed,—if there was both famine to excite men, and you too like a nail
                working into this ulcer? was there not all the more need to apply some remedy, which
                might put an end to both the evil caused by nature, and to the other mischief
                imported into the case? There was then both present dearness and impending famine;
                that is not enough; men were attacked with stones. If that arose from the
                indignation of the common people, without any one having stirred them up, it is a
                great misfortune; but if, it was caused by the instigation of Publius Clodius, it is
                only the habitual wickedness of a wicked man: if both these causes existed,—if there
                was both a fact sufficient of itself to excite the feelings of the multitude, and if
                there were leaders of sedition ready and forearmed; then, does it not seem natural
                for the republic to have had recourse to the protection of the consul and the
                loyalty of the senate? But it is quite plain that one of these causes did exist;
                that there was a difficulty of obtaining provisions, and an extreme scarcity of
                corn, so that men were afraid not only of a continuance of high prices, but of
                actual famine. No one denies it. But I do not wish you, O priests, to suspect that
                that enemy of all tranquillity and peace was likely to seize on this as a pretext
                for conflagration, and massacre, and rapine, unless you see it proved. <milestone
                    n="13" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Who are the men who were openly named in the senate by Quintus Metellus,—your
                brother, O Metellus,—the consul, by whom he said that he had been attacked with
                stones and actually hit? He named Lucius Sergius and Marcus Lollius. Who is that
                Lollius? A man who is not even at this moment by your side without his sword; who,
                while you were tribune of the people, demanded (I will say nothing of his designs
                against myself) to have the murder of Cnaeus Pompeius entrusted to him. Who is
                Sergius? The armour-bearer of Catiline, your own body-guard, the standard-bearer of
                sedition, the exciter of the shopkeepers, a man who has been convicted of assault,
                an assassin, a stoner of men, a man who has depopulated the forum, and blockaded the
                senate-house. With these leaders and others like them, when you, at the time when
                provisions were dear, under pretence of espousing the cause of the poor and
                ignorant, were preparing for sudden attacks on the consuls, on the senate, on the
                property and fortunes of the, rich; when it was impossible for you to find safety if
                affairs remained in a tranquil state; when, the leaders being all desperate men, you
                had your bands of profligates regularly enrolled and distributed into decuries,—did
                it not behoove the senate to take good care that that fatal firebrand did not fall
                upon these vast materials for sedition? <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="14" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>There was, therefore, good cause for adopting an unusual determination. See now
                whether or not I was the person who had the principal share in it. Who was it whom
                that friend of yours, Sergius, whom Lollius, whom the other rascals named when they
                were throwing the stones? who was it that they said ought to provide them with corn?
                was it not I? What was it that that nocturnal mob of boys which had been trained by
                you kept demanding? They were demanding corn of me; as if I superintended the
                corn-market; or as if I were keeping back any corn in store; or as if, in fact, I
                had any management of, or influence whatever in, any affairs of that class at all.
                But the fellow who was thirsting for slaughter had published my name to the
                artisans, and to the ignorant mob. When the senate, in a very full house assembled
                in the temple of the all-good and all-powerful Jupiter, had passed a decree touching
                my dignity with only one dissenting voice, on a sudden, on that very day, a most
                unexpected cheapness followed a time when corn had been excessively dear. <milestone
                    n="15" unit="section"/> Some said, (and I myself am of that opinion,) that the
                immortal gods had shown their approbation of my return by this exercise of their
                power. But some traced that fact back, connecting it with this argument and
                opinion,—that, as all hopes of tranquillity and concord appeared to depend on my
                return, and as there was an incessant dread of sedition connected with my absence,
                so now that all fear of contest was almost at an end, they thought that the state of
                the corn-market was altered; and, because it again had become more unmanageable
                after my return, then corn was demanded of me, on whose arrival virtuous men were in
                the habit of saying that there would be cheapness. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>Lastly, my name was pronounced not only by your band of partisans at your
                instigation, but even after your forces had been routed and scattered, I was
                summoned by name to the senate by the whole Roman people, who at that time were
                assembled around the Capitol, though on that day I was far from well. <milestone
                    n="16" unit="section"/> Being expected, I came. After many opinions had been
                already pronounced, I was asked mine. I delivered one very advantageous to the
                republic, and at the same time necessary for my own interests. Abundance of corn and
                cheapness of price was demanded of me; as if I had any influence in producing such a
                state of things as that. Things were in a very different condition. I was pressed by
                eager expostulation from many good men. I was unable to support the abuse of the
                wicked. I proposed to entrust the business to an influential friend, not in order to
                impose a burden on one to whom I was under such heavy obligations, (for I would
                rather have sunk under it myself, than done that,) but because I saw, what every one
                else saw, that, whatever we promised in behalf of Cnaeus Pompeius, he would most
                easily accomplish by his integrity, wisdom, virtue, and authority, and by his
                invariable good-fortune. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Therefore, whether the
                immortal gods give this to the Roman people as the fruit of my return, that, as on
                my departure there ensued a want of corn, and famine, and devastation, and
                bloodshed, and conflagration, and pillage, and impunity for all crimes, and flight,
                and terror, and discord, so my return is followed by fertility of the lands, by
                abundant harvests, by hopes of tranquillity, by peaceful dispositions on the part of
                the citizens, by a restoration of the courts of justice and of the laws, while
                unanimity on the part of the people and the authority of the senate seem to have
                been brought back in my company; or, if the fact is that I, on my arrival, was
                bound, in return for <pb n="10"/> such kindness, to do something for the Roman
                people by my prudence, authority and diligence; then I do promise, and undertake,
                and pledge myself to do it. I say no more. This, I say, which is sufficient for the
                present occasion, that the republic shall not, on any pretence connected with the
                price of corn, fall into that danger into which some people endeavoured to bring it.
                    <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="18" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Are then my sentiments found fault with in this business which fell especially to my
                share? I rescued affairs of the greatest consequence from the mischief of the most
                imminent danger; and I saved not only it, but you also, from massacre, and
                conflagration, and devastation. No one denies this; as to the pretext of dearness
                there was added that spy of the general misery, who always lit the firebrand of his
                guilt in the misfortunes of the republic. </p>
            <p>He says that nothing ought to have been decreed irregularly to any one. I do not at
                present make the same reply to you that I make to the rest,—That many wars, and
                these wars of the greatest danger and of the greatest importance, both by land and
                sea, have been entrusted to Cnaeus Pompeius out of the regular order. And if any one
                repents of those measures, he must also repent of the victory of the Roman people.
                    <milestone n="19" unit="section"/> I do not deal with you in this manner. I can
                address this argument to those men, who state that if any matter must be entrusted
                to one individual, then they would rather entrust it to Cnaeus Pompeius than to any
                one, but that they make a rule of never entrusting anything to any one in an
                irregular manner; still, after it has been entrusted to Pompeius, that they then
                vindicate and uphold the measure, as is due to the dignity of the man. From praising
                the statements of these men I am hindered by the triumphs of Cnaeus Pompeius, by
                which he (though it was quite out of the regular order of things that he was
                summoned to defend his country) increased the reputation of the Roman people, and
                crowned their empire with honour. At the same time I praise their firmness, which is
                a virtue which I have need to avail myself of, since it was on my proposition that
                he was appointed, quite out of the regular routine, to conduct the war against
                Mithridates and Tigranes. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> But still there are
                some points which I can argue with them; but still, how great is your impudence,
                when you dare to say that nothing ought to be given to any one out of the regular
                routine! You who, when, by an iniquitous law, for some unknown cause you had
                confiscated the property of Ptolemy, King of <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
                    >Cyprus</placeName>, the brother of the King of Alexandria, who was reigning by
                the same right as he was, and had involved the Roman people in the crime,—when you
                had sent a band of robbers from this empire to ravage his kingdom, and goods, and
                property, though there had been a long alliance and friendship between us and his
                father, and grandfather, and still more remote ancestors,—appointed Marcus Cato to
                superintend the carrying away of his money, and the managing the war if any
                individual was found hardy enough to defend his own property. <milestone n="21"
                    unit="section"/> Will you say, “Yes, but what a man Cato was! A most religious,
                most prudent, most gallant man; the firmest friend to the republic, a citizen of a
                most marvellous and almost unique virtue, and wisdom, and purity of life.” Very
                fine, but what is all that to you, when you say that it is untrue that any one ought
                to be appointed to any public duty out of the regular course? <milestone n="9"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And in this matter I am only convicting you of inconsistency; who in the case of this
                very Cato, whom you did not so much promote out of regard for his dignity, as get
                out of the way lest he might hinder your wickedness,—whom you had exposed to your
                Sergii, and Lollii, and Titii, and your other leaders in massacre and conflagration,
                whom you yourself had called the executioner of the citizens, the chief murderer of
                men who had never been condemned, the very fountain of cruelty,—you still by your
                motion conferred this honour and command on him out of the regular course, and
                behaved with such violence, that you were wholly unable to disguise your object and,
                the system of wickedness which you had laid down for yourself. <milestone n="22"
                    unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>You read letters in the assembly which you said had been sent to you by Caius Caesar.
                “Caesar to Pulcher.” And when you proceeded to argue that this was a proof of
                intimacy, because he only used the names of himself and you, and did not add
                “proconsul,” or “tribune of the people,” and then began to congratulate you that you
                had got Marcus Cato out of the way of your tribuneship for the remainder of the
                time, and that you had also taken away for the future the power of giving
                extraordinary commissions;—letters which he never sent to you at all, or which, if
                he did send them, he certainly never meant to be read in the public assembly;—at all
                events, whether he sent them or whether you forged them, your intention with respect
                to the honours conferred upon Cato was revealed by the reading of those letters.
                    <milestone n="23" unit="section"/> But, however, I will say no more about Cato,
                whose eminent virtue, and dignity, and integrity, and moderation in that business
                which he executed, appear like a screen to veil the iniquity of your law and of your
                argument. What more need I say? Who was it who gave to the most infamous man that
                has ever existed, to the most wicked and polluted of all men, that rich and fertile
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>? Who gave him a war to carry on
                against nations who were in a state of profound peace? Who gave him the money which
                was destined for the purchase of lands and which had been taken by violence out of
                the fruits of the achievements of Caesar? Who gave him an unlimited command?<note
                    anchored="true">Gabinius is meant here; but Graevius thinks that there is a good
                    deal of corruption in this passage.</note> And, indeed, when you had given him
                    <placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>, you altered the terms of your
                bargain with him, and you transferred <placeName key="tgn,7002470"
                    >Cilicia</placeName> to the praetor, again quite out of the regular course. And
                then, when the bribe had been increased, you gave <placeName key="tgn,1000140"
                    >Syria</placeName> to Gabinius—expressly naming him. What more? Did you not,
                naming him expressly, deliver over, bound and fettered, to Lucius Piso, the foulest,
                the most cruel, the most treacherous of men, the most infamous of all men, as
                stigmatised for every sort of wickedness and lust, free nations, who had been
                declared free by numerous resolutions of the senate, and even by a recent law of
                your own son-in-law? Did not you, after the recompense for your service and the
                bribe of a province had been paid by him at my expense, still divide the treasury
                with him? <milestone n="24" unit="section"/> Is it so? Did you annul the arrangement
                of the consular provinces, which Caius Gracchus, than whom there hardly ever lived a
                man more devoted to the people, not only abstained from taking from the senate, but
                even passed a solemn law to establish the principle that they were to be settled
                every year by the senate;—did you, I say, disturb that arrangement, and that too
                after it had been formally settled according to the Sempronian law? You gave the
                provinces, in an irregular manner, without casting lots, not to the consuls, but to
                the pests of the republic, expressly naming them. And shall we be found fault with,
                because we have appointed a most illustrious man, who has often been selected before
                on occasions of the greatest danger to the republic, (expressly naming him,) to
                superintend a matter of the most urgent importance, and which was previously in an
                almost desperate condition? <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>What more shall I say? If, then, amid the darkness and impenetrable clouds and storms
                which were then lowering above the republic, when you had driven the senate from the
                helm and turned the people out of the ship, and while you yourself, like a captain
                of pirates, were hastening on with all your sails set, with your most infamous band
                of robbers; if at that time you had been able to carry the resolutions which you
                proposed, and punished, and brought forward, and sold, what place in the whole world
                would have been free from the extraordinary magistrates and commanders invested with
                their power by the great Clodius? <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But at last the indignation of Cnaeus Pompeius, (I will say, even in his hearing,
                what I have felt, and still do feel what ever may be the way in which he takes
                it,)—the indignation I say, of Cnaeus Pompeius, which had been too long concealed
                and slumbering, being at last aroused, came on a sudden to the aid of the republic,
                and raised the city crushed with misfortunes, dumb, weakened, and broken spirited
                through fear to some hope of recovering its liberty and former dignity. And was this
                man not to be appointed to superintend the providing the city with corn? You,
                forsooth, by your law abandoned all the corn, whether belonging to private
                individuals or to the state, all the provinces which supply corn, and all the
                contractors, and all the keys of the granaries, to that most impure of gluttons, the
                taster of your lusts, to that most needy and most impious man, Sextus Clodius, the
                companion of your family, who by his tongue alienated even your sister from you. And
                it was by this action of yours that dearness was first produced, and afterwards
                scarcity. Famine, conflagration, bloodshed, and pillage were impending. Your insane
                frenzy was threatening the fortunes and property of every man. <milestone n="26"
                    unit="section"/> That ill-omened pest of the state even complains that the corn
                should have been taken out of the impure mouth of Sextus Clodius, and that the
                republic in its extremest peril should have implored the aid of that man by whom it
                recollected that it had often been preserved, and had its power <pb n="14"/>
                extended. Clodius thinks that nothing ought to be done out of the regular course.
                What! what sort of law is it that you say that you passed about me, you parricide,
                you fratricide, you murderer of your sister; did you not pass that out of the
                regular course? Was it lawful for you to pass, I will not say a law, but a wicked
                private bill, concerning the ruin of a citizen, the preserver of the republic, as
                all gods and men have long since agreed to call him, and, as you yourself confess,
                when he was not only uncondemned but even unimpeached, amid the mourning of the
                senate and the lamentation of all good men, rejecting the prayers of all <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, while the republic lay oppressed and
                captive at your feet? And was it not lawful for me, when the Roman people implored
                me, when the senate requested me, when the critical state of the republic demanded
                it of me, to deliver an opinion concerning the safety of the Roman people?
                    <milestone n="27" unit="section"/> And if that opinion the dignity of Cnaeus
                Pompeius was increased, in connection with the common advantage, certainly I ought
                to be praised if I seemed to have given my vote for honour of that than who had
                brought his influence to aid in the ensuring of my safety. <milestone n="11"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Let men cease—cease, I say, from hoping that now that I have been restored, I can be
                undermined by the same contrivances by which they formerly smote me when I was
                flourishing. For what pair of men of consular dignity were ever more united in
                friendship in this state than Cnaeus Pompeius and I? Who has ever spoken more
                honourably or more repeatedly of his dignity before the Roman people or to the
                senate than I have? What labour was there so great, or what enmity so formidable, or
                what contest so arduous, that I was unwilling to encounter it for the sake of his
                dignity? and what honour that could be paid me by him, what panegyric of my glory,
                what recompense for my goodwill was ever omitted by him? <milestone n="28"
                    unit="section"/> This union of ours, this unanimity and concert in managing the
                affairs of the republic successfully, this most delightful agreement in life and all
                its duties, certain men, by false reports of conversations and false accusations,
                broke, interrupted; going to him, and warning him to be afraid of me, to guard
                against me, and at the same time telling me that he was hostile to me above all men:
                so that I had net sufficient confidence to ask of him what it was desirable for me
                to ask, nor did he, having been made sore by the jealousies and wickedness of
                certain individuals, promise me with sufficient freedom what my necessities
                required. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/> A great price has been paid for my
                error, O priests, so that I am not only grieved for my folly, but ashamed of it too;
                since, though it was not some sudden and accidental occasion, but many labors of
                long standing, encountered and undertaken long before, which had united me with a
                most gallant and most illustrious man, I still suffered myself to be led away to
                abandon such a friendship, and did not perceive who they were whom it became me
                either to oppose as open enemies, or to distrust as treacherous friends. Let them
                now at length cease to try and excite me with the same language as before: “What is
                that man about? Does not he know how great his influence is, what great achievements
                be has performed with what great honour he has been restored? Why does he do honour
                to the man by whom he was deserted?” <milestone n="30" unit="section"/> But I
                neither think that I was deserted at that time, but rather surrendered; nor do I
                think it needful for me to explain what at the time of that unhappiness to the
                republic was done against me nor how, nor by whose instrumentality it was done. If
                it was beneficial to the republic that that alone, as the victim offered for the
                general safety, should quaff that most unworthy cup of calamity, it may be useful
                also for me to conceal and be silent respecting the men by whose wickedness it was
                brought about. But yet it is the part of an ungrateful man to be silent. Therefore I
                will most willingly proclaim that Cnaeus Pompeius laboured with all his zeal and
                influence as much as any one of you, and with all his means, and labour, and by
                entreaty, and even at his own personal risk, to promote my safety. <milestone n="12"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>This man, O Publius Lentulus, was present at all your counsels, while you were
                thinking of nothing day and night except my safety. He cooperated with you as a most
                influential adviser in planning the conduct to be pursued, as a most faithful ally
                in preparing for it, and as a most fearless assistant in executing it. It was he who
                visited all the municipalities and colonies; it was he who implored the assistance
                of all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, which was eager to afford it;
                it was he who in the senate was the first person to deliver his opinion, and when he
                had delivered it there, he then also entreated the Roman people to preserve me.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="section"/> Wherefore, you may desist from that language
                which you have been using, namely, that the dispositions of the priests were changed
                after my delivering the opinion which I did about the corn. As if they had any
                different opinion from what I myself had about Cnaeus Pompeius, or as if they were
                ignorant what I ought to do either with regard to the expectation of the Roman
                people, or to the services which I have received from Cnaeus Pompeius, or to my own
                circumstances and condition; or as if even, if my sentiments had perchance been
                offensive to any one of the priests, though I know for a certainty that the contrary
                was the case, any priest was on that account going to decide about religion, or any
                citizen about the republic, in any other manner than the laws respecting religious
                ceremonies compelled the one, or the interests and safety of the republic compelled
                the other. </p>
            <p><milestone n="32" unit="section"/> I am aware, O priests, that I have said more
                things which are foreign to this cause, than either your opinion is likely to
                approve of, or than my own inclination prompted. But I was anxious to be acquitted
                in your eyes; and, further, your kindness in listening to me with attention carried
                me on to say more than I had intended. But I will make amends for this by the
                brevity of that part of the speech which relates to the actual matter now brought
                under your examination; and as the affair is divided into two heads,—one relating to
                the laws of religion, and the other to the laws of the state, —I will pass over the
                question of religion, which would take a longer time to discuss, and speak to the
                point of what is the law of the state. <milestone n="33" unit="section"/> For what
                can be so arrogant as for a layman to endeavour to lecture the college of priests
                about religion, about divine affairs, and ceremonies, and sacrifices; or so foolish
                as for a man, if he has found anything of consequence in your books, to take up time
                in detailing it to you; or so superfluous, as to seek to acquire learning on those
                points concerning which our ancestors have laid down the principle that you alone
                have knowledge, and that you alone ought to be consulted? <milestone n="13"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I say that it was not possible, according to our common rights, and according to
                those laws which are in force in this city, for any citizen to be exposed to such
                disaster as mine without a formal trial. I say that this was the law in this state
                even at the time when the kings existed; I say that this was the principle handed
                down to us from our ancestors; I say, moreover, that this is the inalienable
                characteristic of a free state,—that no infringement on the liberties or property of
                a citizen can take place without the formal decision of the senate, or of the
                people, or of those persons who have been appointed as judges in each separate
                matter. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/> Do you not see that I am destroying all
                your proceedings by the roots? that I am arguing, what is manifest, that you did
                nothing whatever according to law,—that you were not a tribune of the people at all?
                I say this, that you are a patrician. I say so before the priests; the augurs are
                present. I take my stand on the common public law. What, O priests is the law
                concerning adoption? Why that he may adopt children who is no longer able to have
                children himself, and who failed in having them when he was of an age to expect it.
                What reason, then, any one has for adopting children, what considerations of family
                or dignity are involved what principles of religion are concerned, are questions
                which are accustomed to be put to the college of priests. What if all these
                circumstances are found to exist in that adoption? The person who adopts him is
                twenty years old; a minor adopts a senator. Does he do so for the sake of having
                children? He is of an age to have them of his own. He has a wife; he has actually
                got children of his own. The father, then, will be disinheriting his own son.
                    <milestone n="35" unit="section"/> What? why should all the sacred rites of the
                Clodian family perish, as far as it depends on you? And that must have been the idea
                of all the priests when you were adopted. Unless, perchance, the question was put to
                you in this way,—whether you were intending to disturb the republic by seditions,
                and whether you wished to be adopted with that object, not in order to become that
                man's son, but only in order to be made a tribune of the people, and by that means
                utterly to overthrow the state? You answered, I presume, that your object was only
                to be made a tribune. That appeared to the priests to be a sufficient reason. They
                approved of it. No questions were asked about the age of the man who was adopting
                you; as was done in the case of Cnaeus Aufidius and Marcus Pupius, each of whom,
                within our recollection, when extremely old, adopted as sons, the one Orestes, and
                the other Piso. And these adoptions, like others, more than I can count, were
                followed by the inheritance of the name and <pb n="18"/> property and sacred rites
                of the family. You are not Fonteius, as you ought to be, nor the heir of your new
                father; nor, though you have lost your right to the sacred ceremonies of your own
                family, have you availed yourself of those which belong to you by adoption. And so,
                having thrown the ceremonies of religion into confusion,—having polluted both
                families, both the one which you have abandoned and the one which you have
                entered,—having violated the legitimate practices of the Romans with respect to
                guardianships and inheritances, you have been made, contrary to all the requirements
                of religion, the son of that man of whom you were old enough to be the father.
                    <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="36" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I am speaking before the priests; I say that that adoption did not take place
                according to the sacerdotal law. In the first place, because your respective ages
                are such that the man who has adopted you as your father might, as far as his age
                went, have been your son; in the second place, because a question is usually put as
                to the reason for the adoption, in order that the adopter may be a person who is
                seeking by regular and sacerdotal law that which by the ordinary process of nature
                he is no longer able to obtain; and that he may adopt a son in such a manner, as to
                in nowise impair the dignity of the families or the reverence belonging to their
                sacred ceremonies; and, above all things, that no false pretence, or fraud, or
                trickery, may creep in; so that this fictitious adoption of a son may appear to
                imitate as far as possible the real case of children being born to a man. <milestone
                    n="37" unit="section"/> But what greater false pretence can there be than for a
                beardless young man, a vigorous man and a husband, to come forward, and to say that
                he wishes to adopt as his own son a senator of the Roman people, and for all men to
                know and see that this senator is adopted, not in order to become really the son of
                the plebeian, but merely in order that he may quit the patrician body, and be made a
                tribune of the people? And all that without any disguise. For in this case the
                adopted son was immediately emancipated, lest he should really have become the son
                of him who adopted him. Why then is he adopted at all? Only approve of this sort of
                adoption, and in a moment the sacred ceremonies of every family, of which you ought
                to be the guardians, will be abolished, and not one patrician will be left. For why
                should any one be willing to be incapable of being made a tribune of the people? to
                have his power of standing for the consulship narrowed? and, while he might arrive
                at the priesthood, not to arrive at it because there is not a vacancy at the moment
                for a patrician?<note anchored="true">When the number of <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >pontifices</foreign> was increased to eight, it was provided that one half
                    of that number should always be plebeians. See <bibl n="Liv. 10.6">Livy, x
                        6.</bibl></note> Whenever anything happens to any one to make it more
                convenient for him to be a plebeian, he will be adopted in the same manner as
                Clodius. <milestone n="38" unit="section"/> And so in a short time the Roman people
                will neither have a king of the sacrifices,<note anchored="true">When the civil and
                    military powers of the king were transferred to the two consuls, these
                    magistrates were not invested with that part of the royal dignity by virtue of
                    which he had been the highest of his nation; but this priestly part of his
                    office was transferred to a priest called <foreign xml:lang="la">rex
                        sacrificulus</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="la">rex sacrorum</foreign>. He
                    was always elected and inaugurated in the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia
                        calata</foreign>, under the presidency of the pontiffs, and was always a
                    patrician, for as he had no influence upon the management of political affairs,
                    the plebeians never coveted this dignity.</note> nor <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >flamines</foreign>,<note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >Flamen</foreign> was the name for any priest who was devoted to the service
                    of one particular god.</note> nor Salii,<note anchored="true">The <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Salii</foreign> were the priests of Mars Gradivus, and were
                    said to have been instituted by Numa. They were twelve in number, chosen from
                    the patricians only, even down to the very latest times.</note> nor one half of
                the rest of the priests, nor any one who has a right to open the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >curiata</foreign>; and the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign> of the
                Roman people must come to an end if no patrician magistrates are created, as there
                will be no interrex,<note anchored="true">An <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >interrex</foreign> was an officer first appointed on the death of Romulus.
                    Under the republic <foreign xml:lang="la">interreges</foreign> were appointed
                    for holding the <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign> for the election of
                    consuls, when the consul, through civil commotions or other causes, had been
                    unable to do so during their year of office. Each <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >interrex</foreign> held the office for only five days. Plebeians were not
                    admissible to this office; and consequently after plebeians were admitted into
                    the Senate, the patrician senators met without the plebeian members to elect an
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">interrex</foreign>.</note> for he must be a
                patrician, and must be nominated by a patrician. I said before the priests, that
                that adoption had not been approved by any decree of this college; that it had been
                executed contrary to every provision of the sacerdotal law; that it ought to be
                considered as no adoption at all; and if there is an end to that, you see at once
                that there is an end likewise of the whole of your tribuneship. <milestone n="15"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="39" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I come now to the augurs and if they have any secret books I do not inquire into
                them; I am not very curious about inquiring into the principles of the augurs. I
                know, what I have learnt in common with all the people, what answers they have
                frequently given in the public assemblies. They say that it is contrary to divine
                law for any public business to be brought before the people when any proper officers
                observing the heavens. Will you venture to deny that, on the day when the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">Lex curiata</foreign><note anchored="true">A <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Lex curiata</foreign> was a law passed by the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">comitia curiata</foreign>. And these <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >comitia</foreign> were held (among other causes) for the purpose of
                    carrying into effect the form of adoption called <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >arrogatio</foreign>. When the question to be proposed had relation to
                    sacred things, the <foreign xml:lang="la">pontifices</foreign> presided in
                    them.</note> concerning you is said to have been passed, the magistrates were
                observing the heavens? A man is here present in court, of the most eminent wisdom,
                and dignity, and authority, Marcus Bibulus. I assert that on that very day he, as
                consul, was observing the heavens. “What then,” you will say, “are then the acts of
                Caius Caesar, that most admirable citizen, invalid in your opinion?” By no means;
                for there is not one of them which concerns me in the least, nor anything else
                except these weapons which by that man's proceedings are hurled at me. <milestone
                    n="40" unit="section"/> But the matter of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign>, which I am now touching on with extreme brevity, has been
                handled in this manner by you. You, when your tribuneship was in danger and was
                falling to pieces as it were, all of a sudden came forward as a patron of the
                    <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>; you brought forward Marcus Bibulus
                and the augurs into the assembly; you questioned the augurs, and they replied that
                when any magistrates was observing the heavens, no business could be transacted in
                the assembly of the people. You questioned Marcus Bibulus, and he told you in reply
                that he had been observing the heavens; and he also said in the public assembly,
                when he was brought forward there by your brother Appius, that you were no tribune
                of the people at all, because you had been adopted contrary to the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>. In the succeeding months your language
                constantly was, that everything which Caius Caesar had done ought to be rescinded by
                the senate, because they had been done in disregard of the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign>; and if they were rescinded, you said that you would bring
                me back on your own shoulders into the city as the guardian of the city. See now, O
                priests, the insanity of the man when by means of his tribuneship he was connected
                to such an extent with the acts of Caesar. <milestone n="41" unit="section"/> If the
                priests deciding according to the law relating to sacrifices, and the augurs
                according to the religious observance due to the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >auspices</foreign>, upset your whole tribuneship, what more do you ask? do you
                want some still more evident argument drawn from the rights of the people and the
                laws? <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>It was perhaps about the sixth hour when I complained in the court of justice (when I
                was defending Caius Antonius, my colleague,) of some things in the republic which
                appeared to me to relate to the cause of that unhappy man. What I said was reported
                by some wicked men to some very eminent citizens in language very different from
                that which I had employed. At the ninth hour on that very same day you were adopted.
                If, while in all other laws there ought to be an interval of three days, it is
                sufficient in a law respecting an adoption that there should be one of three hours,
                I have nothing to object to. But if the same forms are to be observed,—if the senate
                decreed that the people was not bound by the laws of Marcus Drusus, which had been
                passed contrary to the provisions of the Caecilian<note anchored="true">When a law
                    comprised very various provisions relating to matters essentially different, it
                    was called <foreign xml:lang="la">Lex satura</foreign> and the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Lex Caecilia Didia</foreign> forbade the proposing of a
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">Lex satura</foreign>, on the ground that the people
                    might be compelled either to vote for something which they did not approve, or
                    to reject something which they did approve, if it was proposed to them in this
                    manner. <foreign xml:lang="la">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. pp. 559, 561, v.
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">Lex</foreign>.</note> and Didian laws you must see
                that by every description of right which prevails with regard to sacred things, to
                the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, or to the laws, you were not elected
                tribune of the people. <milestone n="42" unit="section"/> And it is not without
                reason that I say no more on this point, for I see that some most eminent men, the
                chief men of the city, have given their decision on different occasions, that you
                could legally proceed with matters which came before the common people; who said
                too, with reference to my own case, though they said that the republic was murdered
                and buried by your motion, still that that burial, miserable and bitter as it was,
                was all according to law: they said that in carrying such a motion as you had
                carried concerning me a citizen, and one who had deserved well of the republic, you
                had inflicted a deadly wound on the republic; but, inasmuch as you had carried it
                with all due reverence for the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, they said
                that you had acted legally. Wherefore we, I imagine, may be allowed to abstain from
                attacking those actions by which they were induced to approve of the establishment
                of your tribuneship. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Suppose, however, that you were as rightly and legally tribune as Rullus himself, who
                is here present, a man most illustrious and honourable on every account; still, by
                what law, or in accordance with what precedent or what custom, did you pass a law
                affecting, by name, the civil rights of a citizen who had not been condemned?
                    <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The sacred laws,—the laws of the Twelve Tables, forbid bills to be brought in
                affecting individuals only; for such a bill is a <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >privilegium</foreign>. No one has ever carried such a bill. There is nothing
                more cruel, nothing more mischievous, nothing which this city can less tolerate.
                What was it in that miserable proscription, and all the other miseries of Sulla's
                time, which was the most remarkable thing which will prevent the cruelties then
                practised from being ever forgotten? I imagine it was the fact that punishments were
                at that time proclaimed on Roman citizens by name without any trial. <milestone
                    n="44" unit="section"/> Will you, then, O priests, by this decision, and by your
                authority, give a tribune of the people power to proscribe whomsoever he chooses?
                For I ask what else proscribing is, excepting proposing such a law as this, “That
                you will decide and order that Marcus Tullius shall no longer be in the city, and
                that his property may become mine?” For this is the effect of what he carried,
                though the language is somewhat different. Is this a resolution of the people? Is
                this a law? Is this a motion? Can you endure this? Can the city endure that a single
                citizen should be removed out of the city by a single line? I, indeed, have now
                endured my share. I have no more violence to fear. I am in dread of no further
                attacks. I have satisfied the hostility of those who envied me; I have appeased the
                hatred of wicked men; I have satiated even the treachery and wickedness of traitors;
                and, what is more, by this time every city, all ranks of men, all gods and men have
                expressed their opinion on my case, which appeared to those profligate men to be
                exposed above all others as a mark for unpopularity. <milestone n="45"
                    unit="section"/> You now, O priests, are bound; as becomes your authority and
                your wisdom, to have regard in your decision to your own interests, and to those of
                your children, and to the welfare of the rest of the citizens. </p>
            <p>For as the forms of proceeding before the people have been appointed by our ancestors
                to be so moderate,—so that in the first place no punishment affecting a man's status
                as a citizen can be joined to any pecuniary fine in the next place, that no one can
                be accused except on a day previously appointed; again, that the prosecutor must
                accuse him before the magistrate three times, a day being allowed to intervene
                between each hearing, before the magistrate can inflict any fine or give any
                decision; and when there is a fourth hearing for the accusation appointed after
                    seventeen<note anchored="true">The Latin is “<foreign xml:lang="la">trinum
                        nundinum prodicta die</foreign>”. “<foreign xml:lang="la">Nundina</foreign>,
                    the ninth day inclusive; this was the Roman market day; because every ninth day
                    the country people came to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> to
                    transact business......three such <foreign xml:lang="la">nundinae</foreign>
                    formed a <foreign xml:lang="la">trinum nundinum</foreign>, or <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">trinundinum</foreign>, i.e. a space of seventeen days. Every
                    bill was posted up during three <foreign xml:lang="la">nundinae</foreign>, that
                    all persons might read it.”—Riddle, Lat. Dict. in v. <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >Nundinus</foreign>.</note> days, on a day appointed on which the judge
                shall give his decision; and when many other concessions have been granted to the
                defendants to give them an opportunity of appeasing the prosecutor, or of exciting
                pity; and besides this the people is a people inclined to listen to entreaties, and
                very apt to give their votes for a defendant's safety; and, beyond all this, if
                anything prevents the cause from being proceeded with on that day, either because of
                the <foreign xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, or on any other plea or excuse, then
                there is an end to the whole cause and to the whole business. <milestone n="18"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="46" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>As these things then are so where is the accusation, where is the prosecutor? where
                are the witnesses? What is more scandalous, than when a man has neither been ordered
                to appear, nor summoned, nor accused, for hired men, assassins, needy and profligate
                citizens, to give a vote touching his status as a citizen, his children and all his
                fortune, and then to think that vote a law? But, if he was able to do this in my
                case, I being a man protected by the honours which I had attained, by the justice of
                my cause, and by the republic; and being not so rich as to make my money an object
                to my enemies, and he had nothing which could be injurious to me, except the great
                chances which were taking place in the affairs of the state, and the critical
                condition of the times; what is likely to happen to those men whose way of life is
                removed from popular honours and from all that renown which gives influence, and
                whose riches are so great that too many men, needy, extravagant, and even of noble
                birth, covet them? <milestone n="47" unit="section"/> Grant this licence to a
                tribune of the people, and then for a moment contemplate in your minds the youth of
                the city, and especially those men who seem now to be anxiously coveting the
                tribunitian power. There will be found, by Jove! whole colleges of tribunes of the
                people, if this law is once established, and they will all conspire against the
                property of all the richest men, when a booty so especially popular and the hope of
                great acquisitions is thus held out to them. </p>
            <p>But what vote is it that this skillful and experienced law-giver has carried? “May
                you be willing and may you command that Marcus Tullius be interdicted from water and
                fire.” A cruel vote, a nefarious vote, one not to be endured even in the case of the
                very wickedest citizen, without a trial. He did not propose a vote, “That he be
                interdicted.” What then? “That he has been interdicted.” O horrible, O prodigious, O
                what wickedness! Did Clodius frame this law, more infamous than even his own
                tongue?—that it has been interdicted to a person to whom it has not been
                interdicted? My good friend Sextus, by your leave, tell me now, since you are a
                logician and are devoted to this science, is it possible for a proposition to be
                made to the people, or to be established by any form of words, or to be confirmed by
                any votes, making that to have been done which has not been done? <milestone n="48"
                    unit="section"/> And have you ruined the public, with the man who drew this law
                for your adviser, and counselor, and minister, a fellow more impure, not only than
                any biped, but even than any quadruped? And you were not so foolish or so mad as to
                be ignorant that this man who violated the laws was Clodius; but that there were
                other men who were accustomed to frame laws: but you had not the least power over
                any one of them, or over any one else who had any character to lose; nor could you
                employ the same framers of laws, or the same architect for your works, as the
                others; nor could you obtain the aid of any priest you chose. Lastly, you were not
                able to discover, not even when you were dividing your plunder, any purchaser, or
                any one to share your plunder with you, out of your own band of gladiators, nor any
                one to support that proscription of yours with his vote except some thief or
                assassin. <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="49" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Therefore, when you, flourishing and powerful, were triumphing in the middle of your
                mob, those friends of yours, safe and happy in having you for their only friend, who
                had entrusted their fate to the people, were repelled<note anchored="true">He refers
                    here to Vatinius, who had lately been an unsuccessful candidate for the
                    aedileship.</note> in such a way that they lost the support of even that
                    <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine</placeName><note anchored="true">The
                        <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine</placeName> tribe was composed of
                    artisans and needy citizens, of whose aid Clodius availed himself largely in
                    creating disturbances.</note> tribe of yours. They who came before a court of
                justice, whether as prosecutors or as defendants, were condemned, though you
                endeavoured to beg them off. Lastly, even that new recruit, Ligur, your venal backer
                and seconder, when he had been disgraced by being passed over in the will of Marcus
                Papirius his brother, who expressed his opinion of him by that action, said that he
                desired to have a legal investigation into the circumstances of his death, and
                accused Sextus Propertius as accessory to it. He did not venture to accuse his
                partners of a crime in which they had no concern, and to endeavour to procure their
                condemnation, lest he himself should have been convicted of bringing false
                accusations. <milestone n="50" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>We are speaking, then, of this law which appears to have been legally brought
                forward, while yet every one that has had anything to do with any part of it, either
                by hand, voice, vote, or by sharing in the plunder, wherever he has been, has come
                off rejected and convicted. </p>
            <p>What shall we say if the proscription is framed in such terms that it repels itself?
                For it is, “Because Marcus Tullius has forged a decree of the senate.” If, then, he
                did forge a decree of the senate, the law was proposed; but if he did not forge one,
                no proposition has been made at all. Does it or does it not appear sufficiently
                decided by the senate that I did not falsely allege the authority of that order, but
                that I, of all the men that have ever lived since the foundation of the city, have
                been the most diligent in my obedience to the senate? In how many ways do I not
                prove that that which you call a law is no law at all? What shall we say if you
                brought many different matters before the people at one and the same time? Do you
                still think that what Marcus Drusus, that admirable man, could not obtain in most of
                his laws,—that what Marcus Scaurus and Lucius Crassus, men of consular rank, could
                not obtain, you can obtain through the agency of the Decurii and Clodii, the
                ministers of all your debaucheries and crimes? <milestone n="51" unit="section"/>
                You carried a proposition respecting me, that I should not be received anywhere,—not
                that I should depart, when you yourself were not able to say that it was unlawful
                for me to remain in <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. <milestone
                    n="20" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>For what could you say? That I had been condemned?, Certainly not. That I had been
                expelled. How could you say that? And yet even that was not stated in your bill that
                I was to depart; there is a penalty for any one who received me, which every one
                disregarded; but there is no mention anywhere of driving me out. However, suppose
                there were,—what are we to say about the collecting of all the common artisans to
                pull down my house? what shall we say about your having your name cut on it? does
                that seem to you to be anything except a plundering of all my property? except that
                you could not by the Licinian law undertake the commission yourself. What are we to
                say about this very matter which you are now arguing before the priests; namely,
                that you consecrated my house, that you erected a memorial, that you dedicated a
                statue in my house, and that you did all these things by one little bit of a bill?
                Do all these things appear to be only one and the same business with the bill which
                you carried against me expressly by name? <milestone n="52" unit="section"/> It is
                just the same thing that you did when you also carried these different enactments in
                one law,—one, that the king of <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>,
                whose ancestors had always been allies and friends to this nation, should have all
                his goods sold by the public crier, and the other, that the exiles should be brought
                back to <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>. “Oh,” says he, “I
                employed the same person on both those matters.” What? Suppose you had given the
                same man a commission to get you an Asiatic coin in <placeName key="tgn,1000004"
                    >Asia</placeName>, and from thence to proceed into <placeName key="tgn,1000095"
                    >Spain</placeName>; and given him leave, after he had departed from <placeName
                    key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, to stand for the consulship, and, after he
                was made consul, to obtain <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> for his
                province; would that be all one measure, because you were mentioning only one man?
                    <milestone n="53" unit="section"/> And if now the Roman people had been
                consulted about that business, and if you had not done everything by the
                instrumentality of slaves and robbers, was it impossible for the Roman people to
                approve of the part of the measure relating to the king of <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, and to approve of that part which affected
                Byzantine exiles? What other force, what other meaning, I should like to know, has
                the Caecilian and Didian law, except this; that the people are not to be forced in
                consequence of many different things being joined in one complicated bill, either to
                accept what it disapproves of; or reject what it approves? </p>
            <p>What shall we say if you carried the bill by violence? is it, nevertheless, a law? Or
                can anything appear to have been done rightfully which was notoriously done by
                violence? And if, at the very time of your getting this law passed, when the city
                was stormed, stones were not thrown, and men did not actually come to blows hand to
                hand, is that any proof that you were able to contrive that disgrace and ruin to the
                city without extreme violence? <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="54"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>When in the Aurelian tribunal you were openly enrolling not only freemen but slaves
                also, got together out of all the streets in the city, were you not at that time
                preparing for violence? When by your edicts, you ordered all the shops to be shut,
                were you aiming not at the violence of the mob, but at a modest and prudent
                gathering of honourable men? When you were having arms collected and carried to the
                temple of Castor, had you no other object beyond preventing others from being able
                to effect anything by violence? But when you tore up and removed the steps of the
                temple of Castor, did you then, in order to be able to act in a moderate manner,
                repel audacious men from the approaches and ascents leading to the temple? When you
                ordered those persons who, in an assembly of virtuous men, had spoken in defence of,
                my safety, to come forward, and had driven away their companions and seconders by
                blows and arms and stones; then, no doubt, you showed that violence was excessively
                disagreeable to you. <milestone n="55" unit="section"/> Oh, but this frantic
                violence of a demented tribune of the people could easily be crushed and put down by
                the virtue and superior numbers of the good citizens. What? when <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName> was given to Gabinius, <placeName
                    key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> to Piso, boundless authority and vast
                sums of money to both of them, to induce them to place everything in your power, to
                assist you, to supply you which followers, and troops, and their own prepared
                centurions, and money, and bands of slaves; to all you with their infamous
                assemblies, to deride the authority of the senate, to threaten the Roman knights
                with death and proscription, to terrify me with threats, to threaten me with
                contests and murder, to fill my house with their friends, which had heretofore been
                full of virtuous men; through fear of proscription; to deprive me of the crowds of
                good men who used to associate with me, to strip me of their protection; to forbid
                the senate, that most illustrious body, not only to fight for me, but even to
                implore men, and to entreat them in my behalf, and, changing their garments, to
                lament my danger,—was not even this violence? <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="56" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Why then did I depart, or what fear was there? I will not say in me. Allow that I am
                timid by nature; what are we to say of so many thousands of the bravest men? what
                did our Roman knights think? what did the senate? what, in short, did all good men
                think? If there was no violence, why did they escort me out of the city with tears,
                instead of reproving and detaining me, or being indignant with me and leaving me? Or
                was I afraid that I could not, while present, resist their accusations if they
                proceeded against me according to the usages and principles of our ancestors?
                    <milestone n="57" unit="section"/> If a day had been appointed for my trial,
                must I have dreaded the investigation? or must I have feared a private bill being
                introduced against me without any trial? A trial in so shameful a cause I suppose I
                am a man who, if the cause were not understood, could not speak so as to explain it
                at all, or could I not make people approve of my cause, when its excellence is such
                that of its own merits it made people approve not only of itself while it was before
                them, but of me also though I was absent? Was the senate, were all ranks of the
                people, were those men who flew hither from all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName> to cooperate in my recall, likely to be more indifferent,
                while I was present, about retaining and preserving me, in that cause which even
                that parricide says was such, that he complains that I was sought out and recalled
                to my previous honours by the whole people? <milestone n="58" unit="section"/> Was
                there then no danger to me whatever in a court of justice; but was I to fear a
                private bill, and that if a penalty were sought to be recovered from me while I was
                present, no one would interpose a veto? Was I so destitute of friends, or was the
                republic so entirely without magistrates? What? supposing the tribes had been
                convoked, would they have approved of a proscription, I will not say against me who
                had deserved so well of them by my efforts for their safety, but would they have
                approved of it in the case of any citizen whatever? Or, if I had been present, would
                those veteran troops of conspirators, and those profligate and needy soldiers of
                yours, and that new force of two most impious consuls, have spared my person, when,
                after that I had, by departing, succumbed to their inhumanity and wickedness, I
                could not though absent satisfy their hostility to me by my misfortunes? <milestone
                    n="23" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="59" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For what injury had my unhappy wife done to you? whom you harassed and plundered and
                ill-treated with every description of cruelty. What harm had my daughter done to
                you? whose incessant weeping and mourning and misery were so agreeable to you,
                though they moved the eyes and feelings of every one else. What had my little son
                done? whom no one ever saw all the time that I was away, that he was not weeping and
                lamenting; what, I say, had he done that you should so often try to murder him by
                stratagem? What had my brother done? who, when, some time after my departure, he
                arrived from his province and thought that it was not worth his while to live unless
                I were restored to him, when his chief and excessive and unprecedented mourning
                seemed to render him an object of pity to every one, was constantly attacked by you
                with arms and violence, he escaped with difficulty out of your hands. <milestone
                    n="60" unit="section"/> But why need I dilate upon your cruelty which you have
                displayed towards me and mine? when you have waged a horrible and nefarious war,
                dyed with every description of hatred against my walls, my roofs, my pillars and
                door-posts. For I do not think that you, when, after my departure, you in the
                covetousness of your hopes had devoured the fortunes of all the rich men, the
                produce of all the provinces, the property of tetrarchs and of kings, were blinded
                by the desire of my plate and furniture. I do not think that that Campanian consul
                with his dancing colleague, after you had sacrificed to the one all <placeName
                    key="tgn,7002733">Achaia</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7001399"
                    >Thessaly</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>,
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                    >Macedonia</placeName> and all the countries of the barbarians, and the property
                of the Roman citizens in those countries, and when you had delivered up to the other
                Sulla, <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>, and the Persians those
                hitherto uninjured and peaceful nations, to plunder, I do not think, I say, that
                they were covetous of my thresholds and pillars and folding doors. <milestone n="61"
                    unit="section"/> Nor, indeed, did the bands and forces of Catiline think that
                they could appease their hunger with the tiles and mortar of my roofs. But as,
                without being influenced by the idea of booty, still out of hatred we are accustomed
                to destroy the cities of enemies;—not of all enemies indeed, but of those with whom
                we have waged any bitter and intestine war; because when our minds have been
                inflamed against any people by reason of their cruelty, there always appears to be
                some war still lingering in their abodes and habitations,<gap reason="* * *"/>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="62" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>No law had been passed respecting me. I had not been ordered to appear in court; I
                had not been summoned. I was absent. I was even in your own opinion a citizen with
                all my rights as such unimpaired, when my house on the <placeName key="tgn,3000935"
                    >Palatine</placeName> hill, and my villa in the district of <placeName
                    key="perseus,Tusculum">Tusculum</placeName>, were transferred one a-piece to
                each of the consuls; decrees of the senate were flying about; marble columns from my
                house were carried off to the father-in-law of the consul in the sight of the Roman
                people; and the consul who was my neighbour at my villa had not only my stock and
                the decorations of my villa, but even my trees transferred to his farm; while the
                villa itself was utterly destroyed, not from a desire of plunder, (for what plunder
                could there be there?) but out of hatred and cruelty. My house on the <placeName
                    key="tgn,3000935">Palatine</placeName> hill was burnt, not by accident, but
                having been set on fire on purpose. The consuls were feasting and reveling amid the
                congratulations of the conspirators, while the one boasted that he had been the
                favourite of Catiline, and the other that he was the cousin of Cethegus. <milestone
                    n="63" unit="section"/> This violence, O priests, this wickedness, this frenzy,
                I, opposing my single person to the storm, warded off from the necks of all good
                men, and I received on my body all the attacks of disaffection, all the
                long-collected violence of the wicked, which, having been long coming to a head,
                with silent and repressed hatred, was at last breaking out now that it had got such
                audacious leaders. Against me alone were directed the consular firebrands hurled
                from the hands of the tribunes; all the impious arrows of the conspiracy, which I
                had once before blunted, now stuck in me. But if, as was the advice of many most
                gallant men, I had determined to contend with violence and arms against violence, I
                should either have gained the day with a great slaughter of wicked men, who
                notwithstanding were citizens, or else all the good men would have been slain, to
                the great joy of the wicked, and I too should have perished together with the
                republic. <milestone n="64" unit="section"/> I saw, that if the senate and people of
                    <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> existed, I should have a speedy
                return with the greatest dignity, and I did not think it possible that such a state
                of affairs should longer continue to exist, as for me not to be allowed to live in
                that republic which I myself had saved. And if I were not allowed to live there, I
                had heard and read that some of the most illustrious men of our country had rushed
                into the middle of the enemy to manifest death for the sake of the safety of their
                army. And could I doubt that if I were to sacrifice myself for the safety of the
                entire republic, I should in this point be better off than the Decii, because they
                could not even hear of their glory, while I should be able to be even a spectator of
                my own renown? <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Therefore your frenzy, being disconcerted, kept making vain attacks. For the
                bitterness of my fortune had exhausted all the violence of all the wicked citizens.
                In such terrible disaster and such wide-spread ruin, there was no room for any new
                cruelty. <milestone n="65" unit="section"/> Cato was next to me. Was there nothing
                which you could do beyond making him who had been my leader and guide in all my
                conduct a partner also in my misfortune? What? Could you banish him? What then? You
                could send him away for the money of <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
                >Cyprus</placeName>. One booty may have been lost; another will be sure to be found;
                only let this man be got out of the way. Accordingly, the hated Marcus Cato is
                commissioned to go to <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, as if it was
                a kindness that was being conferred on him. Two men are removed, whom the wicked men
                could not bear the sight of; one by the most discreditable sort of honour, the other
                by the most honourable possible calamity. <milestone n="66" unit="section"/> And
                that you may be aware that that man had been an enemy not to their persons, but to
                their virtues, after I was driven out, and Cato despatched on his commission, he
                turns himself against that very man by whose advice and by whose assistance he was
                in the habit of saying in the assemblies that he had done and continued to do what
                he was then doing and everything which he had hitherto done. He thought that Cnaeus
                Pompeius, who he saw was in every one's opinion by far the first man in the city,
                would not much longer tolerate his frenzy. After he had filched out of his custody
                by treachery the son of a king who was our friend,—himself being an enemy and a
                prisoner,—and having provoked that most gallant man by this injury, he thought that
                he could contend with him by the aid of those troops against whom I had been willing
                to struggle at the risk of the destruction of all virtuous citizens, especially as
                at first he had the consuls to help him. But after a time Gabinius broke his
                agreement with him; but Piso continued faithful to him. <milestone n="67"
                    unit="section"/> You saw what massacres that man then committed, what men he
                stoned, what numbers he made to flee; how easily by means of his armed bands and his
                daily plots did he compel Cnaeus Pompeius to absent himself from the forum and the
                senate-house, and to confine himself to his own house, even after he had been
                already deserted by the best part of his forces. And from this you may judge how
                great that violence was at its first rise, and when first collected together, when
                even after it was scattered and almost extinct it alarmed Cnaeus Pompeius in this
                way. <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="68" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>That most prudent man, Lucius Cotta, a man most deeply attached to the republic and
                to me, and above all to truth, saw this when he delivered his opinion on the first
                of January. He then considered it unnecessary that any law should be passed for my
                return. He said that I had consulted the interests of the republic; that I had
                yielded to the tempest; that I had been more friendly to you and to the rest of the
                citizens than to myself and to my own relations; that I had been driven away by the
                disturbances of a body of men banded together for purposes of bloodshed, and by an
                unprecedented exercise of power; that no law could possibly have been passed
                affecting my status as a citizen; that no law had been drawn up in writing, that
                none could have any validity; that everything had been done in disregard of the laws
                and of the usages of our ancestors, in a rash and turbulent manner, by violence and
                frenzy. But if that were a law, then it was not lawful for the consuls to refer the
                matter to the senate,<note anchored="true">Because a <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >lex</foreign>, properly so called, was only passed in the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign>, not in the senate. <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Vide</foreign> Smith, Dict. Ant. v. <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >Lex</foreign>.</note> nor for him himself to express his opinion upon it in
                the senate. And as both these things were being done, it was not right that it
                should be decreed that a law should be passed concerning me, lest that which was no
                law at all, should be in consequence decided to be a law. No opinion could be truer,
                sounder, more expedient, or better for the republic. For the wickedness and frenzy
                of the man being stigmatized by it, all danger of similar disgrace to the republic
                for the future was removed. <milestone n="69" unit="section"/> Nor did Cnaeus
                Pompeius, who delivered a most elaborate opinion and most honourable to me, nor did
                you, O priests, who defended me by your decision and authority, fail to see that
                that was no law at all, and that it was rather the heat of the times, an interdict
                of wickedness, a voice of frenzy. But you were anxious to guard against any popular
                odium being excited against you; if we appeared to have been restored without any
                decision of the people. And with the same idea the senate adopted the opinion of
                Marcus Bibulus, a most fearless man, that you should decide the question relating to
                my house: not that he doubted that nothing had been done by Clodius with due regard
                either to the laws, or to the requirements of religion, or to the rights of the
                citizens; but that, as wicked men were so numerous, no one should at any time arise
                and say that there was anything holy about my house. For as often as the senate has
                expressed any opinion at all in my case, so often has it decided that that was no
                law at all, since indeed, according to that writing which that fellow drew up, it
                was forbidden to express any opinion at all. <milestone n="70" unit="section"/> And
                that kindred pair, Piso and Gabinius, saw this. Those men, so obedient to the laws
                and courts of justice, when the senate in very full houses kept constantly
                entreating them to make a motion respecting me,—said that they did not disapprove of
                the object, but that they were hindered by that fellow's law. And this was true; but
                it was law which he had passed about giving them <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                    >Macedonia</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1000140">Syria</placeName>.
                    <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But you, O Publius Lentulus, neither as a private individual nor as consul ever
                thought that it was a law. For when the tribunes of the people made a motion, you as
                consul elect often delivered your opinion concerning my affairs; and from the first
                of January to the time that the whole affair was completed, you persevered in making
                motions respecting me, you proposed a law, you passed it; none of which things could
                legally have been done by you if that thing of Clodius's had been a law. But Quintus
                Metellus your colleague, a most illustrious man, even though he was a brother of
                Clodius, when he joined you in making a motion in the senate respecting my affairs,
                expressed his opinion that that was no law at <pb n="34"/> all which men utterly
                unconnected with Clodius,—namely Piso and Gabinius, considered was a law. <milestone
                    n="71" unit="section"/> But how did those men who had such respect for Clodius's
                laws observe the rest of the laws? The senate indeed, whose authority is of the very
                greatest weight on all questions affecting the power of the laws, as often as it has
                been consulted in my case, has decided that that was no law at all. And you, O
                Lentulus, showed that you were aware of its not being one in that law which you
                carried concerning me. For that law was not framed in such terms as that I might be
                allowed to come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>, but that I should
                come to <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName>. For you did not wish to
                propose to make that lawful for me to do, which was lawful already; but you wished
                me to be in the republic, appearing to have been sent for by the command of the
                Roman people, rather than to have been restored for the purpose of aiding in the
                management of the republic. <milestone n="72" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Did you then, O you most monstrous pest, dare to call that man an exile, when you
                yourself were branded with such wickedness and such crimes that you made every place
                which you approached very like a place of banishment? For what is an exile? The name
                itself is an indication of misfortune, not of disgrace. When, then, is it
                disgraceful? In reality when it is the punishment of guilt; but in the opinion of
                men, when it is the punishment of a condemned person. Is it then owing to any crime
                of mine that I hear the name of an exile, or owing to any judicial sentence? Owing
                to any crime? Even you, whom those satellites of yours call the prosperous Catiline,
                do not dare to affirm that, nor do any one of those men who used to say so, venture
                to say so now. There is not only no one so ignorant now as to say that those actions
                which I did in my consulship were errors; but no one is such an enemy to his country
                as not to confess that the country was preserved by my counsels. <milestone n="28"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="73" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>For what deliberative assembly is there in the whole earth, whether great or little,
                which has not expressed that opinion of my exploits which is most desirable and most
                honourable for me? The greatest council of the Roman people, and of all peoples, and
                nations, and kings, is the senate. That decreed that all men who desired the safety
                of the republic should come forward to defend me alone, and showed its opinion that
                the republic could not have been saved if I had <pb n="35"/> not existed, and could
                not last if I did not return. <milestone n="74" unit="section"/> The next in rank to
                this dignified body is the equestrian order. All the companies of public contractors
                passed most favourable and honourable decrees respecting my consulship and my
                actions. The scriveners, who are much connected with us in matters relating to
                public registers and monuments, took good care that their sentiments and resolutions
                respecting my services to the republic should not be left in doubt. There is no
                corporation in all this city, no body of men either from the higher or lower parts
                of the city,<note anchored="true">The Latin is <foreign xml:lang="la">pagani aut
                        montani</foreign>, and whether it refers to portions of the city, or to
                    people in the suburban districts, Graevius professes himself quite ignorant,
                    saying that this is the only mention of such classes. Riddle translates it (v.
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">paganus</foreign>) “countrymen and mountaineers.” Yet
                    the next words, <foreign xml:lang="la">plebei urbanae</foreign>, seem to show
                    that they refer to some division of the citizens of the city itself.</note>
                (since our ancestors thought fit that the common people of the city should also have
                places of meeting and some sort of deliberative assemblies,) which has not passed
                most honourable resolutions, not merely respecting my safety, but relating also to
                my dignity. <milestone n="75" unit="section"/> For why need I mention those divine
                and immortal decrees of the municipal towns, and of the colonies, and of all
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, by which, as by a flight of
                steps, I seem not only to have returned to my country, but to have mounted up to
                heaven? And what a day was that when the Roman people beheld you, O Publius
                Lentulus, passing a law respecting me, and felt how great a man and how worthy a
                citizen you were. For it is well known that the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus
                    Martius</placeName> had never on any <foreign xml:lang="la">comitia</foreign>
                seen so vast a crowd, or such a splendid assembly of men of every class, age, and
                order. I say nothing of the unanimous judgment and unanimous agreement of the
                cities, nations, provinces, kings,—of the whole world, in short,—as to the services
                which I had done to the whole human race. But what an arrival at and entry into the
                city was mine! Did my country receive me as it ought to receive light and safety
                when brought back and restored to it, or as a cruel tyrant, as you, you herd of
                Catiline, were accustomed to call me? <milestone n="76" unit="section"/> Therefore
                that one day on which the Roman people honoured me by escorting me with immense
                numbers and loud demonstrations of joy from the gate to the Capitol, and from the
                Capitol home, was so delightful to me, that that wicked violence of yours which had
                driven me away appeared not to <pb n="36"/> be a thing from which I ought to have
                been defended, but one which it was worth my while even to purchase. Wherefore that
                calamity, if it deserves to be called a calamity, has put an end to the whole
                previous system of abuse, and has prevented any one for the future from daring to
                find fault with my consulship, which has now been approved of by such numerous, and
                such important, and such dignified decisions, and testimonies, and authorities.
                    <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And if, in all that abuse of yours, you not only impute no disgraceful conduct to me,
                but even add more lustre on my credit, what can exist or be imagined more senseless
                than you? For by one piece of abuse you admit that my country was twice saved by me;
                once when I performed that action which every one avows ought to be remembered for
                ever if it be possible, you thought that I ought to be punished and put to death; a
                second time, when I bore in my own person your own violence and that of the numbers
                who through your agency were inflamed against all virtuous men, in order to avoid
                taking arms, and in that condition bringing into danger that state which I had saved
                when without arms. </p>
            <p>Be it so then. <milestone n="77" unit="section"/> There was not in my case any
                punishment imposed for any offence. Still there was punishment imposed on me by a
                judicial decision. By what decision? Who ever examined me as a defendant under any
                law whatever? Who ever accused me? Who ever prosecuted me? Can then a man who is
                uncondemned be made to bear the punishment of a condemned man? Is this the act of a
                tribune of the people? Is this the act of a friend of the people? Although, when is
                it that a man can call himself a friend of the people, except when he has done
                something for the advantage of the people? Forsooth, has not this principle been
                handed down to us from our ancestors, that no Roman citizen can be deprived of his
                liberty, or of his status as a citizen, unless he himself consents to such a thing,
                as you yourself might learn in your own case? For, although in that adoption of
                yours nothing was done in a legal manner, still I suppose that you were asked,
                whether it was your object that Publius Fonteius should have the same power of life
                and death over you that be would have over an actual son. I ask, if you had either
                silenced it or had been silent, if, nevertheless, the thirty curies <pb n="37"/> had
                passed a vote to this effect would that vote have had the force off law? Certainly
                not. Why? Because the law was established by our ancestors, who were not
                fictitiously and pretendedly attached to the people, but were so in truth and
                wisdom, in such a manner that no Roman citizen could be deprived of his liberty
                against his consent. <milestone n="78" unit="section"/> Moreover, if the decemvirs
                had given an unjust decision to the prejudice of any one's liberty, they established
                a law that any one who chose might on this subject alone, make a motion affecting a
                formal decision already pronounced. But no one will ever lose his status as a
                citizen against his will by any vote of the people. <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"
                /></p>
            <p>The Roman citizens who left <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> and went
                to the Latin colonies could not be made Latins, unless they themselves promoted such
                a change, and gave in their names themselves. Those men who had been condemned on a
                capital charge, did not lose their rights as citizens of this city before they were
                received as citizens of that other city to which they had gone for the sake of
                changing their abode. Our ancestors took care that they should do so, not by taking
                away their rights of citizenship, but only their house, and by interdicting them
                from fire and water within the city. <milestone n="79" unit="section"/> The Roman
                people on the motion of Lucius Sulla, the dictator, in the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia centuriata</foreign>, took away the rights of citizenship from the
                municipal towns, and at the same time took away their lands. The decree about the
                lands was ratified, for that the people had power to pass; but their decree
                concerning the rights of citizenship did not last even as long as the disturbances
                of the time of Sulla. Shall we then say that Lucius Sulla, victorious as he was,
                after he had been restored to the republic, could not in the <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >comitia centuriata</foreign> take away the rights of citizenship from the
                people of Volaterra, even though they were in arms at the time;—and the Volaterrans
                to this day enjoy the rights of citizenship in common with ourselves, being not only
                citizens, but most excellent citizens too;—and allow that Publius Clodius, at a time
                when the republic was utterly overturned, could take away his rights as a citizen
                from a man of consular rank, by summoning an assembly, and hiring bands not only of
                needy citizens, but even of slaves, with Sedulius as their imputed leader, though he
                declares that on that day he was not in <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName> at all? <milestone n="80" unit="section"/> And, if he was not,
                    <pb n="38"/> what could be a more audacious thing than your putting his name to
                that bill? What could be more desperate than your condition, when, even if you told
                a lie about it you could not get up any more respectable authority? But if he was
                the first person who voted for it as he easily might have been, as he was a man who,
                for want of a house, slept all night in the forum, why should he not swear that he
                was at <placeName key="tgn,7002813">Cadiz</placeName>, when you have proved so very
                distinctly that you were at <placeName key="tgn,7009877">Interamna</placeName>? Do
                you, then,—you, a man devoted to the people,—think that our rights as citizens, and
                our freedom, ought to he established on this principle; so that when a tribune of
                the people brings forward a motion, “Do you approve and determine”<gap
                    reason="* * * *"/>if a hundred Sedulii should say that they do approve and
                determine, any one of us may lose our privileges? Our ancestors, then, were not
                attached to the interests of the people, who with respect to the rights of
                citizenship and liberty established those principles which neither the power of
                time, nor the authority of magistrates, nor the decisions of judges, nor the
                sovereign power of the whole people of <placeName key="perseus,Rome"
                    >Rome</placeName>, which in all other affairs is most absolute, can undermine.
                    <milestone n="81" unit="section"/> But you, also, you who take men's rights as
                citizens from them, have also passed a law with respect to public injuries in favour
                of some fellow of <placeName key="perseus,Anagnia">Anagnia</placeName>, of the name
                of Maerula, and he on account of that law has erected a statue to you in my house;
                so that the place itself, in hearing witness to your prodigious injustice, might
                refute the law and inscription on your statue. And that law was a much greater cause
                of grief to the citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Anagnia">Anagnia</placeName>
                than the crimes which that gladiator had committed in that municipal town.
                    <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="82" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>What shall I say, if there is nothing said about the rights of citizenship even in
                that very form of motion which Sedulius declares he never voted for? Do you still
                cling to his authority in order to throw a lustre on the exploits of your splendid
                tribuneship by the dignity of that man? </p>
            <p>But although you passed no law respecting me, to prevent my continuing not only in
                the number of Roman citizens, but even in that rank in which the honours conferred
                on me by the Roman people had placed me; will you still raise your voice to attack
                him whom after the abominable wickedness of the preceding consuls you see honoured
                by the decisions of the senate, of the Roman people, and of all <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>? whom even <pb n="39"/> at the time when I
                was departing you could not deny, even by your own law, to be a senator. For, where
                was it that you passed the law that I should be interdicted from fire and water?
                When Gracchus passed such a decree respecting Publius Popillius, and Saturninus
                respecting Metellus, and other most seditious men respecting other most virtuous and
                gallant citizens, they did not pass a decree that they had been interdicted, which
                could have been quite intolerable but that they should be interdicted. When did you
                insert a clause that the censor should not enter me on the rolls of the senate in my
                proper place? which is a clause in the law concerning every one who has been
                condemned when the interdict is being framed. <milestone n="83" unit="section"/> Ask
                this of Sextus Clodius the framer of your laws. Bid him come forward; he is keeping
                out of the way; but if you order him to be looked for they will find the man in your
                sister's house hiding himself with his head down. But if no one in his senses ever
                called your father a citizen—yes, by Jove, a good citizen, and one very unlike you,
                if no one I say, ever called him an exile, who, when a tribune of the people had
                proposed a bill against him, would not appear on account of the iniquity of that
                period of Cinna's triumph, and who, on that account had his command taken from him;
                if, I say, in his case, a punishment inflicted by law carried no disgrace with it,
                on account of the violent character of those times, could there, in my ease, be any
                penalty against me as if I had been condemned when I never was tried when I never
                was accused when I never was summoned by any tribune of the people, and, especially,
                a penalty which was not mentioned not even in the proposed bill itself? <milestone
                    n="32" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="84" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But just remark what the difference is between that most iniquitous misfortune
                inflicted on your father and between my fortune and condition which I am now
                discussing Lucius Philippus the censor, in reading the roll of the senate, passed
                over his own uncle, your father, a most excellent citizen; the son of a most
                illustrious man, himself a man of such severity of character that if he were alive
                you would not have been suffered to live. For he had no reason to allege why those
                acts should not be ratified which had been done in that republic in which, at that
                very time, he had been willing to take upon himself the office of censor. But as for
                me, Lucius Cotta, a man of censorian rank, said in the senate, on his <pb n="40"/>
                oath, that if he had been censor at the time that I left the city, he should have
                retained me on the list as a senator in my proper place. <milestone n="85"
                    unit="section"/> Who appointed any judge in my place? who of my friends made a
                will at the time that I was absent, and did not give me the same that he would have
                given me if I had been in the city? who was there, I will not say only among the
                citizens, but even among the allies, who hesitated to receive and assist me in
                defiance of your law? Lastly, the whole senate, long before the law was passed
                respecting me, “Voted, that thanks should be given to all those cities by which
                Marcus Tullius...” Was that all? No—it went, “a citizen who had done the greatest
                services to the republic, had been received:” and do you, one single pernicious
                citizen, deny that that citizen has been legally restored, whom the whole senate,
                even while he was absent, considered not only a citizen, but has at all times
                considered a most illustrious one? <milestone n="86" unit="section"/> But as the
                annals of the Roman people and the records of antiquity relate, that great man Caeso
                Quintius, and Marcus Furius Camillus, and Marcus Servilius Ahala, though they had
                deserved exceedingly well of the republic, still had to endure the violence and
                passion of an excited people; and after they had been condemned by the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign> and had gone into banishment, were
                again restored to their former dignity by the same people in a more placable humour.
                But if, in the case of those men who were thus condemned, their calamity not only
                did not diminish the glory of their most illustrious names, but even added fresh
                lustre to it; (for, although it is more desirable to finish the course of one's life
                without pain and without injury, still it contributes more to the immortality of a
                man's glory to have been universally regretted by his fellow-citizens: than never to
                have been injured;) shall a similar misfortune have in my case the force of a
                reproach or of an accusation, when I left the city without any sentence of the
                people, and have been restored by most honourable resolutions of every order of
                society? <milestone n="87" unit="section"/> Publius Popillius was always a brave and
                wise citizen in every point of view; yet in the whole of his life there is nothing
                which sheds a greater lustre on his character than this very calamity. For who would
                have recollected now that he conferred great benefits on the republic, if he had not
                been expelled by the wicked and restored by the good? The conduct of Quintus
                Metellus as a military commander was admirable, his censorship was splendid, his
                whole life was full of wisdom and dignity; and yet it is his calamity which has
                handed down his praises to everlasting recollection. <milestone n="33"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>But if the injury inflicted on them by their enemies was not any disgrace to those
                men who were expelled unjustly, but still who were restored according to law, after
                their enemies had been slain, after the tribunes had brought forward motions
                respecting them; not by the authority of the senate, not by the <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">comitia centuriata</foreign>, not by the decrees of all <placeName
                    key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, not by the universal regret of the state;
                do you think that in my case, who departed uncondemned, who departed at the same
                time as the republic, and returned with the greatest dignity, while you were still
                alive, while one of your brothers was one of the consuls who brought me back, and
                the other was the praetor who demanded my recall, your wickedness ought to be any
                discredit to me? And if the Roman people, being inflamed with passion or envy, had
                driven me out of the city, and afterwards, remembering my services to the republic,
                had recollected itself; and shown its repentance for its rashness and injustice by
                restoring me; yet, in truth, no one would have been so senseless, as to think that
                such conduct on the part of the people ought not rather to be considered an honour
                to me than a disgrace. <milestone n="88" unit="section"/> But now, when of all the
                people no one has accused me, when it is impossible for me to have been condemned,
                seeing that I have never been accused, since I was not even expelled in such a way
                that I could not have got the better of my adversaries if I had contested the point
                with them by force; and when, on the other hand, I have at all times been defrauded
                and praised and honoured by the Roman people; what pretence has any one for thinking
                himself better off than I am, at all events as far as the people are concerned?
                    <milestone n="89" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Do you think that the Roman people consists of these men who can be hired for any
                purpose? who are easily instigated to offer violence to magistrates? to besiege the
                senate? to wish every day for bloodshed, conflagration and plunder? people, indeed,
                whom you could not possibly collect together unless you shut up all the taverns; a
                people to whom you gave the Lentidii, and Lollii, and Plaguleii, and Sergii, for
                leaders. Oh for the splendour and dignity of the Roman people, for kings, for
                foreign nations, for the most distant <pb n="42"/> lands to fear; a multitude
                collected of slaves, of hirelings, of, criminals, and beggars! <milestone n="90"
                    unit="section"/> That was the real beauty and splendour of the Roman people,
                which you beheld in the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus Martius</placeName> at
                that time, when even you were allowed to speak in opposition to the authority and
                wishes of the senate and of all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>. That
                is the people—that, I say, is the people which is the lord of kings, the conqueror
                and commander-in-chief of all nations, which you, O wicked man, beheld in that most
                illustrious day when all the chief men of the city, when all men of all ranks and
                ages considered themselves as giving their votes, not about the safety of a citizen,
                but about that of the state; when men arrive into the Campus, the municipal towns
                having been all emptied, not the taverns. <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="91" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>By the aid of this people, if there had then been real consuls in the republic, or if
                there had been no consuls at all, I should without any difficulty have resisted your
                headlong frenzy and impious wickedness. But I was unwilling to take up the public
                cause against armed violence, without the protection of the people. Not that I
                disapproved of the late rigour of Publius Scipio, that bravest of men, when he was
                only a private individual; but Publius Mucius the consul, who was considered
                somewhat remiss in defending the republic, immediately defended, and, more than
                that, extolled the action of Scipio in many resolutions passed by the senate. But,
                in my case, I, if you were slain, would have had to contend by force of arms against
                the consuls, or if you were alive, against both you and them together. <milestone
                    n="92" unit="section"/> There were many other circumstances also to be feared at
                that time. The contest, would, in truth, have reached the slaves. So great a hatred
                of all good men had still got possession of the minds of impious citizens, being
                burnt as it were into their wicked minds by that ancient conspiracy. </p>
            <p>Here, too, you warn me not to boast. You say that those things are intolerable which
                I am accustomed to assert concerning myself; and being a witty man, you put on quite
                a polite and elegant sort of language. You say that I am accustomed to say that I am
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>; and also to make a frequent
                boast that Minerva is my sister. I will not so much defend myself from the charge of
                insolence in calling myself <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, as from
                that of ignorance in thinking Minerva the sister of
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>. But even if I do say so, I
                at all events claim a virgin for my sister; but you would not allow your sister to
                remain a virgin. Consider rather whether you have not a right to call yourself
                        <persName><surname>Jupiter</surname></persName>, because you have
                established a right to call the same woman both sister and wife. <milestone n="35"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="93" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And since you find fault with me for this, that you assert that I am accustomed to
                speak too boastfully of myself; I ask, who ever heard me speak in this way, or speak
                of myself at all, except when I was compelled, and was doing so of necessity? For
                if, when robberies, and bribery, and lust are imputed to me, I am accustomed to
                reply that the country was saved by my prudence, and labour, and personal danger, I
                ought not to be considered as boasting of my own exploits, so much as refusing to
                confess what is imputed to me. But if, before these most miserable periods of the
                republic, nothing else was ever imputed to me, except the cruelty of my conduct at
                that time when I warded off destruction from the republic, what will you say? Ought
                I when accused in this manner, not to have replied at all, or to have replied in an
                abject tone? <milestone n="94" unit="section"/> But I have always thought it for the
                interest of even the republic itself, that I should uphold by my language the
                propriety and glory of that most noble exploit which I performed by the authority of
                the senate, with the consent of all virtuous men, for the safety of my country;
                especially when I am the only person in this republic who have been able to say on
                oath, in the hearing of the Roman people, that this city and this republic had been
                saved by my exertions. That accusation of cruelty has long since been extinguished,
                because men see that I was regretted, and demanded and sent for back by the wishes
                of all the citizens, not as a cruel tyrant, but as a most merciful parent. Another
                charge has risen up. <milestone n="95" unit="section"/> That departure of mine from
                the city is attacked, which accusation I cannot reply to without the greatest credit
                to myself. For what, O priests, ought I to say? That I lied from a consciousness of
                guilt? But that which was imputed to me as a crime, not only was not a crime, but
                was the most glorious action ever performed since the birth of man. That I feared
                the sentence of the people? But not only was there no trial at any time before the
                people, but if there had been, I should have departed with redoubled glory. That the
                protection of the good was wanting to me? <pb n="44"/> It is false. That I was
                afraid of death? That is an assertion disgraceful to those who make it. <milestone
                    n="36" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="96" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I am therefore compelled to say that which I would not say if I were not compelled.
                (For I have never said anything at all in the way of extolling myself for the sake
                of gaining praise, but only with a view to repel an accusation.) I say, therefore,
                and I say it with the loudest voice I can command, when the inflamed violence of all
                the profligate citizens and conspirators, a tribune of the people being the leader,
                the consuls being their instigators, the senate being beaten down, the Roman knights
                being terrified, the whole city being in suspense and anxiety, was making an attack,
                not so much on me as, through me, on all good men—I say that I then saw that if I
                conquered, there would be but little of the republic left, and if I were conquered,
                none at all. And when I had decided that this would be the case, I lamented indeed
                my separation from my unhappy wife, the desolate state of my most beloved children,
                the distress of my most affectionate and excellent brother, who was away, and the
                sudden ruin of a family which had seemed so thoroughly established; but still I
                preferred to all these considerations the safety of my fellow-citizens, and I
                preferred that the republic should rather fall, if fall it must through the
                departure of one man, than through the slaughter of every one. I hoped (as indeed
                happened) that I, though overthrown, might be raised again by gallant men who were
                still alive; but I expected that if I perished, involving all virtuous men in my
                fall, I could not by any possibility be recovered. <milestone n="97" unit="section"
                /> I felt indeed, O priests, a great and incredible pain; I do not deny it; nor do I
                pretend to that wisdom which some expected of me, who said that I was too much
                dispirited and cast down. Could I, when I was torn from such a number and variety of
                enjoyments, (which I pass over, because even now I cannot speak of them without
                tears,) deny that I was a human being, and repudiate the common feelings of our
                nature? But in that case I should neither call that action of mine praise-worthy,
                nor should I say that any service had been done to the republic by me, if I had only
                given up, for the sake of the republic, those things which I could bear the loss of
                with calmness; and that firmness of the mind, resembling that hardness of body,
                which, even when it is burnt,<pb n="45"/> does not feel it, I should consider
                insensibility rather than virtue. <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="98" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>To encounter voluntarily such great grief of mind, and by oneself to endure, while
                the city is standing, those things which, when a city is taken, befall the conquered
                citizens; to see oneself torn from the embrace of one's friends, one's houses
                destroyed, one's property plundered; above all for the sake of one's country, to
                lose one's country itself to be stripped of the most honourable favours of the Roman
                people, to be precipitated from the highest rank of dignity, to see one's enemies in
                their robes of office demanding to conduct one's funeral before one's death has been
                properly mourned;—to undergo all these troubles for the sake of saving one's
                fellow-citizens, and this with such feelings that you are miserable while absent,
                not being as wise as those philosophers who care for nothing, but being as attached
                to one's relations and to oneself as the common feelings and rights of men
                require,—that is illustrious and godlike glory. For he who with a calm spirit for
                the sake of the republic abandons those things which he has never considered dear or
                delightful is not showing any remarkable good will towards the republic but he who
                abandons those things for the sake of the republic from which he is not torn without
                the greatest agony, his country is dear to that man and he prefers her safety to his
                affection for his own relations. <milestone n="99" unit="section"/> Wherefore that
                fury may burst itself; and it must hear me say these things since it has provoked
                me—I have twice saved the republic both when as consul in the garb of peace I
                subdued armed enemies, and when as a private individual I yielded to the consuls in
                arms. Of each piece of conduct I have reaped the greatest reward—I reaped the reward
                of my first achievement when I saw the senate and all virtuous men, in pursuance of
                a resolution of the senate, change their garments for the sake of my safety; and
                that of my subsequent conduct, when the senate, and the Roman people, and all men,
                whether in a public or a private capacity, decided that without my return the
                republic would not be safe. <milestone n="100" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>But this return of mine, O priests, depends now on your decision. For if you place me
                in my house, then I do plainly see and feel that I am restored, which is what all
                through my cause you have been always labouring to effect by your displays of zeal,
                by your counsels, and influence, and resolutions; <pb n="46"/> but if, my house is
                not only not restored to me, but is even allowed to continue to furnish my enemy
                with a memorial of my distress, of his own wicked triumph, of the public calamity,
                who is there who will consider this a restoration, and not rather an eternal
                punishment? Moreover, my house, O priests, is in the sight of the whole city; and if
                there remains in it that (I will not call it monument of the city, but that) tomb
                inscribed with the name of my enemy, I had better migrate to some other spot, rather
                than dwell in that city in which I am to see trophies erected as tokens of victory
                over me and over the republic. <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="101"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Could I have such hardness of mind or such shamelessness of eye, as to be able in
                that city, the preserver of which the senate has so often unanimously decided that I
                am, to behold my house thrown down, not by my own private enemy, but by the common
                foe, and then again built up and placed in the sight of the whole city, that the
                weeping of the virtuous citizens might know no cessation? The house of Spurius
                Maelius, who aimed at the kingdom, was razed. What else ensued? The Roman people by
                the very name of Aequimaelium, which they gave the place, decided that what had
                happened to Maelius was deserved; the punishment inflicted on his folly was
                approved. The house of Spurius Cassius was destroyed for the same reason; and on the
                same spot was built the temple of Tellus. The house of Marcus Vaccus<note
                    anchored="true">Vitruvius Vaccus (as Livy calls him) was the leader of the
                    Fundani in the war between <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> and
                        <placeName key="perseus,Privernum">Privernum</placeName>. He was taken
                    prisoner in <placeName key="perseus,Privernum">Privernum</placeName>, and put to
                    death. See <bibl n="Liv. 8.19">Livy, lib. viii. c. 19, 20</bibl>.</note> was in
                Vaccus's meadows, which was confiscated and destroyed in order that his crime might
                be kept alive in people's recollection by the name of the place. Marcus Manlius,
                when he had beaten back the attack of the Gauls from the Capitoline steep, was not
                content with the renown of his good deed; he was adjudged to have aimed at regal
                power, and on that account you see that his house was pulled down and the place
                covered with two groves. That therefore which our ancestors considered the greatest
                penalty which could be inflicted on wicked and infamous citizens, am I to undergo
                and to endure, so as to appear to posterity not to have been the extinguisher of
                conspiracy and wickedness, but its author and leader? <milestone n="102"
                    unit="section"/> And will the dignity of the Roman people, O priests, be able to
                support this stain of infamy and inconsistency, while the senate live, while you are
                the chief man of the public council, if the house of Marcus Tullius Cicero appears
                joined with the house of Fulvius Flaccus by the memory of a punishment publicly
                inflicted? Marcus Flaccus because he had acted with Caius Gracchus in a manner
                opposed to the safety of the republic, was put to death by the sentence of the
                senate, and his house was destroyed and confiscated, and on the spot Quintus Catulus
                some time after erected a portico out of the spoils of the Cimbri. But that
                firebrand and fury of his country, when, under those great generals Piso and
                Gabinius, he had taken the city, and occupied, and was in entire possession of it,
                destroyed the memorials of a most illustrious man who was dead, and united my house
                with the house of Marcus Flaccus, in order that he, after he had crushed the senate,
                might inflict on him whom the conscript fathers had pronounced to be the saviour of
                his country, the same punishment which the senate had inflicted on the destroyer of
                the constitution. <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="103"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But will you allow this portico to stand on the <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine
                    Hill</placeName>, and on the most beautiful spot in the whole city, erected as
                an everlasting token to keep alive the recollection of all nations and of all foes
                of the frenzy of the tribunes, of the wickedness of the consuls of the cruelty of
                the conspirators, of the calamity of the republic, and of my sufferings? A portico
                which, out of the affection which you have and always have had for the republic, you
                ought to wish to pull down, not only by your votes, but, if it were necessary, even
                by your hands. Unless, perchance, the religious consecration of it by that chastest
                of pontiffs deters any one. <milestone n="104" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>O that action, which careless men laugh at, but which graver citizens cannot hear of
                without the greatest indignation; has Publius Clodius, who removed religion even out
                of the house of the Pontifex Maximus,<note anchored="true">The Pontifex Maximus was
                    Julius Caesar; and it was in his house that the mysteries of the Bona Dea were
                    being celebrated when Clodius got access to it. On which account Caesar divorced
                    his wife Pompeia.</note> introduced it into mine? Do you, you who are the
                ministers of the religious ceremonies and sacrifices, admit this man to be an
                originator and regulator of public religion? O ye immortal gods! (for I wish you to
                hear these things), does Publius Clodius have the management of your sacred rites?
                Does he feel a reverent awe of your divine power? Is he a man who thinks that all
                human affairs are regulated by your providence? Is he not mocking the authority of
                all those eminent men who are here present? Is he not abusing your authority, O
                priests? Can any expression of religion escape or fall from that mouth? of religion,
                which with that same mouth you have most foully and shamefully violated, by accusing
                the senate of passing severe degrees about religion. <milestone n="40"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="105" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Behold, behold, O priests, this religious man, and if it seems good to you, (and it
                is only the duty of virtuous priests,) warn him that there are some fixed limits to
                religion that a man ought not to be too superstitious. Why was it necessary for you,
                O fanatical man, with an old woman's superstition, to go to see a sacred ceremony
                which was being performed at another person's house? And how was it that you were
                possessed with such weakness of mind as to think it not possible for the gods to be
                sufficiently propitiated, unless you intruded yourself into the religious ceremonies
                of women? Whom of your ancestors did you ever hear of, of those men who were
                attentive to their private religious duties, and who presided over the public
                priesthoods, who were present when a sacrifice was being offered to the Bona Dea? No
                one; not even that great man who became blind: from which it may be easily seen that
                in this life men form many erroneous opinions; when he, who had not knowingly seen
                anything which it was impious to see, lost his eye-sight; but in the case of that
                fellow, who has polluted the ceremonies, not only by his presence, but also by his
                incestuous guilt and, adultery, all the punishment due to his eyes has fallen on the
                blindness of his mind. Can you, O priests, avoid being influenced by the authority
                of this man, so chaste, so religious, so holy, so pious a man, when he says that he,
                with his own hands, pulled down the house of a most virtuous citizen, and with the
                same hands consecrated it to the gods? <milestone n="106" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>What was that consecration of yours? “I had carried a bill,” says he, “to make it
                lawful for me to act.” What? had you not inserted this clause in it, that if there
                was anything contrary to what was right in the bill, it should be invalid? Will you
                then, O priests, by your decision, establish the point that it is right that the
                home of every one of you, and your altars, and your hearths, and your household
                gods, should be at the mercy of the caprice of the tribunes? that it is right for
                any one, not only to throw down the house of that man whom he may have chosen to
                attack with a body of excited men, and may have driven away by violence,—which is an
                act of present insanity, like the effect of a sudden terror,—but for him to bind
                that man and property for all future time by the everlasting obligation of religion?
                    <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="107" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I indeed, O priests, have always understood that in undertaking religious obligations
                the main thing is to interpret what the intention of the immortal gods appears to
                be. Nor is piety towards the gods anything but an honourable opinion of their divine
                power and intentions, while you suppose that nothing is required by them which is
                unjust or dishonourable. That disgrace to the city could not find one single man,
                not even when he had everything in his power, to whom he could adjudge, or deliver,
                or make a present of my house; though he himself was inflamed with a great desire
                for that spot and for the house, and though, on that account alone, that excellent
                man had brought in that exceedingly just bill of his to make himself master of my
                property, yet even in the height of his madness he did not dare to take possession
                of my house, with the desire of which he had been so excited. Do you think that the
                immortal gods were willing to remove into the house of that man to whose labour and
                prudence it was owing that they still retained possession of their own temples,
                dismantled and ruined as it was by the nefarious robbery of a most worthless man?
                    <milestone n="108" unit="section"/> There is not one citizen in this numerous
                people, out of that polluted and blood-thirsty band of Publius Clodius, who laid
                hands on a single article of my property, or who did not in that storm defend it as
                if it had been his own. But they who caught the infection and polluted themselves
                with any partnership in the plunder, or in the purchase of anything, were not able
                to escape every sort of condemnation, whether public or private. Of this property
                then, of which no one touched a single thing without being accounted in every one's
                opinion one of the wickedest of men, did the immortal gods covet my house? Did that
                beautiful Liberty of yours turn out my household gods and the eternal divinities of
                my hearth, in order to be established there herself by you, as if in a conquered
                country? <milestone n="109" unit="section"/> What is there more holy, what is there
                more carefully fenced round with every description of religious respect, than the
                house of every individual citizen? here are his altars, here are his hearths, here
                are his household gods: here all his sacred rites, all his religious ceremonies are
                preserved. This is the asylum of every one, so holy a spot that it is impious to
                drag any one from it. <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>And on this account that man's madness is the more to be rejected by your ears who
                has not only attacked in a manner contrary to all religion those things which our
                ancestors intended to be safe and hallowed among us, as guarded by the sanction of
                religion, but has even made use of the name of religion to overturn them. </p>
            <p><milestone n="110" unit="section"/> And what goddess is she whom you have established
                there? She ought indeed to be the good goddess; since she has been consecrated by
                you. “She is Liberty,” says he. Have you then established her in my house whom you
                have driven out of the whole city? Did you, after you had denied that your
                colleagues,—men invested with the highest power,—were free; after you had closed all
                access to the temple of Castor against every one; after you had ordered in the
                hearing of the Roman people, this most illustrious man, of a most noble family, who
                has received the greatest honours from the Roman people, a priest, and a man of
                consular rank, a citizen of singular gentleness and modesty of character, (a man of
                whom I cannot sufficiently wonder how you can dare to look him in the face,) to be
                kicked and trampled on by your attendants; after you had driven him out of the city
                without being condemned, having proposed a most tyrannical <foreign xml:lang="la"
                    >privilegium</foreign> against him; after you had confined the first man in the
                whole earth to his house; after you had occupied the forum with armed bands of
                profligate men;—did you then place the image of Liberty in that house, which was of
                itself a proof of your most cruel tyranny and of the miserable slavery of the Roman
                people? Was he the man whom Liberty ought, of all men in the world, to have driven
                from his house, whose existence was the only thing that prevented the whole city
                from coming under the power of slaves? <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/><milestone
                    n="111" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But from whence was that Liberty brought? for I sought for her diligently. She is
                said to have been a prostitute at <placeName key="perseus,Tanagra"
                    >Tanagra</placeName>. At no great distance from <placeName key="perseus,Tanagra"
                    >Tanagra</placeName> a marble image of her was placed on her tomb. A certain man
                of noble birth, not altogether unconnected with this holy priest of Liberty, carried
                off this statue to decorate his aedileship. He had in truth cherished the idea of
                surpassing all his predecessors in the splendour of his appointments. Therefore he
                brought away to his own house, like a prudent man as he was, all the statues and
                pictures, all the decorations of any sort, that remained in the temples and public
                places, out of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and out of all the
                islands, for the sake of doing honour to the Roman people. <milestone n="112"
                    unit="section"/> After he understood that he might give up the aedileship, and
                still be appointed praetor by Lucius Piso the consul, provided he had any competitor
                whose name began with the same<note anchored="true">In voting at the election of
                    magistrates, the ballot tickets given to the voters were only marked with the
                    initial of each candidate's name.</note> letter as his own, he stowed away what
                he had prepared for his aedileship in two places, partly in his strong-box, and
                partly in his gardens. He gave the statue which he had taken from the prostitute's
                tomb to that fellow, because it was much more suited to such people as he is than to
                Public Liberty. Can any one dare to profane this goddess, the statue of a harlot,
                the ornament of a tomb, carried off by a thief; and consecrated by a sacrilegious
                infidel? Is it she who is to drive me from my house? Is she the avenger of this
                afflicted city? Is she to be adorned with the spoils of the republic? Is she to be a
                part of that monument which has been erected so as to be a token of the oppression
                of the senate, and to keep alive for ever the recollection of this man's infamy?
                    <milestone n="113" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>O Quintus Catulus! (Shall I appeal rather to the father, or to the son? The memory of
                the son is fresher, and more closely connected with my exploits.) How greatly were
                you mistaken when you thought that I should find the greatest possible reward—a
                reward, too, becoming every day greater in this republic when you said that it was
                impossible for there to be at the same time in this city two consuls hostile to the
                republic. Two have been found who gave over the senate bound hand and foot to a
                frantic tribune; who, by edicts and positive commands, prohibited the conscript
                fathers from entreating the people and coming to it as suppliants on my behalf; who
                looked on while my house was being sacked and plundered; who ordered the damaged
                relics of my property to be carried off to their own houses. <milestone n="114"
                    unit="section"/> I come now to the father. You, O Quintus Catulus, chose the
                house of Marcus Fulvius, though he was the father-in-law of your own brother, to be
                the monument of your victories, in order that every recollection of that man who had
                embraced designs destructive of the republic should be entirely removed from the
                eyes and eradicated from the minds of men if, when you were building that portico,
                any one had said to you that the time would come when that tribune of the people,
                who had despised the authority of the senate and the opinion of all virtuous men,
                should injure and overthrow your monument, while the consuls were not looking on
                only, but even assisting in the work, and should join it to the house of that
                citizen who as consul had defended the republic in obedience to the authority of the
                senate; would you not have answered that that could not possibly happen, unless the
                republic itself was previously overthrown? <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="115" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But remark the intolerable audacity of the man, and at the same time his headlong and
                unbridled covetousness. That fellow never thought of any monument, or any religion;
                he wished to dwell splendidly and magnificently, and to unite two large and noble
                houses. At the same moment that my departure deprived him of all pretence for
                bloodshed, he was begging Quintus Seius to sell him his house; and when he refused
                to do so, he threatened that he would block up all his lights. Postumus declared
                that as long as he was alive that house should never belong to Clodius. That acute
                young man took the hint from his own mouth, as to what was best for him to do; and
                in the most open manner he took the man off by poison. He bought the house, after
                wearying out all the other bidders, for almost half as much again as he thought it
                really worth. What is my object in making this statement. <milestone n="116"
                    unit="section"/> That house of mine is almost entirely empty; scarcely one-tenth
                part of my house has been added to Catulus's portico. The pretence was a promenade,
                and a monument, and that Tanagran lady Liberty, (all Roman liberty having been
                entirely put down). He had set his heart upon a portico with private chambers, paved
                to the distance of three hundred feet, with a fine court surrounded by a colonnade,
                on the <placeName key="tgn,3000935">Palatine Hill</placeName>, commanding a superb
                view, and everything else in character, so as far to surpass all other houses in
                luxury and splendour. And that scrupulous man, while he was both buying and selling
                my house at the same moment, still, even in a time of such darkness as that, did not
                venture to give in his own name as the purchaser. He put up that fellow Scato, a man
                whose virtue it was, no doubt, that had made him poor; so poor that among the Marsi,
                where he was born, he had no house in which he could take refuge from the rain and
                yet he said now that he had purchased the finest house on the <placeName
                    key="tgn,3000935">Palatine</placeName> hill. The lower part of the house he
                assigned not to his own Fonteian family, but to the Clodian family which he had
                quitted; but of all the numerous family of Clodius, no one applied for any share in
                his liberality except those who were utterly destitute from indigence and
                wickedness. <milestone n="45" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="117" unit="section"
                /></p>
            <p>Will you, O priests, sanction this universal and unprecedented tyranny of every sort,
                this impudence and audacity and covetousness? “Oh,” says he, “a priest was present.”
                Are you not ashamed, when the matter is being discussed before the priests, to say
                that a priest was present, not the college of priests? especially when, as tribune
                of the people, you had power to summon them and even to compel their attendance. Be
                it so. You did not call in the whole college. Well. Which of the college was it who
                was present? For he had vested that authority in one individual which belongs to all
                of them; however, the age and rank of the man invest him with additional dignity.
                There was need also of knowledge and although they were all of them learned men,
                still no doubt age gives them still more experience. <milestone n="118"
                    unit="section"/> Who then was it who was present? “The brother,” says he, “of my
                wife.” If we ask what was his authority, although he is of such an age that he
                cannot as yet have much, still even such authority as a young man can have is to be
                considered as diminished in his case, by reason of his near connection with and
                relationship to you. But if we ask what knowledge he has, who could have less than
                he who had only come into the college a few days before? And he was the more bound
                to you by your recent kindness to him, inasmuch as he had seen himself, the brother
                of your wife, preferred by you to your own brother. Although in that matter you took
                care that your brother should not be able to accuse you. </p>
            <p>Do you then call that a dedication, to which you were not able to invite the college
                of pontiffs, or any single priest distinguished by honours conferred on him by the
                Roman people nor even any other young man, though you had some most intimate friends
                in the college? He only was present, if indeed he was present, whom you yourself
                instigated, whom his sister entreated, and whom his mother compelled to be so.
                    <milestone n="119" unit="section"/>
            </p>
            <p>Take care now, O priests, what decision you give in this cause of mine, concerning
                the fortunes of all the citizens. Do you think that the house of every single
                citizen can be consecrated by the word of a priest, if he takes hold of a door-post
                and says something or other? But those dedications, and those religious ceremonies
                respecting temples and shrines, were instituted by our ancestors to do honour to the
                immortal gods, without inflicting any misfortune on their fellow-citizens. A tribune
                of the people has been found, who, assisted by the forces of the consuls, has rushed
                with all the violence of insanity on that citizen, whom, after he had been beaten
                down, the republic itself raised up again with its own hands. <milestone n="46"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="120" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>What next? Suppose any one like that fellow,—for there will not be wanting men who
                will be willing to imitate him,—should by violence oppress some one who does not
                resemble me, to whom the republic does not owe as much as it does to me, and should
                dedicate his house by the agency of one priest; will you determine by your authority
                that a deed done in that manner ought to stand? Will you say, “What priest will such
                a man be able to find?” What? Cannot a tribune of the people be himself a priest
                also at the same time? Marcus Drusus, that most illustrious tribune of the people,
                was a priest also. Therefore, if he had taken hold of a door-post of the house of
                Quintus Caepio his enemy, and had uttered a few words, would the house of Caepio
                have been dedicated to the gods? I say nothing here about the privileges of the
                priesthood, nor about the language of the dedication itself; <milestone n="121"
                    unit="section"/>I say nothing about religion, or religious ceremonies; I do not
                deny that I am ignorant of those matters, of which I should conceal my knowledge,
                even if I were acquainted with them, that I might not appear troublesome to others,
                and over curious to you; although many particulars of your usages do escape, and
                often reach the ears of the laity. I think, for instance, that I have heard that at
                the dedication of a temple, a door-post must be taken hold of. For the door-post is
                there where the entrance to the temple and its folding-door are. But no one ever
                took hold of the posts of a promenade in dedicating that; but if you have dedicated
                a statue or an altar, that cannot be moved from its place afterwards without
                impiety. But you will not be able now to allege this, since you have said that the
                priest did lay hands on the post. </p>
            <p>Although, why do I say anything about the dedication? or why do I discuss your right
                and the religious features of the case, contrary to my original intention?
                    <milestone n="47" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="122" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But, even if I were to allow that everything had been done with the regularities of
                expression, according to ancient and established usages, I should still defend
                myself by the common law of the republic. When, after the departure of that citizen,
                to whose single exertions the senate and all good men had so often decided that the
                safety of the state was owing, you, with the aid of two most wicked consuls, were
                keeping down the republic which was groaning under the oppression of your most
                shameful robberies; when you had dedicated, with the countenance of some obscure
                priest, the house of that man who was unwilling that the country which had been
                preserved by him should perish on any pretence connected with him; could the
                republic when it had recovered itself endure that? <milestone n="123" unit="section"
                /> Once, O priests, give an opening for such religious acts as this, and you will
                very soon find no escape at all for any one's property. If a priest has laid his
                hand on a door-post, and has transferred expressions intended for the honour of the
                immortal gods to the injury of the citizens, will the holy name of religion avail to
                procure the ratification of such an injury, and yet will it not avail if a tribune
                of the people consecrates the goods of any citizen with a form of words no less
                ancient and almost equally solemn? But Caius Atinius, within the recollection of our
                fathers, consecrated the property of Quintus Metellus, who, as censor, had expelled
                him from the senate (your grandfather, O Quintus Metellus, and yours, O Publius
                Servilius, and your great-grandfather, O Publius Scipio;) placing a little brazier
                on the <foreign xml:lang="la">rostra</foreign> and summoning a flute-player to
                assist him. What then? Did that frenzy of a tribune of the people, derived from some
                precedents of extreme antiquity, do any injury to Quintus Metellus, that great and
                most illustrious man? <milestone n="124" unit="section"/> Certainly not. We have
                seen a tribune of the people do the same thing to Cnaeus Lentulus the censor. Did he
                then at all bind the property of Lentulus to any peculiar sanctity? </p>
            <p>But why should I speak of other men? You yourself; I say, with your head veiled,
                having summoned an assembly, having placed a brazier on the spot, consecrated the
                property of your dear friend Gabinius, to whom you had given all the kingdoms of the
                Syrians, and Arabians, and Persians. But if nothing was really effected at that
                time, why should my property be affected by the same measures? if, on the other
                hand, that consecration was valid, why did that abyss of a man, who had swallowed up
                with you all the blood of the republic, raise a villa as high as the heavens on my
                Tusculan estate, out of the funds of the public treasury? And why have I not been
                allowed to look upon the ruins of my property,—I, who am the only person who
                prevented the whole city from being in a similar condition? <milestone n="48"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="125" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I say nothing about Gabinius. Why? Did not Lucius Munius,<note anchored="true">Some
                    editions read Mummius.</note> the most fearless and most excellent of all men,
                consecrate your property by your own precedent? And if, because you yourself are
                concerned, you say that that action ought not to be ratified, did you in that
                splendid tribuneship of yours establish laws which, the moment that they were turned
                against yourself, you repudiated, though you made use of them to ruin other people?
                If that consecration be legal, then what is there in your property which can be
                applied to other than holy uses? Or has a consecration no power, while a dedication
                draws with it the sanctions of religion? What then was the meaning of your summoning
                that flute-player to be a witness? What was the object of your brazier? What became
                of your prayers? What was the meaning of all your old-fashioned expressions? Did you
                wish to lie, to deceive, to abuse the divine reverence due to the immortal gods, in
                order to strike terror into men? For if that act is once ratified—I say nothing
                about Gabinius,—most certainly your house and whatever else you have is consecrated
                to <persName><surname>Ceres</surname></persName>. But if that was a joke of yours,
                what can be more impure than you who have polluted every sort of religion by lies
                and adulteries? <milestone n="126" unit="section"/> “Well, I confess,” says he,
                “that in the case of Gabinius I did behave wickedly.” You see now that the
                punishment which was established by you with reference to another has been turned
                against yourself. But, O man, O you who are the very model of every possible crime
                and wickedness, do you deny with respect to me that which you admit in the case of
                Gabinius,—a man the immodesty of whose childhood, the lust of whose youth, the
                disgrace and indigence of whose subsequent life, the open robberies of whose
                consulship, we have seen,—a man to whom even calamity itself could not happen
                undeservedly? Did do you? that that was a more solemn act which you performed with
                one young man alone for your witness, than it would have been if you had had the
                whole assembly in that character? “Oh,” says he, “a dedication is an act which
                carries the greatest possible quantity of sanctity with it.” <milestone n="49"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="127" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Does not Numa Pompilius appear to be speaking to you? Learn his speech by heart, O
                priests, and flamens. Do you too, O king of the sacrifices, learn of the man of your
                own family; although, indeed, he has quitted that family; but still learn from a man
                entirely devoted to religious observances, and just, and deeply skilled in all
                questions of religion. What? in the case of a dedication do not people inquire who
                says such and such a thing, and what he says, and how? Do you so confuse and mix up
                these matters, that whoever chooses can dedicate whatever he chooses, and in
                whatever manner he chooses? Who were you who performed the dedication? By what right
                did you do so? By what law? According to what precedent? By what power? When and
                where had the Roman people appointed you to manage that business? For I see that
                there is an old tribunitian law, which forbids any one to consecrate any house,
                land, or altar, without the order of the Roman people. Quintus Papirius, who
                proposed this law, did not perceive nor suspect that there would be danger lest
                hereafter the houses or possessions of citizens who had not been condemned might be
                consecrated. For that could not lawfully be done; nor had any one ever done such a
                thing; nor was there any reason why a prohibition should be issued, the effect of
                which appeared likely to be not so much to deter people from an action as to remind
                them of it. <milestone n="128" unit="section"/> But because buildings were
                consecrated,—I do not mean the licenses of private persons, but those which are
                called sacred buildings,—and because lands were consecrated, <pb n="58"/> not in
                such a way that any one who chose might consecrate our farms, but that a general
                might consecrate lands taken from the enemy; and because altars were erected, which
                carried with them a degree of sanctity to the place in which they were consecrated;
                he forbade all these things to be done unless the people ordered them. And if your
                interpretation of these edicts be that they were framed with reference to our houses
                and lands, I make no objection. But I ask, what law was passed that you should
                consecrate my house? where this power was given to you? and by what right you did
                it? And I am not now arguing about religion, but about the property of all of us;
                nor about the sacerdotal law, but about the common law. <milestone n="50"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>The Papirian law forbids any building to be consecrated without the command of the
                people. Grant that that law refers to our houses, and not to the public temples.
                Show me one word of consecration in that law of yours—if it is a law, and not merely
                an expression of your wickedness and cruelty. <milestone n="129" unit="section"/>
                But if then, at the time of that shipwreck of the republic, everything necessary had
                occurred to you, or if the man who drew that law for you at the time of that general
                conflagration of the state had not been making contracts with the Byzantine exiles
                and with the royal ambassadors, but had his mind at leisure to attend to (what I
                will not call the ordinances, but) the monstrous papers which he was drawing, then
                you would have done what you wanted, if not in fact at all events as far as regular
                legal language went. But at one and the same time bonds for money were being drawn,
                treaties with provinces were being entered into, titles of kings were being put up
                for sale, the numbering of all the slaves was going on over the whole city street by
                street enemies were being reconciled, new commands were being given to the Roman
                youth, poison was being prepared for that unhappy Quintus Seius, designs were being
                formed for assassinating Cnaeus Pompeius, the bulwark and protector of the empire,
                and to prevent the senate from having any power, and to cause the good to mourn for
                ever, and to reduce the captive republic, by the treachery of the consuls, to a
                state of subjection to the violence of the tribunes. When such numerous and such
                important designs were all on foot, it is no wonder, especially while you were both
                in such a state of frenzy and <pb n="59"/> blindness, that many things escaped both
                his notice and yours. <milestone n="130" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But take notice now, what the effect of this Papirian law is in such a case as this;
                not such a case as you bring forward, full of wickedness and frenzy. Quintus Marcius
                the censor had made a statue of Concord, and had erected it in a public place. When
                Caius Cassius the censor had transported it into the senate-house, he consulted your
                college, and asked whether there was any reason why he should not dedicate that
                statue and the senate-house to Concord. <milestone n="51" unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I beseech you, O priests, compare man with man, the one time with the other, this
                case with that case. The one man was a censor of the greatest moderation and of the
                highest character; the other was a tribune of the people, of preeminent wickedness
                and audacity. That period was one of tranquillity, when the people enjoyed a full
                measure of liberty, and the senate all its legitimate authority; but your time was a
                time when the liberty of the Roman people was oppressed, and when the authority of
                the senate was destroyed. <milestone n="131" unit="section"/> The proposed measure
                was one full of justice, wisdom, and dignity. For the censor, to whose power (though
                you have abolished that) our ancestors chose to commit the decision respecting the
                dignity of each member of the senate, wished the statue of Concord to be in the
                senate-house, and wished also to dedicate the senate-house to that goddess. It was a
                noble intention, and one worthy of all praise. For he thought that by that measure
                he was enjoining that opinions should be delivered without party spirit or
                dissension, if he bound the place itself and the temple of public counsel by the
                religions reverence due to the goddess Concord. You, when you were keeping down the
                enslaved and oppressed city by the sword, by fear, by edicts, by privileges, by
                bands of abandoned men constantly present, and by the fear of the army which was
                absent and by threats of bringing it up, and by the assistance of the consuls, and
                by your nefarious agreement with them, erected a statue of Liberty in a mocking and
                shameless spirit, rather than with even any pretence to religion. He was dedicating
                a thing in the senate-house, which he was able to dedicate without any inconvenience
                to any one. You have erected an image not of public Liberty, but of licentiousness,
                on what I may call the blood and bones of that citizen <pb n="60"/> who of all
                others has deserved best of the republic. <milestone n="132" unit="section"/> And
                moreover he referred his design to the sacred college: to whom did you refer yours?
                If you deliberated at all, if you had anything which you wished to expiate, or any
                domestic sacrifice which you desired to institute, still according to the ancient
                practice of other men you should have referred the matter to the priests. When you
                were beginning a new temple in the most beautiful spot in the city, with some wicked
                and unheard of object, did you not think that you ought to refer the matter to the
                public priests? But if you did not think it desirable to consult the whole college
                of priests, was there no single one of them who seemed to you a suitable man (of
                those who are eminent among all the citizens for age and honour and authority) for
                you to communicate your intention about the dedication to him? The truth was, not
                that you despised, but that you were afraid of their dignity. <milestone n="52"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>Could you have dared to ask Publius Servilius or Marcus Lucullus, (men by the
                assistance of whose wisdom and authority I as consul snatched the republic out of
                your hands, out of your jaws,) with what words or with what ceremony you could
                consecrate the house of a citizen? (that is my first point;) and in the next place,
                of that citizen, to whom the chief of the senate, to whom all ranks of men, to whom
                all <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, to whom every nation upon earth,
                bore testimony that he had saved this city and empire? What would you say, O you
                most wicked and mischievous disgrace to the city? <milestone n="133" unit="section"
                /> “Come forward, come forward, Lucullus, Servilius, while I dedicate the house of
                Cicero. Come, stand before me, and take hold of the door-post.” You are, in truth, a
                man of extraordinary audacity and impudence, but still your eyes, and countenance,
                and voice would have failed you while those men who, by their dignity, upheld the
                character of the Roman people and the authority of the empire, were striking terror
                into you by their dignified language, and saying that it would be impious for them
                to be present at your frantic deeds, and at such wicked and parricidal attacks on
                the country. <milestone n="134" unit="section"/> And when you saw this, then you
                betook yourself to your kinsman,—not that he was selected by you, but that he was
                left you by the rest. And yet I believe that he,—if he is really descended from
                those men who, it is traditionally reported, learnt their sacred ceremonies from
                Hercules himself; <pb n="61"/> after he had completed his labours,—would not have
                been so cruel with respect to the distress of a brave man, as with his own hands to
                place a tomb on the head of a man still living and breathing; as he either actually
                said and did nothing at all, and bore this as a punishment for the rashness of his
                mother, that he lent his presence though mute, and his name to this sin; or, if he
                did say anything in a few faltering words, and if he did touch the door-post with
                trembling hand, at all events he did nothing regularly or solemnly, nothing
                according to proper usages or established forms. He had seen Murena, his stepfather,
                the consul elect in company with the Allobroges, bring to me when I was consul the
                proofs of the conspiracy for the general destruction. He had heard from him that he
                had twice received safety from me, once as an individual, and a second time in
                common with the whole body of citizens. <milestone n="135" unit="section"/> Who is
                there, then, who can think that this new priest, performing this his first religious
                ceremony, and uttering these his first official words since his admission to the
                priesthood, would not have felt his tongue grow mute, and his hand grow torpid, and
                his mind become weakened and fail through fear; especially when out of all that
                numerous college he saw neither king, nor flamen, nor priest and was compelled
                against his will to become a partner in another's wickedness, and was enduring the
                most terrible punishment of his most disgraceful relationship? <milestone n="53"
                    unit="chapter"/><milestone n="136" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>But to return to the question of the vindication of the public rights, which the
                priests themselves have always adapted not only to their own ceremonies, but also to
                the commands of the people. You have a statement in your records, that Caius Cassius
                the censor consulted the pontifical college about dedicating the statue of Concord,
                and that Marcus Aemilius, the Pontifex Maximus, answered him on behalf of the
                college, that unless the Roman people had appointed him by name to superintend that
                business, it did not appear to them that the statue could properly be consecrated.
                What more? When Licinia,—a vestal virgin, a woman of the highest rank, and invested
                with the most holy of all priesthoods,—in the consulship of Titus Flamininus and
                Quintus Metellus, had dedicated an altar, and a little chapel, and a cushion at the
                foot of the sacred rock; did not Sextus Julius the praetor refer that matter to this
                college, in <pb n="62"/> obedience to the authority of the senate? when Publius
                Scaevola, the Pontifex Maximus, answered on behalf of the college, “that what
                Licinia, the daughter of Caius, had dedicated in a public place without the
                authority of the people, did not appear to be holy.” And with what impartiality and
                with what diligence the senate annulled that act, you will easily see from the words
                of the resolution of the senate. Read the resolution of the senate. [The resolution
                of the senate is read.] <milestone n="137" unit="section"/> Do not you see that a
                commission is given to the praetor of the city, to take care that that which she had
                consecrated should not be accounted holy? and that, if any letters had been engraved
                or inscribed upon it, they should be removed? Shame on the times, and on their
                principles! Then the priests forbade the censor, a most holy man, to dedicate it
                statue to Concord in a temple which had not been duly consecrated. And after that
                the senate voted that that altar, which had been consecrated on a most venerable
                spot, should be taken down in obedience to the authority of the priests, and did not
                permit any memorial of writing to exist as a relic of that dedication. You, O storm
                ravaging your country,—you whirlwind and tempest dispelling peace and
                tranquillity,—did you hope that the republic would endure what you (in the shipwreck
                of the state, when darkness was spread over the republic, when the Roman people was
                overwhelmed, when the senate was overturned and expelled,) pulled down and built up?
                what you, after having violated every feeling of religion, still polluted under the
                name of religion? that it would endure the monument of the destruction of the
                republic which you erected in the house of this citizen who is now speaking, and in
                the city which he had preserved by his own exertions and dangers, to the disgrace of
                the knights and the grief of all virtuous men; that it would endure the inscription
                which you had placed there after having erased the name of Quintus Catulus, one
                moment longer than the time that it was absent from these walls, from which it had
                been driven at the same time that I myself was? </p>
            <p>But if, O priests, you decide that no man who had a right to do so by law performed
                this dedication, and that nothing was dedicated which lawfully might be; then why
                need I prove that third point which I originally proposed to <pb n="63"/> establish;
                namely, that he did not dedicate it with those forms and words which such ceremonies
                require? <milestone n="54" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="138" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>I said at the beginning, that I was not going to say anything about your peculiar
                science; nor about the sacrifices, nor about the recondite laws of the priests. The
                arguments which I have hitherto advanced about the right of dedication, have not
                been drawn from any secret description of books, but are taken from common sources,
                from things openly done by the magistrates and referred to the sacred college, from
                resolutions of the senate, and from the law. Those inner mysteries, what ought to be
                said, or enjoined, or touched, or taken hold of are still your own. <milestone
                    n="139" unit="section"/> But if it were proved that all these things had been
                done in a manner equal to the knowledge of Coruncanius, who is said to have been the
                most experienced of priests; or if that great man Marcus Horatius Pulvillus, who
                when many men out of envy endeavoured to hinder his dedication by false pretences
                about religion, resisted them, and with the greatest firmness dedicated the Capitol,
                had himself presided at such a dedication as this, still I say that accuracy of
                religious observance would not hallow a wicked act; much less can that act have any
                validity which an unskillful young man, a new priest, influenced by the prayers of
                his sister and the threats of his mother, ignorant and unwilling, without
                colleagues, without books, without any adviser or assistant,<note anchored="true"
                    >“The Latin word <foreign xml:lang="la">fictor</foreign>, and the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">fictores</foreign> were among the regular attendants of the
                    priests their office appears to have been when there was a scarcity of victims
                    or when the worshippers could not afford living animals, to make sham figures in
                    flour and paste, or wax: they also made the cakes which were
                    offered.”—Graevius.</note> is said to have performed by stealth, with trembling
                heart and faltering tongue; especially when that impure and impious enemy of all
                religion, who in defiance of all that is right or holy had often been as a woman
                among men, and a man among women, completed the business in so hurried and
                disorderly a manner, that neither his senses, nor his voice, nor his language, had
                any consistency in them. <milestone n="55" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="140"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>It was then reported to you, O priests, and after that it became a common topic of
                conversation, how he, with preposterous language with ill-omened <foreign
                    xml:lang="la">auspices</foreign>, at times interrupting himself, doubting,
                fearing, hesitating, pronounced and <pb n="64"/> did everything in a manner wholly
                different from that which you have recorded as proper in your books. It is, indeed,
                not very strange that in doing an act of such wickedness and such insanity, even his
                audacity could not wholly repress his fear. In truth, if no robber was ever so
                savage and inhuman, as, when he had plundered temples, and then, having been excited
                by dreams or some superstitious feelings, consecrated some altar on a desert shore,
                not to shudder in his mind when compelled to propitiate with his prayers the deity
                whom he has insulted by his wickedness; what do you suppose must have been the
                agitation of mind of that plunderer of every temple, and of every house, and of the
                whole city, when he was consecrating one single altar to avert the vengeance due to
                his numberless acts of wickedness? <milestone n="141" unit="section"/> He could not
                possibly (although the insolence of power had elated his mind, and although he was
                armed by nature with incredible audacity) fail to blunder in his proceedings, or to
                keep constantly making mistakes, especially when he had a priest and teacher who was
                compelled to teach before he had learnt himself. There is great power, not only in
                the divinity of the immortal gods, but also in the republic itself. When the
                immortal gods saw the guardian and protector of their temples driven away in a most
                wicked manner, they were unwilling to quit their temples and to remove into his
                house. Therefore they alarmed the mind of that most insensible man with fear and
                anxiety. But the republic, although that was banished at the same time with myself,
                was still constantly present to the eyes of its destroyer, and from his excited and
                kindled frenzy was constantly demanding my restoration and its own. What marvel then
                is it, if he, urged on by the insanity of fear and drawn on headlong by wickedness,
                was neither able properly to perform the ceremonies which he had begun, nor to utter
                one single word in due order with proper solemnity? <milestone n="56" unit="chapter"
                    /><milestone n="142" unit="section"/></p>
            <p>And as this is the case, O priests, recall now your attention from this subtle
                argument of ours to the general state and interests of the republic, which you have
                before now had many gallant men to assist you in supporting, but which in this cause
                you are upholding on your own shoulders alone. To you the whole future authority of
                the senate, which you yourselves always led in a most admirable manner during the
                discussion of my case; to you that most glorious agitation <pb n="65"/> of
                    <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, and that thronging hither of all
                the municipal towns; to you the <placeName key="tgn,7006964">Campus
                    Martius</placeName>, and the unanimous voice of all the centuries, of which you
                were the chiefs and leaders; to you every company in the city every rank of men all
                men who have any property or any hopes, think that all their zeal for my dignity,
                all their decisions in my favour are not only entrusted, but put wholly under your
                protection. <milestone n="143" unit="section"/> Lastly the immortal gods themselves,
                who protect this city and empire, appear to me to have claimed the credit of my
                return and of the happiness which it has diffused as due to the power and judicial
                sentence of their priests in order to make it evident to all nations and to all
                posterity that I had been restored to the republic by divine agency. For this return
                of mine, O priests and this restoration consists in recovering my house, my
                possessions, my altars, my hearths, and my household gods. And if that fellow with
                his most wicked hands tears up their dwellings and abodes and with the consuls for
                his leaders, as if the city were taken, has thought it becoming to destroy this
                house alone, as if it were the house of its most active defender, still those
                household gods, those deities of my family, will be by you replaced in my house at
                the same time as myself. <milestone n="57" unit="chapter"/><milestone n="144"
                    unit="section"/></p>
            <p>Wherefore, O I pray and entreat you, O thou great God of the Capitol, thee whom the
                Roman people has styled, on account of your kindnesses to us, All Good, and, on
                account of your might All Powerful; and you, O royal Juno; and you, O guardian of
                the city, O Minerva, you who have at all times been my assistant in my counsels, and
                the witness of my exertions; and you too, you who above all others have claimed me
                back and recalled me, you, for the sake of whose habitations most especially it is
                that I am engaged in this contest, O household gods of my fathers, and of my family;
                and you too, who preside over this city and this republic, you do I entreat, from
                whose spires and temples I once repelled that fatal and impious flame, you too do I
                supplicate, O Vesta, whose chaste priestesses I have defended from the rage and
                frenzy and wickedness of men whose renowned and eternal fire I could not suffer
                either to be extinguished in the blood of the citizens or to be confused with the
                conflagration of the whole city, I entreat you all that,—<milestone n="145"
                    unit="section"/>if at that almost <pb n="66"/> fatal crisis of the republic I
                exposed my life, in defence of your ceremonies and temples, to the rage and arms of
                abandoned citizens; and it at a subsequent time, when the destruction of all good
                men was aimed at through my ruin, I invoked your aid, I recommended myself and my
                family to your protection, I devoted myself and my life, on condition that it both
                at that moment, and previously, and in my consulship, disregarding all my own
                advantage, all my own interests, and all reward for my exertions, I strove with all
                my anxiety and thoughts and vigilance for nothing but the safety of my
                fellow-citizens, I might be allowed some day or other to enjoy my country restored
                to me; but if my counsels had been of no service to my country, then, that I might
                endure everlasting misery, separated from all my friends;—I may be allowed to think
                this devotion of my life accepted and approved by the gods, when I am by your favour
                restored to my home. <milestone n="146" unit="section"/> For at present, O priests,
                I am not only deprived of my house, which you are at present inquiring into, but of
                the whole city, to which I appear to be restored. In the most frequented and finest
                part of the city, look to that (I will not say monument, but) wound of the country.
                And as you must see that that sight is to me one which is more to be detested and
                avoided than death itself; do not, I entreat you, allow that man by whose return you
                have thought that the republic too would be restored, to be deprived not only of the
                ornaments suited to his dignity, but even of his part in the city. <milestone n="58"
                    unit="chapter"/></p>
            <p>I am not moved by the plundering of my property, nor by the razing of my houses, nor
                by the devastation of my farms, nor by the booty most cruelly taken by the consuls
                out of my possessions. I have always considered these as perishable and fleeting
                gifts of fortune and of the times, and not as proofs of virtue or genius; and they
                are things, too, of which I have never thought it becoming to wish for plenty and
                abundance, so much as for moderation in enjoying them, and patience if deprived of
                them. <milestone n="147" unit="section"/> In truth, the moderate amount of my family
                property very nearly corresponds to my necessities; and I shall leave a sufficiently
                ample patrimony to my children in the name and memory of their father. But I cannot
                without great discredit to the republic, and great <pb n="67"/> shame and misery to
                myself, continue deprived of my house, which has been taken from me by wickedness,
                and, under pretence of religion, built up again with even more impiety than it was
                pulled down. </p>
            <p>Wherefore, if you consider that my return is pleasing and acceptable to the immortal
                gods, to the senate, to the Roman people, to all <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
                    >Italy</placeName>, to the provinces, to foreign nations, and to yourselves who
                have always taken the lead in and exercised a principal influence over all measures
                connected with my safety, I beg and entreat you, O priests, now, since it is the
                will of the senate that you should do so, to place me, whom you have restored by
                your authority and zeal and votes to my country, with your own hands in my house.
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
