<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>To the Citizens after his Return</title>
    <title>Three orations on the Agrarian law, the four against Catiline, the orations for Rabirius,
     Murena, Sylla, Archias, Flaccus, Scaurus, etc.</title>
    <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
    <author n="Cic.">M. Tullius Cicero</author>
    <editor role="editor" n="Yonge">C. D. Yonge</editor>
    <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
    <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
     <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
     <name>William Merrill</name>
     <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
     <name>David Smith</name>
    </respStmt>
    <funder n="org:NEH">National Endowment For The Humanities (NEH)</funder>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
    <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblStruct>
     <monogr>
      <author>M. Tullius Cicero</author>
      <title>The Orations of Marcus Tullius Cicero, literally translated by C. D. Yonge, B.
       A.</title>
      <imprint>
       <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
       <publisher>Henry G. Bohn, York Street, Covent Garden.</publisher>
       <date>1856</date>
      </imprint>
     </monogr>
    </biblStruct>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  
  <encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  
  <!--<encodingDesc>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Catil.;text=Agr.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
    <refState delim="." unit="chapter"/>
    <refState unit="section"/>
   </refsDecl>
   <refsDecl n="text=Corn.">
    <refState delim=" " unit="text"/>
    <refState unit="speech"/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>-->
  
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
    <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
   </langUsage>
  </profileDesc>
  
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2016-05-20" who="Lisa Cerrato">Review of EpiDoc and CTS work. Minor edits.</change>
   <change when="2016-03-17" who="Zach Himes">Changed section milestones to divs.</change>
   <change when="2015-12-13" who="Zach Himes">Cleaned up teiHeader. Converted to TEI P5 and EpiDoc.</change>
   <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
   <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
   <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">reverting texts back to pre_cts_reorg tagged version</change>
   <change when="2011-03-21" who="lcerrato">fixed typo in while to in which</change>
   <change when="2011-03-17" who="lcerrato">fixing gap tags against source</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
   <change when="2010-07-08" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
   <change when="2009-10-09" who="rsingh04">more reorganizing of texts module by collection</change>
   <change when="2009-09-22" who="rsingh04">fixed references to Cic. Ver.</change>
   <change when="2007-01-04" who="packel">fixed the refsDecls for Cornelius</change>
   <change when="2006-05-05" who="packel">fixed date tags</change>
   <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed thought you shall not perceive them to though...</change>
   <change when="2005-11-21" who="lcerrato">changed: does not the precaution taken of assembling the senate in thus most defensible place thus to this</change>
   <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
   <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
   <change when="2005-03-24" who="lcerrato">Marcus Aquillius changed to Manius Aquilius Agrarian 2.83</change>
   <change when="2005-03-23" who="lcerrato">changed Pro Font. 38 Marcus Aquillius to Manius Aquilius based on Latin and user report</change>
   <change when="2005-01-19" who="mimno">div1s missing type attributes</change>
   <change when="2004-06-14" who="lcerrato">changed Rob. Perd. 31 "heave" to "leave"</change>
   <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
   <change when="2001-03-14" who="lcerrato">changed ought to he to ought to be in first oration against Cataline</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">really fix language ids</change>
   <change when="2000-05-04" who="amahoney">fix language codes</change>
   <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
   <change when="2000-02-22" who="amahoney">fix a couple of broken bibl refs</change>
   <change when="1996-12-02" who="amahoney">replace the refsdecl, which disappeared somehow, and fix a couple of funny syntax errors</change>
   <change when="1996-11-30" who="lcerrato">revised and proofread again</change>
   <change when="1999-10-14" who="dasmith">Added explanatory subtitles to titleStmt</change>
   <change when="1999-09-01" who="dasmith">Removed tag from attribute value.</change>
   <change when="1999-08-12" who="dasmith">Fixed refsDecl</change>
   <change when="1997-11-07" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-10-31" who="textgod">Fixed typo.</change>
   <change when="1997-09-01" who="textgod">Added sections.</change>
   <change when="1997-08-18" who="textgod">Added to repository.</change>
   <change when="1997-07-14" who="DAS">ed.</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 
 <text xml:lang="eng">
  <body>
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:latinLit:phi0474.phi018.perseus-eng2" subtype="translation">

   <head>THE SPEECH OF M. T. CICERO AFTER HIS RETURN. ADDRESSED TO THE PEOPLE.</head>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="commentary" resp="editor">
   <head>THE ARGUMENT.</head>
   <p>The day after Cicero had addressed the preceding speech to the assembly, he returned thanks
    to the people also from the <foreign xml:lang="lat">rostra</foreign> for the zeal which they had
    displayed in his behalf, in the following speech; in which he dwells on very nearly the same
    topics as those which had been the groundwork of his oration to the senate.</p>
  </div>
   

   <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>That which I requested in my prayers of the all-good and all-powerful Jupiter, and the rest of
    the immortal gods, O Romans, at the time when I devoted myself and my fortunes in defence of
    your safety, and tranquillity, and concord,—namely, that if I had at any time preferred my own
    interests to your safety, I might find that punishment, which I was then encountering of my own
    accord, everlasting; but that if I had done those things which I had done out of an honest
    desire to preserve the state, and if I had undertaken that miserable journey on which I was then
    setting out for the sake of ensuring your safety, in order that the hatred which wicked and
    audacious men had long since conceived and entertained against the republic and against all good
    men, might break upon me alone, rather than on every virtuous man, and on the entire republic—if
    I say these were my feelings towards you and towards your children, that in that case, a
    recollection of me, a pity and regret for me should, at some time or other come upon you and the
    conscript fathers, and all Italy, I now rejoice above all things that that request is heard that
    I am bound to perform all that I then vowed, by the judgment of the immortal gods,—by the
    testimony of the senate by the unanimous consent of all Italy,—by the confession of my
    enemies,—by your godlike and never-to-be-forgotten kindness, O citizens of Rome. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2" resp="perseus"><p> For although there is nothing more to be wished for by <pb n="492"/> man
    than prosperous, equal, continual good-fortune in life, flowing on in a prosperous course,
    without any misadventure; still, if all my life had been tranquil and peaceful, I should have
    been deprived of the incredible and almost heavenly delight and happiness which I now enjoy
    through your kindness. What sweeter thing has been given to the race of man, or to each
    individual, by nature, than his own children? To me especially, mine, on account of my
    affectionate nature, and on account of their own excellent qualities, are dearer to me than my
    life. And yet I did not feel that pleasure when they were born, that I feel now when they are
    restored to me. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3" resp="perseus"><p> Nothing was ever more acceptable to any one,
    than my brother is to me. I was not so aware of this when I enjoyed his society, as I became
    when I was deprived of it, and after you again restored me to him and him to me. His own private
    estate is a pleasure to every one. The relics of my fortune, which I have recovered, give me now
    greater delight than they used to give when they were unimpaired. Friendship, familiar
    intercourse, acquaintance with my neighbours, the dependence of one's clients on one, even games
    and days of festival, are things the delights of which I have learnt to appreciate better by
    being deprived of them than I did while I was enjoying them. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4" resp="perseus"><p>
    And honour, dignity, my rank and order, and, above all, your kindness, although they at all
    times appeared to me most splendid possessions, yet, now that they are recovered, after having
    been lost, they appear more bright than if they had never been hidden from my sight. And as for
    my country, O ye immortal gods, it is scarcely possible to express how dear, how delightful it
    is to me. How great is the beauty of Italy! how renowned are its cities! how varied are the
    enchantments of its scenery! What lands, what crops are here! How noble is the splendour of this
    city, and the civilization of its citizens, and the dignity of the republic, and your majesty, O
    people of Rome! Even of old, no one took greater delight in all those things than I did. But as
    good health is more welcome to those who are just recovered from a severe illness than to those
    who have never been sick, so all those things, now that they have been once missed, delight me
    more than they did when enjoyed without interruption. </p></div><milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Why, then, am I making all those statements? To what purpose are they? I wish to make you
    understand that no man ever existed of such eloquence, or of such a god-like and incredible
    genius in oratory, as to be able (I will not say to exaggerate or embellish by his language, but
    even) to count up and describe the importance and number of the kindnesses which I, and my
    brother, and my children, have received from you. I (as was necessarily the case) was born of my
    parents but a little child; it is of you that I am born a man of consular dignity. They gave me
    a brother, without knowing how he would turn out; you have restored him to me after he has been
    tried and proved to be a man of incredible piety. I received the republic from them, when it was
    almost lost; I have recovered it by your means, after every one had acknowledged that it had
    been saved by the labours of one man. The immortal gods gave me children; you restored them to
    me. Besides these things, I have received many things which I wished for from the immortal gods;
    but if it had not been for your good-will, I should have lost all those divine gifts. Last of
    all, those honours which I obtained separately and step by step, I now receive again from you
    all together. So that all that we owed of old to our parents, all that we owed to the immortal
    gods, and all that we owed to you,—all that put together we now owe at this time to the entire
    Roman people.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> For as, in the case of your very kindness itself, its
    magnitude is so great that I cannot do adequate justice to it in my speech; so also in your zeal
    such great good-will and inclination towards me was displayed, that you seem not only to have
    taken my misfortune off from me, but even to have increased my dignity. <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For it was not my youthful sons and many other relations and kinsmen who offered up their
    prayers for my return, as they did for that of Publius Popillius, a most noble man. It was not,
    as it was in the case of Quintus Metellus, that most illustrious man, a son of an age fully
    proved by this time; or Lucius Diadematus, a man of consular rank and of the greatest authority;
    or Caius Metellus, a man of censorian rank; or their children; or Quintus Metellus Nepos, who at
    that time was standing for the consulship; or the sons of his sisters, the Luculli, the
    Servilii, and the Scipios;—for at that time there were many Metelli, or sons of the Metelli, who
    addressed supplications to you and to your fathers for the return of Quintus Metellus. And if my
    own preeminent <pb n="494"/> dignity and most glorious achievements were not of sufficient
    influence, still the piety of my son, the prayers of my relations, the mourning garb of all the
    young men, the tears of all the old, had power to move the Roman people to pity. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>For the case of Caius Marius, who, after those two most illustrious men of consular rank, is
    in the recollection of you and of your ancestors the third man of the same rank who, though a
    man of the most excessive renown, met with the same most unworthy fortune, was very dissimilar
    to mine. For he did not return because of the prayers that were offered for his return; but he
    recalled himself amid the discords of the citizens with an army and by force of arms. But it was
    the godlike and unheard-of authority and virtue of Caius Piso, my son-in-law, and of my most
    unhappy and admirable brother, and their daily tears and mournful appearance, which obtained my
    safety from you, though I was destitute of all other relations, fortified by no extensive
    connections, and by no fear of war or of disturbance. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8" resp="perseus"><p> I had
    but one brother to move your eyes by his mournful appearance, to renew your recollection of and
    your regret for me by his tears, and he had determined, O Romans, if you did not restore me to
    him to share my fortunes in exile. So great was his love towards me, that he thought it would be
    impious for him to be separated from me, not only in our abode in this life, but also in our
    tombs. In my behalf, while I was still present, the senate and twenty thousand men besides
    changed their apparel; for my sake, after I had departed, you saw only the mourning garb and
    misery of one man. He was the one individual who in the forum conducted himself towards me with
    the dutiful affection of a son; who, by his active kindness, might have been taken for my
    parent; who in love was, as he always has been, a real brother. For the mourning and grief of my
    unhappy wife, and the unceasing sorrow of my admirable daughter, and the regret and childish
    tears of my little son, were at times hidden from view by their necessary journeys, and to a
    great extent were confined in the obscurity of their dwelling. <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore your kindness towards us is so much the greater, in that you restored us not to a
    multitude of relations, but to ourselves.
    </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But, as I had no relations, since I could not make them for
    myself, to stand forward and avert my misfortune by their entreaties, on the other hand, (and
    that was no more than my virtue was entitled to procure for me,) I had so many men to urge and
    promote my restoration, that in the number of them and in the credit derivable from their
    numbers I far exceeded all those who had previously had a similar fate. Never was there any
    mention made in the senate of Publius Popillius, a most illustrious and gallant citizen; nor of
    Quintus Metellus, a most noble, wise, and consistent man; nor even of Caius Marius, the guardian
    of your state and of your empire. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10" resp="perseus"><p> Those, my predecessors in
    this fortune, were recalled by motions proceeding from the tribunes, and by no authority of the
    senate. But Marius was not only not restored by the senate, but through the ruin of the senate;
    nor was it the recollection of his mighty deeds that availed to further the return of Caius
    Marius, but his own arms and his warlike preparations. But in my case the senate always
    requested that its authority might prevail; and it brought about my effectual recall the very
    first moment that it was practicable, by the numbers in which it assembled, and by its
    legitimate authority. There were no commotions of municipal cities or colonies on their return.
    But as for me, all Italy three times recalled me by its decrees back to my country. They were
    restored after their enemies had been slain, and after a great slaughter of the citizens had
    taken place; I was brought back when those men by whom I had been driven out had obtained
    provinces, having as one of my enemies a most excellent and humane man, who, as one of the
    consuls, himself seconded the motion for my recall; and after my chief enemy, who had lent his
    voice to the common enemies of the country in order to injure me, was alive only as far as
    breathing went, but in reality was thrust down below even the dead. </p></div><milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Lucius Opimius, that most gallant consul never addressed either the senate or the people
    concerning Publius Popillius. Not only did Caius Marius, who was his enemy, never say a word to
    them about Quintus Metellus, but even the man who succeeded Marius, Marcus Antonius, a most
    eloquent man, and his colleague Aulus Albinus, both abstained from all mention of him. But the
    consuls of last year were continually urged to bring forward a motion in my case; but they,
    unwilling to appear to be doing so out of interested motives, (because the one was my kinsman,
    and I <pb n="496"/> had defended the other on a trial for his life,) and fettered by the
    agreement which they had made about the provinces, endured for the whole of that year the
    complaints of the senate, the grief of all good men, and the groans of Italy. But on the first
    of January, after the orphaned republic had implored the good faith of the consul as her
    legitimate guardian, Publius Lentulus, the consul, the parent and god of our safety, and life,
    and fortune, and memory, and name, as soon as he had discharged the solemn duties of religion,
    thought that there was no human business which ought to occupy him before mine. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12" resp="perseus"><p> And the affair would have been brought to its completion that very day,
    if that tribune <note anchored="true">His name was Serranus.</note> of the people on whom, when
    I was consul and he quaestor, I had heaped the greatest possible kindnesses, though the whole
    senatorial body, and Caius Oppius, his father-in-law, a most virtuous man, threw themselves in
    tears at his feet, had not required a night to consider of it; and that consideration was
    devoted, not to giving back the bribe which he had received, as some fancied, but as was
    afterwards discovered, to getting a larger one. After that, no other business was transacted in
    the senate, and as my recall was hindered by various maneuvers, still, as their inclination was
    plainly shown, the cause of the senate was brought before you in the course of the month of
    January. There was this difference between me and my enemies. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13" resp="perseus"><p>
    I, after I had seen men openly enrolled and registered in the centuries at the tribunal of
    Aurelius; when I understood that the ancient troops of Catiline had been recalled to hopes of
    massacre; when I saw that men of that party, of which I myself was accounted one of the chiefs,
    because some of them envied me, and some feared for themselves, were either betrayers or at
    least deserters of the cause of my safety; when two consuls, bought by an agreement respecting
    their provinces, had given themselves up to be leaders to the enemies of the republic, when they
    saw that their indigence, and their avarice, and their lusts could not be satisfied unless they
    gave me up bound hand and foot to the enemies of my country; when by edicts and positive
    commands they forbade the senate and the Roman knights to weep for me, and to change their
    garments, and address supplications to you; when the bargains made respecting all the provinces,
    when every sort of covenant made with every sort, of person, and the reconciliation of all
    quarrels and the treaties between all sorts of jarring interests, were being ratified in my
    blood; when all virtuous men were willing to die either for me or with me;—I was unwilling to
    take arms and fight for my own safety (as it was quite in my power to do,) since I thought that,
    whether I conquered or was defeated, it would be a grievous thing for the republic.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14" resp="perseus"><p><milestone unit="para"/> But my enemies, when my case was discussed in the month of
    January, having murdered many citizens, thought it worth while to prevent my return, even at the
    expense of causing rivers of blood to flow. <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Therefore, when I was absent, the republic was in such a state, that you thought that I and it
    were equally necessary to be restored. But I thought that there was no republic at all in a city
    in which the senate had no influence,—in which there was impunity for every crime,—where there
    were no courts of justice, but violence and arms bore sway in the forum,—where private men were
    forced to rely on the protection of the walls of their houses, and not on that of the laws,
    where tribunes of the people were wounded while you were looking on,—where men attacked the
    houses of magistrates with arms and firebrands, while the <foreign xml:lang="lat">fasces</foreign> of the consuls are broken and the temples of the immortal gods attacked by
    the incendiary. Therefore, after the republic was banished, I thought that there was no room for
    me in this city, and if the republic were restored, I had no doubt that it would bring me back
    in its company. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15" resp="perseus"><p> Could I doubt when I was perfectly certain
    that Publius Lentulus would be consul the next year, who in the most dangerous crisis of the
    republic had been curule aedile when I was consul, and had been, as such, the partner of all my
    counsels and the sharer of all my dangers, that he would use the medicine which was within reach
    of a consul to restore me to safety who was suffering under wounds inflicted by a consul? Under
    his guidance, and while his colleague, a most merciful and excellent man, at first abstained
    from opposing him, and afterwards cordially cooperated with him, nearly all the rest of the
    magistrates were advocates of my safety and among them were those men of indomitable courage, of
    the most eminent virtue, authority, vigour, and resources, Titus Annius and Publius Sextus, who
    showed the greatest good-will and the most energetic zeal <pb n="498"/> in my behalf; and when
    the same Publius Lentulus came forward as the prime mover of the bill, and his colleague agreed
    in the measure proposed, a most numerous senate, with only one dissenting voice, no one daring
    to intercede with his veto, did honour to my dignity in the most flattering language which it
    could find, and recommended my safety to you and to all the municipalities and colonies.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16" resp="perseus"><p> And so the consuls, the praetors, the tribunes of the
    people, the senate, and all Italy continually begged my safety from you, though I was destitute
    of relations, and not fortified by any extensive connections. Lastly, every one who was
    distinguished by any great kindnesses and honours from you, when they were brought before you by
    Italy, not only expected you to preserve me, but were the asserters, and witnesses, and
    panegyrists of all my exploits. <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>The chief of these men who came forward to exhort and to entreat you in my behalf was Cnaeus
    Pompeius, the greatest man of all who live, or who ever have lived, or who ever shall live, for
    virtue, and wisdom, and true glory; who, as a single man, has conferred on me, a single private
    individual, all the same benefits which he has conferred on the entire republic,—namely, safety,
    ease, and dignity. And what he said was, as I have understood, divided under three heads. In the
    first place, he told you that the republic had been saved by my counsels; and he connected my
    cause with the general safety; and he encouraged you to defend the authority of the senate, the
    constitution of the state, and the fortunes of a deserving citizen: and, in summing up, he laid
    it down that you were entreated by the senate, entreated by the Roman knights, entreated by all
    Italy: and, lastly, he himself did not only entreat you for my safety, but prayed to you in a
    most suppliant manner. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17" resp="perseus"><p> I owe this man, O Romans, such a debt
    as it is hardly right for one man to owe to another. You, following the counsels of this man,
    and the opinion of Publius Lentulus, and the authority of the senate, have replaced me in that
    position in which I had been through your kindness, and that by the votes of the same centuries
    by which you originally placed me there. At the same time you heard from the same place men of
    the greatest eminence—most accomplished and honourable citizens, the chief men of the city, all
    the men of consular rank, all the men of praetorian rank, say the same thing—that it was clear
    by the testimony of everybody, that the republic had been preserved by me alone. Therefore, when
    Publius Servilius, a man of the greatest dignity, and a most accomplished citizen, had said that
    it was through my labours that the republic had been handed over to the magistrates in a sound
    condition, all the rest declared their assent to that statement. But you heard at that time not
    only the authoritative declaration, but the sworn evidence of a most illustrious man, Lucius
    Gellius, who, because he was aware that his fleet had been tampered with, and that he himself
    had been in great danger, said in your assembly that if I had not been consul when I was, the
    republic would have been utterly destroyed. </p></div><milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>I now, O Romans, having been restored to myself, to my friends, and to the republic, owing to
    the evidence of so many men, by this authority of the senate—by such great unanimity of all
    Italy—by such great zeal on the part of all good men—by the particular agency of Publius
    Lentulus, with the cooperation of all the other magistrates—while Cnaeus Pompeius was begging
    for my recall, and while all men favoured it and even the immortal gods showed their approbation
    of it by the fertility and abundance and cheapness of the crops,—promise you, O Romans, all that
    I can do. In the first place, I promise that I will always feel that reverential attachment to
    the Roman people which the most religious men are accustomed to feel for the immortal gods, and
    that your deity shall for the whole of my life be considered by me equally important and holy
    with that of the immortal gods. In the second place, since it is the republic herself that has
    brought me back into the city, I promise that I will on no occasion fail the republic.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19" resp="perseus"><p> But if any one thinks that either my inclinations are
    changed, or my courage weakened, or my spirit broken, he is greatly mistaken. All that the
    violence, and injustice, and the frenzy of wicked men could take from me, it has taken away,
    stripped me of, and destroyed; that which cannot be taken away from a brave man remains and
    shall remain. I saw that most brave man, a fellow-citizen of my own municipal town, Caius
    Marius, since, as if by some fatal necessity, we both had not only to contend with those who
    wished to destroy all these things, but with fortune also—still I saw him, when he was in
    extreme <pb n="500"/> old age, with a spirit not only not broken on account of the greatness of
    his misfortunes, but even strengthened and refreshed by it. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20" resp="perseus"><p>
    And I heard him say that he had been miserable when he was deprived of his country which he had
    delivered from siege; when he heard that his property was taken possession of and plundered by
    his enemies; when he saw his young son a sharer of the same calamity; when, up to his neck in
    the marshes, he only preserved his body and his life by the aid of the Minturnensians, who
    thronged to the place and pitied him; when, having crossed over to Africa in a little boat, he
    had arrived as a beggar and a suppliant among those people to whom he himself had given
    kingdoms; but that now that he had recovered his dignity he would take care, as all those things
    which he had lost had been restored to him, still to preserve that fortitude of mind which he
    never had lost. But there is this difference between myself and him, that he used those means in
    which he was most powerful, namely his arms, in order to revenge himself on his enemies. I, too,
    will use the instrument to which I am accustomed; since it is in war and sedition that there is
    room for his qualities, but in peace and tranquillity that there is scope for mine. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21" resp="perseus"><p> And although he, in his angry mind, laboured for nothing but avenging
    himself on his enemies, I will only think of my enemies as much as the republic herself allows
    me. <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Lastly, O Romans, since they are altogether four classes of men who injured me,—one of them,
    those who were most hostile to me out of hatred to the republic, because I had preserved it
    against their will; another, those who most wickedly betrayed me under pretence of friendship; a
    third, those who envied my credit and dignity, because they, from their laziness, could not
    obtain the same honours; the fourth was composed of those men who, while they ought to have been
    guardians of the republic, sold (as far as was in their power) my safety, the constitution of
    the state, and the dignity of its empire; I will revenge myself on each class in proportion as I
    have been challenged by each—on wicked citizens, by conducting the republic successfully; on my
    perfidious friends, by trusting them in nothing, and taking every sort of precaution against
    them; on the envious, by obeying virtue and glory; on the buyers of provinces, by recalling them
    home, and by exacting from them an account of their conduct in those provinces. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Although I feel greater anxiety as to how I am to show my gratitude to you who have deserved
    excellently well of me than how I am to chastise the injustice and cruelty of my enemies. In
    truth the means of revenging an injury are easier than those of requiting a kindness; because
    there is less trouble in being superior to the wicked than in being equal to the good; and also
    because it is not so necessary to requite bad men as good men for what you are indebted to them.
     </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23" resp="perseus"><p> Hatred may either be appeased by entreaties, or may be laid
    aside out of consideration for the emergencies of the republic and the general advantage, or it
    may be restrained by the difficulty of avenging oneself, or it may be worn out by the antiquity
    of the injury which gave rise to it; but a man ought not to require to be entreated to show
    attention to virtuous men, <note anchored="true">The remainder of this sentence is given up by
     Manutius and Hottoman as hopelessly corrupt and unintelligible.</note>
    <gap reason="lost"/> Nor is the excuse of difficulty to be admitted; nor is it just to limit
    the recollection of a kindness to a certain time or to a fixed day. Lastly, he who is somewhat
    indifferent about seeking revenge is soon openly praised; but he is most exceedingly blamed who
    is in the least slow in requiting such benefits as you have showered on me; and he must
    inevitably be called, not only ungrateful, which itself is serious enough, but impious also. And
    the principle of requiting a kindness is different from that of repaying money; because he who
    keeps the money does not pay it, he who has repaid it has not get it; but in the case of
    gratitude, he who repays it still keeps it and he who keeps it pays it. </p></div><milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24" resp="perseus"><p>
   <milestone unit="para"/>Wherefore, I will cherish the memory of your kindness with undying affection, not only as long
    as I live and breathe, but even after I am dead, the memorials of your kindness to me shall
    still endure. And in showing my gratitude, this I do promise you, (and this I will always
    perform,) that diligence shall never be wanting to me in deliberating on the affairs of the
    republic, nor courage in repelling dangers from the republic, nor loyalty and honesty in plainly
    declaring my opinions, nor freedom in opposing men's inclinations when it is for the interests
    of the republic to do so, nor industry in enduring labour, nor the grateful zeal of my heart in
    promoting everything which may be advantageous to you. </p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25" resp="perseus"><p> And
    this care, O Romans, shall be fixed in my mind for ever, in order that I may appear, not only to
    you, who hold in my heart the power and divine character of the immortal gods, but also to your
    posterity and to all nations, to be entirely worthy of that state which, by the unanimous
    suffrages of its citizens, decided that it could not maintain its own dignity, unless it
    recovered me.</p></div> 
  </div>
 </body></text>

</TEI>
