<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to forty-five -
                    45</title>
                <title>literally translated, with notes and illustrations</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Titus Livius (Livy)</author>
                <editor role="translator">William A. McDevitte, Sen. Class. Mod. Ex. Schol.
                    A.B.T.C.D.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 1.4 Mb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <listBibl default="false">
                    <biblStruct default="false">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>Livy</author>
                            <title> History of Rome by Titus Livius, books thirty-seven to the end,
                                with the epitomes and fragments of the lost books </title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>literally translated, with notes and illustrations, by</resp>
                                <name>William A. McDevitte</name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>York Street, Covent Garden, London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Henry G. Bohn</publisher>
                                <publisher>John Child and son, printers, Bungay</publisher>
                                <date>1850</date>
                            </imprint>
                            <biblScope type="volume">4</biblScope>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="la">Latin </language>
                <language ident="fr">French </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>4/5/2006</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Gregory Crane</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>initial file </item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-10-09" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <pb n="2115" xml:id="p.2115"/>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="45" type="book">
                <head>BOOK XLV.</head>
                <argument>
                    <p> Perseus was captured by Aemilius Paulus in Samothrace. When Anti- ochus,
                        king of Syria, was besieging Ptolemy and Cleopatra, king and queen of Egypt,
                        and ambassadors were sent to him by the senate, to order him to desist from
                        besieging a king in alliance with Rome, on his being informed of the
                        mandates of the senate, he answered, that he would consider what line of
                        conduct he should adopt. Then Popilius, one of the ambassadors, described,
                        with his wand, a circle around the king, and ordered him to give a decided
                        answer before he passed it. By which decided conduct he compelled the king
                        to desist from the war. The embassies of the nations and king, that came to
                        congratulate the Romans, were admitted into the senate-house, with the
                        exception of the embassy from the Rhodians, which was excluded because their
                        feelings in that war were opposed to the Roman people. The next day, when
                        the question was put <quote>that war should be proclaimed against
                            them,</quote> the Rhodian ambassadors pleaded the cause of their country
                        before the senate, and were dismissed in a manner that rendered it uncertain
                        whether they were looked on as enemies or allies. Macedon was reduced to the
                        form of a Roman province. Aemilius Paulus triumphed; although his own
                        soldiers opposed him, because they were dissatisfied with their share of the
                        plunder, and Servius Sulpicius Galba spoke against him: Perseus and his
                        three sons preceded his triumphal chariot. Still the joy of this triumph was
                        not unmingled, for it was rendered remarkable by the death of his two sons:
                        one of whom died before his father's triumph; the death of the other
                        speedily followed. The ceremony of the conclusion of the census was
                        performed by the censors. Three hundred and twelve thousand eight hundred
                        and five citizens were enrolled. Prusias, king of Bithynia, came to Rome, to
                        congratulate the senate on the victory gained over Macedon; and committed
                        his son Nicomedes to the charge of the senate: being full of servility, he
                        called himself the freed-man of the Roman people. </p>
                </argument>
                <milestone n="1" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> ALTHOUGH Quintus Fabius, Lucius Lentulus, and
                    Quintus Metellus, who were sent with the news of the victory, made all possible
                    haste to Rome, yet they found rejoicings for that event anticipated there.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The fourth day after the battle with
                    Perseus, while games were exhibiting in the circus, a faint rumour spread itself
                    suddenly among the people through <pb n="2116" xml:id="p.2116"/> all the seats,
                        <quote>that a battle had been fought in Macedon, and that the king was
                        entirely defeated.</quote> The rumour gathered strength, until at last arose
                    shouting and clapping of hands, as if certain tidings of victory were brought to
                    them. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The magistrates were surprised, and
                    caused inquiry to be made for the originator of this sudden rejoicing;
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> but as none was found, the joy of course
                    vanished, since the matter was uncertain; yet the prestige of conquest still
                    remained impressed on their minds; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and when,
                    on the arrival of Fabius, Lentulus, and Metellus, the fact was established by
                    authentic information, they rejoiced on a twofold account, —on that of the
                    victory, and their happy presage of it. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This
                    exultation in the circus is related in another manner, with equal appearance of
                    probability: that on the fifteenth day before the calends of October, being the
                    second day of the Roman games, as the consul Licinius was going down to give the
                    signal for the race, a courier, who said he came from Macedon, delivered to him
                    a letter decorated with laurel. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As soon as he
                    had started the chariots, he mounted his own, and as he rode back through the
                    circus to the seats of the magistrates, showed to the people the embellished
                    tablets, at the sight of which the multitude, regardless of the games, ran down
                    at once into the middle of the area. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The
                    consul held a meeting of the senate on the spot; and after reading the letter to
                    them, by their direction told the people, before the seats of the magistrates,
                    that <quote> his colleague, Lucius Aemilius, had fought a general engagement
                        with Perseus; that the Macedonian army was beaten and put to flight;
                            <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> that the king had fled with few
                        attendants; and that all the states of Macedon had submitted to the Romans. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On hearing this, a universal shouting and
                    clapping of hands arose among the commons; and most of them, leaving the games,
                    hastened home to communicate the joyful tidings to their wives and children.
                        <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> This was the thirteenth day after the
                    battle was fought in Macedon. </p>
                <milestone n="2" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> On the following day a meeting of the senate
                    was held in the council-chamber, and a general supplication was voted, and
                    likewise a decree of the senate was passed, that the consul should disband all
                    his troops, excepting the legionary soldiers and seamen; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and that their disbandment should be taken into
                    consideration as soon as the deputies from the consul Aemilius, who had sent
                    forward the courier, should <pb n="2117" xml:id="p.2117"/> arrive in town.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> On the sixth day before the calends of
                    October, about the second hour, the deputies came into the city, and proceeded
                    directly to the tribunal in the forum, drawing after them, wherever they went,
                    an immense crowd, composed of those who went forth to meet and escort them.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The senate happened to be then in the
                    council-chamber, and the consul introduced the deputies to them. They were
                    detained there no longer than to give an account, <quote> how very numerous the
                        king's forces of horse and foot had been; how many thousands of them were
                        killed, how many taken; with what small loss of men the Romans had made such
                        havoc of the enemy, and with how small a retinue Perseus had fled;
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that it was supposed he would go to
                        Samothrace, and that the fleet was ready to pursue him; so that he could not
                        escape, either by sea or land. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> They were then brought out into the assembly
                    of the people, where they repeated the same particulars, and the general joy was
                    renewed in such a degree, that no sooner had the consul published an order,
                        <quote> that all the places of worship should <milestone n="7??"
                            unit="section"/> be opened, </quote> than every one proceeded, with as
                    much speed as he could use, to return thanks to the gods, and the temples of the
                    immortal gods, throughout the entire city, were filled with vast crowds, not
                    only of men, but of women. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The senate, being
                    re-assembled, ordered thanksgivings in all the temples, during five days, for
                    the glorious successes obtained by the consul Lucius Aemilius, with sacrifices
                    of the larger kinds of victims. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They also
                    voted that the ships, which lay in the Tiber fit for sea, and ready to sail for
                    Macedon, in case the king had been able to maintain the contest, should
                        <milestone n="10??" unit="section"/> be hauled up, and placed in the docks,
                    and that the seamen belonging to them should be discharged, after receiving a
                    year's pay; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and, together with these, all who
                    had taken the military oath to the consul; that all the soldiers in Corcyra and
                    Brundusium, on the coast of the Hadriatic and in the territory of Larinum, (for
                    in all these places had troops been cantoned, in order that the consul Licinius
                    might, if occasion required, take them over to reinforce his colleague,) should
                    be disbanded. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> The thanksgiving was fixed, by
                    proclamation in the assembly, for the fifth day before the ides of October, and
                    the five days following. </p>
                <milestone n="3" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Two deputies, Caius Licinius Nerva and Publius
                    Decius, arriving from Illyria, brought intelligence that the army of <pb
                        n="2118" xml:id="p.2118"/> the Illyrians was defeated, their king, Gentius,
                    taken prisoner, and all Illyria reduced under the dominion of the Roman people.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> On account of these services, under the
                    conduct and auspices of the praetor, Lucius Anicius, the senate voted a
                    supplication of three days' continuance, and it was accordingly appointed, by
                    proclamation, to be performed on the fourth, third, and second days before the
                    ides of November. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some writers tell us that
                    the Rhodian ambassadors, who had not yet been dismissed, were, when the news of
                    the victory was received, called before the senate in order to expose their
                    absurd arrogance. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On this occasion,
                    Agesipolis, their principal, spoke to this effect: that <quote> they had been
                        sent by the Rhodians to effect an accommodation between the Romans and
                        Perseus; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> because the war subsisting
                        between them was injurious and burdensome to all Greece, and expensive and
                        detrimental to the Romans themselves; but that fortune had acted very
                        kindly, since, by terminating the war after another manner, it afforded them
                        an opportunity of congratulating the Romans on a glorious victory. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This was the discourse of the Rhodians. The
                    senate returned the following answer: that <quote> the Rhodians had sent that
                        embassy, not through anxiety for the interests of Greece, or for the
                        expenses of the Roman people, but merely from their wish to serve Perseus.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For, if their concern had been such as
                        they pretended, they should have sent ambassadors at the time when Perseus,
                        leading an army into Thessaly, had continued, for two years, to besiege some
                        of the cities of Greece, and to terrify others with denunciations of
                        vengeance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> All this time not the least
                        mention of peace was made by the Rhodians; but when they heard that the
                        Romans had passed the defiles, and penetrated into Macedon, and that Perseus
                        was held enclosed by them, then they sent an embassy, from no other motive
                        whatever, but a wish to rescue Perseus from the impending danger. </quote>
                    With this answer the ambassadors were dismissed. </p>
                <milestone n="4" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> About the same time Marcus Marcellus, coming
                    home from Spain, where he had taken Marcolica, a city of note, brought into the
                    treasury ten pounds' weight of gold, and a quantity of silver, amounting to a
                    million of sesterces. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 8072 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While the consul, Paullus Aemilius, lay
                    encamped at Sirae, in Odomantice, as mentioned above, a letter from king Perseus
                        <pb n="2119" xml:id="p.2119"/> was brought to him by three ambassadors of
                    mean appearance, and it is reported that he, on looking at them, shed tears at
                    the uncertainty of the lot of man; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> because he
                    who, a short time before, not content with the kingdom of Macedon, had invaded
                    Dardania and Illyria, and had called out to his aid tile whole Bastarnian
                    nation, now banished from his kingdom after the loss of his army, was forced to
                    take refuge in a little island, where, as a suppliant, he was protected by the
                    sanctity of the place, not by any strength of his own. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> But when he read the address, <quote>King Perseus to the
                        consul Paullus, greeting,</quote> the folly of a man, who seemed insensible
                    to his condition, banished every feeling of compassion; <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> therefore, although there were, in the remaining part of
                    the letter, entreaties ill suited to royalty, yet the embassy was dismissed
                    without an answer and without a letter. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus felt that he must, now that he was conquered, forego the name of king,
                    and consequently sent another letter, inscribed simply with his name, in which
                    he made a request, and obtained it too, that some persons should be sent to him,
                    with whom he might confer on the state and condition of his affairs. <milestone
                        n="7" unit="section"/> Three ambassadors were accordingly despatched,
                    Publius Lentulus, Aulus Postumius Albinus, and Aulus Antonius; but nothing was
                    effected by this embassy, for Perseus clung with all the energy of despair to
                    the regal title, while Paullus insisted on an absolute submission of himself,
                    and every thing belonging to him, to the honour and clemency of the Roman
                    people. </p>
                <milestone n="5" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these things are going on, the fleet of
                    Cneius Octavius put in at Samothrace. When he also, by presenting immediate
                    danger to Perseus's view, was endeavouring at one time by menaces, at another by
                    hopes, to prevail on him to surrender; in this design he was greatly assisted by
                    a circumstance which may have occurred either by accident or design. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Lucius Atilius, a distinguished young man, observing
                    that the people of Samothrace were met in a general assembly, requested
                    permission of the magistrate to address a few words to them; which being
                    granted, he said, — <quote> People <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> of
                        Samothrace, our good hosts; is the account which we have heard true or
                        false, that this island is sacred, and the entire soil holy and inviolable? </quote>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> They all agreed in asserting the supposed
                    sanctity of the place; whereupon he proceeded thus: <quote> Why, <pb n="2120"
                            xml:id="p.2120"/> then, has a murderer, stained with the blood of king
                        Eumenes, presumed to profane it? And though, previous to every sacrifice, a
                        proclamation forbids all who have not pure hands to assist at the sacred
                        rites, will you, nevertheless, suffer your holy places to be polluted by an
                        assassin who bears the mark of blood on his person? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The story of king Eumenes having been nearly
                    murdered by Evander at Delphi, was now well known by report through all the
                    cities of Greece. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The Samothracians,
                    therefore, besides the consideration of their being themselves, as well as the
                    temple and the whole island, in the power of the Romans, were convinced that the
                    censure thrown on them was not unjust, and therefore sent Theondas, their chief
                    magistrate, whom they style king, to Perseus, to acquaint him, that <quote>
                        Evander the Cretan was accused of murder; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                        that they had a mode of trial established among them, by the practice of
                        their ancestors, concerning such as were charged with bringing impure hands
                        into the consecrated precincts of the temple. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> If Evander was confident that he was innocent of the
                        capital charge made against him, let him come forth, and stand a trial; but,
                        if he would not venture to undergo an inquiry, let him free the temple from
                        profanation, and provide for his own safety. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Perseus, calling Evander aside, advised him
                    not on any account to stand a trial, because he was no match for his accusers,
                    either in the merits of the cause, or in influence. He had secret apprehensions
                    that Evander, on being condemned, would expose him, as the instigator of that
                    abominable act. <quote>What then remained,</quote> he said, <quote>but to die
                        bravely?</quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Evander made, openly, no objection; but
                    telling the king that he chose to die by poison rather than by the sword, took
                    measures in secret for effecting his escape. When this was told the king,
                    fearing lest he should direct the anger of the Samothracians against himself as
                    accessory to the escape of a guilty person, he ordered Evander to be put to
                    death. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> No sooner was this rash murder
                    perpetrated, than the idea immediately struck his mind that lie had now drawn on
                    himself the whole of the guilt, which before had affected Evander only; that the
                    latter had wounded Eumenes at Delphi, and he had slain Evander in Samothrace;
                    and thus the two most venerable sanctuaries in the world had, through his means
                    alone, been defiled with human blood. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="2121" xml:id="p.2121"/> However, he avoided the imputation of this deed,
                    by bribing Theondas to tell the people that Evander had laid violent hands on
                    himself. </p>
                <milestone n="6" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But by such an atrocious act, committed on his
                    only remaining friend, on one whose fidelity he had experienced on so many
                    trying occasions, and who, in return for not proving a traitor, was himself
                    betrayed, he alienated the feelings of every one. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> All went over to the Romans as soon as they could, and
                    consequently obliged him, now left almost alone, to adopt the design of flying.
                    He applied to a Cretan, called Oroandes, to whom the coast of Thrace was well
                    known, since he carried on traffic in that country, to take him on board his
                    vessel, and convey him to Cotys. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> At one of the
                    promontories of Samothrace, is the harbour of Demetrium; there the vessel lay.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> About sun-set every thing necessary for
                    the voyage was carried thither, together with as much money as could be
                    transported with secrecy; and at midnight, the king himself, with three persons,
                    who were privy to his flight, going out through a back door into a garden near
                    his chamber, and having, with much difficulty, climbed over the wall, went down
                    to the shore. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Oroandes had set sail, at the
                    dusk of the evening, the very moment the money arrived, and was now steering for
                    Crete. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Perseus, after he could not find the
                    ship in the harbour, wandered about for a long time on the coast, but at last,
                    fearing the approach of day, and not daring to return to his lodging, he hid
                    himself in a dark corner at one side of the temple. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The royal pages was the name given among the Macedonians to
                    a band of the children of the leading noblemen, who were selected to wait on the
                    king: this band had accompanied Perseus in his flight, and did not even now
                    desert him, until a proclamation was made by the herald of Cneius Octavius,
                    that, <quote> if the <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> royal pages, and other
                        Macedonians, then in Samothrace, would come over to the Romans, they should
                        have impunity, liberty, and all their property, both what they had in the
                        island, and what they had left in Macedon. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On this notice they all passed over to the
                    Romans, and gave in their names to Caius Postumius, a military tribune. Ion of'
                    Thessalonica delivered up to Octavius the king's younger children also; nor was
                    any one now left with Perseus, except Philip, his eldest son. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Then, after uttering many execrations against fortune, and
                    the gods to whom the temple belonged, <pb n="2122" xml:id="p.2122"/> for not
                    affording aid to a suppliant, he surrendered himself and his son to Octavius,
                    who gave orders to put him on board the praetor's ship; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> the remainder of his money was put on board the same ship;
                    and the fleet immediately returned to Amphipolis. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Thence Octavius sent the king into the camp to the consul,
                    having previously sent forward a letter to inform him that he was a prisoner,
                    and on the road thither. </p>
                <milestone n="7" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Paullus, considering this a second victory, as
                    it really was, offered sacrifices on receiving the intelligence; then, calling a
                    council, and reading to them the praetor's letter, he sent Quintus Aelius Tubero
                    to meet the king; the rest he desired to remain assembled in the praetorium.
                    Never, on any other occasion, did so great a multitude gather about a spectacle.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> In the time of their fathers, king Syphax
                    had been made prisoner, and brought into the Roman camp; but, besides that he
                    could not be compared with Perseus, either in respect of his own reputation or
                    that of his country, he was at the time merely a subordinate party in the
                    Carthaginian war, as Gentius was in the Macedonian. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Whereas Perseus was the principal in this war; and was not
                    only highly conspicuous through his own personal renown, and that of his father,
                    grandfather, and other relations in blood and extraction, but of these, two
                    shone with unparalleled lustre, —Philip, and Alexander the Great, who made the
                    empire of the Macedonians the first in the world. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Perseus came into the camp, dressed in mourning, unattended
                    by any of his countrymen, except his own son, who being a sharer in the
                    calamity, made him more wretched. He could not advance on account of the number
                    of persons that had collected to see him, until the lictors were sent by the
                    consul, and they, after clearing the way, opened a passage to the praetorium.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The consul arose to do him honour, but
                    ordered the rest to keep their seats, and, advancing a little, held out his
                    right hand to the king, on his entrance; and raised him up when he endeavoured
                    to throw himself at his feet: nor would he suffer him to embrace his knees, but
                    led him into the tent, and desired him to sit on the side opposite to the
                    officers assembled in council. </p>
                <milestone n="8" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The first question asked Perseus was, <quote>
                        by what injuries had he been compelled to enter into a war against the Roman
                        people with such violent animosity, and to bring himself and his kingdom to
                        the extremity of danger? </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> While all expected <pb n="2123"
                        xml:id="p.2123"/> his answer, fixing his eyes on the ground, he wept a long
                    time in silence. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The consul, again addressing
                    him, said, <quote> If you had succeeded to the government in early youth, I
                        should have wondered less at your not being sensible of the great importance
                        of the friendship, or enmity, of the Roman people: <milestone n="4"
                            unit="section"/> but that was not the case, as you bore a part in the
                        war which your father waged with us, and, afterwards, must have remembered
                        the peace which we observed towards him with the strictest sincerity. What
                        then was your design in preferring war to peace, with those, whose power in
                        war and whose good faith in peace, you had so fully experienced? </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Neither questions nor reproaches could draw an
                    answer from him: on which the consul added, <quote> Howsoever these things may
                        have occurred, whether through the frailty of mankind, or accident, or
                        necessity, be of good spirits. The clemency of the Roman people, displayed
                        in the distress of numerous kings and nations, affords you not only hope,
                        but almost perfect confidence of safety. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> This he said in the Greek language to Perseus;
                    and then, turning to his own people, he said, in the Latin tongue, <quote> You
                        observe this striking instance of the instability of human affairs. To you,
                        young men, principally, I address the observation. In the hour of
                        prosperity, therefore, we ought to adopt against no man measures dictated by
                        either pride or violence, nor confide implicitly in present advantages;
                        since we know not what the evening may produce. <milestone n="7"
                            unit="section"/> He is really a man, whose spirit neither prosperity can
                        elate by success, nor adversity break by misfortune. </quote> On the
                    dismissal of the council, the charge of guarding the king is given to Quintus
                    Aelius. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Perseus was invited to dine that day
                    with the consul, and every other honour, which could be shown him under existing
                    circumstances, was paid to him. </p>
                <milestone n="9" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The troops were immediately sent off to their
                    winter cantonments. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Amphipolis furnished the
                    greater part with quarters, and the towns in that neighbourhood received the
                    rest. Thus ended the war between the Romans and Perseus, which had lasted,
                    without intermission, four years; and thus ended a kingdom, long renowned
                    through a great part of Europe, and throughout all Asia. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> From Caranus, who was their first king, they reckoned
                    Perseus the fortieth. Perseus came to the crown in the consulate of Quintus
                    Fulvius and Lucius Manlius, received the title of king from the senate in <pb
                        n="2124" xml:id="p.2124"/> that of Marcus Junius and Aulus Manlius, and
                    reigned eleven years. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The Macedonians were
                    little known by fame until the reign of Philip, son of Amyntas; although the
                    empire began to increase in his time, and through his agency, still it was
                    confined within the limits of Europe, extending over all Greece, with a part of
                    Thrace, and Illyria. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Afterwards the power of
                    Macedon poured down like a deluge on Asia, and in the course of the thirteen
                    years of the reign of Alexander, reduced under its dominion that almost immense
                    tract which had constituted the empire of the Persians. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Hence it overspread the Arabias and India, as far as where
                    the Red Sea forms the utmost boundary of the earth. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> At that time their empire and name were the first in the
                    world; but on the death of Alexander, it was torn asunder into a number of
                    kingdoms, whilst his successors, in the general scramble for power, dismembered
                    it by their struggles. From the time of its highest elevation to this its final
                    downfal, it stood one hundred and fifty years. </p>
                <milestone n="10" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the news of the victory, obtained by the
                    Romans, was carried into Asia, Antenor, who lay with a fleet of small vessels at
                    Phanae, sailed over to Cassandrea. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Caius
                    Popilius, who staid at Delos to protect the ships bound to Macedon, learning
                    that the war there was at an end, and that the enemy's fleet had left its
                    station, sent home the Athenian squadron, and proceeded on his voyage for Egypt,
                    to finish the business of the embassy with which he was charged, <milestone
                        n="3??" unit="section"/> in order that he might meet Antiochus before he
                    should approach the walls of Alexandria. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> When
                    the ambassadors, after sailing along the coast of Asia, arrived at Loryma, a
                    port somewhat more than twenty miles from Rhodes, and just opposite to that
                    city, some of the principal Rhodians (for the news of the victory had by this
                    time reached them too) met them, and requested them <quote> to sail over to
                        their city; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> that it was of the utmost
                        consequence to the character and safety of the Rhodian state that they
                        should, in person, inform themselves of what had been done, and what was
                        then passing at Rhodes; so as to carry to Rome intelligence, founded on
                        their own knowledge, and not on vague reports. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> After refusing for a long time, they were at
                    length prevailed on to submit to a short delay of their voyage, for the sake of
                    the safety of an allied city. When they came to Rhodes, the same persons, by
                    urgent entreaties, persuaded <pb n="2125" xml:id="p.2125"/> them to come into a
                    general assembly. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The arrival of the
                    ambassadors rather heightened, than allayed, the fears of the public. For
                    Popilius enumerated all the hostile expressions and actions, both of the
                    community and of individuals, during the war: <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    and, being naturally of an austere temper, he magnified the atrociousness of the
                    matters which he mentioned, by the sternness of his countenance, and the
                    harshness of his tone of voice; <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> so that, as he
                    had no cause of personal quarrel with their state, people judged from the
                    severity of one Roman senator, what was the feeling of the whole senate towards
                    them. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> The speech of Caius Decimius was more
                    moderate; for he said, <quote> that in most of the particulars mentioned by
                        Popilius, the blame lay, not on the nation, but on a few incendiary
                        ringleaders of the populace, who, employing their tongues for hire, procured
                        the passing of several decrees, full of flattery towards the king;
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and had sent those embassies, at
                        which the Rhodians should always feel not less shame than grief; all which
                        proceedings, however, if the people were disposed to act properly, would
                        fall on the heads of the guilty. </quote> He was heard with great
                    satisfaction; not only because he extenuated the offences of the community, but
                    because he threw the whole blame on the authors of their misconduct. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> When, therefore, their own magistrates spoke in
                    answer to the Romans, the speech of those who endeavoured to exculpate them, in
                    some <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> measure, from the charges advanced by
                    Popilius, was not so pleasing to them as the advice of those who concurred with
                    the opinion of Decimius, in the necessity of giving up the principal instigators
                    to atone for their crime. A decree was therefore immediately passed, that all
                    who should be convicted of having, in any instance, spoken or acted in favour of
                    Perseus, against the Romans, should be condemned to die. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> Several of those concerned had left the city on the arrival
                    of the Romans: others put an end to their own lives. The ambassadors staid only
                    five days at Rhodes, and then proceeded to Alexandria. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> Nor were the trials instituted, pursuant to the decree
                    passed in their presence, carried on at Rhodes with less activity; and this
                    perseverance of the Rhodians, in the execution of that business, was entirely
                    owing to the mild behaviour of Decimius. </p>
                <milestone n="11" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these events were going on, Antiochus,
                    after a fruitless attempt on the walls of Alexandria, had retired: <pb n="2126"
                        xml:id="p.2126"/> and being now master of all the rest of Egypt, he left, at
                    Memphis, the elder Ptolemy, whose restoration to the throne was the pretended
                    object of his armament, though, in reality, he meant to attack him, as soon as
                    he should have vanquished his competitors; and then he led back his army into
                    Syria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Ptolemy, who was not ignorant of his
                    intention, conceived hopes, that, while he held his younger brother under
                    terror, and in dread of a siege, he might be received into Alexandria, provided
                    his sister favoured the design, and his brother's friends did not oppose it.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Accordingly, he never ceased sending
                    proposals to his sister first, and his brother and his friends afterwards, until
                    he effected an accommodation with them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> His
                    suspicions of Antiochus were awakened by this circumstance, that, when he gave
                    him possession of the rest of Egypt, he left a strong garrison in Pelusium: a
                    plain proof that he kept that key of Egypt in his hands, in order that he might
                    be able, whenever he pleased, to introduce an army again into the country;
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and he foresaw, that the final issue of a
                    civil war with his brother must be, that the conqueror, thoroughly weakened by
                    the contest, would be utterly unable to contend with Antiochus. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> In these prudent observations of the elder brother, the
                    younger, and those about him, concurred; while their sister greatly promoted the
                    negotiation, both by her advice and entreaties. Accordingly, peace being made
                    with the approbation of all, the elder Ptolemy was received into Alexandria,
                    without any opposition even from the populace; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    who, during the war, had been severely distressed by a general scarcity, not
                    only in consequence of the siege, but from receiving no provisions from the rest
                    of Egypt after the enemy had retired from the walls. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> Although it was reasonable to suppose that Antiochus would
                    be rejoiced at these events, if he had really marched his army into Egypt for
                    the purpose of reinstating Ptolemy on the throne, —(the plausible pretext which
                    he had professed to all the states of Asia and Greece, in his answers to their
                    embassies, and in the letters that he wrote,) —yet he was so highly offended,
                    that he prepared to make war on the two brothers, with much greater acrimony and
                    fury of resentment than he had shown against the one. He instantly sent his
                    fleet to Cyprus; and, as soon as the spring appeared, he directed his route
                    towards Egypt at the head of his army, and advanced into Cœle- <pb n="2127"
                        xml:id="p.2127"/> syria. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Near Rhinocolura
                    he was met by ambassadors from Ptolemy, who gave him thanks, because through his
                    assistance he had recovered the throne of his fathers; and requested him to
                    secure to him the enjoyment of the benefit, which he had himself conferred; and
                    rather to signify what he wished to be done, than from an ally to become an
                    enemy, and proceed by force of arms. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> To this
                    he answered, that <quote> he would neither recall his fleet, nor stop the march
                        of his army, on any other conditions than the cession of all Cyprus and the
                        city of Pelusium, together with the lands adjoining the Pelusian mouth of
                        the Nile; </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and he even named a particular day, on or
                    before which he expected to receive an answer that these demands were complied
                    with. </p>
                <milestone n="12" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the time fixed for the suspension of
                    hostilities had elapsed, <hi rend="italics">Antiochus ordered the commanders of
                        his fleet</hi> to sail up the mouth of the Nile to Pelusium, while <hi
                        rend="italics">he himself entered Egypt,</hi> through the deserts of Arabia.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">He was amicably received by the people</hi> about Memphis, as
                    he was, afterwards, by the rest of the Egyptians; some being led by inclination,
                    others by fear; and he proceeded thus, by short marches, down to Alexandria.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The Roman ambassadors met him after
                    crossing the river at Eleusine, four miles from that city. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> On their approach he saluted them, and held out his right
                    hand to Popilius; but Popilius put into his hand a written tablet, containing
                    the decree of the senate, and desired him first to peruse that. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> On perusing it, he said, that he, after calling his friends
                    together, would consult on what was to be done; on which Popilius, with the
                    usual asperity of his disposition, drew a line round the king, with a wand which
                    he held in his hand, and said, <quote>Before you go out of that circle, give me
                        an answer to report to the senate.</quote> Astonished at such a peremptory
                    injunction, the king hesitated for some time; but at last replied, <quote>I will
                        do as the senate directs.</quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Popilius then thought proper to stretch out
                    his right hand to him; as to a friend and ally. <milestone n="7" unit="section"
                    /> Antiochus having retired out of Egypt, on the day appointed, the ambassadors,
                    after confirming by their influence the reconciliations between the brothers, as
                    concord was far from being established among them, sailed to Cyprus: from which
                    they sent home the ships of Antiochus, which had fought and defeated an Egyptian
                    fleet. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This embassy attracted a great share of
                    respect from all <pb n="2128" xml:id="p.2128"/> nations; because it had
                    manifestly rescued Egypt out of the hands of the Syrian, when he had it within
                    his grasp, and restored to the race of Ptolemy the kingdom of their forefathers.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> While one of the consuls of this year
                    distinguished his administration by a glorious victory, the reputation of the
                    other was thrown into the shade, because he had no opportunity of displaying his
                    talents. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> When, in the beginning of his
                    administration, he had appointed his troops to assemble, he entered the
                    consecrated place without due auspices; and the augurs, on the matter being laid
                    before them, pronounced the appointment improper. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Going into Gaul, he lay encamped near the long plains, at
                    the foot of the mountains Sicimina and Papirus, and passed the winter in the
                    same country with the troops of the Latin allies. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> The Roman legions staid all the while in the city, because
                    the day had been irregularly appointed for the meeting of the soldiers.
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The praetors went to their several
                    provinces, except Caius Papirius Carbo, to whose lot Sardinia had fallen; the
                    senate having commanded him to administer justice, at Rome, between natives and
                    foreigners; a duty to which he had been already named. </p>
                <milestone n="13" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Popilius, with his colleagues in the embassy
                    to Antiochus, returned to Rome, and gave information, that all disputes between
                    the kings had terminated, and that the army had marched out of Egypt into Syria.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Soon after, ambassadors arrived from the
                    kings themselves. Those of Antiochus represented, that <quote> their king had
                        considered a peace, which was agreeable to the senate, as preferable to a
                        victory, how complete soever, and had, accordingly, obeyed the order of the
                        Roman ambassadors, as implicitly as if it had been a mandate of the gods. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> They then offered his congratulations on their
                    victory, <quote>to which,</quote> they said, <quote> the king would have
                        contributed with <milestone n="4??" unit="section"/> his utmost power, if
                        any commands to that effect had been given him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The ambassadors of Ptolemy, in the joint names
                    of that prince and Cleopatra, presented their thanks, acknowledging that <quote>
                        they were more indebted to the senate and people of Rome than to their own
                        parents, more than to the immortal gods; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        since through their intervention they had been relieved from a most
                        distressing siege, and had recovered the kingdom of their fathers, when it
                        was almost entirely lost. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The answer given by the senate was that
                        <quote> Antiochus had acted rightly and properly, in complying <pb n="2129"
                            xml:id="p.2129"/> with the demand of their ambassadors; and that his
                        conduct was pleasing to the senate and people of Rome. </quote> To Ptolemy
                    and Cleopatra, king and queen of Egypt, they answered, that <quote> the senate
                        rejoiced very much, that any benefit or advantage had accrued to the
                        Egyptian monarchs, through their instrumentality; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> and would take care, that they should always have
                        reason to consider, that the strongest bulwark of their kingdom lay in the
                        protection of the Roman people. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Caius Papirius, the praetor, was commissioned
                    to send the usual presents to the ambassadors. <milestone n="10" unit="section"
                    /> A letter now arrived from Macedon, which doubled the public joy, as it
                    brought information that <quote>king Perseus was in the hands of the
                        consul.</quote> After the ambassadors were dismissed, a controversy between
                    deputies from Pisa and others from Luna came on; <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> the former, complaining that they were dispossessed of
                    their lands by the Roman colonists; while the latter insisted that the lands in
                    question had been marked out to them by the triumvirs. The senate sent five
                    commissioners to examine and fix the boundaries, Quintus Fabius Buteo, Publius
                    Cornelius Blasio, Tiberius Sempronius Musca, Lucius Naevius Balbus, and Caius
                    Apuleius Saturninus. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> A joint embassy from the
                    three brothers, Eumenes, Attalus, and Athenaeus, came with congratulations on
                    the victory; and Masgaba, son of king Masinissa, having landed at Puteoli,
                    Lucius Manlius, the quaestor, was immediately despatched with money to meet him,
                    and conduct him to Rome at the public expense. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                    /> An audience of the senate was immediately given him on his arrival. This
                    young prince spoke in such a manner that he made services, which were
                    meritorious in themselves, still more gratifying. He recounted what numbers of
                    foot and horse, how many elephants, and what quantities of corn his father had
                    sent into Macedon in aid of the Romans during the last four years. <milestone
                        n="14" unit="section"/>
                    <quote>But there were two things,</quote> he said, <quote> that made him blush;
                        one, the senate having sent by their ambassadors a request, instead of an
                        order, to furnish necessaries for their army; the other, their having sent
                        money in payment for the corn. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Masinissa
                        well remembered that the kingdom which he held had been acquired, and
                        increased, and multiplied by the Roman people; and contenting himself with
                        the management of it, acknowledged the right and sovereignty to be vested in
                        those who granted it to him. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> It was just,
                            <pb n="2130" xml:id="p.2130"/> therefore, to take, and not to ask from
                        him nor purchase, any of the produce of lands made over by themselves.
                        Whatever remained, after supplying the Roman people, would be fully
                        sufficient for Masinissa. </quote>
                    <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> That with these instructions he parted with
                    his father; but he was afterwards overtaken by some horsemen, who announced to
                    him the conquest of Macedon, with directions to congratulate the senate, and
                    acquaint them that his father felt so much joy at that circumstance, that he
                    wished to come to Rome, and in the Capitol to offer thanks to Jupiter supremely
                    good and great. He requested, therefore, that if it were not disagreeable, the
                    senate would give him permission to do so. </p>
                <milestone n="14" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Masgaba was answered, that <quote> his father,
                        Masinissa, acted as became a prince of a benevolent and grateful
                        disposition; to such a degree that, by acknowledging the kindness of his
                        friends, he added value and dignity to it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                        The Roman people had been assisted by him in the Carthaginian war with
                        exertions at once faithful and brave; by the favour of the Roman people he
                        had obtained his kingdom, and had afterwards, in the successive wars with
                        the three kings, discharged with his usual readiness every duty. That it was
                        not surprising, that a king who had so intimately blended his own interests,
                        and those of his kingdom, with the interests of the Romans, should be
                        delighted at the victory of the Roman people. <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> That he should return thanks to the immortal gods for
                        the victory of the Roman people, before the tutelary deities of his family;
                        that his son could return thanks in his stead at Rome; as he had already
                        said enough in the way of congratulation, both in his own name and in his
                        father's. But that the senate were of opinion, that his leaving his own
                        kingdom, and going out of Africa, besides being inconvenient to himself, was
                        detrimental to the Roman people. </quote> On Masgaba making a request that
                    Hanno, son of Hamilcar, <hi rend="italics">might be brought to Rome as a</hi>
                    hostage in the place <hi rend="italics"> of some other, the senate replied, that
                        they could not reasonably require hostages from the Carthaginians, at the
                        choice of any other person. </hi>
                    <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The quaestor was ordered, by a vote of the
                    senate, to purchase presents for the young prince to the value of one hundred
                    pounds' weight of silver, to accompany him to Puteoli, to defray all his
                    expenses while he staid in Italy, and to hire two ships to carry him and the
                    retinue of the king to Africa; <pb n="2131" xml:id="p.2131"/> clothes were given
                    to every one of his attendants, both freemen and slaves. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Soon after this a letter was brought concerning Masinissa's
                    other son, Misagenes, stating that, after the conquest of Perseus, he was sent
                    by Lucius Paullus, with his horsemen, to Africa; and that while he was on his
                    voyage in the Adriatic Sea, his fleet was dispersed, and himself, in a bad state
                    of health, driven into Brundusium with only three ships. Lucius Stertinius, the
                    quaestor, was sent to him to Brundusium, with presents of the same kind as those
                    given to his brother at Rome, and he was ordered to provide lodgings for the
                    prince and his retinue, and <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Crevier
                        supplement: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                        <quote>
                            <p> every thing necessary for his health and convenience; and that the
                                expenses of himself and his en- tire retinue should be paid
                                liberally; that he should look out for ships by which the prince
                                might pass over into Africa with ease and safety. The quaestor was
                                ordered to give to each of the horsemen a pound of silver, and five
                                hundred sesterces. The assemblies, for the election of consuls for
                                the ensuing year, were held by Caius Licinius the consul. Quintus
                                Aelius Paetus, Marcus Junius Pennus, were appointed consuls. Then
                                Quintus Cassius Longinus, Manius Juventius Thalna, Ti- berius
                                Claudius Nero, Aulus Manlius Torquatus, Cneius Fulvius Gillo, C.
                                Licinius <milestone n="7??" unit="section"/> Nerva, were made
                                praetors. In the same year the censors, Tiberius Sempronius Gracchus
                                and Caius Claudius Pulcher, at length united in passing <milestone
                                    n="8??" unit="section"/> a decree on a matter, which had been
                                for a long time discussed among themselves in different disputes.
                                Gracchus, when the freed- men, after being repeatedly confined
                                within the four city tribes, had once more spread themselves through
                                them all, wished to pluck up by the root the evil which was alway
                                send- ing fresh shoots, and to exclude from enrolment all who had
                                ever been slaves. Claudius struggled energetically against him, and
                                made frequent references to the institutions of their ancestors, who
                                had often tried to restrain the freed-men, but never to totally
                                exclude them from the rights of citizens. He said that some
                                relaxation of the former strictness had been conceded even by the
                                censors, Caius Flaminius and Lucius Aemilius. And <milestone n="9??"
                                    unit="section"/> indeed, although even at that time those dregs
                                of the people had spread themselves through all the tribes, and it
                                appeared requisite to reduce them again within what might be
                                considered their original settlement, still at the time some
                                important concessions were made to several of that rank. </p>
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="2132" xml:id="p.2132"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="15" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <hi rend="italics">For by those censors</hi> the freed-men were enrolled in the
                    four city tribes, excepting such as had a son more than five years old, who was
                    their own offspring; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> all these the censors
                    ordered to be surveyed in the tribe wherein they had been surveyed within the
                    last five years; and such as had a farm, or farms, in the country, exceeding in
                    value thirty thousand sesterces, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 242
                            <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 3 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> were allowed the privilege of being included in the country tribes.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Though this reservation was made in their
                    favour, yet Claudius still insisted, that <quote> a censor could not, without an
                        order of the people, take away from any man, and much less from a whole
                        class of men, the right of suffrage. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For
                        though he can remove a man from his tribe, which is nothing more than
                        ordering him to change it, yet he cannot, therefore, remove him out of all
                        the thirty-five tribes; which would be to strip him of the rights of a
                        citizen, and of liberty; not to fix where he should be surveyed, but to
                        exclude him from the survey. </quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> These points were discussed by the censors,
                    who at last came to this compromise: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> that out
                    of the four city tribes, they should openly, in the court of the temple of
                    Liberty, select one by lot, in which they should include all those who had ever
                    been in servitude. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The lot fell on the
                    Aesquiline tribe; on which Tiberius Gracchus published an order, that all sons
                    of freed-men should be surveyed in that tribe. This proceeding gained the
                    censors great honour with the senate, who gave thanks to Sempronius for his
                    perseverance in so good a design, and also to Claudius for not obstructing it.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Greater numbers were expelled from the
                    senate, and ordered to sell their horses, by them than by their predecessors.
                    They both concurred in removing from their tribes and disfranchising the same
                    persons, in every instance; nor did one of them remove any mark of disgrace
                    inflicted by the other. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> They petitioned that,
                    according to custom, the year and half's time allowed for enforcing the repairs
                    of buildings, and for approving the execution of works contracted for, should be
                    prolonged; but Cneius Tremellius, a tribune, protested against it, because he
                    had not been chosen into the senate. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> This
                    year Caius Cicereius dedicated a temple to Juno Monita on the Alban mount, five
                    years after he had vowed it; and Lucius Postumius Albinus was inaugurated flamen
                    of Mars. </p>
                <milestone n="16" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls, Quintius Aelius and Marcus
                    Junius, hav- <pb n="2133" xml:id="p.2133"/> ing proposed the business of
                    distributing the provinces, the senate decreed that Spain, which during the
                    Macedonian war had been but one province, should be again formed into two;
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and that the present governors, Lucius
                    Paullus and Lucius Anicius, should continue in the government of Macedonia and
                    Illyria, until, with the concurrence of commissioners, they should adjust the
                    affairs of those countries disordered by the war, and reduce them to a form of
                    government different from the regal. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> The
                    provinces assigned to the consuls were Pisae and Gaul, with two legions to each,
                    containing separately five thousand two hundred foot and four hundred horse. The
                    lots of the praetors were as follows: the city jurisdiction fell to Quintus
                    Cassius; the foreign, to Manius Juventius Thalna; Sicily, to Tiberius Claudius
                    Nero; Hither Spain, to Cneius Fulvius; and to Caius Licinius Nerva, Farther
                    Spain. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Sardinia had fallen to Aulus Manlius
                    Torquatus, but he could not proceed thither, being detained by a decree of the
                    senate, to preside at trials of capital offences. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> The senate was then consulted concerning prodigies which
                    were reported: the temple of the tutelar deities, on the Velian hill, had been
                    struck by lightning; and two gates, and a large part of the wall, in the town of
                    Minervium. At Anagnia, a shower of earth had fallen; and, at Lanuvium, a blazing
                    torch was seen in the sky. Marcus Valerius, a Roman citizen, reported, that at
                    Calatia, on the public lands, blood had flowed from his hearth, during three
                    days and two nights. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> On account of this last
                    occurrence in particular, the decemvirs were directed to consult the books; on
                    which they ordered a general supplication for one day, and sacrificed in the
                    forum fifty goats. On account of the other prodigies, there was a supplication
                    for another day, with sacrifices of the larger victims, and the city was
                    purified. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Then, with reference to the
                    gratitude due to the immortal gods, the senate decreed, that, "forasmuch as
                    their enemies were subdued, and the kings Perseus and Gentius, with Macedon and
                    Illyria, were in the power of the Roman people, whatever offerings were made in
                    all the temples by Appius <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> Claudius and
                    Marcus Sempronius, the consuls, on occasion of the conquest of king Antiochus,
                    offerings of the same value should then be made, and that Quintus Cassius and
                    Manius Juventius, the praetors, should superintend them. </p>
                <milestone n="17" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> They then constituted commissioners, by whose
                    advice <pb n="2134" xml:id="p.2134"/> the generals, Lucius Paullus and Lucius
                    Anicius, were to regulate the affairs of their provinces; ten for Macedon, and
                    five for Illyria. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Those nominated for Macedon
                    were, Aulus Postumius Luscus, Caius Claudius, both of whom had been censors,
                    Caius Licinius Crassus, the colleague of Paullus in the consulship; he then held
                    the province of Gaul, as he had the command continued to him. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> To these, who were of consular rank, the senate added
                    Cneius Domitius Aenobarbus, Servius Cornelius Sulla, Lucius Junius, Caius
                    Antistius Labeo, Titus Numisius Tarquiniensis, and Aulus Terentius Varro.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The following were nominated for Illyria:
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> Publius Aelius Ligus, a man of consular
                    rank, Caius Cicereius, Cneius Baebius Tamphilus, (he had been praetor the last
                    year, as had Cicereius many years before,) Publius Terentius Tuscivicanus, and
                    Publius Manilius. The consuls were then advised by the senate, that, as one of
                    them must go into Gaul, in the room of <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> Caius
                    Licinius, who was appointed a commissioner, they should, as soon as possible,
                    either settle their provinces between themselves, or cast lots, as might be
                    agreeable to them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They chose to cast lots;
                    when Pisae fell to Marcus Junius, (who was ordered to introduce to the senate
                    the embassies that came to Rome from all quarters, with congratulations before
                    he went to his province,) and Gaul to Quintus Aelius. </p>
                <milestone n="18" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> But although men of such characters were sent
                    on the commission, that confident hopes might be entertained that the generals,
                    influenced by their counsel, would determine on nothing derogatory either to the
                    clemency or dignity of the Roman people, yet the heads of a plan of settlement
                    were considered in the senate, that the said commissioners might carry, from
                    Rome to the generals, an outline of the entire plan. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> First, it was determined, that <quote> the Macedonians and
                        Illyrians should be free; in order to demonstrate to all the world that the
                        arms of the Roman people did not bring slavery to the free, but freedom to
                        slaves, and that the nations which already enjoyed freedom, should be
                        convinced that it would be safe and permanent under the protection of the
                            <hi rend="italics">Roman people;</hi> and that such nations as lived
                        under regal government should be convinced that their princes, under awe of
                        the Roman people, would be, at present, more just and mild; <milestone n="3"
                            unit="section"/> and that, should war break out at any time between
                        their kings and the Roman people, the issue would bring victory to <pb
                            n="2135" xml:id="p.2135"/> the latter, and liberty to themselves.
                            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> It was also provided, that the farming
                        both of the Macedonian mines, which produced a very large profit, and that
                        of crown lands, should be abolished; as business of this kind could not be
                        managed without the intervention of revenue farmers; <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> and wherever a tax-contractor was employed, either the
                        rights of the people were a nonentity, or the freedom of the allies
                        destroyed. Nor could the Macedonians themselves conduct such affairs; for
                        while they afforded the managers opportunities of acquiring plunder for
                        themselves, there never would be wanting causes of disputes and seditions.
                            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> It was further determined, that there
                        should be a general council of the nation; lest the perverseness of the
                        populace might, some time or other, convert into pestilent licentiousness
                        the liberty granted by the senate with a wholesome degree of moderation:
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> but that Macedonia should be divided
                        into four districts, each of which should have a council of its own; and
                        that they should pay to the Roman people half the tribute which they used
                        formerly to pay to their kings. </quote>
                    <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Similar instructions were given respecting
                    Illyria. Other particulars were left to the generals and commissioners; whose
                    investigation of matters on the spot would enable them to form more accurate
                    plans. </p>
                <milestone n="19" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Among the many embassies from kings, nations,
                    and states, Attalus, the brother of Eumenes, attracted the general attention in
                    a very particular manner; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for he was received
                    by those who had served along with him in the late war, with even greater
                    demonstration of kindness than if Eumenes had come in person. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Two reasons, both, apparently, highly honourable, had
                    induced him to come; one to offer congratulations, which were quite proper, in
                    the case of a victory to which he himself had contributed; the other to complain
                    of disturbances raised by the Gauls, and of a defeat received, by which his
                    brother's kingdom was endangered. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> But he had,
                    also, secret hopes of honours and rewards from the senate, which he could
                    scarcely receive without infringing on his duty to his brother. There were among
                    the Romans some evil advisers, who were working on his ambition by promises.
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> They told him, that <quote> the general
                        opinion concerning Attalus and Eumenes was, that one was a steady friend to
                        the Romans, and that the other was not a faithful ally either to them or to
                        Perseus. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> That it was not easy to determine
                        whether the <pb n="2136" xml:id="p.2136"/> requests that he might make for
                        himself, or those against his brother, were more likely to be obtained from
                        the senate; so entirely were all disposed to gratify the ones and to grant
                        nothing to the other. </quote>
                    <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> As the event proved, Attalus was one of those
                    who would have coveted all that hope can promise to itself, had not the prudent
                    admonitions of one friend put a curb on those passions, which were growing
                    wanton through prosperity. He had, in his retinue, a physician, called Stratius,
                    sent to Rome by Eumenes, who distrusted Attalus, for the purpose of watching
                    over his conduct, and giving him faithful advice, if he should perceive him
                    swerve from his allegiance. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> This man, although
                    he had to address ears already prepossessed, and a mind already biassed, yet, by
                    addressing him at judiciously selected times, restored the thing to its proper
                    state, even after it had become almost desperate. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> He said that <quote> different kingdoms grew into power by
                        different means: that their kingdom being lately formed, and unsupported by
                        any long-established strength, was upheld solely by the concord of the
                        brothers; for, while one bore the title and the ornament which distinguishes
                        the head of a sovereign, each of the brothers was considered as a king.
                            <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> As to Attalus, in particular, being
                        the next in years, was there any man who did not consider him as king?
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> and that, not only because they
                        perceived his present power to be great, but because there was not a doubt
                        but he must ascend the throne, in a very short time, in consequence of the
                        age and infirmity of Eumenes, who had no legitimate issue </quote> (for he
                    had not at this time acknowledged the son who afterwards reigned). <quote> To
                        what purpose, then, employ violence, to attain what must come to him
                        presently without any exertions on his part? <milestone n="12"
                            unit="section"/> Besides, a new storm had fallen on the kingdom, from
                        the insurrection of the Gauls, which could scarcely be resisted by the most
                        perfect harmony and union of the brothers. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
                        /> But if to a foreign war domestic dissensions were added, the evil could
                        not be checked; nor would he effect any thing else than preventing his
                        brother from dying on the throne, and depriving himself of the hope of
                        ascending it. If both modes of acting were honourable, —either to preserve
                        the kingdom for his brother, or to take it from him, —yet the honour that
                        would result to him from the preservation of the kingdom, since it was
                        united to brotherly love, would be the greater. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> The latter <pb n="2137" xml:id="p.2137"/> indeed, would
                        be detestable, and bordering nearly on parricide; what room, then, could
                        there be for deliberation? For, whether did he mean to demand a share of the
                        kingdom, or to seize the whole? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> If he
                        would demand a share, then both, by the separation of their strength, would
                        be rendered feeble, and exposed to injuries of every kind; if the whole,
                        would he then require his elder brother, reduced to a private station, at
                        his time of life and labouring under such bodily infirmities, to live in
                        exile, and die in such a wretched state. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>
                        For, not to mention the catastrophes of undutiful brothers recorded in
                        stories, the fate of Perseus seemed a striking instance, who, prostrated at
                        the feet of a victorious enemy, laid down, in the temple of the
                        Samothracians, before the gods, who, as it were, demanded satisfaction for
                        his crimes, the crown which he had seized after the death of his brother.
                            <milestone n="17" unit="section"/> Those very men, </quote> he
                    continued, <quote> who not through friendship for him, but enmity to Eumenes,
                        had instigated him to the adoption of such measures, would praise his
                        affection and firmness, if he preserved to the last his allegiance to his
                        brother. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="20" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These arguments prevailed in the mind of
                    Attalus. Therefore, on being introduced to the senate, he congratulated them on
                    their success, and made mention of his own services during the war, and those of
                    his brother, whatever he had performed; of the defection of the Gauls, which had
                    lately happened, and which had caused violent commotions; <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> and he entreated that they should send ambassadors to those
                    people, by whose authority they should be summoned to desist. After delivering
                    these messages respecting the general interest of the state, he requested a
                    grant of Aenus and Maronea to himself. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Having
                    thus disappointed the hopes of those who expected that he, after arraigning his
                    brother's conduct, would solicit a partition of the kingdom, he retired from the
                    senate-house. Seldom on other occasions was either a king or private person
                    heard with such a degree of favour and approbation by all; during his stay he
                    received presents and honours of every description, and they treated him
                    similarly at his departure. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of the many
                    embassies which came from Greece and Asia, that of the Rhodians engaged the
                    greatest share of the public attention. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At
                    first they appeared in white, the colour which was most becoming to persons
                    congratulating others, for had they worn mourning, they might seem to be la- <pb
                        n="2138" xml:id="p.2138"/> menting the misfortunes of Perseus. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Afterwards the senate, being consulted by the consul,
                    Marcus Junius, (the ambassadors standing in the Comitium,) whether they should
                    grant them lodgings, entertainments, and an audience of the senate, they voted
                    that no duty of hospitality was due to them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    When the consul came out of the senate-house, after the Rhodians had told him
                    that they were come to congratulate the Romans on their late success, and to
                    clear their state of the charges made against it, and requested an audience of
                    the senate, he returned this answer, that <quote> it was the custom of the
                        Romans both to grant audience in their senate, and to perform other acts of
                        kindness and hospitality to their friends and allies; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> but that the Rhodians had not deserved in that war to
                        be ranked in the number of friends or allies. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> On hearing this, they all prostrated
                    themselves on the ground, beseeching the consul and all present not to think it
                    right that new and false imputations should operate more powerfully to their
                    prejudice, than their long course of services, which they had themselves
                    witnessed. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> They immediately assumed a
                    mourning dress, and going round to the houses of the principal men, supplicated
                    with prayers and tears that their cause might be heard before they were
                    condemned. </p>
                <milestone n="21" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Marcus Juventius Thalna, the praetor who had
                    the jurisdiction between natives and foreigners, stimulated the public
                    resentment against the Rhodians, and promulgated a bill, that <quote> war should
                        be declared against the Rhodians, and that the people should choose one of
                        the magistrates of the present year, who should be sent with a fleet to
                        carry on that war; </quote> with the hope that he himself should be the
                    person chosen. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Two of the plebeian tribunes,
                    Marcus Antonius and Marcus Pomponius, opposed this proceeding. But the praetor,
                    on his part, commenced the business in an unprecedented and pernicious manner;
                    for without first consulting the senate, and without acquainting the consuls, of
                    his own sole judgment he proposed to the people the question, <quote>was it
                        their will and order that war should be declared against the
                        Rhodians?</quote> whereas, ever until then, the senate was first consulted
                    concerning the war, and then the business was laid before the people. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> On the other side, the plebeian tribunes <hi
                        rend="italics">opposed this proceeding;</hi> although it was a received rule
                    that no tribune should protest against a proposal, until opportunity was given
                        <pb n="2139" xml:id="p.2139"/> to private citizens to argue for and against
                    it; in consequence of which it had often happened that some, who had avowed no
                    intention of protesting, having discovered defects in the law from the
                    discourses of those who opposed it, on that account did protest; and some who
                    came avowedly to protest, abstained from it, being convinced by the arguments of
                    those who spoke in favour of the law. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> On this
                    occasion the praetor and tribunes vied with each other in doing every thing out
                    of time. <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> Crevier supplement:
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        <quote>
                            <p> While the tribunes blamed the hasty proceeding of the praetor, they
                                imitated the example by protesting before their time. The only
                                pretence they alleged for it was, the necessity for adjourning the
                                entire deliberation concerning the Rhodians until the return of the
                                general and the ten commissioners from Macedon, who, after most
                                carefully weighing the matter ac- cording to the communications
                                received in their letters and tab- lets, were likely to give certain
                                information relative to the feelings which each state had borne
                                towards Perseus or the Romans. But when the praetor, nevertheless,
                                persisted in his determination, the matter came to this, that
                                Antonius, the tri- bune of the commons, after bringing <milestone
                                    n="6??" unit="section"/> the ambassadors before the people,
                                dragged down from the rostrum Thalna, who was attempting to ascend
                                it contrary to his wishes, and was be- ginning to address the
                                people, and gave the Rhodians an opportunity of speaking before the
                                general assembly. But although the violent and impetuous attempt of
                                the praetor had been defeated by corresponding firmness on the part
                                of the tribune, still anxiety did not as yet leave the minds of the
                                Rhodians; for the senators bore them a most unfriendly feel- ing; so
                                that the Rhodians were relieved from the impending evil for the
                                present, rather than completely rescued from it. Therefore, when a
                                meeting of the senate was granted to them, after requesting it for a
                                long time and frequently, on their introduction by the consul they
                                lay at first for a long time with their persons prostrated on the
                                ground; afterwards, when the consul raised them up and ordered them
                                to speak, Asty- medes, whose appearance was most calculated to
                                excite pity, spoke to the following effect: "Conscript fathers, this
                                grief and degradation of allies, who enjoyed your friendship a short
                                time ago, cannot fail to be pitied even by those who are <milestone
                                    n="7??" unit="section"/> irri- tated against us; and how much
                                more justly will compassion enter your minds, if you will but
                                consider the hard conditions <pb n="2140" xml:id="p.2140"/> under
                                which we this day, in your presence, plead the cause of our state,
                                already almost <milestone n="8??" unit="section"/> condemned. Others
                                are accused prior to their condemnation; nor do they suffer
                                punishment until their guilt is ascertained. </p>
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <milestone n="22" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Whether we Rhodians have transgressed, or
                    not, is yet doubtful; meanwhile we suffer punishments and disgraces of all
                    sorts. In former times, when we visited Rome, after the conquest of Carthage,
                    after the defeat of Philip, and after that of Antiochus, we <hi rend="italics"
                        >were escorted</hi> from a mansion furnished us by the public, into the
                    senate-house, to present our congratulations to you, conscript fathers, and,
                    from the senate-house to the Capitol, carrying offerings to your gods.
                        <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> But now, from a vile and filthy inn,
                    scarcely gaining a reception for our money, treated as enemies, and forbid to
                    lodge within the city, we come in this squalid dress to the Roman senate-house:
                    we, Rhodians, on whom a short time ago you bestowed the provinces of Lycia and
                    Caria; <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> on whom you conferred the most ample
                    rewards and honours. You order even the Macedonians and Illyrians, as we hear,
                    to be free; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> though they were in servitude
                    before they waged war with you: (nor do we envy the good fortune of any; on the
                    contrary, we acknowledge therein the usual clemency of the Roman people.)
                        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> But will you convert, from allies into
                    enemies, the Rhodians, who were guilty of nothing more than remaining neutral
                    during the war? You are in truth the same Romans, who boast that your wars are
                    successful because they are just; who glory not so much in the issue of them, in
                    that you conquer, as in the commencement of them, because you do not undertake
                    them without a just cause. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The attack on
                    Messana, in Sicily, made the Carthaginians your enemies. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> The siege of Athens, and attempt to reduce Greece to
                    slavery, together with the assistance of men and money given to Hannibal, led to
                    hostilities with Philip. Antiochus, on the invitation of the Aetolians, your
                    enemies, came over in person with a fleet from Asia to Greece; and by seizing
                    Demetrias, Chalcis, and the pass of Thermopylae, endeavoured to dispossess you
                    of empire. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The motives to your war with
                    Perseus were his attacks on your allies, and his putting to death the princes
                    and leading members of certain states. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> But, if
                    we are doomed to ruin, to what motive will our misfortune be ascribed? I do not
                    yet separate the cause <pb n="2141" xml:id="p.2141"/> of the state from that of
                    our countrymen, Polyaratus and Dino, with others, whom we have brought hither in
                    order to deliver them into your hands. But supposing every one of us were
                    equally guilty, I ask what was our crime with respect to the late war?
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> We favoured the interest of Perseus; and
                    we have supported that prince against you in like manner as, in the wars of
                    Antiochus and Philip, we supported you against those kings. <milestone n="11"
                        unit="section"/> Now, in what manner we are accustomed to assist our allies,
                    and with what vigour to conduct wars, ask Caius Livius and Lucius Aemilius
                    Regillus, who commanded your fleets on the coasts of Asia. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> Your ships never fought a battle without us. We, with our
                    own fleet, fought one engagement at Samos and a second on the coast of
                    Pamphylia, against that distinguished commander, Hannibal. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> The victory, which we gained in the latter, was the more
                    glorious to us because, although we lost a great part of our navy and the flower
                    of our youth in the unsuccessful action at Samos, we were not deterred from
                    venturing again to give battle to the king's fleet on its return from Syria.
                        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> These matters I have mentioned not out of
                    ostentation, (that would ill become our present situation,) but to remind you in
                    what way the Rhodians assist their allies. </p>
                <milestone n="23" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "When Philip and Antiochus were subdued, we
                    received from you very ample rewards. If the fortune of Perseus were such as
                    yours now is by the favour of the gods and your own courage, and we were to go
                    into Macedon, to the victorious king, to demand rewards from him, what merit
                    should we have to plead? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Is it that he was
                    aided by us with money or corn; with land or sea forces? Had we defended his
                    garrison? where had we, either under his generals or by ourselves? If he should
                    inquire where were our soldiers or ships acting in concert with his; what answer
                    could we give? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Perhaps we might be pleading
                    our cause before him, if successful, as we are now, before you. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> All that we have gained by sending ambassadors to both, to
                    mediate a peace, is, that we received no thanks from either party, and incurred
                    from one of them accusations and danger. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Perseus, indeed, might justly object to us what you cannot, conscript fathers,
                    that at the commencement of the war we sent ambassadors to Rome, promising
                    supplies of all sorts requisite for the war, and engaging to be ready, as in
                    former wars, with our docks, our <pb n="2142" xml:id="p.2142"/> arms, and our
                    men. It was your fault that we did not perform this, since you, whatever was the
                    reason, rejected our assistance on that occasion. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> We have, therefore, neither acted in any instance as
                    enemies, nor been deficient in the duty of well-affected allies; but we were
                    prevented by you from performing it. What then shall we say? Rhodians, has there
                    been nothing said or done in your country which you disapprove of, and at which
                    the Roman people would be justly offended? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Henceforth I do not mean to defend what has been done, (I am not so weak,) but
                    to distinguish the cause of the public from the guilt of private men. For there
                    is no nation whatever that has not, generally, some ill-disposed members, and
                    always an ignorant populace. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I have heard,
                    that even among the Romans there have been men who worked themselves into power
                    by courting the multitude; that the plebeians sometimes seceded from you, and
                    that the government was not always in your hands. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> If it were possible for this to happen in a state so well
                    constituted, who can wonder at there being some among us, who, out of a wish to
                    gain the king's friendship, led our commons astray by bad advice? <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> Yet they effected nothing more than our remaining
                    inactive, without infringing on our duty. I shall not pass by that, which has
                    been made the heaviest charge against our state during the war. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> We sent ambassadors at the same time to you and
                    Perseus, to mediate a peace; and that unfortunate design was, by a furious
                    orator, as we afterwards heard, rendered foolish to the last degree; for it is
                    ascertained that he spoke in such a manner as Caius Popilius, the Roman
                    ambassador, should have spoken, when you sent him to the two kings, Antiochus
                    and Ptolemy, to induce them to cease from hostilities. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> But still, whether this conduct is to be called arrogance
                    or folly, it was the same towards Perseus as towards you. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> States, as well as individuals, have their different
                    characters; some are violent, others daring, others timid; some addicted to
                    wine, others more particularly to women. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Fame
                    says that the Athenian nation was quick and bold, beyond its strength, in
                    beginning an enterprise; and that the Lacedaemonian was dilatory and backward in
                    entering upon business, even when confident of success. <milestone n="15"
                        unit="section"/> I cannot deny that Asia, throughout its whole extent,
                    produces men too much inclined to vanity, and that the speech of even the <pb
                        n="2143" xml:id="p.2143"/> Rhodians is too much tinctured with vain-glory,
                    because we seem to have the pre-eminence above the neighbouring states;
                        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/> and that, too, owing not so much to our
                    strength as to the marks of honour and esteem conferred on us by you. That
                    embassy received on the spot sufficient reproof for its immediate misconduct,
                    when it was dismissed with so severe an answer. <milestone n="17" unit="section"
                    /> But, if the disgrace which we then suffered was too trifling, surely the
                    present mournful and suppliant embassy would be a sufficient expiation for an
                    embassy even more insolent than that was. Irritable men hate arrogance; men of
                    sense despise it, particularly if shown in words; more especially, if it be
                    shown by an inferior towards a superior; but no one has ever yet thought it
                    deserving of capital punishment. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> There was,
                    in truth, danger lest the Rhodians should contemn the Romans! Some men have
                    spoken, even of the gods, in terms too presumptuous; <milestone n="19"
                        unit="section"/> yet we have never heard of any one being struck with
                    thunder on that account. </p>
                <milestone n="24" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> What charge then remains, of which we are to acquit ourselves, since
                        there has been no hostile act on our part, and the insolent language of an
                        ambassador, though grating to the ear, has not deserved the ruin of a state.
                            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Conscript fathers, I hear that the
                        estimate of the penalty for our secret wishes has become the subject of your
                        conversation. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Some assert that we favoured
                        the king, and therefore that we should be punished with war; others, that we
                        did indeed wish him success, but ought not, on that account, to suffer the
                        penalty of war, since it has not been so instituted either by the practice
                        or laws of any state, that if any one should wish an enemy to perish, he
                        should be condemned, provided that he did nothing towards effecting his
                        wishes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> We feel, indeed, grateful to those
                        who absolve us from the punishment, though not from the crime; but we lay
                        down this law for ourselves: if we all entertained the wishes of which we
                        are accused, we will then make no distinction between the will and the deed:
                        let us all be punished. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If some of our
                        people in power favoured you, and others the king, I do not demand, that for
                        the sake of us who were on your side, the favourers of the king may be
                        saved; but I deprecate our perishing through them. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> You are not more inveterate against them than is our
                        state itself; and most of them, when they ascertained this, fled, or put
                        themselves to death, the others have been condemned by us, and <pb n="2144"
                            xml:id="p.2144"/> they will soon be in your power, conscript fathers.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The rest of us Rhodians, as we have
                        merited no thanks during the war, so neither have we deserved punishment.
                        Let the accumulation of our former services atone for our present
                        dereliction of duty. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> You have recently
                        waged war with three kings: let not the circumstance of our having been
                        inactive in one of these wars, be more injurious to us than our having
                        fought on your side in the other two has served us. <milestone n="9"
                            unit="section"/> Consider Philip, Antiochus, and Perseus, as you would
                        three votes; two of them acquit us; one, although it would be unfavourable,
                        is nevertheless doubtful. If they were to sit in judgment over us, we would
                        be condemned. Conscript fathers, you are to decide, whether Rhodes is to
                        continue on the earth or to be utterly destroyed. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> You are not deliberating concerning war, conscript
                        fathers, for though it is in your power to declare war, it is not in your
                        power to wage it, as not a single Rhodian will take up arms against you.
                            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If you persist in your anger, we will
                        beg time from you, until we carry home an account of this unhappy embassy.
                        We will then, every free person of all the Rhodians, both men and women,
                        with all our wealth, embark in ships, and leaving the seats of our tutelar
                        deities, both public and private, repair to Rome, where, heaping together in
                        the Comitium, at the door of your senate-house, all our gold <milestone
                            n="12??" unit="section"/> and silver, all the public and private
                        property that we possess, we will submit our persons, and those of our wives
                        and children, to your disposal; that, whatever we are to suffer, we may
                        suffer here. Let our city be sacked and burned far away from our view.
                            <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> The Romans may pass a judgment, that
                        the Rhodians are enemies; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> but we have
                        also a right, in some degree, to judge ourselves; and we never will judge
                        ourselves your enemies, nor do one hostile act, should we even suffer
                        extreme calamities. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="25" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After so mournful a speech, they all
                    prostrated themselves again, and as supplicants, held out olive branches; but at
                    length they were raised, and withdrew from the senate-house. <milestone n="2"
                        unit="section"/> They then began to ask the opinions of the senators. The
                    most inveterate against the Rhodians were those, who as consuls, praetors, or
                    lieutenant-generals, had been engaged in the war with Macedon. Marcus Porcius
                    Cato was the principal supporter of their cause, who, though naturally austere,
                    acted his part as a senator, on this occasion, with much mild- <pb n="2145"
                        xml:id="p.2145"/> ness and lenity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> I will
                    not introduce here a specimen of his copious eloquence, by relating what he
                    said: his speech is extant, and is comprised in the fifth book of his
                    Antiquities. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> The answer given to the Rhodians
                    was, that <quote>they should neither be declared enemies, nor any longer remain
                        in alliance with Rome.</quote>
                    <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> At the head of this embassy were Philocrates
                    and Astymedes. They determined that half their number, with Philocrates, should
                    carry home to Rhodes an account of their proceedings; and that the other half,
                    with Astymedes, should remain at Rome, that they might be acquainted with what
                    passed, and inform their countrymen. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> For the
                    present, they were commanded to remove their governors out of Lycia and Caria,
                    before a certain day. This intelligence was announced at Rhodes; and although it
                    was galling in itself, yet as the Rhodians were relieved from the dread of a
                    greater evil, for they had feared a war, the announcement created joy.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> They therefore immediately voted a
                    present, amounting in value to twenty thousand pieces of gold, and deputed
                    Theatetus, the commander of their fleet, on that embassy. They wished to procure
                    an alliance with the Romans; but, in such a manner, as that no order of the
                    people should pass concerning it, nor any thing be committed to writing; for in
                    either of these cases, if they failed in suc- ceeding, there would be greater
                    disgrace in the refusal. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The admiral of the
                    fleet was empowered, singly, to negotiate that business, if he could effect it
                    without any law being brought forward at Rome on the subject; <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> for, during a considerable length of time, they had
                    maintained a friendship with the Romans, in such a manner as not to bind
                    themselves by a treaty of alliance, for no other reason than that they might
                    neither preclude the kings from all hope of their assistance, if any of them
                    should need it, nor themselves from a participation of the advantages which
                    might accrue from the good fortune and liberality of the said kings. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> At this time, however, an alliance seemed
                    particularly desirable, not to render them more secure from others, (for
                    excepting the Romans, they feared none,) but to make them less suspected by the
                    Romans themselves. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> About this time, the
                    Caunians revolted from them, and the Mylasensians seized on the towns of the
                    Euromensians. The spirit of their community was not so totally broken as to
                    hinder their perceiving, that, if Lycia and <pb n="2146" xml:id="p.2146"/> Caria
                    were taken from them by the Romans, their other provinces would either assert
                    their own freedom by a revolt, or be seized on by their neighbours; <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> and that they themselves would then be shut up in a
                    small island; within the shores of a barren country, which could by no means
                    maintain the numerous people in so large a city. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> They therefore sent out, with all speed, a body of troops,
                    and reduced the Caunians to obedience, though they had received succours from
                    Cybara: and afterwards defeated in a battle at Orthosia the Mylassians and
                    Alabandians, who, having seized the province of Euroma, had marched against them
                    with their allied forces. </p>
                <milestone n="26" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Whilst these events are occurring in Rhodes,
                    different matters are going on in Macedon and Rome; in the mean time, in
                    Illyria, Lucius Anicius, having reduced king Gentius under his power, as before
                    mentioned, placed Gabinius over a garrison that he posted in Scodra, which had
                    been the capital of the kingdom; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> and appointed
                    Caius Licinius commander in Rhizon and Olcinium, which were towns very
                    conveniently situated. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Leaving these two in
                    charge of Illyria, he marched with the rest of his forces into Epirus. Here,
                    Phanota was the first place which submitted to him; the whole multitude, with
                    fillets on their heads, coming out to meet him. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
                    /> Placing a garrison there, he went over into Molossis, all the towns of which
                    province, except Passora, Tecmo, Phylace, and Horreum, having surrendered, he
                    marched first against Passora. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The two men of
                    the greatest authority in that city, were Antinous and Theodotus, who were
                    remarkable for their warm attachment to Perseus, and hatred to the Romans; the
                    same individuals had instigated the whole nation to revolt from the Romans.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> These men, since they had no hope of
                    pardon, owing to their consciousness of guilt, shut the gates, that they might
                    be buried under the general ruin of their country, and exhorted the multitude to
                    prefer death to slavery. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> No man dared to open
                    his lips against men of such transcendent power. At last one Theodotus, a young
                    man of distinction, (when his greater dread of the Romans had overpowered the
                    lesser fear of his own leaders,) exclaimed, <quote> What madness has seized you,
                        to make the public accessory to the crimes of two individuals? <milestone
                            n="8" unit="section"/> I have often heard mention made of men who
                        offered themselves to death for the sake of their country; but those are the
                        first that were ever found, who required that <pb n="2147" xml:id="p.2147"/>
                        their country should perish for them. Why not open our gates, and submit to
                        that power to which the whole world has submitted? </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> As he spoke thus, the multitude followed him;
                    on which Antinous and Theodotus rushed out on the advanced guards of the enemy,
                    and freely exposing themselves to their weapons, were slain, and the city was
                    surrendered to the Romans. Through a similar obstinacy in Cephalus, a man in
                    power, the gates of Tecmo were shut: when he was put to death, Anicius received
                    the surrender of the town. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Neither Phylace
                    nor Horreum stood a siege. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Having thus
                    reduced Epirus, Anicius distributed his troops in winter quarters, through the
                    most convenient towns; and returning into Illyria, held a general convention at
                    Scodra, where the five commissioners had arrived from Rome, and to which place
                    he had summoned the principal men from all parts of the province. <milestone
                        n="12" unit="section"/> There, with advice of the council, he proclaimed
                    from his tribunal, that <quote> the senate and people of Rome granted freedom to
                        the Illyrians; and that he would withdraw his garrisons from all their
                        towns, citadels, and castles. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That the
                        Issensians and Taulantians, with the Pirustans, that were included among the
                        Dassaretians, the Rhizonites, and the Olcinians, should not only enjoy
                        liberty, but likewise an immunity from taxes; because when Gentius was in
                        his full strength, they had revolted to the Romans. <milestone n="14"
                            unit="section"/> That the same exemption was granted to the Daorseans;
                        because they forsook Caravantius, and came over with their arms to the
                        Romans; and that the Scodrans, Dassaretians, Selepitans, and the rest of the
                        Illyrians, should pay half the taxes which they had formerly paid to their
                        king. </quote>
                    <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> He then divided Illyria into three districts;
                    he made the first division out of the people above mentioned, the second
                    comprehended all the Labeatians, and the third the Agranonites, Rhizonites, and
                    Olcinians, with the contiguous states. Having established this constitution in
                    Illyria, he returned into Epirus, to his winter quarters at Passaro. </p>
                <milestone n="27" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While these matters are passing in Illyria,
                    Paullus, before the arrival of the ten commissioners, sent his son Quintus
                    Maximus, who was by this time returned from Rome, to sack Agassae and Aeginium:
                    Agassae, because the inhabitants, after surrendering their city to the consul,
                    and volun- tarily soliciting an alliance with Rome, had revolted again to <pb
                        n="2148" xml:id="p.2148"/> Perseus: the crime of the people of Aeginium was
                    of a late date; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> not giving credit to the
                    report <milestone n="3??" unit="section"/> of the Romans being victorious, they
                    had treated with hostile cruelty some soldiers who came into the city.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> He also detached Lucius Postumius to
                    pillage the city of Aenia; because the inhabitants had continued in arms with
                    more obstinacy than the neighbouring states. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Autumn now drew nigh; at the commencement of this season, when he resolved to
                    make a tour through Greece, in order to take a view of those curiosities, which,
                    being celebrated by fame, are represented as greater than they really are when
                    examined by the eye, he gave the command of his quarters to Caius Sulpicius
                    Gallus, and, with <milestone n="6??" unit="section"/> a moderate retinue, began
                    his journey, accompanied by his son Scipio, and Athenaeus, king Eumenes'
                    brother, and directed his route through Thessaly to the famous oracle at Delphi;
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> where he offered sacrifices to Apollo,
                    and, in honour of his victory, destined for his own statues some unfinished
                    columns in the vestibule, on which they had intended to place statues of king
                    Perseus. He also visited the temple of Jupiter Trophonius at Lebadia; <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> where, after viewing the mouth of the cave, through
                    which people applying to the oracle descend, in order to obtain information from
                    the gods, he sacrificed to Jupiter and Hercyna, who have a temple there; and
                    then went down to Chalcis, to see the curiosities of the Euripus, and of the
                    island of Eubœa, which is there united to the continent by a bridge. <milestone
                        n="9" unit="section"/> From Chalcis he passed by sea to Aulis, a port three
                    miles distant, famous for having been formerly the station of Agamemnon's fleet
                    of one thousand ships, and distinguished also for the temple of Diana, in which
                    that king of kings sought a passage for his fleet to Troy, by offering his
                    daughter Iphigenia as a victim at the altar. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                    Thence he came to Oropus, in Attica; where an ancient prophet is worshipped as a
                    god, and has an old temple, rendered delightful by the surrounding springs and
                    streams. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> He then went to Athens, which,
                    though filled with only the decayed relics of ancient grandeur, still contained
                    many things worthy of observation; the citadel, the port, the walls connecting
                    Piraeeus with the city; the dockyards, the monuments of illustrious generals,
                    the statues of gods and men, alike remarkable for the variety of the materials
                    and the ingenuity of the artists. </p>
                <milestone n="28" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> After sacrificing to Minerva, the guardian of
                    the citadel, <pb n="2149" xml:id="p.2149"/> he continued his journey, and on the
                    second day arrived at Corinth. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The city was
                    then flourishing, as this visit was prior to its fall; the citadel too, and the
                    isthmus, afforded admirable views; the former, within the walls, and towering up
                    to an immense height, yet abounding with springs; and the latter, separating by
                    a narrow neck two seas, which wash it on the east and west. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> He next visited the celebrated cities of Sicyon and Argos;
                    then Epidaurus, which, though unequal to them in opulence, was yet remarkable
                    for a famous temple of Esculapius, which, standing at five miles' distance from
                    the city, was at that time rich in offerings, which the sick had dedicated to
                    that deity, as an acknowledgment for the remedies which restored them to health;
                    but now, full of the traces of them only, whence they have been torn away.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Thence he proceeded to Lacedaemon,
                    renowned, not for magnificent works of art, but for its laws and discipline; and
                    then, passing through Magalopolis, he went up to Olympia. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Here, having taken a view of all things worthy of notice,
                    and beholding Jupiter in a manner present before him, he was struck with the
                    deepest reverence; therefore he ordered preparations to be made for a sacrifice,
                    with more than usual magnificence, and as if he were going to make offerings in
                    the Capitol; <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> having made his circuit through
                    Greece in such a manner as not to inquire into the sentiments which any one,
                    either in his public or private capacity, entertained in the war against
                    Perseus, lest he might disturb the minds of the allies with any kind of
                    apprehensions. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> On his way back to Demetrias, a
                    crowd of Aetolians, in mourning apparel, met him: on his expressing surprise,
                    and asking the reason of this proceeding, he was told that five hundred and
                    fifty of the chief of their countrymen had been put to death by Lyciscus and
                    Tisippus, who surrounded their senate with Roman soldiers, sent by their
                    commander Baebius; that others had been driven into exile; and that the accusers
                    were in possession of the goods of the killed and exiled. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> They were ordered to wait on him at Amphipolis; and then,
                    having met Cneius Octavius at Demetrias, who informed him that the ten
                    commissioners were landed, he laid aside all other business, and went to
                    Apollonia to meet them. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> And when Perseus,
                    owing to the negligence of his guard, had come hither to meet him from
                    Amphipolis, (the distance is a day's journey,) Aemilius spoke to him with great
                    courtesy; <pb n="2150" xml:id="p.2150"/> but is said to have severely
                    reprimanded Caius Sulpicius, when he reached the camp at Amphipolis; <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> first, for allowing Perseus thus to ramble through
                    the province, and next, for indulging the soldiers so far as to suffer them to
                    strip the buildings on the city walls of the tiles, in order to cover their own
                    winter huts. These tiles he ordered to be carried back, the buildings to be
                    repaired, and put in their former condition. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>
                    He gave in charge to Aulus Postumius, Perseus, with his elder son Philip, and
                    sent them into a place of confinement; his daughter and younger son he ordered
                    to be brought from Samothrace to Amphipolis, and treated them with all possible
                    kindness. </p>
                <milestone n="29" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the day arrived, on which he had ordered
                    ten chiefs from each of the states to attend at Amphipolis, and all the writings
                    wherever deposited, and the money belonging to the king, to be brought thither,
                    he seated himself, with the ten commissioners, on his tribunal, while the whole
                    multitude of the Macedonians surrounded him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>
                    Though they were inured to the government of a king, yet the strange tribunal
                    presented a terrible appearance; the path that was cleared towards the praetor
                    by the removal of the people, the herald, the sergeant, were all objects strange
                    to their eyes and ears, and capable of inspiring awe in allies, much more in
                    conquered enemies. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Silence being proclaimed by
                    the herald, Paullus declared in the Latin language the regulations adopted by
                    the senate, and by himself with the advice of the council; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and the praetor, Cneius Octavius, (for he too was present,)
                    translated them into the Greek language, and read them aloud First of all he
                    ordered, that <quote> the Macedonians should live free; possessing the same
                        cities and lands as before; governed by their own laws, and creating annual
                        magistrates; and that they should pay to the Roman people one-half of the
                        taxes which they had paid to their kings. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                        Next, that Macedon should be divided into four districts. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> That the division which should be deemed the first,
                        should comprehend the lands between the rivers Strymon and Nessus: to this
                        territory should be added the territory beyond the Nessus, towards the east,
                        wherein Perseus had possessed villages, castles, or towns, excepting Aenus,
                        Maronea, and Abdera; and the country beyond the Strymon, verging towards the
                        west, including all Bisaltica, with Heraclea, which they call Sintice.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That the second dis- <pb n="2151"
                            xml:id="p.2151"/> trict should be the country enclosed by the river
                        Strymon, on the east, where were excepted Sintice-Heraclea and Bisaltica,
                        and by the river Axius on the west; to which should be added the Pœnians,
                        who dwelt near the river Axius, and on its right bank. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> The third district comprised the territory bounded by
                        the river Axius on the east, the Peneus on the west, and Mount Bora on the
                        north. That to this division should be joined that tract of Paeonia, which
                        stretches along the western side of the Axius; Edessa also, and Berœa,
                        should be united to it. The fourth district was to consist of the country on
                        the north of Mount Bora, touching Illyria on one side, and Epirus on the
                        other. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then appointed the capitals of
                        the districts in which the councils should be held: of the first district,
                        Amphipolis; of the second, Thessalonica; of the third, Pella; and of the
                        fourth, Pelagonia. In these he ordered that the councils of the several
                        districts should be assembled, the public money deposited, and the
                        magistrates elected. </quote>
                    <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> He then gave notice, <quote> that it was
                        determined, that there should not be intermarriage, nor liberty to purchase
                        lands or houses, out of the limits of' their respective districts, that the
                        mines of gold and silver must not be worked; but those of iron and copper
                        might. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The tax imposed upon such persons as worked
                    them, was one half of that which they had paid to the king. He likewise forbade
                    the use of imported salt. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> To the Dardanians,
                    who laid claim to Paeonia, because it had formerly been theirs, and was
                    contiguous to their territory, he declared that, <quote>he gave liberty to all
                        who had been under subjection to Perseus.</quote>
                    <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> After the refusal of Paeonia, he granted them
                    liberty to purchase salt, and ordered that the third district should bring it
                    down to Stobi, in Paeonia; and he fixed the price to be paid for it. He
                    prohibited them from cutting ship timber themselves, or suffering others to cut
                    it. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> To those districts which bordered on the
                    barbarians, (and excepting the third, this was the case with them all,) he gave
                    permission to keep armed forces on their frontiers. </p>
                <milestone n="30" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> These terms, announced on the first day of the
                    convention, affected the minds of those who were present with very different
                    emotions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Liberty being granted them beyond
                    their expectation, and the annual tribute being lightened, gave them high
                    satisfaction; but then, by the prohibition of a commercial intercourse between
                    the districts, Macedon appeared dismem- <pb n="2152" xml:id="p.2152"/> bered,
                    like an animal torn asunder into separate limbs, which stood in need of mutual
                    aid from each other; so little did the Macedonians themselves know how great was
                    the extent of their country, how aptly it was formed for a division, and how
                    content each part could be with its own resources. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> The first division contains the Bisaltians, men of the
                    greatest courage (residing beyond the river Nessus, and on both sides of the
                    Strymon); it has many peculiar productions of the vegetable kingdom, and mines
                    also, and the advantages derived from the city of Amphipolis, which, standing
                    just in the way, shuts up every passage into Macedonia from the east. <milestone
                        n="4" unit="section"/> The second division has two very remarkable cities,
                    Thessalonica and Cassandria, and the country of Pallene, producing grain and
                    fruits in abundance; its harbours at Torone and Mount Athos, (they call the
                    latter the port of Aenea,) besides others, some of which are conveniently
                    situated opposite Eubœa, and some upon the Hellespont, give it opportunities for
                    maritime business. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The third district has the
                    celebrated cities of Edessa, Berœa, and Pella; and is partly inhabited by the
                    Vettians, a warlike people; also by great numbers of Gauls and Illyrians, who
                    are industrious husbandmen. The fourth district is occupied by the Eordaeans,
                    Lyncestans, and Pelagonians, to whom are joined Atintania, Stymphalis, and
                    Elemiotis. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All this tract is cold and rough,
                    and unfavourable to tillage; it has men whose dispositions are like the land
                    that they till. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Their vicinity to the
                    barbarians renders them more ferocious; for they at one time inure them to arms,
                    and at another are in peace, and introduce their customs among them. <milestone
                        n="8" unit="section"/> Having separated the interests of the several
                    districts of Macedon by this division, he declared that he would give them a
                    constitution which should bind the Macedonians in general, when he was prepared
                    to give them a body of laws also. </p>
                <milestone n="31" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The Aetolians were then summoned to appear; in
                    which trial the inquiry was directed to discover, rather, which party had
                    favoured the Romans, and which the king, than which had done, and which suffered
                    injury; for the murderers were absolved from guilt, and likewise the banishment
                    of the exiles confirmed, and the death of the citizens overlooked. <milestone
                        n="2" unit="section"/> Aulus Baebius alone was condemned for having lent
                    Roman soldiers as agents in the butchery. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> This
                    result in the case of the Aetolians puffed up the party which favoured the
                    Romans to <pb n="2153" xml:id="p.2153"/> an intolerable degree of arrogance,
                    throughout all the states and nations of Greece; and subjected all those, on
                    whom the slightest suspicion of being in the king's interest fell, to be trodden
                    under their feet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Of the leading men in the
                    states, there were three parties; two of which paying servile court either to
                    the Romans, or the kings, sought to aggrandize themselves by enslaving their
                    countries; while one, adopting a middle course, and struggling against both,
                    stood up in support of their laws and liberty. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>
                    Although the last had the greatest share of the affection of their countrymen,
                    still they had the least interest among foreigners. The partisans of the Romans
                    being elated by the success of their party, alone held the offices of
                    magistracy, and alone were employed on embassies. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> Great numbers of these, coming from the diets of
                    Peloponnesus, Bœotia, and other parts of Greece, filled the ears of the ten
                    commissioners with insinuations, that <quote> those who, through folly, had
                        openly boasted of being friends and intimates of Perseus, were not the only
                        persons who had favoured his cause; much greater numbers had done so in
                        secret. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> That there was another party, who
                        under pretence of supporting liberty, had, in the diets, advanced every
                        measure contrary to the Romans; <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> and that
                        those nations would not continue faithful, unless the spirit of these
                        parties was broken, and the influence of those, who had no other object than
                        the advancement of the Roman power, was augmented and strengthened. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> These persons, whose names were given in by
                    this clique, were summoned by the general's letter out of Aetolia, Acarnania,
                    Epirus, and Bœotia, to follow him to Rome, and plead their cause. Two of the ten
                    commissioners, Caius Claudius and Cneius Domitius, went to Achaia, that they
                    might, on the spot, summon by proclamation the persons implicated. <milestone
                        n="10" unit="section"/> This was done for two reasons; one was because they
                    believed that the Achaeans would have greater spirit and confidence than the
                    rest, and might disobey, and perhaps even endanger Callicrates, and other
                    authors of the charges, and informers. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The
                    other reason for summoning them on the spot, was, that the commissioners had in
                    their possession letters from the chief men of the other nations, which had been
                    found among the king's papers; but with regard to the Achaeans the charges were
                    not clear, because no letters of theirs had been discovered. When the Aetolians
                    were dismiss- <pb n="2154" xml:id="p.2154"/> ed, the Acarnanian nation was
                    called in. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> No alteration was made in their
                    situation, only Leucas was disunited from their council. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Then making more extensive inquiries respecting those who
                    had, publicly or privately, favoured the king, they extended their jurisdiction
                    even into Asia, and sent Labeo to demolish Antissa, in the island of Lesbos, and
                    to remove the inhabitants to Methymna; <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>
                    because they had received within their port, and supplied with provisions,
                    Antenor, the commander of the king's fleet, while cruising with his squadron on
                    the coast of Lesbos. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> Two distinguished men
                    were beheaded, Andronicus, son of Andronicus, an Aetolian, because, imitating
                    his father, he had borne arms against the Roman people; and Neo, a Theban, by
                    whose advice his countrymen had formed an alliance with Perseus. </p>
                <milestone n="32" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> This examination into foreign matters having
                    intervened, the general assembly of the Macedonians was again <milestone n="2??"
                        unit="section"/> summoned, and information was given them that <quote> with
                        regard to the government of Macedon, they must elect senators called by
                        themselves Synedroi, by whose advice the republic should be directed. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Then was read a list of Macedonians of
                    distinction, who, with their children above fifteen years of age, were ordered
                    to go before him into Italy. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> This injunction,
                    at first view cruel, appeared afterwards to the Macedonian populace to have been
                    intended in favour of their freedom. For the persons named were Perseus's
                    friends and courtiers, the generals of his armies, and the commanders of his
                    ships or garrisons; men accustomed to pay servile obedience to the king, and to
                    domineer haughtily over others; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> some
                    immoderately rich, others vying in expense with those to whom they were unequal
                    in fortune, all living in regal pomp and luxury; in a word, none possessed of a
                    disposition suited to a member of a commonwealth, and all incapable of paying
                    due obedience to the laws, and of enjoying an equal participation of liberty.
                        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> All, therefore, who had held any
                    employment under the king, even those who had been upon the most trivial
                    embassies, were ordered to leave Macedon and go into Italy; and the penalty of
                    death was denounced against any who disobeyed the mandate. <milestone n="7"
                        unit="section"/> He framed laws for Macedon with such care, that he seemed
                    to be giving them not to vanquished foes, but to allies who had merited well;
                    laws so wise, that even experience (which is the only corrector of laws) could
                    not find <pb n="2155" xml:id="p.2155"/> any fault in them after a long trial.
                        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Turning from serious business, he
                    celebrated with great pomp at Amphipolis games, for which he had been making
                    preparations for a long time, having sent people to the states and kings in Asia
                    to give notice of the intended diversions, and in his late tour through Greece
                    he had himself mentioned his design to the principal people. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> There came thither from every region in the world,
                    multitudes of artists of every sort, skilled in such exhibitions, and vast
                    numbers of wrestlers and noble horses; deputations also came with victims and
                    every other mark of respect usually shown out of regard to gods or men, in great
                    games of Greece. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> Hence it came to pass, that
                    the people admired not only the magnificence, but likewise the skill displayed
                    in the entertainments; in which kind of business the Romans were, at that time,
                    quite inexperienced. Feasts were also provided for the ambassadors with the same
                    degree of care and opulence. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> They made
                    frequent mention of an expression of his, that to furnish out a feast, and to
                    conduct games, seldom fell to the lot of him who knew how to conquer. </p>
                <milestone n="33" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> When the games of every kind were finished, he
                    put the brazen shields on board the ships; the rest of the arms, being all
                    collected together in a huge pile, the general himself, after praying to Mars,
                    Minerva, mother Lua, and the other deities, to whom it is right and proper to
                    dedicate the spoils of enemies, set fire <milestone n="2??" unit="section"/> to
                    them with a torch, and then the military tribunes who stood round all threw fire
                    on the same. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> It was remarkable, that, at such
                    a general congress of Europe and Asia, where such multitudes were assembled,
                    some to congratulate the victors, some to see the shows; <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> and where such numerous bodies of land and naval forces
                    were quartered, so great was the plenty of every thing, and so moderate the
                    price of provisions, that presents of divers articles were made by the general
                    to private persons, and states, and nations; not only for their present use, but
                    even to carry home with them. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The stage
                    entertainments, the gymnastics, and the horse races, did not afford a more
                    pleasing spectacle to the crowd which had assembled, than the Macedonian booty,
                    which was all exposed to view, consisting of the ornaments of the palace at
                    Pella, namely, statues, pictures, tapestry, and vases, formed of gold, silver,
                    brass, and ivory, in so elaborate a manner, that they seemed intended not merely
                    for present <pb n="2156" xml:id="p.2156"/> show, like the furniture of the
                    palace of Alexandria, but even for continual use. <milestone n="6"
                        unit="section"/> These were embarked in the fleet, and given in charge to
                    Cneius Octavius, to be carried to Rome. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Paullus, after dismissing the ambassadors with great courtesy, crossed the
                    Strymon, and encamped at the distance of a mile from Amphipolis; then resuming
                    his march, he arrived on the fifth day at Pella. <milestone n="8" unit="section"
                    /> Having passed by that city, he halted for two days at a place called
                    Spelaeum, and detached his son Quintus Maximus and Publius Nasica, with half of
                    the troops, to lay waste the country of the Illyrians, who had assisted Perseus
                    in the war, ordering them to meet him at Oricum; then, taking the road to
                    Epirus, on his fifteenth encampment, he reached the city of Passaro. </p>
                <milestone n="34" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Not far from this was the camp of Anicius, to
                    whom he sent a letter, desiring him not to be alarmed at any thing that should
                    happen, for <quote> the senate had granted to his soldiers the plunder of those
                        cities in Epirus which had revolted to Perseus. </quote>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Having despatched centurions, who were to give
                    out that they came to bring away the garrisons, in order that the Epirotes might
                    be free, as well as the Macedonians; he summoned before him ten of the principal
                    men of each city, and after giving them strict injunctions that all their gold
                    and silver should be brought into the public street, he then sent cohorts to the
                    several states. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Those that were destined for
                    the more remote states set out earlier than those who were sent to the nearer,
                    that they might all arrive on the same day. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>
                    The tribunes and centurions were instructed how to act. Early in the morning all
                    the treasure was collected; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> at the fourth hour
                    the signal was given to the soldiers to plunder, and so ample was the booty
                    acquired, that the shares distributed were four hundred denariuses <note
                        anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 12 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 18 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to a horseman, and two hundred to a footman. One hundred and fifty
                    thousand persons were led away captive. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> Then
                    the walls of the plundered cities, they were about seventy in number, were
                    razed; the effects sold, and the soldiers' shares paid out of the price.
                        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Paullus then marched down to the sea to
                    Oricum, having by no means satisfied the wishes of his men as he had imagined,
                    for they were enraged at being excluded from sharing in the spoil of the king,
                    as if they had not waged any war in Macedon. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>
                    When he found, at Oricum, the troops sent with his son Max- <pb n="2157"
                        xml:id="p.2157"/> imus and Scipio Nasica, he embarked the army, and sailed
                    over to Italy. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Anicius, a few days after,
                    having held a convention of the rest of the Epirotes and Acarnanians, and having
                    ordered those of their chiefs, whose cases he had reserved for consideration, to
                    follow him into Italy, waited only for the return of the ships that the
                    Macedonian army had used, and then passed over to Italy. <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> At the time that these events took place in Macedon and
                    Epirus, the ambassadors that had been sent with Attalus, to put a stop to
                    hostilities between the Gauls and king Eumenes, arrived in Asia. Having agreed
                    to a suspension of arms for the winter, the Gauls were gone home, and the king
                    had retired to Pergamus into winter quarters, where he fell sick of a grievous
                    disease. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> The first appearance of spring drew
                    out both parties from their respective homes; the Gauls had advanced as far as
                    Synnada, while Eumenes had collected from every quarter his forces, at Sardis.
                        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Then the Romans held a conference with
                    Solovettius, general of the Gauls, at Synnada, and Attalus accompanied them; but
                    it was not thought proper that he should enter the camp of the Gauls, lest the
                    passions of either party might be heated by debate. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> Publius Licinius held a conference with the Gallic
                    chieftain, and brought back word that he was rendered more haughty by the
                    attempt to persuade him; so that it might, therefore, seem matter of wonder that
                    the mediation of Roman ambassadors should have had <milestone n="14??"
                        unit="section"/> so great influence on Antiochus and Ptolemy, two powerful
                    kings, as to make them instantly conclude a peace; and yet, that it had no
                    influence with the Gauls. </p>
                <milestone n="35" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The captive kings, Perseus and Gentius, with
                    their children, were the first brought to Rome, and put in custody, and next the
                    other prisoners; then such of the Macedonians and principal men of Greece as had
                    been ordered to come to Rome; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> for of these,
                    not only such as were at home were summoned by letter, but even those who were
                    said to be at the courts of the kings. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> In a
                    few days after, Paullus was carried up the Tiber to the city, in a royal galley
                    of vast size, which was moved by sixteen tiers of oars, and decorated with
                    Macedonian spoils, consisting not only of beautiful armour, but of tapestry,
                    which had been the property of the king; while the banks of the river were
                    covered with the multitudes that poured out to do him honour. After a few days,
                    arrived Ani- <pb n="2158" xml:id="p.2158"/> cius, and Cneius Octavius with his
                    fleet. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A triumph was voted by the senate to
                    all three: and instructions were given to Quintus Cassius, the praetor, to apply
                    to the plebeian tribunes, who, by the authority of the senate, should propose to
                    the commons the passing of an order to invest them with military command during
                    the day on which they should ride through the city in triumph. Those in the
                    middle rank are never assailed by popular displeasure, which usually aims at the
                    highest. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> With regard to the triumphs of
                    Anicius and Octavius, no hesitation was made; yet they detracted from the merits
                    of Paullus, with whom these men could not, without blushing, set themselves in
                    comparison. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> He had kept his soldiers under the
                    ancient rules of discipline, and had made smaller donations out of the spoil,
                    than they hoped to receive, since the treasures of the king were so large; for
                    if he had indulged their avarice, there would have left nothing to be carried to
                    the treasury. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> The whole Macedonian army was
                    disposed to attend negligently in support of their commander, at the assembly
                    held for the passing of the order. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> But Servius
                    Sulpicius Galba, (who had been military tribune of the second legion in Macedon,
                    and who was a personal enemy of the general,) by his own importunities, and by
                    soliciting them through the soldiers of his own legion, had instigated them to
                    attend in full numbers, to give their votes, and to <quote> take revenge on a
                        haughty and morose commander, by rejecting the order proposed for his
                        triumph. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> The commons of the city would
                        follow the judgment of the soldiery. Was it probable that he could not give
                        the money? The soldiers could confer honours! Let him not hope to reap the
                        fruits of gratitude among those from whom he had not merited them. </quote>
                </p>
                <milestone n="36" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The soldiers were urged on by these
                    expressions, and when, in the Capitol, Tiberius Sempronius, tribune of the
                    commons, proposed the order, and private citizens had an opportunity of speaking
                    on the law, no one came forward to speak in favour of it, as there was not a
                    doubt entertained of its passing. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Whereupon
                    Servius Galba suddenly came forward and demanded of the tribune, that, <quote>
                        as it was then the eighth hour, and as there would not be time enough to
                        produce all the reasons for not ordering a triumph to Lucius Aemilius, they
                        should adjourn to the next day, and proceed with the business <pb n="2159"
                            xml:id="p.2159"/> early in the morning: for he would require an entire
                        day to plead that cause. </quote>
                    <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> When the tribune desired, that he would say
                    then whatever he chose to object; by his speech he protracted the affair until
                    night, representing to the people and reminding the soldiers, that <quote> the
                        duties of the service had been enforced with unusual severity; that greater
                        toil and greater danger had been imposed on them than the occasion required;
                        while, on the other hand, in respect of rewards and honours, every thing was
                        conducted on the narrowest scale; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> and if
                        such commanders succeeded, military employment would become more irksome and
                        more laborious to the soldiers, while it would produce to the conquerors
                        neither riches nor honours. That the Macedonians were in a better condition
                        than the Roman soldiers. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> If they would
                        attend next day, in full numbers, to reject the order, men in power would
                        learn, that every thing was not in the disposal of the commander, but that
                        there was something in that of the soldiery. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> The soldiers, instigated by such arguments,
                    filled the Capitol next day with such a crowd, that no one else could find room
                    to vote. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> When the tribes which were first
                    called in gave a negative to the question, the principal men in the state ran
                    together to the Capitol, crying out, that <quote> it was a shameful thing that
                        Lucius Paullus, after his success in such an important war, should be robbed
                        of a triumph; that commanders should be given up, in a state of subjection,
                        to the licentiousness and avarice of their men. <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> As it was, too many errors were made through a desire
                        to gain popularity; but what must be the consequence if the soldiers were
                        raised into the place of masters over their generals? </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> All heaped violent reproaches on Galba. At
                    last, when the uproar was calmed, Marcus Servilius, who had been consul and
                    master of the horse, requested from the tribunes that they would begin the
                    proceedings anew, and give him an opportunity of speaking to the people.
                        <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> These, after withdrawing to deliberate,
                    being overcome by the influence of the leading men of the state, began the
                    proceedings over again, and declared that they would call back the tribes as
                    soon as Servilius and other private persons should have delivered their
                    sentiments. </p>
                <milestone n="37" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Servilius then said: "Romans, if we had no
                    other means of judging what a consummate commander Lucius Aemilius was, this one
                    would be sufficient: that, notwithstanding <pb n="2160" xml:id="p.2160"/> he had
                    in his camp soldiers so fickle and mutinously inclined, with an enemy so noble,
                    so zealous, and so eloquent, to stir up the passions of the multitude, yet he
                    never had any sedition in his army. That strictness of discipline, which they
                    now hate, kept them then in order. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Subjected
                    to the ancient rules, they did not mutiny. If truly, Servius Galba wished to
                    make his debut as an orator in the case of Lucius Paullus, and to give a
                    specimen of his eloquence, still he ought not to obstruct his triumph, since, if
                    there was no other reason in its favour, the senate had judged it to be well
                    merited. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> But on the day after the triumph,
                    when he should see Aemilius in a private station, he should prefer a charge, and
                    prosecute him according to the laws; <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> or else,
                    at a later period, when he himself should be invested with magistracy, let him
                    cite Paullus to a trial, and accuse his enemy before the people. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> By such conduct Lucius Paullus would both receive the
                    reward of his proper conduct, a triumph for extraordinary success in war, and
                    also meet punishment, if he had committed any thing unworthy of his former or
                    present reputation. Instead of which, he has undertaken to detract from the
                    merits of a man to whom he cannot impute either crime or dishonour. <milestone
                        n="6" unit="section"/> Yesterday he demanded a whole day, for making his
                    charges against Lucius Paullus, and he spent four hours, which remained of that
                    day, in delivering a speech to that purpose. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    What accused man was ever so transcendently wicked, that the offence of his life
                    could not be set forth in that number of hours? And yet, in all that time, what
                    did he object to him, that Lucius Paullus, if actually on his trial, would have
                    wished to be denied? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> Let any one with me fancy
                    for a moment, two assemblies: one composed of the soldiers who served in
                    Macedon; the other, of sounder judgment, unbiassed either by favour or dislike;
                    where the whole body of the Roman people is the judge. <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> Let the cause of the accused be pleaded, first, before the
                    citizens, peaceably assembled in their gowns. Servius Galba, what have you to
                    say before the Roman citizens? for such a discourse, as you made before, is
                    totally precluded. You were obliged to stand at your posts with too much
                    strictness and attention; the watches were visited with too much exactness and
                    severity; you had more fatigue than formerly, because the general himself went
                    the rounds, and enforced the duties. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> On the
                    same day you per- <pb n="2161" xml:id="p.2161"/> formed a march, and, without
                    repose, were led forth to battle. Even when you had gained a victory, he did not
                    allow you rest: he led you immediately in pursuit of the enemy. When he has it
                    in his power to make you rich, by dividing the spoil, he intends to carry the
                    king's treasure in his triumph, and deposit it in the treasury. <milestone
                        n="11" unit="section"/> Though these arguments may have some incentive to
                    stimulate the passions of soldiers, who imagine that too little deference has
                    been shown to their licentious temper, and too little indulgence to their
                    avarice; <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> yet they would have no kind of
                    influence on the judgment of the Roman people; who, though they should not
                    recollect old accounts, and what they heard from their parents, of the numerous
                    defeats suffered in consequence of the desire of commanders to gain popularity,
                    or of victories gained in consequence of strict enforcement of discipline;
                        <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> yet must they surely remember, what a
                    difference there was in the last Punic war between Marcus Minucius, the master
                    of the horse, and Quintus Fabius Maximus, the dictator. <milestone n="14"
                        unit="section"/> The accuser, therefore, would soon know, that any defence,
                    on the part of Paullus, would be superfluous. </p>
                <milestone n="38" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> "Let us now pass to the other assembly; and
                    here I am not to address you as citizens, but as soldiers, if, indeed, this name
                    can cause a blush, and inspire you with shame, for your injurious treatment of
                    your general. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> And I for my part feel my own
                    mind affected in a very different manner, when I suppose myself speaking to an
                    army, from what it was, just now, when my speech was addressed to the commons of
                    the city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> For what say you, soldiers, is there
                    any man in Rome, except Perseus, that wishes there should be no triumph over
                    Macedon; and are you not tearing him in pieces with the same hands with which
                    you subdued the Macedonians? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> That man, who
                    would hinder you from entering the city in triumph, would, if it had been in his
                    power, have hindered you from conquering. Soldiers, you are mistaken, if you
                    imagine that a triumph is an honour to the general only, and not to the soldiers
                    also, as well as to the whole Roman people. This honour does not belong to
                    Paullus alone. Many who failed of obtaining a triumph from the senate, have
                    triumphed on the Alban Mount. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> No man can wrest
                    from Lucius Paullus the honour of having brought the Macedonian war to a
                    conclusion, any more than he can from Caius Lutatius, that of <pb n="2162"
                        xml:id="p.2162"/> putting an end to the first Punic war, or from Publius
                    Cornelius, that of finishing the second; or from those who, <hi rend="italics"
                        >since those generals,</hi> have triumphed. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
                    /> Neither will a triumph add to, or diminish, the honour of Lucius Paullus as a
                    commander: <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> the character of the soldiers, and
                    of the whole Roman people, is more immediately concerned therein, lest they
                    should incur the imputation of envy and ingratitude towards one of their most
                    illustrious citizens, and appear to imitate, in this respect, the Athenians, who
                    have persecuted their distinguished men by exciting the hatred of the populace.
                    Sufficient error was committed by your ancestors in the case of Camillus, whom
                    they treated injuriously, before the city was recovered from the Gauls through
                    his means; error sufficient, and more than sufficient, was committed by you in
                    the case of Publius Africanus. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> How must we
                    blush, when we reflect that the habitation and house of the conqueror of Africa
                    was at Liternum; that his tomb is shown at Liternum! <milestone n="9"
                        unit="section"/> And shall Lucius Paullus, equal to any of those men in
                    renown, receive from you an equal share of ill-treatment? <milestone n="10"
                        unit="section"/> Let then this infamy be first blotted out, which is
                    shameful in the eyes of other nations, and injurious to ourselves; for who will
                    wish to resemble either Africanus, or Paullus, in a state ungrateful and
                    inimical to the virtuous? <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> If there were no
                    disgrace in the case, and the question merely concerned glory, what triumph does
                    not imply the general glory of the Roman race? Are all the numerous triumphs
                    over the Gauls, the Spaniards, and the Carthaginians, called the triumphs of the
                    generals only, or of the Roman people? As the triumphs were celebrated not
                    merely over Pyrrhus, or Hannibal, or Philip, but over the Epirotes and
                    Carthaginians; so it was not the individual Manius Curius, or Publius Cornelius,
                    nor Titus Quinctius, but the Romans, that triumphed. <milestone n="12"
                        unit="section"/> This, indeed, is the peculiar case of the soldiers, who,
                    themselves both crowned with laurel, and conspicuous for the presents each one
                    has received, proclaim the triumph by name, and march in procession through the
                    city, singing their own and their commander's praises. <milestone n="13"
                        unit="section"/> If, at any time, soldiers are not brought home from a
                    province to such honours, they murmur; and yet, even in that case, they consider
                    themselves distinguished, even in their absence, because by their hands the
                    victory was obtained. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> Soldiers, if it should
                    be asked, for what purpose you were brought <pb n="2163" xml:id="p.2163"/> home
                    to Italy, and not disbanded immediately, when the business of the province was
                    finished; why you came to Rome, in a body, round your standards; why you loiter
                    here, and do not repair to your several homes: what other answer can you give,
                    than that you wished to be seen triumphing? And, certainly, you have a right to
                    show yourselves as conquerors. </p>
                <milestone n="39" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Triumphs have been lately celebrated over Philip, father of the present
                        king, and over Antiochus. Both these triumphs over them took place when they
                        were in possession of their thrones, and shall there be no triumph over
                        Perseus, who has been taken prisoner, and, with his children, brought away
                        to the city? But if Lucius Paullus, as a private citizen, should, amid the
                        crowd of gowned citizens, interrogate, from the lower ground, those mounting
                        to the Capitol in a chariot, and clad in gold and purple, —'Lucius Anicius,
                        Cneius Octavius, whether do you esteem yourselves, or me, more deserving of
                        a triumph?' <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> I am confident they would
                        yield him the chariot, and, through shame, themselves present to him their
                        ensigns of honour. And do ye choose, citizens, that Gentius should be led in
                        procession, rather than Perseus; do you wish to triumph over an accessary,
                        rather than over the principal in the war? Shall the legions from Illyria,
                        and the crews of the fleet, enter the city with laurel crowns; and shall the
                        Macedonian legions, after being refused a triumph, be only spectators of
                        other men's glories? What then will become of such a rich booty, the spoils
                        of a victory so lucrative? Where shall be buried so many thousand suits of
                        armour, stripped from the bodies of the enemy? shall they be sent back to
                        Macedon? Where shall be lodged the statues of gold, of marble, and of ivory:
                        the pictures, the tapestries, such a quantity of wrought silver and gold,
                        and such a mass of royal money? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Shall they
                        be conveyed to the treasury by night, as if they were stolen? What? when
                        will that greatest of shows, the celebrated and powerful captive king,
                        Perseus, be exhibited to the eyes of a victorious people? Most of us
                        remember what a concourse the captured king Syphax, an auxiliary only in the
                        Punic war, caused; and shall the captured king, Perseus, with his sons,
                        Philip and Alexander, names so illustrious, be withdrawn from the eager gaze
                        of the state? <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> All men are eagerly anxious
                        to behold Lucius Paullus himself, twice consul, the conqueror of Greece,
                        entering the <pb n="2164" xml:id="p.2164"/> city in his triumphal chariot.
                        We made him consul for this very purpose, that he should finish a war which
                        had been protracted for four years, to our great shame. When he obtained
                        that province by lot, and when he was setting out for it, with presaging
                        minds, we destined to him victory and triumph; and shall we now, when he is
                        victorious, refuse him a triumph; shall we defraud, not only men, but the
                        gods also of the honours due to them? For a triumph is due to the gods also,
                        and not to men only: your ancestors commenced every business of importance
                        with worshipping them, and ended all in the same manner. <milestone n="5"
                            unit="section"/> The consul, or praetor, (when going to his province and
                        to a war, dressed in his military robe, and attended by his lictors,) offers
                        vows in the Capitol; and when he returns victorious, after bringing the war
                        to a conclusion, carries in triumph to the Capitol, to the deities to whom
                        he made the vows, the due offering of the Roman people. The victims that
                        precede him are not the most immaterial part of the procession, —to
                        demonstrate that the commander comes home with thanksgivings to the gods for
                        the success granted to the state. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> You may
                        slay at sacrifices performed by different persons, all those victims, which
                        he has claimed to be led in his triumph. Do you intend to interrupt those
                        banquets of the senate which (whether they are meant for the gratification
                        of men, or both of gods and men) are not partaken of either in any private
                        or even public unconsecrated place, but only in the Capitol, —because such
                        is the will of Servius Galba? Shall the gates be shut against the triumph of
                        Lucius Paullus? <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Shall Perseus, king of
                        Macedon, with his children, the multitude of other captives, and the spoils
                        of the Macedonians, be left behind on this side of the river? Shall Lucius
                        Paullus, in a private character, go straight from the gate to his house, as
                        if returning home from his country-seat? And do you, centurion, and you,
                        soldiers, listen to the votes of the senate respecting your general,
                        Paullus, rather than to what Servius Galba may invent? Listen to me, who say
                        this, rather than to him. He has learned nothing, but to speak; and even
                        that with rancour and malice. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> I have
                        three-and-twenty times fought against the enemy, on challenges; from every
                        one with whom I engaged, I brought off spoils. I have my body plentifully
                        marked with honourable scars, all received in front. </quote> It is said
                    that he then stripped himself, and men- <pb n="2165" xml:id="p.2165"/> tioned in
                    what war each of his wounds was received; while he was showing these, he
                    happened to uncover what ought to be concealed, and a swelling in his groins
                    raised a laugh among those near him. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> He then
                    said, "This too, which excites your laughter, I got by continuing days and
                    nights on horseback; nor do I feel either shame or sorrow for it, any more than
                    for these scars, since it never prevented me from rendering effectual service to
                    the republic, either in peace or war. An aged soldier, I have shown to youthful
                    soldiers this body of mine, often wounded by the weapons of the enemy. Let Galba
                    expose his, which is sleek and unhurt. Tribunes, be pleased to call back the
                    tribes to vote. Soldiers, I <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> The
                        conclusion of this speech is lost. The effect of it was, that the order for
                        the triumph of Lucius Paullus passed unanimously. The beginning of the
                        account of the procession is also lost. As we have adopted Twiss's text in
                        our translation, we give here the continuation of the history, which has
                        been derived chiefly from Plutarch: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>
                        <quote>
                            <p> will go down among you, and will follow you as you proceed to give
                                your votes, and I will mark the turbulent and ungrateful, and such
                                as require that they should not be governed by the general, but that
                                he should become their willing slave, through a desire to gain
                                popularity." The great body of the soldiers felt so deeply the
                                justice of this reproof, that they changed their minds, so that all
                                the tribes, when recalled to give their votes, <milestone n="11??"
                                    unit="section"/> passed unanimously the bill concerning the
                                triumph. There- fore Paullus, having at length overcome the malice
                                and detrac- tion of his enemies, celebrated a triumph over king
                                Perseus and the Macedonians, which lasted three days, namely, the
                                fourth, third, and second days, before the calends of December. This
                                triumph, whether we consider the greatness of the con- quered king,
                                or the appearances of the images, or the quantity of money, was by
                                far the most magnificent that was ever cele- brated, so that by its
                                greatness it precluded all comparison with occurrences of a similar
                                nature. The people having raised stands, like those in the theatre,
                                along the market-place and the other streets of the city, by which
                                the procession was to move, were spectators, <milestone n="12??"
                                    unit="section"/> and were dressed in white gowns. All the tem-
                                ples were open, and were wreathed with garlands and smoking with
                                incense. The lictors and beadles kept the whole extent of the
                                streets clear, and the way open, by removing from the middle of them
                                the mob, which was crowding together and wandering about. <pb
                                    n="2166" xml:id="p.2166"/> Although the gorgeous spectacle was
                                destined to occupy three <milestone n="13??" unit="section"/> days,
                                as we have already mentioned, yet the first day scarcely sufficed
                                for the procession of the statues and paintings, which were placed
                                on two hundred and fifty chariots. The next day all the most
                                beautiful and most magnificent arms of the Mace- donians were
                                carried along on many waggons; and these arms were glittering with
                                all the brightness of steel, or lately polished brass, and were
                                piled up in such a manner with regard to one another, that although
                                they seemed to be heaped up in masses rather than artificially
                                arranged, yet they presented to the eye a striking appearance, owing
                                to this very fortuitous and con- fused arrangement: helmets were
                                mixed with shields, and coats of mail with greaves, and Cretan
                                targets, and Thracian bucklers, and quivers, in one heap with the
                                bridles of horses, and naked swords exposing their threatening
                                points, and Macedonian spears projecting from the sides. And as all
                                these arms were loosely bound together, whenever they clashed with
                                one another in the carriage, they sent forth a certain terrible and
                                martial sound, so that not even the arms of the conquered could
                                    <milestone n="14??" unit="section"/> be viewed without a feeling
                                of fear. Then more than seven hundred and fifty vases, filled with
                                coined silver, were borne along by three thousand men. Each vase
                                contained three talents, and was borne by four men. There were some
                                who bore silver bowls, and goblets, and cups, and vessels made of
                                horn, remarkable as well for the beauty of their arrangement, as for
                                their size and weight, and the sur- passing workmanship of the
                                raised carving. On the third day, at the very dawn, the trumpeters
                                began the march, playing not only the festal strains which were
                                usual in solemn pro- cessions, but <milestone n="15??"
                                    unit="section"/> also sounding the war-notes, as if they were
                                advancing to battle. A hundred and twenty fat oxen with gilded
                                horns, and adorned with fillets and wreaths of flowers, were led
                                along. Young men, begirt with bands of exquisite workmanship, led
                                the bulls along; and to them were added as companions, boys who bore
                                golden and silver goblets. Then followed the persons who bore the
                                coined gold in seventy-seven vases, each of which contained three
                                talents, like those in which the silver was carried. Then was seen
                                the sacred goblet, ten talents in weight, adorned with precious
                                gems, which Paullus had ordered to be made, <milestone n="16??"
                                    unit="section"/> and also the goblets of Antigonus and Seleucus,
                                and the cups made by Thericles, and other dis- <pb n="2167"
                                    xml:id="p.2167"/> tinguished artists, all made of gold, with
                                which the saloons of Perseus had been furnished. After them came the
                                chariot of Perseus, laden with his arms, and a diadem in addition. A
                                band of captives followed, namely, Bethys, the son of king Cotys,
                                who had been sent by his father into Macedon as a hostage, and
                                subsequently taken by the Romans along with the children of Perseus;
                                then the children of Perseus themselves, accom- panied by a band of
                                tutors and guardians, who in tears stretched forth their hands
                                mournfully to the spectators, and instructed the boys to implore
                                suppliantly the mercy of the victorious people. There were two sons
                                and one daughter who excited the greater commiseration in the
                                spectators, because they themselves, on account of their age,
                                    <milestone n="17??" unit="section"/> could scarcely comprehend
                                their misfortunes. Therefore the majority of the spectators could
                                not refrain from tears, and a sort of silent grief saddened the
                                minds of all, and prevented them from en- joying real pleasure, as
                                long as the children met their gaze. Behind his children walked
                                Perseus with his wife, in a mourn- ing robe, dressed in sandals,
                                after the Greek custom, like a person stupified and astonished, whom
                                the greatness of his calamities seemed to have deprived of reason.
                                Then followed a crowd of friends and acquaintances, in whose
                                countenances deep grief was depicted, for whenever they gazed on the
                                king they <milestone n="18??" unit="section"/> wept bitterly,
                                demonstrating clearly that they were grieved on account of his
                                calamities, but forgot their own. Perseus had endeavoured to avert
                                this ignominy by entreaties, and had sent persons to Aemilius, to
                                beg that he should not be led in the triumphal procession. Aemilius
                                smiled at the dastardly spirit of the wretch, and said, <quote>that
                                    this request was formerly, and is even now, under his own
                                    actions and power;</quote> thereby giving him a silent hint,
                                that he should avoid by a noble death that of which he was afraid.
                                But his irresolute mind was not capa- ble of adopting so determined
                                a design, and under the soothing influence of some hope, he
                                preferred being considered part of his own spoil. Then four hundred
                                golden <milestone n="19??" unit="section"/> crowns were car- ried
                                along, which had been sent by almost all the states of Greece and
                                Asia, through their ambassadors, as gifts to Paullus, and an
                                expression of their joy for his victory: their value, if they were
                                considered intrinsically, was immense, yet they con- stituted a
                                slight addition to the enormous treasures which were borne in that
                                triumph. </p>
                        </quote>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="2168" xml:id="p.2168"/>
                </p>
                <milestone n="40" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> Valerius Antias tells us, that the total of
                    the captured gold and silver, carried in the procession, was one hundred and
                    twenty millions of sesterces; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 968,750
                            <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note> but from the number of chariots, and the weights of the gold and silver,
                    specifically set down by himself, the amount is unquestionably made much
                    greater. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> An equal sum, it is said, had been
                    either expended on the late war, or dissipated during the flight, when he sought
                    Samothrace; and it was more wonderful on this account, because so large a
                    quantity of money had been amassed within the space of the thirty years that
                    intervened since Philip's war with the Romans, partly out of the produce of the
                    mines, and partly from the other branches of revenue. <milestone n="3"
                        unit="section"/> Philip began war against the Romans almost destitute of
                    money; Perseus, on the contrary, was immensely rich. <milestone n="4"
                        unit="section"/> Last came Paullus himself, in his chariot, making a very
                    majestic appearance, both from the dignity of his person, and from his age.
                    After his chariot, among other illustrious personages, were his two sons,
                    Quintus Maximus and Publius Scipio; then the cavalry, troop by troop, and the
                    cohorts of infantry, each in its order. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> The
                    donative distributed among them was one hundred denariuses <note anchored="true"
                        place="unspecified"> 3 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 4 <hi rend="italics"
                            >s</hi> . 7 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to each footman, double to a centurion, and triple to a horseman; and it
                    is believed that he would have given as much more to the infantry, and in the
                    same proportion to the others, had they not objected to his attaining the
                    present honour, or had they answered with thankful acclamations, when that sum
                    was announced as their reward. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> But Perseus,
                    led through the city of his enemies in chains, before the chariot of the
                    general, his conqueror, was not the only instance at the time of the misfortunes
                    incident to mankind; another appeared even in the victorious Paullus, though
                    glittering in gold and purple. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> For, of two
                    sons, (whom, after having given away two others on adoption, he had retained at
                    home, the sole heirs of his name, household gods, and estate,) the younger,
                    about twelve years old, died five days before the triumph, and the elder
                    fourteen years of age, three days after it; who ought to have been carried in
                    the chariot with their father, dressed in the praetexta, and anticipating, in
                    their hopes, the like kind of honours for themselves. <milestone n="8"
                        unit="section"/> A few days after, at a general assembly granted by Marcus
                    Antonius, tribune of the people, after Paullus has descanted on <milestone
                        n="9??" unit="section"/> his own proper services, as usually done <pb
                        n="2169" xml:id="p.2169"/> by other commanders, his speech was memorable,
                    and worthy of a Roman chief. </p>
                <milestone n="41" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
                    <quote> Although, Romans, I think you are not ignorant that I have successfully
                        administered the state, nor that two dreadful strokes have lately crushed my
                        house; since now my triumph and now the funerals of my two sons have been
                        exhibited to your view; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> yet permit me, I
                        pray you, to take in few words, and with that temper which becomes me, a
                        comparative view of my own private situation, and the happy state of the
                        public. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> Departing from Italy, I sailed
                        from Brundusium at sun-rise; at the ninth hour, with my whole squadron, I
                        reached Corcyra. On the fifth day after that I offered sacrifice to Apollo,
                        at Delphi, in expiation of myself, of your armies and fleets. <milestone
                            n="4" unit="section"/> From Delphi I arrived on the fifth day in the
                        camp; where, having received the command of the army, and altered several
                        matters which greatly impeded success, I advanced into the country; as the
                        enemy's camp was impregnable, and Perseus could not be brought to an action,
                        I forced the pass of Petra in the very face of his guards, and at length,
                        compelled the king to come to an engagement, and gained a complete victory.
                            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> I reduced Macedonia under the power of
                        the Romans; and in fifteen days finished a war, which four consuls before me
                        had for four years conducted in such a manner, that each left it to his
                        successor more formidable than he had found it. <milestone n="6"
                            unit="section"/> Other prosperous events followed in consequence of
                        this; all the cities of Macedon submitted; the royal treasure came into my
                        hands; the king himself, with his children, was taken in the temple of
                        Samothrace, just as if the gods themselves delivered him into my hands.
                            <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> I now thought my good fortune
                        excessive, and on that account to be suspected; I began to dread the dangers
                        of the sea in carrying away the king's vast treasure, and transporting the
                        victorious army. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> When all arrived in
                        Italy, after a prosperous voyage, and I had nothing further to wish, I
                        prayed that (as fortune generally from the highest elevation rolls
                        backwards) my own house, rather than the commonwealth, might feel the
                        change. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> I hope, therefore, that the
                        republic is free from danger, by my having undergone such an extraordinary
                        calamity, as to have my triumph, in mockery as it were of human fortunes,
                        intervene between the funerals of my two sons. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> And though Perseus and myself are at <pb n="2170"
                            xml:id="p.2170"/> present exhibited as the most striking examples of the
                        vicissitudes of mortals, yet he, —who, himself in captivity, saw his
                        children led captive, —has them still in safety; <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> while I, who triumphed over him, went up in my chariot
                        to the Capitol from the funeral of one son, and came down from the Capitol
                        to the bed of the other, just expiring; nor out of so large a family of
                        children is there one remaining to bear the name of Lucius Aemilius Paullus.
                            <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> For, as out of a numerous progeny,
                        the Cornelian and Fabian families have two of them who were given in
                        adoption. In the house of Paullus, except the old man, none remains.
                        However, your happiness, and the prosperous state of the commonwealth,
                        console me for this ruin of my house. </quote>
                    <milestone n="42" unit="chapter"/> These words, expressed with such magnanimity,
                    moved the minds of the audience with deeper commiseration than if he had with
                    tears bewailed the loss of his children in the most plaintive terms. </p>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> Cneius Octavius celebrated a naval triumph
                    over king Perseus, on the calends of December. That triumph was without
                    prisoners or spoils. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> He distributed to each
                    seaman seventy-five denariuses; <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 2 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 5 <hi rend="italics"
                            >d.</hi>
                    </note> to the pilots who were on board, twice that sum; and to the masters of
                    ships, four times. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> A meeting of the senate was
                    then held. The fathers ordered that Quintus Cassius should conduct king Perseus
                    and his son Alexander to Alba, to be there kept in custody; but that he should
                    retain his attendants, money, plate, and furniture. <milestone n="5"
                        unit="section"/> Bitis, son to the king of Thrace, was sent to Carseoli;
                    with the hostages he had given to Macedon, the rest, who had been led in
                    triumph, were ordered to be shut up in prison. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    A few days after this passed, ambassadors came from Cotys, king of Thrace,
                    bringing money to ransom his son and the said hostages. When they were
                    introduced to an audience of the senate, and alleged, as an argument, in excuse
                    of Cotys, that he had not voluntarily assisted Perseus in the war, but had been
                    compelled to do it; <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> and likewise requested the
                    senate to allow the hostages to be ransomed, at any price that should be judged
                    proper; the following answer was returned to them: that <quote> the Roman people
                        remembered the friendship which had subsisted between them and Cotys, and
                        likewise his predecessors, and the Thracian nation; <milestone n="8"
                            unit="section"/> that the giving of hostages was the very fault laid to
                        his charge, and not an id="p.2171" n="2171"/&gt; apology for it; <milestone
                            n="9" unit="section"/> for Perseus, even when at rest from others, could
                        not be formidable to the Thracian nation, much less when he was embroiled in
                        a war with Rome. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> But that notwithstanding
                        that Cotys had preferred the favour of Perseus to the friendship of the
                        Roman people, yet the senate would consider rather what suited their own
                        dignity, than what treatment he had merited; and would send home his son and
                        the hostages; that the kind acts of the Roman people were always gratuitous,
                        and that they chose to leave the value of them in the memory of the
                        receivers, rather than to demand it at the time. </quote>
                    <milestone n="11" unit="section"/> Titus Quintius Flamininus, Caius Licinius
                    Nerva, and Marcus Caninius Rebilus were nominated ambassadors to conduct the
                    hostages to Thrace; and a present of two thousand <hi rend="italics">asses</hi>
                    <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 6 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi> 9 <hi
                            rend="italics">s.</hi> 2 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> was made to each of the Thracian ambassadors. Bithys was fetched from
                    Carseoli, and, accompanied by the hostages, was sent to his father along with
                    the ambassadors. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/> Some of the king's ships
                    which were taken from the Macedonians, which were of a size never seen before,
                    were hauled ashore in the field of Mars. </p>
                <milestone n="43" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> While the memory of the Macedonian triumph was
                    remaining not only in the minds but almost before the eyes of the people, Lucius
                    Anicius triumphed over king Gentius and the Illyrians, on the day of the
                    festival of Quirinus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> These exhibitions were
                    considered rather as similar than equal. The commander himself was inferior;
                    Anicius was not to be compared in renown with Aemilius; a praetor, in dignity of
                    office, with a consul; neither could Gentius be set on a level with Perseus, nor
                    the Illyrians with the Macedonians; nor the spoils, nor the money, nor the
                    presents obtained in one country, with those obtained in the other. <milestone
                        n="3" unit="section"/> But though the late triumph outshone the present, yet
                    the latter, when considered by itself, appeared very far from contemptible.
                        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> For Anicius had, in the space of a few
                    days, entirely subdued the Illyrian nation, though they were remarkable for
                    their courage both on land and sea, and confident in the strength of their
                    position; he had also taken their king and the whole royal family. <milestone
                        n="5" unit="section"/> He carried in his triumph many military standards,
                    and much spoil of other sorts, with all the royal furniture; and also
                    twenty-seven pounds' weight of gold, and nineteen of silver, besides three
                    thousand denariuses, <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 96 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi> 17 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 6 <hi
                            rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> and, in Illyrian money, the amount of one hundred and twenty thousand.
                        <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 3874 <hi rend="italics">l.</hi>
                    </note>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>
                    <pb n="2172" xml:id="p.2172"/> Before his chariot were led Gentius, with his
                    queen and children; Caravantius, the king's brother, and several Illyrian
                    nobles. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/> Out of the booty he gave forty-five
                    denariuses <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 1 <hi rend="italics"
                            >l.</hi> 9 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 1 <hi rend="italics">d.</hi>
                    </note> to each footman, double that sum to a centurion, triple it to a
                    horseman; to the Latin allies the like sums as to natives, and to the seamen the
                    same as to the soldiers. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> The soldiers attended
                    this triumph with greater demonstrations of joy than that of Aemilius, and the
                    general was celebrated in abundance of songs. Valerius Antias says, that twenty
                    thousand sesterces <note anchored="true" place="unspecified"> 161,458 <hi
                            rend="italics">l.</hi> 6 <hi rend="italics">s.</hi> 8 <hi rend="italics"
                            >d.</hi>
                    </note> were produced by the sale of the booty, besides the gold and silver
                    carried to the treasury; but, as no sources appeared from which such a sum could
                    be raised, I have set down my authority instead of asserting the fact.
                        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> King Gentius, with his queen, children,
                    and brother, was, pursuant to an order of the senate, taken to Spoletium, to be
                    kept there in custody; the rest of the prisoners were thrown into prison at
                    Rome; but the people of Spoletium refusing the charge, the royal family was
                    removed to Iguvium. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/> There remained of the
                    Illyrian spoil, two hundred and twenty barks, which Quintus Cassius, by order of
                    the senate, distributed among the Corcyreans, Apollonians, and Dyrrachians. </p>
                <milestone n="44" unit="chapter"/>
                <p>
                    <milestone n="1" unit="section"/> The consuls of this year, after merely
                    ravaging the lands of the Ligurians, as the enemy never brought an army into the
                    field, returned to Rome to elect new magistrates, without having performed any
                    matter of importance; and on the first day on which the assembly could meet,
                    they appointed Marcus Claudius Marcellus, and Caius Sulpicius Gallus, consuls.
                    Lucius Livius, Lucius Appuleius Saturninus, Aulus Licinius Nerva, Publius
                    Rutilius Calvus, Publius Quintilius Varus, and Marcus Fonteius, were elected
                    praetors on the next day. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/> The two city
                    provinces, the two Spains, Sicily, and Sardinia were decreed to these praetors.
                        <milestone n="3" unit="section"/> There was an intercalation made in the
                    calendar this year, which took place on the day after the feast of Terminus. One
                    of the augurs, Caius Claudius, died this year, and Titus Quintus Flamininus was
                    chosen in his place by the college. The flamen quirinalis, Quintus Fabius
                    Pictor, died also. This year king Prusias arrived at Rome with his son
                    Nicomedes. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/> Coming into the city with a large
                    retinue, he went directly from the gate to the forum, to the tribunal of the
                    praetor, Quintus Cassius; <milestone n="5" unit="section"/> and a crowd <pb
                        n="2173" xml:id="p.2173"/> immediately collecting, he said, that <quote> he
                        came to pay his respects to the deities inhabiting the city of Rome, and to
                        the Roman senate and people, to congratulate them on their conquest of the
                        two kings, Perseus and Gentius, and the augmentation of their empire by the
                        reduction of Macedon and Illyria under their dominion. </quote>
                    <milestone n="6" unit="section"/> When the praetor told him that, if he chose
                    it, he would procure him audience of the senate on the same day, he desired two
                    days' time, in which he might go round and visit the temples of the gods, see
                    the city, and his acquaintances and friends. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>
                    Lucius Cornelius Scipio, then quaestor, who had been sent to Capua to meet him,
                    was appointed to conduct him around Rome. A house was likewise provided, capable
                    of lodging him and his retinue with convenience. On the third day after, he
                    attended at a meeting of the senate. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/> He
                    congratulated them on their success, recounted his own deserts towards them
                    during the war, and then requested that <quote> he might be allowed to fulfil a
                        vow of sacrificing ten large victims in the Capitol, and one to Fortune at
                        Praeneste; a vow which had been made for the success of the Roman people. He
                        further desired that the alliance with him might be renewed; and that the
                        territory taken from king Antiochus, and not granted to any other, but now
                        in possession of the Gauls, might be given to him. </quote>
                    <milestone n="9" unit="section"/> Lastly, he recommended to the senate his son
                    Nicomedes. He was assisted by the interest of all those who had commanded armies
                    in Macedon; his requests therefore were granted, except that with regard to the
                    territory, concerning which he received this answer: that <quote> they would
                        send ambassadors to examine the matter on the spot. <milestone n="10"
                            unit="section"/> If the territory in question had become the property of
                        the Roman people, and if no grant had been made of it, they would deem no
                        other so deserving of a present of the kind as Prusias. <milestone n="11"
                            unit="section"/> But if it had not belonged to Antiochus, it evidently,
                        in consequence, did not become the property of the Roman people; or if it
                        had been already granted to the Gauls, Prusias must excuse the Roman people
                        if they <milestone n="12??" unit="section"/> did not choose to confer a
                        present on him in violation of the rights of others. A present cannot be
                        acceptable to the receiver, which he knows the donor may take away whenever
                        he thinks proper. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/> That they cheerfully
                        accepted his recommendation of Nicomedes; and Ptolemy, king of Egypt, was an
                        instance of the great care with which the Roman people supported the
                        children of their <pb n="2174" xml:id="p.2174"/> friends. </quote>
                    <milestone n="14" unit="section"/> With this answer Prusias was dismissed.
                    Presents were ordered to be given him to the value of * * * * sesterces, besides
                    vases of silver, weighing fifty pounds. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/> And
                    they voted that gifts should be given to his son Nicomedes of the same value
                    with those given to Masgaba, the son of king Masinissa; and that the same
                    victims, and other matters pertaining to sacrifices, should be furnished to the
                    king at the public expense, as to the Roman magistrates, whenever he chose to
                    make the offering, either at Rome or at Praeneste; <milestone n="16"
                        unit="section"/> and that twenty ships of war should be assigned to him, and
                    which were then lying at Brundusium, of which he should have the use until he
                    arrived at the fleet which was presented to him. <milestone n="17"
                        unit="section"/> That Lucius Cornelius Scipio should not quit him, but
                    defray all his expenses, and those of his retinue, until they went on board the
                    ships. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/> We are told that Prusias was
                    wonderfully rejoiced at the kind treatment which he received from the Roman
                    people; that he refused all that had been offered to himself, but ordered his
                    son to receive the present of the Roman people. <milestone n="19" unit="section"
                    /> Such are the accounts given of Prusias by our own writers. Polybius, however,
                    represents that king as having degraded the majesty of his name, —and says that
                    he used to meet the ambassadors, wearing a cap, and having his head shaved,
                    calling himself a freed slave of the Roman people, and, accordingly, bearing the
                    badges of that class; <milestone n="20" unit="section"/> that likewise at Rome,
                    when coming into the senate-house, he stooped down and kissed the threshold;
                    called the senate his tutelar deities, and used other expressions not so
                    honourable to the hearers as disgraceful to himself. <milestone n="21"
                        unit="section"/> He staid in the city and its vicinity not more than thirty
                    days, and then returned to his kingdom, and the war that had been carried on in
                    Asia. <gap/>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
